<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!-- This template is for creating an Internet Draft using xml2rfc,
     which is available here: http://xml.resource.org. -->
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!-- One method to get references from the online citation libraries.
     There has to be one entity for each item to be referenced. 
     An alternate method (rfc include) is described in the references. -->

<!ENTITY RFC2119 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3376 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3376.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3810 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3810.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4601 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4601.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6052 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6052.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6145 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6145.xml">
]>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<!-- used by XSLT processors -->
<!-- For a complete list and description of processing instructions (PIs), 
     please see http://xml.resource.org/authoring/README.html. -->
<!-- Below are generally applicable Processing Instructions (PIs) that most I-Ds might want to use.
     (Here they are set differently than their defaults in xml2rfc v1.32) -->
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<!-- give errors regarding ID-nits and DTD validation -->
<!-- control the table of contents (ToC) -->
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<!-- generate a ToC -->
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<!-- the number of levels of subsections in ToC. default: 3 -->
<!-- control references -->
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<!-- use symbolic references tags, i.e, [RFC2119] instead of [1] -->
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<!-- sort the reference entries alphabetically -->
<!-- control vertical white space 
     (using these PIs as follows is recommended by the RFC Editor) -->
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<!-- do not start each main section on a new page -->
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<!-- keep one blank line between list items -->
<!-- end of list of popular I-D processing instructions -->

<rfc category="std" docName="draft-taylor-pim-v4v6-translation-02" ipr="trust200902">
  <!-- category values: std, bcp, info, exp, and historic
     ipr values: trust200902, noModificationTrust200902, noDerivativesTrust200902
     pre5378Trust200902
     you can add the attributes updates="NNNN" and obsoletes="NNNN" 
     they will automatically be output with "(if approved)" -->

  <!-- ***** FRONT MATTER ***** -->

  <front>
    <!-- The abbreviated title is used in the page header - it is only necessary if the 
         full title is longer than 39 characters -->

    <title abbrev="Dual-Stack PIM With Translation">Operation of a Dual-Stack Multicast Router With Address Translation</title>

    <!-- add 'role="editor"' below for the editors if appropriate -->

    <!-- Another author who claims to be an editor -->

    <author fullname="Tom Taylor" initials="T." surname="Taylor">
      <organization>Huawei Technologies</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>

          <!-- Reorder these if your country does things differently -->

          <city>Ottawa</city>

          <region></region>

          <code></code>

          <country>Canada</country>
        </postal>

        <phone></phone>

        <email>tom.taylor.stds@gmail.com</email>

        <!-- uri and facsimile elements may also be added -->
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Cathy Zhou" initials="C."  surname="Zhou">
      <organization>Huawei Technologies</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Bantian, Longgang District</street>
          <city>Shenzhen</city>
          <code>518129</code>
          <country>P.R. China</country>
        </postal>
        <phone></phone>
        <email>cathy.zhou@huawei.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    
    <date year="2012" />

    <!-- If the month and year are both specified and are the current ones,
    xml2rfc will fill in the current day for you. If only the current year is
    specified, xml2rfc will fill in the current day and month for you. If the
    year is not the current one, it is necessary to specify at least a month
    (xml2rfc assumes day="1" if not specified for the purpose of calculating
    the expiry date).  With drafts it is normally sufficient to specify just
    the year. -->

    <!-- Meta-data Declarations -->

    <area>Routing</area>

    <workgroup>Internet Engineering Task Force</workgroup>

    <!-- WG name at the upperleft corner of the doc,
         IETF is fine for individual submissions.  
	 If this element is not present, the default is "Network Working Group",
         which is used by the RFC Editor as a nod to the history of the IETF. -->

    <keyword>PIM</keyword>
    <keyword>multicast transition</keyword>

    <!-- Keywords will be incorporated into HTML output
         files in a meta tag but they have no effect on text or nroff
         output. If you submit your draft to the RFC Editor, the
         keywords will be used for the search engine. -->

    <abstract>
      <t>This document describes the procedures required for correct
      operation of a multicast router in a mixed IPv4 and IPv6 environment,
      where some or all of the multicast group and unicast source addresses
      can be translated between IPv4 and IPv6, and where incoming multicast
      data may need to be forwarded into both IPv4 and IPv6 distribution trees. The
      router is assumed to support Protocol Independent Multicast - Sparse
      Mode (PIM-SM, RFC 4601) in an environment consisting of a mixture of
      IPv4 and IPv6 local hosts and PIM peers. The work is easily generalized to
      other versions of PIM.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>During the transition from IPv4 to IPv6, operators need to maintain
      their services, including multicast services. Depending on how the 
      operator evolves its networks, the situation may arise where sources
      and receivers support different IP versions, or where some part of the
      network path between the source and receiver supports one IP version,
      and a succeeding portion supports the other.
      <xref target="ID.v4v6-multicast-ps"/> describes a number of potential
      use cases that can occur. </t>
      
      <t>If IPv4 sources needed to be received only by IPv4 receivers, IPv6
      sources needed to be received only by IPv6 receivers, and the network
      were dual stack, a multicast router could simply run parallel IPv4
      and IPv6 PIM state machines with no interaction between them. In the
      transitional circumstances described above, however, it is necessary
      to be able to map between IPv4 and IPv6 source and group addresses.
      Such a mapping introduces interactions between the two PIM state
      machines within the multicast router. The situation becomes more
      complicated if, for administrative reasons, no translation is
      possible/permitted for some addresses. As will be seen below, the
      changes to PIM operation under these circumstances will not be large,
      but do require some care.  </t>
      
      <t>A number of authors have already worked on multicast translation.
      One of the earliest works on the topic was
      <xref target="ID.venaas-v4v6mcastgw"/>, 
      which was aimed at giving IPv6 receivers access to
      IPv4 sources. The document defines a 1-1 mapping of IPv4 multicast
      group addresses onto a subset of IPv6 addresses defined by a /96 IPv6
      multicast prefix. The multicast router is assumed to sit on the
      boundary between an IPv4 and IPv6 network, and serves as a rendezvous
      point for all groups within the /96 prefix so that it can keep track of
      all IPv6 sources and receive all of their data. It appears to the IPv4
      network as an IPv4 multicast host.</t>
      
      <t>Succeeding documents have built on the foundations established by 
      <xref target="ID.venaas-v4v6mcastgw"/>, taking advantage of advances in
      translation standardized by the IETF BEHAVE Working Group. Implementations
      of the gateway concept have also appeared, with <xref target="Kiviniemi"/> 
      as a notable example. <xref target="Kiviniemi"/> is useful for its summary
      of related developments up to 2009 and for its extensive discussion of the
      challenges of translation of multicast data packets.</t>
      
      <t>The present document assumes a more general mode of operation. PIM
      messages are exchanged with IPv4 as well as IPv6 peers. The multicast
      router is not necessarily the rendezvous point for translated
      multicast groups. Instead, reliance is placed on the underlying
      routing tables to ensure that reverse paths pass through dual stack multicast
      routers like the one described in this document when translation
      between IPv4 and IPv6 is required. </t>
      
      <t>Also unlike previous work, the present document takes the details
      of translation more or less for granted, with the expectation that
      they are documented elsewhere. (References are given where available.)
      Its focus is squarely on changes in behaviour required for correct
      functioning of the multicast router in the assumed environment.</t>
      
      <t>The discussion which follows is framed in terms of a model of
      multicast router operation. Needless to say, this model is a
      descriptive device, not a recommendation for implementation. Following
      the main discussion, <xref target="messages"/> summarizes the
      processing required for each PIM message type.</t>
      
      <t>This document assumes the use of Protocol Independent Multicast - Sparse
      Mode (PIM-SM) <xref target="RFC4601"/>. Its recommendations can easily be
      generalized to other flavours of PIM.</t>
      
      <section title="Terminology">
      
        <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
        "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
        document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
        target="RFC2119">RFC 2119</xref>.</t>
        
        <t>This document uses the following terms from Section 2.1 of 
        <xref target="RFC4601"/>:
        <list style="symbols">
          <t>Rendezvous Point (RP);</t>
          <t>Multicast Routing Information Base (MRIB);</t>
          <t>Tree Information Base (TIB);</t>
          <t>RPF Neighbour;</t>
          <t>upstream;</t>
          <t>downstream.</t>
        </list>
        </t>
        
      </section>
    </section>
    
     
    <section anchor="model" title="Model of Multicast Router Operation">

      <t><xref target="fig_legacy"/> provides a model of multicast operation
      in the absence of address translation. This model consists of four
      main components: the local host protocol interface, the PIM state machine,
      route determination (including the MRIB), and the multicast data 
      forwarder. </t>

      <figure anchor="fig_legacy" title="Model of Multicast Router Operation In the Absence of Address Translation">
        <artwork>
                             +------------+
                             | Local host |
       Local hosts &lt;-------->| protocol   |
                             | interface  |
                             | (IGMP/MLD) |
                             +------------+
                                   |
                                   |
                             +------------+
 Incoming messages*          |    PIM     |          Outgoing messages*
   from peers       -------->|   state    |-------->    to peers
                             |  machine   |
                             +------------+
                                /       \
                               /         \
    Hello         +---------------+    +------------+
  messages &lt;----->|   Route       |    | Multicast  |&lt;-------
                  | determination |    |     data   |
 Routing   &lt;----->|               |    | forwarding |-------->
 protocols        +---------------+    +------------+
                             
        </artwork>
        <postamble>* PIM Join/Prune, Assert, Register, and Register Stop messages</postamble>
      </figure>

      <t>The local host protocol interface provides the router portion of
      the host protocol: Internet Group Management Protocol (IGMP) <xref
      target="RFC3376"/> for IPv4 or Multicast Listener Discovery (MLD)
      <xref target="RFC3810"/> for IPv6. It passes listener state changes
      for individual groups and sources to the PIM state machine. </t>
      
      <t>Route determination is built on the Multicast Routing Information Base
      (MRIB), as well as the secondary address information provided by Hello
      messages received from neighbouring peers. Upon request from the PIM
      state machine, it provides the address of the next hop neighbour (RPF
      neighbour) toward a given rendezvous point (RP) or source, and identifies 
      the interface leading to that neighbour. It also provides metrics in 
      support of Assert processing.</t>

      <t>Multicast data forwarding receives multicast data packets, passes 
      the source and destination (multicast group) addresses to the PIM state
      machine, and is passed in return the identifiers of the interfaces out 
      of which they must be forwarded.</t>
      
      <t>Finally, the PIM state machine executes the protocol procedures
      described in <xref target="RFC4601"/> and thereby creates and
      maintains the Tree Information Base (TIB). As well as the interactions
      with the the other components described above, it exchanges
      Join/Prune, Assert, Register, and Register Stop messages with its
      peers.</t>
      
      <t><xref target="fig_xlat"/> shows the changes to the model when address translation is introduced. Three new components are added to the picture: address mapping, routing version selection, and multicast data packet processing. Very briefly, address mapping maps source, group, and rendezvous point (RP) addresses between IPv4 and IPv6 in either direction, or returns an indication that no mapping exists. Routing version selection decides whether the next hop toward a rendezvous point or source should be IPv4 or IPv6. Multicast data packet processing accepts a packet of one version and outputs a packet of the other version. This may be accomplished through translation or, possibly, through encapsulation. Further details for all of these components and the changes needed in the PIM state machine will emerge from the discussion that follows. </t>

      <figure anchor="fig_xlat" title="Model of Multicast Router Operation When Address Translation Is Possible">
        <artwork>
                             +------------+
                             | Local host |
       Local hosts &lt;-------->| protocol   |
                             | interface  |
                             | (IGMP/MLD) |
                             +------------+
                                   |
                                   |
                         +----------------+         
                         |    Address     |
                         |    mapping     |
                         |   +------------+
 Incoming messages*      |   |    PIM     |          Outgoing messages*
   from peers       ---->|   |   state    |-------->    to peers
                         |   |  machine   |
                         +---+------------+
                                /       \
                               /         \
    Hello         +---------------+    +------------+
  messages &lt;----->|   Route       |    | Multicast  |&lt;-------
                  | determination |    |     data   |
 Routing   &lt;----->| (IPv4, IPv6)  |    | forwarding |-------->
 protocols        +---------------+    +------------+
                          |                   |
                          |                   |
                  +---------------+    +------------+
                  |    Routing    |    | Multicast  |
                  |    version    |    | data packet|
                  |   selection   |    | processing |
                  +---------------+    +------------+
                   
                             
        </artwork>
        <postamble>* PIM Join/Prune, Assert, Register, and Register Stop messages</postamble>
      </figure>

    </section>  <!-- model -->
    
    <section anchor="princip" title="Principles of Operation">

      <t>This section justifies the changes to the model shown in 
      <xref target="fig_xlat"/> and provides further details of its 
      operation.</t>
      
      <t>The basic consideration behind the proposed model is that
      downstream listeners have to be served in the IP version they support,
      but it is desirable to receive individual streams from upstream in
      only one version to avoid unnecessary duplication. Address mapping is
      unavoidable in this situation. It is actually required for three
      reasons:
      <list style="symbols">
        <t>internally to the PIM state machine, so state and state-modifying
        events involving the same source, group, or RP can be collected
        together regardless of the IP version used to represent its address; </t>
        
        <t>externally, to send messages in the appropriate IP version to PIM
        peers and local hosts; and </t>
        
        <t>to support multicast data packet processing when the packet
        must be forwarded in a different IP version from that in which it was
        received.</t>
      </list>
      </t>
      
      <t>Address mapping can be done at various points in the process. The
      representation in <xref target="fig_xlat"/> assumes the following:
      <list style="symbols">
        <t>Source and group addresses in incoming Join/Prune, Assert, and,
        depending on the role of the router, Register or Register Stop
        messages are passed to the address mapper. The mapper returns either a
        corresponding address in the other version or and indication that no
        mapping is available. </t>
        
        <t>Similarly, source and group addresses in the messages received by
        the local host protocol interface are mapped before the messages are
        passed to the PIM state machine.</t>

        <t>The PIM state machine accepts the mapped addresses and indications
        along with the original messages, and stores them in the state
        information it maintains.</t>
      </list>
      </t>
      
      <t>[To add: references pertaining to the "how" of address mapping.]</t>
      
      <t>As a result, when a message arrives that updates downstream
      listener state, the PIM state machine is able to relate that state
      change to the state it already holds for the source or group
      concerned, even if that earlier state was established by a request in
      the other IP version. This is because it can match on the mapped
      counterpart to the address in the earlier request. </t>
      
      <t>Consider now the case that, as a result of downstream events, the
      PIM state machine decides to send a Join/Prune message upstream. When
      only one IP version was involved, that was the only IP version that
      had to be considered when choosing the next hop toward the RP or
      source. In the situation presented here, however, it is possible that
      both IPv4 and IPv6 next-hop neighbours are available. A new function,
      routing version selection, is needed to make the decision.</t>
      
      <t>At this point, no general rule can be given for how routing version
      selection makes its decision. The obvious initial step is to determine
      whether the RP or source is reachable in both IP versions. It is
      assumed for the sake of this discussion that separate IPv4 and IPv6
      MRIBs are maintained by the routing determination component. If the
      target source or RP proves to be reachable by both IPv4 and IPv6, the
      associated routing metrics can be made available to routing version
      selection. However, it may well be that these metrics are not
      comparable. Routing version selection may make use of heuristics, but
      most likely will be based on local policy. That could take the form of
      a simple table mapping from target address to preferred next-hop address
      family. </t>
      
      <t>Once the IP version of the outgoing Join/Prune message has been
      determined, the PIM state machine can populate the source and group
      addresses in the message with the same IP version. In the present
      narrative, this does not require another call to address translation
      because the necessary mappings have been retained as part of stored 
      state. Other implementations are obviously possible. </t>
      
      <t>Assert logic becomes more complicated in the dual-stack scenario
      assumed here. One open issue is how to compare metrics if this router
      will acquire the multicast flow concerned using a different IP version
      from the version used by its rival peer. As noted below, Assert
      messages have to sent out in both versions, because they have to be
      understood by downstream as well as upstream entities.</t>
      
      <t>[That topic may need more detailed discussion. Also to do: add
      references and detail the challenges of multicast data packet
      processing.]</t>

    </section>  <!-- princip -->
    
    <section anchor="mods" title="Modifications To RFC 4601">

      <t>[This section should provide detailed changes needed to the
      specifications in RFC 4601, starting with the state data
      maintained.]</t>

    </section>  <!-- mods -->
   
    <section anchor="messages" title="Processing of PIM Messages and Multicast Data Packets">
  	  
  	  <section anchor="hello" title="Hello Messages">
  	 
  	 	  <t>Hello messages are not translated. Rather, the differences between 
  	 	  the IPv4 and IPv6 versions are as follows:
  	 	  <list style="symbols">
  	 	 	  <t>In the packet header, the source address varies between the 
  	 	 	  IPv4 primary address and the IPv6 link-local address on that 
  	 	 	  interface. The destination address is the IPv4 or 
  	 	 	  IPv6 ALL_PIM_ROUTERS multicast address as applicable.</t>
  	 	 	  
  	 	 	  <t>The Address List option varies between the list of secondary IPv4
  	 	 	  addresses on that interface and the list of secondary IPv6 addresses
  	 	 	  on that interface</t>
  	 	  </list>
  	 	  </t>
  	 
  	  </section>
  	 
  	  <section anchor="regis" title="Register and Register Stop Messages">
  	  
  	    <t>The Register and Register Stop messages are routed as unicast 
  	    messages.</t>
  	
  		  <t> Section 4.9.3 of <xref target="RFC4601"/> requires the header of 
  		  the multicast data packet encapsulated within a Register message to
  		  have the same address family as the packet header of the Register
  		  message itself. This may require translation of the enclosed 
  		  packet header to match the outer header. The procedures described in
  		  <xref target="RFC6145"/> MUST be applied to the header as a whole. 
  		  Translation of the source and group addresses (the packet source and
  		  destination addresses) is done as described in <xref target="model"/>.
  		  </t>
    
        <t>The Register Stop message takes its contents from the received Register 
        message, and needs no translation.</t>
  	
  	  </section>
  	  
  	  <section anchor="joinp" title="Join/Prune Messages">
  	  
  	    <t>Join/Prune messages MUST be sent in the IP version indicated by the
  	    MRIB when it identifies an RPF neighbour.</t>
  	  
  	  	<t>Care must be taken when switching from the Rendezvous Point Tree to
  	  	the shortest-path tree for a given source. The Prune for the Rendezvous
  	  	Point Tree MUST be sent in the IP version of the RPF neighbour for that
  	  	tree. This implies that in the (*,G) state described in Section 4.1.3 
  	  	of <xref target="RFC4601"/>, the address family of the last RPF
  	  	neighbour used MUST be retained, and the address itself MUST NOT be 
  	  	translated. </t>
  	 
  	 	  <t>Multicast group addresses and all joined and pruned source
  	 	  addresses contained in the message are translated as described in
  	 	  <xref target="princip"/>.</t>
  	 	  
  	  </section>
  	  
  	  
  	  <section anchor="assert" title="Assert Messages">
  	 
  	    <t>Assert messages need to reach both upstream and downstream neighbours
  	    on a LAN. Hence, if the subject router PIM has received Hello messages
  	    in both IP versions on an interface to which an Assert is to be forwarded,
  	    it MUST send the Assert message in both IP versions. </t>

  	 	  <t>The multicast group address and source address contained in the
  	 	  message are translated as described in <xref target="princip"/>.</t>
  	 
  	  </section>
  	 
  	  
  	  <section anchor="data" title="Multicast Data Packets">
  	 
  	 	  <t>This section applies to multicast data packets being forwarded 
  	 	  directly rather than being encapsulated in Register messages.
  	 	  The procedures described in <xref target="RFC6145"/> MUST be applied
  	 	  to the header as a whole. Translation of the source and group addresses
  	 	  (the packet source and destination addresses) is done as described in
  	 	  <xref target="princip"/>.</t>
  	 
  	  </section>
  	 
  	  
      
    </section><!-- messages -->
   

    <section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>Thanks to Simon Perrault for comments on the first version of this
      document.</t>
    </section>

    <!-- Possibly a 'Contributors' section ... -->

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
    
      <t>This memo includes no request to IANA.</t>

    </section>

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
      
      <t>TBD</t>
      
    </section>
  </middle>

  <!--  *****BACK MATTER ***** -->

  <back>
    <!-- References split into informative and normative -->

    <references title="Normative References">
      &RFC2119;
      &RFC4601;
      &RFC6052;
      &RFC6145;

     <reference anchor="I-D.mboned-64-multicast-address-format">
       <front>
          <title>IPv4-Embedded IPv6 Multicast Address Format (Work in progress)</title>
         <author initials="M." surname="Boucadair" fullname="M. Boucadair">
           <organization>France Telecom</organization>
         </author>
         <author initials="J." surname="Qin" fullname="J. Qin">
           <organization>ZTE</organization>
         </author>
         <author initials="Y." surname="Lee" fullname="Y. Lee">
           <organization>Comcast</organization>
         </author>
         <author initials="S." surname="Venaas" fullname="S. Venaas">
           <organization>Cisco Systems</organization>
         </author>
         <author initials="X." surname="Li" fullname="X. Li">
           <organization>CERNET Center/Tsinghua University</organization>
         </author>
         <author initials="M." surname="Xu" fullname="M. Xu">
           <organization>Tsinghua University</organization>
         </author>
         <date month="February" year="2012"/>
       </front>
    </reference>
    
    </references>
    
<references title="Informative References">
  
  &RFC3376;
  &RFC3810;

  <reference anchor="ID.v4v6-multicast-ps">
    <front>
      <title>IPv4-IPv6 Multicast: Problem Statement and Use Cases (Work in Progress)</title>
      <author initials="C." surname="Jacquenet" fullname="C. Jacquenet">
        <organization>France Telecom Orange</organization>
      </author>
      <author initials="M." surname="Boucadair" fullname="M. Boucadair">
        <organization>France Telecom Orange</organization>
      </author>
      <author initials="Y." surname="Lee" fullname="Y. Lee">
        <organization>Comcast</organization>
      </author>
      <author initials="J." surname="Qin" fullname="J. Qin">
        <organization>Cisco Systems</organization>
      </author>
      <author initials="T." surname="Tsou" fullname="T. Tsou">
        <organization>Huawei Technologies (USA)</organization>
      </author>
      <author initials="Q." surname="Sun" fullname="Q. Sun">
        <organization>China Telecom</organization>
      </author>
      <date month="May" year="2012"/>
    </front>
  </reference>
  
  <reference anchor="ID.venaas-v4v6mcastgw">
    <front>
      <title>An IPv4 - IPv6 multicast gateway (Expired Internet Draft)</title>
      <author initials="S." surname="Venaas" fullname="S. Venaas">
        <organization>Uninett</organization>
      </author>
      <date month="February" year="2003"/>
    </front>
  </reference>
  
    <reference anchor="Kiviniemi">
    <front>
      <title>Implementation of an IPv4 to IPv6 Multicast Translator (Master's Thesis)</title>
      <author initials="T." surname="Kiviniemi" fullname="T. Kiviniemi">
        <organization>Helsinki University of Technology</organization>
      </author>
      <date month="October" year="2009"/>
    </front>
    <format type="PDF" target="http://www.elisanet.fi/teemuki/translator/thesis.pdf" />
    <annotation>Author's summary: <eref target="http://iki.fi/teemuki/translator/" />
    </annotation>
  </reference>
</references>    

  </back>
</rfc>
