<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY RFC1998 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1998.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4271 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4271.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6480 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6480.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.ietf-sidr-bgpsec-protocol SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-sidr-bgpsec-protocol.xml">
]>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="rfc2629.xslt" ?> <!-- used by XSLT processors -->
<?rfc strict="yes" ?> <!-- give errors regarding ID-nits and DTD validation -->
<?rfc toc="yes"?> <!-- generate a ToC -->
<?rfc tocdepth="2"?> <!-- the number of levels of subsections in ToC. default: 3 -->
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?> <!-- use symbolic references tags, i.e, [RFC2119] instead of [1] -->
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?> <!-- sort the reference entries alphabetically -->
<?rfc compact="yes" ?> <!-- do not start each main section on a new page -->
<?rfc subcompact="yes" ?> <!-- keep one blank line between list items -->
<rfc category="info" docName="<draft-grow-simple-leak-attack-bgpsec-no-help-00>" ipr="trust200902">
<!-- end of popular PIs -->

  <front>
    <title>Route Leaks & MITM Attacks Against BGPSEC</title>
    <author fullname="Danny McPherson" initials="D." surname="McPherson">
      <organization>Verisign, Inc.</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
      <street>12061 Bluemont Way</street>
      <city>Reston</city>
      <region>VA</region>
      <code>20190</code>
      <country>USA</country>
        </postal>
      <phone>+1 703.948.3200</phone>
      <email>dmcpherson@verisign.com</email>
<!-- <uri/> -->
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Shane Amante" initials="S." surname="Amante">
      <organization>Level 3 Communications, Inc.</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>1025 Eldorado Boulevard</street>
          <city>Broomfield</city>
          <region>CO</region>
          <code>80021</code>
          <country>US</country>
        </postal>
      <phone>+1 720.888.1000</phone>
      <email>shane@level3.net</email>
<!-- <uri/> -->
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Eric Osterweil" initials="E." surname="Osterweil">
      <organization>Verisign, Inc.</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
      <street>12061 Bluemont Way</street>
      <city>Reston</city>
      <region>VA</region>
      <code>20190</code>
      <country>USA</country>
        </postal>
      <email>eosterweil@verisign.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date year="2012" />
      <area>RTG</area>
      <workgroup>SIDR</workgroup>
<!-- <keyword/> -->
<!-- <keyword/> -->
<!-- <keyword/> -->
<!-- <keyword/> -->
    <abstract>
      <t> This document describes a very simple attack vector that 
          illustrates how RPKI-enabled BGPSEC machinery as currently 
          defined can be easily circumvented in order to launch a 
          Man In The Middle (MITM) attack via BGP.  It is meant to 
          serve as input to the IETF's Secure Inter-Domain Routing 
          working group during routing security requirements discussions 
          and subsequent specification.
      </t>
    </abstract>
  </front>
  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>This document describes a very simple attack vector that
         illustrates how RPKI-enabled BGPSEC 
         <xref target="I-D.ietf-sidr-bgpsec-protocol"/> machinery, as 
         currently defined, can be easily circumvented in order to launch a
         Man In The Middle (MITM) attack via BGP <xref target="RFC4271"/>.  
         It is meant to serve as input to the IETF's SIDR Working Group 
         during routing security requirements discussions and subsequent 
         specification.
      </t>
      
      <t>This draft shows evidence that the attack vector described herein is 
        extremely common, with over 9.6 million candidate instances 
        being recorded since 2007.
        As a result of this evidence (and additional contextual knowledge),
        the authors believe the capability to prevent leaks and 
         MITM leak-attacks should be a 
         first-order engineering objective in any secure routing 
         architecture.
      </t>

      <t>While the formal definition of a route leak has proven elusive
         in the literature, their rampant occurrence and persistent
         operational threats have proven to be anything but elusive.
         This document is intended to serve as an existence 
         proof for this threat vector, and any supplementary formal models are
         left for future work.
       </t>

    </section>

    <section title="Discussion">
      <t>In order to understand how a MITM attack can be launched with this
         attack vector,
         assume a multi-homed Autonomous System (AS), AS1, connects to
         two ISPs (ISP1 & ISP2), and wishes to insert themselves in the
         data-path between a target network (prefix P) connected to ISP2
         and systems in ISP1's network in order to launch a Man In The
         Middle (MITM) attack.  Further, assume that an RPKI-enabled
         BGPSEC <xref target="I-D.ietf-sidr-bgpsec-protocol"/> as currently 
         defined is fully deployed by all parties in this scenario and 
         functioning as designed.
      </t>
      <figure>
        <preamble></preamble>
          <artwork 
                  alt='[picture of topology 1]'>

             +------+        +------+
             | ISP1 |        | ISP2 |_
             +------+        +------  \
                  \         /    (  P  )
                   \       /      \___/
                    +-----+
                    | AS1 |
                    +-----+

          </artwork>
        <postamble>This figure depicts a multi-homed AS1, who is connected to
          two upstream ISPs (ISP1 and ISP2).</postamble>
      </figure>

      <t>Network operators on the Internet today typically prefer customer
         routes over routes learned from bi-lateral or settlement free peers.
         Network operators commonly accomplish this via application of one
         or more BGP <xref target="RFC4271"/> Path Attributes, most commonly, 
         LOCAL_PREF as illustrated in <xref target="RFC1998"/>, that are 
         evaluated earlier in the BGP Path Selection process than AS_PATH 
         length.
      </t>

      <t>As currently defined, <xref target="I-D.ietf-sidr-bgpsec-protocol"/> only provides two functions:</t>

      <t>
      <list style="numbers">
        <t>Is an Autonomous System authorized to originate
           an IP prefix?
        </t>
        <t>Is the AS_PATH (or any similarly derived attribute such as BGPSEC_Path)
          in the route the same as the list of ASes through which the NLRI traveled?
        </t>
      </list>
      </t>

      <t>In order for an attacker (AS1) to divert traffic from ISP1
         for prefix P through their AS they simply fail to scope the
         propagation of the target prefix P (received from ISP2) by
         announcing a (syntactically correct) BGPSEC update for prefix
         P to ISP1.  This vulnerability is what the authors refer to
         as a 'route leak' or a 'leak-attack' (when intent aligns with
         actions).  It is important to note that the default
         behavior in BGP <xref target="RFC4271"/> is to announce all 
         best paths to external BGP peers, unless explicitly scoped 
         by a BGP speaker through configuration.  Because ISP1 prefers 
         prefixes learned from customers (AS1) over prefixes learned 
         from peers (ISP2), they begin forwarding traffic for prefix P
         destinations through the attacker's AS (AS1).  Voila!
       </t>

       <t>It is important to note that the route leaks described herein are
         NOT 'misorginiations.'  Rather, these are cases in which routes are
         propagated with their authentic origins, but are 
         misdirected through unexpected intermediaries.
       </t>

      <t>It should be understood that any multi-homed AS can potentially 
         launch such an attack, even if through simple misconfiguration, 
         as is a common occurrence today on the Internet.  As a matter of
         fact, advertising these prefixes is the default behavior is many 
         BGP implementations, and explicit action must be taken to not
         advertise all prefixes learned in BGP.
         Such occurrences have been historically archived <xref
           target="ROUTE_LEAK_DETECTION_TOOL"/> and
         presented to the operational community <xref target="NANOG_LEAK_TALK"/>
         since 2007.  To date, over 9.6 million such events have been recorded
         and are queriable <xref target="ROUTE_LEAK_DETECTION_TOOL"/>.
         This corpus serves as a low pass filter, and likely contains
         some degree of false positives.  Thus, while some may debate 
         how many of the occurrences were malicious, or how many were actually
         real leaks, the corpus itself (and its sheer size) serves as evidence 
         of the large magnitude of this problem.  Determination 
         of benign versus malicious intent in these situations is usually 
         imperceptible, and as such, preventative controls are requisite.
       </t>

       <t>
         To illustrate the above point, consider the events that transpired on
         November 6th, 2012 <xref target="LEAK_ATTACK_ON_GOOGLE"/>.  On that day
         a large Internet property (who services hundreds of billions of public end user transactions 
         every day) became unreachable for roughly 27 minutes.  At a transaction
         volume like that, an outage of 27 minutes is a very visible (and likely financially
         measurable) event.  In this case, services became unreachable because a peered 
         AS improperly propagated the impacted party's AS' prefix(s).  In leaks such as this, there exists 
         public acknowledgment by the impacted party that <xref target="RFC6480"/> and
         <xref target="I-D.ietf-sidr-bgpsec-protocol"/> would be unable to detect or
         remediate this attack.
       </t>

       <t>In an environment where <xref target="I-D.ietf-sidr-bgpsec-protocol"/> is fully deployed, it is expected
         that there would be 
         high assurances that guard the syntactic integrity of the AS_PATH 
         (or BGPSEC_Path) attribute.  As such, one would expect that
         such an attribute would, indeed, accurately reflect the attacker's 
         AS number in the appropriate location of the AS_PATH; however, 
         it would not prevent an attacker from inserting his AS in the first
         place.  That is, nothing in <xref target="I-D.ietf-sidr-bgpsec-protocol"/> would 
         stop an attacker from launching this type of leak-attack.
      </t>

      <t>Discussion of out of band methods to mitigate this attack
         are beyond the scope of this document, as its objective is to 
         inform routing protocol design choices currently being 
         considered within the IETF's SIDR Working Group.
      </t>

    </section>

    <section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">
    </section>

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
    </section>

    <section title="Security Considerations">
      <t> This document describes an attack on an RPKI-enabled BGPSEC
          and is meant to inform the IETF Secure Inter-Domain Routing
          working group on the vulnerability that exists as a result of
          "leaks" and attacks that conform to this type of behavior.  
      </t>
      <t>The authors believe the capability to prevent leaks and leak-attacks should be a 
         first-order engineering objective in any secure routing 
         architecture.
      </t>
    </section>

  </middle>
  <back>
    <references title="Informative References">
      &RFC1998;
      &RFC4271;
      &RFC6480;
      &I-D.ietf-sidr-bgpsec-protocol;

      <reference anchor="ROUTE_LEAK_DETECTION_TOOL" target="http://puck.nether.net/bgp/leakinfo.cgi">
        <front>
          <title abbrev="PUCK ROUTE LEAKS">BGP Routing Leak Detection System Routing Leak Detection System</title>
          <author initials="J" surname="Mauch">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>
          <date month="September" year="2007"/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="NANOG_LEAK_TALK" target="http://www.nanog.org/meetings/nanog41/presentations/mauch-lightning.pdf">
        <front>
          <title abbrev="PUCK LEAK TALK">Detecting Routing Leaks by Counting</title>
          <author initials="J" surname="Mauch">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>
          <date month="October" year="2007"/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="LEAK_ATTACK_ON_GOOGLE" target="http://blog.cloudflare.com/why-google-went-offline-today-and-a-bit-about">
        <front>
          <title abbrev="GOOGLE LEAK">Why Google Went Offline Today and a Bit about How the Internet Works</title>
          <author initials="CF" surname="CloudFlare">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>
          <date month="November" year="2012"/>
        </front>
      </reference>

    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
