<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
    <!ENTITY rfc2119 PUBLIC ''
      'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml'>
    <!ENTITY rfc5735 PUBLIC ''
      'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5735.xml'>
    <!ENTITY rfc4035 PUBLIC ''
      'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4035.xml'>
    <!ENTITY rfc4034 PUBLIC ''
      'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4034.xml'>
    <!ENTITY rfc4033 PUBLIC ''
      'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4033.xml'>
    <!ENTITY rfc4193 PUBLIC ''
      'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4193.xml'>
    <!ENTITY rfc2671 PUBLIC ''
      'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2671.xml'>
    <!ENTITY rfc1034 PUBLIC ''
      'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1034.xml'>
    <!ENTITY rfc1035 PUBLIC ''
      'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1035.xml'>
]>

<rfc category="exp" ipr="trust200902" docName="draft-vandergaast-edns-client-subnet-00">

<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>

<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc iprnotified="no" ?>
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>

    <front>
        <title>Client subnet in DNS requests</title>
        <author initials='C.' surname="Contavalli" fullname='Carlo Contavalli'>
            <organization>Google</organization>
            <address>
              <postal>
                <street>1600 Amphitheater Parkway</street>
                <city>Mountain View</city>
                <region>CA</region>
                <code>94043</code>
                <country>US</country>
              </postal>

              <email>ccontavalli@google.com</email>
            </address>
        </author>
        <author initials='W.W.' surname="van der Gaast"
                fullname='Wilmer van der Gaast'>
            <organization>Google</organization>
            <address>
              <postal>
                <street>Gordon House, Barrow Street</street>
                <city>Dublin</city>
                <code>4</code>
                <country>IE</country>
              </postal>

              <email>wilmer@google.com</email>
            </address>
        </author>
        <author initials='S.' surname="Leach"
                fullname='Sean Leach'>
            <organization>VeriSign</organization>

            <address>
              <postal>
                <street>21355 Ridgetop Circle</street>
                <city>Dulles</city>
                <region>VA</region>
                <code>20166</code>
                <country>US</country>
              </postal>
              <email>sleach@verisign.com</email>
            </address>
        </author>
        <author initials='D.' surname="Rodden"
                fullname='Darryl Rodden'>
            <organization>Neustar</organization>

            <address>
              <postal>
                <street>46000 Center Oak Plaza</street>
                <city>Sterling</city>
                <region>VA</region>
                <code>20166</code>
                <country>US</country>
              </postal>

              <email>darryl.rodden@neustar.com</email>
            </address>

        </author>
        <date month="January" year="2011" />
        <area>int</area>
        <workgroup>dnsext</workgroup>
        <abstract><t>This draft defines an EDNS0 extension to carry
            information about the network that originated a DNS query,
            and the network for which a reply can be cached.</t></abstract>
    </front>

    <middle>
        <section title="Introduction">
          <t>Many Authoritative nameservers today return different replies
            based on the perceived topological location of the user.  These
            servers use the IP address of the incoming query to identify that
            location.  Since most queries come from intermediate recursive
            resolvers, the source address is that of the recursive rather
            than of the query originator.</t>

          <t>Traditionally and probably still in the majority of instances,
            recursive resolvers are reasonably close in the topological sense
            to the stub resolvers or forwarders that are the source of
            queries.  For these resolvers, using their own IP address is
            sufficient for authority servers that tailor responses based upon
            location of the querier.</t>

            <t>Increasingly though a class of remote recursive servers has arisen
            that serves query sources without regard to topology.  The motivation
            for a query source to use a remote recursive server varies but is
            usually because of some enhanced experience, such as greater cache
            security or applying policies regarding where users may connect.
            (Although political censorship usually comes to mind here, the same
            actions may be used by a parent when setting controls on where a minor
            may connect.)  When using a remote recursive server, there can no
            longer be any assumption of close proximity between the originator and
            the recursive, leading to less than optimal replies from the authority
            servers.</t>

            <t>A similar situation exists within some ISPs where the
            recursive servers are topologically distant from some edges of the ISP
            network, resulting in less than optimal replies from the authority
            servers.</t>

            <t>This draft defines an EDNS0 option to convey network
            information that is relevant to the message but not otherwise included
            in the datagram.  This will provide the mechanism to carry sufficient
            network information about the originator for the authority server to
            tailor responses.  It also provides for the authority server to
            indicate the scope of network addresses that the tailored answer is
            intended.  This EDNS0 option is intended for those recursive and
            authority servers that would benefit from the extension and not for
            general purpose deployment.  It is completely optional and can safely
            be ignored by servers that choose not to implement it or enable it.</t>

            <t>
            This draft also includes guidelines on how to best cache those
            results and provides recommendations on when this protocol
            extension should be used.
            </t>

            <section title="Requirements notation">
                <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL",
                "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY",
                and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as
                described in <xref target="RFC2119"/>.</t>
            </section>
          </section>

        <section title="Terminology">
            <t><list style="hanging">
                <t hangText="Stub Resolver:">
                A simple DNS protocol implementation on the client side
                as described in <xref target="RFC1034"/> section 5.3.1.</t>
                <t hangText="Authoritative Nameserver:">
                A nameserver that has authority over one or more DNS zones.
                These are normally not contacted by clients directly but by
                Recursive Resolvers. Described in <xref target="RFC1035"/>
                chapter 6.</t>
                <t hangText="Recursive Resolver:">
                A nameserver that is responsible for resolving domain names
                for clients by following the domain's delegation chain,
                starting at the root. Recursive Resolvers frequently use
                caches to be able to respond to client queries quickly.
                Described in <xref target="RFC1035"/> chapter 7.</t>
                <t hangText="Intermediate Nameserver:">
                Any nameserver (possibly a Recursive Resolver) in between
                the Stub Resolver and the Authoritative Nameserver.</t>
                <t hangText="Third-party Nameserver:">
                Recursive Resolvers provided by parties that are not
                Internet Service Providers (ISPs). These services are often
                offered as substitutes for ISP-run nameservers.</t>
                <t hangText="Optimized reply:">
                A reply from a nameserver that is optimized for the node
                that sent the request, normally based on performance (i.e.
                lowest latency, least number of hops, topological
                distance, ...).
                </t>
                <t hangText="Topologically close:">
                Refers to two hosts being close in terms of number of hops
                or time it takes for a packet to travel from one host to the other.
                The concept of topological distance is only loosely related to the
                concept of geographical distance: two geographically close hosts can
                still be very distant from a topological perspective.
                </t>
            </list></t>
        </section>

        <section title="Overview" anchor="overview">
         <t>The general idea of this document is to provide an
         EDNS0 option so that Recursive Resolvers can, if they
         are willing to, forward details about the network a query
         is coming from when talking to other Nameservers.
         </t><t>
         The format of this option is described in <xref target="format" />,
         and is meant to be added in queries originated by Intermediate Nameservers
         in a way transparent to Stub Resolvers and end users, as
         described in <xref target="originating" />.</t>
         <t>As described in <xref target="responding" />, an Authoritative
         Nameserver could use this EDNS0 option as a hint to better locate
         the network of the end user, and provide a better answer.</t>
         <t>Its reply would contain an EDNS0 client-subnet option, clearly
         indicating that (1) the server made use of this information and (2)
         the answer is tied to the network of the client.</t>
         <t>As described in <xref target="caching" />, Intermediate Nameservers
         would use this information to cache the reply.</t>
         <t>Some Intermediate Nameservers may also have to be able to forward
         edns-client-subnet queries they receive. This is described in
         <xref target="transitivity" />.</t>
         <t>The mechanisms provided by edns-client-subnet raise various
         security related concerns, related to cache growth, the ability to
         spoof EDNS0 options, and privacy.
         <xref target="security" /> explores various mitigation techniques.
         </t>
         <t>The expectation, however, is that this option will only be
         enabled (and used) by Recursive Resolvers and Authoritative Nameserver
         that incur in geolocation issues.</t>
         <t>Most Recursive Resolvers, Authoritative Nameservers and Stub
         Resolver will never know about this option, and keep working as
         usual.</t>
         <t>Failure to support this option or its improper handling will
         at worst cause sub-optimal geolocation, which is a pretty common
         occurrence in current CDN setups and not a cause of concern.</t>
         <t><xref target="originating" /> also provides a mechanism for
         Stub Resolvers to signal Recursive Resolvers that they do not
         want an edns-client-subnet with their network to be added.
         </t><t>Additionally, owners of resolvers with edns-client-subnet
         enabled are allowed to choose how many bits of the address of
         received queries to forward, or to reduce the number of bits
         forwarded for queries already including an edns-client-subnet option.
         </t>
       </section>

       <section title="Option format" anchor="format">
           <t>This draft uses an EDNS0 (<xref target="RFC2671"/>) option to
           include client IP information in DNS messages. The option
           is structured as follows:</t>

           <figure><artwork align="left"><![CDATA[
             +0 (MSB)                            +1 (LSB)
  +---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+
0: |                          OPTION-CODE                          |
   +---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+
2: |                         OPTION-LENGTH                         |
   +---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+
4: |                            FAMILY                             |
   +---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+
6: |          SOURCE NETMASK       |        SCOPE NETMASK          |
   +---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+
7: |                           ADDRESS...                          /
   +---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+
]]></artwork></figure>

            <t><list style="symbols">
                <t>(Defined in <xref target="RFC2671"/>) OPTION-CODE, 2
                octets, for edns-client-subnet is TBD.</t>
                <t>(Defined in <xref target="RFC2671"/>) OPTION-LENGTH,
                2 octets, contains the length of the payload (everything after
                OPTION-LENGTH) in bytes.</t>
                <t>FAMILY, 2 octets, indicates the family of the address
                contained in the option, using address family codes as
                assigned by IANA in
                <eref target="http://www.iana.org/assignments/address-family-numbers/">
                IANA-AFI</eref>.</t>
            </list>

            The format of the address part depends on the value of FAMILY. This document
            only defines the format for FAMILY 1 (IP version 4) and 2
            (IP version 6), which are as follows:

            <list style="symbols">
                <t>SOURCE NETMASK, unsigned byte representing the length of the
                  netmask pertaining to the query. In replies, it mirrors the
                  same value as in the requests.</t>

                <t>SCOPE NETMASK, unsigned byte representing the length of the
                  netmask pertaining to the reply. In requests, it MUST be set
                  to 0. In responses, this may or may not match SOURCE NETMASK.
                </t>

                <t>ADDRESS, variable number of octets, contains either an IPv4
                or IPv6 address (depending on FAMILY), truncated to the
                number of bits indicated by the SOURCE NETMASK field, with
                bits set to 0 to pad up to the end of the last octet used.</t>
            </list>

            All fields are in network byte order. Throughout the document, we
            will often refer to "longer" or "shorter" netmasks, corresponding
            to netmasks that have a "higher" or "lower" value when represented
            as integers.
            </t>
        </section>

        <section title="Protocol description">
          <section anchor="originating" title="Originating the option">
            <t>
              The edns-client-subnet option should generally be added
              by Recursive Resolvers when querying other servers, as
              described in <xref target="send_when" />.
            </t>

            <t>
              In this option, the server should include the IP
              of the client that caused the query to be generated, truncated to
              a number of bits specified in the SOURCE NETMASK field.
            </t>

            <t>
              The IP of the client can generally be determined by looking
              at the source IP indicated in the IP header of the request.
            </t>

            <t>
              A Stub Resolver MAY generate DNS queries with
              an edns-client-subnet option with SOURCE NETMASK set to 0 
              (i.e. 0.0.0.0/0)
              to indicate that the Recursive Resolver MUST NOT add address
              information of the client to its queries.
              The Stub Resolver may also add non-empty edns-client-subnet
              options to its queries, but Recursive Resolvers are not required
              to accept/use this information.
            </t>

            <t>
              For privacy reasons, and because the whole IP address is
              rarely required to determine an optimized reply, the ADDRESS
              field in the option SHOULD be truncated to a certain number of
              bits, chosen by the administrators of the server, as described
              in <xref target="security" />.
            </t>
          </section>

          <section anchor="responding" title="Generating a response">
            <t>
              When a query containing an edns-client-subnet option is received,
              an Authoritative Nameserver supporting edns-client-subnet MAY use
              the address information specified in the option in order to
              generate an optimized reply.
            </t>

            <t>Authoritative servers that have not implemented or enabled
              support for the edns-client-subnet may safely ignore the option
              within incoming queries.  Such a server MUST NOT include an
              edns-client-subnet option within replies to indicate lack of support
              for the option.</t>

            <t>
              Requests with wrongly formatted options (i.e. wrong size) MUST
              be rejected and a FORMERR response must be returned to the
              sender, as described by <xref target="RFC2671"/>, Transport
              Considerations.
            </t>

            <t>
              If the Authoritative Nameserver decides to use information
              from the edns-client-subnet option to calculate a response, it
              MUST include the option in the response to indicate that the
              information was used (and has to be cached accordingly).
              If the option was not included in a query, it MUST NOT be
              included in the response.
            </t>

            <t>
              The FAMILY, ADDRESS and SOURCE NETMASK in the response MUST
              match those in the request. Echoing back the address and netmask
              helps to mitigate certain attack vectors, as described in
              <xref target="security" />.</t>

            <t>The SCOPE NETMASK in the reply indicates the netmask of the
              network that the answer is intended for.</t>

            <t>A SCOPE NETMASK value larger than the SOURCE NETMASK indicates
              that the address and netmask provided in the query was not specific
              enough to select a single, best response, and that an optimal
              reply would require at least SCOPE NETMASK bits of address
              information.</t>

            <t>
              Conversely, a shorter SCOPE NETMASK indicates that more bits than
              necessary were provided.
            </t>

            <t>
              As not all netblocks are the same size, an Authoritative
              Nameserver may return different values of SCOPE NETMASK for
              different networks.
            </t>

            <t>
              In both cases, the value of the SCOPE NETMASK in the reply has
              strong implications with regard to how the reply will be cached by
              Intermediate Nameservers, as described in <xref target="caching" />.
            </t>

            <t>
              If the edns-client-subnet option in the request is not used at all
              (for example if an optimized reply was temporarily unavailable
              or not supported for the requested domain name), a server
              supporting edns-client-subnet MUST indicate that no bits of the
              ADDRESS in the request have been used by specifying a SCOPE
              NETMASK of 0 (equivalent to the networks 0.0.0.0/0 or ::/0).
            </t>

            <t>
              If no optimized answer could be found at all for the FAMILY,
              ADDRESS and SOURCE NETMASK indicated in the query, the
              Authoritative Nameserver SHOULD still return the best result it
              knows of (i.e. by using the query source IP address instead, or a
              sensible default), and indicate that this result should only be
              cached for the FAMILY, ADDRESS and SOURCE NETMASK indicated in
              the request. The server will indicate this by copying the
              SOURCE NETMASK into the SCOPE NETMASK field.
            </t>
          </section>

          <section anchor="caching"
            title="Handling edns-client-subnet replies and caching">
            <t>
              When an Intermediate Nameserver receives a reply containing an
              edns-client-subnet option, it will return a reply to its client
              and may cache the result.
            </t>

            <t>
              If the FAMILY, ADDRESS and SOURCE NETMASK fields in the reply
              don't match the fields in the corresponding request, the full
              reply MUST be dropped, as described in <xref target="security" />.
            </t>

            <t>
              In the cache, any resource record in the answer section will be
              tied to the network specified by the FAMILY, ADDRESS and SCOPE
              NETMASK fields, as detailed below.
            </t>

            <t>
              If another query is received matching the entry in the cache,
              the resolver will verify that the FAMILY and ADDRESS that
              represent the client match any of the networks in the cache
              for that entry.
            </t>

            <t>
              If the address of the client is within any of the networks in
              the cache, then the cached response MUST be returned as usual.
              In case the address of the client matches multiple networks in
              the cache, the entry with the highest SCOPE NETMASK value MUST
              be returned, as with most route-matching algorithms.
            </t>

            <t>
              If the address of the client does not match any network in
              the cache, then the Recursive Resolver MUST behave as if no
              match was found and perform resolution as usual.
              This is necessary to avoid sub-optimal replies in the
              cache from being returned to the wrong clients, and to
              avoid a single request coming from a client on a different
              network from polluting the cache with a sub-optimal reply
              for all the users of that resolver.
            </t>

            <t>
              Note that every time a Recursive Resolver queries an
              Authoritative Nameserver by forwarding the edns-client-subnet option
              that it received from another client, a low SOURCE NETMASK in the
              original request could cause a sub-optimal reply to be returned
              by the Authoritative Nameserver.
            </t>

            <t>
              To avoid this sub-optimal reply from being served from cache
              for clients for which a better reply would be available,
              the Recursive Resolver MUST check the SCOPE NETMASK that was
              returned by the Authoritative Nameserver:
              <list style="symbols">
                <t>If the SCOPE NETMASK in the reply is longer than the
                   SOURCE NETMASK, it means that the reply might be sub-optimal.
                   A Recursive Resolver MUST return this entry from cache only
                   to queries that do not contain or allow a longer
                   SOURCE NETMASK to be forwarded.</t>

                <t>If the SCOPE NETMASK in the reply is shorter or equal to the
                   SOURCE NETMASK, the reply is optimal, and SHOULD
                   be returned from cache to any client within the network
                   indicated by ADDRESS and SCOPE NETMASK.</t>
              </list>
            </t>

            <t>
              When another request is performed, the existing entries SHOULD
              be kept in the cache until their TTL expires, as per standard
              behavior.
            </t>

            <t>
              As another reply is received, the reply will be tied to a
              different network. The server SHOULD keep in cache both replies,
              and return the most appropriate one depending on the address
              of the client.
            </t>

            <t>
              Any reply containing an edns-client-subnet option considered invalid
              should be treated as if no edns-client-subnet option was specified at
              all.
            </t>

            <t>
              Replies coming from servers not supporting edns-client-subnet or
              otherwise not containing an edns-client-subnet option SHOULD be
              considered as containing a SCOPE NETMASK of 0 (e.g., cache the
              result for 0.0.0.0/0 or ::/0) for all the supported families.
            </t>

            <t>
              In any case, the response from the resolver to the client
              MUST NOT contain
              the edns-client-subnet option if none was present in the client's
              original request. If the original client request contained a
              valid edns-client-subnet option that was used during recursion,
              the Recursive Resolver MUST include the edns-client-subnet option
              from the Authoritative Nameserver response in the response
              to the client.
            </t>

            <t>
              Enabling support for edns-client-subnet in a recursive resolver will
              significantly increase the size of the cache, reduce the number of
              results that can be served from cache, and increase the load on
              the server. Implementing the mitigation techniques described in
              <xref target="security" /> is strongly recommended.
            </t>
          </section>

          <section anchor="transitivity" title="Transitivity">
            <t>
              Generally, edns-client-subnet options will only be present in DNS
              messages between a Recursive Resolver and an Authoritative
              Nameserver, i.e. one hop. In certain configurations however (for
              example multi-tier nameserver setups), it may be necessary to
              implement transitive behaviour on Intermediate Nameservers.
            </t>

            <t>
              It is important that any Intermediate Nameserver that implements
              transitive behaviour (i.e. forward edns-client-subnet
              options received from their clients) MUST fully implement the
              caching behaviour described in <xref target="caching" />.
            </t>

            <t>
              Intermediate Nameservers (including Recursive Resolvers) supporting
              edns-client-subnet MUST forward options with SOURCE NETMASK set to
              0 (i.e. anonymized), such an option MUST NOT be replaced with an
              option with more accurate address information.
            </t>

            <t>
              An Intermediate Nameserver MAY also forward edns-client-subnet
              options with actual address information. This information MAY match
              the source IP address of the incoming query, and MAY have more or
              less address bits than the Nameserver would normally include in a
              locally originated edns-client-subnet option.
            </t>

            <t>
              If for any reason the Intermediate Nameserver does not want to use
              the information in an edns-client-subnet option it receives (too
              little address information, network address from an IP range not
              authorized to use the server, private/unroutable address space,
              ...) it SHOULD drop the query and return a REFUSED response. Note
              again that an edns-client-subnet option with 0 address bits MUST
              NOT be refused.
            </t>
          </section>
        </section>

        <section title="IANA Considerations">
            <t>We request IANA to assign an option code for edns-client-subnet, as
              specified in <xref target="RFC2671"/>. Within this document, the
              text 'TBD' should be replaced with the option code assigned by
              IANA.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="DNSSEC Considerations">
          <t>
            The presence or absence of an OPT resource record containing an
            edns-client-subnet option in a DNS query does not change the usage
            of those resource records and mechanisms used to provide
            data origin authentication and data integrity to the DNS,
            as described in <xref target="RFC4033" />, <xref target="RFC4034" />
            and <xref target="RFC4035" />.
          </t>
        </section>

        <section title="NAT Considerations">
          <t>Special awareness of edns-client-subnet in devices that perform NAT
          as described in <xref target="RFC2663"/> is not required, queries
          can be passed through as-is. The client's network address MUST NOT be
          added, and existing edns-client-subnet options, if present, MUST NOT
          be modified by NAT devices.</t>

          <t>Recursive Resolvers sited behind NAT devices MUST NOT add their
          external network address in an edns-client-subnet options, and MUST behave
          exactly as described in the previous sections.</t>

          <t>Note that Authoritative Nameservers or Recursive Resolvers can
          still provide an optimized reply by looking at the source IP of the
          query.</t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="security" title="Security Considerations">
          <section title="Privacy">
            <t>With the edns-client-subnet option, the network address of the
            client that initiated the resolution becomes visible to all
            servers involved in the resolution process. Additionally, it
            will be visible from any network traversed by the DNS
            packets.</t>

            <t>To protect users' privacy, Recursive Resolvers are strongly
            encouraged to conceal part of the IP address of the user by
            truncating IPv4 addresses to 24 bits. No recommendation is
            provided for IPv6 at this time, but IPv6 addresses should be
            similarly truncated in order to not allow to uniquely identify
            the client.</t>

            <t>Users who wish their full IP address to be hidden can include
            an edns-client-subnet option specifying the wildcard address
            0.0.0.0/0 (i.e. FAMILY set to 1 (IPv4), SOURCE NETMASK to 0 and no
            ADDRESS). As described in previous sections, this option will
            be forwarded across all the Recursive Resolvers supporting
            edns-client-subnet, which MUST NOT modify it to include the network
            address of the client.
            </t>

            <t>
            Note that even without edns-client-subnet options, any server queried
            directly by the user will be able to see the full client IP
            address.
            Recursive Resolvers or Authoritative Nameservers MAY use the
            source IP address of requests to return a cached entry or to
            generate an optimized reply that best matches the request.
            </t>
          </section>

          <section title="Birthday attacks">
            <t>edns-client-subnet adds information to the q-tuple. This allows
            an attacker to send a caching Intermediate Nameserver multiple
            queries with spoofed IP addresses either in the edns-client-subnet
            option or as the source IP. These queries will trigger multiple
            outgoing queries with the same name, type and class, just
            different address information in the edns-client-subnet option.</t>

            <t>With multiple queries for the same name in flight, the
            attacker has a higher chance of success in sending a matching
            response (with the address 0.0.0.0/0 to still get it cached
            for many hosts).</t>

            <t>To counter this, every edns-client-subnet option in a response
            packet MUST contain the full FAMILY, ADDRESS and SOURCE NETMASK
            fields from the corresponding request. Intermediate
            Nameservers processing a response MUST verify that these
            match, and MUST discard the entire reply if they do not.</t>
          </section>

          <section title="Cache pollution">
            <t>It is simple for an arbitrary resolver or client to provide
            false information in the edns-client-subnet option, or to send UDP
            packets with forged source IP addresses.</t>

            <t>This could be used to:
              <list style="symbols">
                <t>pollute the cache of intermediate resolvers, by filling
                   it with results that will rarely (if ever) be used.</t>
                <t>reverse engineer the algorithms (or data) used by
                   the Authoritative Nameserver to caclulate the optimized
                   answer.</t>
                <t>mount a DoS attack against an intermediate resolver, by
                   forcing it to perform many more recursive queries than
                   it would normally do, due to how caching is handled
                   for queries containing the edns-client-subnet option.</t>
              </list>
            </t>
 
            <t>Even without malicious intent, third-party Recursive Resolvers
            providing answers to clients in multiple networks will need to
            cache different replies for different networks, putting
            more pressure on the cache.</t>

            <t>To mitigate those problems:</t>

            <t><list style="symbols">
                <t>Recursive Resolvers implementing edns-client-subnet should only
                enable it in deployments where it is expected to bring clear
                advantages to the end users. For example, when expecting clients
                from a variety of networks or from a wide geographical area.
                Due to the high cache pressure introduced by edns-client-subnet,
                the feature must be disabled in all default configurations.</t>

              <t>Recursive Resolvers should limit the number of networks and
                answers they keep in the cache for a given query.</t>

              <t>Recursive Resolvers should limit the number of total different
                networks that they keep in cache.</t>

              <t>Recursive Resolvers should never send edns-client-subnet options
                with SOURCE NETMASKs providing more bits in the ADDRESS than
                they are willing to cache responses for.</t>

              <t>Recursive Resolvers should implement algorithms to improve the
                cache hit rate, given the size constraints indicated above.
                Recursive Resolvers may, for example, decide to discard more
                specific cache entries first.</t>

              <t>Authoritative Nameservers and Recursive Resolvers should
                discard known to be wrong or known to be forged edns-client-subnet
                options. They must at least ignore unroutable addresses,
                such as some of the address blocks defined in <xref target="RFC5735" />
                and <xref target="RFC4193" />, and should ignore and never
                forward edns-client-subnet options specifying networks
                or addresses that are known not to be served by those servers
                when feasible.
              </t>

              <t>Authoritative Nameservers consider the edns-client-subnet option
                just as a hint to provide better results. They can decide to
                ignore the content of the edns-client-subnet option based on
                black or white lists, rate limiting mechanisms, or any other
                logic implemented in the software.</t>
            </list></t>
          </section>
        </section>

        <section anchor="send_when" title="Sending the option">
          <t>When implementing a Recursive Resolver, there are two strategies
          on deciding when to include an edns-client-subnet option in a query.
          At this stage it's not clear which strategy is best.</t>
          
          <section title="Probing">
            <t>A Recursive Resolver can send the edns-client-subnet option with
            every outgoing query. However, it is RECOMMENDED that Resolvers
            remember which Authoritative Nameservers did not return the option
            with their response, and omit client address information from
            subsequent queries to those Nameservers.</t>
            
            <t>Additionally, Recursive Resolvers MAY be configured to never
            send the option when querying root and TLD servers, as these are
            unlikely to generate different replies based on the IP of the
            client.</t>
            
            <t>When probing, it is important that several things are
            probed: support for edns-client-subnet, support for
            EDNS0, support for EDNS0 options, or possibly an unreachable
            Nameserver. Various implementations are known to drop DNS packets
            with OPT RRs (with or without options), thus several probes are
            required to discover what is supported.</t>
            
            <t>Probing, if implemented, MUST be repeated periodically (i.e.
            daily). If an Authoritative Nameserver indicates edns-client-subnet
            support for one zone, it is to be expected that the Nameserver
            supports edns-client-subnet for all its zones. Likewise, an
            Authoritative Nameserver that uses edns-client-subnet information
            for one of its zones, MUST indicate support for the option in
            all its responses. If the option is supported but not actually used
            for generating a response, its SCOPE NETMASK value SHOULD be
            set to 0.</t>
          </section>
          
          <section title="Whitelist">
            <t>As described previously, it is expected that only a few
            Recursive Resolvers will need to use edns-client-subnet, and that
            it will generally be enabled only if it offers a clear benefit
            to the users.</t>
            
            <t>To avoid the complexity of implementing a probing and detection
            mechanism (and the possible query loss/delay that may come with it),
            an implementation could decide to use a statically configured
            whitelist of Authoritative Namesevers to send the option to.
            Implementations MAY also allow additionally configuring this based
            on other criteria (i.e. zone, qtype).</t>

            <t>An additional advantage of using a whitelist is that partial
            client address information is only disclosed to Nameservers that
            are known to use the information, improving privacy.</t>
            
            <t>A major drawback is scalability. The operator needs to track
            which Nameservers support edns-client-subnet, making it harder
            for new Authoritative Nameservers to start using the option.</t>
          </section>
        </section>

        <section title="Example">
          <t><list style="numbers">
              <t>A stub resolver SR with IP address 192.0.2.37 tries to
                resolve www.example.com, by forwarding the query to the
                Recursive Resolver R from IP address IP, asking for
                recursion.</t>

              <t>R, supporting edns-client-subnet, looks up www.example.com in
                its cache. An entry is found neither for www.example.com,
                nor for example.com.</t>

              <t>R builds a query to send to the root and .com servers.
                The implementation of R provides facilities so an administrator
                can configure R not to forward edns-client-subnet in certain
                cases. In particular, R is configured to not include an
                edns-client-subnet option when talking to TLD or root
                nameservers, as described in <xref target="originating"/>.
                Thus, no edns-client-subnet option is added, and
                resolution is performed as usual.</t>
 
              <t>R now knows the next server to query: Authoritative Nameserver
                ANS, responsible for example.com.</t>
 
              <t>R prepares a new query for www.example.com, including an
                edns-client-subnet option with:
                <list style="symbols">
                  <t>OPTION-CODE, set to TBD.</t>
                  <t>OPTION-LENGTH, set to 0x00 0x07.</t>
                  <t>FAMILY, set to 0x00 0x01 as IP is an IPv4 address.</t>
                  <t>SOURCE NETMASK, set to 0x18, as R is configured to conceal
                     the last 8 bits of every IPv4 address.</t>
                  <t>SCOPE NETMASK, set to 0x00, as specified by this document
                     for all requests.</t>
                  <t>ADDRESS, set to 0xC0 0x00 0x02, providing only the first
                     24 bits of the IPv4 address.</t>
                </list>
              </t>

              <t>The query is sent. Server ANS understands and uses
                edns-client-subnet. It parses the edns-client-subnet
                option, and generates an optimized reply.</t>

              <t>Due to the internal implementation of the Authoritative
                Nameserver ANS, ANS finds a reply that is optimal for the whole
                /16 of the client that performed the request.</t>

              <t>The Authoritative Nameserver ANS adds an edns-client-subnet
                 option in the reply, containing:
                 <list style="symbols">
                   <t>OPTION-CODE, set to TBD.</t>
                   <t>OPTION-LENGTH, set to 0x00 0x07.</t>
                   <t>FAMILY, set to 0x00 0x01.</t>
                   <t>SOURCE NETMASK, set to 0x18, copied from the request.</t>
                   <t>SCOPE NETMASK, set to 0x10, indicating a /16 network.</t>
                   <t>ADDRESS, set to 0xC0 0x00 0x02, copied from the
                      request.</t>
                 </list>
              </t>

              <t>The Recursive Resolver R receives the reply containing an
                 edns-client-subnet option. The resolver verifies that FAMILY,
                 SOURCE NETMASK, and ADDRESS match the request. If not, the
                 option is discarded.</t>

              <t>
                The reply is interpreted as usual. Since the reply
                contains an edns-client-subnet option, the ADDRESS, SCOPE NETMASK,
                and FAMILY in the response are used to cache the entry.
              </t>

              <t>R sends a response to stub resolver SR, without including
                an edns-client-subnet option.</t>

              <t>R receives another request to resolve www.example.com.
                This time, a reply is cached. The reply, however, is tied
                to a particular network. If the address of the client
                matches any network in the cache, then the reply is
                returned from the cache. Otherwise, another query is
                performed. If multiple results match, the one with the
                longest SCOPE NETMASK is chosen, as per common best-network
                match algorithms.
              </t>
          </list></t>

        </section>

        <section title="Acknowledgements">
          <t>
          The authors wish to thank the following people for reviewing early
          drafts of this document and for providing useful feedback: Paul
          S. R. Chisholm, B. Narendran, Leonidas Kontothanassis, David
          Presotto, Philip Rowlands, Chris Morrow, Kara Moscoe, Alex Nizhner,
          Warren Kumari, Richard Rabbat from Google, Terry Farmer, Mark Teodoro,
          Edward Lewis, Eric Burger from Neustar, David Ulevitch, Matthew
          Dempsky from OpenDNS, Patrick W. Gilmore from Akamai,
          Colm MacCarthaigh, Richard Sheehan and all the other people that
          replied to our emails on various mailing lists.
          </t>
        </section>

        <appendix title="Document Editing History">
          <appendix title="Changes since edns-client-ip-01">
            <t><list style="symbols">
              <t>Document version number reset from -02 to -00 due to
              the rename to edns-client-subnet.</t>

              <t>Clarified example (dealing with TLDs, and various
              minor errors).</t>

              <t>Referencing RFC5035 instead of RFC1918.</t>

              <t>Added a section on probing (and how it should be done)
              vs. whitelisting.</t>

              <t>Moved description on how to forward edns-client-subnet
              option in dedicated section.</t>

              <t>Queries with wrongly formatted edns-client-subnet options
              should now be rejected with FORMERR.</t>

              <t>Added an "Overview" section, providing an introduction to
              the document.</t>

              <t>Intermediate Nameservers can now remove an edns-client-subnet
              option, or reduce the SOURCE NETMASK to increase privacy.</t>

              <t>Added a reference to DoS attacks in the Security section.</t>

              <t>Don't use "network range", as it seems to have different
              meaning in other contexts, and turned out to be confusing.</t>

              <t>Use shorter and longer netmasks, rather than higher or lower.
              Add a better explanation in the format section.</t>

              <t>Minor corrections in various other sections.</t>
            </list></t>
          </appendix>

          <appendix title="Changes since edns-client-ip-00">
            <t><list style="symbols">
              <t>Rewritten problem statement to be more clear about the
              goal of edns-client-subnet and the fact that it's entirely
              optional.</t>

              <t>Wire format changed to include the original address and
              netmask in responses in defence against birthday attacks.</t>

              <t>Security considerations now includes a section about
              birthday attacks.</t>

              <t>Renamed edns-client-ip in edns-client-subnet, following
              suggestions on the mailing list.</t>

              <t>Clarified behavior of resolvers when presented with an
              invalid edns-client-subnet option.</t>

              <t>Fully take multi-tier DNS setups in mind and be more clear
              about where the option should be originated.</t>

              <t>Added a few definitions in the Terminology section, and
              a few more aesthetic changes in the rest of the document.</t>

            </list></t>
          </appendix>
        </appendix>
    </middle>

    <back>
        <references title='Normative References'>
            &rfc2119;
            &rfc5735;
            &rfc4035;
            &rfc4034;
            &rfc4033;
            &rfc4193;
            &rfc2671;
            &rfc1035;
            &rfc1034;
        </references>

        <references title='Informative References'>
            <reference anchor="RFC2663">
                <front>
                    <title>IP Network Address Translator (NAT)
                    Terminology and Considerations</title>

                    <author initials="P." surname="Srisuresh">
                        <organization>
                          Lucent Technologies
                        </organization>
                    </author>

                    <author initials="M." surname="Holdrege">
                        <organization>
                          Lucent Technologies
                        </organization>
                    </author>
                </front>

                <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="2663" />
            </reference>
        </references>
    </back>

</rfc>
