<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [

    <!ENTITY RFC1035 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1035.xml">
    <!ENTITY RFC2119 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
  <!ENTITY RFC2045 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2045.xml">
  <!ENTITY RFC2629 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2629.xml">
    <!ENTITY RFC5280 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5280.xml">
    <!ENTITY RFC3552 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3552.xml">
    <!ENTITY RFC3642 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3642.xml">    
    <!ENTITY RFC4033 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4033.xml">
    <!ENTITY RFC4055 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4055.xml">
  <!ENTITY RFC4234 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4234.xml">
  <!ENTITY RFC4648 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4648.xml">
    <!ENTITY RFC5395 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5395.xml">
    <!ENTITY RFC5070 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5070.xml">
    <!ENTITY RFC6046 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6046.xml">
]>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<rfc category="std" docName="draft-ietf-pkix-caa-06" ipr="trust200902">

    <front>
        <title abbrev="Certification Authority Authorization">DNS Certification Authority Authorization (CAA) Resource Record</title>
        <author fullname="Phillip Hallam-Baker" initials="P. M." surname="Hallam-Baker">
            <organization>Comodo Group Inc.</organization>
            <address>
                <email>philliph@comodo.com</email>
            </address>
        </author>
        <author fullname="Rob Stradling" initials="R. N." surname="Stradling">
            <organization>Comodo CA Ltd.</organization>
            <address>
                <email>rob.stradling@comodo.com</email>
            </address>
        </author>

        <date day="21" month="April" year="2012" />

        <area>General</area>

        <workgroup>Internet Engineering Task Force</workgroup>

        <keyword>DNS</keyword>
        <keyword>DNSSEC</keyword>
        <keyword>PKIX</keyword>
        
        <abstract>
            <t>
                The Certification Authority Authorization (CAA) DNS Resource Record allows a
                DNS domain name holder to specify the certificate signing certificate(s)
                authorized to issue certificates for that domain.
                CAA resource records allow a public Certification Authority to implement additional
                controls to reduce the risk of unintended certificate mis-issue. 
            </t>
        </abstract>
    </front>

    <middle>
        <section title="Definitions">
            <section title="Requirements Language">
                <t>
                    The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
                    "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
                    document are to be interpreted as described in <xref target="RFC2119">RFC 2119</xref>.
                </t>
            </section>
            <section title="Defined Terms">
                <t>The following terms are used in this document:</t>
                <t>
                    <list style="hanging">

                        <t hangText="Authorization Entry">
                            An authorization assertion that grants or denies a specific set of permissions 
                            to a specific group of entities.</t>
                        <t hangText="Canonical Domain Name">
                            A Domain Name that is not an alias.
                            </t>
                        <t hangText="Canonical Domain Name Value">
                            The value of a Canonical Domain Name. The value resulting from applying alias
                            transformations to a Domain Name that is not canonical.
                        </t>
                        <t hangText="Certificate">
                            An X.509 Certificate, as specified in <xref target="RFC5280">RFC 5280</xref>.
                    </t>
                      <t hangText="Certificate Evaluator">
                        A party other than a Relying Party that evaluates the trustworthiness of 
                        certificates issued by Certification Authorities.
                      </t>
                      <t hangText="Certification Authority (CA)">
                        An Issuer that issues Certificates in accordance with a specified
                        Certification Policy.
                      </t>
                      <t hangText="Certification Policy (CP)">
                            Specifies the criteria that a Certification Authority undertakes to meet
                            in its issue of certificates.</t>
                        <t hangText="Certification Practices Statement (CPS)">
                            Specifies the means by which the criteria of the Certification Policy
                            are met. In most cases this will be the document against which the
                            operations of the Certification Authority are audited.</t>

                        <t hangText="Domain">
                            The set of resources associated with a DNS Domain Name.</t>
                        <t hangText="Domain Name">
                            A DNS Domain name as specified in <xref target="RFC1035">RFC 1035</xref>
                        and revisions.
                    </t>
                        <t hangText="Domain Name System (DNS)">
                            The Internet naming system specified in <xref target="RFC1035">RFC 1035</xref>
                            and revisions.
                        </t>
                        <t hangText="DNS Security (DNSSEC)">
                            Extensions to the DNS that provide authentication services as specified in 
                            <xref target="RFC4033">RFC 4033</xref>
                        and revisions.
                    </t>
                      <t hangText="Issuer">
                        An entity that issues Certificates.
                      </t>
                        <t hangText="Extended Issuer Authorization Set">
                            The most specific Issuer Authorization Set that is active for a domain.
                            This is either the Issuer Authorization Set for the domain itself, or
                            if that is empty, the Issuer Authorization Set for the corresponding 
                            Public Delegation Point.
                        </t>
                        <t hangText="Issuer Authorization Set">
                            The set of Authorization Entries for a domain name that are flagged
                            for use by Issuers. Analogous to an Access
                            Control List but with no ordering specified.</t>
                        <t hangText="Public Delegation Point">
                            The Domain Name suffix under which DNS names are delegated by a public 
                            DNS registry such as a Top Level Directory.
                            </t>
                        <t hangText="Public Key Infrastructure X.509 (PKIX)">
                            Standards and specifications issued by the IETF that apply the
                            <xref target="X.509">X.509</xref> certificate standards specified
                            by the ITU to Internet applications as specified in
                            <xref target="RFC5280">RFC 5280</xref> and related documents.
                        </t>
                        <t hangText="Resource Record (RR)">
                            A set of attributes bound to a Domain Name.</t>
                        <t hangText="Relying Party">
                            A party that makes use of an application whose operation depends on
                            use of a Certificate for making a security decision.</t>
                        <t hangText="Relying Application">
                            An application whose operation depends on
                            use of a Certificate for making a security decision.
                        </t>

                    </list>
                </t>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section title="Introduction">
            <t>
                The Certification Authority Authorization (CAA) DNS Resource Record allows a
                DNS domain name holder to specify the Certification Authorities authorized 
                to issue certificates for that domain. Publication of CAA resource records 
                allow a public Certification Authority (CA) to implement additional
                controls to reduce the risk of unintended certificate mis-issue.
            </t>
            <t>
                Conformance with a published CAA record is a necessary but not sufficient
                condition for issue of a certificate.
                Before issuing a certificate, a PKIX CA is required to validate the 
                request according to the policies set out in its Certificate Policy 
                Statement. In the case of a public CA that validates certificate requests
                as a third party, the certificate will be typically issued under 
                a public root certificate embedded in one or more relevant Relying Applications.
            </t>
            <t>
                Criteria for inclusion of embedded root certificates in applications 
                are outside the scope of this document but typically require the CA to publish a 
                Certificate Practices Statement (CPS) that specifies how the requirements
                of the Certificate Policy (CP) are achieved and provide an annual
                audit statement of their performance against their CPS performed by
                an independent third party auditor.
            </t>
            <t>
                Verification of certificate requests against CAA records published in
                the corresponding domain is currently under consideration by the 
                CA-Browser Forum as a required element of the Basic Requirements for
                Certificate issue.
            </t>
            <t>
                CAA records only describe the current state of Certification Authority
                certificate issue authority. Since a certificate is typically valid 
                for at least a year, it is possible that a certificate that is not
                conformant with the CAA records currently published was conformant
                with the CAA records published at the time that it was issued. Thus 
                Relying Applications MUST NOT use failure to conform to currently 
                published CAA records specifying issue authorization as a certificate
                validity criteria.
            </t>
          <t>
            CAA Records MAY be used by Certificate Evaluators as a possible indicator 
            of a security policy violation. Such use SHOULD take account of the 
            possibility that the published CAA records changed between the time the 
            certificate was issued and the time that they were observed by the 
            Certificate Evaluator.
          </t>

            <section title="The CAA RR type">
                <t>
                    A CAA RR publishes a CAA property entry that corresponds to the 
                    specified domain name. Multiple property entries MAY be associated 
                    with the same domain name by publishing multiple CAA RRs at that 
                    domain name. Each property 
                    entry MAY be tagged with one or more of the following flag values:

                </t>
                <t>
                    <list style="hanging">
                        <t hangText="Critical">
                            If set, indicates that the corresponding property entry
                            tag MUST be understood if the semantics of the CAA 
                            record are to be correctly understood by the specified
                            audience.</t>
                        <t>Issuers MUST NOT issue certificates for a domain if
                        the Extended Issuer Authorization Set contains unknown
                        property entry tags that have both the Issuer and Critical
                        bits set.
                        </t>                     
                    </list>
                </t>
               <t>
                    The following
                    properties are defined:
                    
                </t>
                <t>
                    <list style="hanging">
                        <t hangText="issue &lt;Domain Name&gt; [; &lt;tag=value&gt; ]*">
                            The issue property entry declares an authorization entry
                            granting authorization to issue to the holder of the 
                            specified domain name or a party acting under the express 
                            written authority of the holder of the domain name.
                        </t>
                      <t hangText="iodef &lt;URL&gt;">
                        Specifies a URL to which an issuer
                        MAY report certificate
                        issue requests that are inconsistent with the issuer's Certification
                        Practices or Certification Policy or that a certificate evaluator may
                        use to report observation of a possible policy violation. The IODEF 
                        format is used.
                        <xref target="RFC5070"/>
                      </t>
                    </list>
                </t>

                <t>
                    The following example informs CAs that certificates MUST NOT be issued
                    except by the holder of the domain name 'ca.example.net' or an
                    authorized agent thereof.
                    Since the policy is published
                    at the Public Delegation Point, the policy applies to all subordinate
                    domains under example.com.
                </t>
                <figure>
                    <artwork>
<![CDATA[$ORIGIN example.com
.       CAA 0 issue "ca.example.net"]]>
                    </artwork>
                </figure>
              <t>
                If the domain name holder specifies one or more iodef properties, a
                certificate issuer MAY report invalid certificate requests to that address.
                In the following example the domain name holder specifies that reports MAY
                be made by means of email with the IODEF data as an attachment or a Web 
                service or both:
              </t>
              <figure>
                <artwork>
<![CDATA[$ORIGIN example.com
.       CAA 0 issue "ca.example.net"
.       CAA 0 iodef "mailto:security@example.com"
.       CAA 0 iodef "http://iodef.example.com/"]]>
                </artwork>
              </figure>
              <t>
                    A certificate issuer MAY specify additional parameters that allow
                    customers to specify additional parameters governing certificate issue.
                    For example, the Certification Policy under which the certificate is 
                    to be issued or the authentication process to be used.
                </t>

                <figure>
                    <artwork>
<![CDATA[$ORIGIN example.com
.       CAA 0 issue "ca.example.net; account=230123"]]>
                    </artwork>
                </figure>
              <t>
                The syntax and semantics of such parameters is left to site policy and is
                 outside the scope of this document.
              </t>
                    <t>
                    Future versions of this specification MAY use the critical
                    flag to introduce new semantics that MUST be understood for
                    correct processing of the record, preventing Certification
                    Authorities that do not recognize the record from issuing 
                    certificates.
                    </t>
                    <t>
                      In the following example, the property 'tbs' is flagged as
                      critical. Neither the example.net CA, nor any other issuer is
                      authorized to issue under either policy unless the processing rules for the
                      'tbs' property tag are understood.
                    </t>
                    <figure>
                        <artwork>
<![CDATA[$ORIGIN example.com
.       CAA 0 issue "ca.example.net; policy=ev"
.       CAA 128 tbs "Unknown" ]]>
                        </artwork>
                    </figure>
                  <t>
                    Note that the above restrictions only apply to issue of certificates.
                    Since the validity of an end entity certificate is typically a 
                    year or more it is quite possible that the CAA records published
                    at a domain will change between the issue of the certificate and 
                    verification by a relying party.
                  </t>

                </section>
            </section>
            <section title="Certification Authority Processing">

                <t>
                    Before issue of a certificate, a compliant CA MUST check for publication
                    of a relevant CAA Resource Record(s) and if such record(s) are published, that
                    the certificate requested is consistent with them. If the certificate
                    requested is not consistent with the relevant CAA RRs, the CA MUST
                    NOT issue the certificate.
                </t>
                <t>
                    The Issuer Authorization Set for a domain name consists of the set of
                    all CAA Authorization Entries declared for the canonical form
                    of the specified domain.
                </t>
              <t>
                The Extended Issuer Authorization Set for a domain name is determined as
                follows:
              </t>
              <t>
                <list style='symbols'>
                  <t>
                    If the Issuer Authorization Set for the domain is empty, the
                    Extended Issuer Authorization Set is empty.
                  </t>
                  <t>
                    If the immediately superior node in the DNS hierarchy is a
                    Public Delegation Point, the Extended Issuer Authorization Set 
                    is empty.
                  </t>
                  <t>
                    Otherwise the Extended Issuer Authorization Set is that of the
                    immediately superior node in the DNS hierarchy.
                  </t> 
                </list>
                
              </t>
              <t>
                For example, if the zone example.com has a CAA record defined for
                caa.example.com and no other domain in the zone, the Issuer Authorization
                Set is empty for all domains other than caa.example.com. The 
                Extended Issuer Authorization Set is empty for example.com (because
                .com is a Public Delegation Point) and for x.example.com. The Extended 
                Issuer set for x.caa.example.com, x.x.caa.example.com, etc. is the
                Issuer Authorization Set for caa.example.com.
              </t>                  
                  

                <t>
                    If the Extended Issuer Authorization Set for a domain name is not empty, a
                    Certification Authority MUST NOT issue a certificate unless it conforms
                    to at least one authorization entry in the Extended Issuer Authorization Set.
                </t>            

                <section title="Canonical Domain Name">
                    <t>
                        The DNS defines the CNAME and DNAME mechanisms for specifying 
                        domain name aliases. The canonical name of a DNS name is the
                        name that results from performing all DNS alias operations.
                    </t>
                    <t>
                        An issuer MUST perform CNAME and DNAME
                        processing as defined in the DNS specifications <xref target="RFC1035">
                        1035</xref> to resolve CAA records.
                    </t>
                </section>
                <section title="Use of DNS Security">
                    <t>
                      Use of DNSSEC to authenticate CAA RRs is strongly recommended but
                      not required. An issuer MUST NOT issue certificates if doing so would
                      conflict with the corresponding extended issuer authorization set
                      whether the corresponding DNS records are signed or not.
                    </t>
                    <t>
                      Use of DNSSEC allows an issuer to acquire and archive a non-repudiable
                      proof that they were authorized to issue certificates for the domain.
                    </t>
                </section>
                <section title="Archive">
                    <t>
                      A compliant issuer SHOULD maintain an archive of the DNS transactions
                      used to verify CAA eligibility.
                    </t>
                    <t>
                      In particular an issuer SHOULD ensure that where DNSSEC data is
                      available that the corresponding signature and NSEC/NSEC3 records
                      are preserved so as to enable later compliance audits.
                    </t>
                </section>
            </section>



        <section title="Mechanism">
            <section title="Syntax">
                <t>
                    A CAA RR contains a single property entry consisting of a tag value pair. 
                    Each tag represents
                    a property of the CAA record. The value of a CAA property is that
                    specified in the corresponding value field.
                </t>
                <t>
                    A domain name MAY have multiple CAA RRs associated with it 
                     and a given property MAY
                    be specified more than once. 
                </t>

                <t>
                    The CAA data field contains one property entry.  
                    A property entry consists of the following data fields:
                </t>
                <figure>
                    <artwork>
<![CDATA[+0-1-2-3-4-5-6-7-|0-1-2-3-4-5-6-7-|
| Flags          | Tag Length = n |
+----------------+----------------+...+---------------+
| Tag char 0     | Tag Char 1     |...| Tag Char n-1  |
+----------------+----------------+...+---------------+
+----------------+----------------+.....+---------------+
| Data byte 0    | Data byte 1    |.....| Data byte m-1 |
+----------------+----------------+.....+---------------+]]>
                    </artwork>
                </figure>
                <t>
                    Where n is the length specified in the tag length field 
                    and m is the remaining octets in the data field (m = d - n - 2) 
                    where d is the length of the data section.
                </t>
                <t>
                The data fields are defined as follows:
                </t>
                <t>
                    <list style="hanging">
                        <t hangText="Flags">One octet containing the following fields:

                        
                        <list style="hanging">
                            <t hangText="Bit 0: Issuer Critical Flag">
                                If the value is set (1), the critical flag is asserted and the
                                property
                                MUST be understood if the CAA record is to be correctly processed
                                by a certificate issuer.
                            </t>
                            <t>
                                A Certification Authority MUST NOT issue certificates for any
                                Domain that contains a CAA critical property for an unknown
                                or unsupported property type that has the issuer bit set.
                            </t>
                        </list>
                        </t>
                            <t>
                            Note that according to the conventions set out in  <xref target="RFC1035">RFC 1035</xref>
                            Bit 0 is the Most Significant Bit and Bit 7 is the Least Significant. 
                            Thus the flags value 1 means that bit 7 is set while a value of 128 
                            means that bit 0 is set according to this convention.
                            </t>
                      <t>
                        All other bit positions are reserved for future use.
                      </t>
                      <t>
                        To ensure compatibility with futuree extensions to CAA, DNS records 
                        compliant with this version of the CAA specification
                        MUST clear (0) all reserved flags bits.
                        Applications that interpret CAA records MUST ignore the value of all 
                        reserved flag bits.
                      </t>
                        <t hangText="Tag Length">
                            A single octet containing an unsigned integer
                            specifying the tag length
                            in octets. The tag length MUST be at least 1 and
                            SHOULD be no more than 15.
                        </t>


                        <t hangText="Tag">The property identifier, a sequence of ASCII characters.</t>
                        <t>
                            Tag values MAY contain ASCII characters a through z
                            and the numbers 0 through 9. Tag values MUST NOT contain
                            any other characters. Matching of tag values is case
                            insensitive.
                        </t>

                        <t hangText="Value">A sequence of octets representing the property
                        value. Property values are encoded as binary values and MAY employ
                        sub-formats.</t>
                        <t>
                        The length of the value field is specified implicitly as the remaining
                        length of the enclosing Resource Record data field.
                        </t>
                    </list>
                    
                </t>

                <section title="Canonical Presentation Format" anchor="zoneformat">

                <t>
                    The canonical presentation format of the CAA record is as follows:
                </t>
                  <figure>
                    <artwork>
<![CDATA[CAA <flags> <tag> <data>]]>
                    </artwork>
                  </figure>
                    <t>
                    Where:
                    </t>
                    <t>
                        <list style="hanging">
                            <t hangText="flags">Is an unsigned integer between 0 and 255.</t>
                            <t hangText="tag">
                                Is a non-zero sequence of ASCII letter and
                                numbers in lower case.
                            </t>
                            <t hangText="data">
                                Is the ascii text Encoding of the value field
                            </t>
                        </list>
                    </t>
                </section>    
            </section>

          <section title="CAA issue Property">
            <t>
              The issue property is used to request that certificate issuers
              perform CAA issue restriction processing for the domain and to 
              grant authorization to specific certificate issuers.
            </t>
            <t>
              The CAA issue property value has the following sub-syntax (specified in 
              ABNF as per <xref target="RFC4234"/>).
            </t>
            <figure>
            <artwork>
<![CDATA[Property = space [domain] * (space ";" parameter) space

domain = label *("." label)
label = 1* (ALPHA / DIGIT / "_" / "-" )

space = *(SP / HTAB)

parameter =  / space tag "=" value

tag = 1* (ALPHA / DIGIT)

value = *VCHAR | DQUOTE *(%x20-21 / %x23-7E) DQUOTE 
]]>
            </artwork>
            </figure>            

            <t>
              A CAA record with an issue parameter tag that does not specify a
              domain name
              is a request that certificate issuers
              perform CAA issue restriction processing for the corresponding 
              domain without granting
              authorization to any certificate issuer.
            </t>
            <t>
              This form of issue restriction would be appropriate for use with
              a domain that the domain name owner does not intend to be used.
            </t>
            <t>
              For example, the following CAA record set requests that
              no certificates be issued for the domain 'nocerts.example.com'
              by any certificate issuer.
            </t>
            <figure>
              <artwork>
<![CDATA[nocerts.example.com       CAA 0 issue ";"]]>
              </artwork>
            </figure>
            <t>
              A CAA record with an issue parameter tag that specifies a
              domain name
              is a request that certificate issuers
              perform CAA issue restriction processing for the corresponding
              domain and grants
              authorization to the certificate issuer specified by the domain name.
            </t>
            <t>
              For example, the following CAA record set requests that
              no certificates be issued for the domain 'certs.example.com'
              by any certificate issuer other than the example.net certificate issuer.
            </t>
            <figure>
              <artwork>
<![CDATA[certs.example.com       CAA 0 issue "example.net"]]>
              </artwork>
            </figure>
            <t>
              CAA authorizations are additive. thus the result of specifying both the empty 
              issuer and a specified issuer is the same as specifying just the specified 
              issuer alone.
            </t>
            <t>
              An issuer MAY choose to specify issuer-parameters that further constrain the
              issue of certificates by that issuer. For example specifying that certificates
              are to be subject to specific validation polices, billed to certain 
              accounts or issued off specific roots.
            </t>
            <t>
              The syntax and semantics of issuer-parameters are determined by the
              issuer alone.
            </t>
          </section>
          <section title="CAA iodef Property">
            <t>
              The iodef property specifies a means of reporting certificate
              issue requests or cases of certificate issue for the corresponding 
              domain that violate the security policy of the issuer or the domain 
              name holder.
            </t>
            <t>
              The Incident Object Description Exchange Format (IODEF) <xref target="RFC5070"/>
              is used to 
              present the incident report in machine readable form.
            </t>
            <t>
              The iodef property takes a URL as its parameter. The URL scheme type 
              determines the method used for reporting:
            </t>
            <t>
              <list style="hanging">
                <t hangText="mailto">
                  The IODEF incident report is reported as a MIME email attachment 
                  to an SMTP email that is submitted to the mail address specified.
                  The mail message sent SHOULD contain a brief text message to alert
                  the recipient to the nature of the attachment.
                </t>
                <t hangText="http or https">
                  The IODEF report is submitted as a Web Service request to the
                  HTTP address specified using the protocol specified in 
                  <xref target="RFC6046"/>.
                </t>
              </list>
            </t>
         
          </section>
          
        </section>
        <section title="Security Considerations">
            <t>CAA Records assert a security policy that the holder of a domain name 
            wishes to be observed by certificate issuers. The effectiveness of CAA
            records as an access control is thus dependent on observance of CAA 
            constraints by issuers.
            </t>
          <t>
            Observance of CAA records by issuers is subject to accountability controls
            and proposed industry requirements.
          </t>
            <t>
            While a Certification Authority can choose to ignore published CAA 
            records, doing so increases the both the probability that they will 
            mis-issue a certificate and the consequences of doing so. Once it is
            known that a CA observes CAA records, malicious registration requests 
            will  disproportionately target the negligent CAs that do not,
            and so the mis-issue rate amongst the negligent CAs will increase.
            Since the CA could clearly have avoided the mis-issue by performing
            CAA processing, the likelihood of sanctions against the negligent CA
            is increased. Failure to observe CAA issue restrictions provides an
            objective criteria for excluding issuers from embedded roots of trust.
            </t>
            <t>
            In contrast, a Certification Authority that processes CAA records
            correctly can reasonably claim that any residual 
            mis-issue event could have been avoided had the Domain Name holder
            published appropriate CAA records.
            </t>

            <section title="Mis-Issue by Authorized Certification Authority">
                <t>
                    Use of CAA records does not provide protection against mis-issue
                    by an authorized Certification Authority. 
                </t>
                <t>
                    Domain name holders SHOULD ensure that the CAs they authorize to issue
                    certificates for their domains employ appropriate controls to ensure
                    that certificates are only issued to authorized parties within their
                    organization.
                </t>
                <t>
                    Such controls are most appropriately determined by the domain name
                    holder and the authorized CA(s) directly and are thus out of scope 
                    of this document.
                </t>
            </section>
            <section title="Suppression or spoofing of CAA records">
                <t>
                    Suppression of the CAA record or insertion of a bogus CAA record could
                    enable an attacker to obtain a certificate from a CA that was not 
                    authorized to issue for that domain name.
                </t>

                <section title="Certification Authorities">
                    <t>
                        Since a certificate issued by a CA can be valid for several years,
                        the consequences of a spoofing or suppression attack are much
                        greater for Certification Authorities and so additional countermeasures
                        are justified.
                    </t>
                <t>
                    A CA MUST mitigate this risk by employing DNSSEC verification whenever
                    possible and rejecting certificate requests in any case where it is
                    not possible to verify the non-existence or contents of a relevant
                    CAA record.
                </t>
                <t>
                    In cases where DNSSEC is not deployed in a corresponding domain, a 
                    CA SHOULD attempt to mitigate this risk by employing appropriate
                    DNS security controls. For example all portions of the DNS lookup
                    process SHOULD be performed against the authoritative name server.
                    Cached data MUST NOT be relied on but MAY be used to support additional
                    anti-spoofing or anti-suppression controls.
                </t>
                </section>

            </section>
            <section title="Denial of Service">
                <t>
                    Introduction of a malformed or malicious CAA RR could in theory
                    enable a Denial of Service attack.
                </t>
                <t>
                    This specific threat is not considered to add significantly to 
                    the risk of running an insecure DNS service.
                </t>
              <section title="Issuer">
                <t>
                  An attacker could in principle perform a Denial of Service attack
                  against an issuer by requesting a certificate with a maliciously long 
                  DNS name. In practice the DNS protocol imposes a maximum name length
                  and the protocol does not exacerbate the existing need to mitigate
                  Denial of Service attacks to any meaningful degree.
                </t>
              </section>
            </section>
            <section title="Abuse of the Critical Flag">
                <t>
                    A Certification Authority could make use of the critical flag
                    to trick customers into publishing records which prevent 
                    competing Certification Authorities from issuing certificates
                    even though the customer intends to authorize multiple 
                    providers.
                </t>
                <t>
                    In practice, such an attack would be of minimal effect since 
                    any competent competitor that found itself unable to issue certificates 
                    due to lack of support for a property marked critical SHOULD
                    investigate the cause and report the reason to the customer
                    who will thus discover the deception. It is thus unlikely that the attack would 
                    succeed and the attempt might lay the perpetrator open to 
                    civil or criminal sanctions.
                </t>
            </section>
        </section>

        <section title="IANA Considerations">
            <section title="Registration of the CAA Resource Record Type">
              <t>
                [Note to IANA, the CAA resource record has already been assigned. 
                On issue of this draft as an RFC, the record should be updated to 
                reflect this document as the authoritative specificaton and this
                paragraph (but not the following ones deleted]
              </t>
                <t>
                    IANA has assigned Resource Record Type 257 for the CAA Resource
                    Record Type and added the line depicted below to the registry named
                    Resource Record (RR) TYPEs and QTYPEs as defined in BCP 42 RFC 5395
                    [RFC5395] and located at
                    http://www.iana.org/assignments/dns-parameters.
                </t>
                <figure>
                    <artwork>
<![CDATA[             Value and meaning                                Reference
-----------  ---------------------------------------------    ---------
CAA          257 Certification Authority Restriction          [RFC-THIS]]]>
</artwork>
                </figure>
            </section>
            <section title="Certification Authority Authorization Properties">
              <t>
                [Note to IANA, this is a new registry that needs to be created and this 
                paragraph but not the following ones deleted.]
              </t>
                <t>
                    IANA has created the Certification Authority Authorization Properties
                    registry with the following initial values:
                </t>
                <figure>
                    <artwork>
<![CDATA[
             Meaning                                          Reference
-----------  -----------------------------------------------  ---------
issue        Authorization Entry by Domain                    [RFC-THIS]
iodef        Report incident by means of IODEF format report  [RFC-THIS]
auth         Reserved
path         Reserved
policy       Reserved]]>
                    </artwork>
                </figure>

                <t>
                    Addition of tag identifiers requires a public specification 
                    and expert review as set out in <xref target="RFC5395">RFC5395</xref>
                </t>
            </section>
        </section>

    </middle>



    <back>
        <references title="Normative References">
            &RFC1035;
            &RFC2045;
            &RFC2119;
            &RFC4033;
            &RFC4055;
          &RFC4234;
            &RFC5280;            
            &RFC5395;
            &RFC5070;
            &RFC6046;
          <reference anchor="X.509">
                <front>
                    <title>
                        ITU-T Recommendation X.509 (11/2008): Information
                        technology - Open systems interconnection - The
                        Directory: Public-key and attribute certificate
                        frameworks
                    </title>
                    <author>
                        <organization>
                            International Telecommunication Union
                        </organization>
                    </author>
                    <date month="November" year="2008"/>
                </front>
                <seriesInfo name="ITU-T Recommendation" value="X.509"/>
                <format type="HTML" target="http://www.itu.int/itu-t/recommendations/rec.aspx?rec=X.509"/>
            </reference>


        </references>
<!--        <references title="Non Normative References">

        </references> -->

    </back>
</rfc>
