<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!-- One method to get references from the online citation libraries.
     There has to be one entity for each item to be referenced. 
     An alternate method (rfc include) is described in the references. -->

<!ENTITY RFC2119 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3279 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3279.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5035 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5035.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5280 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5280.xml">
]>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<!-- used by XSLT processors -->
<!-- For a complete list and description of processing instructions (PIs), 
     please see http://xml.resource.org/authoring/README.html. -->
<!-- Below are generally applicable Processing Instructions (PIs) that most I-Ds might want to use.
     (Here they are set differently than their defaults in xml2rfc v1.32) -->
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<!-- give errors regarding ID-nits and DTD validation -->
<!-- control the table of contents (ToC) -->
<?rfc toc="no"?>
<!-- generate a ToC -->
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<!-- the number of levels of subsections in ToC. default: 3 -->
<!-- control references -->
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<!-- use symbolic references tags, i.e, [RFC2119] instead of [1] -->
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<!-- sort the reference entries alphabetically -->
<!-- control vertical white space 
     (using these PIs as follows is recommended by the RFC Editor) -->
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<!-- do not start each main section on a new page -->
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<!-- keep one blank line between list items -->

<?rfc autobreaks="yes" ?>

<rfc category="std" docName="draft-ietf-pkix-certid-keyid-00" ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="Unambiguous Certificate and Key IDs">Syntaxes for Unambiguous Naming
		of Certificates and Public Keys</title>

    <author fullname="Sean Leonard" initials="S.L." surname="Leonard">
      <organization>Penango, Inc.</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>1215 K Street</street>
					 <street>17th Floor</street>
          <city>Sacramento</city><region>CA</region><code>95814</code>
          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>

        <email>dev+ietf@seantek.com</email>
				 <uri>http://www.penango.com/</uri>
        <!-- uri and facsimile elements may also be added -->
      </address>
    </author>

    <date month="February" year="2010" />
    <!-- If the month and year are both specified and are the current ones, xml2rfc will fill 
         in the current day for you. If only the current year is specified, xml2rfc will fill 
	 in the current day and month for you. If the year is not the current one, it is 
	 necessary to specify at least a month (xml2rfc assumes day="1" if not specified for the 
	 purpose of calculating the expiry date).  With drafts it is normally sufficient to 
	 specify just the year. -->
    <!-- Meta-data Declarations -->
    <area>Security</area>

    <workgroup>Network Working Group</workgroup>

    <!-- WG name at the upperleft corner of the doc,
         IETF is fine for individual submissions.  
	 If this element is not present, the default is "Network Working Group",
         which is used by the RFC Editor as a nod to the history of the IETF. -->

   <keyword>otherName</keyword>
   <keyword>CertID</keyword>
	 <keyword>KeyID</keyword>
	 <keyword>ESSCertIDv2</keyword>
	 <keyword>GeneralName</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>This document provides methods to unambiguously identify a particular
			certificate and a particular public key that may or may not be in
			a certificate. This document further provides syntaxes for these methods
			in the otherName field of a GeneralName structure, as used throughout
			the PKIX standards.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>When working with X.509 certificates and other cryptographic structures, it
			may be desirable to refer to another certificate, or to a raw public key,
			directly and unambiguously.
			The "gold standard" for certificates is to refer to the
			certificate's issuer name and serial number. Furthermore,
			<xref target="PKIX" /> and <xref target="X.509" />
			define a subject key identifier extension, which provides a means of identifying
			distinct keys used by the same subject.</t>
			<t>Unfortunately, neither the issuer name and serial number, nor the subject key
			identifier, are guaranteed to be universally unique. Multiple CA certificates
			can share the same subject name, and their use depends on the state of the trust
			anchors during certificate path validation. The subject key identifier is
			meant to facilitate path construction <xref target="PKIX" />, but is only unique
			to the extent that the certificate issuer guarantees it to be unique
			within some domain.</t>
			<t>Therefore, this document provides a pair of ASN.1 structures to unambiguously
			identify a particular certificate and a particular public key. The method
			used here follows the same philosophy as the CertID (ESSCertIDv2 structure)
			in <xref target="RFC5035" format="none">RFC 5035</xref>: digest the
			target with a cryptographic hash algorithm, and optionally
			refer to the target using standardized naming. Using this method,
			an implementation can cryptographically verify
			that the right certificate or public key is chosen,
			but can also use standard methods to locate
			the certificate or public key
			if the search facility does not index by the particular hash.</t>
			<t>This document further defines otherName syntaxes for these structures, suitable
			for experession in a GeneralName. That way, any protocol or format that uses
			a GeneralName or GeneralNames can unambiguously name a certificate or key.</t>

      <section title="Requirements Language">
        <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
        "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
        document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
        target="RFC2119" format="none">RFC 2119</xref>.</t>
      </section>
    </section>
		
		<section title="CertID Structure for Identifying Certificates">
			<t>The following structure unambiguously identifies a certificate by its hash.
			This structure is simply ESSCertIDv2 from
			<xref target="RFC5035" format="none">RFC 5035</xref>, with additional clarifying
			semantics discussed below.</t>
			<figure>
				<artwork><![CDATA[
  CertID ::= ESSCertIDv2
]]></artwork>
			</figure>
			<figure>
			<preamble>ESSCertIDv2 is reproduced below for convenience.</preamble>
				<artwork><![CDATA[
    ESSCertIDv2 ::=  SEQUENCE {
        hashAlgorithm           AlgorithmIdentifier
               DEFAULT {algorithm id-sha256},
        certHash                 Hash,
        issuerSerial             IssuerSerial OPTIONAL
    }

    Hash ::= OCTET STRING

    IssuerSerial ::= SEQUENCE {
        issuer                   GeneralNames,
        serialNumber             CertificateSerialNumber
    }
]]></artwork>
			</figure>
			<t>The fields of CertID (ESSCertIDv2, as used here) are defined as follows.</t>
			<t>hashAlgorithm contains the identifier of the algorithm used
			in computing certHash.</t>
			<t>certHash is computed over the entire DER-encoded certificate, including
			the signature, tag, and length octets, using the algorithm specified in
			hashAlgorithm.</t>
			<t>issuerSerial holds the identification of the certificate.
			issuerSerial is optional. If present, it may be used to facilitate lookup
			of the certificate. Additionally, an implementation may use issuerSerial
			to eliminate a certificate from consideration early if the implementation
			does not support the certificate type.</t>
			<t>The issuerSerial field is normative if it is present. Specifically,
			if a certificate is found that matches the issuerSerial, but does not match
			the hash, an implementation MUST skip or reject that certificate,
			because it does not match the hash. If a certificate is found that matches
			the hash, but does not match the issuerSerial, an implementation MUST
			skip or reject that certificate, because it does not match the issuerSerial.
			The assumption is that the implementation that generated CertID must have
			the certificate and must be able to process it in order to create a proper
			issuerSerial for it.</t>
			<t>The semantics of issuerSerial are the same as those in
			<xref target="RFC5035" format="none">RFC 5035</xref>.</t>
		</section>
		<section title="KeyID Structure for Identifying Public Keys">
			<t>Unlike the CertID structure, there is no corresponding universal structure
			(among the various standards surveyed) to unambiguously name a public key.
			This section defines KeyID, which is such a structure.</t>
			<figure>
				<artwork><![CDATA[
  KeyID ::= CHOICE {
    subjectPublicKeyInfo  [0] SubjectPublicKeyInfo,
    subjectPublicKeyRef   [1] SubjectPublicKeyRef }

  SubjectPublicKeyRef ::= SEQUENCE {
    hashAlgorithm AlgorithmIdentifier
      DEFAULT {algorithm id-sha256},
    keyHash Hash,
    subjectPublicKeyAlgorithm AlgorithmIdentifier OPTIONAL,
    subjectKeyIdentifier SubjectKeyIdentifier OPTIONAL,
    subjectKeyCert ESSCertIDv2 OPTIONAL }
]]></artwork>
			</figure>
			<t>A KeyID is a CHOICE of a SubjectPublicKeyInfo, defined
			in <xref target="PKIX" />, or a SubjectPublicKeyRef, defined here.
			When KeyID is a SubjectPublicKeyInfo,
			the public key is simply the public key inside of the SubjectPublicKeyInfo.
			When KeyID is a SubjectPublicKeyRef, the public key is the one	that matches
			the following parameters in the SubjectPublicKeyRef.</t>
			<t>SubjectPublicKeyRef includes a hashAlgorithm and a keyHash. The keyHash is
			the output of the hash algorithm identified by hashAlgorithm computed over
			the entire DER-encoded SubjectPublicKeyInfo, including the tag
			and length octets.</t>
			<t>subjectPublicKeyAlgorithm, subjectKeyIdentifier, and subjectKeyCert may
			be included to facilitate lookup of the public key. Additionally, an
			implementation may use subjectPublicKeyAlgorithm to eliminate a public key
			from consideration early if the implementation does not support the algorithm,
			or does not have any keys derived for use with the algorithm.</t>
			<t>The subjectPublicKeyAlgorithm field is normative if it is present.
			When subjectPublicKeyAlgorithm is present, the public key
			MUST have an AlgorithmIdentifier that matches, in addition to a matching
			keyHash.</t>
			<t>If subjectKeyIdentifier or subjectKeyCert are present, an implementation
				MAY use these identifiers to look up a subject public key. Unlike
				subjectPublicKeyAlgorithm, these identifiers
				are not normative. Specifically, if a public key
				is found that is contained within a certificate that matches the particular
				subjectKeyIdentifier, subjectKeyCert, or both, but does not match
				the hash and subjectPublicKeyAlgorithm (if present),
				an implementation MUST skip or reject that public key, because it does not match
				the hash and subjectPublicKeyAlgorithm (if present).
				If public key #1 is found that matches the hash and subjectPublicKeyAlgorithm
				(if present), but public key #1 differs from public key #2 in a certificate
				identified by subjectKeyIdentifier, subjectKeyCert, or both, the
				implementation MUST select public key #1. Similarly, if an implementation
				finds a public key #3 that matches the hash and subjectPublicKeyAlgorithm
				(if present), but cannot find a certificate that matches subjectKeyIdentifier,
				subjectKeyCert, or both, the implementation MUST select public key #3.
				The implementation MUST NOT reject
				public key #3 on the basis that the certificate is missing.
				</t>
			<t>This document does not define the results if two different public keys match
			the same hash and subjectPublicKeyAlgorithm (if present), irrespective
			of whether a single key or certificate containing a key matches on the
			other fields. However, a sensible approach would be to reject both
			keys, and to consider the result a hash collision.</t>
			<t>When generating a KeyID, an implementation may generate a SubjectPublicKeyInfo
			or a SubjectPublicKeyRef. When processing a KeyID, an implementation that
			complies with this document MUST process both SubjectPublicKeyInfo and
			SubjectPublicKeyRef.</t>
			<t>When generating a SubjectPublicKeyRef, an implementation MUST only generate
			subjectKeyCert and subjectKeyIdentifier fields that it believes to be true.
			For example, if a certificate #4 contains a subjectKeyIdentifier 'ABCD'h,
			the implementation may serialize the subjectKeyIdentifier in the
			SubjectPublicKeyRef
			structure as 'ABCD'h, or may omit it entirely. An implementation MAY
			also choose to serialize the subjectKeyIdentifier as a value that it
			received or generated via another method, such as from another certificate.
			However, this document RECOMMENDS that the subjectKeyIdentifier be the
			same subjectKeyIdentifier as recorded in the certificate #4, when certificate #4
			contains a subjectKeyIdentifier.
			</t>
			<t>Other than these requirements, an implementation may choose any subjectKeyCert
			or subjectKeyIdentifier at its discretion. No semantic meaning is inferable
			from choosing a particular subjectKeyCert or subjectKeyIdentifier.
			However, generating these fields based on information that the receiver
			is most likely to have, such as by including the named certificate
			as part of the broader protocol, would be sensible.</t>
			<t>Generating a KeyID that is a public key by value (SubjectPublicKeyInfo) is useful
			when the public key is sufficiently small, such as an elliptic curve
			public key. By way of example, a SHA-512 hash is 64 octets.
			A DER-encoded SubjectPublicKeyRef that identifies a key using SHA-512 will be
			at least 81 octets; with a subjectKeyCert, it will likely be 160
			octets or more. In contrast, an ECC key with a 256-bit prime modulus has
			a DER-encoded SubjectPublicKeyInfo of approximately (TBD) octets. The savings
			in size alone, not to mention the time saved looking up the public
			key from a database, warrant including the public key by value with SubjectPublicKeyInfo
			instead of by reference with SubjectPublicKeyRef.</t>
			<t>A KeyID can only refer to a public key of an asymmetric keypair; it MUST NOT
			refer to a symmetric key or to an asymmetric private key.
			The <xref target="Security" format="none">Security Considerations</xref>
			section provides further discussion.</t>
		</section>
		
		<section title="GeneralName Definitions" anchor="GeneralName_Defs">
			<t>This section defines the CertIDName and KeyIDName as forms of otherName
			in the GeneralName structure defined in <xref target="PKIX" />.</t>
			<t>When referring to certificates, this document does not limit the selection
			to X.509 public key certificates. The IssuerSerial structure
			<xref target="RFC5035" />
			contains a GeneralNames field that can accomodate other types of
			certificates, such as attribute certificates.</t>
			<section title="CertIDName">
				<t>A CertIDName has the following object identifier and syntax when used in
				a GeneralName.</t>
				<figure>
					<artwork><![CDATA[
  id-on-certID OBJECT IDENTIFIER ::= { id-on TBD }

  CertIDName ::= CertID
]]></artwork>
				</figure>
			</section>
			<section title="KeyIDName">
				<t>A KeyIDName has the following object identifier and syntax when used in
				a GeneralName.</t>
				<figure>
					<artwork><![CDATA[
  id-on-keyID OBJECT IDENTIFIER ::= { id-on TBD }

  KeyIDName ::= KeyID
]]></artwork>
				</figure>
			</section>
			<section title="Usage Guide">
				<t>GeneralName is a very versatile structure because it appears in
				many cryptographic protocols. This document does not define
				all the possible circumstances in which a GeneralName/otherName
				with id-on-certID or id-on-keyID may occur, or the complete semantics
				in such circumstances. However, some possible (non-normative) usages follow.</t>
				<t>When a protocol uses one
				or more GeneralNames to name services or endpoints, id-on-certID
				and id-on-keyID might constrain the service or endpoint to
				use the particular named certificate or key. For example, if a service
				is named in the Authority Information Access extenison
				of an X.509 certificate, a GeneralName with otherName id-on-certID
				might constrain the service so that it can only be accessed
				when it presents the associated certificate.</t>
				<t>The CertIDName and KeyIDName GeneralName types are not intended
				to change or extend certificate validation procedures. In the previous example,
				using id-on-certID merely names a service by its certificate.
				How the client locates the service, and
				whether the client accepts the service's certificate, are separate matters.
				A client might use the optional issuerSerial in CertIDName
				to retrieve the certificate, which the client validates using
				the the certificate path validation algorithm. If valid,
				the certificate may then provide
				a subject alternative name containing a uniformResourceIdentifier
				or dNSName to access the service using TCP/IP. A client
				would not access the service unless the certificate is valid,
				which the client determines as a local matter.
				</t>
			</section>
		</section>

    <!-- This PI places the pagebreak correctly (before the section title) in the text output. -->

    <?rfc needLines="8" ?>

    <section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>The author thanks Russ Housley and Jim Schaad for direction and guidance
			during the development of this document.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>This memo includes no request to IANA.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
			<t>The CertID and KeyID structures defined here provide integrity checking of
			the named certificate or key, but are not themselves integrity-checked. An
			implementer should use these structures within other integrity-checked
			structures, such as within X.509 public key or attribute certificates.</t>
			<t>Weak hash algorithms will limit the utility of these structures.
			An implementation must skip or reject certificates or keys when the
			cryptographic integrity of the hash function is in doubt.
			On the other hand, an advanced algorithm may not be broadly compatible
			with all possible relying parties. Implementers should be aware of this tension
			when choosing a hash algorithm.</t>
      <t>A KeyID MUST NOT refer to a symmetric key or to an asymmetric private key.
			Referring to such keys by value (with SubjectPublicKeyInfo)
			would destroy the security properties
			of keeping such keys secret, since KeyID is intended for use in public documents
			such as certificates or other signed objects. Similar considerations
			apply to referring to such keys by reference
			(with SubjectPublicKeyRef). Additionally,
			<xref target="PKIX" format="none">RFC 5280 (PKIX)</xref> and
			<xref target="RFC3279" format="none">RFC 3279</xref>
			fix the semantics of SubjectPublicKeyInfo
			(and by extension, SubjectPublicKeyRef) to asymmetric public keys.
			</t>
			<t>The GeneralName syntaxes in <xref target="GeneralName_Defs" /> only provide
			"name" semantics; "bind" semantics are not implied. In particular,
			an X.509 public key certificate binds a subject named in the subject Name field
			and the subjectAltName extension to a single public key. The mere use of CertIDName
			or KeyIDName in such a certificate does not bind the subject to
			additional public keys. However, other specifications are free
			to create "bind" semantics within their scopes.
			</t>
    </section>
    <?rfc needLines="8" ?>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      &RFC2119;
      <reference anchor="PKIX">
<front>
<title>Internet X.509 Public Key Infrastructure Certificate and Certificate Revocation List (CRL) Profile</title>
<author initials='D.' surname='Cooper' fullname='D. Cooper'>
<organization /></author>
<author initials='S.' surname='Santesson' fullname='S. Santesson'>
<organization /></author>
<author initials='S.' surname='Farrell' fullname='S. Farrell'>
<organization /></author>
<author initials='S.' surname='Boeyen' fullname='S. Boeyen'>
<organization /></author>
<author initials='R.' surname='Housley' fullname='R. Housley'>
<organization /></author>

<author initials='W.' surname='Polk' fullname='W. Polk'>
<organization /></author>
<date year='2008' month='May' />
</front>
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='5280' />
<format type='TXT' octets='352580' target='ftp://ftp.isi.edu/in-notes/rfc5280.txt' />
      </reference>
      &RFC5035;
      &RFC3279;
      <reference anchor="X.509">
			<!-- TIP: remove the quotes in the text output -->
<front><title>Information technology - Open Systems Interconnection -
The Directory: Public-key and attribute certificate frameworks</title>
<author><organization>ITU-T Recommendation X.509 (2005) | ISO/IEC 9594-8:2005</organization></author>
</front>
      </reference>
    </references>

    <section anchor="app-asn1" title="ASN.1 Modules">
      <t>This Appendix will provide ASN.1 modules in a future
			revision.</t>
			<section anchor="app-asn1-1988" title="1988 ASN.1 Module">
				<t>TBD</t>
			</section>
    </section>
  </back>
</rfc>
