<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<rfc ipr="trust200902" docName="draft-cheneau-csi-send-sig-agility-00" updates="RFC3971">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="Signature Algorithm Agility in SEND">
			Signature Algorithm Agility in the Secure Neighbor Discovery (SEND) Protocol
		</title>
    <author initials="T.C" surname="Cheneau" fullname="Tony Cheneau">
      <organization abbrev="TMSP">
				Institut TELECOM, TELECOM SudParis, CNRS SAMOVAR UMR 5157 
			</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>9 rue Charles Fourier </street>
          <city>Evry</city>
          <code>91011</code>
          <country>France</country>
        </postal>
        <email>tony.cheneau@it-sudparis.eu</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author initials="M.M" surname="Maknavicius" fullname="Maryline Laurent-Maknavicius">
      <organization abbrev="TMSP">
				Institut TELECOM, TELECOM SudParis, CNRS SAMOVAR UMR 5157 
			</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>9 rue Charles Fourier </street>
          <city>Evry</city>
          <code>91011</code>
          <country>France</country>
        </postal>
        <email>maryline.maknavicius@it-sudparis.eu</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author initials="S.S" surname="Shen" fullname="Sean Shen">
      <organization abbrev="Huawei">Huawei</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>4, South 4th Street, Zhongguancun</street>
          <city>Beijing</city>
          <code>100190</code>
          <country>P.R. China</country>
        </postal>
        <email>sean.s.shen@gmail.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author initials="M.C.V" surname="Vanderveen" fullname="Michaela Vanderveen">
      <organization abbrev="Qualcomm">
				Qualcomm
			</organization>
      <address>
        <email>mvandervn@gmail.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date month="October" year="2009"/>
    <area>Internet</area>
    <workgroup>CGA &amp; SEND maintenance</workgroup>
    <keyword>CGA</keyword>
    <keyword>RSA</keyword>
    <keyword>ECDSA</keyword>
    <abstract>
      <t>This draft describes a mechanism to enable the Secure Neighbor Discovery (SEND) protocol to select
				between different signature algorithms to use with Cryptographically Generated Addresses (CGA).  </t>
    </abstract>
  </front>
  <middle>
    <section anchor="sec-intro" title="Introduction">
      <t> The usage scenarios associated with neighbor discovery have recently been
				extended to include environments with mobile or nomadic nodes. 
				Many of these nodes have limited battery power and computing resources. Therefore, heavy public key signing
				algorithms like RSA are not feasible to support on such constrained nodes.  Fortunately, more lightweight
				yet secure signing algorithms do exist and have been standardized, e.g. Elliptic Curve based algorithms.</t>
      <t>It is then a worthwhile goal to extend secure neighbor discovery to support signing and corresponding hashing 
				algorithm agility. Besides 
				accommodating power-constrained nodes, signing and hashing algorithm agility is also desired as a safety measure
				over time, to offer alternatives when cryptanalysis of one type of algorithm makes significant progress.
			  
			</t>
      <t>The aim of this memo is to outline options for allowing public key signing algorithm and hashing algorithm 
				agility for nodes configured to perform secure neighbor discovery operations.
				The extent to which these options impact existing specifications <xref target="RFC3971"/> and
				<xref target="RFC3972"/> is also addressed.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="sec-problem-overview" title="Overview">
      <section title="Compatibility with existing specifications">
        <t>	The current SEND protocol specification, <xref target="RFC3971"/>, mandates the use of the RSA signature algorithm. 
				Since the time of its writing, different signature algorithms have been shown to be secure and have been 
				adopted by other protocols in an effort to reduce key length, signature generation and verification time, and 
				increase security level.

				This shift in signature algorithm adoption particularly benefits  lightweight devices, which are 
				power and memory-limited but in need of secure signing algorithms support. For these reasons, we feel that 
				the restriction on the signature algorithm for SEND is no longer warranted.</t>
        <section title="Classification of SEND nodes">
          <t>At the time of this writing, there are no known large-scale or even small-scale deployment of <xref target="RFC3971"/>-compatible devices.
				However, in the interest of caution, we assume that there exist nodes that support only the RSA algorithm and that are configured
				to perform secure neighbor discovery. Such nodes may not be updated in the near term or for the foreseeable future.
				On the other hand, it appears that there will be deployments of nodes that support only Elliptic Curve Cryptography as their
				public key algorithm, i.e. ECDSA as a signature algorithm, rather than traditional RSA. </t>
          <t> To ensure that all possible network/link configurations are considered when designing a signature agility solution, 
				we categorize nodes (hosts and routers) according to their support for different signature algorithms, as follows: 
				<list style="hanging"><t hangText="Type H1 host:"><vspace blankLines="1"/> A host that only supports one type of  signature algorithm and has a CGA generated 
										with the public key of this algorithm.  </t><t>Examples of this type of hosts: an old host that does not support signature agility, 
											 i.e. only supports RSA signature algorithm; or, a host that only supports ECDSA signature.</t><t hangText="Type H2 host:"><vspace blankLines="1"/> A host that supports multiple signature algorithms and has a CGA generated with 
						only one key selected from among its supported algorithms.</t><t>Examples of this type of hosts: (1) a host that supports RSA and ECDSA signature algorithms, 
										but only has a CGA derived with an RSA public key; (2) a host that supports RSA and ECDSA signature algorithms, 
										but only has a CGA derived with an ECC public key. </t><t hangText="Type H3 host:"><vspace blankLines="1"/>A host that supports multiple signature algorithms and has a CGA generated with 
										multiple keys of different supported algorithms.</t><t>Such CGA generation is made possible by the introduction of a new  CGA extension (see companion
											draft <xref target="cheneau-csi-cga-pk-agility"/>). Such hosts can be compatible with hosts of other types  for
										secure neighbor discovery.</t><t hangText="Type H4 host:"><vspace blankLines="1"/> A host that supports multiple signature algorithms and has multiple CGAs, each of which is  
										 associated with a single key of one supported algorithm.  For simplicity,
										we do not consider hosts that have multiple CGAs, one or more of which are generated from multiple public
										keys. </t><!-- TC 2/16/2009, Marcelo thinks we should clarify the first sentence --><t> A node MUST select and settle on one CGA when building a trust relationship with another device via SeND (more 
											below). In such cases, a destination node may be reached at a CGA associated with a signature algorithm 
											that the originating node cannot verify.  The destination node will need to securely redirect the originating node 
											to one of its other CGA(s) (presumably with a common signature algorithm). The need for a method to secure 
											the binding between the two CGAs of the destination node  is still an open problem.</t><t>Based on this reasoning, consideration of H4 type nodes is left for future work. <!-- MCV 2/27: this way
										 	we don't appear lazy :-) --></t></list></t>
          <t>Routers are more likely to possess 
					the resources necessary to support multiple signature and hashing algorithms. It is also more feasible
					that routers employ certificates. However, for a basic signature agility solution, we do not mandate that 
					routers support multiple signature and hashing algorithms. </t>
          <t>Possible router devices with different signature algorithm support ability are: 
				<list style="hanging"><t hangText="Type R1 router:"><vspace blankLines="1"/>A router that only supports one type of signature algorithm and has a CGA and Certificate with 
						a public key of this algorithm.  </t><t>Such routers are expected to be commonplace, as compliance with <xref target="RFC3971"/> suffices for them. </t><t hangText="Type R2 router:"><vspace blankLines="1"/> A router that supports multiple types of signature algorithms and has one CGA and Certificate with 
										a public key of one of the algorithm types.  </t><t>This type of router can sign and verify signatures of the type of certificate it owns, and additionally, 
										 it can verify signatures of other algorithm types. </t><t hangText="Type R3 router:"><vspace blankLines="1"/>A router that supports multiple types of signature algorithms
						and has one CGA composed of multiple Publics Keys and multiple certificates containing each a Public Key.</t><t hangText="Type R4 router:"><vspace blankLines="1"/>A router that supports multiple types of signature algorithms and has multiple CGAs 
										and Certificates with public key of several different algorithm types.  </t><t>This type of router can sign and verify signatures of multiple types. Such routers may not be attractive to 
											build and deploy due to increased requirements on its resources. Moreover using multiple CGAs (with no bindings) 
											may make that routers appear as having multiple identities.</t></list>
				</t>
          <t>Note that all types of router presented above can be configured to use SEND over multiple interfaces or to have multiple addresses on the same interface. In this case, the router will use separate CGAs. Such configuration is treated in this draft as if the different addresses refer to separate entities.</t>
        </section>
        <section title="Principal Scenarios">
          <t>Based on the discussion above, a SEND agility solution should at least properly deal with the communication between devices of type H1, H2, H3, R1, R2 and R3.</t>
          <t>
            <list style="empty">
              <t>An H1 or R1 node interacting with an H2 or R2 node: i.e., a node supporting only RSA (for example, 
					an old non-agility node which only supports RFC3971) and a node supporting 
					both RSA and ECDSA (or other new algorithms). These two nodes may <!-- TC s/must/may/ --> be able to perform secure neighbor discovery.</t>
              <t>An H1 or R1 node interacting with another H1 or R1 node, but their algorithms differ: e.g., a node supporting only 
					RSA (for example, an old non-agility node which only supports RFC3971) and a node supporting only 
					ECDSA (or other new algorithms). In this case, implementations supporting SEND signature agility solution 
					may likely realize the incompatibility, while older implementations may not. </t>
              <t>An H2, H3 or R2 node interacting with another H2, H3, or R2 node: e.g., two nodes that support at least one signature algorithms 
					in common will be able to perform secure neighbor discovery.</t>
              <t>An additional rule for  H2, H3 or R2, R3 node interacting with another H2, H3, or R2, R3 node applies: two nodes that support two or more signature algorithms 
					in common (one of which is likely preferred over the other), will be able to perform secure neighbor discovery with any of these signature algorithms.</t>
            </list>
          </t>
        </section>
      </section>
      <!-- 2/13/2009 TC: is this section required at all ? It looks like a roadmap for all of us. I think the content should be spread among the document. Can I ?
			MCV 2/20 >> I like this section. It outlines the goal of this entire doc. You can move it around but please don't split it.
			If anything it should go at the beginning, in case readers wondering why we're doing this.
			TC 2/20: I won't touch this for the -00 version then :) -->
      <section title="Agility Requirements">
        <t>We hold the following to be requirements on a signing algorithm agility solution for SEND: </t>
        <t>
          <list style="symbols">
            <t>A Signature-Algorithm-Agility-Node should be able to communicate with a Non-Signature-Algorithm-Agility-Node, 
					but not necessarily employ SEND. Traditional ND should suffice, to accommodate nodes that only support 
					one type of Signature Algorithm, which may not be RSA. Local policy MAY disable this behavior, namely
					the use of unsecured ND messages when communicating with a node that does not share any common signature
					algorithm.</t>
            <t>Two Signature-Algorithm-Agility nodes that support a common Signature Algorithm and hashing algorithm 
					should be able to communicate 
					using  SEND and sign messages using the common Signature Algorithm and hash algorithm.</t>
            <t>The current SEND/CGA specifications should incur as few changes as possible.</t>
          </list>
        </t>
      </section>
      <section title="Mechanism for Agility Support of CGA and SEND">
        <t>To achieve signature agility for SEND, it must be possible for a CGA to be generated from and to be securely associated with 
				multiple public keys corresponding to different signature algorithms. This capability is described in the companion 
				draft <xref target="cheneau-csi-cga-pk-agility"/>. </t>
        <t>This document  proposes an update to  <xref target="RFC3971"/>  to allow two SEND nodes to choose an appropriate signature algorithm. 
			This solution encompasses the following:
			<list style="symbols"><t>A "Supported Signature Algorithm" Neighbor Discovery Protocol option which contains a list of
					signing and hashing algorithms that the sender node supports for SEND purposes and its interaction with the Neighbor Cache; </t><t>A modification of the "RSA Signature" option defined in the SEND specification;</t></list></t>
        <t> We define the aforementioned options format and provide processing rules for both senders 
				and receivers of SEND messages employing the new options, as well as example negotiation message flows.</t>
			<t>
				Note that the ECC support for SEND is described in document <xref target="cheneau-csi-ecc-sig-agility"/>.
			</t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section anchor="sec-pki_opt" title="Supported Signature Algorithm Option">
      <t> The Supported Signature Algorithm (SSA) NDP option contains a list of signing and hashing algorithm pairs
				that the sender node supports.  The format of this option is described in
				<xref target="fig-supp_PKI"/>:</t>
      <figure anchor="fig-supp_PKI" title="Supported Signature Algorithm option">
        <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[
 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|     Type      |    Length     |           Reserved            |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
| Sig. Alg. 1   | Sig. Alg. 2   |  Sig. Alg 3.  | Sig. Alg 4.   |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
~                                                               ~
|                          ...                                  |
~                                                               ~
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|     ...      | Sig. Alg. N  |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+ ]]></artwork>
      </figure>
      <t>
        <list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="Type"><vspace blankLines="1"/> NDP option type, TBA. See <xref target="sec-iana"/>.</t>
          <t hangText="Length"><vspace blankLines="1"/> The length of the option 
						<!-- TC 05/28/09: previous text was "value 0 is invalid", but 1 is too -->
						(including the Type, Length fields), in octets.  8-bit unsigned integer,  the values lower than 2 are invalid.</t>
          <t hangText="Reserved"><vspace blankLines="1"/> Reserved for future use. This 16-bit field  MUST be set 
						to zero by the sender, and MUST be ignored by the receiver.</t>
          <t hangText="Signature Algorithm"><vspace blankLines="1"/>
						A one-octet long field indicating a signature algorithm and the corresponding hash algorithm that 
						this node supports; this support implies at least ability to verify signatures of this Signature Algorithm algorithm.
						
						<vspace blankLines="1"/>
						If the first leftmost bit, bit 0, is set to 0, it indicates that the emitter is able to perform signature checks only (i.e. no signature 
						generation with this type of signature algorithm).
						If this bit is set to 1, it indicates that the emitter has a public key of this type and can generate signatures.
						Bit 1 and 2 are reserved.
						Bit 3 to 7 are named  Signature Type Identifier subfield and encode an identifier for the signature algorithm and corresponding hash algorithm.
						Default values for the Signature Type Identifier subfield defined in this document are taken in part from the IANA-defined numbers
						for the IKEv2 protocol, i.e. IANA registry named "IKEv2 Authentication Method":
						<!-- TC 04/20/09 concerning the Signature Type Identifier, quoting Sean:
						 We will include the negotiation of both digital
						signature and hash functions. The "to be negotiated" hash functions include two
						parts: the hash function used in producing a signature, also the hash function
						used in "key hash" of signature option. So the combination might involve 3
						elements: RSA         /   SHA256           /  SHA   256 sgn-alg
						sgn-used-hash    key-hash

						Although people already argued a lot whether the two hash functions should be
						demanded to be same, but there is not a conclusion yet, so we should keep the
						place for both hash functions. What do you think?
						TC: I agree we can do that if Hash Threat people agree with our reasoning
						MCV: 4/23: I think it will be too wasteful: we have only one byte, and many such combinations.
						I would define only the ones with the same hash function,  to start with. Other combos can be
						added later
						-->


						<list style="symbols"><!-- TC 04/22/09: we should define a value (maybe 0) for RSA/SHA-1 (old RFC 3971 nodes) --><!-- TC 05/28/09: stepping in and assigning 0 to RSA/SHA-1, removed the "reserved value",
							maybe we should "reserve" another range or another value  -->
							<t>Value 0 is RSA/SHA-1 (compatible with <xref target="RFC3971"/>)</t>
							<t>Value 1 is RSA/SHA-256</t>
							<t>Section 5 of document <xref target="cheneau-csi-ecc-sig-agility"/> provides values for ECDSA signature algorithm</t>
                                                    
                                               </list>
						The Signature/hash Algorithm combinations SHOULD be included in order of preference.
					</t>
          <t>
						A SSA option MAY be built to respect a Local Policy. 
						However, the SSA option MUST not indicate Signature Algorithm(s) that the emitting node's CGA does not support
						and MUST contain at least one Signature Algorithm with the first bit on (i.e. this Signature Algorithm is available for signature generation).
					</t>
        </list>
      </t>
      <section title="Neighbor Cache interactions">
        <t>
					Neighbor Cache MUST have the ability to store Supported Signature Algorithm information for each entry (i.e. IPv6 address).
					Supported Signature Algorithm information for an entry MAY be empty (e.g. entry created by a RFC 3971 node or an unverifiable message).
				</t>
      </section>
      <section title="Processing Rules for Senders">
        <t>If a node has been configured to use SEND, then all Neighbor Solicitation,
					Neighbor Advertisement, Router Solicitation, Router Advertisement, and Redirect messages
					it sends MUST contain the Supported Signature Algorithm option.  
					This option MUST contain in the Signature Algorithm field(s) all the
					signature algorithms it is willing to use in signature generation and verification. 
				</t>
      </section>
      <section title="Processing Rules for Receivers">
        <t>Upon receiving a SEND packet with a Supported Signature Algorithm Option, a receiver performs the following operations:
					<list style="symbols"><t>
							When a message is a  Neighbor Solicitation or a Router Solicitation, the receiving node  
							computes the intersection between the set of Supported Signature Algorithm indicated 
							by the option and its own. If the set is empty, this means the node will not be able to use a 
							Signature Algorithm that the initiating node can check. Given the local policy, 
							a receiver node MAY still respond to the received message using its "preferred" Signature 
							Algorithm (even if the node knows the receiver will not be able to verify the Signature Algorithm). 
							If the set is not empty, the receiving node will choose one of the algorithms among the set 
							in order to generate a Universal Signature Option. 
						</t><t>
							If a message passes the SEND verifications (CGA verification, Timestamp, Nonce, Universal Signature Option verification) and contains a Supported Signature Algorithm Option, 
							the information of the Supported Signature Algorithm in the Neighbor Cache is updated by the information contained in the 
							Supported Signature Option attached to the message.
						</t><t>
							If a message does not pass the SEND verifications because of a unverifiable RSA Signature Option or Universal Signature Option, if it contains a Supported Signature Algorithm Option,
							and the Neighbor Cache entry associated to that node does not contain any information about the Supported Signature Algorithm, the Neighbor Cache
							entry SHOULD be updated with the information contained in the Supported Signature Algorithm Option.
						</t></list>
				</t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section anchor="Univ-Sig-Option" title="SEND Universal Signature Option">
      <t>We propose replacing the RSA Signature Option by a new algorithm-independent signature option. 
				The "Universal Signature Option" is an updated version of the RSA Signature Option, that allows a node to 
				specify which of its potential multiple keys it is using. 
				To achieve this, we use the 16-bit reserved field of the RSA Signature Option, and define a new 8-bit
				 field that contains the position of the Public Key associated with the signature and a new 5-bit Signature 
				Type Identifier field that details the type of algorithms used to generate the Digital Signature.
			</t>
      <figure title="Universal Signature Option format" anchor="sig-opt-format">
        <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[
    0                   1                   2                   3
    0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |     Type      |    Length     | Key Position  | Res.|  Sig ID |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |                                                               |
   |                          Key Hash                             |
   |                                                               |
   |                                                               |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |                                                               |
   .                                                               .
   .                       Digital Signature                       .
   .                                                               .
   |                                                               |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |                                                               |
   .                                                               .
   .                           Padding                             .
   .                                                               .
   |                                                               |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+]]></artwork>
      </figure>
      <t>
        <list style="hanging"><t hangText="Type"><vspace blankLines="1"/>
					Same value as in <xref target="RFC3971"/>: 12.
				</t><t hangText="Length"><vspace blankLines="1"/>
					The length of the option (including the Type, Length, Reserved,
					Key Hash, Digital Signature, and Padding fields) in units of 8
					octets.
				</t><t hangText="Key Position"><vspace blankLines="1"/>
					An 8-bit field indicating which Public Key in the CGA Parameters data structure (carried in the 
					CGA option) has been used to compute the Digital Signature and is hashed in the Key Hash field. The index starts at 0, meaning
					the key is the one in the	Public Key field. Values greater than 1 refer to Public Key found in the CGA Extension field 
					(as defined in the companion document <xref target="cheneau-csi-cga-pk-agility"/>]).
					<!-- TC 05/29/09: this can be useful if the PK is cached and no CGA options are sent (this can happen for RAs messages) -->
					Value 255 is a reserved value that indicates no CGA option in the message contains the Public Key.
					
				</t><t hangText="Reserved"><vspace blankLines="1"/>
					A 3-bit field reserved for future use.  The value MUST be
					set to zero by the sender and MUST be ignored by the
					receiver.
				</t>
 in
				<t hangText="Signature Type Identifier"><vspace blankLines="1"/>
					Signature Type Identifier is a 5-bit field. It corresponds to the Signature Type Identifier subfield (bits 3 to 7 of the Signature Algorithm field)
					in the Supported Signature Algorithm option . It indicates the type of signature contained in the Digital Signature field.
				</t>
				<t hangText="Key Hash"><vspace blankLines="1"/><!-- TC 04/20/09 inconsistant with the previous paragraph (in the SSAO), where we state that value 0 is left for future usage --><!--If the Signature Type Identifier value is 0 then this field 
					is computed using SHA-1 value of the public key used for constructing
					the signature. This Key Hash is computed the same way as the Key Hash
					in RSA Signature Option described in <xref target="RFC3971"/>. -->
					A 128-bit field containing the most significant (leftmost) 128 bits of a hash of the public key used for constructing the signature.
					It is computed using the same hash function as used in generating digital signature 
					(indicated in Signature Type Identifier). 
					<!--If the Signature Type Identifier value is different than 0 then this field is computed using SHA-256 <xref target="FIPS.180-2"/> value 
					of the public key used for constructing the signature. The SHA-256 hash is computed over the
					presentation used in the Public Key field of the CGA Parameters
					data structure carried in the CGA option.  -->
					The hash value is computed over the presentation used in the Public Key field of the CGA Parameters
					data structure carried in the CGA option. Its purpose is to
					associate the signature with a particular key known by the
					receiver.  Such a key can either be stored in the certificate
					cache of the receiver or be received in the CGA option in the same
					message.
 


				</t>
				<t hangText="Digital Signature"><vspace blankLines="1"/>
					A variable-length field containing a signature constructed by using the sender's private key associated to 
					the public key pointed by the Key Position field. The signature type is determined from the value of the Signature Type Identifier field.

					<list style="symbols"><t>If the value of the Signature Type Identifier field is 0 and the Key Position field is set to 0, the Digital 
							Signature field is computed the same way as the Digital Signature field of the RSA Signature Option described in <xref target="RFC3971"/>. These values are compatible with <xref target="RFC3971"/>.</t><t> If the value of the Signature Type Identifier field is 0 and the Key Position field is different than 0, this Digital 
							Signature field is computed the same way as
							the Digital Signature field of the RSA Signature Option described in <xref target="RFC3971"/> except that the associated Public Key in the Key Hash field is pointed by the value of the Key Position field.  </t><!-- TC 05/29/09: changed values in this paragraph and also rephrased, to fit to the previously defined values --><t>

							If the value of the Signature Type Identifier field is 1, then this Digital Signature field is computed the same way 
							as the Digital Signature field of the RSA Signature Option described in <xref target="RFC3971"/> except that the 
							signature is computed with the RSASSA-PKCS1-v1_5 algorithm (as defined in <xref target="PKCS1"/>) and the SHA-256 hash function. The Key Position field indicates the position of the Public Key signed in the Key Hash field.
							</t>
							<t>
								Values for ECDSA signature algorithm are defined in Section 6 of <xref target="cheneau-csi-ecc-sig-agility"/>.
							</t>

						</list>
					This field starts after the Key Hash field.  The length of the
					Digital Signature field is determined by the length of the Universal
					Signature option minus the length of the other fields (including
					the variable length Pad field).

					
				</t>
				<!-- TC 10/06/09: comment addressed to Maryline: this sentence is from RFC 3971 -->
				<t hangText="Padding">
					This variable-length field contains padding, as many bytes long as
					remain after the end of the signature.
				</t>

			</list>
      </t>
      <t>
			A Neighbor Solicitation/Advertisement, 	Router Solicitation/Advertisement and Redirect message 
			MAY contain more than one Universal Signature Option, as long as it does not  exceed the MTU.
			This is particularly useful for routers operating in  heterogeneous networks,
			where hosts have a disjoint set of supported signature algorithms. For information on how to compute the message size, see <xref target="key_sizes"/>.
		</t>
      <section title="Processing Rules for Senders">
        <t>When sending a SEND message spontaneously, an emitter node CAN choose a signature algorithm of its 
				preference (defined by its local policy) among the corresponding Public Keys carried in the CGA option. Using this signature 
				algorithm, the node  computes the Digital Signature and fills the Key Position field with the position
				 of the key in the CGA Parameters data structure.</t>
        <t>If the node has been configured to use SEND, then all Neighbor Solicitation,
			Neighbor Advertisement, Router Advertisement, and Redirect messages
			MUST contain at least one Universal Signature option.  Router Solicitation messages
			not sent with the unspecified source address MUST contain the Universal
			Signature option.</t>
        <t>A node sending a message with one or more Universal Signature option(s) MUST construct
			the message as follows:

				<list style="symbols"><t> If the node has previously received hints (e.g. a NDP message with a Supported Signature Algorithm 
					option or an entry in the Neighbor Cache) on the type of Signature Algorithm it should use, it MUST restrict
					 its choice on those Signature Algorithms.
					</t><t>The message is then constructed in its entirety, without any of the Universal
						Signature options.</t><t>The Universal Signature option(s) is (are) added as the last option in the
						message.</t><!-- TC 05/29/09: I think we should refere to our own draft here --><t>The data to be signed is constructed as explained in <xref target="RFC3971"/>,
						under the description of the Digital Signature field.</t><t>The message, in the form defined above, is signed by using the
						configured private key associated to the selected Signature Algorithm, and the result
						 <!-- PKCS#1 v1.5 --> signature
						is encapsulated into the Digital Signature field.
						<!-- TC 2/20/2009: I'm too short on time, but it should be rephrased for the -01 version -->
						<!-- TC 05/29/09: I don't plan to rephrase this text, I'm more likely to comment it out,
						as it is a repeated version of the text above -->
						<!-- text that should have be rephrase vvvvvv
						When using RSA, this signature is a PKCS#1 v1.5 signature. When using ECDSA, the 
						signature value is as defined in <xref target="FIPS-186-3"/>.  The length
						of the Digital Signature field is determined by the length of the Universal Signature option 
						minus the length of the other fields (including the variable length Padding field). -->

					</t></list>
			</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="sec_receiver" title="Processing Rules for Receivers">
        <!-- TC 04/24/09: added the text with the "unverifiable USO" to solve the problem with the DAD -->
        <t>Neighbor Solicitation, Neighbor Advertisement, Router Advertisement,
				and Redirect messages without any Universal Signature option or
				with an unverifiable Universal Signature option MUST be
				treated as unsecured (i.e., processed in the same way as NDP messages
				sent by a non-SEND node). See Section 8 of <xref target="RFC3971"/>.</t>
        <t>Router Solicitation messages without any Universal Signature option MUST
				also be treated as unsecured, unless the source address of the
				message is the unspecified address.</t>
        <t>Redirect, Neighbor Solicitation, Neighbor Advertisement, Router
				Solicitation, and Router Advertisement messages containing one or more Universal
				Signature option MUST be checked as follows:
				<list style="symbols"><t>The receiver MUST ignore any options that come after the first Universal
						Signature option.  (The options are ignored for both signature
						verification and NDP processing purposes.)</t><t>The Key Hash field MUST correspond to a known public key,
						either one learned from the CGA option in the same message and by the position indicated in the Key Position field
						message, or one known by other means.</t><t>The Digital Signature field MUST have correct encoding and MUST
						not exceed the length of the Universal Signature option minus the
						Padding.</t><t>The Digital Signature verification MUST show that the signature
						has been calculated as specified in the previous section.</t><t>If the use of a trust anchor has been configured, a valid
						certification path (see Section 6.3 of <xref target="RFC3971"/>) between the receiver's trust
						anchor and the sender's public key MUST be known.</t></list>
			</t>
        <t>Messages that do not pass all the above tests MUST be silently
			discarded if the host has been configured to accept only secured ND
			messages.  The messages MAY be accepted if the host has been
			configured to accept both secured and unsecured messages but MUST be
			treated as unsecured messages.  The receiver MAY also otherwise
			silently discard packets (e.g., as a response to an apparent CPU
			exhausting DoS attack).</t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section title="Basic negotiation">
      <section anchor="sec-nego-overview" title="Overview">
        <t>This section describes different configurations of SEND-enabled nodes with varying signing capabilities and their interaction during the negotiation phase.</t>
        <t>Case 1: when both nodes support the same two Signature Algorithms, they can pick the Signature Algorithm they prefer for signing and are able to verify each others signature. <xref target="fig-neg1"/> is an example of such a message flow.</t>
        <figure anchor="fig-neg1" title="Basic negotiation - Case 1">
          <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[
Node A                                    Node B

NS
{CGA option,
RSA Signature option. 
Supported-Signature-Algo option
(RSA sign & verif, ECC sign & verif)}  
                     -------->
                                NA
                                {CGA option,
                                ECC Signature option
                                Supported-Signature-Algo option
                                (ECC sign & verif, RSA sign & verif)}
                     <-------- 

IPv6 traffic         <------->  IPv6 traffic ]]></artwork>
        </figure>
        <t>
				Case 2: two nodes sharing at least one common Signing Algorithm must be able to securely communicate.
				<xref target="fig-neg2"/> is an example of such a message flow.
			</t>
        <figure anchor="fig-neg2" title="Basic negotiation - Case 2">
          <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[
Node A                                      Node B

NS
{CGA option,
RSA Signature option. 
Supported-Signature-Algo option
(RSA sign & verif, ECC sign & verif)}
                       -------->
                                   NA
                                   {CGA option,
                                   ECC Signature option
                                   Supported-Signature-Algo option
                                   (ECC sign & verif)}
                       <--------   
                                   (At this point, Node B could not 
                                   authenticate Node A's Neighbor
                                   Solicitation)

                       --------> (unidirectionnal) IPv6 traffic

                                   NS
                                   {CGA option,
                                   ECC Signature option
                                   Supported-Signature-Algo option
                                   (ECC sign & verif)}
                       <--------
NA
{CGA option,
ECC Signature option. 
Supported-Signature-Algo option
(RSA sign & verif, ECC sign & verif)}        
                       -------->   

IPv6 traffic           <------->  IPv6 traffic ]]></artwork>
        </figure>
        <t>
				Case 3: when two nodes have a disjoint set of Signature Algorithm support for signing, but the two nodes are able to verify each others, a full negotiation is possible.
				<xref target="fig-neg3"/> is an example of such a message flow.
			</t>
        <figure anchor="fig-neg3" title="Basic negotiation - Case 3">
          <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[
Node A                                    Node B

NS
{CGA option,
RSA Signature option. 
Supported-Signature-Algo option
(RSA sign & verif, ECC verif only)}
                      -------->
                               NA
                               {CGA option,
                               ECC Signature option
                               Supported-Signature-Algo option
                               (ECC sign & verif, RSA verif only)}
                     <--------  

IPv6 traffic         <------->  IPv6 traffic ]]></artwork>
        </figure>
        <t>
				Case 4: when two nodes have a disjoint set of Signature Algorithm support for signing, but one node is able to verify, a partial negotiation is possible.
				<xref target="fig-neg4"/> is an example of such a message flow.
			</t>
        <figure anchor="fig-neg4" title="Basic negotiation - Case 4">
          <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[
Node A                                    Node B

NS
{CGA option,
RSA Signature option. 
Supported-Signature-Algo option
(RSA sign & verif)} 
                     -------->
                                NA
                                {CGA option,
                                ECC Signature option
                                Supported-Signature-Algo option
                                (ECC sign & verif, RSA verif only)}
                    <--------    

          (...depending on local policies...)
IPv6 traffic        <------->  IPv6 traffic ]]></artwork>
        </figure>
        <!-- TC 05/26/09: I'm not sure the following text is useful, please tell me if you think so
	TC 10/06/09: Maryline thinks the following text can be useful, de commenting it 
	-->
			<t>Upon receiving the Neighbor Solicitation message, node B determines, through the Supported Signature Algorithm option, that node A
				will not be able to verify any of its signature algorithm. However, based on their local policy, node B may answer and node A might decide
				to trust the unsecure Neighbor Discovery (thus being vulnerable), see <xref target="sec_receiver"/>. </t> 
      </section>
      <section title="Sending Unsolicited Messages">
        <t>
				When sending unsolicited message, a node MAY have to rely on the entries of its Neighbor Cache.
				The Neighbor Cache will provide hints concerning the Signature Algorithm supported by the neighbors.
				Neighbor Cache can assist the node in the Signature Algorithm selection process when:
				<list style="symbols"><t>
						A router advertises unsolicited Router Advertisement message to the All-Nodes multicast address
						(e.g. to indicate a prefix lifetime is going down to 0).
						The router needs to know which signature algorithm(s) to use in order to send verifiable messages to hosts.
						To do so, the router MAY rely on the Neighbor Cache and compute an intersection of the set of all Supported Signature Algorithms.
						The router will then be able to advertise a Router Advertisement signed multiple times 
						with the resulting subset of Supported Signature Algorithms or
						advertise multiple Router Advertisements, each signed with a single Signature Algorithm part of the intersection.
					</t><t>
						A node sends unsolicited Neighbor Advertisement (e.g. when changing its Link-Layer address). This is similar to the previous
						problem and can also be solved using the Neighbor Cache the same way.
					</t><t>
						A router sends a Redirect message to a host. Choosing a supported signature algorithm  
						without probing the node can be difficult. However, Neighbor Cache will most likely contain
						an entry for the host, prior to the decision to send a Redirect message, because of the Address
						Resolution process. 
						<!-- TC 04/22/09: well, not really true, because the previous message could have be unsecured, must find a way to rephrase -->
						This entry should contain information on the Supported Signature Algorithm(s) 
						and thus provide hints concerning the Signature Algorithm to choose to sign the Redirect messages.
					</t></list>
			</t>
        <t>
				Note that the information on the neighbors with which a communication has occurred recently or is ongoing are in the Neighbor Cache and are maintained up to date through the Neighbor Unreachability Detection procedure.
			</t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section anchor="secc" title="Security Considerations">
        <!-- TC 09/22/09: I do not know if we need to add a reference to the ECC document here -->
        <t><xref target="Univ-Sig-Option"/> presents a new Universal Signature Option. A recommended use of this option is to allow signatures of equivalent security level (i.e. Public Keys with equivalent key lengths). See also section 4 of the companion draft <xref target="cheneau-csi-cga-pk-agility"/>. </t>
      <t>
			Usage of SHA-1 for signature is strongly NOT RECOMMENDED, and when available should be preferred by the usage of SHA-256. SHA-1 security has
			been proved to be flawed in the light of recent attacks <xref target="Recent_SHA-1_Attack"/> <xref target="NIST-st"/>.
		</t>
      <t>
			The Universal Signature Option is vulnerable to downgrade attacks. That is, given that a node can employ multiple signature types, an attacker may choose to use a flawed one. To mitigate this issue, nodes are allowed, on a local policy, to refuse to check certain types of signature (i.e. those which are know to be flawed) and will treat the associated messages as unsecured. When trying to completely mitigate downgrade attacks, an administrator MAY deploy SEND-secured nodes only authorizing a single signature algorithm scheme. This comes at a price of a reduced interoperability.
		</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="sec-iana" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t><xref target="sec-pki_opt"/> defines a Signature Type Identifier subfield containing new values corresponding to different Signature Algorithm. This document requests creation of a new registry to the IANA.</t>
    </section>
    <section title="Acknowledgments" anchor="ack">
      <t> The authors gratefully acknowledge the contributions of Marcelo Bagnulo, Gabriel Montenegro, 
			Greg Daley, Dave Thaler, Steve Kent, Jari Arko, and Francis Dupont for their helpful feedback.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>
  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <reference anchor="RFC3972">
        <front>
          <title>Cryptographically Generated Addresses (CGA)</title>
          <author initials="T." surname="Aura" fullname="T. Aura">
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <date year="2005" month="March"/>
          <abstract>
            <t>This document describes a method for binding a public signature key to an IPv6 address in the Secure Neighbor Discovery (SEND) protocol.  Cryptographically Generated Addresses (CGA) are IPv6 addresses for which the interface identifier is generated by computing a cryptographic one-way hash function from a public key and auxiliary parameters.  The binding between the public key and the address can be verified by re-computing the hash value and by comparing the hash with the interface identifier.  Messages sent from an IPv6 address can be protected by attaching the public key and auxiliary parameters and by signing the message with the corresponding private key.  The protection works without a certification authority or any security infrastructure. [STANDARDS TRACK]</t>
          </abstract>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="3972"/>
        <format type="TXT" octets="51473" target="ftp://ftp.isi.edu/in-notes/rfc3972.txt"/>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="RFC3971">
        <front>
          <title>SEcure Neighbor Discovery (SEND)</title>
          <author initials="J." surname="Arkko" fullname="J. Arkko">
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <author initials="J." surname="Kempf" fullname="J. Kempf">
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <author initials="B." surname="Zill" fullname="B. Zill">
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <author initials="P." surname="Nikander" fullname="P. Nikander">
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <date year="2005" month="March"/>
          <abstract>
            <t>IPv6 nodes use the Neighbor Discovery Protocol (NDP) to discover other nodes on the link, to determine their link-layer addresses to find routers, and to maintain reachability information about the paths to active neighbors.  If not secured, NDP is vulnerable to various attacks.  This document specifies security mechanisms for NDP.  Unlike those in the original NDP specifications, these mechanisms do not use IPsec. [STANDARDS TRACK]</t>
          </abstract>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="3971"/>
        <format type="TXT" octets="123372" target="ftp://ftp.isi.edu/in-notes/rfc3971.txt"/>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="RFC4982">
        <front>
          <title>Support for Multiple Hash Algorithms in Cryptographically Generated Addresses (CGAs)</title>
          <author initials="M." surname="Bagnulo" fullname="M. Bagnulo">
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <author initials="J." surname="Arkko" fullname="J. Arkko">
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <date year="2007" month="July"/>
          <abstract>
            <t>This document analyzes the implications of recent attacks on commonly used hash functions on Cryptographically Generated Addresses (CGAs) and updates the CGA specification to support multiple hash algorithms. [STANDARDS TRACK]</t>
          </abstract>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="4982"/>
        <format type="TXT" octets="20961" target="ftp://ftp.isi.edu/in-notes/rfc4982.txt"/>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="cheneau-csi-cga-pk-agility">
        <front>
          <title>Support for Multiple Signature Algorithms in Cryptographically Generated 
						Addresses (CGAs)</title>
          <author initials="T.C" surname="Cheneau" fullname="Tony Cheneau">
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <author initials="M.M" surname="Laurent-Maknavicius" fullname="Maryline Laurent-Maknavicius">
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <author initials="S.S" surname="Shen" fullname="Sean Shen">
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <author initials="M.C.V." surname="Vanderveen" fullname="Michaela Vanderveen">
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <date month="October" year="2009"/>
          <abstract>
            <t>This document defines an extension field for the CGA Parameters data structure
				specified in RFC 3972.  This extension field carries a Public Key 
				that is used in Cryptographically Generated Address (CGA) generation. This extension
				enables protocols using CGAs, such as SEND, to use multiple Public Key signing algorithms
				and/or multiple Public Keys.</t>
          </abstract>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-cheneau-csi-cga-pk-agility-00"/>
        <format type="TXT" target="http://www.ietf.org/internet-drafts/draft-cheneau-csi-cga-pk-agility-00.txt"/>
      </reference>
    </references>
    <references title="Informative References">
      <reference anchor="cheneau-csi-ecc-sig-agility">
        <front>
          <title>ECCpublic key and signature support in Cryptographically Generated Addresses (CGA) and in the Secure Neighbor Discovery (SEND)</title>
          <author initials="T.C" surname="Cheneau" fullname="Tony Cheneau">
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <author initials="M.M" surname="Laurent-Maknavicius" fullname="Maryline Laurent-Maknavicius">
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <author initials="S.S" surname="Shen" fullname="Sean Shen">
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <author initials="M.C.V." surname="Vanderveen" fullname="Michaela Vanderveen">
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <date month="October" year="2009"/>
          <abstract>
            <t>This draft describes a mechanism to deploy Elliptic Curve Cryptography (ECC) alongside with Cryptographically Generated Addresses (CGA) and the Secure Neighbor Discovery.
		    This document provides basic skeleton for other Signature Algorithms to be integrated in CGA and SEND.  </t>
          </abstract>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-cheneau-csi-ecc-sig-agility-00"/>
        <format type="TXT" target="http://www.ietf.org/internet-drafts/draft-cheneau-csi-ecc-sig-agility-00.txt"/>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="RFC2460">
        <front>
          <title abbrev="IPv6 Specification">Internet Protocol, Version 6 (IPv6) Specification</title>
          <author initials="S.E." surname="Deering" fullname="Stephen E. Deering">
            <organization>Cisco Systems, Inc.</organization>
            <address>
              <postal>
                <street>170 West Tasman Drive</street>
                <street>San Jose</street>
                <region>CA</region>
                <code>95134-1706</code>
                <country>USA</country>
              </postal>
              <phone>+1 408 527 8213</phone>
              <facsimile>+1 408 527 8254</facsimile>
              <email>deering@cisco.com</email>
            </address>
          </author>
          <author initials="R.M." surname="Hinden" fullname="Robert M. Hinden">
            <organization>Nokia</organization>
            <address>
              <postal>
                <street>232 Java Drive</street>
                <street>Sunnyvale</street>
                <region>CA</region>
                <code>94089</code>
                <country>USA</country>
              </postal>
              <phone>+1 408 990 2004</phone>
              <facsimile>+1 408 743 5677</facsimile>
              <email>hinden@iprg.nokia.com</email>
            </address>
          </author>
          <date year="1998" month="December"/>
          <area>Internet</area>
          <keyword>internet protocol version 6</keyword>
          <keyword>IPv6</keyword>
          <abstract>
            <t>
							This document specifies version 6 of the Internet Protocol (IPv6),
							also sometimes referred to as IP Next Generation or IPng.
				</t>
          </abstract>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="2460"/>
        <format type="TXT" octets="85490" target="ftp://ftp.isi.edu/in-notes/rfc2460.txt"/>
        <format type="HTML" octets="99496" target="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/html/rfc2460.html"/>
        <format type="XML" octets="93343" target="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/xml/rfc2460.xml"/>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="RFC3756">
        <front>
          <title>IPv6 Neighbor Discovery (ND) Trust Models and Threats</title>
          <author initials="P." surname="Nikander" fullname="P. Nikander">
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <author initials="J." surname="Kempf" fullname="J. Kempf">
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <author initials="E." surname="Nordmark" fullname="E. Nordmark">
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <date year="2004" month="May"/>
          <abstract>
            <t>The existing IETF standards specify that IPv6 Neighbor Discovery (ND) and Address Autoconfiguration mechanisms may be protected with IPsec Authentication Header (AH).  However, the current specifications limit the security solutions to manual keying due to practical problems faced with automatic key management.  This document specifies three different trust models and discusses the threats pertinent to IPv6 Neighbor Discovery.  The purpose of this discussion is to define the requirements for Securing IPv6 Neighbor Discovery.  This memo provides information for the Internet community.</t>
          </abstract>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="3756"/>
        <format type="TXT" octets="56674" target="ftp://ftp.isi.edu/in-notes/rfc3756.txt"/>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="RFC4581">
        <front>
          <title>Cryptographically Generated Addresses (CGA) Extension Field Format</title>
          <author initials="M." surname="Bagnulo" fullname="M. Bagnulo">
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <author initials="J." surname="Arkko" fullname="J. Arkko">
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <date year="2006" month="October"/>
          <abstract>
            <t>This document defines a Type-Length-Value format for Cryptographically Generated Address (CGA) Extensions.  This document updates RFC 3972. [STANDARDS TRACK]</t>
          </abstract>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="4581"/>
        <format type="TXT" octets="7636" target="ftp://ftp.isi.edu/in-notes/rfc4581.txt"/>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="RFC4861">
        <front>
          <title>Neighbor Discovery for IP version 6 (IPv6)</title>
          <author initials="T." surname="Narten" fullname="T. Narten">
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <author initials="E." surname="Nordmark" fullname="E. Nordmark">
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <author initials="W." surname="Simpson" fullname="W. Simpson">
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <author initials="H." surname="Soliman" fullname="H. Soliman">
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <date year="2007" month="September"/>
          <abstract>
            <t>This document specifies the Neighbor Discovery protocol for IP Version 6.  IPv6 nodes on the same link use Neighbor Discovery to discover each other's presence, to determine each other's link-layer addresses, to find routers, and to maintain reachability information about the paths to active neighbors. [STANDARDS TRACK]</t>
          </abstract>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="4861"/>
        <format type="TXT" octets="235106" target="ftp://ftp.isi.edu/in-notes/rfc4861.txt"/>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="NIST-st" target="http://csrc.nist.gov/groups/ST/hash/statement.html">
        <front>
          <title>NIST Comments on Cryptanalytic Attacks on SHA-1</title>
          <author>
            <organization>National Institute of Standards and Technology</organization>
          </author>
        </front>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="PKCS1">
        <front>
          <title>RSA Encryption Standard, Version 2.1</title>
          <author>
            <organization>RSA Laboratories</organization>
          </author>
          <date month="November" year="2002"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="PKCS" value="1"/>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="FIPS.180-2" target="http://csrc.nist.gov/publications/fips/fips180-2/fips180-2.pdf">
        <front>
          <title>Secure Hash Standard</title>
          <author>
            <organization>National Institute of Standards and Technology</organization>
          </author>
          <date month="August" year="2002"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="FIPS" value="PUB 180-2"/>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="SEC1" target="http://secg.org">
        <front>
          <title>
						SEC 1: Elliptic Curve Cryptography
					</title>
          <author>
            <organization>
							Standards for Efficient Cryptography Group
						</organization>
          </author>
          <date month="September" year="2000"/>
        </front>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="Recent_SHA-1_Attack" target="http://eurocrypt2009rump.cr.yp.to/837a0a8086fa6ca714249409ddfae43d.pdf">
        <front>
          <title>SHA-1 collisions now 2^52</title>
          <author initials="C.M" surname="McDonald" fullname="Cameron McDonald">
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <author initials="P.H" surname="Haukes" fullname="Philip Hawkes">
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <author initials="J.P" surname="Pieprzyk" fullname="Josef Pieprzyk">
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <date month="May" year="2009"/>
          <abstract>
            <t>Authors announced that a new path to find SHA-1 collision has complexity 2^52. Practical collisions 
							are within resources of a well funded organisation and paper will appear on Eprint soon.</t>
          </abstract>
        </front>
      </reference>
    </references>
    <section anchor="key_sizes" title="On the number of Public Keys supported per CGA">
      <texttable anchor="table_RSA_PK" title="Common sizes for DER-encoded RSA Public Key">
        <ttcol align="center">RSA key length (bits)</ttcol>
        <ttcol align="center">Public exponent</ttcol>
        <ttcol align="center">Size of the DER-encoded Public Key (bytes)</ttcol>
        <c>384</c>
        <c>3 or 17</c>
        <c>76</c>
        <c>384</c>
        <c>65537</c>
        <c>78</c>
        <c>512</c>
        <c>3 or 17</c>
        <c>92</c>
        <c>512</c>
        <c>65537</c>
        <c>94</c>
        <c>1024</c>
        <c>3 or 17</c>
        <c>160</c>
        <c>1024</c>
        <c>65537</c>
        <c>162</c>
        <c>2048</c>
        <c>3 or 17</c>
        <c>292</c>
        <c>2048</c>
        <c>65537</c>
        <c>294</c>
        <c>3072</c>
        <c>3 or 17</c>
        <c>420</c>
        <c>3072</c>
        <c>65537</c>
        <c>422</c>
        <c>7680</c>
        <c>3 or 17</c>
        <c>996</c>
        <c>7680</c>
        <c>65537</c>
        <c>998</c>
        <c>15360</c>
        <c>3 or 17</c>
        <c>1956</c>
        <c>15360</c>
        <c>65537</c>
        <c>1958</c>
        <!-- <postamble>Common sizes for DER-encoded RSA Public Keys</postamble> -->
      </texttable>
      <texttable anchor="table_RSA_sig" title="Common sizes of the Digital Signature field when using RSA">
        <ttcol align="center">RSA Key Length (in bits)</ttcol>
        <ttcol align="center">Size of the Digital Signature field without padding</ttcol>
        <c>384</c>
        <c>48</c>
        <c>512</c>
        <c>64</c>
        <c>1024</c>
        <c>128</c>
        <c>2048</c>
        <c>256</c>
        <c>3072</c>
        <c>384</c>
        <c>7680</c>
        <c>960</c>
        <c>15360</c>
        <c>1920</c>
        <!-- <postamble>Common sizes of Digital Signature field when using RSA</postamble> -->
      </texttable>
      <t>
				When using multiple public keys to form a CGA, one may reach the maximum number 
				of possible public keys <!--MCV 6/1/09: where is this constraint coming from?? 
				TC 06/03/09: maximum here means that if you exceed this number, the size is over the MTU size, this isn't a "constrain"
				--> before each Neighbor 
				Discovery Message exceed the Maximum Transfer Unit (which must be at least 1280 octets according to 
				<xref target="RFC2460"/>). This section aims to approximate this limit.
			</t>
      <t>
				Numerous factors (presence and number of option, size of public keys, etc)  influence the size of the Neighbor 
				Discovery message. For example, when sending a SEND-secured Router Advertisement message:
				<list style="symbols"><t>The IPv6 header is 40 bytes long. Described in <xref target="RFC2460"/>.</t><t>The bare Router Advertisement message (without any option) is 16 bytes long. Described in <xref target="RFC4861"/>.</t><t>A Prefix Information Option (can appear more than once) is 32 bytes long. Described in <xref target="RFC4861"/>.</t><t>A Source Link-Layer Option, when a IEEE 802 address is used, is 8 bytes long. Described in <xref target="RFC4861"/>.</t><t>A MTU Option is 8 bytes long. Described in <xref target="RFC4861"/>.</t><t>The CGA Option is the size of the CGA Parameters data structure plus 4 bytes rounded up to the closest multiple of 8 value. This option is defined in <xref target="RFC3971"/>.
						The CGA Parameters data structure (defined in <xref target="RFC3972"/> size depends on the following fields:
						<list style="symbols"><t>Modifier: 16 bytes long.</t><t>Subnet Prefix: 8 bytes long.</t><t>Collision Count: 1 byte long.</t><t>Public Key:  variable size. <xref target="table_RSA_PK"/> provides size of the commonly used DER-encoded RSA Public Keys. 
								</t><t>Extension(s): variable size. Public Key Extension field defined in <xref target="cheneau-csi-cga-pk-agility"/> is 4 bytes plus the 
								size of the Public Key long. Public Key size are defined in <xref target="table_RSA_PK"/>.</t></list>
					</t><t>The Timestamp Option is 16 bytes long. Defined in <xref target="RFC3971"/>.</t><t>The Nonce Option minimum size is 8 bytes long. Defined in <xref target="RFC3971"/>.</t><t>The Universal Signature Option depends on the size of the Digital Signature. The fixed part of the option is 20 bytes long. 
						This option is updated in this document. <xref target="table_RSA_sig"/> presents common sizes for usual Digital Signature field when using RSA. 
						 This option size must be a multiple of 8 bytes.</t></list>
			</t>
      <!-- TC 04/28/09: only use one option (MTU, SLLO, Prefix) per message and sending multiple messages to announce all this option is allowed for RAs -->
      <t>
			A Router Advertisement message, carrying a Prefix Information Option and a Source Link-Layer Option, without Nonce, with one 1024-bits long RSA Public Key and a 
				Public Exponent of 3 in the CGA Option is 456 bytes long. 			</t>
    </section>
  </back>
</rfc>
