<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!-- This template is for creating an Internet Draft using xml2rfc,
     which is available here: http://xml.resource.org. -->
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [

<!ENTITY RFC3777    PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3777.xml'>
<!ENTITY RFC4333    PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4333.xml'>
]>

<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='http://xml.resource.org/authoring/rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc tocompact="no" ?>
<?rfc tocindent="no" ?>
<?rfc comments="yes" ?>
<?rfc inline="yes" ?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc iprnotified="no" ?>
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>

<rfc
  category="bcp"
  ipr="trust200902"
  updates="3777"
  docName="draft-leiba-3777upd-eligibility-01">

  <front>
    <title abbrev="NonCom Eligibility Update">
    Update to RFC 3777 to Clarify Nominating Committee Eligibility of IETF Leadership
    </title>

    <author initials='B.' surname='Leiba' fullname='Barry Leiba'>
      <organization>Huawei Technologies</organization>
      <address>
        <phone>+1 646 827 0648</phone>
        <email>barryleiba@computer.org</email>
        <uri>http://internetmessagingtechnology.org/</uri>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author initials='S.' surname='Moonesamy' fullname='S. Moonesamy'>
      <organization></organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>76, Ylang Ylang Avenue</street>
          <city>Quatres Bornes</city>
          <country>Mauritius</country>
        </postal>
        <email>sm+ietf@elandsys.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date/>
    <area>General</area>
    <workgroup></workgroup>

    <abstract>
      <t>
        RFC 3777 specifies that "sitting members" of
        the IAB and IESG "may not volunteer to serve on the nominating commitee".
        Since that document was written the IAOC was formed, and that body is not
        covered by RFC 3777.  There is also uncertainty about whether ex-officio members
        and liaisons are included as "sitting members".  This document clarifies those situations.
     </t>
    </abstract>

  </front>

  <middle>
    <section anchor="intro" title="Introduction">
      <t>
        The "Operation of the Nominating and Recall Committees" document
        <xref target="RFC3777"/> defines the nominating committee (NomCom) process.
        One of the key points in the process and in the selection of the NomCom is
        that the IETF wants to avoid having its top leadership be self-selecting:
        the leaders should not be the ones who choose the leaders.
        The selection of the NomCom, therefore, excludes those individuals who are
        in top leadership positions currently.
      </t>
      <t>
        That said, it would be bad to eliminate people who have the experience
        necessary to understand of the IETF process: those individuals can bring
        a broader perspective to the NomCom and will help ensure that the
        people it selects for the leadership positions are better prepared to
        fulfill the roles.
      </t>
      <t>
        RFC 3777 specifies that "sitting members" of
        the IAB and IESG "may not volunteer to serve on the nominating committee".
        Since that document was written the IETF Administrative Oversight Committee (IAOC)
        was formed, and that body is not
        covered by RFC 3777.  There is also uncertainty about whether ex-officio members
        liaisons, and such are included as "sitting members".
        This document clarifies those situations, with the understanding that the intent
        of RFC 3777 was to exclude those currently in IETF leadership positions, or who
        would otherwise have a conflict of interest, from voting on the selection of
        the new leadership.
      </t>
      <t>
        This document also excludes certain individuals who are directly paid for their work with
        the IETF, and who, therefore, have a direct personal financial incentive in
        the selection of the leadership boards.
        We limit this exclusion to a few people who are paid for long-term full-time work.
        In practice, they are unlikely to volunteer for the NomCom anyway,
        so this addition makes little practical change.
      </t>
      <t>
        In order to allow the largest reasonable list of potential NomCom members,
        we do not want to exclude those at lower levels of IETF leadership.
        In particular, this document does *not* exclude participation from working
        group chairs, IRTF research group chairs, members of directorates and special
        review teams, and members of other advisory bodies.
        <vspace/>
        <cref>Some had suggested eliminating the RFC Series Oversight Committee (RSOC)
        members, for example; we do not think that is a good idea.</cref>
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="addIAOC" title="Addition of the IAOC to the Text of RFC 3777">
      <t>
        RFC 3777 specifies processes involving the IAB and the IESG in a number of places.
        For some of those situations, the "IAOC Member Selection Guidelines and Process"
        document <xref target="RFC4333"/> covers what's needed for the IAOC.
        This document makes the following updates to add the IAOC to certain of the processes
        that are not covered there.
      </t>
      <t>
        Note that the change below to Section 4, bullet 15 also puts additional restrictions
        on who may volunteer as a voting member of the NomCom.
      </t>

      <t>
        Section 2 ("Definitions") is updated as follows:
        <list style="symbols">

          <t>Paragraphs 5 and 6 are replaced by this:
            <list style="hanging" hangIndent="3">
            <t hangText="nominee:">
      A person who is being or has been considered for one or more
      open positions of the IESG, the IAB, or the IAOC.
            </t>
            <t hangText="sitting member:">
      A person who is currently serving a term of
      membership in the IESG, the IAB, the IAOC, or the ISOC Board of Trustees.
            </t></list>
          </t>
        </list>
      </t>

      <t>
        Section 3 ("General") is updated as follows:
        <list style="symbols">

          <t>Bullet 7, sub-bullet 1 is replaced by this:
            <list style="empty"><t>
         The IETF Executive Director informs the nominating committee of
         the IESG, IAB, and IAOC positions to be reviewed.
            <vspace blankLines="1"/>
         The IESG, the IAB, and the IAOC are responsible for providing summary of the
         expertise desired of the candidates selected for their
         respective open positions to the Executive Director.  The
         summaries are provided to the nominating committee for its
         consideration.
            </t></list>
          </t>

          <t>In bullet 7, sub-bullet 3, the following is inserted between
        paragraphs 3 and 4:
            <list style="empty"><t>
          The sitting IESG members review the IAOC candidate.
            </t></list>
          </t>
        </list>
      </t>

      <t>
        Section 4 ("Nominating Committee Selection") is updated as follows:
        <list style="symbols">

          <t>Bullet 3, paragraph 1 is replaced by this:
            <list style="empty"><t>
       The nominating committee comprises at least a Chair, 10 voting
       volunteers, 4 liaisons, and an advisor.
            </t></list>
          </t>

          <t>Bullet 3, paragraph 6 is replaced by this:
            <list style="empty"><t>
       The IESG, IAB, and IAOC liaisons are selected according to rules stated
       elsewhere in this document.
            </t></list>
          </t>

          <t>Bullet 7, paragraph 3 is replaced by this:
            <list style="empty"><t>
       Liaisons from the IESG, the IAB, and the IAOC are expected to provide
       information to the nominating committee regarding the operation,
       responsibility, and composition of their respective bodies.
            </t></list>
          </t>

          <t>Bullet 7, paragraph 5 is replaced by this:
            <list style="empty"><t>
       Liaisons from the IESG, the IAB, the IAOC, and the Internet Society Board of
       Trustees (if one was appointed) are expected to review the
       operation and executing process of the nominating committee and
       to report any concerns or issues to the Chair of the nominating
       committee immediately.  If they can not resolve the issue between
       themselves, liaisons must report it according to the dispute
       resolution process stated elsewhere in this document.
            </t></list>
          </t>

          <t>Bullet 8, only paragraph is replaced by this:
            <list style="empty"><t>
       For each of the IAB, the IESG, and the IAOC, the sitting members appoint a liaison from
       their current membership, someone who is not sitting in an open
       position, to serve on the nominating committee.
            </t></list>
          </t>

          <t>Bullet 13, paragraph 1 is replaced by this:
            <list style="empty"><t>
       The Chair obtains the list of IESG, IAB, and IAOC positions to be
       reviewed and announces it along with a solicitation for names of
       volunteers from the IETF community willing to serve on the
       nominating committee.
            </t></list>
          </t>

          <t>Bullet 15 is replaced by these two bullets:
            <list style="hanging" hangIndent="5">
              <t hangText="15.1.">
        Members of the Internet Society Board of Trustees and sitting
        members of the IAB, the IESG, and the IAOC, including members
        in ex-officio positions, and not including liaisons, may not volunteer
        to serve as voting members of the nominating committee.
              </t>
              <t hangText="15.2.">
        People serving in the IETF Secretariat and the RFC Editor may not volunteer to
        serve as voting members of the nominating committee.
              </t>
            </list>
          </t>

          <t>In bullet 16, to correct an erratum, the last paragraph is replaced by this:
            <list style="empty"><t>
       One possible selection method is described in RFC 3797 [1].
            </t></list>
          </t>
        </list>
      </t>

      <t>
        Section 5 ("Nominating Committee Operation") is updated as follows:
        <list style="symbols">

          <t>In bullet 11, the last paragraph is replaced by this:
            <list style="empty"><t>
       Members of the IETF community who were recalled from any nominating-committee-appointed
       leadership position during the previous two years are not eligible to be
       considered for filling any open position.
            </t></list>
          </t>
        </list>
      </t>

    </section>

    <section anchor="security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>
        This is a procedural document, and is entirely unrelated to security.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>
        No IANA actions are requested by this document, and the RFC Editor is asked to remove
        this section before publication.
      </t>
    </section>  
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      &RFC3777;
    </references>
    <references title="Informative References">
      &RFC4333;
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
