<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">

<rfc category="std" ipr="pre5378Trust200902" docName="draft-ietf-ntp-dhcpv6-ntp-opt-06.txt">

<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>

<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="no"?>
<?rfc iprnotified="no" ?>
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>

<front>
  <title abbrev="NTP Server Option for DHCPv6">
    Network Time Protocol (NTP) Server Option for DHCPv6
  </title>

  <author fullname="Richard Gayraud" initials="R.G." surname="Gayraud">
    <address>
      <email>richard.gayraud@free.fr</email>
    </address>
  </author>

  <author fullname="Benoit Lourdelet" initials="B.L." surname="Lourdelet">
    <organization>Cisco Systems, Inc.</organization>
    <address>
      <postal>
        <street>Village ent. GreenSide, Bat T3,</street>
        <street>400, Av de Roumanille,</street>
        <code></code>
        <city>06410 BIOT - Sophia-Antipolis Cedex</city>
        <country>France</country>
      </postal>
      <phone>+33 4 97 23 26 23</phone>
      <email>blourdel@cisco.com</email>
    </address>
  </author>

  <date/>

  <abstract>
  <t> The NTP Server Option for Dynamic Host Configuration Protocol for IPv6 (DHCPv6) provides NTP (Network Time 
      Protocol version 4) Server location information to DHCPv6 hosts.</t>
  </abstract>


</front>

<middle>


<!---------------------------------------------------------------->

<section title="Introduction">

<t> This document defines a DHCPv6 option and associated
    suboptions to provide Network Time Protocol version 4 
    [draft-ntpv4] or greater Server location information to DHCPv6 hosts. </t>

</section>

<section title="Requirements notation">

<t> The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL",
    "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY",
    and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as
    described in <xref target="RFC2119"/>. </t>

</section>

<section title="Related Work and Usage Model">

<t> The NTP service is publicly offered on the Internet by a number
    of organizations. Those Servers can be used but should not be abused, so
    any method which is tasked to disseminate locations of NTP Servers
    must act responsibly in a manner that does not lead to public
    Server overloading.
    When using DHCPv6 to offer NTP Server location, and if there is a
    need to distribute a host with a hardcoded configuration,
    this configuration MUST NOT include Server location that is
    not part of the organization that distributes this device.
    Typical usage of this option is to specify an NTP Server that is part
    of the organization that operates the DHCPv6 Server.
 </t>

<t> The location of the NTP service, like any other Internet service, 
    can be specified by an IP address or a Fully Qualified Domain Name (FQDN).
    By design, DHCP 
    offers information to multiple devices and is prone to 
    amplification of mistakes, so great care must be taken to 
    define its configuration. Specification of the NTP service by
    FQDN offers a level of indirection that works as
    a possible mitigation tool in case of misconfiguration.
    DNS can be used to redirect misconfigured clients to an 
    IPv6 address that is not configured on any host instead of having to change the 
    address of the NTP Server itself.</t>

<t> While the NTP specification defines a comprehensive set of
    configuration parameters, modification of those parameters is best
    left to the decision of the client itself. The DHCPv6 option for
    NTP is therefore restricted to Server location. </t>


</section>

<!---------------------------------------------------------------->

<section title="NTP Server Option for DHCPv6">

<t> This option serves as a container for Server location information 
    related to one NTP Server or Simple Network Time Protocol (SNTP) <xref target="RFC4330"/> Server.
    This option can appear multiple 
    times in a DHCPv6 message. Each instance of this option is 
    to be considered by the NTP client or SNTP client as a Server to include
    in its configuration. </t>

<t> The option itself does not contain any value. Instead, it 
    contains one or several suboptions that carry NTP Server or SNTP Server  
    Server location. This option MUST include one,
    and only one, time source suboption. The currently defined 
    time source suboptions are: NTP_OPTION_SRV_ADDR, NTP_OPTION_SRV_MC_ADDR, 
    NTP_OPTION_SRV_FQDN. It carries the NTP Server or SNTP Server location,
    as a  unicast or multicast IPv6 address or as an NTP Server
    or SNTP Server FQDN.
    More time source suboptions may be defined in the future.
    While the FQDN option offers the most deployment flexibility,
    resiliency as well as security, the IP address options are  
    defined to cover cases where a DNS dependancy is not desirable.</t>
    
<t> If the NTP Server or SNTP Server location is an IPv6 multicast address,
    the client SHOULD use this address as an NTP multicast
    group address and listen to messages sent to this group in 
    order to synchronize its clock. </t>

<figure><artwork align="left"><![CDATA[
The format of the NTP Server Option is:

   0                   1                   2                   3
   0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
  +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
  |      OPTION_NTP_SERVER        |          option-len           |
  +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
  |                         suboption-1                           |
  :                                                               :
  +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
  |                         suboption-2                           |
  :                                                               :
  +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
  :                                                               :
  +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
  |                         suboption-n                           |
  :                                                               :
  +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
    
    option-code: OPTION_NTP_SERVER (TBD_IANA),

    option-len: Total length of the included suboptions. 
]]></artwork></figure>

    
<t> This document does not define any priority relationship between the client's 
    embedded configuration (if any) and the NTP or SNTP Servers discovered via 
    this option. In particular, the client is allowed to simultaneously
    use its own configured NTP Servers or SNTP Servers and the Servers discovered 
    via DHCP. </t>


<section title="NTP Server Address Suboption">

<t> This suboption is intended to appear inside the
    OPTION_NTP_SERVER option. It specifies the IPv6 unicast address
    of an NTP Server or SNTP Server available to the client.
</t>

<figure><artwork align="left"><![CDATA[
The format of the NTP Server Address Suboption is:

   0                   1                   2                   3
   0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
  +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
  |    NTP_SUBOPTION_SRV_ADDR     |        suboption-len = 16     |
  +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
  |                                                               |
  |                                                               |
  |                   IPv6 address of NTP Server                  |
  |                                                               |
  +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+

    IPv6 address of the NTP Server: An IPv6 address,  

    suboption-code: NTP_SUBOPTION_SRV_ADDR (1),
  
    suboption-len: 16.
]]></artwork></figure>

</section>
<!---------------------------------------------------------------->

<section title="NTP Multicast Address Suboption">

<t> This suboption is intended to appear inside the
    OPTION_NTP_SERVER option. It specifies the IPv6 address
    of the IPv6 multicast group address used by NTP on the local network.
</t>

<figure><artwork align="left"><![CDATA[
The format of the NTP Multicast Address Suboption is:

   0                   1                   2                   3
   0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
  +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
  |    NTP_SUBOPTION_MC_ADDR      |        suboption-len = 16     |
  +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
  |                                                               |
  |                                                               |
  |                   Multicast IPv6 address                      |
  |                                                               |
  +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+

    

    Multicast IPv6 address: An IPv6 address, 

    suboption-code: NTP_SUBOPTION_MC_ADDR (2),
  
    suboption-len: 16.
]]></artwork></figure>

</section>
<!---------------------------------------------------------------->


<section title="NTP Server FQDN Suboption">

<t> This suboption is intended to appear inside the
    OPTION_NTP_SERVER option. It specifies the FQDN of an NTP Server 
    or SNTP Server available to the client. </t>

<figure><artwork align="left"><![CDATA[
The format of the NTP Server FQDN Suboption is:

   0                   1                   2                   3
   0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
  +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
  |    NTP_SUBOPTION_SRV_FQDN     |         suboption-len         |
  +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
  |                                                               |
  |                      FQDN of NTP Server                       |
  :                                                               :
  +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+

    suboption-code: NTP_SUBOPTION_SRV_FQDN (3),

    suboption-len: Length of the included FQDN field,
       
    FQDN: Fully Qualified Domain Name of the NTP Server or SNTP Server.
	 This field MUST be encoded as described in [RFC3315], 
          section 8. Internationalized Domain Name are not allowed 
          in this field.
]]></artwork></figure>

</section>
</section>


<!---------------------------------------------------------------->

<section title="Appearance of this Option">

<t> The OPTION_NTP_SERVER option can appear multiple times in a
    DHCPv6 message. The order in which these options appear is not 
    significant. The client uses its usual algorithms to determine 
    which Server(s) or multicast group(s) should be prefered to 
    synchronize its clock.</t>

<t> The OPTION_NTP_SERVER option MUST NOT appear in messages other 
    than the following: Solicit, Advertise, Request, Renew, Rebind, 
    Information-Request, and Reply. If this option appears in 
    messages other than those specified above, the receiver MUST
    ignore it.</t>

<t> The option number for this option MAY appear in the "Option
    Request" option <xref target="RFC3315"/> in the following
    messages: Solicit, Request, Renew, Rebind, Information-Request,
    and Reconfigure. If this option number appears in the
    "Option Request" option in messages other than those specified
    above, the receiver SHOULD ignore it.</t>

</section>

<!---------------------------------------------------------------->

<section title="Security Considerations">

<t> This option could be used by an intruder to advertise the 
    address of a malicious NTP Server or SNTP Server and adversely affect
    the clock of clients on the network. The consequences of such 
    an attack can be critical, because many security protocols 
    depend on time synchronization to run their algorithms. 
    As an example, an attacker could break connectivity 
    between SEND-enabled nodes <xref target="RFC3971"/>, simply
    by affecting the clock on these nodes.</t>

<t> To prevent these attacks, it is strongly advisable to 
    secure the use of this option either by: </t>
   
<figure><artwork align="left"><![CDATA[
   -  using the NTPv4 Autokey public key authentication, as defined 
      in [draft-autokey] or,

   -  using authenticated DHCP as described in [RFC3315] section 21.
]]></artwork></figure>

</section>

<!---------------------------------------------------------------->

<section title="RFC 4075 Deprecation">

<t> <xref target="RFC4075"/> (SNTP Configuration Option for DHCPv6)
    provides some degree of automatic time Server configuration 
    for IPv6, as it specifies how to transmit SNTP 
    <xref target="RFC4330"/> Servers addresses through DHCPv6. However
    this approach is not suitable for all NTP 
    deployments. It is not an extensible mechanism and introduces
    some semantic confusion throught the use of the "SNTP" acronym.
    Additionally the approach of only offering IPv6 
    addresses to specify Server location does not meet NTP requirements 
    that make use of a FQDN (Fully Qualified Domain Name) as well.
    For all the abovementioned reasons, 
    this document makes <xref target="RFC4075"/> deprecated.</t>

</section>

<!---------------------------------------------------------------->

<section title="IANA Considerations">

<t> When this document is published, the IANA is requested to
     assign an option code from the "DHCPv6 Options Codes" registry
     for OPTION_NTP_SERVER.</t>

<t> IANA is required to maintain a new number space of NTP time source
   suboptions, located in the BOOTP-DHCP Parameters Registry. The
   initial suboptions are described in section 4 of this document.

   IANA assigns future NTP time source suboptions with a "IETF
   Consensus" policy as described in [RFC5226]. Future proposed
   suboptions are to be referenced symbolically in the Internet-Drafts
   that describe them, and shall be assigned numeric codes by IANA when
   approved for publication as an RFC.</t> 

</section>

</middle>

<!---------------------------------------------------------------->

<back>
<references title='Normative References'>

   <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3315" ?>
   <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5226" ?>
   
   <reference anchor="draft-ntpv4">
     <front>
       <title>
         Network Time Protocol Version 4 Protocol And
         Algorithms Specification
       </title>
       <author surname="Burbank" initials="J">
         <organization/></author>
       <author surname="Kasch" initials="W">
         <organization/></author>
       <author surname="Martin" initials="J">
         <organization/></author>
       <author surname="Mills" initials="D">
         <organization/></author>
       <date month="September" year="2008" />
     </front>
     <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-ietf-ntp-ntpv4-proto-11" />
   </reference>
    
  <!---<?rfc include="reference.I-D.ietf-ntp-autokey" ?>--->

   <reference anchor="draft-autokey">
     <front>
       <title>
         Network Time Protocol Version 4 Autokey Specification
       </title>
       <author surname="Haberman" initials="B">
         <organization/></author>
       <author surname="Mills" initials="D">
         <organization/></author>
       <date month="July" year="2009" />
     </front>
     <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-ietf-ntp-autokey-06" />
   </reference>
</references>

<references title='Informative References'>

   <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119" ?>

   <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3971" ?>

   <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4075" ?>

   <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4330" ?>


</references>

</back>
</rfc>
