<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!-- First draft by Mark McFadden with editing by Lyman Chapin -->
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY rfc1034 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1034.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc1035 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1035.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc1591 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1591.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc2119 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc2606 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2606.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc4234 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4234.xml">
]>
<rfc category="std" docName="draft-chapin-rfc2606bis-00.txt" ipr="trust200902">
  <?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>

  <?rfc toc="yes" ?>

  <?rfc symrefs="no" ?>

  <?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>

  <?rfc iprnotified="no" ?>

  <?rfc strict="yes" ?>

  <front>
    <title>Reserved Top Level Domain Names</title>

    <author fullname="Lyman Chapin" initials="L" surname="Chapin">
      <organization>Interisle Consulting Group</organization>

      <address>
        <phone>+1 617 686 2527</phone>

        <email>lyman@interisle.net</email>

        <uri>http://www.interisle.net</uri>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Mark McFadden" initials="M" surname="McFadden">
      <organization abbrev="ICC">InterConnect Communications
      Ltd</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Merlin House</street>

          <street>Station Road</street>

          <city>Chepstow</city>

          <code>NP16 5PB</code>

          <country>UK</country>
        </postal>

        <phone>+1 608 628 2674</phone>

        <email>markmcfadden@icc-uk.com</email>

        <uri>http://www.icc-uk.com</uri>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date day="31" month="May" year="2011" />

    <abstract>
      <t>The Internet Domain Name System (DNS) defines a tree of names
      starting with root, ".", immediately below which are top level domain
      (TLD) names such as ".com" and ".us". RFC2606 reserved a small
      number of TLD names for use in documentation examples, private testing,
      experiments, and other circumstances in which it is desirable to avoid
      conflict with current or future actual TLD names in the DNS. The
      evolution of Internet engineering and operation practices since RFC2606
      was published in 1999, and the expected addition of new TLD
      names to the DNS, recommend this update to the list of reserved TLD
      names, and the creation of a "reserved TLD name registry" to which
      additional names may be added as new requirements arise.</t>

      <t>It is important to note that TLD names may be reserved, in other
      contexts, for policy, political, or other reasons that are distinct from
      the IETF's concern with Internet engineering and operations. This
      document reserves TLD names only for operational and engineering
      reasons.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section anchor="intro" title="Introduction">
      <t>The Internet Domain Name System is documented in <xref
      target="RFC1034">RFC1034</xref>, <xref target="RFC1035">RFC1035</xref>,
      <xref target="RFC1591">RFC1591</xref> and numerous additional Requests
      for Comment. It defines a tree of names starting with root, ".",
      immediately below which are top level domain names such as ".com" and
      ".us". Below top level domain names there are normally additional levels
      of names.</t>

      <t><xref target="RFC2606">RFC2606</xref> reserved a small number of TLD
      names which, without fear of conflicts with current or future actual top
      level domain names in the global DNS, can be used for private testing of
      existing DNS related code, examples in documentation, DNS related
      experimentation, invalid DNS names, or other similar uses. <xref
      target="RFC2606">RFC2606</xref> also noted that the Internet Assigned
      Numbers Authority (IANA) reserves the label "example" at the second
      level below the TLDs .com, .net, and .org.</t>

      <t>Since <xref target="RFC2606">RFC2606</xref> was published in 1999,
      Internet engineering and operation practices have evolved in ways that
      recommend this update to the list of reserved TLD names, and the
      creation of a "reserved TLD name registry" to which additional labels
      may be added as new requirements arise. This update is also prompted by
      the expected advent of new TLDs which might, in the absence of the
      reservations for which this document provides, introduce TLD labels that
      could create engineering and operational problems for root server
      operators and other DNS infrastructure providers.</t>

      <t>It is important to note that TLD names may be reserved, in other
      contexts, for policy, political, or other reasons that are distinct from
      the IETF's concern with Internet engineering and operations. This
      document reserves TLD names only for operational and engineering
      reasons.</t>

      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
      document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
      target="RFC2119"></xref>.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="legacy" title="Legacy Reserved Top Level Domain Names">
      <t>The four top level domain name labels reserved by <xref
      target="RFC2606">RFC2606</xref> for testing and documentation examples
      remain reserved:</t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>test</t>

          <t>example</t>

          <t>invalid</t>

          <t>localhost</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>".test" is recommended for use in testing of current or new DNS
      related code.</t>

      <t>".example" is recommended for use in documentation or as
      examples.</t>

      <t>".invalid" is intended for use in online construction of domain names
      that are sure to be invalid and which it is obvious at a glance are
      invalid.</t>

      <t>The ".localhost" TLD has traditionally been statically defined in
      host DNS implementations as having an A record pointing to the loop back
      IP address and is reserved for such use. Any other use would conflict
      with widely deployed code which assumes this use.</t>

      <t>This document makes no changes to the IANA reservation of the label
      "example" at the second level.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="new"
             title="Additional Reserved Top Level Domain Names and Reserved TLD Name Registry">
      <t>In its report of a quantitative study of queries to the DNS root
      servers entitled <eref
      target="http://www.icann.org/en/committees/security/sac045.pdf">"Invalid
      Top Level Domain Queries at the Root Level of the Domain Name
      System"</eref> [or, SAC 045] ICANN's Security and Stability Advisory
      Committee "calls attention to the potential problems that may arise
      should a new TLD applicant use a string that has been seen with
      measurable (and meaningful) frequency in a query for resolution by the
      root system and the root system has previously generated a
      response."</t>

      <t>Of particular concern is the case in which a string "has been queried
      and a root name server has responded to the query with a non-existent
      domain (NXDOMAIN) result, i.e., the string has not been delegated but
      has been queried." SAC 045 reports the results of a <eref
      target="http://www.caida.org/publications/presentations/2009/rssac_dns/rssac_dns.pdf">CAIDA
      measurement study</eref> which found that "NXDOMAIN responses
      account for more than 25 percent of the total responses from root name
      servers observed in the study, and the top ten such strings account for
      10 percent of the total query load."</t>

      <t><eref
      target="http://www.icann.org/en/committees/security/sac045.pdf">SAC
      045</eref> describes in detail the engineering and operational problems
      that would ensue from the delegation, as new valid TLD names, of
      previously invalid labels that have frequently appeared in queries to
      the root: "If the [new TLD label] were to be approved and the TLD
      included in the root zone, queries to the root level of the DNS for a
      string that hitherto returned NXDOMAIN would begin to return positive
      responses containing name servers of the new TLD."</t>

      <t>Recommendation (2) of <eref
      target="http://www.icann.org/en/committees/security/sac045.pdf">SAC
      045</eref> calls for the community to develop principles for
      "prohibiting the delegation of additional strings to those already
      identified in <xref target="RFC2606">RFC2606</xref>." As the first step
      in that process, based on the data reported by <eref
      target="http://www.icann.org/en/committees/security/sac045.pdf">SAC
      045</eref>, this document adds to the list of names that may not be used
      for top-level domains the following labels:</t>

      <t><list>
          <t>.local</t>

          <t>.localdomain</t>

          <t>.domain</t>

          <t>.lan</t>

          <t>.home</t>

          <t>.host</t>

          <t>.corp</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>To facilitate the further steps that may be taken to pursue
      Recommendation (2) of <eref
      target="http://www.icann.org/en/committees/security/sac045.pdf">SAC
      045</eref>, IANA is requested to publish a new registry of TLD names
      reserved by the IETF. This Reserved TLD Name Registry should simply list
      the reserved TLD names with a reference in each case to the authority
      for reserving the name. New names may be added to the registry through
      "IETF Specification Required" as provided by <xref
      target="RFC4234">RFC4234</xref>. The initial contents of the registry
      are the names listed in Appendix A of this document.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>One of the reasons cited in Section 1 for reserving specific labels
      that cannot be used for valid top level domain names in the global DNS
      is to make it possible for those labels to be used safely in other
      contexts, without risk of conflict with "real" domain names. Reserving
      these labels therefore effectively encourages their use in
      locally-defined domain names that may resolve differently in different
      local contexts. An application that looks up "foo.local" on private
      network A, for example, may get a different result if it looks up
      "foo.local" on private network B. </t>

      <t>A name that resolves differently depending on where the lookup
      request is made presents obvious security issues for any application
      that does not expect this behavior. These issues arise from the use of
      any locally-defined labels in domain names, whether or not they are
      reserved. </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="iab" title="IAB Considerations">
      <t>There are no architectural implications related to reserving
      individual strings at the top level of the DNS.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="iana" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>According to <xref target="RFC2606">RFC2606</xref>, IANA agreed to
      the top level domain reservations in that document. However, IANA was
      not instructed to publish a list of reserved names.</t>

      <t>IANA is requested to publish a new registry of TLD strings reserved
      by the IETF. The Reserved TLD Name registry will consist of a list of
      reserved TLD names and a reference for each entry to the document that
      put the strings into reserved status.</t>

      <t>New strings are to be added to the registry through "IETF
      Specification Required" as provided by <xref
      target="RFC4234">RFC4234</xref>. The initial content of the full
      registry is located in the Appendix to this document.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>Several studies have shown that a large fraction of the lookup
      queries seen by the DNS root servers request information about invalid
      TLDs. THe authors thank CAIDA, and in particular kc claffy, for their
      work in this area. The authors are also indebted to the contributors to
      SAC 045 which provided the impetus for this first step at identifying a
      particular set of strings to be reserved. David Conrad provided helpful
      input about potential security concerns surrounding the reservation of
      strings at the root.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="registry"
             title="Appendix - Initial Registry of Reserved Top Level Domain Names">
      <t>This is the initial registration for the registry of Reserved Top
      Level Names in the DNS. The IANA is asked to use this material as
      guidance for the creation of the initial registry. Future registrations
      in this registry will be done through "IETF Specification Required" as
      provided by <xref target="RFC4234">RFC4234</xref>.</t>

      <texttable anchor="ianaregistry">
        <ttcol align="center">Label</ttcol>

        <ttcol align="center">Reference</ttcol>

        <c>.corp</c>

        <c>RFCxxx</c>

        <c>.domain</c>

        <c>RFCxxx</c>

        <c>.example</c>

        <c>RFC2606,RFCxxx</c>

        <c>.home</c>

        <c>RFCxxx</c>

        <c>.host</c>

        <c>RFCxxx</c>

        <c>.invalid</c>

        <c>RFC2606,RFCxxx</c>

        <c>.lan</c>

        <c>RFCxxx</c>

        <c>.local</c>

        <c>RFCxxx</c>

        <c>.localdomain</c>

        <c>RFCxxx</c>

        <c>localhost</c>

        <c>RFC2606,RFCxxx</c>

        <c>test</c>

        <c>RFC2606,RFCxxx</c>

        <postamble>NOTE TO RFC EDITOR: The correct number of this document
        should be substituted in the table above upon publication. At that
        time this editing note should be deleted.</postamble>
      </texttable>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      &rfc1034;

      &rfc1035;

      &rfc1591;

      &rfc2119;

      &rfc2606;

      &rfc4234;
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
