<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<rfc category="std" docName="draft-bryant-pwe3-packet-pw-02.txt"
     ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="Packet PW">Packet Pseudowire Encapsulation over an MPLS
    PSN</title>

    <author fullname="Stewart Bryant" initials="S" role="editor"
            surname="Bryant">
      <organization>Cisco Systems</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>250, Longwater, Green Park,</street>

          <city>Reading</city>

          <region>Berks</region>

          <code>RG2 6GB</code>

          <country>UK</country>
        </postal>

        <email>stbryant@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Luca Martini" initials="L" surname="Martini">
      <organization>Cisco Systems</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>9155 East Nichols Avenue, Suite 400</street>

          <city>Englewood</city>

          <region>CO</region>

          <code>80112</code>

          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>

        <email>lmartini@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="George Swallow" initials="G" surname="Swallow">
      <organization>Cisco Systems</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>1414 Massachusetts Ave</street>

          <city>Boxborough</city>

          <region>MA</region>

          <code>01719</code>

          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>

        <email>swallow@cisco.com</email>

        <uri></uri>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Andy Malis" initials="A" surname="Malis">
      <organization>Verizon Communications</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>117 West St.</street>

          <city>Waltham</city>

          <region>MA</region>

          <code>02451</code>

          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>

        <email>andrew.g.malis@verizon.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date year="2009" />

    <area>Internet Area</area>

    <workgroup>Network Working Group</workgroup>

    <keyword>Sample</keyword>

    <keyword>Draft</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>This document describes a pseudowire that is used to transport a
      packet service over an MPLS PSN is the case where the client LSR and the
      server PE are co-resident in the same equipment. For correct operation
      these clients require a multi-protocol interface with fate sharing
      between the client protocol suite. The packet pseudowire may be used to
      carry all of the required layer 2 and layer 3 protocols between the pair
      of client LSRs.</t>
    </abstract>

    <note title="Requirements Language">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
      document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
      target="RFC2119">RFC2119</xref>.</t>
    </note>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction ">
      <t>There is a need to provide a method of carrying a packet service over
      an MPLS PSN in a way that provides isolation between the two networks.
      The server MPLS network may be an MPLS network or a network conforming
      to the MPLS-TP <xref target="RFC5317"></xref>. The client may also be
      either a MPLS network of a network conforming to the MPLS-TP.
      Considerations regarding the use of an MPLS network as a server for an
      MPLS-TP network are outside the scope of this document.</t>

      <t><!--Look at next taking int a/c section 3.4.1 of TP arch-->Where the
      client equipment is connected to the server equipment via physical
      interface, the same data-link type MUST be used to attach the clients to
      the Provider Edge equipments (PE)s, and a pseudowire (PW) of the same
      type as the data-link MUST be used <xref target="RFC3985"></xref>. The
      reason that inter-working between different physical and data-link
      attachment types is specifically disallowed in the pseudowire
      architecture is because this is a complex task and not a simple
      bit-mapping exercise. The inter-working is not limited to the physical
      and data-link interfaces and the state-machines. It also requires a
      compatible approach to the formation of the adjacencies between attached
      client network equipment. As an example the reader should consider the
      differences between router adjacency formation on a point to point link
      compared to a multi-point to multi-point interface (e.g. Ethernet).</t>

      <t>A further consideration is that two adjacent MPLS LSRs do not simply
      exchange MPLS packets. They exchange IP packets for adjacency formation,
      control, routing, label exchange, management and monitoring purposes. In
      addition they may exchange data-link packets as part of routing (e.g.
      IS-IS hellos and IS-IS LSPs) and for OAM purposes such as Link Layer
      Discovery protocol [IEEE standard 802.1AB-2009]. Thus the two clients
      require an attachment mechanism that can be used to multiplex a number
      of protocols. In addition it is essential to the correct operation of
      the network layer that all of these protocols fate share.</t>

      <t><!--End of look at next....-->Where the client LSR and server PE is
      co-located in the same equipment, the data-link layer can be simplified
      to a simple protocol identifier (PID) that is used to multiplex the
      various data-link types onto a pseudowire. This is the method that
      described in this document.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Network Reference Model">
      <t>The network reference model for the packet pseudowire operating in an
      MPLS network is shown in <xref target="PKT-PW-NR"></xref>. This is an
      extension of Figure 3 "Pre-processing within the PWE3 Network Reference
      Model" from <xref target="RFC3985"></xref>.</t>

      <t><figure anchor="PKT-PW-NR">
          <preamble></preamble>

          <artwork><![CDATA[
               PW                            PW
            End Service                   End Service
                |                            |
                |<------- Pseudowire ------->|
                |                            |
                |          Server            |
                |     |<- PSN Tunnel ->|     |
                |     V                V     |   
-------   +-----+-----+                +-----+-----+   -------
       )  |     |     |                |     |     |  (
client  ) | MPLS| PE1 |      PW1       | PE2 | MPLS| ( Client
MPLS PSN )+ LSR1+............................+ LSR2+( MPLS PSN
        ) |     |     |                |     |     | (
       )  |     |     |================|     |     |  (
-------   +-----+-----+                +-----+-----+   --------
                ^                            ^
                |                            |
                |                            |
                |<---- Emulated Service----->|
                |                            |
         Virtual physical             Virtual physical
            termination                  termination

]]></artwork>

          <postamble>MPLS Pseudowire Network Reference Model</postamble>
        </figure></t>

      <t>In this model LSRs, LSR1 and LSR2, are part of the client MPLS packet
      switched network (PSN). The PEs, PE1 and PE2 are part of the server PSN,
      that is to be used to provide connectivity between the client LSRs. The
      attachment circuit that is used to connect the MPLS LSRs to the PEs is a
      virtual interface within the equipment. A packet pseudowire is used to
      provide connectivity between these virtual interfaces. This packet
      pseudowire is used to transport all of the required layer 2 and layer 3
      between protocols between LSR1 and LSR2.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Forwarding Model">
      <t>The packet PW forwarding model is illustrated in <xref
      target="fwd-model"></xref>. The forwarding operation can be likened to a
      virtual private network (VPN), in which a forwarding decision is first
      taken at the client layer, an encapsulation is applied and then a second
      forwarding decision is taken at the server layer.</t>

      <t><figure anchor="fwd-model">
          <preamble></preamble>

          <artwork><![CDATA[         +------------------------------------------------+
         |                                                |
         |  +--------+                        +--------+  |
         |  |        |   Pkt   +-----+        |        |  |
      ------+        +---------+ PW1 +--------+        +------
         |  | Client |    AC   +-----+        | Server |  |
  Client |  | LSR    |                        | LSR    |  | Server 
 Network |  |        |   Pkt   +-----+        |        |  | Network
      ------+        +---------+ PW2 +--------+        +------
         |  |        |    AC   +-----+        |        |  |
         |  +--------+                        +--------+  |
         |                                                |
         +------------------------------------------------+

]]></artwork>

          <postamble>Packet PW Forwarding Model</postamble>
        </figure></t>

      <t>A packet PW PE comprises three components, the client LSR, PW
      processor and a server LSR. Note that <xref target="RFC3985"></xref>
      does not formally indicate the presence of the server LSR because it
      does not concern itself with the server layer. However it is useful in
      this document to recognise that the server LSR exists.</t>

      <t>It may be useful to first recall the operation of a layer two PW such
      as an Ethernet PW <xref target="RFC4448"></xref> within this model. The
      client LSR is not present and packets arrive directly on the attachment
      circuit (AC) which is part of the client network. The PW undertakes any
      header processing, if configured to do so, it then pushes the PW control
      word (CW), and finally pushes the PW label. The PW function then passes
      the packet to the LSR function which pushes the label needed to reach
      the egress PE and forwards the packet to the next hop in the server
      network. At the egress PE, the packet typically arrives with the PW
      label at top of stack, the packet is thus directed to the correct PW
      instance. The PW instance performs any required reconstruction using, if
      necessary, the CW and the packet is sent directly to the attachment
      circuit.</t>

      <t>Now let us consider the case client layer MPLS traffic being carried
      over a packet PW. An LSR belonging to the client layer is embedded
      within the PE equipment. This is a type of native service processing
      element <xref target="RFC3985"></xref>. This LSR determines the next hop
      in the client layer, and pushes the label needed by the next hop in the
      client layer. It then passes the packet to the correct PW instance
      indicating the packet protocol type. If the PW is configured to require
      a CW this is pushed. The PW instance then examines the protocol type and
      pushes a label that identifies the protocol type to the egress PE. The
      PW instance then proceeds as it would for a layer two PW, by pushing the
      PW label and then handing the packet to the server layer LSR for
      delivery. At egress, the packet again arrives with the PW label at the
      top of stack which causes the packet to be passed to the correct PW
      instance. This PW instance knows that the PW type is a packet PW, and
      hence that it needs to interpret the next label as a protocol type
      identifier. If necessary the CW is then popped and processed. The packet
      is then passed to the egress client LSR together with information that
      identifies the packet protocol type. The egress client LSR then forwards
      the packet in the normal manner for a protocol of that type.</t>

      <t>Note that although the description above is written in terms of the
      behaviour of an MPLS LSR, the processing model would be similar for an
      IP packet, or indeed any other protocol type.</t>

      <t>Note that the semantics of the PW between the client LSRs is a point
      to point link.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="The Protocol Identifier Label">
      <t>Protocol identifier labels (PIDLs) are allocated by the egress PE.
      One PIDL is required for each unique protocol type that the egress PE
      must forward to its client LSRs. PIDLs MUST be allocated from the
      per-platform label space. PIDLs MUST NOT be reserved labels. The mapping
      between protocol type and PIDL is either signaled to the ingress PE
      using the procedure described in <xref target="PIDLS"></xref>, or is
      configured at the ingress PE.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Encapsulation ">
      <t>The Protocol Stack Reference Model for a packet PW is shown in <xref
      target="PStack"></xref> below</t>

      <figure anchor="PStack" title="PWE3 Protocol Stack Reference Model">
        <artwork><![CDATA[
   +-------------+                                +-------------+
   |  Client     |                                |  Client     |
   |  network    |                                |  network    |
   |  layer      |         Client Service         |  layer      |
   |  service    |<==============================>|  service    |
   +-------------+            Pseudowire          +-------------+
   |Demultiplexer|<==============================>|Demultiplexer|
   +-------------+                                +-------------+
   |   Server    |                                |   Server    | 
   |    PSN      |            PSN Tunnel          |    PSN      |
   |   MPLS      |<==============================>|   MPLS      |
   +-------------+                                +-------------+
   |  Physical   |                                |  Physical   |
   +-----+-------+                                +-----+-------+

]]></artwork>

        <postamble></postamble>
      </figure>

      <t></t>

      <t>The corresponding packet PW encapsulation is shown in <xref
      target="Encap"></xref>.</t>

      <figure anchor="Encap"
              title="Encapsulation of a pseudowire with a pseudowire load balancing label">
        <artwork><![CDATA[
   +-------------------------------+
   |            Client             |
   |          Network Layer        |
   |            packet             |  n octets
   |                               |
   +-------------------------------+ 
   |    Optional Control Word      |  4 octets
   +-------------------------------+
   |        PID Label (S=1)        |  4 Octets
   +-------------------------------+
   |          PW label             |  4 octets
   +-------------------------------+
   |   Server MPLS Tunnel Label(s) |  n*4 octets (four octets per label)
   +-------------------------------+
 

]]></artwork>

        <postamble></postamble>
      </figure>

      <t></t>

      <t>Where the CW is not used another method is needed to multiplex PW OAM
      into the PW. This can be accomplished using one of the methods described
      in <xref target="RFC5085"></xref>, or by using an ACH indicated using a
      generic alert label <xref target="RFC5586"></xref>.</t>

      <t>The setting the TTL of an MPLS label is a matter of local policy on a
      PE. However when sending the PID label the TTL SHOULD be set to 1 to
      avoid forwarding a mis-routed packet beyond the first PE receiving
      it.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Packet Pseudowire Control Word">
      <t>The packet pseudowire control word (CW) is optional.</t>

      <t>Where the CW is used, it conforms to the preferred pseudowire MPLS
      control word defined by Figure 2 of <xref target="RFC4385"></xref>. For
      reference the packet pseudowire control word is shown in <xref
      target="PKT-PW-CW"></xref>. The definitions of the fragmentation (FRG),
      length and sequence number fields are to be found in <xref
      target="RFC4385"></xref>.</t>

      <t><figure anchor="PKT-PW-CW">
          <preamble></preamble>

          <artwork><![CDATA[
0                   1                   2                   3
0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1

+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|0 0 0 0| Flags |FRG|  Length   | Sequence Number               |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+


]]></artwork>

          <postamble>Packet Pseudowire Control Word</postamble>
        </figure></t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="PIDLS" title="Signaling the PID Label">
      <t>To signal the label binding between an MPLS label, and the desired
      PIDL the new Label Distribution protocol (LDP) Forwarding Equivalence
      Class (FEC) element is defined below is used.</t>

      <section title="The Protocol FEC Element">
        <t>To distribute the PID FEC we define a new FEC element containing
        the PID number. This is shown in <xref
        target="LDP-PID-FEC-ELM"></xref>.<figure anchor="LDP-PID-FEC-ELM">
            <artwork><![CDATA[
 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|   Prot (0x83) |   Reserved    |         Protocol type         | 
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+


]]></artwork>

            <postamble>LDP PID FEC Element</postamble>
          </figure></t>

        <texttable align="left" style="headers">
          <preamble>Where</preamble>

          <ttcol width="30%">Field</ttcol>

          <ttcol>Meaning</ttcol>

          <c>Prot</c>

          <c>FEC element number 0x83 has been allocated from the IANA registry
          "Forwarding Equivalence Class (FEC) Type Name Space" .</c>

          <c>Reserved</c>

          <c>These reserved bits for future use are to be set to 0 on transmit
          and ignored on receive.</c>

          <c>Protocol Type</c>

          <c>This 16 bit field contain the protocol type as allocated in the
          IANA registry "PPP Data Link Layer (DLL) Protocol Numbers"<eref
          target="http://www.iana.org/assignments/ppp-numbers"> </eref> <xref
          target="RFC1661"></xref>.</c>
        </texttable>

        <t></t>
      </section>

      <section title="Procedures to distribute the PID FEC. ">
        <t>The LDP procedures defined in <xref target="RFC5036"></xref> are
        used to distribute the PID label binding to the protocol ID type. The
        LDP liberal label retention independent mode is used to distribute the
        PID label bindings, however the LDP Label request procedures MUST also
        be supported for the PID label FEC as required by <xref
        target="RFC5036"></xref>. Once a Protocol FEC label mapping is
        advertised by a PE, it will be used for all packet PWs that require
        that protocol. A PE MUST mark a local virtual interface as faulted if
        the PE has not received a remote label binding for a protocol that is
        configured on the interface. Similarly, if a label withdraw is
        received for a particular protocol, all virtual interfaces using
        packet PWs that have that specific protocol configured MUST receive
        the appropriate fault condition. This FEC MUST only be used in
        conjunction with the packet PW, and MPLS packets containing only the
        advertised MPLS label MUST NOT be sent to the PE that advertised this
        FEC. The use of this FEC element without the packet PW label is
        undefined.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Status Indication">
      <t>A pseudowire status indicating a fault can be considered equivalent
      to interface down and SHOULD be passed across the virtual interface to
      the local LSR. This improves scaling in PE with large numbers of
      co-resident LSRs and with LSRs that have large numbers of interfaces
      mapped to pseudowires.</t>

      <t>The mechanism described for the mapping of pseudowire status to the
      virtual interface state that are described in <xref
      target="RFC4447"></xref> and in section 10 of <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-pwe3-segmented-pw"></xref> apply to the packet
      pseudowire. Pseudowire status messages indicating pseudowire or remote
      virtual interface faults MUST be mapped to a fault indication on the
      local virtual interface.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Setting the load balance label">
      <t>The client service may wish the packet PW to take advantage of any
      Equal Cost Multi-Path (ECMP) support in the server layer. In this case a
      load balance label as described in <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-pwe3-fat-pw"></xref> may be included in the MPLS label
      stack. Indeed without this feature there will be significant
      polarization of the traffic in the network, since most of the client
      traffic will be either MPLS or IP and therefore most of the traffic
      between a pair of PEs will be carried with the same pair of bottom of
      stack labels. The FAT label must be inserted at the bottom of stack,
      i.e. below the PIDL as shown in <xref target="FatEncap"></xref>.</t>

      <t><figure anchor="FatEncap"
          title="Encapsulation of a pseudowire with a pseudowire load balancing label">
          <artwork><![CDATA[   +-------------------------------+
   |            Client             |
   |          Network Layer        |
   |            packet             |  n octets
   |                               |
   +-------------------------------+ 
   |    Optional Control Word      |  4 octets 
   +-------------------------------+
   |        FAT Label (S=1)        |  4 octets   
   +-------------------------------+
   |        PID Label (S=0)        |  4 Octets
   +-------------------------------+
   |          PW label             |  4 octets
   +-------------------------------+
   |   Server MPLS Tunnel Label(s) |  n*4 octets (four octets per label)
   +-------------------------------+
 
    
 

]]></artwork>

          <postamble></postamble>
        </figure></t>

      <t>Where the client service is MPLS it would be appropriate to copy the
      client layer, bottom of stack MPLS label into the FAT label. Where the
      client layer is IP the FAT label would typically be calculated by
      hashing on the source and destination addresses, the protocol ID and
      higher-layer flow-dependent fields such as TCP/UDP ports, L2TPv3 Session
      ID&rsquo;s etc.</t>

      <t>The exact specification of the method of selecting an appropriate
      load balance label value is outside the scope of this document.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Client Network Layer Model">
      <t>The packet PW appears as a single point to point link to the client
      layer. Network Layer adjacency formation and maintenance between the
      client equipments will the follow normal practice needed to support the
      required relationship in the client layer. The assignment of metrics for
      this point to point link is a matter for the client layer. In a hop by
      hop routing network the metrics would normally be assigned by
      appropriate configuration of the embedded client network layer equipment
      (e.g. the embedded client LSR). Where the client was using the packet PW
      as part of a traffic engineered path, it is up to the operator of the
      client network to ensure that the server layer operator provides the
      necessary service layer agreement.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Congestion Considerations ">
      <t>This pseudowire is normally used to carry IP, MPLS and their
      associated support protocols over an MPLS network. There are no
      congestion considerations beyond those that ordinarily apply to an IP or
      MPLS network. Where the packet protocol being carried is not IP or MPLS
      and the traffic volumes are greater than that ordinarily associated with
      the support protocols in an IP or MPLS network, the congestion
      considerations being developed for PWs apply <xref
      target="RFC3985"></xref>, <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-pwe3-ms-pw-arch"></xref>.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Security Considerations">
      <t>The packet pseudowire provides no means of protecting the contents or
      delivery of the pseudowire packets on behalf of the client packet
      service. The packet pseudowire may, however, leverage security
      mechanisms provided by the MPLS Tunnel Layer. A more detailed discussion
      of pseudowire security is given in <xref target="RFC3985"></xref>, <xref
      target="RFC4447"></xref> and <xref target="RFC3916"></xref>.</t>

      <t>The Protocol FEC, and corresponding label is only used in the context
      of a packet PW, and it does not change the security implications already
      discussed in <xref target="RFC4447"></xref>.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="IANA Considerations ">
      <t>Editor's note - the text below was provided to me but I cannot see
      the reservation in the registry.</t>

      <t>A FEC element allocation of 0x83 has already be made by IANA.
      However, IANA are requested to up date the registry "Forwarding
      Equivalence Class (FEC) Type Name Space" with a reference to this RFC
      number once the number is allocated.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>The authors acknowledge the contribution make by Sami Boutros, Giles
      Herron, Siva Sivabalan and David Ward to this document.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119"?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.4447'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.4385'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.1661'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.5085'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.5586'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.5036'?>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.3985'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-pwe3-segmented-pw'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.5317'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.3916'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-pwe3-fat-pw'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.4448'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-pwe3-ms-pw-arch'?>
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
