<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='./rfc2629.xslt' ?>

<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="no"?>
<?rfc compact="no" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<?rfc linkmailto="yes" ?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" >

<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='./rfc2629.xslt' ?>

<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="no" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<rfc ipr="trust200902" docName="draft-gutmann-cms-hmac-enc-05.txt" category="std">

  <!-- ======================================================================== -->
  <front>
    <title abbrev="MAC-Enc-in-CMS">Using MAC-authenticated Encryption in the Cryptographic Message Syntax (CMS)</title>
    <author initials="P." surname="Gutmann" fullname="Peter Gutmann">
      <organization abbrev="University of Auckland">University of Auckland</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Department of Computer Science</street>
          <city>University of Auckland</city>
          <city>Auckland</city>
          <country>New Zealand</country>
        </postal>
        <email>pgut001@cs.auckland.ac.nz</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date year="2011"/>
    <area>Security Area</area>
    <workgroup>S/MIME Working Group</workgroup>
    <keyword>Internet-Draft</keyword>
    <abstract>
      <t>

This document specifies the conventions for using MAC-authenticated encryption
with the Cryptographic Message Syntax (CMS) authenticated-enveloped-data
content type.  This mirrors the use of a MAC combined with an encryption
algorithm that's already employed in IPsec, SSL/TLS, and SSH, which is widely
supported in existing crypto libraries and hardware, and has been extensively
analysed by the crypto community.

      </t>
    </abstract>

  </front>
  <!-- ======================================================================== -->
  <middle>

    <!-- ====================================================================== -->
    <section anchor="introduction" title="Introduction">
      <t>

This document specifies the conventions for using MAC-authenticated encryption
with the Cryptographic Message Syntax (CMS) authenticated-enveloped-data
content type.  This mirrors the use of a MAC combined with an encryption
algorithm that's already employed in IPsec, SSL/TLS, and SSH, which is widely
supported in existing crypto libraries and hardware, and has been extensively
analysed by the crypto community.

      </t>
      <section anchor="mustshouldmay" title="Conventions Used in This Document">
        <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT",
          "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described
          in <xref target="RFC2119"/>.</t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <!-- ====================================================================== -->
    <section anchor="usecase" title="Background">
      <t>

Integrity-protected encryption is a standard feature of session-oriented
security protocols like <xref target="IPsec"/>, <xref target="SSH"/>, and
<xref target="TLS"/>, but until recently wasn't available for message-based
security protocols like CMS, although <xref target="OpenPGP"/> added a form of
integrity protection by encrypting a SHA-1 hash of the message alongside the
message contents to provide authenticate-and-encrypt protection.  Usability
studies have shown that users expect encryption to provide integrity
protection <xref target="Garfinkel"/>, creating cognitive dissonance problems
when the security mechanisms don't in fact provide this assurance.

      </t>
      <t>

This document applies the same encrypt-and-authenticate mechanism already
employed in IPsec, SSH, and SSL/TLS, to CMS (technically some of these
actually use authenticate-and-encrypt rather than encrypt-and-authenticate,
since what's authenticated is the plaintext and not the ciphertext).  This
mechanism is widely supported in existing crypto libraries and hardware, and
has been extensively analysed by the crypto community
<xref target="EncryptThenAuth"/>.

      </t>
    </section>
    <!-- ====================================================================== -->
    <section anchor="overview" title="CMS Encrypt-and-Authenticate Overview">
      <t>

Conventional CMS encryption uses a content encryption key (CEK) to encrypt a
message payload.  Authenticated encryption requires two keys, one for
encryption and a second one for authentication.  Like other mechanisms that
use authenticated encryption, this document employs a pseudorandom function
(PRF) to convert a single block of keying material into the two keys required
for encryption and authentication.  This converts the standard CMS encryption
operation:

        <figure><artwork><![CDATA[
    KEK( CEK ) || CEK( data )
        ]]></artwork></figure>

into:

        <figure><artwork><![CDATA[
    KEK( master_secret ) || MAC( CEK( data ) )
        ]]></artwork></figure>

where the MAC and encryption keys are derived from the master_secret via:

        <figure><artwork><![CDATA[
    MAC-K := PRF( master_secret, "authentication" );
    CEK-K := PRF( master_secret, "encryption" );
        ]]></artwork></figure>

      </t>
      <section anchor="overview_rationale" title="Rationale">
        <t>

There are several possible means of deriving the two keys required for the
encrypt-and-authenticate process from the single key normally provided by the
key exchange or key transport mechanisms.  Several of these however have
security or practical issues.  For example any mechanism that uses the single
exchanged key in its entirety for encryption (using, perhaps, PRF( key ) as
the MAC key) can be converted back to unauthenticated data by removing the
outer MAC layer and rewriting the CMS envelope back to plain EnvelopedData or
EncryptedData.  By applying the PRF intermediate step, any attempt at a
rollback attack will result in a decryption failure.

      </t>
      <t>

The option chosen here, the use of a PRF to derive the necessary sets of
keying material from a master secret, is well-established through its use in
IPsec, SSH, and SSL/TLS, and is widely supported in both crypto libraries and
in encryption hardware.

      </t>
      <t>

The PRF used is PBKDF2 because its existing use in CMS makes it the most
obvious candidate for such a function.  If in the future a universal PRF, for
example <xref target="HKDF"/>, is adopted then this can be substituted for
PBKDF2 by specifying it in the prfAlgorithm field covered in
<xref target="enc-auth"/>.

      </t>
      <t>

The resulting processing operations consist of a combination of the operations
used for the existing CMS content types EncryptedData and AuthenticatedData,
allowing them to be implemented relatively simply using existing code.

      </t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <!-- ====================================================================== -->
    <section anchor="enc-auth" title="CMS Encrypt-and-Authenticate ">
      <t>

The encrypt-and-authenticate mechanism is implemented within the existing CMS
RecipientInfo framework by defining a new pseudo-algorithm type authEnc which
is used in place of a monolithic encrypt and hash algorithm.  The
RecipientInfo is used as a key container for the master secret used by the
pseudo-algorithm from which the encryption and authentication keys for
existing single-purpose encrypt-only and MAC-only algorithms are derived.
Thus instead of using the RecipientInfo to communicate (for example) an AES or
HMAC-SHA1 key, it communicates an authEnc keying value from which the
required AES encryption and HMAC-SHA1 authentication keys are derived.

      </t>
      <t>

The authEnc pseudo-algorithm comes in two forms, one conveying 128 bits of
keying material and one conveying 256 bits:

        <figure><artwork><![CDATA[
    id-smime OBJECT IDENTIFIER ::= { iso(1) member-body(2)
                us(840) rsadsi(113549) pkcs(1) pkcs9(9) 16 }

    id-alg  OBJECT IDENTIFIER ::= { id-smime 3 }

    id-alg-authEnc-128 OBJECT IDENTIFIER ::= { id-alg 15 }
    id-alg-authEnc-256 OBJECT IDENTIFIER ::= { id-alg 16 }
        ]]></artwork></figure>

The algorithm parameters are:

        <figure><artwork><![CDATA[
    AuthEncParams ::= SEQUENCE {
        prfAlgorithm   [0] AlgorithmIdentifier DEFAULT PBKDF2,
        encAlgorithm       AlgorithmIdentifier,
        macAlgorithm       AlgorithmIdentifier
        }
        ]]></artwork></figure>

      </t>
      <t>
        <list style="empty">

        <t>prfAlgorithm is the PRF algorithm used to convert the authEnc value
        into the encryption and MAC keys.  The default PRF is
        <xref target="PBKDF2"/> (which in turn has a default PRF algorithm of
        HMAC-SHA1).</t>

        <t>encAlgorithm is the encryption algorithm and associated parameters
        to be used to encrypt the content.</t>

        <t>macAlgorithm is the MAC algorithm and associated parameters to be
        used to authenticate/integrity-protect the content.</t>

        </list>
      </t>
      <t>

When the PRF AlgorithmIdentifier is used to specify a PRF other than the
default PBKDF2-with-HMAC-SHA1 one, the salt parameter MUST be an empty (zero-
length) string and the iterationCount MUST be one, since these values aren't
used in the PRF process. In their encoded form, these two parameters have the
value 08 00 02 01 01.

      </t>
      <section anchor="processing" title="Encrypt-and-Authenticate Message Processing">
        <t>

The randomly-generated authEnc key to be communicated via the RecipientInfo(s)
is converted to separate encryption and authentication keys and applied to the
encrypt-and-authenticate process as follows.  The notation
"PRF( key, salt, iterations )" is used to denote an application of the PRF to
the given keying value and salt, for the given number of iterations:

      </t>
      <t>
        <list style="numbers">

          <t>

The MAC algorithm key is derived from the authEnc key via:

          <figure><artwork><![CDATA[
        MAC-K ::= PRF( authEnc_key, "authentication", 1 );
          ]]></artwork></figure>

          </t>

          <t>
The encryption algorithm key is derived from the authEnc key via:

          <figure><artwork><![CDATA[
        Enc-K ::= PRF( authEnc_key, "encryption", 1 );
          ]]></artwork></figure>

          </t>

          <t>

The data is processed as described in <xref target="AuthEnv"/>, and
specifically since the mechanisms used are a union of EncryptedData and
AuthenticatedData, as per <xref target="CMS"/>.  The one exception to this is
that the EncryptedContentInfo.ContentEncryptionAlgorithmIdentifier data is
MACed before the encrypted content is MAced.  The EncryptedData processing is
applied to the data first and then the AuthenticatedData processing is applied
to the result, so that the nesting is:

          <figure><artwork><![CDATA[
        MAC( contentEncrAlgoID || encrypt( content ) );
          ]]></artwork></figure>

          </t>

<t>If authenticated attributes are present then they are encoded as described
in <xref target="AuthEnv"/> and MACed after the encrypted content, so that the
processing is:

          <figure><artwork><![CDATA[
        MAC( contentEncrAlgoID || encrypt( content ) || authAttr );
          ]]></artwork></figure>

          </t>

        </list>
      </t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="processing-rationale" title="Rationale">
        <t>

When choosing between encrypt-and-authenticate and authenticate-and-encrypt
the more secure option is encrypt-and-authenticate.  There has been extensive
analysis of this in the literature, the best coverage is probably
<xref target="EncryptThenAuth"/>.

        </t>
        <t>

The EncryptedContentInfo.ContentEncryptionAlgorithmIdentifier is the SEQUENCE
containing the id-alg-authEnc-128/id-alg-authEnc-256 OBJECT IDENTIFIER and its
associated AuthEncParams.  This data is MACed exactly as encoded, without any
attempt to re-code it into a canonical form like DER.

        </t>
        <t>

The EncryptedContentInfo.ContentEncryptionAlgorithmIdentifier must be
protected alongside the encrypted content otherwise an attacker could
manipulate the encrypted data indirectly by manipulating the encryption
algorithm parameters, which wouldn't be detected through MACing the encrypted
content alone.  For example by changing the encryption IV it's possible to
modify the results of the decryption after the encrypted data has been
verified via a MAC check.

        </t>
        <t>

The authEnc pseudo-algorithm has two "key sizes" rather than the
one-size-fits-all that the PRF impedance-matching would provide.  This is done
to address real-world experience in the use of AES keys where users demanded
AES-256 alongside AES-128 because of some perception that the former was
"twice as good" as the latter.  Providing an option for keys that go to 11
avoids potential user acceptance problems when someone notices that the
authEnc pseudo-key has "only" 128 bits when they expect their AES keys to be
256 bits long.

        </t>
        <t>

Using a fixed-length key rather than making it a user-selectable parameter is
done for the same reason as AES' quantised key lengths: there's no benefit to
allowing, say, 137-bit keys over basic 128- and 256-bit lengths, it adds
unnecessary complexity, and if the lengths are user-defined then there'll
always be someone who wants keys that go up to 12.  Providing a choice of two
commonly-used lengths gives users the option of choosing a "better" key size
should they feel the need, while not overloading the system with unneeded
flexibility.

        </t>
        <t>

The use of the PRF AlgorithmIdentifier presents some problems because it's
usually not specified in a manner that allows it to be easily used as a
straight KDF.  For example PBKDF2 has parameters:

          <figure><artwork><![CDATA[
    PBKDF2-params ::= SEQUENCE {
        salt OCTET STRING,
        iterationCount INTEGER (1..MAX),
        prf AlgorithmIdentifier {{PBKDF2-PRFs}}
                                DEFAULT algid-hmacWithSHA1
        }
          ]]></artwork></figure>

of which only the prf AlgorithmIdentifier is used here.  In order to avoid
having to define new AlgorithmIdentifiers for each possible PRF, this
specification sets any parameters not required for KDF functionality to no-op
values.  In the case of PBKDF2 this means that the salt has length zero and
the iteration count is set to one, with only the prf AlgorithmIdentifier
playing a part in the processing.  Although it's not possible to know what
form other PRFs-as-KDFs will take, a general note for their application within
this specification is that any non-PRF parameters should similarly be set to
no-op values.

        </t>
        <t>

Specifying a MAC key size gets a bit tricky, most MAC algorithms have some de
facto standard key size and for HMAC algorithms this is usually the same as
the hash output size.  For example for HMAC-MD5 it's 128 bits, for HMAC-SHA1
it's 160 bits, and for HMAC-SHA256 it's 256 bits.  Other MAC algorithms also
have de facto standard key sizes, for example for AES-based MACs it's the AES
key size, 128 bits for AES-128 and 256 bits for AES-256.  This situation makes
it difficult to specify the key size in a normative fashion since it's
dependent on the algorithm type that's being used.  If there is any ambiguity
over which key size should be used then it's recommended that the size be
specified explicitly in the macAlgorithm AlgorithmIdentifier.

        </t>
        <t>

As with other uses of PRFs for cryto impedance matching in protocols like
IPsec, SSL/TLS and SSH, the amount of input to the PRF generally doesn't match
the amount of output.  The general philosophical implications of this are
covered in various analyses of the properties and uses of PRFs.  If you're
worried about this then you can try and approximately match the authEnc "key
size" to the key size of the encryption algorithm being used, although even
there a perfect match for algorithms like Blowfish (448 bits) or RC5 (832
bits) is going to be difficult.

        </t>
        <t>

Apart from the extra step added to key management, all of the processing is
already specified as part of the definition of the standard CMS content-types
Encrypted/EnvelopedData and AuthenticatedData.  This significantly simplifies
both the specification and the implementation task, as no new
content-processing mechanisms are introduced.

        </t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="test-vectors" title="Test Vectors">
        <t>

The following test vectors may be used to verify an implementation of
MAC-authenticated encryption.  This represents a text string encrypted and
authenticated using the password "Password" via CMS PasswordRecipientInfo.
The encryption algorithm used is triple DES, whose short block size (compared
to AES) makes it easier to corrupt arbitrary bytes for testing purposes within
the self-healing CBC mode which will result in correct decryption but a failed
MAC check.

        </t>
        <t>

The test data has the following characteristics:

        </t>
        <t>
          <list style="empty">

          <t>version is set to 0.</t>

          <t>originatorInfo isn't needed and is omitted.</t>

          <t>recipientInfos uses passwordRecipientInfo to allow easy testing
          with a fixed text string.</t>

          <t>authEncryptedContentInfo uses the authEnc128 pseudo-algorithm with
          a key of 128 bits used to derive triple DES and HMAC-SHA1 keys.</t>

          <t>authAttrs aren't used and are omitted.</t>

          <t>mac is the 20-byte HMAC-SHA1 MAC value.</t>

          <t>unauthAttrs aren't used and are omitted.</t>

          </list>
        </t>
        <t>

        <!-- In the following, the numeric OID values have to be wrapped
             onto the next line or xml2rfc complains about excessively-long
             lines.  The start of the numeric OID value is immediately under
             the text name on the line above
        -->
        <figure><artwork><![CDATA[
   0  227: SEQUENCE {
   3   11:   OBJECT IDENTIFIER authEnvelopedData
                               (1 2 840 113549 1 9 16 1 23)
  16  211:   [0] {
  19  208:     SEQUENCE {
  22    1:       INTEGER 0
  25   97:       SET {
  27   95:         [3] {
  29    1:           INTEGER 0
  32   27:           [0] {
  34    9:             OBJECT IDENTIFIER pkcs5PBKDF2
                                         (1 2 840 113549 1 5 12)
  45   14:             SEQUENCE {
  47    8:               OCTET STRING B7 EB 23 A7 6B D2 05 16
  57    2:               INTEGER 5000
         :               }
         :             }
  61   35:           SEQUENCE {
  63   11:             OBJECT IDENTIFIER pwriKEK
                                         (1 2 840 113549 1 9 16 3 9)
  76   20:             SEQUENCE {
  78    8:               OBJECT IDENTIFIER des-EDE3-CBC
                                           (1 2 840 113549 3 7)
  88    8:               OCTET STRING 66 91 02 45 6B 73 BB 99
         :               }
         :             }
  98   24:           OCTET STRING
         :             30 A3 7A B5 D8 F2 87 50 EC 41 04 AE 89 99 26 F0
         :             2E AE 4F E3 F3 52 2B A3
         :           }
         :         }
 124   82:       SEQUENCE {
 126    9:         OBJECT IDENTIFIER data (1 2 840 113549 1 7 1)
 137   51:         SEQUENCE {
 139   11:           OBJECT IDENTIFIER authEnc128
                                       (1 2 840 113549 1 9 16 3 15)
 152   36:           SEQUENCE {
 154   20:             SEQUENCE {
 156    8:               OBJECT IDENTIFIER des-EDE3-CBC
                                           (1 2 840 113549 3 7)
 166    8:               OCTET STRING D2 D0 81 71 4D 3D 9F 11
         :               }
 176   12:             SEQUENCE {
 178    8:               OBJECT IDENTIFIER hmacSHA (1 3 6 1 5 5 8 1 2)
 188    0:               NULL
         :               }
         :             }
         :           }
 190   16:         [0] 3A C6 06 61 41 5D 00 7D 11 35 CD 69 E1 56 CA 10
         :         }
 208   20:       OCTET STRING
         :         33 65 E8 F0 F3 07 06 86 1D A8 47 2C 6D 3A 1D 94
         :         21 40 64 7E
         :       }
         :     }
         :   }
        ]]></artwork></figure>

        </t>
        <t>

        <!-- In the following, the output of uuencode/uuenview needs to be
             hand-edited to make each line 72 chars long.
        -->
        <figure><artwork><![CDATA[
-----BEGIN PKCS7-----
MIHjBgsqhkiG9w0BCRABF6CB0zCB0AIBADFho18CAQCgGwYJKoZIhvcNAQUMMA4ECLfrI6dr
0gUWAgITiDAjBgsqhkiG9w0BCRADCTAUBggqhkiG9w0DBwQIZpECRWtzu5kEGDCjerXY8odQ
7EEEromZJvAurk/j81IrozBSBgkqhkiG9w0BBwEwMwYLKoZIhvcNAQkQAw8wJDAUBggqhkiG
9w0DBwQI0tCBcU09nxEwDAYIKwYBBQUIAQIFAIAQOsYGYUFdAH0RNc1p4VbKEAQUM2Xo8PMH
BoYdqEcsbTodlCFAZH4=
-----END PKCS7-----
        ]]></artwork></figure>

        </t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <!-- ====================================================================== -->
    <section anchor="smimecaps" title="SMIMECapabilities Attribute">
      <t>

An S/MIME client SHOULD announce the set of cryptographic functions that it
supports by using the S/MIME capabilities attribute <xref target="SMIME"/>.
If the client wishes to indicate support for MAC-authenticated encryption, the
capabilities attribute MUST contain the authEnc128 and/or authEnc256 OID
specified above with algorithm parameters ABSENT.  The other algorithms used
in the authEnc algorithm such as the MAC and encryption algorithm are selected
based on the presence of these algorithms in the SMIMECapabilities or by
mutual agreement.

      </t>
    </section>
    <!-- ====================================================================== -->
    <section anchor="security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>

Unlike other CMS authenticated-data mechanisms like SignedData and
AuthenticatedData, AuthEnv's primary transformation isn't authentication but
encryption, so that AuthEnvData may decrypt successfully (in other words the
primary data transformation present in the mechanism will succeed) but the
secondary function of authentication using the MAC value that follows the
encrypted data could still fail.  This can lead to a situation in which an
implementation might output decrypted data before it reaches and verifies the
MAC value.  In other words decryption is performed inline and the result is
available immediately, while the authentication result isn't available until
all of the content has been processed.  If the implementation prematurely
provides data to the user and later comes back to inform them that the earlier
data was, in retrospect, tainted, this may cause users to act prematurely on
the tainted data.

        </t>
        <t>

This situation could occur in a streaming implementation where data has to be
made available as soon as possible (so that the initial plaintext is emitted
before the final ciphertext and MAC value are read), or one where the quantity
of data involved rules out buffering the recovered plaintext until the MAC
value can be read and verified.  In addition an implementation that tries to
be overly helpful may treat missing non-payload trailing data as non-fatal,
allowing an attacker to truncate the data somewhere before the MAC value and
thereby defeat the data authentication.  This is complicated even further by
the fact that an implementation may not be able to determine, when it
encounters truncated data, whether the remainder (including the MAC value)
will arrive presently (a non-failure) or whether it's been truncated by an
attacker and should therefore be treated as a MAC failure.  (Note that this
same issue affects other types of data authentication like signed and MACd
data as well, since an over-optimistic implementation may return data to the
user before checking for a verification failure is possible).

        </t>
        <t>

The exact solution to these issues is somewhat implementation-specific, with
some suggested mitigations being as follows: Implementations should buffer the
entire message if possible and verify the MAC before performing any
decryption.  If this isn't possible due to streaming or message-size
constraints then implementations should consider breaking long messages into a
sequence of smaller ones, each of which can be processed atomically as above.
If even this isn't possible then implementations should make obvious to the
caller or user that an authentication failure has occurred and that the
previously-returned or output data shouldn't be used.  Finally, any
data-formatting problem such as obviously truncated data or missing trailing
data should be treated as a MAC verification failure even if the rest of the
data was processed correctly.

      </t>
    </section>
    <!-- ====================================================================== -->
    <section anchor="iana" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>

This document contains two algorithm identifiers defined by the SMIME Working
Group Registrar in an arc delegated by RSA to the SMIME Working Group: iso(1)
member-body(2) us(840) rsadsi(113549) pkcs(1) pkcs-9(9) smime(16) modules(0).
No action by IANA is necessary for this document or any anticipated updates.

      </t>
    </section>
    <!-- ====================================================================== -->
    <section anchor="ack" title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>

The author would like to thank Jim Schaad and the members of the S/MIME
mailing list for their feedback on this document.

      </t>
    </section>
    <!-- ====================================================================== -->

  </middle>
  <!-- ======================================================================== -->
  <back>

    <references title="Normative References">

      <reference anchor='CMS'>
        <front>
          <title>Cryptographic Message Syntax (CMS)</title>
          <author fullname="Russ Housley" initials="R" surname="Housley">
            <organization />
          </author>
          <date year='2009' month='September' />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name='RFC' value='5652' />
        <format type='TXT' target='http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc5652.txt' />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor='AuthEnv'>
        <front>
          <title>Cryptographic Message Syntax (CMS) Authenticated-Enveloped-Data Content Type</title>
          <author fullname="Russ Housley" initials="R" surname="Housley">
            <organization />
          </author>
          <date year='2007' month='November' />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name='RFC' value='5083' />
        <format type='TXT' target='http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc5083.txt' />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor='PBKDF2'>
        <front>
          <title>PKCS #5: Password-Based Cryptography Specification</title>
          <author fullname="Burt Kaliski" initials="B" surname="Kaliski">
            <organization abbrev="RSA">RSA Laboratories</organization>
          </author>
          <date year='2000' month='September' />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name='RFC' value='2898' />
        <format type='TXT' target='http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc2898.txt' />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor='RFC2119'>
        <front>
          <title abbrev='RFC Key Words'>Key words for use in RFCs to Indicate Requirement Levels</title>
          <author initials='S.' surname='Bradner' fullname='Scott Bradner'>
            <organization>Harvard University</organization>
          </author>
          <date year='1997' month='March' />
          <area>General</area>
          <keyword>keyword</keyword>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name='BCP' value='14' />
        <seriesInfo name='RFC' value='2119' />
        <format type='TXT' target='ftp://ftp.isi.edu/in-notes/rfc2119.txt' />
        <format type='HTML' target='http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/html/rfc2119.html' />
        <format type='XML' target='http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/xml/rfc2119.xml' />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor='SMIME'>
        <front>
          <title>Secure/Multipurpose Internet Mail Extensions (S/MIME) Version 3.2 Message Specification</title>
          <author fullname="Blake Ramsdell" initials="B" surname="Ramsdell">
            <organization>Brute Squad Labs</organization>
          </author>
          <author fullname="Sean Turner" initials="S" surname="Turner">
            <organization>IECA, Inc</organization>
          </author>
          <date year='2010' month='January' />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name='RFC' value='5751' />
        <format type='TXT' target='http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc5751.txt' />
      </reference>

    </references>
    <references title="Informative References">

      <reference anchor='HKDF'>
        <front>
          <title>HMAC-based Extract-and-Expand Key Derivation Function (HKDF)</title>
          <author fullname="Hugo Krawczyk" initials="H" surname="Krawczyk">
            <organization abbrev="IBM">IBM Research</organization>
          </author>
          <author fullname="Pasi Eronen" initials="P" surname="Eronen">
            <organization abbrev="Nokia">Nokia Research Center</organization>
          </author>
          <date year='2010' month='May' />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name='RFC' value='5869' />
        <format type='TXT' target='http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc5869.txt' />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor='EncryptThenAuth'>
        <!-- No-one seems to know how to reference publications like
             conference proceedings in RFC-XML, this is one attempt... -->
        <front>
          <title>The Order of Encryption and Authentication for Protecting Communications (or: How Secure Is SSL?)</title>
          <author fullname="Hugo Krawczyk" initials="H" surname="Krawczyk">
            <organization abbrev="IBM">IBM Research</organization>
          </author>
          <date year='2001' month='August' />
<!--      <note>Proceedings of Crypto'01, Springer-Verlag LNCS No.2139, p.310</note> -->
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name='Springer-Verlag LNCS' value='2139' />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="OpenPGP">
        <front>
          <title>OpenPGP Message Format</title>
          <author fullname="Jon Callas" initials="J" surname="Callas">
            <organization abbrev="PGP Corporation">PGP Corporation</organization>
          </author>
          <author fullname="Lutz Donnerhacke" initials="L" surname="Donnerhacke">
            <organization abbrev="IKS">IKS GmbH</organization>
          </author>
          <author fullname="Hal Finney" initials="H" surname="Hal">
            <organization abbrev="PGP Corporation">PGP Corporation</organization>
          </author>
          <author fullname="David Shaw" initials="D" surname="Shaw">
            <organization />
          </author>
          <author fullname="Rodney Thayer" initials="R" surname="Thayer">
            <organization />
          </author>
          <date month="November" year="2007"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name='RFC' value='4880' />
        <format type='TXT' target='http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc4880.txt' />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor='SSH'>
        <front>
          <title>The Secure Shell (SSH) Transport Layer Protocol</title>
          <author fullname="Tatu Ylonen" initials="T" surname="Ylonen">
            <organization abbrev="SSH">SSH Communications Security Corp</organization>
          </author>
          <author fullname="Chris Lonvick" initials="C" surname="Lonvick">
            <organization abbrev="Cisco">Cisco Systems, Inc</organization>
          </author>
          <date year='2006' month='January' />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name='RFC' value='4253' />
        <format type='TXT' target='http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc4253.txt' />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor='TLS'>
        <front>
          <title>The Transport Layer Security (TLS) Protocol Version 1.2</title>
          <author fullname="Tim Dierks" initials="T" surname="Dierks">
            <organization abbrev="Independent">Independent</organization>
          </author>
          <author fullname="Eric Rescorla" initials="E" surname="Rescorla">
            <organization abbrev="RTFM">RTFM, Inc</organization>
          </author>
          <date year='2008' month='August' />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name='RFC' value='5246' />
        <format type='TXT' target='http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc5246.txt' />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor='IPsec'>
        <front>
          <title>Security Architecture for the Internet Protocol</title>
          <author fullname="Stephen Kent" initials="S" surname="Kent">
            <organization abbrev="BBN">BBN Technologies</organization>
          </author>
          <author fullname="Karen Seo" initials="K" surname="Seo">
            <organization abbrev="BBN">BBN Technologies</organization>
          </author>
          <date year='2005' month='December' />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name='RFC' value='4301' />
        <format type='TXT' target='http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc4301.txt' />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor='Garfinkel'>
        <!-- See the earlier comment for conference proceedings -->
        <front>
          <title>Design Principles and Patterns for Computer Systems That Are Simultaneously Secure and Usable</title>
          <author fullname="Simson Garfinkel" initials="S" surname="Garfinkel">
            <organization abbrev="MIT">Massachusetts Institute of Technology</organization>
          </author>
          <date year='2005' month='May' />
        </front>
      </reference>

    </references>
    <!-- ====================================================================== -->
  </back>
</rfc>
