<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!-- This template is for creating an Internet Draft using xml2rfc,
     which is available here: http://xml.resource.org. -->
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!-- One method to get references from the online citation libraries.
     There has to be one entity for each item to be referenced. 
     An alternate method (rfc include) is described in the references. -->
<!ENTITY RFC2119 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6333 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6333.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6264 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6264.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6146 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6146.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.ietf-intarea-ipv6-required SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-intarea-ipv6-required.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.ietf-behave-lsn-requirements SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-behave-lsn-requirements.xml">
]>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<!-- used by XSLT processors -->
<!-- For a complete list and description of processing instructions (PIs), 
     please see http://xml.resource.org/authoring/README.html. -->
<!-- Below are generally applicable Processing Instructions (PIs) that most I-Ds might want to use.
     (Here they are set differently than their defaults in xml2rfc v1.32) -->
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<!-- give errors regarding ID-nits and DTD validation -->
<!-- control the table of contents (ToC) -->
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<!-- generate a ToC -->
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<!-- the number of levels of subsections in ToC. default: 3 -->
<!-- control references -->
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<!-- use symbolic references tags, i.e, [RFC2119] instead of [1] -->
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<!-- sort the reference entries alphabetically -->
<!-- control vertical white space 
     (using these PIs as follows is recommended by the RFC Editor) -->
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<!-- do not start each main section on a new page -->
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<!-- keep one blank line between list items -->
<!-- end of list of popular I-D processing instructions -->
<rfc category="bcp" docName="draft-george-ipv6-support-01" ipr="trust200902"
     updates="">
  <!-- category values: std, bcp, info, exp, and historic
     ipr values: full3667, noModification3667, noDerivatives3667
     you can add the attributes updates="NNNN" and obsoletes="NNNN" 
     they will automatically be output with "(if approved)" -->

  <!-- ***** FRONT MATTER ***** -->

  <front>
    <!-- The abbreviated title is used in the page header - it is only necessary if the 
         full title is longer than 39 characters -->

    <title abbrev="IPv6-support">IPv6 Support Within IETF work</title>

    <!-- add 'role="editor"' below for the editors if appropriate -->

    <!-- Another author who claims to be an editor -->

    <author fullname="Wesley George" initials="W" surname="George">
      <organization>Time Warner Cable</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>13820 Sunrise Valley Drive</street>

          <!-- Reorder these if your country does things differently -->

          <city>Herndon</city>

          <region>VA</region>

          <code>20171</code>

          <country>US</country>
        </postal>

        <phone>+1 703-561-2540</phone>

        <email>wesley.george@twcable.com</email>

        <!-- uri and facsimile elements may also be added -->
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Chris Donley" initials="C" surname="Donley">
      <organization>Cablelabs</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>858 Coal Creek Circle</street>

          <!-- Reorder these if your country does things differently -->

          <city>Louisville</city>

          <region>CO</region>

          <code>80027</code>

          <country>US</country>
        </postal>

        <phone>+1-303-661-9100</phone>

        <email>C.Donley@cablelabs.com</email>

        <!-- uri and facsimile elements may also be added -->
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Lee Howard" initials="L" surname="Howard">
      <organization>Time Warner Cable</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>13820 Sunrise Valley Drive</street>

          <!-- Reorder these if your country does things differently -->

          <city>Herndon</city>

          <region>VA</region>

          <code>20171</code>

          <country>US</country>
        </postal>

        <phone>+1-703-345-3513</phone>

        <email>lee.howard@twcable.com</email>

        <!-- uri and facsimile elements may also be added -->
      </address>
    </author>

    <date day="21" month="February" year="2012"/>

    <!-- If the month and year are both specified and are the current ones, xml2rfc will fill 
         in the current day for you. If only the current year is specified, xml2rfc will fill 
	 in the current day and month for you. If the year is not the current one, it is 
	 necessary to specify at least a month (xml2rfc assumes day="1" if not specified for the 
	 purpose of calculating the expiry date).  With drafts it is normally sufficient to 
	 specify just the year. -->

    <!-- Meta-data Declarations -->

    <area>General</area>

    <workgroup>Internet Engineering Task Force</workgroup>

    <!-- WG name at the upperleft corner of the doc,
         IETF is fine for individual submissions.  
	 If this element is not present, the default is "Network Working Group",
         which is used by the RFC Editor as a nod to the history of the IETF. -->

    <keyword>IETF IPv4 IPv6 protocol</keyword>

    <!-- Keywords will be incorporated into HTML output
         files in a meta tag but they have no effect on text or nroff
         output. If you submit your draft to the RFC Editor, the
         keywords will be used for the search engine. -->

    <abstract>
      <t>This document recommends that IETF formally require its standards
      work to be IP version agnostic or to explicitly include support for
      IPv6, with some exceptions. It recommends that future IPv4 work be
      limited to solving documented operational problems identified through
      deployment experience.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t><xref target="I-D.ietf-intarea-ipv6-required"/> gives guidance to
      implementers that in order to ensure interoperability and proper
      function after IPv4 exhaustion, IP-capable devices need to support IPv6,
      because global IPv4 exhaustion creates many circumstances where the use
      of IPv6 will no longer be optional.</t>

      <t>In the above draft, IETF is making the recommendation that IP-capable
      devices need to support IPv6. Therefore, it is imperative that the
      results of IETF efforts enable implementers to follow that
      recommendation. This document provides explicit recommendations and
      guidance as to how IETF itself should handle future work as it relates
      to Internet Protocol versions.</t>

      <section title="Requirements Language">
        <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
        "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
        document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
        target="RFC2119">RFC 2119</xref>.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Requirements and Recommendation">
      <t>When considering support for IPv4 vs IPv6 within IETF work, the
      general goal is to provide tools that enable networks and applications
      to operate seamlessly in any combination of IPv4-only, dual-stack, or
      IPv6-only as their needs dictate.</t>

      <t>As IPv6 deployment grows, IETF will naturally focus on features and
      protocols that enhance and extend IPv6, along with continuing work on
      items that are IP version agnostic. New features and protocols will not
      typically be introduced for use as IPv4-only. However, as of this
      document's writing, there is no documented requirement for all IETF work
      to support IPv6, either implicitly by being network-layer agnostic or
      explicitly by having an IPv6-specific implementation.</t>

      <t>Due to the existing operational base of IPv4, it is not realistic to
      completely bar further work on IPv4 within the IETF at this time, nor to
      formally declare it historic. This draft is viewed as a first step in
      IPv4's eventual phase-out, in that it limits IPv4-specific activities
      within the IETF to a few key areas. Until the time when IPv4 is no
      longer in wide use and/or declared historic, the IETF needs to continue
      to update IPv4-only protocols and features for vital operational or
      security issues. Similarly, IETF needs to continue the work related to
      IPv4-to-IPv6 transition tools for migrating more traffic to IPv6. As the
      transition to IPv6-capable networks accelerates, it is also likely that
      some changes may be necessary in IPv4 protocols to facilitate
      decommissioning IPv4 in a way that does not create unacceptable impact
      to applications or users. These sorts of IPv4-focused activities should
      be allowed to continue, especially if they are accompanied by real
      operational experience documenting the problem to be solved.</t>

      <t>Generally, the IETF should be focused on two goals as it relates to
      IP version support:</t>

      <t><list style="numbers">
          <t>Transition technologies that enable IPv6</t>

          <t>Complete support for IPv6-only operation</t>
        </list>It is helpful to clarify what the above statements mean.
      "Transition technologies" is a fairly broad term that can be interpreted
      in a lot of different ways. At its broadest, it includes providing IPv6
      support over an IPv4 network and vice versa, methods to interwork
      IPv4-only devices and IPv6-only devices, as well as technologies to
      extend IPv4's life despite the lack of additional globally unique
      addresses to provide to hosts and networks. This document makes the
      distinction between those technologies which provide a path for an
      IPv4-only network to become dual-stack or otherwise use native IPv6, and
      those which primarily serve to extend the life of IPv4 while not
      providing a path to native IPv6 support on the network in question. The
      IETF needs to be focusing their work on transition mechanisms that
      provide progress toward native IPv6, are simple, stateless, and use
      mechanisms which preserve end-to-end connectivity as much as
      possible.</t>

      <t>While the eventual end state may be networks and end points that are
      IPv6-only, the timeframe for that to become a reality is likely to be
      different within each network. This means that there are multiple
      legitimate use cases for continued support for IPv4, including methods
      to translate between IPv4-only hosts and IPv6-only hosts, as well as
      methods for IPv4 address sharing in order to reduce the impact of IPv4
      exhaustion on implementations that still use IPv4. The IETF has provided
      several soutions that have implementations to address the need to keep
      business running and users happy during this transition, including Dual
      Stack Lite <xref target="RFC6333">RFC 6333</xref>, NAT64 <xref
      target="RFC6146">RFC 6146</xref>, as well as Carrier Grade NAT (<xref
      target="I-D.ietf-behave-lsn-requirements"/> and <xref
      target="RFC6264">RFC 6264</xref>). As the above documents complete the
      IETF document lifecycle and become RFCs, and the BEHAVE WG closes after
      completion of its charter, this should comprise a body of solutions to
      meet the needs of the majority of IPv4's continued use cases such that
      work on additional protocols to extend the life of IPv4 no longer needs
      to be an area of focus for the IETF.</t>

      <t>[**authors' note, remove before publication**]</t>

      <t>This document is not intended to be yet another survey of available
      transition mechanisms, so the list above does not have to be exhaustive.
      The intent was to cite the most likely candidates for wide deployment as
      evidence that there exists a consensus solution for each major case.
      There are a number of other drafts that could be included in the above
      list of solutions, but as draft documents, they have not yet found
      consensus. For example, A+P is an Experimental RFC (6346), and its
      derivative works such as MAP
      (draft-mdt-softwire-mapping-address-and-port) and potentially 4rd-
      {E,T,U}, dIVI-PD, stateless 4over6, etc. are current internet-draft
      documents. Under the structure proposed in this document, a working
      group would need to find consensus on a problem statement, defining a
      real operational problem that the proposed solution would solve, before
      any proposed solution could be adopted as a WG item.</t>

      <t>[end author's note]</t>

      <t>It is not possible to document completely which technologies and
      drafts are and are not acceptable, so this document is intended to be a
      guideline for working groups and IESG members when evaluating new and
      existing work, rather than being an exhaustive list. There are corner
      cases and use cases for which the existing solutions may not be a
      perfect fit, as well as unsolved theoretical problems, but standardizing
      solutions for every possible permutation moves into the realm of
      diminishing returns, and solutions applicable only to one or two
      networks are best pursued between the operator and their vendors. Thus,
      further work on IPv4-extension protocols such as those mentioned MUST be
      triggered by a draft documenting actual operational experiences,
      focusing on problems encountered in deployment that the IETF needs to
      solve through protocol changes. This will ensure that IETF is focusing
      its energies on solving real operational problems that exist in IPv4 and
      transition technologies, rather than interesting theoretical problems,
      corner cases or new features.</t>

      <t>To put this set of guidelines succinctly:</t>

      <t><list style="empty">
          <t>IETF SHOULD continue to update IPv4-only protocols and features
          to address vital operational or security issues.</t>

          <t>IETF work SHOULD update existing IPv4 to IPv6 transition and
          interworking technologies as necessary to address operational
          problems encountered during the implementation phase.</t>

          <t>IETF work SHOULD continue to make updates to IPv4 protocols and
          features to facilitate IPv4 decommissioning</t>

          <t>IETF work that is not related to the above exceptions MUST be IP
          version agnostic (because it is implemented above the network layer)
          or MUST explicitly support IPv6.</t>

          <t>IETF SHOULD NOT initiate new IPv4 extension technology
          development.</t>

          <t>IETF work MAY support IPv6-only applications and protocols,
          especially in cases where supporting the protocol or feature in IPv4
          would be difficult or impossible.</t>

          <t>IETF work SHOULD continue to update IPv4-only protocols and
          applications to support IPv6 as necessary and appropriate.</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>This last item raises a question about where feature parity between
      IPv4 and IPv6 fits into the discussion. In this context, feature parity
      ensures that there are no gaps where functionality exists in IPv4 but
      has no equivalent in IPv6. Note that this does not mean a direct 1:1
      relationship where every feature that exists in IPv4 will exist in IPv6.
      This is because IPv6 eliminates the need for some features that exist in
      IPv4, IPv4 supports some legacy features that are no longer in use, and
      some existing IPv4 features are integrated into other parts of IPv6. In
      addition, as new features and implementations take advantage of the
      differences between IPv6 and IPv4, it is expected that IPv6 will surpass
      IPv4 and certain features and protocols will not have specific support
      for IPv4. A comprehensive list of needed parity items and enhancements
      for IPv6 is outside the scope of this document, but this document
      recommends that the charters and work items of currently active IETF
      Working Groups (WGs) be evaluated to ensure that they are supporting a
      goal to eliminate of any remaining places in IETF standards and
      protocols where IPv4 is required for complete and proper function, and
      that they do not focus on IPv4 extension technologies. This document
      does not suggest a timeline where this must be completed, as it will
      likely happen organically over a long period of time.</t>
    </section>

    <!-- This PI places the pagebreak correctly (before the section title) in the text output. -->

    <?rfc needLines="8" ?>

    <section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>Thanks to the following people for their comments: Jari Arkko, Ralph
      Droms, Scott Brim, Margaret Wasserman. Thanks also to Randy Bush, Mark
      Townsley, and Dan Wing for their discussion in IntArea WG at IETF 81 in
      Taipei, TW regarding transition technologies, IPv4 life extension, and
      IPv6 support.</t>
    </section>

    <!-- Possibly a 'Contributors' section ... -->

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>This memo includes no request to IANA.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>This document generates no new security considerations because it is
      not defining a new protocol. However, it is important to note that the
      recommendations above to stop work on IPv4-only protocols and
      applications include an exception for fixes to critical security issues.
      The definition of critical in this context will be left to the
      appropriate ADs, but while IPv4 is still in wide use, it is expected
      that these exceptions will occur from time to time.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <!-- References split into informative and normative -->

    <!-- There are 2 ways to insert reference entries from the citation libraries:
     1. define an ENTITY at the top, and use "ampersand character"RFC2629; here (as shown)
     2. simply use a PI "less than character"?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119.xml"?> here
        (for I-Ds: include="reference.I-D.narten-iana-considerations-rfc2434bis.xml")

     Both are cited textually in the same manner: by using xref elements.
     If you use the PI option, xml2rfc will, by default, try to find included files in the same
     directory as the including file. You can also define the XML_LIBRARY environment variable
     with a value containing a set of directories to search.  These can be either in the local
     filing system or remote ones accessed by http (http://domain/dir/... ).-->

    <references title="Normative References">
      <!--?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"?-->

      &RFC2119;
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <!-- Here we use entities that we defined at the beginning. -->

      &I-D.ietf-intarea-ipv6-required;

      &I-D.ietf-behave-lsn-requirements;

      &RFC6146;

      &RFC6264;

      &RFC6333;

      <!-- A reference written by by an organization not a person. -->
    </references>

    <!-- Change Log

v00 2006-03-15  EBD   Initial version

v01 2006-04-03  EBD   Moved PI location back to position 1 -
                      v3.1 of XMLmind is better with them at this location.
v02 2007-03-07  AH    removed extraneous nested_list attribute,
                      other minor corrections
v03 2007-03-09  EBD   Added comments on null IANA sections and fixed heading capitalization.
                      Modified comments around figure to reflect non-implementation of
                      figure indent control.  Put in reference using anchor="DOMINATION".
                      Fixed up the date specification comments to reflect current truth.
v04 2007-03-09 AH     Major changes: shortened discussion of PIs,
                      added discussion of rfc include.
v05 2007-03-10 EBD    Added preamble to C program example to tell about ABNF and alternative 
                      images. Removed meta-characters from comments (causes problems).  -->
  </back>
</rfc>
