<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY RFC2119 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC2328 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2328.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3392 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3392.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4360 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4360.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4364 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4364.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4577 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4577.xml">
]>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc iprnotified="no" ?>
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<rfc category="std" ipr="trust200902" docName="draft-freedman-l3vpn-ospf2-4364-ce-01">
	<front>
		<title abbrev="draft-freedman-l3vpn-ospf2-4364-ce-01">
                    OSPF Version 2 as the Customer Edge/Customer Protocol for BGP/MPLS IP VPNs
                 </title>
		<author initials="D." surname="Freedman" fullname="David Freedman">
			<organization abbrev="Claranet">
                        Claranet
                    </organization>
			<address>
				<postal>
					<street/>
					<city>London</city>
					<country>UK</country>
				</postal>
				<phone>+44 20 7685 8000</phone>
				<email>david.freedman@uk.clara.net</email>
			</address>
		</author>
		<date year="2012"/>
		<area>General</area>
		<workgroup>Internet Engineering Task Force</workgroup>
		<keyword>BGP</keyword>
		<keyword>OSPF</keyword>
		<keyword>OSPFv2</keyword>
		<keyword>MPLS</keyword>
		<keyword>SHAM</keyword>
		<keyword>VPN</keyword>
		<abstract>
			<t>
				RFC4577 (OSPF as the Provider/Customer Edge Protocol for BGP/MPLS IP VPNs) proposes a mechanism for the use of
				the Open Shortest Path First V2 ("OSPF", RFC2328) protocol between the Provider Edge ("PE") and Customer Edge ("CE") routers
				within a BGP/MPLS IP Virtual Private Network ("IPVPN", RFC4364). 
			</t>
			<t>
				The standard provides for use of such a provider VPN to join discontiguous locations together, preserving the OSPF
				area and domain behaviour. 
			</t>
			<t>
				This document describes a technique for utilising the same, IPVPN network infrastructure without 
				the requirement to enable the OSPF protocol on the PE/CE interface and thus relieve the PE router of OSPF duties. 
			</t>
		</abstract>
	</front>
	<middle>
		<section anchor="introduction" title="Introduction">
			<t>
				<xref target="RFC4577"/> describes a mechanism whereby discontiguous locations belonging to the same OSPF area and domain
				are connected by use of an <xref target="RFC4364"/> IPVPN network. 
			</t>
			<t>
				The premise (see <xref target="intro-original"/>) is that OSPF <xref target="RFC2328"/> routing information from a site is learned by the attached
				PE router through an OSPF adjacency with the site's CE router. This OSPF routing information is learned in the context of 
				a Virtual Routing and Forwarding ("VRF") instance intended to trigger redistribution into the provider BGP as a VPN-IPv4 route 
				through the addition of various Extended Communities <xref target="RFC4360"/> such as "Route Target" (to select the desired 
				destination VRFs when imported by other PE routers),  "OSPF Domain Identifier" (to determine if the route should be treated
				as internal or external to the CE OSPF domain) and "OSPF Route Type" (to encode the LSA type as it was received from the OSPF
				neighbor).
            </t>
			<t>
				When a remote PE router, importing such routes into a VRF (due to a matching Route-Target in a VRF import policy), locates the OSPF 
				extended communities, it uses them to originate OSPF LSAs to its attached CE. Providing the OSPF domain ID is the same, 
				BGP routes can be redistributed back into the CE-attached OSPF area using the information encoded in the BGP update, fooling
				the attached site into thinking that there is a contiguous OSPF domain.
			</t>
			<t>
				"Sham Links" may then be created between VPN residing endpoints on all involved PE routers, to provide simulated 
				intra-area links, ensuring that any "Backdoor" links between C routers are not automatically selected by OSPF 
				in preference to the provider network links (which would normally be treated as inter-area had the Sham Link not been present).
			</t> 
			<figure anchor="intro-original">
				<artwork>
		               Sham Link
		             _____________
		            /             \
		           /    ,-----.    \
		          [PE1]; IPVPN +[PE2]
		            |  :  BGP  +  |
		OSPF        |   `-----'   |    OSPF
		            |             |
		Site A    [CE1]         [CE2]   Site B
		            |    Area 0   |
		OSPF        |             |    OSPF
		          [ C1]         [C3 ]
		OSPF      ,-'             `.   OSPF
		       [ C2]              [C4 ]
		         \__________________/
		             Backdoor Link
        		</artwork>
			</figure>
		</section>
		<section anchor="Problem" title="Problem Statement">
			<t>
				The author infers from the title and language in RFC4577 that the original intention of the document was to provide
				OSPF functionality over an IPVPN network through use of the Provider's PE routers. 
				Since the Provider may use the PE router for multiple customers, and OSPF is based on repeated execution 
				of the Shortest Path First ("SPF") algorithm, this approach may create computation scaling considerations for the PE 
				as the number or complexity of customer topologies using this technology on the PE increases.
			</t>
		</section>
		<section anchor="Solution" title="Solution Statement">
			<t> 
				This document proposes a mechanism for providing this OSPF functionality over IPVPN networks, using only CE routers
				in a single OSPF domain.
				A CE router that performs this function is to be known as an O-CE router. Only IP and BGP are therefore required
				between the O-CE and PE, this is illustrated below in <xref target="solution-new"/>
			</t>
			<figure anchor="solution-new">
				<artwork>
                                ,-----.    
		          [PE1]; IPVPN +[PE2]
		            |  :       +  |
		      BGP   |   `-----'   |   BGP 
		            |    Sham     |
		Site A [O-CE1]--------- [O-CE2]  Site B
		            |    Link     |
		     OSPF   |    Area 0   |   OSPF
		          [ C1]         [C3 ]
		 OSPF     ,-'             `.     OSPF
		       [ C2]              [C4 ]
		         \__________________/
		             Backdoor Link
        		</artwork>
			</figure>
			<t>
				By removing the OSPF from the PE router and placing the responsibility on the O-CE, the provider's existing IPVPN PE routers 
				are no longer forced to run the SPF algorithm since this task can be delegated to the O-CE which does not have the same scaling 
				concerns (it does not share this task with multiple customer domains).
			</t>
		</section>
		<section anchor="domains" title="Domains">
			<t>
				An O-CE is intended to only operate in one OSPF domain, known as the O-CD (O-CE Domain). 
				Though the O-CD is intended to be operator configured on the O-CE, it may instead be automatically discovered 
				(but such mechanisms are outside the scope of this document).
				It is assumed that the reachability signalled in the O-CD reflects the reachability inside the corresponding attached provider VRF.
			</t>
			<t>
				An O-CE receiving reachability information via BGP from the IPVPN network from the provider VRF 
				should interact with the C router domain with respect to the O-CD in line with <xref target="RFC4577"/> Section 4.1. 
				In these cases, the O-CE MAY choose to accept reachability concerning a domain other than the O-CD, 
				in such case the O-CE must flood this information as extra-area (type 5/7).
			</t>
		</section>
		<section anchor="sham" title="Sham Links">
			<t>
				RFC4577 makes the following requirement of creating Sham Links (Sec 4.2.7.3):
			</t>
		   <figure><artwork>
   An OSPF protocol packet is regarded as having been received on a
   particular Sham Link if and only if the following three conditions
   hold:

      -  The packet arrives as an MPLS packet, and its MPLS label stack
         causes it to be "delivered" to the local Sham Link endpoint
         address.

      -  The packet's IP destination address is the local Sham Link
         endpoint address.

      -  The packet's IP source address is the remote Sham Link endpoint
         address.
		 	</artwork></figure>
		<t>
			Although RFC4577 marks the use of Sham Links as "OPTIONAL", creation of such links, with respect to the above
			stated, require that the implementation transmit the OSPF protocol packets over MPLS transport.
		</t>
		<t> 
			Since the intention of this document is to ensure that only IP and BGP are required between O-CE routers, this document
			relaxes the requirements stated in this RFC section, by removing the requirement for the packet to arrive as an MPLS 
			packet. Since the routing information is redistributed into the BGP and labelled by the PE router for use within the 
			Provider's IPVPN network, an additional MPLS LSP is not required.
		</t>
		<t> 
			This document adds the requirement that BGP should be used as a PE/O-CE protocol and that Extended Communities be made
			available to both peers through mutual negotiation of the relevant BGP capability <xref target="RFC3392"/>.
		</t>
		</section>
		<section anchor="behavior" title="Behavioral Considerations">
			<t>
				This document makes the following summary recommendations in respect to behavior:
				<list style="numbers">
					<t>
						That the requirement stated in Section 3 (Requirements) of RFC4577, that OSPF is used as a PE/CE routing protocol
						be relaxed, such that BGP is used as a PE/O-CE routing protocol and that BGP extended communities are enabled between PE and O-CE. 
						A mechanism to filter said communities SHOULD be made available to the operator to ensure that no other (unwanted) 
						extended communities are injected to or from the provider space. 
					</t>
					<t> 
						That the requirement stated in Section 4.2.7.3 (OSPF Protocol on Sham Links) of RFC4577 with regards to the requirement that the OSPF
						protocol packet be received as an MPLS packet, be relaxed in an O-CE router implementation. In its place, the O-CE router MUST
						verify that the OSPF protocol packet is valid based on the operator configuration of valid Sham Link endpoints.
					</t>
				</list>
			</t>
		</section>
		<section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
			<t>
				The Behavioral Considerations (<xref target="behavior"/>) specify that particular behavioral patterns of RFC4577 be 
				relaxed, references to ensuring appropriate security of these modified behaviors can be found here. 
			</t>
			<t>
				It is important to note that the O-CE operates only in the context of the O-CD, this means that the RFC4577 requirements
				supporting multiple domain/instance behaviors are not relevant in the scope of the O-CE. 
			</t>
		</section>
		<section anchor="ACK" title="Acknowledgements">
			<t>
				The author would like to thank Paul Wells for his valuable input. 
            </t>
		</section>
	</middle>
	<back>
		<references title="Normative References">
		   &RFC2119;
		   &RFC2328;
		   &RFC3392;
		   &RFC4360;
		   &RFC4364;
		   &RFC4577;
        </references>
	</back>
</rfc>
