<?xml version='1.0'?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [

<!ENTITY RFC3348    PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3348.xml'>
<!ENTITY RFC3501    PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3501.xml'>
<!ENTITY RFC5226    PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5226.xml'>
<!ENTITY RFC5234    PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5234.xml'>
<!ENTITY RFC6154    PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6154.xml'>

]>

<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='http://xml.resource.org/authoring/rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc tocompact="no" ?>
<?rfc tocindent="no" ?>
<?rfc comments="yes" ?>
<?rfc inline="yes" ?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc iprnotified="no" ?>
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="yes"?>

<rfc
  category="std"
  ipr="trust200902"
  updates="3348,3501,6154"
  docName="draft-iceman-imap-specialuse-important-01">

  <front>
    <title abbrev="IMAP Special-Use: Important">
      IMAP LIST Special-Use Attribute: \Important
    </title>

    <author initials='B.' surname='Leiba' fullname='Barry Leiba'>
      <organization>Huawei Technologies</organization>
      <address>
        <phone>+1 646 827 0648</phone>
        <email>barryleiba@computer.org</email>
        <uri>http://internetmessagingtechnology.org/</uri>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author initials="E." surname="Iceman" fullname="Eric Iceman">
      <organization>Google, Inc.</organization>
      <address>
        <email>iceman@google.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date/>
    <area>Applications</area>
    <keyword>IMAP attributes</keyword>

    <abstract><t>
      RFC 6154 created an IMAP Special-Use LIST extension and defined an initial set of attributes.        This document defines a new attribute, "\Important", and establishes a new IANA registry for IMAP folder attributes, updating RFCs 3348, 3501, and 6154.
    </t></abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>
        <xref target="RFC6154"/> defines an extension to the Internet Message Access Protocol (IMAP) LIST command <xref target="RFC3501"/> for special-use mailboxes.  The extension allows servers to provide extra information (attributes) about the purpose of a mailbox and defines an initial set of special-use attributes.  There are now three RFCs that define mailbox attributes, and no registry for those attributes.
      </t>
      <t>
        This document defines a new special-use attribute, "\Important", to designate a mailbox that will hold messages that are considered important for the user, by some externally defined criteria.  This document also creates a registry for IMAP mailbox attributes and registers both the new attribute and those defined earlier, updating <xref target="RFC3348"/>, <xref target="RFC3501"/>, and <xref target="RFC6154"/>.
      </t>

      <section title="Conventions used in this document">
        <t>
          In examples, "C:" indicates lines sent by a client that is connected
          to a server.  "S:" indicates lines sent by the server to the client.
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Definition of the 'Important' Attribute">
      <t>
        The "\Important" mailbox attribute is a signal that the mailbox contains messages that are likely important to the user.  For example, the system might automatically put messages there based on available signals (such as who the message is from, who else the message is addressed to, evaluation of the subject or content).  Or it might be a way for users to train the system as to what messages are important (the system can learn patterns from the messages the user copies to that mailbox).
      </t>
      <t>
        <cref>
        Possible change here: Cyrus has suggested (1) removal of the last sentence above, about learning, and (2) definition of an $Important message keyword, and reference to \Important as a virtual mailbox to collect all such messages (as \Flagged does).
        </cref>
      </t>
      <t>
        This is distinct from the "\Flagged" attribute in that evaluation of importance here is based on heuristics, whereas "\Flagged" is typically based on the setting of the IMAP flag of the same name.
      </t>
      <section title="Formal Syntax">
        <t>
          The following syntax specification updates the one in <xref target="RFC6154"/>, Section 6, using Augmented Backus-Naur Form (ABNF) as described in <xref target="RFC5234" />.
          <figure><artwork>
    use-attr      =/  "\Important"
          </artwork></figure>
        </t>
      </section>
      <section title="Example">
        <t>
          In the following example, the mailbox called "Important Messages" is the one designated with the "\Important" attribute.
          <figure><artwork>
    C: t1 list "" "Imp*"
    S: * LIST (\HasNoChildren \Important) "/" "Important Messages"
    S: * LIST (\HasNoChildren) "/" "Imported Wine"
    S: t1 OK Success
          </artwork></figure>
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Security Considerations">
      <t>
        The security considerations in <xref target="RFC6154"/>, Section 7, apply equally to this extension.  In particular, "Conveying special-use information to a client exposes a small bit of extra information that could be of value to an attacker."  Moreover, identifying a place where "important" messages are kept could give an attacker a strategic starting point.  If the algorithm by which messages are determined to be important is well known, still more information is exposed -- perhaps, for example, there is an implication that the senders of these messages are particularly significant to the mailbox owner, and perhaps that is information that should not be made public.
      </t>
      <t>
        As noted in RFC 6154, it is wise to protect the IMAP channel from passive eavesdropping, and to defend against unauthorized discernment of the identity of a user's "\Important" mailbox.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="iana" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>[[RFC Editor: Please replace "THIS RFC" throughout this section with the identification given to this document, and remove this paragraph.]]</t>

      <section title="Creation of the IMAP LIST Special-Use Attributes Registry">
        <t>
          IANA is asked to create a new registry in the group "Internet Message Access Protocol (IMAP) 4 Registries".  The new registry will be called "IMAP Mailbox Name Attributes", and will have two references: RFC 3501, Section 7.2.2, and THIS RFC, <xref target="iana"/>.
        </t>
        <t>
          The registry entries will contain three fields:
        </t>
        <t>
          <list style="numbers">
            <t>Attribute Name</t>
            <t>Description</t>
            <t>Reference</t>
          </list>
        </t>
        <t>
          IANA will keep this list in alphabetical order by Attribute Name, which is registered without the initial backslash ("\").
        </t>
        <t>
          New registrations will be accepted through the Expert Review policy <xref target="RFC5226"/> (and see <xref target="DEinst"/>).  New registrations are requested through the IANA Considerations section in an RFC, or, for requests that do not come from an RFC, by sending email to IANA asking for a new IMAP Mailbox Name Attribute and giving the requested values for each of the three fields.
        </t>
      </section>
      <section title="Initial entries for the registry">
        <t>The registry will initially contain these entries:
        <figure><artwork>
+===============+===================================+===========+
| Attribute     | Description                       | Reference |
| Name          |                                   |           |
+===============+===================================+===========+
| All           | All messages                      | [RFC6154] |
+---------------+-----------------------------------+-----------+
| Archive       | Archived messages                 | [RFC6154] |
+---------------+-----------------------------------+-----------+
| Drafts        | Messages that are working drafts  | [RFC6154] |
+---------------+-----------------------------------+-----------+
| Flagged       | Messages with the \Flagged flag   | [RFC6154] |
+---------------+-----------------------------------+-----------+
| HasChildren   | Has accessible child mailboxes    | [RFC3348] |
+---------------+-----------------------------------+-----------+
| HasNoChildren | Has no accessible child mailboxes | [RFC3348] |
+---------------+-----------------------------------+-----------+
| Important     | Messages deemed important to user | THIS RFC  |
+---------------+-----------------------------------+-----------+
| Junk          | Messages identified as Spam/Junk  | [RFC6154] |
+---------------+-----------------------------------+-----------+
| Marked        | Server has marked the mailbox as  | [RFC3501] |
|               | "interesting"                     |           |
+---------------+-----------------------------------+-----------+
| NoInferiors   | No hierarchy under this name      | [RFC3501] |
+---------------+-----------------------------------+-----------+
| Noselect      | The mailbox is not selectable     | [RFC3501] |
+---------------+-----------------------------------+-----------+
| Sent          | Sent mail                         | [RFC6154] |
+---------------+-----------------------------------+-----------+
| Trash         | Messages the user has discarded   | [RFC6154] |
+---------------+-----------------------------------+-----------+
| Unmarked      | No new messages since last select | [RFC3501] |
+===============+===================================+===========+
        </artwork></figure>
        </t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="DEinst" title="Instructions to the Designated Expert">
        <t>
          The expert reviewer, who will be designated by the IESG, is expected to provide only a general review of the requested registration, checking that the reference and description are adequate for understanding the intent of the registered attribute.  Efforts should also be made to generalize the intent of an attribute so that multiple implementations with the same requirements may reuse existing attributes.  Except for this check, this is intended to be very close to a first come first served policy, and the expert should not block serious registration requests with a reasonable reference.  The reference may be to any form of documentation, including a web page, but consideration should be given to providing one that is expected to be long-lived and stable.
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Changes During Document Development">
      <t><cref>RFC Editor: Please remove this section prior to publication.</cref></t>
      <t>Changes in -01
        <list style="symbols">
        <t>
          Expanded the new registry to all mailbox name attributes, and added the attributes from 3501 and 3348 (suggested by Alexey).  This also adds those two documents to the "updates" list.
        </t>
        <t>
          Recorded Cyrus's suggestion to define $Important.
        </t>
        </list>
      </t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      &RFC3501;
      &RFC5226;
      &RFC5234;
      &RFC6154;
    </references>
    <references title="Informative References">
      &RFC3348;
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
