<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<rfc category="std" docName="draft-psarkar-rtgwg-rlfa-node-protection-02" ipr="trust200902">

  <!-- ***** FRONT MATTER ***** -->

  <front>
    <title>Remote-LFA Node Protection and Manageability</title>

    <!-- add 'role="editor"' below for the editors if appropriate -->

    <author initials="P." surname="Sarkar" fullname="Pushpasis Sarkar" role="editor">
      <organization>Juniper Networks, Inc.</organization>
      <address>
      <postal>
      <street>Electra, Exora Business Park</street>
      <city>Bangalore</city>
      <region>KA</region>
      <code>560103</code>
      <country>India</country>
      </postal>
      <email>psarkar@juniper.net</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Hannes Gredler" initials="H." surname="Gredler">
      <organization>Juniper Networks, Inc.</organization>
      <address>
      <postal>
      <street>1194 N. Mathilda Ave.</street>
      <city>Sunnyvale</city>
      <region>CA</region>
      <code>94089</code>
      <country>US</country>
      </postal>
      <email>hannes@juniper.net</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author initials="S." surname="Hegde" fullname="Shraddha Hegde">
      <organization>Juniper Networks, Inc.</organization>
      <address>
      <postal>
      <street>Electra, Exora Business Park</street>
      <city>Bangalore</city>
      <region>KA</region>
      <code>560103</code>
      <country>India</country>
      </postal>
      <email>shraddha@juniper.net</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author initials="H." surname="Raghuveer" fullname="Harish Raghuveer">
      <organization>Juniper Networks, Inc.</organization>
      <address>
      <postal>
      <street>Electra, Exora Business Park</street>
      <city>Bangalore</city>
      <region>KA</region>
      <code>560103</code>
      <country>India</country>
      </postal>
      <email>hraghuveer@juniper.net</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Chris Bowers" initials="C." surname="Bowers">
      <organization>Juniper Networks, Inc.</organization>
      <address>
      <postal>
      <street>1194 N. Mathilda Ave.</street>
      <city>Sunnyvale</city>
      <region>CA</region>
      <code>94089</code>
      <country>US</country>
      </postal>
      <email>cbowers@juniper.net</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author initials="S" surname="Litkowski" fullname="Stephane Litkowski">
      <organization>Orange</organization>
      <address>
        <!-- postal><street/><city/><region/><code/><country/></postal -->
      <!-- <phone/> -->
      <!-- <facsimile/> -->
      <email>stephane.litkowski@orange.com</email>
      <!-- <uri/> -->
      </address>
    </author>

    <date day="18" month="November" year="2013"/>

    <area>Routing</area>

    <workgroup>Routing Area Working Group</workgroup>

    <keyword>LFA</keyword>
    <keyword>Remote-LFA</keyword>
    <keyword>IGP</keyword>
    <keyword>Node Protection</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>The loop-free alternates computed following the current 
      <xref target="I-D.ietf-rtgwg-remote-lfa">Remote-LFA</xref>
      specification gaurantees only link-protection. The resulting 
      Remote-LFA nexthops (also called PQ-nodes), may not gaurantee 
      node-protection for all destinations being protected by it.</t>

      <t>This document describes procedures for determining if a given 
      PQ-node provides node-protection for a specific destination or 
      not. The document also shows how the same procedure can be utilised 
      for collection of complete characteristics for alternate paths. 
      Knowledge about the characteristics of all alternate path is precursory  
      to apply operator defined policy for eliminating paths not fitting 
      constraints.</t>
    </abstract>

    <note title="Requirements Language">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
      document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
      target="RFC2119">RFC2119</xref>.</t>
    </note>
  </front>

  <middle>
  <section title="Introduction">
    <t>The <xref target="I-D.ietf-rtgwg-remote-lfa">Remote-LFA</xref>
    specification provides loop-free alternates that gaurantees only 
    link-protection. The resulting Remote-LFA alternate nexthops (also
    referred to as the PQ-nodes) may not provide node-protection for
    all destinations covered by the same, in case of failure of the 
    primary nexthop node. Neither does the specification provide a means 
    to determine the same.</t>

    <t>Also, the <xref target="I-D.ietf-rtgwg-lfa-manageability">
    LFA Manageability</xref> document, requires a computing router to 
    find all possible (including all possible Remote-LFA) alternate nexthops, 
    collect the complete set of path characteristics for each alternate path,  
    run a alternate-selection policy (configured by the operator), and find 
    the best alternate path. This will require the Remote-LFA implementation 
    to gather all the required path characteristics along each link on the 
    entire Remote-LFA alternate path.</t>

    <t>With current LFA <xref target="RFC5286"/> and Remote-LFA implementations, 
    the forward SPF (and reverse SPF) is run on the computing router and its 
    immediate 1-hop routers as the roots. While that enables computation of  
    path attributes (e.g. SRLG, Admin-groups) for first alternate path segment 
    from the computing router to the PQ-node, there is no means for the computing 
    router to gather any path attributes for the path segment from the PQ-node to 
    destination. Consecutively any policy-based selection of alternate paths 
    will consider only the path attributes from the computing router up until 
    the PQ-node.</t>

    <t> This document describes a procedure for determining node-protection 
    with Remote-LFA. The same procedure are also extended for collection 
    of complete set of path attributes, enabling more accurate policy-based 
    selection for alternate paths obtained with Remote-LFA.</t>
  </section>

  <section title="Node Protection with Remote-LFA">

    <section title="The Problem">
      <t>To better illustrate the problem and the solution proposed in this 
      document the following topology diagram from the 
      <xref target="I-D.ietf-rtgwg-remote-lfa">Remote-LFA</xref>
      draft is being re-used with slight modification.</t>

      <figure anchor="ring-topology-1" title="Topology 1">
        <artwork>
                                          D1
                                         /
                                    S-x-E
                                   /     \
                                  N       R3--D2
                                   \     /
                                   R1---R2
        </artwork>
      </figure>

      <t>In the above topology, for all (non-ECMP) destinations reachable via 
      the S-E link there is no standard LFA alternate. As per the 
      <xref target="I-D.ietf-rtgwg-remote-lfa">Remote-LFA</xref> alternate 
      specifications node R2 being the only PQ-node for the S-E link provides
      nexthop for all the above destinations. <xref target="table1"/> 
      below, shows all possible primary and Remote-LFA alternate paths for each
      destination.</t>

      <texttable anchor="table1" title="Remote-LFA backup paths via PQ-node R2">
        <ttcol align="left">Destination</ttcol>
        <ttcol align="left">Primary Path</ttcol>
        <ttcol align="left">PQ-node</ttcol>
        <ttcol align="left">Remote-LFA Backup Path</ttcol>
        <c>R3</c>
        <c>S->E->R3</c>
        <c>R2</c>
        <c>S=>N=>R1=>R2->R3</c>
        <c>E</c>
        <c>S->E</c>
        <c>R2</c>
        <c>S=>N=>R1=>R2->R3->E</c>
        <c>D1</c>
        <c>S->E->D1</c>
        <c>R2</c>
        <c>S=>N=>R1=>R2->R3->E->D1</c>
        <c>D2</c>
        <c>S->E->R3->D2</c>
        <c>R2</c>
        <c>S=>N=>R1=>R2->R3->D2</c>
      </texttable>

      <t>A closer look at <xref target="table1"/> shows that, while the 
      PQ-node R2 provides link-protection for all the destinations, it does
      not provide node-protection for destinations E and F. In the event of
      the node-failure on primary nexthop E, the alternate path from Remote-LFA
      nexthop R2 to E and D1 also becomes unavailable. So for a Remote-LFA
      nexthop to provide node-protection for a given destination, it is
      mandatory that, the shortest path from the given PQ-node to the given
      destination MUST not traverse the primary nexthop. </t>

      <t> In another extension of the topology in <xref target="ring-topology-1"/>
      let us consider an additional link between N and E.</t>

      <figure anchor="ring-topology-2" title="Topology 2">
	<artwork>
                                          D1
                                         /
                                    S-x-E
                                   /   / \
                                  N---+   R3--D2
                                   \     /
                                   R1---R2
	</artwork>
      </figure>

      <t> In the above topology, the S-E link is no more on any of the 
      shortest paths from N to R3. Hence R3 is also included in both the 
      Extended-P space and PQ space of E (w.r.t S-E link). 
      <xref target="table2"/> below, shows all possible primary and R-LFA 
      alternate paths via PQ-node R3, for each destination reachable 
      through the S-E link in the above topology. The R-LFA alternate 
      paths via PQ-node R2 remains same as in <xref target="table1"/>.</t>

      <texttable anchor="table2" title="Remote-LFA backup paths via PQ-node R3">
        <ttcol align="left">Destination</ttcol>
        <ttcol align="left">Primary Path</ttcol>
        <ttcol align="left">PQ-node</ttcol>
        <ttcol align="left">Remote-LFA Backup Path</ttcol>
        <c>R3</c>
        <c>S->E->R3</c>
        <c>R3</c>
        <c>S=>N=>E=>R3</c>
        <c>E</c>
        <c>S->E</c>
        <c>R3</c>
        <c>S=>N=>E=>R3->E</c>
        <c>D1</c>
        <c>S->E->D1</c>
        <c>R3</c>
        <c>S=>N=>E=>R3->E->D1</c>
        <c>D2</c>
        <c>S->E->D1</c>
        <c>R3</c>
        <c>S=>N=>E=>R3->D2</c>
      </texttable>

      <t>Again a closer look at <xref target="table2"/> shows that, unlike 
      <xref target="table1"/>, where the single PQ-node R2 provided node-protection, 
      for destinations R3 and G, if we choose R3 as the R-LFA nexthop, it does not 
      provide node-protection for R3 and D1 anymore. If S chooses R3 as the R-LFA 
      nexthop, in the event of the node-failure on primary nexthop E, the alternate 
      path from S to R-LFA nexthop R3 also becomes unavailable. So for a Remote-LFA 
      nexthop to provide node-protection for a given destination, it is also mandatory 
      that, the shortest path from S to the chosen PQ-node MUST not traverse the 
      primary nexthop node.</t>

    </section>

    <section title="Few Additional Definitions">

      <t> This document adds and enhances the following definitions extending 
      the ones  mentioned in <xref target="I-D.ietf-rtgwg-remote-lfa">Remote-LFA
      </xref> draft.</t>

      <section title="Link-Protecting Extended P-Space">
        <t> The <xref target="I-D.ietf-rtgwg-remote-lfa">Remote-LFA</xref> draft 
	already defines this. The link-protecting extended P-space for a link S-E 
	being protected is the set of routers that are reachable from one or more 
        direct neighbors of S, except primary node E, without traversing the S-E  
        link on any of the shortest path from the direct neighbor to the router. 
        This MUST exclude any direct neighbor for which there is atleast one ECMP 
        path from the direct neighbor traversing the link(S-E) being protected.</t>

        <t> A node Y is in link-protecting extended P-space w.r.t to the link
        (S-E) being protected, if and only if, there exists atleast one direct 
	neighbor of S, Ni, other than primary nexthop E, that satisfies the 
        following condition.</t> 

        <figure anchor="lp-extp-cond" title="Link-Protecting Ext-P-Space Condition">
          <artwork>
D_opt(Ni,Y) &lt; D_opt(Ni,S) + D_opt(S,E) + D_opt(E,Y)

Where, 
  D_opt(A,B) : Distance on most optimum path from A to B.
          E  : The primary nexthop on shortest path from S 
               to destination.
         Ni  : A direct neighbor of S other than primary 
               nexthop E.
          Y  : The node being evaluated for link-protecting 
               extended P-Space.

	  </artwork>
        </figure>

      </section>

      <section anchor="np-extp-space" title="Node-Protecting Extended P-Space">

        <t> The node-protecting extended P-space for a primary nexthop node E being 
	protected, is the set of routers that are reachable from one or more direct 
        neighbors of S, except primary node E, without traversing the node E. This 
        MUST exclude any direct neighbors for which there is atleast one ECMP path 
        from the direct neighbor traversing the node E being protected.</t>

        <t> A node Y is in node-protecting extended P-space w.r.t to the node 
        E being protected, if and only if, there exists atleast one direct neighbor 
	of S, Ni, other than primary nexthop E, that satisfies the following 
        condition.</t>

        <figure anchor="np-extp-cond" title="Node-Protecting Ext-P-Space Condition">
          <artwork>

D_opt(Ni,Y) &lt; D_opt(Ni,E) + D_opt(E,Y)

Where, 
  D_opt(A,B) : Distance on most optimum path from R1 to B.
          E  : The primary nexthop on shortest path from S 
               to destination.
          Ni : A direct neighbor of S other than primary 
               nexthop E.
           Y : The node being evaluated for node-protecting 
               extended P-Space.

	  </artwork>
        </figure>

        <t> It must be noted that a node Y satisfying the condition in 
        <xref target="np-extp-cond"/> above only guarantees that the R-LFA alternate 
        path segment from S via direct neighbor Ni to the PQ-node Y is not affected 
	in the event of a node failure of E. It does not yet guarantee that the path 
        segment from PQ-node Y to the destination is also unaffected by the same 
	failure event.</t>

      </section>

      <section title="Q-Space">
        <t> The <xref target="I-D.ietf-rtgwg-remote-lfa">Remote-LFA</xref> draft 
	already defines this. The Q-space for a link S-E being protected is the 
	set of routers that can reach primary node E, without traversing the S-E  
        link on any of the shortest path from the node Y to primary nexthop E. 
        This MUST exclude any destination for which there is atleast one ECMP 
        path from the node Y to the primary nexthop E traversing the link(S-E) 
        being protected.</t>

        <t> A node Y is in Q-space w.r.t to the link (S-E) being protected, 
        if and only if, the following condition is satisfied.</t> 

        <figure anchor="q-cond" title="Q-Space Condition">
          <artwork>
D_opt(Y,E) &lt; D_opt(S,E) + D_opt(Y,S)

Where, 
  D_opt(A,B) : Distance on most optimum path from R1 to B.
          E  : The primary nexthop on shortest path from S 
               to destination.
          Y  : The node being evaluated for Q-Space.

	  </artwork>
        </figure>

      </section>

      <section title="Link-Protecting PQ Space">

        <t> A node Y is in link-protecting PQ space w.r.t to the link (S-E) being 
        protected, if and only if, Y is present in both link-protecting extended 
        P-space and the Q-space for the link being protected.</t> 

      </section>

      <section title="Candidate Node-Protecting PQ Space">
        <t> A node Y is in candidate node-protecting PQ space w.r.t to the node (E) 
        being protected, if and only if, Y is present in both node-protecting extended 
        P-space and the Q-space for the link being protected.</t> 

        <t> Again it must be noted that a node Y being in candidate node-protecting 
        PQ-space does not guarantee that the R-LFA alternate path via the same, in 
	entirety, is unaffected in the event of a node failure of primary nexthop node 
	E. It only guarantees that the path segment from S to PQ-node Y is unaffected 
        by the same failure event. The PQ-nodes in the candidate node-protecting 
        PQ space may provide node protection for only a subset of destinations 
        that are reachable through the corresponding primary link.</t>
      </section>

    </section>

    <section anchor="node-protecting-rlfa" 
     title="Computing Node-protecting R-LFA Path">
      <t> The R-LFA alternate path through a given PQ-node to a given
      destination comprises of two path segments as follows.</t>

      <t><list style='numbers'>
	<t>Path segment from the computing router to the
	PQ-node (Remote-LFA alternate nexthop), and</t>
	<t>Path segment from the PQ-node to the destination
	being protected. </t>
      </list></t>

      <t> So to ensure a R-LFA alternate path for a given destination provides 
      node-protection we need to ensure that none of the above path segments are 
      unaffected in the event of failure of the primary nexthop node. Sections 
      <xref target="plr-to-pq"/> and <xref target="pqnode-to-dest"/> shows 
      how this can be ensured.</t>

      <section anchor="plr-to-pq" 
       title="Computing Candidate Node-protecting PQ-Nodes for Primary nexthops">

        <t> To choose a node-protecting R-LFA nexthop for a destination R3, router S  
	needs to consider a PQ-node from the candidate node-protecting PQ-space for 
        the primary nexthop E on shortest path from S to R3. As mentioned in 
        <xref target="np-extp-space"/>, to consider a PQ-node as candidate node-protecting 
        PQ-node, there must be atleast one direct neighbor Ni of S, such that all 
        shortest paths from Ni to the PQ-node does not traverse primary nexthop 
        node E.</t>

        <t> Implementations should run the inequality in <xref target="np-extp-space"/> 
        <xref target="np-extp-cond"/> for all direct neighbor, other than primary nexthop 
        node E, to determine whether a PQ-node Y is also a candidate node-protecting PQ-node. 
        All of the metrics needed by this inequality would have been already collected 
        from the forward SPFs rooted at each of direct neighbor S, computed as part of 
        standard LFA <xref target="RFC5286"/> implementation. With reference to the 
        topology in <xref target="ring-topology-2"/>, <xref target="table3"/> below 
        shows how the above condition can be used to determine the candidate node-protecting 
        PQ-space for S-E link (primary nexthop E)</t>

        <texttable anchor="table3" 
         title="Node-protection evaluation for R-LFA repair tunnel to PQ-node">
        <ttcol align="center">PQ-node (Y)</ttcol>
        <ttcol align="center">Direct Nbr (Ni)</ttcol>
        <ttcol align="center">D_opt (Ni,Y)</ttcol>
        <ttcol align="center">D_opt (Ni,E)</ttcol>
        <ttcol align="center">D_opt (E,Y)</ttcol>
        <ttcol align="center">Condition Met</ttcol>
        <c>R2</c>
        <c>N</c>
        <c>2 (N,R2)</c>
        <c>1 (N,E)</c>
        <c>2 (E,R2)</c>
        <c>Yes</c>
        <c>R3</c>
        <c>N</c>
        <c>2 (N,R3)</c>
        <c>1 (N,E)</c>
        <c>1 (E,R3)</c>
        <c>No</c>
        </texttable>

        <t>As seen in the above <xref target="table3"/> , R3 does not meet the 
        node-protecting extended-p-space inequality And so, while R2 is in candidate 
        node-protecting PQ space, R3 is not.</t>

        <t>Some SPF implementations may also produce a list of links and nodes traversed 
        on the shortest path(s) from a given root to others. In such implementations, 
        router S may have executed a forward SPF with each of it's direct neighbors as 
        the SPF root, executed as  part of the standard LFA <xref target="RFC5286"/> 
        computations. So S may re-use the list of links and nodes collected from the same 
        SPF computations, to decide whether a PQ-node Y is a candidate node-protecting PQ-node or 
        not. A PQ-node Y shall be considered as a node-protecting, if and only if, 
        there is atleast one direct neighbor of S, other than the primary nexthop 
        E, for which, the primary nexthop node E does not exist on the list of nodes 
        traversed on any of the shortest path(s) from the direct neighbor to the 
        PQ-node. <xref target="table4"/> below is an illustration of the mechanism with 
        the topology in <xref target="ring-topology-2"/>.</t>

        <texttable anchor="table4" title="Protection of Remote-LFA tunnel to the PQ-node">
          <ttcol align="left">PQ-node</ttcol>
          <ttcol align="left">Repair Tunnel Path(Repairing router to PQ-node)</ttcol>
          <ttcol align="left">Link-Protection</ttcol>
          <ttcol align="left">Node-Protection</ttcol>
          <c>R2</c>
          <c>S->N->R1->R2</c>
          <c>Yes</c>
          <c>Yes</c>
          <c>R2</c>
          <c>S->E->R3->R2</c>
          <c>No</c>
          <c>No</c>
          <c>R3</c>
          <c>S->N->E->R3</c>
          <c>Yes</c>
          <c>No</c>
        </texttable>

        <t>As seen in the above <xref target="table4"/> while R2 is candidate node-protecting
        Remote-LFA nexthop for R3 and G, it is not so for E and F, since the
        primary nexthop E is in the shortest path from R2 to E and F.</t>

      </section>

      <section anchor="pqnode-to-dest" 
       title="Computing node-protecting paths from PQ-nodes to destinations">

        <t> Once a computing router finds all the candidate node-protecting PQ-nodes for a 
        given directly attached primary link, it shall follow the procedure in proposed 
        in this section, to choose one or more node-protecting R-LFA paths, for 
        destinations reachable through the same primary link in the primary SPF graph.</t>

        <t> To find a node-protecting R-LFA path for a given destination, the computing 
        router needs to pick a subset of PQ-nodes from the candidate node-protecting PQ-space for 
        the corresponding primary nexthop, such that all the path(s) from the PQ-node(s) 
        to the given destination remain unaffected in the event of a node failure of 
        primary nexthop node. To ensure this, the computing router will need to ensure 
        that, the primary nexthop node should not be on any of the shortest paths 
        from the PQ-node to the given destination.</t>  


        <t> This document proposes an additional forward SPF computation for each of 
        the PQ-nodes, to discover all shortest paths from the PQ-nodes to the destination. 
        The additional forward SPF computation for each PQ-node, shall help determine, 
        if a given primary nexthop node is on the shortest paths from the PQ-node to 
        the given destination or not. To determine if a given PQ-node provides 
        node-protecting alternate for a given destination, the primary nexthop node 
        should not be on any of the shortest paths from the PQ-node to the given 
        destination. After running the forward SPF on a PQ-node (from the node-protecting 
        PQ-space) the computing router shall run the inequality in 
        <xref target="node-prot-ineq-2"/> below. PQ-nodes that does not qualify the 
        condition for a given destination, does not gaurantee node-protection for 
        the path segment from the PQ-node to the given destination.</t>

        <figure anchor="node-prot-ineq-2" 
         title="Node-Protecting Condition for PQ-node to Destination">
          <artwork>
D_opt(Y,D) &lt; D_opt(Y,E) + Distance_opt(E,D)

Where, 
  D_opt(A,B) : Distance on most optimum path from R1 to B.
          D  : The destination node.
          E  : The primary nexthop on shortest path from S 
               to destination.
          Y  : The node-protecting PQ-node being evaluated 
          </artwork>
        </figure>

        <t>All of the above metric costs except D_opt(Y, D), can be obtained with 
        forward and reverse SPFs with E(the primary nexthop) as the root, run as 
        part of the regular LFA and Remote-LFA implementation. The Distance_opt(Y, D) 
        metric can only be determined by the additional forward SPF run with PQ-node 
        Y as the root. With reference to the topology in <xref target="ring-topology-2"/>, 
        <xref target="table5"/> below shows how the above condition can be used 
        to determine node-protection with node-protecting PQ-node R2.</t>

        <texttable anchor="table5" 
         title="Node-protection evaluation for R-LFA path segment between PQ-node 
         and destination">
          <ttcol align="center">Destination (D)</ttcol>
          <ttcol align="center">Primary-NH (E)</ttcol>
          <ttcol align="center">D_opt (Y, D)</ttcol>
          <ttcol align="center">D_opt (Y, E)</ttcol>
          <ttcol align="center">D_opt (E, D)</ttcol>
          <ttcol align="center">Condition Met</ttcol>
          <c>R3</c>
          <c>E</c>
          <c>1 (C,D)</c>
          <c>2 (C,E)</c>
          <c>1 (E,D)</c>
          <c>Yes</c>
          <c>E</c>
          <c>E</c>
          <c>2 (C,E)</c>
          <c>2 (C,E)</c>
          <c>0 (E,E)</c>
          <c>No</c>
          <c>D1</c>
          <c>E</c>
          <c>3 (C,F)</c>
          <c>2 (C,E)</c>
          <c>1 (E,F)</c>
          <c>No</c>
          <c>D2</c>
          <c>E</c>
          <c>2 (C,G)</c>
          <c>2 (C,E)</c>
          <c>1 (E,G)</c>
          <c>Yes</c>
        </texttable>

        <t>As seen in the above example above, R2 does not meet the node-
        protecting inequality for destination E, and F. And so, once again, 
        while R2 is a node-protecting Remote-LFA nexthop for R3 and G, 
        it is not so for E and F.</t>

        <t>In SPF implementations that also produce a list of links and nodes 
        traversed on the shortest path(s) from a given root to others, 
        to determine whether a PQ-node provides node-protection for a given 
        destination or not, the list of nodes computed from forward SPF run 
        on the PQ-node, for the given destination, should be inspected. In case 
        the list contains the primary nexthop node, the PQ-node does not 
        provide node-protection. Else, the PQ-node guarantees node-protecting 
        alternate for the given destination. Below is an illustration of the 
        mechanism with candidate node-protecting PQ-node R2 in the topology in 
        <xref target="ring-topology-2"/>.</t>

        <texttable anchor="table6" 
          title="Protection of Remote-LFA path between PQ-node and destination">
          <ttcol align="left">Destination</ttcol>
          <ttcol align="left">Shortest Path (Repairing router to PQ-node)</ttcol>
          <ttcol align="left">Link-Protection</ttcol>
          <ttcol align="left">Node-Protection</ttcol>
          <c>R3</c>
          <c>R2->R3</c>
          <c>Yes</c>
          <c>Yes</c>
          <c>E</c>
          <c>R2->R3->E</c>
          <c>Yes</c>
          <c>No</c>
          <c>D1</c>
          <c>R2->R3->E->D1</c>
          <c>Yes</c>
          <c>No</c>
          <c>D2</c>
          <c>R2->R3->D2</c>
          <c>Yes</c>
          <c>Yes</c>
        </texttable>

        <t>As seen in the above example while R2 is candidate node-protecting
        R-LFA nexthop for R3 and G, it is not so for E and F, since the
        primary nexthop E is in the shortest path from R2 to E and F.</t>

        <t>The procedure described in this document helps no more than to  
        determine whether a given Remote-LFA alternate provides node-protection 
        for a given destination or not. It does not find out any new Remote-LFA 
        alternate nexthops, outside the ones already computed by standard 
        Remote-LFA procedure. However, in case of availability of more than one 
        PQ-node (Remote-LFA alternates) for a destination, and node-protection 
        is required for the given primary nexthop, this procedure will eliminate 
        the PQ-nodes that do not provide node-protection and choose only the ones  
        that does.</t> 

      </section>

      <section title="Limiting extra computational overhead">

        <t> In addition to the extra reverse SPF computation, one per directly 
        connected neighbor, suggested by the <xref target="I-D.ietf-rtgwg-remote-lfa">
        Remote-LFA</xref> draft, this document proposes a forward SPF per PQ-node 
        discovered in the network. Since the average number of PQ-nodes found in  
        any network is considerably more than the number of direct neighbors of the 
        computing router, the proposal of running one forward SPF per PQ-node may 
	add considerably to the overall SPF computation time.</t>

        <t> To limit the computational overhead of the approach proposed, this 
        document proposes that implementations MUST choose a subset from the entire 
        set of PQ-nodes computed in the network, with a finite limit on the number 
        of PQ-nodes in the subset. Implementations MUST choose a default value 
        for this limit and may provide user with a configuration knob to override 
        the default limit. Implementations MUST also evaluate some default 
        preference criteria while considering a PQ-node in this subset. Finally, 
        implementations MAY also allow user to override the default preference 
        criteria, by providing a policy configuration for the same.</t> 

        <t> A suggested default criteria for PQ-node selection will be to put a score 
        on each PQ-node, proportional to the number of primary interfaces and remote 
        destination routers being protected by it, and then pick PQ-nodes based on 
        this score. A more appropriate heuristsics can be devised, based on 
        in-depth study of coverage provided by R-LFA, in the networks where they 
        are mostly deployed. The same can then be used for PQ-node selection.</t>

        <t> Once a subset of PQ-nodes is found, computing router shall run a forward 
        SPF on each of the PQ-nodes in the subset to continue with procedures proposed 
        in section <xref target="pqnode-to-dest"/>.</t>

      </section>

    </section>

  </section>

  <section title="Manageabilty of Remote-LFA Alternate Paths">
    <section title="The Problem">
      <t>With the regular <xref target="I-D.ietf-rtgwg-remote-lfa">Remote-LFA</xref> 
      functionality the computing router may compute more than one PQ-node
      as usable Remote-LFA alternate nexthops. Additionally an alternate selection
      policy may be configured to enable the network operator to choose one
      of them as the most appropriate Remote-LFA alternate. For such policy-based 
      alternate selection to run, all the relevant path characteristics for each 
      the alternate paths (one through each of the PQ-nodes), needs to be
      collected. As mentioned befor in section <xref target="node-protecting-rlfa"/> 
      the R-LFA alternate path through a given PQ-node to a given destination 
      comprises of two path segments.</t>

      <t>The first path segment (i.e. from the computing router to the PQ-node) 
      can be calculated from the regular forward SPF done as part of standard and 
      remote LFA computations. However without the mechanism proposed in section 
      <xref target="pqnode-to-dest"/> of this document, there is no way to 
      determine the path characteristics for the second path segment (i.e from the
      PQ-node to the destination). In the absence of the path characteristics for the 
      second path segment, two Remote-LFA alternate path may be equally preferred 
      based on the first path segments characteristics only, although the 
      second path segment attributes may be different.</t>

    </section>

    <section title="The Solution">
      <t>The additional forward SPF computation proposed in section 
      <xref target="pqnode-to-dest"/> document shall also collect links, nodes and 
      path characteristics along the second path segment. This shall enable collection 
      of complete path characteristics for a given Remote-LFA alternate path to a 
      given destination. The complete alternate path characteristics shall then 
      facilitate more accurate alternate path selection while running the alternate 
      selection policy.</t>

    </section>
  </section>

  <section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">
    <t>Many thanks to Bruno Decraene for his useful comments.</t>
  </section>

  <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
    <t>N/A. - No protocol changes are proposed in this document.</t>
  </section>

  <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
    <t>This document does not introduce any change in any of the
    protocol specifications. It simply proposes to run an extra SPF rooted
    on each PQ-node discovered in the whole network.</t>
  </section>
  </middle>

  <!-- *****BACK MATTER ***** -->

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"?>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5286.xml"?>
      <?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.draft-ietf-rtgwg-remote-lfa-02.xml"?>
      <?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.draft-ietf-rtgwg-lfa-manageability-00.xml"?>
      <?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.draft-litkowski-rtgwg-node-protect-remote-lfa-00.xml"?>
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
