<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY rfc3986 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3986.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc4301 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4301.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc3261 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3261.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc3264 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3264.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc3325 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3325.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc3428 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3428.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc3515 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3515.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc3693 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3693.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc3550 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3550.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc3551 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3551.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc3711 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3711.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc3825 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3825.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc3840 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3840.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc3841 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3841.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc3856 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3856.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc3966 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3966.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc4119 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4119.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc4033 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4033.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc4103 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4103.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc4190 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4190.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc4474 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4474.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc4504 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4504.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc4568 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4568.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc5077 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5077.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc4776 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4776.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc4967 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4967.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc4975 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4975.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc5012 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5012.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc5031 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5031.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc5069 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5069.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc5139 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5139.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc5222 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5222.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc5223 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5223.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc5359 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5359.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc5491 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5491.xml">
<!ENTITY draft-ietf-sipping-config-framework SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-sipping-config-framework.xml">
<!ENTITY draft-ietf-sip-gruu SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-sip-gruu.xml">
<!ENTITY draft-ietf-sip-outbound SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-sip-outbound.xml">
<!ENTITY draft-ietf-sip-sips SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-sip-sips.xml">
<!ENTITY draft-ietf-sip-location-conveyance SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-sip-location-conveyance.xml">
<!ENTITY draft-ietf-ecrit-phonebcp SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-ecrit-phonebcp.xml">
<!ENTITY draft-ietf-geopriv-http-location-delivery SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-geopriv-http-location-delivery.xml">
<!ENTITY draft-barnes-geopriv-lo-sec SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.barnes-geopriv-lo-sec.xml">
<!ENTITY draft-ietf-geopriv-lis-discovery SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-geopriv-lis-discovery.xml">
]>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc iprnotified="no" ?>
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<rfc category="info" ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="Emergency Call Framework">Framework for Emergency Calling
    using Internet Multimedia</title>

    <author fullname="Brian Rosen" initials="B.R." surname="Rosen">
      <organization abbrev="NeuStar">NeuStar, Inc.</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>470 Conrad Dr</street>

          <city>Mars</city>

          <region>PA</region>

          <code>16046</code>

          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>

        <email>br@brianrosen.net</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Henning Schulzrinne" initials="H.S."
            surname="Schulzrinne">
      <organization abbrev="Columbia U.">Columbia University</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Department of Computer Science</street>

          <street>450 Computer Science Building</street>

          <city>New York</city>

          <region>NY</region>

          <code>10027</code>

          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>

        <phone>+1 212 939 7042</phone>

        <email>hgs@cs.columbia.edu</email>

        <uri>http://www.cs.columbia.edu</uri>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="James Polk" initials="J.P" surname="Polk">
      <organization>Cisco Systems</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>3913 Treemont Circle</street>

          <city>Colleyville</city>

          <region>Texas</region>

          <code>76034</code>

          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>

        <phone>+1-817-271-3552</phone>

        <email>jmpolk@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Andrew Newton" initials="A.N." surname="Newton">
      <organization>TranTech/MediaSolv</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>4900 Seminary Road</street>

          <city>Alexandria</city>

          <region>VA</region>

          <code>22311</code>

          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>

        <phone>+1 703 845 0656</phone>

        <email>andy@hxr.us</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date year="2010" />

    <area>rai</area>

    <workgroup>ecrit</workgroup>
<abstract>
<t>The IETF has standardized various aspects of placing emergency calls. 
This document describes how all of those component parts are used to support emergency calls from citizens 
and visitors to authorities.</t>
</abstract></front><middle>
<section title="Terminology">
<t>This document uses terms from <xref target="RFC3261"></xref>, <xref target="RFC5222"/> and <xref target="RFC5012"></xref>.  
In addition the following terms are used:
<list style="hanging">
<t hangText="Access network:">
The access network supplies IP packet service to an endpoint. Examples of access networks include digital subscriber lines (DSL), cable modems, IEEE 802.11, WiMaX, enterprise local area networks and cellular data networks.</t>

<t hangText="Confidence:">
Confidence is an estimate indicating how sure the measuring system is that the actual location of the endpoint is within the bounds defined by the uncertainty value, expressed as a percentage. For example, a value of 90% indicates that the actual location is within the uncertainty nine times out of ten.</t>

<t hangText="Dispatch Location:">The dispatch location is the location used for dispatching 
responders to the person in need of assistance.  
The dispatch location must be sufficiently precise to easily locate the caller; 
it typically needs to be more accurate than the routing location.</t>

<t hangText="Location configuration:">
During location configuration, an endpoint learns its physical location.</t>

<t hangText="Location Configuration Protocol (LCP):">
A protocol used by an endpoint to learn its location.</t>

<t hangText="Location conveyance:">
Location conveyance delivers location information to another element.</t>

<t hangText="Location determination:">
Location determination finds where an endpoint is physically located.  
For example, the endpoint may contain a Global Navigation Satellite System (GNSS) receiver used to measure its own 
location or the location may be determined by a network administrator using a wiremap database.</t>

<t hangText="Location Information Server (LIS):"> A Location Information Server stores location information for retrieval by an authorized entity.</t>

<t hangText="Mobile device:">
A mobile device is a user agent that may change its physical location and 
possibly its network attachment point during an emergency call.</t>

<t hangText="NENA (National Emergency Number Association):"> The National Emergency 
Number Association is an organization of professionals to "foster the technological 
advancement, availability and implementation of a universal emergency telephone number system in North America."  
It develops emergency calling specifications and procedures.</t>

<t hangText="Nomadic device (user):">
A nomadic user agent is connected to the network temporarily, for relatively short durations,
but does not move significantly during the during the 
emergency call.
Examples include a laptop using an IEEE 802.11 hotspot or a desk IP phone that is moved 
occasionally from one cubicle to another.</t>

<t hangText="Physical location:">
A physical location describes where a person or device is located in physical space, 
described by a coordinate system. It is distinguished from the network location, 
described by a network address.
</t>
<t hangText="PSAP:">
Public Safety Answering Point, the call center that answers emergency calls.</t>
<t hangText="Routing Location:">
The routing location of a device is used for routing an emergency call and may 
not be as precise as the Dispatch Location.</t>

<t hangText="Stationary device:">
An stationary device is not mobile and is connected to the network at a fixed, 
long-term-stable physical location. Examples include home PCs or pay phones.</t>

<t hangText="Uncertainty:">
Uncertainty is an estimate, expressed in a unit of length, indicating the diameter 
of a circle that contains the endpoint with the probability indicated by the confidence 
value.</t>
</list></t>
</section><section title="Introduction">
<t>Requesting help in an emergency using a communications device such as a telephone or mobile phone
is an accepted practice in many parts of the world. As communications devices increasingly utilize 
the Internet to interconnect and communicate, users will expect to use such devices 
to request help. This document describes 
establishment of a communications session by a user to a "Public Safety Answering Point" (PSAP), 
that is, a call center established by response agencies to accept emergency calls. 
Such citizen/visitor-to-authority calls can be distinguished from those that are created by 
responders (authority-to-authority) using public communications infrastructure often involving 
some kind of priority access as defined in Emergency Telecommunications Service (ETS) in IP 
Telephony <xref target="RFC4190"></xref>. They also can be distinguished from emergency warning 
systems that are authority-to-citizen.</t>
<t>Supporting emergency calling requires cooperation by a number of elements, their vendors and 
service providers. This document discusses how end device and applications create emergency calls, how access 
networks supply location for some of these devices, how service providers assist the establishment 
and routing, and how PSAPs receive calls from the Internet.</t>
<t>The emergency response community will have to upgrade their facilities to support a wider 
range of communications services, but cannot be expected to handle wide variations in device and 
service capability. New devices and services are being made available that could be used to 
make a request for help that are not traditional telephones, and users are increasingly expecting 
to use them to place emergency calls. However, many of the technical advantages of Internet 
multimedia require re-thinking of the traditional emergency calling architecture. This challenge 
also offers an opportunity to improve the operation of emergency calling technology, while potentially 
lowering its cost and complexity.</t> 
<t>It is beyond the scope of this document to enumerate and discuss all the differences between 
traditional (Public Switched Telephone Network) and IP-based telephony, but calling on the Internet 
is characterized by:
<list style="symbols">
<t>the interleaving over the same infrastructure of a wider variety of services; </t> 
<t>the separation of the access provider from the application provider; </t> 
<t>media other than voice (for example, video and text in several forms); </t> 
<t>the potential mobility of all end systems, including endpoints nominally thought of as fixed systems 
and not just those using radio access technology. For example, consider a wired phone connected to a router 
using a mobile data network such as EV-DO as an uplink.</t> 
</list></t>
<t>This document focuses on how devices using the Internet can place emergency calls and how PSAPs 
can handle Internet multimedia emergency calls natively, rather than describing how circuit-switched 
PSAPs can handle VoIP calls. In many cases, PSAPs making the transition from circuit-switched 
interfaces to packet-switched interfaces may be able to use some of the mechanisms described here, 
in combination with gateways that translate packet-switched calls into legacy interfaces, e.g., 
to continue to be able to use existing call taker equipment. There are many legacy telephone 
networks that will persist long after most systems have been upgraded to IP origination and 
termination of emergency calls. Many of these legacy systems route calls based on telephone numbers. 
Gateways and conversions between existing systems and newer systems defined by this document will be 
required. Since existing systems are governed primarily by local government regulations and national 
standards, the gateway and conversion details will be governed by national standards and thus are 
out of scope for this document.</t>
<t>Existing emergency call systems are organized locally or nationally; there are currently no international 
standards. However, the Internet crosses national boundaries, and thus international standards for 
equipment and software are required. To further complicate matters, VoIP endpoints can be connected 
through tunneling mechanisms such as virtual private networks (VPNs). Tunnels can obscure the identity 
of the actual access network that knows the location. This significantly complicates emergency calling, 
because the location of the caller and the first element that routes emergency calls can be on different 
continents, with different conventions and processes for handling of emergency calls.</t> 
<t>The IETF has historically refused to create national variants of its standards. Thus, this document 
attempts to take into account best practices that have evolved for circuit switched PSAPs, but makes no 
assumptions on particular operating practices currently in use, numbering schemes or organizational 
structures.</t> 
<t>This document discusses the use of the Session Initiation Protocol (SIP) <xref target="RFC3261"></xref> 
by PSAPs and calling parties. While other inter-domain call signaling protocols may be used for emergency 
calling, SIP is ubiquitous and possesses the proper support of this use case. Only protocols such as 
H.323, XMPP/Jingle, ISUP and SIP are suitable for inter-domain communications, ruling out Media Gateway
Controller protocols 
such as MGCP or H.248/Megaco. The latter protocols can be used by the enterprise or carrier 
placing the call, but any such call would reach the PSAP through a media gateway controller, similar to 
how inter-domain VoIP calls would be placed. Other signaling protocols may also use protocol translation 
to communicate with a SIP-enabled PSAP.</t> 
<t>Existing emergency services rely exclusively on voice and conventional text telephony ("TTY") media 
streams. However, more choices of media offer additional ways to communicate and evaluate the situation 
as well as to assist callers and call takers in handling emergency calls. For example, instant messaging 
and video could improve the ability to communicate and evaluate the situation and to provide appropriate 
instruction prior to arrival of emergency crews. Thus, the architecture described here supports the 
creation of sessions of any media type, negotiated between the caller and PSAP using existing SIP protocol 
mechanisms <xref target="RFC3264"></xref>.</t> 
<t>This document focuses on the case in which all three steps in the 
emergency calling process -- location configuration, call routing, and 
call placement - can be and are performed by the calling endpoint, 
with the endpoint's Access Service Provider supporting the process by 
providing location information.  Calls in this case may be routed 
via an application-layer Communications Service Provider (e.g., a 
Voice Service Provider), but need not be.  The underlying protocols 
can also be used to support other models in which parts of the process 
are delegated to the Communications Service Provider.  This document 
does not address in detail either these models or interoperability 
issues between them and the model described here.</t>
<t>Since this document is a framework document, it does not include normative behavior.  A companion document, <xref 
target="I-D.ietf-ecrit-phonebcp"></xref>, describes Best Current Practice for this subject and contains normative 
language for devices, access and calling network elements.</t>  
<t>Supporting emergency calling does not require any specialized SIP header fields, request methods, 
status codes, message bodies, or event packages, but does require that existing mechanisms be used in 
certain specific ways, as described below. User Agents (UAs) unaware of the recommendations in this draft may 
be able to place emergency calls, but functionality may be impaired. For example, if the UA does not 
implement the location mechanisms described, an emergency call may not be routed to the correct PSAP, 
and if the caller is unable to supply his exact location, dispatch of emergency responders may be delayed. 
Suggested behavior for both endpoints and servers is provided.</t> 
<t>From the point of view of the PSAP, three essential elements characterize an emergency call:
<list style="symbols">
<t>The call is routed to the most appropriate PSAP, based primarily on the location of the 
caller.</t>
<t>The PSAP must be able to automatically obtain the location of the caller with sufficient accuracy to 
dispatch a responder to help the caller.</t>
<t>The PSAP must be able to re-establish a session to the caller if for any reason the original session 
is disrupted.</t> 
</list></t>
</section><section title="Overview of how emergency calls are placed">
<t>An emergency call can be distinguished (<xref target="Identifying"></xref>) from any other call 
by a unique Service URN <xref target="RFC5031"></xref> that is placed in the call 
set-up signaling when a home or visited emergency dial string is detected. Because emergency services 
are local to specific geographic regions, a caller must obtain his
location (<xref target="Location"></xref>) prior to making emergency calls. To get this location, either a form of 
measuring, for example, GNSS (<xref target="EndSystemMeasuredLocation"></xref>) is deployed, or
the endpoint is configured (<xref target="LocationConfiguration"></xref>) 
with its location from the access network's Location Information Server (LIS) using a Location Configuration Protocol (LCP). The location is conveyed 
(<xref target="Conveyance"></xref>) in the SIP signaling with the call. The call is routed 
(<xref target="Routing"></xref>) based on location using the LoST protocol 
<xref target="RFC5222"></xref>, which maps a location to a set of PSAP URIs. Each URI 
resolves to a PSAP or an Emergency Services Routing Proxy (ESRP) that serves as an incoming proxy for a group of PSAPs. 
The call arrives at the PSAP with the location included in the INVITE request.</t> 
<t>The following is a quick overview for a typical Ethernet connected telephone using SIP signaling.
It illustrates one set of choices for various options presented later in this document.
<list style="symbols">
<t>The phone "boots" and connects to its access network.</t> 

<t>The phone gets location via a Location Configuration Protocol (LCP), for example from the DHCP server in 
civic <xref target="RFC4776"></xref> and/or geo
<xref target="RFC3825"></xref> forms, a HELD server <xref target="I-D.ietf-geopriv-http-location-delivery"></xref> 
or the first level switch's LLDP server <xref target="LLDP"></xref>.</t> 

<t>The phone obtains the local emergency dial string(s) from the LoST <xref target="RFC5222"></xref> 
server for its current location. It also receives and caches the PSAP URI obtained from the LoST server.</t>

<t>Some time later, the user places an emergency call.  The phone recognizes an emergency call from the dial strings and uses 
the "urn:service:sos" <xref target="RFC5031"></xref> URN to mark an emergency call.</t> 

<t>It refreshes its location via DHCP and updates the PSAP's URI by querying the LoST mapping server with its location.</t> 

<t>It puts its location in the SIP INVITE request in a Geolocation header 
<xref target="I-D.ietf-sip-location-conveyance"></xref> and forwards the call using its normal 
outbound call processing, which commonly involves an outbound proxy.</t> 

<t>The proxy recognizes the call as an emergency call and routes the call using normal SIP routing 
mechanisms to the URI specified.</t> 

<t>The call routing commonly traverses an incoming proxy server (ESRP) in the emergency services network. 
That proxy would route the call to the PSAP.</t>

<t>The call is established with the PSAP and mutually agreed upon media streams are created.</t> 

<t>The location of the caller is displayed to the call taker.</t>
</list></t>
      <figure anchor="fig1" title="Emergency Call Component Topology">
        <artwork>
       Configuration Servers          
 . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .
 .                               .
 .   +--------+    +----------+  .    
 . +--------+ |  +----------+ |  .  
 . | LIS    | |  | SIP      | |  .  
 . |        |-+  | Registrar|-+  .  
 . +--------+    +----------+    .  
 .   ^               ^           .                              
 . . | . . . . . . . | . . . . . .                        
     |               |                                       
     |[M1][M4]       |[M2]
     |               |         +--------+                     
     |+--------------+       +--------+ |           
     ||                      | LoST   | |                        
     ||+--------------------&gt;| Servers|-+                         
     |||        [M3][M5]     +--------+       +-------+           
     |||                                      | PSAP2 |          
     |||                                      +-------+          
     |||                                                           
     |||  [M6]  +-------+ [M7]+------+ [M8]+-------+         
   Alice ------&gt;| Proxy |----&gt;| ESRP |----&gt;| PSAP1 |-----&gt; Call-Taker
                +-------+     +------+     +-------+               
                                                                   
                                              +-------+           
                                              | PSAP3 |           
                                              +-------+          

</artwork></figure>
      <figure anchor="fig2" title="Message Flow">
        <artwork>
The typical message flow for this example using Alice as the caller:
[M1] Alice -> LIS:  LCP Request(s) (ask for location)
     LIS -> Alice:  LCP Reply(s) (replies with location)
[M2] Alice -> Registrar: SIP REGISTER
     Registrar -> Alice: SIP 200 OK (REGISTER)
[M3] Alice -> LoST Server: Initial LoST Query (contains location)
     Lost Server -> Alice: Initial LoST Response (contains 
                       PSAP-URI and dial string)

Some time later, Alice dials or otherwise initiates an emergency call:

[M4] Alice -> LIS:  LCP Request (update location)
     LIS -> Alice:  LCP Reply (replies with location)
[M5] Alice -> LoST Server: Update LoST Query (contains location)
     Lost Server -> Alice: LoST Response (contains PSAP-URI)
[M6] Alice -> Outgoing Proxy: SIP INVITE (service URN, 
                                     Location and PSAP URI)
[M7] Outgoing Proxy -> ESRP: SIP INVITE (service URN, 
                                     Location and PSAP URI)
[M8] ESRP -> PSAP: SIP INVITE (service URN, Location and PSAP URI)

The 200 OK response is propagated back from the PSAP to Alice and the 
ACK response is propagated from Alice to the PSAP.
</artwork></figure>
<t>Figure 1 shows emergency call component topology and the text above shows call establishment. 
These include the following components:
<list style="symbols">
<t>Alice - who places the emergency call.</t> 
<t>Configuration Servers - Servers providing Alice's UA its IP address and other configuration 
information, perhaps including location by-value or by-reference. Configuration servers also may include a SIP 
registrar for Alice's UA. Most SIP UAs will register, so it will be a common scenario for UAs 
that make emergency calls to be registered with such a server in the originating calling network. 
Registration would be required for the PSAP to be able to call back after an emergency call is 
completed. All the configuration messages are labeled M1 through M3, but could easily require 
more than 3 messages to complete.</t> 
<t>LoST server - Processes the LoST request for location plus a Service URN to a PSAP-URI, 
either for an initial request from a UA, or an in-call routing by the proxy server in the 
originating network, or possibly by an ESRP.</t> 
<t>ESRP - Emergency Services Routing Proxy, a SIP proxy server that is the incoming call proxy in the emergency 
services domain. The ESRP makes further routing decisions (e.g., based on PSAP state and the location 
of the caller) to choose the actual PSAP that handles the call. In some jurisdictions, this may 
involve another LoST query.</t> 
<t>PSAP - Emergency calls are answered at a Public Safety Answering Point, a call center.</t> 
</list></t>
<t>Generally, Alice's UA either has location configured manually, has an integral location measurement 
mechanism, or it runs a LCP [M1] to obtain location from the access (broadband) network. 
Alice's UA then will most likely register [M2] with a SIP registrar. This allows her to be 
contacted by other SIP entities. Next, her UA will perform an initial LoST query [M3] to learn a 
URI for use if the LoST query fails during an emergency call, or to use to test the emergency call 
mechanism. The LoST response contains the dial string for emergency calls appropriate for the 
location provided.</t> 
<t>At some time after her device has booted, Alice initiates an emergency call. She may do this 
by dialing an emergency dial string valid for her current ("local") location, or for her "home" 
location.</t> 
<t>The UA recognizes the dial string. The UA attempts to refresh its location [M4], and with that 
location, to refresh the LoST mapping [M5], in order to get the most accurate information to use 
for routing the call. If the location request or the LoST request fails, or takes too long, the 
UA uses values it has cached.</t> 
<t>The UA creates a SIP INVITE [M6] request that includes the location.
<xref target="I-D.ietf-sip-location-conveyance"></xref> defines a SIP Geolocation header that 
contains either a location-by-reference URI or a <xref target="RFC3986"></xref> "cid" URL 
indicating where in the message body the location-by-value is.</t> 
<t>The INVITE message is routed to the ESRP [M7], which is the first inbound proxy for the 
emergency services domain. This message is then routed by the ESRP towards the most appropriate 
PSAP for Alice's location [M8], as determined by the location and other information.</t> 
<t>A proxy in the PSAP chooses an available call taker and extends the call to its UA.</t> 
<t>The 200 OK response to the INVITE request traverses the path in reverse, from call taker 
UA to PSAP proxy to ESRP to originating network proxy to Alice's UA. The ACK request completes the call 
set-up and the emergency call is established, allowing the PSAP call-taker to talk to Alice 
about Alice's emergency.</t> 
</section><section anchor="WhichDevices" title="Which devices and services should support emergency calls">
<t>Current PSAPs support voice calls and real-time text calls placed through PSTN facilities or systems 
connected to the PSTN. Future PSAPs will however support Internet 
connectivity and a wider range of media types and provide higher functionality. In general, 
if a user could reasonably expect to be able to place a call for help with the device, then the 
device or service should support emergency calling. Certainly, any device or service that looks 
like and works like a telephone (wired or mobile) should support emergency calling, but 
increasingly, users have expectations that other devices and services should work.</t>
<t>Devices that create media sessions and exchange audio, 
video and/or text, and have the capability to establish sessions to a wide variety of addresses, 
and communicate over private IP networks or the Internet, should support emergency calls.</t> 
<t>Traditionally, enterprise support of emergency calling is provided by the telephony service provider
to the enterprise.  In some more recent systems, the enterprise PBX assists emergency calling by providing more
fine grained location in larger enterprises.  In the future, the enterprise may provide the connection to
emergency services itself, not relying on the telephony service provider.</t>
</section><section anchor="Identifying" title="Identifying an emergency call">
<t>Using the PSTN, emergency help can often be summoned by dialing a nationally designated, 
widely known number, regardless of where the telephone was purchased. The appropriate number 
is determined by the infrastructure the telephone is connected to. However, this number differs 
between localities, even though it is often the same for a country or region, as it is in many 
countries in the European Union. In some countries, there is only one uniform digit sequence that is used 
for all types of emergencies. In others, there are several sequences that are specific to the 
type of responder needed, e.g., one for police, another for fire. For end systems, on the other 
hand, it is desirable to have a universal identifier, independent of location, to allow the 
automated inclusion of location information and to allow the device and other entities in the 
call path to perform appropriate processing within the signaling protocol in an emergency call 
set-up.</t> 
<t>Since there is no such universal identifier, as part of the overall emergency calling 
architecture, common emergency call URNs are defined in 
<xref target="RFC5031"></xref>. For a single number environment the urn
is "urn:service:sos". Users are not expected to "dial" an emergency URN. Rather, appropriate 
emergency dial strings are translated to corresponding service URNs, carried in the Request-URI 
of the INVITE request. Such translation is best done by the endpoint, because, among other reasons, 
emergency calls convey 
location in the signaling, but non-emergency calls do not normally do that. If the device 
recognizes the emergency call, it can include location. A signaling intermediary (proxy server) 
can also recognize emergency dial strings if the endpoint fails to do so. </t>
<t>For devices that are mobile or nomadic, an issue arises of whether the home or 
visited dial strings should be used. Many users would prefer that their home dialing 
sequences work no matter where they are. However, local laws and regulations may require that the visited 
dialing sequence(s) work. Therefore, the visited dial string must work.  Devices may have a way to
be configured or learn home dial strings.</t> 
<t>LoST <xref target="RFC5222"></xref> provides the mechanism for obtaining the dialing sequences 
for a given location. LoST servers must return dial strings for emergency
services. If the endpoint does not support the translation 
of dial strings to service URNs, the dialing sequence from the endpoint to its proxy is represented as a dial 
string <xref target="RFC4967"></xref> and the outgoing proxy must recognize the dial string 
and translate it to the equivalent service URN. To determine the local emergency dial string, the proxy needs the 
location of the endpoint. This may be difficult in situations where the user can roam or be 
nomadic. Endpoint recognition of emergency dial strings is therefore preferred. If
a service provider is unable to guarantee that it can correctly determine local emergency
dialstrings, wherever its subscribers may be, then it is required that the endpoint do the recognition.</t>
<t>Note: The emergency call practitioners consider it undesirable to have a single button emergency call user interface element. 
These mechanisms tend to result in a very high rate of false or accidental emergency calls. 
In order to minimize this rate, practitioners recommend that device should only initiate emergency calls based on entry of 
specific emergency call dial strings.  Speed dial mechanisms may effectively create single button emergency
call invocation and practitioners recommend they not be permitted.  </t> 
</section><section anchor="Location" title="Location and its role in an emergency call">
<t>Location is central to the operation of emergency services. Location is used for two purposes in 
emergency call handling: routing of the call and dispatch of 
responders. It is frequently the case that 
the caller reporting an emergency is unable to provide a unique, valid location themselves. For this 
reason, location provided by the endpoint or the access network is needed. For practical 
reasons, each PSAP generally handles only calls for a certain geographic area, with overload 
arrangements between PSAPs to handle each others' calls. Other calls that reach it by accident must 
be manually re-routed (transferred) to the most appropriate PSAP, increasing call handling delay 
and the chance for errors. The area covered by each PSAP differs by jurisdiction, where some 
countries have only a small number of PSAPs, while others decentralize PSAP responsibilities to 
the level of counties or municipalities.</t> 
<t>In most cases, PSAPs cover at least a city or town, but there are some areas where PSAP 
coverage areas follow old telephone rate center boundaries and may straddle more than one city. 
Irregular boundaries are common, often for historical reasons. Routing must be done based on actual
PSAP service boundaries -- the closest PSAP, or the PSAP that serves the nominal city name provided 
in the location, may not be the correct PSAP.</t> 
<t>Accuracy of routing location is a complex subject. Calls must be routed quickly, but accurately, 
and location determination is often a time/accuracy tradeoff, especially with mobile devices or 
self measuring mechanisms.  if more accurate routing location is not available it is considered 
acceptable to base a routing decision on an accuracy 
equal to the area of one sector of a mobile cell site.</t> 
<t>Routing to the most appropriate PSAP is always based on the location of the caller, 
despite the fact that some emergency calls are placed on behalf of someone else, and the location 
of the incident is sometimes not the location of the caller. In some cases, there are other 
factors that enter into the choice of the PSAP that gets the call, such as time of day, caller media 
requests and language preference and call load. However, location 
of the caller is the primary input to the routing decision.</t>
<t>Many mechanisms used to locate a caller have a relatively long "cold start" time. 
To get a location accurate enough for dispatch may take as much as 30 seconds. This is too long to 
wait for emergencies. Accordingly, it is common, especially in mobile systems, to use a coarse 
location, for example, the cell site and sector serving the call, for call routing purposes, and then 
to update the location when a more precise value is known prior to dispatch. In this document we 
use "routing location" and "dispatch location" when the distinction matters.</t>
<t>Accuracy of dispatch location is sometimes determined by local regulation, and is constrained 
by available technology. The actual requirement is more stringent than available technology can deliver: It is required that 
a device making an emergency call close to the "demising" or separation wall between two 
apartments in a high rise apartment building report location with sufficient accuracy to 
determine on what side of the wall it is on. This implies perhaps a 3 cm accuracy requirement. 
As of the date of this memo, assisted GNSS uncertainty in mobile phones with 95% confidence cannot be relied upon to be less than hundreds of meters.  As
technology advances, the accuracy requirements for location will need to be tightened.  Wired systems 
using wire tracing mechanisms can provide location to a wall jack in specific room on a floor in a building,
and may even specify a cubicle or even smaller resolution.  As this discussion illustrates, emergency
call systems demand the most stringent location accuracy available.</t>
<t>In 
Internet emergency calling, where the endpoint is located is determined using a variety of 
measurement or wire-tracing methods. Endpoints may be configured with their own location by 
the access network. In some circumstances, a proxy server may insert location into the signaling 
on behalf of the endpoint. The location is mapped to the URI to send the call to, and the 
location is conveyed to the PSAP (and other elements) in the signaling. The terms 'determination', 'configuration', 'mapping', and 'conveyance' are used for specific aspects of location handling in IETF protocols. 
Likewise, we employ 
Location Configuration Protocols, Location Mapping Protocols, and Location Conveyance Protocols 
for these functions. </t>
<t>This document provides guidance for generic network configurations with respect to location.  It is
recognized that unique issues may exist in some network deployments.  The
IETF will continue to investigate these unique situations and provide
further guidance, if warranted, in future documents.</t>
<section anchor="LocationTypes" title="Types of location information">
<t>Location can be specified in several ways: 
<list style="hanging">
<t hangText="Civic:">
Civic location information describes the location of a person or object by a street address 
that corresponds to a building or other structure. Civic location may include more fine grained 
location information such as floor, room and cubicle. Civic information comes in two forms: 
<list style="hanging">
<t hangText="'Jurisdictional':">refers to a civic location using actual political subdivisions, 
especially for the community name.</t> 
<t hangText="'Postal':        ">refers to a civic location for mail delivery. The name of the post office sometimes does 
not correspond to the community name and a postal address may contain post office boxes or street addresses that do 
not correspond to an actual building.  Postal addresses are generally unsuitable for emergency call dispatch because the 
post office conventions (for community name, for example) do not match those known 
by the responders. The fact that they are unique can sometimes be exploited to 
provide a mapping between a postal address and a civic address suitable to dispatch 
a responder to.  In IETF location protocols, there is an element (Postal Community Name) 
that can be included in a location to provide the post office name as well as the 
actual jurisdictional community name.  There is also an element for a postal code.
There is no other accommodation for postal addresses in these protocols.</t>
</list></t>
<t hangText="Geospatial (geo):">
Geospatial addresses contain longitude, latitude and altitude information based on an understood 
datum and earth shape model (datum). While there have been many datums developed over time, most modern 
systems are using or moving towards the WGS84 <xref target="WGS84"></xref> datum.</t> 
<t hangText="Cell tower/sector:">
Cell tower/sector is often used for identifying the location of a mobile handset, especially for 
routing of emergency calls. Cell tower and sectors identify the cell tower and the antenna sector 
that a mobile device is currently using. Traditionally, the tower location is represented as a 
point chosen to be within a certain PSAP service boundary who agrees to take calls originating 
from that tower/sector, and routing decisions are made on that point. Cell/sector information 
could also be represented as an irregularly shaped polygon of geospatial coordinates reflecting 
the likely geospatial location of the mobile device. Whatever representation is used must route 
correctly in the LoST database, where "correct" is determined by local PSAP management.</t> 
</list></t>
<t>In IETF protocols, both civic and geospatial forms are supported. The civic forms include both 
postal and jurisdictional fields. A cell tower/sector can be represented as a geo point  
or polygon or civic location. Other forms of location representation must be mapped into either a geo or civic for 
use in emergency calls.</t>
<t>For emergency call purposes, conversion of location information from civic to geo or vice versa 
prior to conveyance is not desirable. The location should be sent in the form it was determined. 
Conversion between geo and civic requires a database. Where PSAPs need to convert from whatever form 
they receive to another for responder purposes, they have a suitable database. However, if a 
conversion is done before the PSAP's, and the database used is not exactly the same one the PSAP uses, 
the double conversion has a high probability of introducing an error.</t> 
</section><section anchor="LocationDetermination" title="Location determination">
<t>As noted above, location information can be entered by the user or installer of a device ("manual configuration"), 
measured by the end system, can be delivered to the end system by some protocol or measured by a 
third party and inserted into the call signaling. </t>
<t>In some cases, an entity may have multiple sources of location information, possibly partially 
contradictory. This is particularly likely if the location information is determined both by the 
end system and a third party. Although self measured location (e.g., GNSS) is attractive, location information provided
by the access network could be much more accurate, and more reliable in some environments such as
high rise buildings in dense urban areas.</t>
<t>The closer an entity is to the source of location,
the more likely it is able to determine which location is most appropriate for a particular purpose when there 
are more than one location determinations for a given endpoint. 
In emergency calling, the PSAP is the least likely to be able to appropriately choose which location to use
when multiple
conflicting locations are presented to it.  While all available locations can be sent towards the PSAP, the
order of the locations should be the sender's best attempt to guide the recipient of which one(s) to use.</t>
<section anchor="UserLocation" title="User-entered location information">
<t>Location information can be maintained by the end user or the installer of an endpoint in the 
endpoint itself, or in a database.</t> 
<t>Location information routinely provided by end users is almost always less reliable than measured or wire 
database information, as users may mistype location information or may enter civic address 
information that does not correspond to a recognized (i.e., valid, see Section 
<xref target="Validation"></xref>) address. Users can forget to change the data when the location of 
a device changes.</t> 
<t>However, there are always a small number of cases where the automated mechanisms used by the 
access network to determine location fail to accurately reflect the actual location of the endpoint. 
For example, the user may deploy his own WAN behind an access network, effectively removing an endpoint 
some distance from the access network's notion of its location. To handle these exceptional cases, there must be some mechanism provided 
to manually provision a location for an endpoint by the user or by the access network on behalf of a user. 
The use of the mechanism introduces the possibility of users falsely declaring themselves to be 
somewhere they are not. As an aside, normally, if an emergency caller insists that he is at a location 
different from what any automatic location determination system reports he is, responders will always 
be sent to the user's self-declared location. However, this is a matter of local policy and is outside 
the scope of this document.</t> 
</section><section anchor="WireDatabase" title='Access network "wire database" location information'>
<t>Location information can be maintained by the access network, relating some form of identifier for 
the end subscriber or device to a location database ("wire database"). In enterprise LANs, wiremap 
databases map Ethernet switch ports to building locations. In DSL installations, the local telephone 
carrier maintains a mapping of wire-pairs to subscriber addresses.</t> 
<t>Accuracy of location historically has been to a street address level. However, this is not sufficient 
for larger structures. The PIDF Location Object <xref target="RFC4119"></xref> extended by <xref target="RFC5139"/> and 
<xref target="RFC5491"></xref> permits interior building/floor/room 
and even finer specification of location within a street address. When possible, interior 
location should be supported.</t> 
<t>The threshold for when interior location is needed is approximately 650 square meters.  This value is derived 
from USA fire brigade recommendations of spacing of alarm pull stations. However, interior 
space layout, construction materials and other factors should be considered. </t> 
<t>Even for IEEE 802.11 wireless access points, wire databases may provide sufficient location 
resolution. The location of the access point as determined by the wiremap may be supplied as 
the location for each of the clients of the access point. However, this may not be true for 
larger-scale systems such as IEEE 802.16 (WiMAX) and IEEE 802.22 that typically have larger 
cells than those of IEEE 802.11. The civic location of an IEEE 802.16 base station may be of 
little use to emergency personnel, since the endpoint could be several kilometers away from the 
base station.</t> 
<t>Wire databases are likely to be the most promising solution for residential users 
where a service provider knows the customer's service address. The service provider can then 
perform address validation (see <xref target="Validation"></xref>), similar to the 
current system in some jurisdictions.</t> 
</section><section anchor="EndSystemMeasuredLocation" title="End-system measured location information">
<t>Global Positioning System (GPS) and similar Global Navigation Satellite Systems (e.g., GLONAS and Galileo) receivers may be 
embedded directly in the end device. GNSS produces relatively high precision location fixes in 
open-sky conditions, but the technology still faces several challenges in terms of performance 
(time-to-fix and time-to-first-fix), as well as obtaining successful location fixes within 
shielded structures, or underground. It also requires all devices to be equipped with the 
appropriate GNSS capability.  
Many mobile devices require using some kind of "assist", that may be operated by the access 
network (A-GPS) or by a government (WAAS). A device may be able to use multiple sources of assist data.</t> 
<t>GNSS systems may be always enabled and thus location will always be available accurately immediately 
(assuming the device can "see" enough satellites). Mobile devices may not be able to sustain the 
power levels required to keep the measuring system active. In such circumstances, when location is 
needed, the device has to start up the measurement mechanism. This typically takes tens of seconds, 
far too long to wait to be able to route an emergency call. For this reason, devices that  
have end-system measured location mechanisms but need a cold start period lasting more than a couple
seconds need another way to get a routing location. 
Typically this would be a location associated with a radio link (cell site/sector).</t>
</section><section anchor="NetworkMeasuredLocation" title="Network measured location information">
<t>The access network may locate end devices. Techniques include:
<list style="hanging">
<t hangText="Wireless triangulation:">
Elements in the network infrastructure triangulate end systems based on signal strength, 
angle of arrival or time of arrival. Common mechanisms deployed include:
<list style="symbols">
<t>Time Difference Of Arrival - TDOA</t> 
<t>Uplink Time Difference Of Arrival - U-TDOA</t> 
<t>Angle of Arrival - AOA</t> 
<t>RF fingerprinting</t> 
<t>Advanced Forward Link Trilateration - AFLT</t> 
<t>Enhanced Forward Link Trilateration - EFLT</t>
</list>
Sometimes multiple mechanisms are combined, for example A-GPS with AFLT.</t> 
<t hangText="Location beacons:">
A short range wireless beacon, e.g., using Bluetooth or infrared, announces its location 
to mobile devices in the vicinity. This allows devices to get location from the beacon source's location.</t>
</list></t>
</section></section><section anchor="WhoAddsLocation" title="Who adds location, endpoint or proxy">
<t>The IETF emergency call architecture prefers endpoints to learn their location and supply it 
on the call. Where devices do not support location, proxy servers may have to 
add location to emergency calls. Some calling networks have relationships 
with all access networks the device may be connected to, and that may allow the proxy to 
accurately determine the location of the endpoint. However, NATs and other middleboxes often make it 
impossible to determine a reference identifier the access network could provide to a LIS to determine the 
location of the device. Systems designers are discouraged from relying on proxies to add location. 
The technique 
may be useful in some limited circumstances as devices are upgraded to meet the requirements of 
this document, or where relationships between access networks and calling networks are feasible 
and can be relied upon to get accurate location.</t> 
<t>Proxy insertion of location complicates dial string recognition. As noted in 
<xref target="Location"></xref>, local dial strings depend on the location of the caller. 
If the device does not know its own location, it cannot use the LoST service to learn the 
local emergency dial strings. The calling network must provide another way for the device 
to learn the local dial string, and update it when the user moves to a location where the 
dial string(s) change, or do the dial string determination itself.</t>
</section><section anchor="LocationReference" title="Location and references to location">
<t>Location information may be expressed as the actual civic or geospatial value but can be 
transmitted as by value (wholly contained within the signaling message) or by reference 
(i.e., as a URI pointing to the value residing on a remote node waiting to be dereferenced).</t>
<t>When location is transmitted by value, the location information is available to entity in the call path.
On the other hand, location objects can be large, and only represent a single snapshot of the 
device's location. Location references are small and can be used to represent a time-varying 
location, but the added complexity of the dereference step introduces a risk that location 
will not be available to parties that need it.</t>
</section><section anchor="LocationConfiguration" title="End system location configuration">
<t>Unless a user agent has access to provisioned or locally measured location information, 
it must obtain it from the access network. There are several location configuration protocols 
(LCPs) that can be used for this purpose including DHCP, HELD and LLDP: 
<list style="hanging">
<t hangText="DHCP">
can deliver civic <xref target="RFC4776"></xref> or geospatial  
<xref target="RFC3825"></xref> information. User agents need to support both formats. Note 
that a user agent can use DHCP, via the DHCP REQUEST or INFORM messages, even if it uses 
other means to acquire its IP address.</t> 
<t hangText="HELD"> 
<xref target="I-D.ietf-geopriv-http-location-delivery"></xref> can deliver a civic or 
geo location object, by value or by reference, via a layer 7 protocol. The query typically uses the IP address 
of the requester as an identifier and returns the location value or reference associated 
with that identifier. HELD is typically carried in HTTP.</t> 
<t hangText="Link-Layer Discovery Protocol">
<xref target="LLDP"></xref> with Media Endpoint Device extensions 
<xref target="LLDP-MED"></xref> can be used to deliver location information directly from 
the Layer 2 network infrastructure, and also supports both civic and geo formats 
identical in format to DHCP methods.</t>
</list></t>
<t>Each LCP has limitations in the kinds of networks that can reasonably support it. For 
this reason, it is not possible to choose a single mandatory-to-deploy LCP. For endpoints 
with common network connections (such as an Ethernet jack or a WiFi connection) serious 
incompatibilities would ensue unless every network supported every protocol, or 
alternatively, every device supported every protocol. For this reason, a mandatory-to-implement
list of LCPs is 
established in <xref target="I-D.ietf-ecrit-phonebcp"></xref>. Every endpoint that could 
be used to place emergency calls must implement all of the protocols on the list. Every 
access network must deploy at least one of them. Since it is the 
variability of the networks that prevent a single protocol from being acceptable, it 
must be the endpoints that implement all of them, and to accommodate a wide range of 
devices, networks must deploy at least one of them.</t> 
<t>Often, network operators and device designers believe that they have a simpler 
environment and some other network specific mechanism can be used to provide location. 
Unfortunately, it is very rare to actually be able to limit the range of devices that 
may be connected to a network.
For example, existing mobile networks are being used to support routers and LANs 
behind a wireless data network WAN connection, with Ethernet connected phones 
connected to that. It is possible that the access network could support a protocol not 
on the list, and require every handset in that network to use that protocol for emergency 
calls. However, the Ethernet-connected phone won't be able to acquire location, and the 
user of the phone is unlikely to be dissuaded from placing an emergency call on that phone. 
The widespread availability of gateways, routers and other network-broadening devices 
means that indirectly connected endpoints are possible on nearly every network. 
Network operators and vendors are cautioned that shortcuts to meeting this requirement 
are seldom successful.</t> 
<t>Location for non-mobile devices is normally expected to be acquired at network 
attachment time and retained by the device. It should be refreshed when the cached value 
expires. For example, if DHCP is the acquisition protocol, refresh of location 
may occur when the IP address lease is renewed. At the time of an emergency call, 
the location should be refreshed, with the retained location used if the location 
acquisition does not immediately return a value. Mobile devices may determine location 
at network attachment time and periodically thereafter as a backup in case location 
determination at the time of call does not work. Mobile device location may be 
refreshed when a TTL expires or the device moves beyond some boundaries (as provided by 
<xref target="RFC5222"></xref>). Normally, mobile devices will acquire its 
location at call time for use in an emergency call routing. See  
<xref target="LocationUpdate"></xref> for a further discussion on location updates 
for dispatch location.</t>
<t>There are many examples of endpoints which are user agent applications running on a more general 
purpose device, such as a personal computer.  On some systems, layer 2 protocols like DHCP and LLDP may
not be directly accessible to applications.  It is desirable for an operating system to have an API which 
provides the location of the device for use by any application, especially those supporting emergency calls.</t>
</section><section anchor="WhenConfigure" title="When location should be configured">
<t>Devices should get routing location immediately after obtaining local network 
configuration information. The presence of NAT and VPN tunnels (that assign new IP 
addresses to communications) can obscure identifiers used by LCPs to determine 
location, especially for HELD. In some cases, such as residential NAT devices, 
the NAT is placed between the endpoint and the access network demarcation point and thus the IP address 
seen by the access network is the right identifier for location of the residence. 
However, in many enterprise environments, VPN tunnels can obscure the actual IP address. 
Some VPN mechanisms can be bypassed so that a query to the LCP can be designated to go 
through the direct IP path, using the correct IP address, and not through the 
tunnel. In other cases, no bypass is possible. Of course, LCPs that use layer 2 
mechanisms (DHCP Location options and LLDP-MED) are usually immune from such problems 
because they do not use the IP address as the identifier for the device seeking 
location.</t> 
<t>It is desirable that routing location information be periodically refreshed. 
A LIS supporting a million subscribers each refreshing once per day would need 
to support a query rate of 1,000,000 / (24 * 60 * 60) = 12 queries per second.</t> 
<t>It is desirable for routing location information to be requested immediately 
before placing an emergency call. However, if there is any significant delay in 
getting more recent location, the call should be placed with the most recent 
location information the device has. In mobile handsets, routing is often 
accomplished with the cell site and sector of the tower serving the call, 
because it can take many seconds to start up the location determination mechanism 
and obtain an accurate location.</t>
<t>There is a tradeoff between the time it takes to get a routing location and 
the accuracy (technically, confidence and uncertainty) obtained. Routing an 
emergency call quickly is required. However, if location can be substantially 
improved by waiting a short time (e.g., for some sort of "quick fix"), it's 
preferable to wait. Three seconds, the current nominal time for a quick 
fix, is a very long time add to post dial delay.</t>
<t>NENA recommends <xref target="NENAi3TRD"></xref> that IP based systems complete calls in two seconds from last dial 
press to ring at PSAP.</t> 
</section><section anchor="Conveyance" title="Conveying location in SIP">
<t>When an emergency call is placed, the endpoint should include location in the 
call signaling. This is referred to as "conveyance" to distinguish 
it from "configuration". In SIP, the location information is conveyed following 
the procedures in <xref target="I-D.ietf-sip-location-conveyance"></xref>. 
Since the form of the location information obtained by the acquisition protocol may not 
be the same as the conveyance protocol uses (PIDF-LO <xref target="RFC4119"></xref>), 
mapping by the endpoint from the LCP form to PIDF may be required.</t> 
</section><section anchor="LocationUpdate" title="Location updates">
<t>As discussed above, it may take some time for some measurement mechanisms 
to get a location accurate enough for dispatch, and a routing location with less 
accuracy may be provided to get the call established quickly. The PSAP needs the 
dispatch location before it sends the call to the responder. This requires an 
update of the location.  In addition, the location of some mobile callers, e.g., in a vehicle or aircraft, 
can change significantly during the emergency call. </t> 
<t>A PSAP has no way to request an update of a location provided by value. If the UAC 
gets new location, it must signal the PSAP using a new INVITE or an UPDATE transaction
with a new Geolocation header to supply the new location.</t> 
<t>With the wide variation in determination mechanisms, the PSAP does not know when 
accurate location may be available.  The preferred mechanism is 
that the LIS notifies the PSAP when an accurate 
location is available rather than requiring a poll operation from the PSAP to 
the LIS.  The SIP Presence subscription <xref target=
"RFC3856"></xref> provides a suitable mechanism.</t>
<t>When using a HELD dereference, the PSAP must specify the value "emergencyDispatch"
for the ResponseTime parameter.  Since typically the LIS is local relative to the PSAP, 
the LIS can be aware of the update requirements of the PSAP</t>
</section><section anchor="MultipleLocations" title="Multiple locations">
<t>Getting multiple locations all purported to describe the location of the caller
is confusing to all, and should be avoided.  Handling multiple locations at the point
where a PIDF is created is discussed 
in <xref target="RFC5491"></xref>. Conflicting location 
information is particularly harmful if different routes (PSAPs) result from 
LoST queries for the multiple locations.  When they occur anyway, the general guidance
is that the entity earliest in the chain generally has more knowledge than later
elements to make an intelligent decision, especially about which location will be
used for routing.  It is permissible to send multiple locations towards the PSAP,
but the element that chooses the route must select exactly one location to use
with LoST.</t>
<t>Guidelines for dealing with multiple 
locations are also given in <xref target="RFC5222"></xref>. 
If a UA gets multiple locations, it must choose the one to use for routing, but it
may send all of the locations it has in the signaling. 
If a proxy is inserting location and has multiple locations, it must choose 
exactly one to use for routing, marking it as such (per 
<xref target="I-D.ietf-sip-location-conveyance"></xref>, and send it as well as any others it has.</t> 
<t>The UA or proxy should have the ability to understand how and from whom it learned 
its location, and should include this information in the location objects 
that are sent to the PSAP.  That labeling provides the call-taker with 
information to make decisions upon, as well as guidance for what to ask the caller 
and what to tell the responders.</t> 
<t>The call must indicate the location information that has been used for routing, 
so that the same location information is used for all call routing decisions. 
The location conveyance mechanism 
<xref target="I-D.ietf-sip-location-conveyance"></xref> contains a parameter 
for this purpose.</t>
<t>Endpoints or proxies may be tempted to send multiple versions of the same location.  For example
a database may be used to "geocode" or "reverse geocode",
that is, convert from civic to geo or vice versa.  It is very problematic to use derived
locations in emergency calls.  The PSAP and the responders have very accurate databases which they
use to convert, most commonly from a reported geo to a civic suitable for dispatching responders.  If one database
is used to convert from, say, civic to geo, and another converts from geo to civic, errors will often occur
where the databases are slightly different.  "Off by one" errors are serious when responders
go to the wrong location.
Derived locations should be marked with a "derived" method token <xref target="RFC4119"/>.
If an entity gets a location which has a measured or other original method, and another with
a derived method, it must use the original value for the emergency call.</t>
</section><section anchor="Validation" title="Location validation">
<t>Validation in this context means both that there is a mapping from the address 
to a PSAP and that the PSAP understands how to direct responders to the location.
It is recommended that location be validated prior to a device placing 
an actual emergency call; some jurisdictions require that this be done. 
</t><t> 
Determining the addresses that are valid can be difficult. There are, for example, 
many cases of two names for the same street, or two streets with the same name, but different "suffixes" (Avenue, Street, Circle) 
in a city. In some countries, the current system provides validation. 
For example, in the United States of America, the Master Street Address Guide (MSAG) records 
all valid street addresses and is used to ensure that the service addresses in 
phone billing records correspond to valid emergency service street addresses. 
Validation is normally only a concern for civic addresses, although there could be 
some determination that a given geo is within at least one PSAP service boundary; that is, 
a "valid" geo is one where there is a mapping in the LoST server.</t> 
<t>LoST <xref target="RFC5222"></xref> includes a location validation 
function. Validation is normally performed when a location is entered 
into a Location Information Server. It should be confirmed periodically, 
because the mapping database undergoes slow change and locations which previously validated may eventually
fail validation. Endpoints may wish 
to validate locations they receive from the access network, and will need to 
validate manually entered locations. Proxies that insert location may wish to 
validate locations they receive from a LIS. When the test functions 
(<xref target="Testing"></xref>) are invoked, the location used should be validated.</t>
<t>When validation fails, the location given must not be used for an emergency call.
If validation is completed when location is first loaded into a LIS, any problems
can be found and fixed before devices could get the bad location. Failure of validation
arises because an error is made in determining the location, although occasionally
the LoST database is not up to date or has faulty information.  In either case, the
problem must be identified and corrected before using the location.</t> 
</section><section anchor="DefaultLocation" title="Default location">
<t>Occasionally, the access network cannot determine the actual location of 
the caller. In these cases, it must supply a default location. The default location 
should be as accurate as the network can determine. For example, in a cable network, 
a default location for each Cable Modem Termination System (CMTS), with a 
representative location for all cable modems served by that CMTS could be provided 
if the network is unable to resolve the subscriber to anything more precise than the CMTS. 
Default locations must be marked as such so that the PSAP knows that the 
location is not accurate.</t> 
</section><section anchor="OtherLocation" title="Location format conversion">
<t>The endpoint is responsible for mapping any form of location it receives from 
an LCP into PIDF-LO form if the LCP did not directly return a PIDF-LO.</t>
</section>
</section><section title="LIS and LoST discovery">
<t>Endpoints must be able to discover a LIS if the HELD protocol is used, and a LoST server.
DHCP options are defined for this purpose, namely
<xref target="I-D.ietf-geopriv-lis-discovery"></xref>  and 
<xref target="RFC5223"></xref>.</t>
<t>Until such DHCP records are widely available, it may be necessary for the service 
provider to provision a LoST server address in the device.  The endpoint can also do a DNS SRV query 
to find a LoST server.  In any environment, more than one
of these mechanisms may yield a LoST server, and they may be different.  
The recommended priority is DHCP first, provisioned value second, and DNS SRV 
query in the SIP domain third.</t>
</section><section anchor="Routing" title="Routing the call to the PSAP">
<t>Emergency calls are routed based on one or more of the following criteria 
expressed in the call setup request (INVITE): 
<list style="hanging">
<t hangText="Location:">
Since each PSAP serves a limited geographic region and transferring existing 
calls delays the emergency response, calls need to be routed to the most 
appropriate PSAP. In this architecture, emergency call setup requests contain 
location information, expressed in civic or geospatial coordinates, that allows 
such routing.</t> 
<t hangText="Type of emergency service:">
In some jurisdictions, emergency calls for specific emergency services such as fire, police, ambulance or mountain 
rescue are directed to just those emergency-specific PSAPs. This mechanism is 
supported by marking emergency calls with the proper service identifier 
<xref target="RFC5031"></xref>.  Even in single number jurisdictions,
not all services are dispatched by PSAPs and may need alternate URNs to route calls
to the appropriate call center.</t> 
<t hangText="Media capabilities of caller:">
In some cases, emergency call centers for specific caller media preferences, 
such as typed text or video, are separate from PSAPs serving voice calls. 
ESRPs are expected to be able to provide routing based on media. Also, even if media 
capability does not affect the selection of the PSAP, there may be call takers 
within the PSAP that are specifically trained, e.g., in interactive text or 
sign language communications, where routing within the PSAP based on the media 
offer would be provided.</t> 
</list></t>
<t>Providing a URL to route emergency calls by location and by type of service is the primary function LoST 
<xref target="RFC5222"></xref> provides. LoST accepts a query with 
location (by-value) in either civic or geo form, plus a service identifier, 
and returns a URI (or set of URIs) to route the call to. Normal SIP 
<xref target="RFC3261"></xref> routing functions are used to resolve the URI 
to a next hop destination.</t> 
<t>The endpoint can complete the LoST mapping from its location at boot time, 
and periodically thereafter. It should attempt to obtain a "fresh" location, 
and from that a current mapping when it places an emergency call.  
If accessing either its location acquisition or mapping functions fail, 
it should use its cached value. The call would follow its normal outbound 
call processing.</t>
<t>Determining when the device leaves the area provided by the LoST service 
can tax small mobile devices. For this reason, the LoST server should return 
a simple (small number of points) polygon for geospatial location. This can be a simple enclosing 
rectangle of the PSAP service area when the reported point is not near an edge, or a smaller polygonal
edge section when the reported location is near an edge. Civic location is 
uncommon for mobile devices, but reporting that the same mapping is good 
within a community name, or even a street, may be very helpful for WiFi 
connected devices that roam and obtain civic location from the access point they are 
connected to.</t> 
<t>Networks that support devices that do not implement LoST mapping themselves 
may need the outbound proxy do the mapping. If the endpoint recognized the call was
an emergency call, provided the correct service URN and/or included location on
the call in a Geolocation header, a proxy server could easily accomplish the mapping.</t>
<t>However, if the endpoint did not recognize the call was an emergency call, and thus
did not include location, the proxy's task is more difficult.  It is often difficult 
for the calling network to accurately 
determine the endpoint's location.  The endpoint may have its own location, 
but would not normally include 
it on the call signaling unless it knew it was an emergency call. 
There is no mechanism provided in 
<xref target="I-D.ietf-sip-location-conveyance"></xref> for a proxy to 
request the endpoint supply its location, because that would open the endpoint 
to an attack by any proxy on the path to get it to reveal location. 
The proxy can attempt to redirect a call to the service URN which, if the device 
recognizes the significance, would include location in the redirected call from the device. 
All networks elements should detect emergency calls and supply default location 
and/or routing if it is not already present.</t> 
<t>The LoST server would normally be provided by the local emergency authorities, although the access network or calling
network might run its own server using data provided by the emergency authorities.  Some enterprises may have local responders 
and call centers, and could operate their own LoST server, providing URIs to in-house "PSAPs".  Local regulations
might limit the ability of enterprises to direct emergency calls to in-house services.</t>
<t>The ESRP, which is a 
normal SIP proxy server in the signaling path of the call, may use a variety of PSAP state information, the 
location of the caller, and other criteria to onward route the call to the PSAP. 
In order for the ESRP to route on media choice, the initial INVITE request has to 
supply an SDP offer.</t>
</section><section anchor="Signaling" title="Signaling of emergency calls">
<section anchor="TLS" title="Use of TLS">
<t>Best Current Practice for SIP user agents <xref target="RFC4504"/> including 
handling of audio, video and real-time text <xref target="RFC4103"/> should be 
applied.  As discussed above, location is carried in all emergency calls in the call 
signaling. Since emergency calls carry privacy-sensitive information, they 
are subject to the requirements for geospatial protocols 
<xref target="RFC3693"></xref>. In particular, signaling information should 
be carried in TLS, i.e., in 'sips' mode with a ciphersuite which includes
strong encryption (e.g., AES).  There are exceptions
in <xref target="RFC3693"></xref> for emergency calls.  For example, local
policy may dictate that location is sent with an emergency call even if the 
user's policy would otherwise prohibit that. Nevertheless, protection from eavesdropping
of location by encryption should be provided.</t>
<t>It is unacceptable to have 
an emergency call fail to complete because a TLS connection was not created 
for any reason. Thus, the call should be attempted with TLS, but if the TLS 
session establishment fails, the call should be automatically retried without TLS.
<xref target="I-D.ietf-sip-sips"></xref> recommends that to achieve this effect
the target specifies a sip URI, but use TLS on the outbound connection.  An element
that receives a request over a TLS connection should attempt to create a TLS connection
to the next hop.</t> 
<t>In many cases, persistent TLS connections can be maintained between elements 
to minimize the time needed to establish them <xref target="I-D.ietf-sip-outbound"></xref>.
In other circumstances, use of session resumption <xref target="RFC5077"></xref> is
recommended.  IPsec <xref target="RFC4301"></xref> is an acceptable alternative to TLS when
used with an equivalent crypto suite.</t>
<t>Location may be used for routing by 
multiple proxy servers on the path.  Confidentiality mechanisms such as S/MIME encryption of SIP signaling <xref 
target="RFC3261"></xref> cannot be used because they obscure location. 
Only hop-by-hop mechanisms such as TLS 
should be used. Implementing 
location conveyance in SIP mandates inclusion of TLS support.</t>

</section><section anchor="UAsignaling" title="SIP signaling requirements for User Agents">
<t>SIP UAs that recognize local dial strings, insert location, and perform emergency 
call routing will create SIP INVITE messages with the Service URN in the 
Request URI, the LoST-determined URI for the PSAP in a Route header, and the 
location in a Geolocation header. The INVITE request must also have appropriate 
call back identifiers (in Contact and From headers). 
To enable media sensitive routing, the call should 
include an SDP offer.</t>
<t>SIP caller preferences <xref target="RFC3841"></xref> can be used to signal how the PSAP 
should handle the call. For example, a language preference expressed in an Accept-Language header 
may be used as a hint to cause the PSAP to route the call to a call taker who speaks the 
requested language.  SIP caller preferences may also be used to indicate a need to invoke a relay 
service for communication with people with disabilities in the call.</t> 
</section><section anchor="ProxySignaling" title="SIP signaling requirements for proxy servers">
<t>At least one SIP proxy server in the path of an emergency call must be able to assist 
UAs that are unable to provide any of the location based routing steps and 
recognition of dial strings. A Proxy can recognize the lack of location awareness by the lack of a Geolocation header.  They can recognize the lack of dial string recognition by the presence of the local emergency call dial string in the From header without the service URN being present.  They should obtain the location of the endpoint if possible, and use a default location
if they can not, inserting it in a Geolocation header.  They should query LoST with the location and put the resulting 
URI in a Route, with the appropriate service URN in the Request URI.  In any event, they are also expected to provide 
information for the caller using SIP Identity or P-Asserted-Identity.  It is often a regulatory matter whether calls normally marked as anonymous are passed as anonymous when they are emergency calls.  Proxies must conform to the local regulation or practice.</t>
</section></section><section anchor="Callbacks" title="Call backs">
<t>The call-taker must be able to reach the emergency caller if the original 
call is disconnected. In traditional emergency calls, wireline and wireless 
emergency calls include a callback identifier for this purpose. There are two kinds of call backs.  When a call is dropped,
or the call taker realizes that some important information is needed that it doesn't have, it must call back the device that 
placed the emergency call.  The PSAP, or a responder, may need to call back the caller much later, and for that purpose, it wants a normal
SIP Address of Record.  In SIP systems, 
the caller must include a Contact header field in an emergency call containing  a globally routable URI, possibly a GRUU <xref target="I-D.ietf-sip-gruu"></xref>. This identifier would be used to 
initiate call-backs immediately by the call-taker if, for example, the call is 
prematurely dropped.  A concern arises with B2BUAs that manipulate Contact headers.  
Such B2BUAs should always include a Contact header that routes to the same device being available for call backs.</t>
<t>In addition, a call-back identifier as an Address of Record (AoR) must be included either as the URI in 
the From header field <xref target="RFC3261"></xref> verified by SIP Identity 
<xref target="RFC4474"></xref> or as a network asserted URI 
<xref target="RFC3325"></xref>.  If the latter, the PSAP will need to establish a suitable spec(t) with the proxies that send it emergency calls.  This identifier would be used to initiate a 
call-back at a later time and may reach the caller, not necessarily on the 
same device (and at the same location) as the original emergency call as per 
normal SIP rules.  It is often a regulatory matter whether calls normally marked as anonymous are passed as anonymous when they are emergency calls.  Proxies must conform to the local regulation or practice.</t> 
</section><section anchor="MidCall" title="Mid-call behavior">
<t>Some PSAPs often include 
dispatchers, responders or specialists on a call.  Some responder's dispatchers are not located in the primary 
PSAP, the call may have to be transferred to another PSAP. Most often this will be an attended 
transfer, or a bridged transfer.  Therefore a PSAP may need to a REFER request <xref target="RFC3515"></xref> 
a call to a bridge 
for conferencing. Devices which normally involve the user
in transfer operations should consider the effect of such interactions when a stressed user places an emergency call.
Requiring UI manipulation during such events may not be desirable.  Relay services for communication 
with people with disabilities may be included in the call with the bridge.  The UA should be prepared to have the call 
transferred (usually attended, but possibly blind) per
<xref target="RFC5359"></xref>.</t>  
</section><section anchor="Termination" title="Call termination">
<t>It is undesirable for the caller to terminate an emergency call. 
PSAP terminates a call using the normal SIP call termination 
procedures, i.e., with a BYE request.</t> 
</section><section anchor="DisableFeatures" title="Disabling of features">
<t>Certain features that can be invoked while a normal call is active are 
not permitted when the call is an emergency call. Services such as call waiting, 
call transfer, three way call and hold should be disabled.</t>
<t>Certain features such as call forwarding can interfere with calls from a PSAP and should be disabled.  There is no way to
reliably determine a PSAP call back. 
A UA may be able to determine a PSAP call back by examining the domain of incoming calls after placing an 
emergency call and comparing that to the domain of the answering PSAP from the emergency call. 
Any call 
from the same domain and directed to the supplied Contact header or AoR after an emergency call should be 
accepted as a call-back from the PSAP if it occurs within a reasonable time after an emergency call was placed.</t>
</section><section anchor="Media" title="Media">
<t>PSAPs should always accept RTP media streams <xref target="RFC3550"></xref>. 
Traditionally, voice has been the only media stream accepted by PSAPs. In some 
countries, text, in the form of Baudot codes or similar tone encoded signaling 
within a voiceband is accepted ("TTY") for persons who have hearing disabilities. 
Using SIP signaling includes the capability to negotiate media. Normal SIP 
offer/answer <xref target="RFC3264"></xref> negotiations should be used to agree 
on the media streams to be used. PSAPs should accept real-time text 
<xref target="RFC4103"></xref>. All PSAPs should accept G.711 A-law (and mu-law 
in North America) encoded voice as described in <xref target="RFC3551"></xref>. 
Newer text forms are rapidly appearing, with instant messaging now very common, 
PSAPs should accept IM with at least "pager-mode" MESSAGE request <xref target="RFC3428"></xref> 
as well as Message Session Relay Protocol 
<xref target="RFC4975"></xref>. Video may be important to support Video Relay 
Service (sign language interpretation) as well as modern video phones.</t>
<t>It is desirable for media to be kept secure by the use of Secure RTP 
<xref target="RFC3711"></xref>, using SDES <xref target="RFC4568"/> for keying. </t>
</section><section anchor="Testing" title="Testing">
<t>Since the emergency calling architecture consists of a number of pieces operated 
by independent entities, it is important to be able to test whether an emergency 
call is likely to succeed without actually occupying the human resources at a PSAP. 
Both signaling and media paths need to be tested since NATs and firewalls may 
allow the session setup request to reach the PSAP, while preventing the exchange 
of media.</t> 
<t><xref target="I-D.ietf-ecrit-phonebcp"/>includes a description of an 
automated test procedure that validates routing, signaling and media path continuity. 
This test would be used within some random interval after boot time, and whenever the device location changes 
enough that a new PSAP mapping is returned by the LoST server.</t>
<t>The PSAP needs to be able to control frequency and duration of the test, and 
since the process could be abused, it may temporarily or permanently suspend its 
operation.</t> 
<t>There is a concern associated with testing during a so-called 
"avalanche-restart" event where, for example a large power outage affects a large 
number of endpoints, that, when power is restored, all attempt to reboot and, 
possibly, test. Devices need to randomize their initiation of a boot time test 
to avoid the problem.</t> 
</section><section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
<t>Security considerations for emergency calling have been documented in 
<xref target="RFC5069"></xref>
and <xref target="I-D.barnes-geopriv-lo-sec"></xref>. </t>
</section><section title="IANA Considerations">
<t>This document has no actions for IANA.</t>
</section><section title="Acknowledgments">
<t>This draft was created from a draft-schulzrinne-sipping-emergency-arch-02 
together with sections from draft-polk-newton-ecrit-arch-considerations-02.</t> 
<t>Design Team members participating in this draft creation include Martin Dolly, Stu Goldman, Ted Hardie,  
Marc Linsner, Roger Marshall, Shida Schubert, Tom Taylor and Hannes Tschofenig,.  
Further comments and input were provided by Richard Barnes, Barbara 
Stark and James Winterbottom.</t> 
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Informative References">
      &rfc3986;

      &rfc4301;

      &rfc3261;

      &rfc3264;

      &rfc3325;

      &rfc3428;

      &rfc3515;

      &rfc3693;

      &rfc3550;

      &rfc3551;

      &rfc3711;

      &rfc3825;


      &rfc3841;

      &rfc3856;

      &rfc4119;

 
      &rfc4103;

      &rfc4190;

      &rfc4474;
      &rfc4504;
      &rfc4568;

      &rfc4776;
      &rfc4967;

      &rfc4975;
      &rfc5012;
      &rfc5031;
      &rfc5069;
      &rfc5077;

      &rfc5139;
      &rfc5222;
      &rfc5223;
      &rfc5359;
      &rfc5491;

      &draft-ietf-sip-location-conveyance;

      &draft-ietf-sip-gruu;

      &draft-ietf-sip-outbound;

      &draft-ietf-sip-sips;

      &draft-ietf-ecrit-phonebcp;

      &draft-ietf-geopriv-http-location-delivery;

      &draft-barnes-geopriv-lo-sec;

      &draft-ietf-geopriv-lis-discovery;

      <reference anchor="LLDP">
        <front>
          <title>IEEE802.1ab Station and Media Access Control</title>

          <author fullname="">
            <organization>IEEE</organization>
          </author>

          <date day="01" month="Dec" year="2004" />
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="LLDP-MED">
        <front>
          <title>ANSI/TIA-1057 Link Layer Discovery Protocol - Media Endpoint
          Discovery</title>

          <author fullname="">
            <organization>TIA</organization>
          </author>

          <date year="" />
        </front>
      </reference>
 

     <reference anchor="NENAi3TRD">
        <front>
          <title>08-751 NENA i3 Technical Requirements for </title>

          <author fullname="">
            <organization>NENA</organization>
          </author>

          <date year="2006" />
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="WGS84">
        <front>
          <title>NIMA Technical Report TR8350.2, Department of Defense World
          Geodetic System 1984, Its Definition and Relationships With Local
          Geodetic Systems, Third Edition</title>

          <author fullname="">
            <organization>NIMA</organization>
          </author>

          <date day="4" month="July" year="1997" />
        </front>
      </reference>
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>


