<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
	<!ENTITY RFC2119 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
	<!ENTITY RFC5213 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5213.xml">
]>

<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<!-- used by XSLT processors -->
<!-- For a complete list and description of processing instructions (PIs), 
     please see http://xml.resource.org/authoring/README.html. -->
<!-- Below are generally applicable Processing Instructions (PIs) that most I-Ds might want to use.
     (Here they are set differently than their defaults in xml2rfc v1.32) -->
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<!-- give errors regarding ID-nits and DTD validation -->
<!-- control the table of contents (ToC) -->
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<!-- generate a ToC -->
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<!-- the number of levels of subsections in ToC. default: 3 -->
<!-- control references -->
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<!-- use symbolic references tags, i.e, [RFC2119] instead of [1] -->
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<!-- sort the reference entries alphabetically -->
<!-- control vertical white space 
     (using these PIs as follows is recommended by the RFC Editor) -->
<?rfc compact="no" ?>
<!-- do not start each main section on a new page -->
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<!-- keep one blank line between list items -->
<!-- end of list of popular I-D processing instructions -->

<rfc category="info" docName="draft-hong-netext-scenario-logical-interface-00" ipr="trust200902">

  <!-- ***** FRONT MATTER ***** -->

  <front>
    <!-- The abbreviated title is used in the page header - it is only necessary if the 
         full title is longer than 39 characters -->

    <title abbrev="Scenarios of HNP on Logical interface">
	Scenarios of the usage of multiple home network prefixes on a logical interface
	</title>

    <!-- add 'role="editor"' below for the editors if appropriate -->

    <!-- Another author who claims to be an editor -->

    <author fullname="Yong-Geun Hong" initials="Y.G.Hong" role=""
            surname="Hong">
      <organization>ETRI</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>161 Gajeong-Dong Yuseung-Gu</street>

          <!-- Reorder these if your country does things differently -->

          <city>Daejeon</city>

          <region></region>

          <code>305-700</code>

          <country>Korea</country>
        </postal>

        <phone>+82 42 860 6557</phone>

        <email>yonggeun.hong@gmail.com</email>

        <!-- uri and facsimile elements may also be added -->
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Joo-Sang Youn" initials="J.S.Youn" role=""
            surname="Youn">
      <organization>DONG-EUI Univ.</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>

          <!-- Reorder these if your country does things differently -->

          <city>Busan</city>

          <region></region>

          <code></code>

          <country>Korea</country>
        </postal>

        <phone>+82 51 890 1993</phone>

        <email>joosang.youn@gmail.com</email>

        <!-- uri and facsimile elements may also be added -->
      </address>
    </author>

    <date month="July" year="2010" />

    <!-- If the month and year are both specified and are the current ones, xml2rfc will fill 
         in the current day for you. If only the current year is specified, xml2rfc will fill 
	 in the current day and month for you. If the year is not the current one, it is 
	 necessary to specify at least a month (xml2rfc assumes day="1" if not specified for the 
	 purpose of calculating the expiry date).  With drafts it is normally sufficient to 
	 specify just the year. -->

    <!-- Meta-data Declarations -->

    <area>General</area>

    <workgroup>Network Working Group</workgroup>

    <!-- WG name at the upperleft corner of the doc,
         IETF is fine for individual submissions.  
	 If this element is not present, the default is "Network Working Group",
         which is used by the RFC Editor as a nod to the history of the IETF. -->

    <keyword>Internet Draft</keyword>

    <!-- Keywords will be incorporated into HTML output
         files in a meta tag but they have no effect on text or nroff
         output. If you submit your draft to the RFC Editor, the
         keywords will be used for the search engine. -->

    <abstract>
    <t>
	 	A logical interface is used to hide the change of network interface from the upper host IP layer and it also can be used for a multiple interfaces mobile node in PMIPv6 domain. If a LMA assigns multiple home network prefixes to a multiple interfaces mobile node with a logical interface, a logical interface has various usages of the multiple home network prefixes. As following general PMIPv6 operations described in RFC 5213, all multiple home network prefixes are shown to host IP layer. Also, the logical interface hides the existence of multiple home network prefixes and shows only one home network prefix to host IP layer. In this internet draft, we describe various scenarios of the usage of multiple home network prefixes on a logical interface. 
	  </t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
	<!-- Section 1 -->
    <section title="Introduction">
		<t>
		Proxy Mobile IPv6 (PMIPv6)<xref target="RFC5213"/> is a network based IP mobility support protocol, which does not require any modifications to mobile nodes. PMIPv6 
makes it possible to support mobility for IPv6 nodes without an involvement of mobile
nodes. That is, on behalf of mobile nodes, a mobile access gateway (MAG) in the 
network performs the signaling for mobility management with a local mobility anchor (LMA).				
		</t>

		<t>
		Due to the simultaneous usage of multiple interfaces in a mobile node and the change of network interfaces, IETF netext working group has studied the hiding access technology changes from host IP layer. Link layer implementation such as “logical interface” can hide the actually used physical interfaces and the change of physical interfaces from the IP layer. Many operating systems offer support to the usage of logical interface over multiple physical interfaces without any big efforts.  In another internet draft <xref target="I-D.melia-netext-logical-interface-support-00"/>, operations details of the logical interface are explained and it identifies the applicability of the usage of logical interface. 		
		</t>

		<t>
	  PMIPv6 specification allow mobile nodes to connect PMIPv6 domain through multiple network interfaces for simultaneous access and a LMA may allocate more than one home network prefix for a given interface of the mobile node. In basic PMIPv6 specification, the multiple home network prefixes that the LMA allocates to a mobile node are shown totally to the host IP stack of the mobile node. But, if a mobile node utilizes a logical interface to hide the change of network interfaces, we can extend the usage of multiple home network prefixes. First, as following general PMIPv6 operations described in RFC 5213, all multiple home network prefixes are shown to host IP layer. Second, for some reasons such as the session continuity, only one home network prefix is shown to the host IP stack of the mobile node even though the LMA allocates multiple home network prefixes. In this case, the logical interface does some necessary jobs to hide the existence of multiple interfaces and also the existence of multiple home network prefixes. And the logical interface does some necessary jobs when network interfaces are changed and/or home network prefixes are changed. 
		</t>
    </section>

  <!-- Section 2 -->
  <section title="Requirements Language">
  <t>
  In this document, the key words "MAY", "MUST, "MUST NOT", "OPTIONAL", "RECOMMENDED", "SHOULD", and "SHOULD NOT", are to be interpreted as
described in <xref target="RFC2119"/>.
  
  </t>  
  </section>
  

	<!-- Section 3 -->
	<section title="Multihoming support on a logical interface in PMIPv6">
		<t>
		In PMIPv6 specification, to provide multihoming support, it describes three key aspects as following.
		</t>

		<t>
		<list style="symbols">
		<t>
    When a mobile node connects to a PMIPv6 domain through multiple interfaces for simultaneous access, the LMA MUST allocate a mobility session for each of the attached interfaces.
    </t>

		<t>
    The LMA MAY allocate more than one home network prefix for a given interface of the mobile node.
    </t>
    
		<t>
    The LMA MUST allow for a handoff between two different interfaces of a mobile node. In such a scenario, all the home network prefixes associated with one interface (part of one mobility session) will be associated with a different interface of the mobile node.
    </t>
    </list>
    </t> 

		<t>
		Even though a logical interface is adopted in a multiple interface mobile node in PMIPv6 domain, the above three aspects SHOULD be applied. 
		</t>

		<t>
		For the regarding of first aspect, if a logical interface is used, even though multiple network interfaces are used in a mobile node, only one logical interface is shown to both host IP stack of the mobile node and the LMA. So, in this case, the LMA allocates a mobility session for the logical interface of a mobile node and one mobility session of the logical interface is generated.
		</t>

		<t>
		For the regarding of second aspect, in basic PMIPv6 specification, if a LMA allocates multiple home network prefixes to a multiple interfaces mobile node, these multiple home network prefixes are totally shown to the host IP stack of the mobile node. This is effective when a logical interface is used. But, due to the usage of a logical interface in a mobile node in PMIPv6 domain, we can extend the allocation method of multiple home network prefixes to a mobile node. As same as the role of a logical interface to hide the change of multiple interfaces, the logical interface can hide the existence and the change of multiple home network prefixes. In the next section, we describe more detail.
		</t>

		<t>
		For the regarding of third aspect, this description is no longer effective because only one logical interface is shown to the LMA and the LMA assumes that the mobile node has one interface even though it has multiple interfaces. But, the PMPv6 specification SHOULD be extended to consider a handoff between two different physical interfaces of a mobile node with a logical interface.
		</t>

	</section>


	<!-- Section 4 -->
    <section title="The usage of multiple home network prefixes on a logical interface">
    
    <section title="Scenario 1 – All home network prefixes are shown to IP host stack">
    <t>
		The fist scenario of the usage of multiple home network prefixes on a logical interface is same as described in internet draft of “Logical Interface Support for multi-mode IP Hosts <xref target="I-D.melia-netext-logical-interface-support-00"/>.” The role of a logical interface is only to hide the existence of multiple network interfaces and the change of network interfaces. The home network prefixes that a LMA allocates to a multiple interface mobile node are totally shown to host IP stack of the mobile node. The logical interface simply bypass the home network prefixes between host IP stack and physical interfaces.
		</t>
		
		<t>
		 Figure 1 shows this case. As shown in Figure 1, if the LMA allocates two home network prefixes HNP-1, HNP-2 to the mobile node, these two home network prefixes are shown to IP host stack of the mobile node. As a result of receiving multiple home network prefixes in IP host stack, two different IPv6 addresses HNP-1::zzz/128 and HNP-2::zzz/128 are generated. 
		</t>

		<!-- Figure 1 -->
		<figure anchor='hnpsce-1' title="All HNP are shonw to IP host stack">
			<preamble></preamble>
			<artwork>

                                    LMA's Binding Table
                                    +================================+
                           +----+   | HNP   MN-ID  CoA   ATT   LL-ID |
                           |LMA |   +================================+
                           +----+   | HNP-1  MN-1  PCoA-1  5    ZZZ  |
                            //\\    | HNP-2  MN-1  PCoA-2  4    ZZZ  |
                 +---------//--\\-----------+
                (         //    \\           )
                (        //      \\          )
                 +------//--------\\--------+
                       //          \\
               PCoA-1 //            \\ PCoA-2
                   +----+          +----+
            (WLAN) |MAG1|          |MAG2| (WiMAX)
                   +----+          +----+
                      \               /
                       \             /
                  HNP-1 \           / HNP-2
                         \         /
                          \       /
                     +-------+ +-------+
                     | if_1  | | if_2  |
                     |(WLAN) | |(WiMAX)|
                     +-------+-+-------+
                     |     Logical     |
        (LL-ID: ZZZ) |    Interface    | HNP-1::zzz/128
                     +-----------------| HNP-2::zzz/128
                     |       MN        |
                     +-----------------+
 
			</artwork>
		</figure>

		</section>
		
    <section title="Scenario 2 – Only one home network prefix is shown to IP host stack">
		
		<t>
		In above scenario 1, basic PMIPv6 operations can be applied even though a logical interface is used. Multihoming support and inter-technology handoff support is provided without any modification of PMIPv6 operations but for flow mobility, it needs method to transfer a subset of multiple home network prefixes.
		</t>
		
		<t>
		In scenario 1, one application that uses one specific home network prefix cannot utilize the multiplicity of home network prefixes. For on-going session continuity, applications cannot change their home network prefix during packet sending/receiving. Even though a logical interface supports the inter-technology handoff between different network interfaces, applications should use same home network prefix before/after handoff.
		</t>
		
		<t> 
		But, if a logical interface supports the change of network interface and also the change of home network prefix, applications can utilize the multiplicity of home network prefixes. As a same manner of the handling of network interface, only one home network prefix is shown to host IP stack of the mobile node. And the logical interface manages the relation between multiple home network prefixes and the home network prefix that is shown to host IP stack and dynamically update them. In this case, only one logical interface and one home network prefix is shown to host IP stack of the mobile node.
		</t>
		
		<t>
		Figure 2 shows this case. As shown in Figure 2, if the LMA allocates two home network prefixes HNP-1, HNP-2 to the mobile node, only one home network prefix is shown to IP host stack of the mobile node. As a result of receiving single home network prefix in IP host stack, one IPv6 addresses HNP-1::zzz/128 is generated.
		</t>
 	
		<!-- Figure 2 -->
		<figure anchor='hnpsce-2' title="Only one HNP is shown to IP host stack">
			<preamble></preamble>
			<artwork>

                                    LMA's Binding Table
                                    +================================+
                           +----+   | HNP   MN-ID  CoA   ATT   LL-ID |
                           |LMA |   +================================+
                           +----+   | HNP-1  MN-1  PCoA-1  5    ZZZ  |
                            //\\    | HNP-2  MN-1  PCoA-2  4    ZZZ  |
                 +---------//--\\-----------+
                (         //    \\           )
                (        //      \\          )
                 +------//--------\\--------+
                       //          \\
               PCoA-1 //            \\ PCoA-2
                   +----+          +----+
            (WLAN) |MAG1|          |MAG2| (WiMAX)
                   +----+          +----+
                      \               /
                       \             /
                  HNP-1 \           / HNP-2
                         \         /
                          \       /
                     +-------+ +-------+
                     | if_1  | | if_2  |
                     |(WLAN) | |(WiMAX)|
                     +-------+-+-------+
                     |     Logical     |
        (LL-ID: ZZZ) |    Interface    | 
                     +-----------------| HNP-1::zzz/128
                     |       MN        |
                     +-----------------+
 
			</artwork>
		</figure>

		</section>
    </section>


    <!--section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>This template was derived from an initial version written by Pekka
      Savola and contributed by him to the xml2rfc project.</t>

      <t>This document is part of a plan to make xml2rfc indispensable <xref
      target="DOMINATION"></xref>.</t>
    </section-->

    <!-- Possibly a 'Contributors' section ... -->

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>
	  TBD.
	  </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>This document has no actions for IANA.</t>
    </section>

  </middle>

  <!--  *****BACK MATTER ***** -->

  <back>
    <!-- References split into informative and normative -->

    <!-- There are 2 ways to insert reference entries from the citation libraries:
     1. define an ENTITY at the top, and use "ampersand character"RFC2629; here (as shown)
     2. simply use a PI "less than character"?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119.xml"?> here
        (for I-Ds: include="reference.I-D.narten-iana-considerations-rfc2434bis.xml")

     Both are cited textually in the same manner: by using xref elements.
     If you use the PI option, xml2rfc will, by default, try to find included files in the same
     directory as the including file. You can also define the XML_LIBRARY environment variable
     with a value containing a set of directories to search.  These can be either in the local
     filing system or remote ones accessed by http (http://domain/dir/... ).-->

    <references title="Normative References">
		&RFC2119;
		&RFC5213;
	</references>

    <references title="Informative References">
     <!-- A reference written by by an organization not a person. -->

		<reference anchor="I-D.melia-netext-logical-interface-support-00">
		   <front>
			   <title>Logical Interface Support for multi-mode IP Hosts, draft-melia-netext-logical-interface-support-00 (work in progress)</title>
			   <author initials="T." surname="Melia" fullname="">
			   <organization/>
			   </author>
			   <author initials="S." surname="Gundavelli" fullname="">
			   <organization/>
   			   </author>
			   <date month="July" year="2010"/>
		   </front>
		</reference>
    </references>



  </back>
</rfc>
