<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
	<!ENTITY RFC3775 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3775.xml">
	<!ENTITY RFC3344 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3344.xml">
	<!ENTITY RFC3963 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3963.xml">
	<!ENTITY RFC5213 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5213.xml">
]>

<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<!-- used by XSLT processors -->
<!-- For a complete list and description of processing instructions (PIs), 
     please see http://xml.resource.org/authoring/README.html. -->
<!-- Below are generally applicable Processing Instructions (PIs) that most I-Ds might want to use.
     (Here they are set differently than their defaults in xml2rfc v1.32) -->
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<!-- give errors regarding ID-nits and DTD validation -->
<!-- control the table of contents (ToC) -->
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<!-- generate a ToC -->
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<!-- the number of levels of subsections in ToC. default: 3 -->
<!-- control references -->
<?rfc symrefs="no"?>
<!-- use symbolic references tags, i.e, [RFC2119] instead of [1] -->
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<!-- sort the reference entries alphabetically -->
<!-- control vertical white space 
     (using these PIs as follows is recommended by the RFC Editor) -->
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<!-- do not start each main section on a new page -->
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<!-- keep one blank line between list items -->
<!-- end of list of popular I-D processing instructions -->

<rfc category="info" docName="draft-hong-netext-hybrid-hnp-01" ipr="trust200902">

  <!-- ***** FRONT MATTER ***** -->

  <front>
    <!-- The abbreviated title is used in the page header - it is only necessary if the 
         full title is longer than 39 characters -->

    <title abbrev="Hybrid Home Network Prefix">
	Hybrid home network prefix for multihoming in PMIPv6
	</title>

    <!-- add 'role="editor"' below for the editors if appropriate -->

    <!-- Another author who claims to be an editor -->

    <author fullname="Yong-Geun Hong" initials="Y.G.Hong" role=""
            surname="Hong">
      <organization>ETRI</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>161 Gajeong-Dong Yuseung-Gu</street>

          <!-- Reorder these if your country does things differently -->

          <city>Daejeon</city>

          <region></region>

          <code>305-700</code>

          <country>Korea</country>
        </postal>

        <phone>+82 42 860 6557</phone>

        <email>yonggeun.hong@gmail.com</email>

        <!-- uri and facsimile elements may also be added -->
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Joo-Sang Youn" initials="J.S.Youn" role=""
            surname="Youn">
      <organization>DONG-EUI Univ.</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>

          <!-- Reorder these if your country does things differently -->

          <city>Busan</city>

          <region></region>

          <code></code>

          <country>Korea</country>
        </postal>

        <phone>+82 51 890 1993</phone>

        <email>joosang.youn@gmail.com</email>

        <!-- uri and facsimile elements may also be added -->
      </address>
    </author>

    <date month="March" year="2010" />

    <!-- If the month and year are both specified and are the current ones, xml2rfc will fill 
         in the current day for you. If only the current year is specified, xml2rfc will fill 
	 in the current day and month for you. If the year is not the current one, it is 
	 necessary to specify at least a month (xml2rfc assumes day="1" if not specified for the 
	 purpose of calculating the expiry date).  With drafts it is normally sufficient to 
	 specify just the year. -->

    <!-- Meta-data Declarations -->

    <area>General</area>

    <workgroup>Network Working Group</workgroup>

    <!-- WG name at the upperleft corner of the doc,
         IETF is fine for individual submissions.  
	 If this element is not present, the default is "Network Working Group",
         which is used by the RFC Editor as a nod to the history of the IETF. -->

    <keyword>Internet Draft</keyword>

    <!-- Keywords will be incorporated into HTML output
         files in a meta tag but they have no effect on text or nroff
         output. If you submit your draft to the RFC Editor, the
         keywords will be used for the search engine. -->

    <abstract>
      <t>
	  Proxy Mobile IPv6 (PMIPv6) supports multihoming where a mobile node can connect to a PMIPv6 domain through multiple interfaces for simultaneous access. However, for an inter-technology handoff, PMIPv6 does not allow simultaneous access since all the home network prefixes associated with one interface are associated with another interface of a mobile node. In this document, we propose a hybrid home network prefix assignment (HHNPA) scheme where both the static prefix model and the dynamic prefix model are used for simultaneous access. The static prefix model is used within the general PMIPv6 domain. On the other hand, the dynamic prefix model is employed for inter-technology handoff. That is, for IP session continuity during inter-technology handoff, a dynamic prefix model is used on both interfaces.
	  </t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
	<!-- Section 1 -->
    <section title="Introduction">
		<t>
		Mobile IPv6 [RFC3775]<xref target="RFC3775"/> and Mobile IPv4 [RFC3344]<xref target="RFC3344"/> are host based IP mobility support protocols. On the other hand, Proxy Mobile IPv6 (PMIPv6) [RFC5213]<xref target="RFC5213"/> is a network based IP mobility support protocol, which does not require any modifications to mobile nodes(MNs). PMIPv6 makes it possible to support mobility for IPv6 nodes without an involvement of a MN. That is, on behalf of MNs, a mobile access gateway (MAG) in the network performs the signaling for mobility management with a local mobility anchor (LMA).
		</t>

		<t>
		PMIPv6 defines basic operations for registration, deregistration, and tunnel management. However, it does not define protocol operations for supporting seamless handover for a MN with multiple network interfaces (i.e., inter-technology handoff) <xref target="I-D.devarapalli-netext-multi-interface-support-00"/>. While PMIPv6 itself supports handover across different interfaces and access types, there are several issues for efficient inter-technology handoff, e.g., how to set interface identifier, how to use the same address on multiple interfaces, how to select an access technology, and how to detect and manage a handover event <xref target="I-D.krishnan-netext-intertech-ps"/>. 
		</t>

		<t>
		PMIPv6 basically support multihoming where a MN can connect to a PMIPv6 domain through multiple interfaces for simultaneous access and inter-technology handoff between different multiple interfaces. If a MN with multiple interfaces connects to a PMIPv6 domain over multiple access networks, the LMA will allocate a unique set of home network prefixes (HNPs) for each of the connected interfaces. However, when the MN performs an inter-technology handoff, the LMA will newly assign all the home network prefixes, which are associated with the first interface, to the second interface. Consequently, the existing mobility sessions with the second interface will be disrupted. Fundamentally, this problem has been caused due to the fact that each of the attached interfaces must be assigned one or more unique prefixes in PMIPv6. Therefore, to solve this problem, we propose a hybrid home network prefix assignment (HHNPA) scheme where both the static prefix model and the dynamic prefix model are employed and dynamically selected. That is, for IP session continuity after inter-technology handoff, a dynamic home network prefix is used on both interfaces. 
		</t>

      <!--section title="Requirements Language">
        <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
        "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
        document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
        target="RFC2119">RFC 2119</xref>.</t>
      </section-->
    </section>

	<!-- Section 2 -->
	<section title="Problem statement of multihoming support in PMIPv6">
		<t>
		To support multiple mobility sessions for a single MN with multiple interfaces, PMIPv6 creates mobility sessions per interface and each mobility session should be managed as a separate binding cache (BC) entry. Note that although the LMA can allocate more than one home network prefix to an interface, all these prefixes are managed by one mobility session. The LMA allows a handoff between two different interfaces of a MN.  In such a scenario, all the home network prefixes associated with one interface will be associated with another interface of the MN.  The decisions on when to create a new mobility session and when to update an existing mobility session are based on the handover hint included in the Proxy Binding Update message.
		</t>

		<t>
		Basic operations for multiple interfaces in PMIPv6 are as follows. First of all, the MAG decides whether to inform the LMA of the attachment of the second interface (or an inter-technology handoff), and then the MAG sends a Proxy Binding Update (PBU) message. When the LMA receives the PBU message, it verifies the request message. If the PBU message includes a handoff indicator flag of 1 (i.e., initial attachment), the LMA allocates a new mobility session for second interface and thus the LMA has multiple Binding Cache entries. On the other hand, if the PBU message has a handoff indicator flag of 2 (i.e., inter-technology handoff), all the home network prefixes associated with the first interface will be associated with the second interface. Figures 1 and 2 describe the operations of two cases: initial attachment and inter-technology handoff. In particular, as shown in Figure 2, for inter-technology handoff, HNP_2 is overwritten with HNP_1 and then the existing mobility session 1 is removed from the binding cache entry at the LMA. 
		</t>

		<!-- Figure 1 -->
		<figure anchor='hhnpa-1' title="Multihoming in PMIPv6 : Initial attachment">
			<preamble></preamble>
			<artwork>

               +----+                
               |LMA |                  LMA BC entry   
               +----+                 (before assigning
                //\\                   multiple mobility sessions)
     +---------//--\\-------------+    -----------------                    
    (         //    \\  PMIPv6     )   MN:if_1 [HNP_1] --> MAG1    
    (        //      \\  domain    )
     +------//--------\\----------+    
           //          \\             
          //            \\             LMA BC entry  
       +----+           +----+        (after assigning     
       |MAG1|           |MAG2|         multiple mobility sessions)  
       +----+           +----+         -----------------   
         |                |            MN:if_1 [HNP_1] --> MAG1  
         |                |            MN:if_2 [HNP_2] --> MAG2
   HNP_1 | if_1      if_2 | HNP_2      
         +------[MN]------+

			</artwork>
		</figure>

		<!-- Figure 2 -->
		<figure anchor='hhnpa-2' title="Multihoming in PMIPv6 : Inter-technology handoff">
			<preamble></preamble>
			<artwork>

               +----+                
               |LMA |                  LMA BC entry   
               +----+                 (before inter-technology
                //\\                   handoff)
     +---------//--\\-------------+    -----------------                    
    (         //    \\  PMIPv6     )   MN:if_1 [HNP_1] --> MAG1    
    (        //      \\  domain    )   MN:if_2 [HNP_2] --> MAG2
     +------//--------\\----------+    
           //          \\             
          //            \\             LMA BC entry  
       +----+           +----+        (after inter-technology     
       |MAG1|           |MAG2|         handoff)  
       +----+           +----+         -----------------   
         |                |             
         |                |            MN:if_2 [HNP_1] --> MAG2
   HNP_1 | if_1      if_2 | HNP_2      
         +------[MN]------+
	
			</artwork>
		</figure>

		<t>
		These multihoming operations in PMIPv6 have the following problems.
		</t>

		<t>
		Fist, since the LMA assigns the same home network prefix to the second interface after inter-technology handoff and updates the existing Binding Cache entry, the previous binding information of the second interface can be removed. Therefore, the existing flows through the second interface may be disrupted  <xref target="I-D.devarapalli-netext-multi-interface-support-00"/>.
		</t>

		<t>
		In addition, since there is no way to enable flow-specific handoffs, compelled handoff of unwanted IP flows can be performed due to inter-technology handoff. The existing multihoming operations have drawbacks in terms of implementation.
		</t>

		<t>
		As mentioned before, the MAG should set the handoff indicator flag (e.g., 1 for initial attachment or 2 for inter-technology handoff). However, the MAG does not have sufficient information on multihoming support and thus it is not an easy task to distinguish initial attachment and interface handoff <xref target="I-D.krishnan-netext-intertech-ps"/>.
		</t>

		<t>
		Moreover, all home network prefixes are determined when the first mobility session is generated for a corresponding interface. Therefore, there is no way to add or delete a new home network prefix <xref target="I-D.jeyatharan-netext-multihoming-ps"/>. To address these issues, we propose a hybrid home network prefix assignment scheme in the next section.
		</t>

	</section>


	<!-- Section 3 -->
    <section title="Hybrid home network prefix assignment">
        <t>
		In terms of home network prefix allocation in PMIPv6, the per-MN prefix model is mandatory whereas the shared prefix model is not supported. In the per-MN prefix model, home network prefixes are assigned to a MN and these prefixes are exclusively used by the MN; no other MNs share the home network prefix. Note that all assigned prefixes are unique and they are parts of one mobility session.  If the MN simultaneously attaches to a PMIPv6 domain through multiple interfaces, each of the attached interfaces must be assigned one or more unique prefixes. Therefore, when performing an inter-technology handoff based on the per-MN prefix model, simultaneous access to the PMIPv6 domain is not allowed. If it is able to separate prefixes into the purpose of inter-technology handoff and the purpose of simultaneous access, PMIPv6 may support both interface handoff and simultaneous access at the same time. Based on this idea, we propose a hybrid home network prefix assignment (HHNPA) scheme to use both the static and dynamic home network prefix models. 
		</t>

		<t>		
		Figure 3 introduces the concept of the HHNPA scheme where the LMA divides home network prefixes into a static home network prefix and a dynamic home network prefix. The static home network prefix (based on the per-MN prefix model) is used within the PMIPv6 domain. On the other hand, the dynamic home network prefix is employed for inter-technology handoffs. 
		</t>

		<!-- Figure 3 -->
		<figure anchor='hhnpa-3' title="Prefix model in HHNPA">
			<preamble></preamble>
			<artwork>

         +--------------------------------+           
         |                                |                  
         |               +----------------+---------------+
         |               |                |               |
         |     HNP_1     |      HNP_2     |     HNP_3     |
         |(static prefix)|(dynamic prefix)|(static prefix)| 
         |               |                |               | 
         |               +----------------+---------------+
         |                                |       if_2   
         +--------------------------------+   
                if_1          
		
			</artwork>
		</figure>

		<t>
		In the dynamic prefix model, dynamic prefixes are assigned into only one interface and they are switchable between interfaces. Dynamic prefixes are not used multiple interfaces simultaneously. In contrast to dynamic prefixes, static prefixes cannot be switchable between interfaces. As shown in Figure 4, HNP_1 is static prefix and it is used at only if_1. HNP_3 is static prefix and it is used at only if_2. HNP_2 is dynamic prefix and it can be used both if_1 and if_2. In this figure, HNP_1 and HNP_3 are used for simultaneous access and HNP_2 is used for inter-technology handoff. 
		</t>

		<!-- Figure 4 -->
		<figure anchor='hhnpa-4' title="Usage scenario of HHNPA scheme">
			<preamble></preamble>
			<artwork><![CDATA[

                           +----+                
                           |LMA |      
                           +----+      
                            //\\                
                 +---------//--\\-------------+ 
                (         //    \\  PMIPv6     )
                (        //      \\  domain    )
                 +------//--------\\----------+    
                       //          \\             
                      //            \\          
                  +----+           +----+      
                  |MAG1|<--HNP_2-->|MAG2|      
                  +----+           +----+      
                    |                |         
                    |                |         
              HNP_1 | if_1      if_2 | HNP_3      
                    +------[MN]------+
					
			]]></artwork>
		</figure>

		<t>
		Figure 5 describes the message flow in the HHNPA scheme. At the starting time, a MN is attached the PMIPv6 domain through MAG_1 using interface 1. After that, the MN is attached the PMIPv6 domain through MAG_2 using interface 2. When second interface of the MN is attached to the LMA, the LMA acknowledges that the MN is a multiple interfaces node and prepares to allocate a dynamic prefix. The LMA sends two PBA messages to MAG_1 and MAG_2. The two PBA messages destined to MAG_1 and MAG_2 includes a home network prefix option (HNP_2: dynamic prefix).
		</t>

		<!-- Figure 5 -->
		<figure anchor='hhnpa-5' title="Message flow of HHNPA scheme">
			<preamble></preamble>
			<artwork><![CDATA[
   
      +------+                +-----+     +-----+                +-----+
      |  MN  |                |MAG_1|     |MAG_2|                | LMA |
      +------+                +-----+     +-----+                +-----+
       |   |                     |           |                      |
       |   |MN[if_1] attach  MAG_1           |                      |
       |   |-------------------->|         (MN-ID, if_1, ...)       |
       |   |                     |---------------PBU--------------->|
       |   |                     |           |                      |
       |   |                     |(MN-ID, if_1, HNP_1:static prefix)|
       |   |                     |<--------------PBA----------------|
       |   |                     |           |                      |
       |   |                     |========= Bi-Dir Tunnel ==========|
       |   |<---RtAdv[HNP_1]-----|           |                      |
       |   |                     |<----------data to HNP_1----------|
       |   |<---data to HNP_1----|                                  |
       |   |                     |           |                      |
       |- - - MN[if_2] attach MAG_2--------->|   (MN-ID, if_2, ...) |
       |   |                     |           |----------PBU-------->|
       |   |                     |           |                      |
       |   |                     |   (MN-ID, if_2, HNP_3:static prefix)
       |   |                     |           |<--------PBA----------|
       |   |                     |           |                      |
       |   |                     |           |===== Bi-Dir Tunnel===|		
       |<-------RtAdv[HNP_3]-----------------|                      |
       |   |                     |           |                      |
       |   |                     |  (MN-ID, if_2, HNP_2:dynamic prefix)
       |   |                     |           |<-------*PBA*---------|
       |<-------RtAdv[HNP_2]-----------------|                      |
       |   |                     |           |                      |
       |   |                     |  (MN-ID, if_1, HNP_2:dynamic prefix)
       |   |                     |<--------------*PBA*--------------|
       |   |<---RtAdv[HNP_2]-----|           |                      |
       |   |                     |           |<----data to HNP3-----|
       |   |<---data to HNP3-----------------|                      |
       |   |                     |           |                      |
    [if_2][if_1]

			]]></artwork>
		</figure>

		<t>
		After the completion of attachment of the MN through two interfaces, the operations of interface handoff of the MN are as depicted in Figure 6 and Figure 7. As shown in Figure 6, the dynamic prefix HNP_2 is assigned into interface 1. If the MN wants inter-technology handoff, the MN gives some hint of inter-technology handoff to the MAG_2. The MAG_2 which receives hint of inter-technology handoff sends a PBU message with a handoff indicator value of 2 to the LMA. The LMA which receives this PBU message updates the Binding Cache entry filed which is related to dynamic prefix HNP_2. The updated fields of Binding Cache entry are interface and tunnel information. After the completion of updating of Binding Cache entry, the LMA sends data which is relation to HNP_2 to the MAG_2.
		</t>

		<!-- Figure 6 -->
		<figure anchor='hhnpa-6' title="Usage scenario of dynamic prefix in HHNPA scheme">
			<preamble></preamble>
			<artwork>

               +----+                
               |LMA |                  LMA BC entry   
               +----+                 (before inter-handoff)
                //\\                   -----------------                    
     +---------//--\\-------------+    MN:if_1 [HNP_1] --> MAG1    
    (         //    \\  PMIPv6     )   MN:if_2 [HNP_3] --> MAG2    
    (        //      \\  domain    )   MN:if_1 [HNP_2] --> MAG1
     +------//--------\\----------+    
           //          \\             
          //            \\             LMA BC entry  
       +----+           +----+        (after inter-handoff)  
       |MAG1|-->HNP_2-->|MAG2|         -----------------   
       +----+           +----+         MN:if_1 [HNP_1] --> MAG1  
         |                |            MN:if_2 [HNP_3] --> MAG2
         |                |            MN:if_2 [HNP_2] --> MAG2
   HNP_1 | if_1      if_2 | HNP_3      
         +------[MN]------+

			</artwork>
		</figure>

		<t>
		The HHNPA scheme has advantages of deciding a handoff indication flag. After the LMA assigns static and dynamic home network prefixes to MAGs, if MAG_2 receives handoff hint, MAG_2 checks the existence of the MN_identifier. If the MN_identifier related to the dynamic prefix HNP_2 is exist, the MAG_2 acknowledges that there is a mobility session of inter-technology handoff. So, the MAG_2 can easily determine the value of handoff indication. This operation is depicted in Figure 7.
		</t>

		<!-- Figure 7 -->
		<figure anchor='hhnpa-7' title="Setting of handoff indicator flag in HHNPA scheme">
			<preamble></preamble>
			<artwork>

               +----+                
               |LMA |                  LMA BC entry   
               +----+                 (before inter-handoff)
                //\\                   -----------------                    
     +---------//--\\-------------+    MN:if_1 [HNP_1] --> MAG1    
    (         //    \\  PMIPv6     )   MN:if_2 [HNP_3] --> MAG2    
    (        //      \\  domain    )   MN:if_1 [HNP_2] --> MAG1
     +------//--------\\----------+    
           //          \\             
          //            \\             Routing table in MAG1  
       +----+           +----+         -----------------   
       |MAG1|-->HNP_2-->|MAG2|         HNP_1, HNP_2(dynamic) -> MN:if_1
       +----+           +----+         
         |                |            Routing table in MAG1  
         |                |            -----------------
   HNP_1 | if_1      if_2 | HNP_3      HNP_3, HNP_2(dynamic) -> MN:if_2
         +------[MN]------+

			</artwork>
		</figure>
    </section>


    <!--section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>This template was derived from an initial version written by Pekka
      Savola and contributed by him to the xml2rfc project.</t>

      <t>This document is part of a plan to make xml2rfc indispensable <xref
      target="DOMINATION"></xref>.</t>
    </section-->

    <!-- Possibly a 'Contributors' section ... -->

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>
	  TBD.
	  </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>This document has no actions for IANA.</t>
    </section>

  </middle>

  <!--  *****BACK MATTER ***** -->

  <back>
    <!-- References split into informative and normative -->

    <!-- There are 2 ways to insert reference entries from the citation libraries:
     1. define an ENTITY at the top, and use "ampersand character"RFC2629; here (as shown)
     2. simply use a PI "less than character"?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119.xml"?> here
        (for I-Ds: include="reference.I-D.narten-iana-considerations-rfc2434bis.xml")

     Both are cited textually in the same manner: by using xref elements.
     If you use the PI option, xml2rfc will, by default, try to find included files in the same
     directory as the including file. You can also define the XML_LIBRARY environment variable
     with a value containing a set of directories to search.  These can be either in the local
     filing system or remote ones accessed by http (http://domain/dir/... ).-->

    <references title="Normative References">
		&RFC3775;
		&RFC3344;
 		&RFC3963;
		&RFC5213;
	</references>

    <references title="Informative References">
     <!-- A reference written by by an organization not a person. -->

		<reference anchor="I-D.devarapalli-netext-multi-interface-support-00">
		   <front>
			   <title>Multiple Interface Support with Proxy Mobile IPv6, draft-devarapalli-netext-multi-interface-support-00 </title>
			   <author initials="V." surname="Devarapalli" fullname="">
			   <organization/>
			   </author>
			   <author initials="N." surname="Kant" fullname="">
			   <organization/>
   			   </author>
			   <author initials="H." surname="Lim" fullname="">
			   <organization/>
			   </author>
			   <author initials="C." surname="Vogt" fullname="">
			   <organization/>
			   </author>

			   <date month="March" year="2009"/>
		   </front>
		</reference>

		<reference anchor="I-D.krishnan-netext-intertech-ps">
		   <front>
			   <title>Issues with network based inter-technology handovers, draft-krishnan-netext-intertech-ps-02 </title>
			   <author initials="S." surname="Krishnan" fullname="">
			   <organization/>
			   </author>
			   <author initials="H." surname="Yokota" fullname="">
			   <organization/>
   			   </author>
			   <author initials="T." surname="Melia" fullname="">
			   <organization/>
			   </author>
			   <author initials="C." surname="Bernardos" fullname="">
			   <organization/>
			   </author>

			   <date month="July" year="2009"/>
		   </front>
		</reference>

		<reference anchor="I-D.jeyatharan-netext-multihoming-ps">
		   <front>
			   <title>Multihoming Problem Statement in NetLMM, draft-jeyatharan-netext-multihoming-ps-01 </title>
			   <author initials="M." surname="Jeyatharan" fullname="">
			   <organization/>
			   </author>
			   <author initials="C." surname="Ng" fullname="">
			   <organization/>
   			   </author>

			   <date month="March" year="2009"/>
		   </front>
		</reference>

    </references>



  </back>
</rfc>
