<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<!-- Extra statement used by XSLT processors to control the output style. -->
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<rfc category="exp" ipr="trust200902"  
 docName="draft-ietf-marf-reporting-discovery-01" category="std">
	<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
	<?rfc tocompact="yes" ?>
	<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
	<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
	<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
	<front>
		<!-- The abbreviated title is used in the page header - it is only
		 necessary if the full title is longer than 42 characters -->
		<title abbrev="ARF Reporting Discovery">
			A&nbsp;DNS&nbsp;TXT&nbsp;Record&nbsp;for
    		Advertising&nbsp;and&nbsp;Discovering&nbsp;Willingness
			to&nbsp;Provide&nbsp;or&nbsp;Receive&nbsp;ARF&nbsp;Reports
    	</title>
		<!-- add 'role="editor"' below for the editors if appropriate -->
		<author initials="J.D." surname="Falk" fullname="J.D. Falk">
			<organization>Return Path</organization>
			<address>
				<postal>
					<street>100 Mathilda Place, Suite 100</street>
					<city>Sunnyvale</city>
					<region>CA</region>
					<code>94086</code>
					<country>US</country>
				</postal>
				<email>ietf@cybernothing.org</email>
				<uri>http://www.returnpath.net/</uri>
			</address>
		</author>
		<date/>
		<area>Applications</area>
		<workgroup>Mail Abuse Reporting Format WG</workgroup>
		<keyword>Standards Track</keyword>
		<abstract>
			<t>This document defines a method for network operators to
			advertise their willingness to send feedback about received
			email to other parties, and for those other parties to
			advertise their willingness to receive such feedback.</t>
		</abstract>
	</front>
	<middle>
		<section title="Introduction">
			<t> As the spam problem continues to expand and potential
		    solutions evolve, network operators are increasingly
		    exchanging abuse reports among themselves and other
		    parties.  While <xref target="MARF-BASE"/> defines the
			Abuse Reporting Format (ARF) for these reports, it assumes 
			that the operators will use some undefined method to 
			discover each other and enter into any necessary agreements. </t>

			<t> The advertisement method defined in this memo is
			intended to ease the process for potential ARF recipients
			to discover whether a particular ADministrative Management
			Domain (ADMD)
			has the facility and willingness to generate ARF reports, 
			and for ARF generators to discover whether a particular ADMD is
			able and willing (and authorized) to receive ARF reports.</t>
			
			<t> While written primarily for initial discovery and configuration
			of feedback relationships, it is expected that these advertisements
			will also be useful for updating participants when parameters have
			changed. </t>
			
			<t> Further, while this document only defines a DNS TXT record
			to contain these advertisements, other methods may be defined in
			the future. </t>

			<t> This document only defines the process for advertisement
			and discovery of feedback recipients.  Determination of
			when it is appropriate to send feedback or how trust may be
			established between report generators and report consumers 
			is outside the scope of this document.
			It is assumed that best practices will continue to evolve over
			time, and will be codified in future documents. </t>
			
			<t> Similarly, nothing in this draft is intended to preclude other
			methods that a Feedback Generator might use to determine where
			to send a report. For example, if the report were to be keyed off
			of the domain of an email address or a URL inside of the body of
			a message this discovery mechanism may be inappropriate. </t>
		</section>
		
		<section title="Purpose">
			<t> The reports defined in <xref target="MARF-BASE"/> are
			intended to inform mail operators about:
			
			<list style="symbols"><t> email abuse originating from their networks; </t>
					<t> potential issues with the perceived quality of outbound mail, such
				    as email service providers sending mail that attracts the
				    attention of automated abuse detection systems. </t></list>
			
			To support these and other related purposes, this document addresses
			two primary use cases:
			
			<list style="symbols"><t> Any ADMD may advertise its willingness to 
					receive reports from the internet at large,
					given particular criteria included in or
					referenced by the advertisement; </t>

					<t> Any ADMD may advertise their willingness to
					provide reports to the Internet at large,
					given particular criteria included in or
					referenced by the advertisement; </t> </list> </t>

			<t> Further, an ADMD which is generating reports may 
			query the advertisement of an ADMD that wishes to receive
			reports, in order to confirm that an out-of-band request to 
			receive reports is legitimate and/or to determine if any of the
			characteristics of the request have changed. </t>

			<t> This specification inherits from 
			<xref target="MARF-BASE"/> that it is intended
			specifically for communications among providers
			regarding email abuse and related issues, and
			SHOULD NOT be used for other reports unless those
			feedback-types specifically mention this document.  For 
			example, the <xref target="DKIM-REPORTING"/> extension
			includes its own ARF recipient discovery method
			that should not be confused with the method
			defined in this memo. </t>
		</section>
		
		<section title="Requirements">
			<t> The advertisement and discovery process must be easily
			accessible to the software involved in providing email
			service, preferably using concepts and technologies an
			email operator can be assumed to be familiar with.  Thus,
			following the examples of <xref target="DKIM"/> and
			<xref target="DKIM-REPORTING"/>, the advertisement is
			in the form of a <xref target="DNS"/> TXT record.  While
			this may provide challenges for offline processing, this
			is outweighed by the advantages of security and 
			maintainability. </t>

			<t> In order to reflect current usage, advertisements must
			also provide the ability to reference complex "terms of
			service" or other documents outside of the scope of a
			simple discovery method.  This is accomplished through
			the inclusion of a URI. </t>

			<t> And finally, the advertisement must be readable by
			humans (assuming they have access to this RFC) as well
			as software specifically written for the purpose. </t>
		</section>

		<section title="Language">
			<t> This section defines various terms used throughout
			this document. </t>
			<section title="General">
				<t> The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT",
			    "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
			    "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED",
			    "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document
			    are to be interpreted as described in
			    <xref target="KEYWORDS"/>. </t>
			</section>
			<section title="Email Specific">
				<t><xref target="EMAIL-ARCH"/> introduces
			    several terms and concepts that are used
			    in this memo, and thus readers are advised
			    to become familiar with it as well. </t>
			</section>
			<section title="ARF Specific">
				<t><xref target="MARF-BASE"/> introduces terms 
				and concepts that are necessary for a full
				understanding of this memo, and thus readers
				are advised to read it before continuing. </t>
			</section>
		</section>
		
		<section anchor="advertisements" title="Characteristics of a Feedback Reporting Advertisement">
			<t> An advertisement of willingness to generate or receive
				feedback is accomplished by publishing a TXT record in the
				<xref target="DNS"/> using the name '_report' within the given
				DNS domain. </t>
				
			<t> This record will contain a sequence of "tag=value" pairs, separated
				by semicolons.  The tags and possible values are described in the 
				next two sections, followed by the precise ABNF grammar. </t>

			<t> In the case of a feedback consumer, the advertisement should be 
				published in the DNS domain matching the <xref target="DKIM"/>
				'd=' value used on outgoing signatures, and/or in the DNS 
				domain matching the one present in the 
				<xref target="SMTP"/> MAIL commands it issues when sending
				mail, and/or in the DNS domain referenced by the DNS PTR 
				record (sometimes called "reverse DNS") of the IP address of 
				the border MTA used to transfer the message. </t>

			<t> In the case of a feedback generator, to inquire whether or 
				not an ADMD wishes to receive feedback reports, the DNS 
				domain to which the report should be sent is determined 
				(using the <xref target="DKIM"/> d= string) and 
				then a TXT record query to the above name is issued.  For 
				example, if a report generator wishes to generate a report 
				about a message bearing DNS domain ‘example.com’, the 
				generator would issue a TXT record query for 
				`_report.example.com’. </t>

			<t> Feedback generators SHOULD NOT send reports to
				ADMDs that are not in any way responsible for the reported 
				message, for both security and efficiency reasons.  
				Responsibility can be ascertained as described in 
				<xref target="auth-checks"/>, and by applying local policy. </t>
				
			<t> In the case of a feedback generator who wishes to advertise
				that reports are available, the TXT record is placed by the
				DNS domain at which they receive mail.  For example, to
				advertise reports regarding mail received at example.net, the
				advertisement is placed in _report.example.net. </t>
								
			<section anchor="consumer" title="Feedback Consumers">
				<t> A "Feedback Consumer" is an entity which wishes to receive
					feedback.  In most cases, the Feedback Consumer will be within
					the same ADMD as the identifier (domain name or IP address)
					used to determine the source of a message. </t>
					
				<t> The following tags are defined for Feedback Consumers: </t>
				
				<t>
					<list style="hanging">
						<t hangText="r"> the address to which reports should 
							be sent.  Required; there is no default. This
							address MUST be able to respond to an emailed subscription 
							verification request; see Security Considerations below.</t>
						<t hangText="rf"> the format of the report requested; 
							currently only "ARF" (<xref target="MARF-BASE"/>) 
							is supported.  
							Optional; defaults to ARF. </t>
						<t hangText="ri"> requested report interval; may not be 
							supported by all implementors.  Optional; if 
							omitted, all reports may be sent. </t>
						<t hangText="rt"> colon-separated list of ARF
							(<xref target="MARF-BASE"/>) feedback types for 
							which reports are requested. Optional; if omitted, 
							all report types may be sent. </t>
						<t hangText="re"> email address of a person or role 
							account responsible for handling any issues related 
							to receiving reports.  Optional, but SHOULD be 
							defined; defaults to abuse@ the DNS domain. 
							</t>
						<t hangText="rp"> stated policy, as listed below.  
							Optional; defaults to "o". </t>
						<t hangText="ru"> URI for additional contact 
							information.  Optional, but SHOULD be defined; 
							there is no default value. </t>
					</list>
				</t>
				
				<section title="Feedback Consumer Policies">
					<t> Policies are listed in the "rp" tag, described above.
				
				<list style="hanging">
					
					<t hangText="o"> open to reports from all sources.  This
						is the default. </t>
						
					<t hangText="c"> closed; no reports are requested.  This
						option is intended for testing purposes, or for feedback
						arrangements which have been set up using methods
						outside of the scope of this document. </t></list> </t>
				</section>
				
				<section title="Feedback Consumer re= Default">
					<t> As described above, the default re= value is abuse@ the DNS
						domain.  Report Generators are cautioned that re= is the
						address of a responsible person; this address may not be
						equipped to parse ARF reports.  Instead, ARF reports MUST
						only be sent to the address in the r= value. </t>

					<t> Feedback Consumers are similarly cautioned that deciding
						not to publish an advertisement in accordance with this
						specification does not guarantee that all Report Generators
						won't send unsolicited ARF reports to your abuse@ or 
						postmaster@ address.  Thus, all domain owners are encouraged to 
						publish explicit information even in case it happens to agree 
						with the default values: in addition to better clarity, it may 
						also improve caching. </t>
				</section>
			</section>
			
			<section anchor="generator" title="Feedback Generators">
				<t> A "Feedback Generator" is an entity which generates feedback
					reports.  Often, the Feedback Generator is within the same ADMD
					as the mail server which received the message. </t>
					
				<t> The following tags are defined for Feedback Generators: </t>
					
				<t>
					<list style="hanging">
						<t hangText="gf"> the format of reports offered; 
							currently only "ARF" (<xref target="MARF-BASE"/>) 
							is supported.  Optional; defaults to "ARF". </t>
						<t hangText="gt"> colon-separated list of ARF 
							(<xref target="MARF-BASE"/>) feedback types for 
							which reports are available. (Optional; if omitted, 
							any report types may be generated.)</t>
						<t hangText="ge"> email address of a person (or role 
							account) responsible for handling any issues 
							related to receiving reports.  Optional, but SHOULD 
							be defined; defaults to postmaster@ the DNS domain. 
							</t>
						<t hangText="gp"> stated policy, as listed below.  		
							Optional; defaults to "o". </t>
						<t hangText="gu"> URI for additional information.  This
							field SHOULD be defined for a policy of "o" or "c",
							and MUST be defined when the policy is "r".  
							Otherwise, the field is optional; there is no 
							default. </t>
					</list>
				</t>
				
				<section title="Feedback Generator Policies">
					<t> Policies are listed in the "gp" tag, described above. </t>
					<t>
						<list style="hanging">
							<t hangText="o"> open to providing reports to any
								consumer.  This option is the default policy. 
								</t>
							<t hangText="r"> open to providing reports only 
								after the prospective consumer has completed an
								application process, which may be found at the 
								URI defined by the "gu" tag above. </t>
							<t hangText="c"> closed; no reports are available.
								This option is intended for testing purposes, or for 
								feedback arrangements which have been set up using 
								methods outside of the scope of this document. 
								</t>
						</list>
					</t>
				</section>
			</section>
			
			<section title="Combining Generator and Consumer Tags in the Same Record">
				<t> It is common for a Feedback Generator to also act as a Feedback Consumer.
					When this happens, they MAY include both types of tags in the same TXT
					record. </t>
					
				<t> When parsing these records, implementors MUST accept both types of tags 
					in the same record, and MUST NOT expect the tags to appear in any 
					particular order.  Implementors MUST ignore any unfamiliar tags or 
					other unexpected text. </t>
			</section>

			<section title="Note about URIs">
				<t> While this memo assumes that advertisements will
				contain http:// or similar URIs, implementors 
				should be aware that the URI-related fields can 
				carry many different types of data depending on 
				the URI scheme used. For more information, please 
				consult the URI Schemes registry maintained by IANA. </t>
			</section>
			
			<section anchor="format_abnf" title="Formal Definition">
				<t> The formal definition using <xref target="ABNF"/> 
					is TBD. 
				</t>
			</section>
		</section>
		
		<section anchor="examples" title="Example Records for Various Use Cases">
			<t> While (in the author's mind) these examples address many of the
				most common use cases, implementers MUST NOT assume that only
				these configurations will ever be seen on the real live
				internet. </t>
				
			<section title="Example Feedback Consumer Records">
				<t> Perhaps the most common scenario today is where a sender of
					bulk commercial email wishes to receive any complaints about
					messages originating from the servers under their control.  These
					servers are identified by IP address or range.  The PTR record for
					one of the IP addresses in question is "outmail5.example.com", so
					the advertisement could be: </t>
					
				<t> _report.outmail5.example.com TXT "r=complaints@example.com; rf=ARF; 	
					rt=abuse,fraud,virus,other; re=isprelations@example.com;" </t>
				
				<t> This would need to be repeated for each PTR record, perhaps 
					outmail1.example.com through outmail7.example.com.  (NOTE: per
					<xref target="DNS"/>, you cannot have both PTR and TXT 
					associated with the same DNS record.  Instead, the TXT record is
					associated with the _destination_ of the PTR pointer.)</t>
					
				<t> Or, if they sign all of their outbound mail with a 
					<xref target="DKIM"/> d= string of "example.com", they could place the same 
					advertisement in a TXT record at _report.example.com. </t>
					
				<t> example.com TXT "r=complaints@example.com; rf=ARF; 
					rt=abuse,fraud,virus,other; re=isprelations@example.com;" </t>
					
				<t> Another common scenario is of a mailbox or access provider
					who wishes to receive complaints about mail sent by their
					users. That record would be very similar, and would again be
					applied to PTR and/or d= domains: </t>
					
				<t> example.com TXT "r=abuse@example.net; rf=ARF; 
					rt=abuse,fraud,virus; re=postmaster@example.net;" </t>
			</section>
			
			<section title="Example Feedback Generator Records">
				<t> The most common scenario today is where a large mailbox
					provider offers feedback to qualified Feedback Consumers
					who have filled out an application form.  While the full
					application process cannot be adequately represented
					inside of a single DNS record, the "gp" and "gu" fields
					permit advertisement of this policy: </t>
					
				<t> example.net TXT "gf=ARF; gt=abuse; ge=postmaster@example.net; 
					gp=r; gu=http://postmaster.example.net/fbl/" </t>
					
				<t> However, it is rare for a Feedback Generator -- most often a
					mailbox provider or similar service -- to not also be
					a Feedback Consumer.  If they wish to place an advertisement
					using the PTR method, there is usually no conflict.  However,
					if their outbound mail is signed with <xref target="DKIM"/>
					and the d= value is the same domain at which they receive mail,
					then the advertisement will need to contain both generator
					and consumer tags: </t>
					
				<t> example.net TXT "gf=ARF; gt=abuse; ge=postmaster@example.net;
					gp=r; gu=http://postmaster.example.net/fbl/"; rf=ARF;
					r=abuse+arf@example.net; rt=abuse,fraud,other;
					re=postmaster@example.net;" </t>
					
				<t> Or, they MAY split the Generator and Consumer tags into
					separate TXT records under the same domain. </t>
									
				<t> Were a Feedback Generator to only offer authentication
					results, they could advertise thusly: </t>
					
				<t> "gf=ARF; gt=auth; ge=postmaster@example.net; gp=o;
					gu=http://postmaster.example.net/auth/" </t>
			</section>
								
		</section>
		
		<section anchor="auth-checks" title="Authentication of Reported Message">
			<t><xref target="AUTH-METHODS"/> and its extensions define a 
			number of authentication methods that allow the recipient of a message
			to determine which ADMD is responsible for the message.  A Report
			Generator MUST utilize one or more of these methods to ensure that
			reports are being sent to a Report Consumer within the correct ADMD,
			and furthermore it is RECOMMENDED that the Report Consumer utilize
			these same methods to ensure that a message reported to them was 
			indeed sent by who they think it was sent by.  For example:</t>
			
			<section title="DKIM signatures">
				<t> Any valid DKIM signature in the reported message provides a
					domain name, either the signature "d" tag, or the domain-part of
					the signature "i" tag.</t>
			</section>
			<section title="SPF authorized sender">
				<t> When the check_host() function described in <xref target="SPF"/>
					results in a "pass" for the envelope sender, the domain part of
					that address.  Otherwise, if a "pass" is obtained for the
					HELO/EHLO name, that domain name is used.</t>
			</section>
		</section>
		<section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
			<t> This memo will create an IANA registry of MARF discovery record
				tags and their legal values and defining documents; this section
				is yet to be written. </t>
		</section>
		<section anchor="security" title="Security Considerations">
			<t> The following security considerations apply when
		    generating or processing a feedback report: </t>
			<section anchor="sc-inherited" title="Inherited from MARF-BASE">
				<t> All of the Security Considerations from
			    <xref target="MARF-BASE"/> are inherited here. </t>
			</section>
			<section title="These Need Fleshing Out">
				<t> Subscription verification requests. </t>
				
				<t> [DNSSEC] SHOULD be used to ensure authenticity of all DNS
					requests and replies. </t>
					
				<t> Reference the data redaction discussion that will appear in
					an updated dkim-reporting draft soon. </t>
					
				<t> Feedback destination mailboxes are potentially sinks for
					private information, and should be secured accordingly.  The
					precise methods of securing mailbox files are outside of the
					scope of this document. </t>
					
				<t> Additional security considerations are likely, and TBD. </t>
			</section>
			<section title="Privacy considerations">
				<t> [Should these be moved to a BCP?] </t>
				
				<t> When recipients report received messages as spam, they deny
					any involvement with whoever may turn out to be responsible of
					authoring or forwarding that mail.  Users submit that spam to
					the community at large in the hope that a corrective action may
					be taken.  In that respect, the only privacy issue is to avoid to
					further divulge the email addresses of reporting users, or let
					them be profiled.  Suitably redacted email addresses are an
					acceptable remedy.  Responsible senders are advised to include
					opaque tokens as necessary, in order to reconstruct needed data.</t>
					
				<t> However, users may also err.  Unwanted smear may result in
					case a message containing confidential data is erroneously
					reported as spam.  Authentication and policies are concerned with
					avoiding such circumstances.  Recipients of special addresses
					at an ADMD that handled a given message could have intercepted the
					message when they signed or relayed it, if they wanted to,
					therefore it is less of a concern to forward abuse reports there.</t>
					
				<t> Contact addresses for a given domain name should bear such
					name as their domain parts.  Generators may treat non-conforming
					addresses with great suspicion, possibly avoiding to relay to them.</t>
			</section>
		</section>
		<section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">
			<t> This document was heavily influenced by discussions on the
			topic within the IRTF Anti-Spam Research Group, collected at
			<xref target="ASRG-ABUSE"/>. </t>
		</section>
		<section anchor="Contributors" title="Contributors">
			<t> Many thanks to Murray Kucherawy, Alessandro Vesely, Todd
				Herr, Jacob Rideout, Derek Diget, Yakov Shafranovitch,
				Barry Leiba, Tim Draegen, Michael Adkins, and Tanguy Ortolo
				for their suggestions and contributions. </t>
		</section>
	</middle>
	<back>
		<references title="Normative References">
			<reference anchor="ABNF">
				<front>
					<title> Augmented BNF for Syntax
				        Specifications: ABNF </title>
					<author initials="D." surname="Crocker" fullname="D. Crocker">
						<organization>
						Brandenburg InternetWorking
					</organization>
					</author>
					<author initials="P." surname="Overell" fullname="P. Overell">
						<organization>
						THUS plc.
					</organization>
					</author>
					<date month="January" year="2008"/>
				</front>
				<seriesInfo name="RFC" value="5234"/>
			</reference>
			<reference anchor="KEYWORDS">
				<front>
					<title> Key words for use in RFCs to Indicate
				        Requirement Levels </title>
					<author initials="S." surname="Bradner" fullname="S. Bradner">
						<organization>
						Harvard University
					</organization>
					</author>
					<date month="March" year="1997"/>
				</front>
				<seriesInfo name="RFC" value="2119"/>
			</reference>
			<reference anchor="SMTP">
				<front>
					<title> Simple Mail Transfer Protocol </title>
					<author initials="J." surname="Klensin" fullname="J. Klensin (editor)">
						<organization/>
					</author>
					<date month="October" year="2008"/>
				</front>
				<seriesInfo name="RFC" value="5321"/>
			</reference>
			<reference anchor="MARF-BASE">
				<front>
					<title> An Extensible Format for Email Feedback Reports </title>
					<author initials="Y." surname="Shafranovich" fullname="Y. Shafranovich">
						<organization>
						ShafTek Enterprises
					</organization>
					</author>
					<author initials="J." surname="Levine" fullname="J. Levine">
						<organization>
						Domain Assurance Council
					</organization>
					</author>
					<author initials="M." surname="Kucherawy" fullname="M. Kucherawy">
						<organization>
						Cloudmark
					</organization>
					</author>
					<date month="April" year="2010"/>
				</front>
				<seriesInfo name="RFC" value="5965"/>
			</reference>
			<reference anchor="DNS">
				<front>
					<title> Domain Names -- Implementation
				        and Specification </title>
					<author initials="P." surname="Mockapetris" fullname="P. Mockapetris">
						<organization>
						ISI
					</organization>
					</author>
					<date month="November" year="1987"/>
				</front>
				<seriesInfo name="RFC" value="1035"/>
			</reference>
			<reference anchor="AUTH-METHODS">
				<front>
					<title>Message Header Field for Indicating Message Authentication Status</title>
					<author initials="M." surname="Kucherawy" fullname="M. Kucherawy">
						<organization/>
					</author>
					<date year="2009" month="April"/>
					<abstract>
						<t> This memo defines a new header field for use with electronic mail messages 
							to indicate the results of message authentication efforts.  Any 
							receiver-side software, such as mail filters or Mail User Agents (MUAs), may 
							use this message header field to relay that information in a convenient way 
							to users or to make sorting and filtering decisions. [STANDARDS TRACK]</t>
					</abstract>
				</front>
				<seriesInfo name="RFC" value="5451"/>
				<format type="TXT" octets="97404" target="http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc5451.txt"/>
			</reference>
			<reference anchor="MAILBOX-NAMES">
				<front>
					<title abbrev="Mailbox Names">MAILBOX NAMES FOR COMMON SERVICES, ROLES AND FUNCTIONS</title>
					<author initials="D." surname="Crocker" fullname="Dave Crocker">
						<organization>Internet Mail Consortium</organization>
						<address>
							<postal>
								<street>127 Segre Ave.</street>
								<street>Santa Cruz</street>
								<country>CA</country>
							</postal>
							<phone>+1 408 246 8253</phone>
							<email>dcrocker@imc.org</email>
						</address>
					</author>
					<date year="1997" month="May"/>
					<area>Applications</area>
					<keyword>mail</keyword>
				</front>
				<seriesInfo name="RFC" value="2142"/>
				<format type="TXT" octets="12195" target="http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc2142.txt"/>
				<format type="HTML" octets="29012" target="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/html/rfc2142.html"/>
				<format type="XML" octets="16712" target="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/xml/rfc2142.xml"/>
			</reference>
			<reference anchor="SPF">
				<front>
					<title>Sender Policy Framework (SPF) for Authorizing Use of Domains in E-Mail, Version 1</title>
					<author initials="M." surname="Wong" fullname="M. Wong">
						<organization/>
					</author>
					<author initials="W." surname="Schlitt" fullname="W. Schlitt">
						<organization/>
					</author>
					<date year="2006" month="April"/>
				</front>
				<seriesInfo name="RFC" value="4408"/>
				<format type="TXT" octets="105009" target="http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc4408.txt"/>
			</reference>
		</references>
		<references title="Informative References">
			<reference anchor="ASRG-ABUSE">
				<front>
					<title> Abuse Reporting Standards Subgroup
				        of the ASRG </title>
					<author>
						<organization>
						Anti-Spam Research Group (ASRG)
					        of the Internet Research
						Task Force (IRTF)
					</organization>
					</author>
					<date month="May" year="2005"/>
				</front>
				<format type="HTML" target="http://asrg.sp.am/subgroups/abuse_reports.shtml"/>
			</reference>
			<reference anchor="DKIM">
				<front>
					<title> DomainKeys Identified Mail (DKIM)
				        Signatures </title>
					<author initials="E." surname="Allman" fullname="E. Allman">
						<organization>
						Sendmail, Inc.
					</organization>
					</author>
					<author initials="J." surname="Callas" fullname="J. Callas">
						<organization>
						PGP Corporation
					</organization>
					</author>
					<author initials="M." surname="Delany" fullname="M. Delany">
						<organization>
						Yahoo!, Inc.
					</organization>
					</author>
					<author initials="M." surname="Libbey" fullname="M. Libbey">
						<organization>
						Yahoo!, Inc.
					</organization>
					</author>
					<author initials="J." surname="Fenton" fullname="J. Fenton">
						<organization>
						Cisco Systems, Inc.
					</organization>
					</author>
					<author initials="M." surname="Thomas" fullname="M. Thomas">
						<organization>
						Cisco Systems, Inc.
					</organization>
					</author>
					<date month="May" year="2007"/>
				</front>
				<seriesInfo name="RFC" value="4871"/>
			</reference>
			<reference anchor="DKIM-REPORTING" target="http://tools.ietf.org/html/draft-ietf-marf-dkim-reporting">
				<front>
					<title> Reporting of DKIM Verification Failures </title>
					<author initials="M." surname="Kucherawy" fullname="M. Kucherawy">
						<organization>
						Cloudmark
					</organization>
					</author>
					<date month="April" year="2010"/>
				</front>
			</reference>
			<reference anchor="EMAIL-ARCH">
				<front>
					<title> Internet Mail Architecture </title>
					<author initials="D." surname="Crocker" fullname="D. Crocker">
						<organization>
						Brandenburg InternetWorking
					</organization>
					</author>
					<date month="July" year="2009"/>
				</front>
				<seriesInfo name="RFC" value="5598"/>
			</reference>
		</references>

		<section anchor="public_discussion" title="Public Discussion and Support">
			<t> [REMOVE BEFORE PUBLICATION] </t>
			<t> Public discussion of this proposed specification
		    is handled via the marf@ietf.org
		    mailing list.  The list is open.  Access to subscription
		    forms and to list archives can be found at
		    http://www.ietf.org/mail-archive/web/marf/current/maillist.html </t>
		</section>
		<section anchor="doc_history" title="Document History &amp; Open Issues">
			<t> [REMOVE BEFORE PUBLICATION] </t>
			<section title="draft-jdfalk-marf-reporting-discovery-00">
				<t>
					<list style="symbols">
						<t> NEEDED: WG input, references cleanup, ABNF and 
							other formal definitions, and probably lots of 
							other stuff. </t>
						<t> QUESTION: should this include IODEF as a format? </t>
					</list>
				</t>
			</section>
			<section title="draft-jdfalk-marf-reporting-discovery-01">
				<t>
					<list style="symbols">
						<t> Changed from "Experimental" to "Standards Track". </t>
						<t> Various non-normative textual &amp; formatting 
							improvements, most importantly changing "hangtext"
							to "hangText" because xml2rfc is (surprisingly)
							case-sensitive. </t>
						<t> Added the PTR record as another place to look for
							advertisements published by ARF consumers.  (This
							may require additional clarifications later in 
							the text.) </t>
						<t> Moved a few references from normative to
							informative. </t>
						<t> Questions &amp; needs listed for version 00  
							remain valid. </t>
					</list>
				</t>
			</section>
			<section title="draft-jdfalk-marf-reporting-discovery-02">
				<t>
					<list style="symbols">
						<t> Added authentication-related and privacy considerations
							sections written by Alessandro Vesely. </t>
						<t> Questions &amp; needs listed for versions 00 and 01
							remain valid. </t>
					</list>
				</t>
			</section>
			<section title="draft-jdfalk-marf-reporting-discovery-03">
				<t>
					<list style="symbols">
						<t> Removed references to end-user report submissions; those should
							be left for a separate document, and probably be discoverable in 
							the same way as MUA settings. </t>
						<t> Rewrote some confusing parts. </t>
						<t> Added the examples section. </t>
						<t> QUESTION: should the advertisement be published 
							somewhere other than DNS? </t>
						<t> Questions &amp; needs listed for earlier versions
							remain valid. </t>
						<t> QUESTION: should this document include a description of how the
							complaint feedback signup process works today, and how this
							proposal would change it?  Or is that a separate Informational
							document? </t>
						<t> QUESTION: should the current Privacy Considerations section
							be moved to a separate BCP? </t>
					</list>
				</t>
			</section>
			<section title="draft-ietf-marf-reporting-discovery-00">
				<t>
					<list style="symbols">
						<t> This draft now belongs to the MARF WG. Yay! </t>
						<t> Added "Feedback Consumer re= Default" section. </t>
					</list>
				</t>
			</section>
			<section title="draft-ietf-marf-reporting-discovery-01">
				<t>
					<list style="symbols">
						<t> Minor wording change to clarify DKIM d= domain. </t>
						<t> Removed unused references. </t>
					</list>
				</t>
			</section>
		</section>
	</back>
</rfc>
