<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<rfc category="std" docName="draft-brandt-6man-lowpanz-00" ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="IPv6 over G.9959">Transmission of IPv6 packets over ITU-T
    G.9959 Networks</title>

    <author fullname="Anders Brandt" initials="A." surname="Brandt">
      <organization>Sigma Designs</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Emdrupvej 26A, 1.</street>

          <city>Copenhagen O</city>

          <code>2100</code>

          <region/>

          <country>Denmark</country>
        </postal>

        <phone/>

        <facsimile/>

        <email>anders_brandt@sigmadesigns.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Jakob Buron" initials="J." surname="Buron">
      <organization>Sigma Designs</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Emdrupvej 26A, 1.</street>

          <city>Copenhagen O</city>

          <code>2100</code>

          <region/>

          <country>Denmark</country>
        </postal>

        <phone/>

        <facsimile/>

        <email>jakob_buron@sigmadesigns.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date day="8" month="February" year="2013"/>

    <area>Internet Area</area>

    <workgroup>IPv6 Maintenance WG</workgroup>

    <keyword>Z-Wave</keyword>

    <keyword>IP over foo</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>This document describes the frame format for transmission of IPv6
      packets and a method of forming IPv6 link-local addresses and
      statelessly autoconfigured IPv6 addresses on ITU-T G.9959 networks.</t>
    </abstract>

    <note title="Requirements Language">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
      document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
      target="RFC2119"/>.</t>
    </note>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Author's notes">
      <t>This chapter MUST be deleted before going for last call.</t>

      <section title="Reader's guidance">
        <t>This document borrows heavily from RFC4944, "Transmission of IPv6
        Packets over IEEE 802.15.4 Networks". The process of creating this
        document was mainly a simplification; removing the following
        topics:</t>

        <t><list style="symbols">
            <t>EUI-64 link-layer addresses</t>

            <t>Fragmentation layer</t>

            <t>Mesh routing</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>The 16-bit short addresses of 802.15.4 have been changed to 8-bit
        G.9959 NodeIDs.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>The ITU-T G.9959 recommendation <xref target="G.9959"/> targets
      low-power Personal Area Networks (PANs). This document defines the frame
      format for transmission of IPv6 <xref target="RFC2460"/> packets as well
      as the formation of IPv6 link-local addresses and statelessly
      autoconfigured IPv6 addresses on G.9959 networks.</t>

      <t>The general approach is to adapt elements of the 6LoWPAN <xref
      target="RFC4944"/> specification to G.9959 networks. G.9959 provides a
      Segmentation and Reassembly (SAR) layer for transmission of datagrams
      larger than the G.9959 MAC PDU.</t>

      <t>In addition to IPv6 application communication, the frame format
      defined in this specification may be used by IPv6 routing protocols such
      as <xref target="RFC6550">RPL</xref> or <xref
      target="P2P-RPL">P2P-RPL</xref> to implement IPv6 routing over G.9959
      networks.</t>

      <t>G.9959 networks may implement mesh routing between nodes below the IP
      layer. Mesh routing is out of scope of this document.</t>

      <section title="Terms used">
        <t>AES: Advanced Encryption Scheme</t>

        <t>EUI-64: Extended Unique Identifier</t>

        <t>HomeID: Link-Layer Network Identifier</t>

        <t>IID: Interface IDentifier</t>

        <t>MAC: Media Access Control</t>

        <t>MTU: Maximum Transmission Unit</t>

        <t>NodeID: Link-Layer Node Identifier (Short Address)</t>

        <t>PAN: Personal Area Network</t>

        <t>PDU: Protocol Data Unit</t>

        <t>SAR: Segmentation And Reassembly</t>

        <t>ULA: Unique Local Address</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="ITU-T G.9959 parameters to use for IPv6 transport">
      <t>This chapter outlines properties applying to the PHY and MAC of
      G.9959 and how to use these for IPv6 transport.</t>

      <section title="Addressing mode">
        <t>G.9959 defines how a unique 32-bit HomeID network identifier is
        assigned by a network controller and how an 8-bit NodeID host
        identifier is allocated. NodeIDs are unique within the logical network
        identified by the HomeID. The logical network identified by the HomeID
        maps directly to an IPv6 subnet identified by one or more IPv6
        prefixes.</t>

        <t>An IPv6 host SHOULD construct its link-local IPv6 address and
        routable IPv6 addresses from the G.9959 NodeID in order to facilitate
        IP header compression as described in <xref target="RFC6282"/>.</t>

        <t>A word of caution: since HomeIDs and NodeIDs are handed out by a
        network controller function during inclusion, identifier validity and
        uniqueness is limited by the lifetime of the logical network
        membership. This can be cut short by a mishap occurring to the network
        controller. Having a single point of failure at the network controller
        suggests that deployers of high-reliability applications should
        carefully consider adding redundancy to the network controller
        function.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="IPv6 Multicast support">
        <t><xref target="RFC3819"/> recommends that IP subnetworks support
        (subnet-wide) multicast. G.9959 supports direct-range IPv6 multicast
        while subnet-wide multicast is not supported natively by G.9959.
        Subnet-wide multicast may be provided by an IP routing protocol or a
        mesh routing protocol operating below the LoWPAN layer. Mesh routing
        is out of scope of this document.</t>

        <t>IPv6 multicast packets MUST be carried via G.9959 broadcast.</t>

        <t>As per <xref target="G.9959"/>, this is accomplished as
        follows:</t>

        <t><list style="numbers">
            <t>The destination HomeID of the G.9959 MAC PDU MUST be the HomeID
            of the logical network</t>

            <t>The destination NodeID of the G.9959 MAC PDU MUST be the
            broadcast NodeID (0xff)</t>
          </list>G.9959 broadcast MAC PDUs are only intercepted by nodes
        within the logical network identified by the G.9959 HomeID.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="G.9959 MAC PDU size and IPv6 MTU">
        <t>IPv6 packets MUST use G.9959 transmission profiles which support
        MAC PDU payload sizes of 150 bytes or higher, e.g. the R3 profile.</t>

        <t><xref target="RFC2460"/> specifies that IPv6 packets may be up to
        1280 octets. However, a full IPv6 packet does not fit in an G.9959 MAC
        PDU. The maximum G.9959 R3 MAC PDU payload size is 158 octets. G.9959
        link-layer security imposes an overhead, which in the extreme case
        leaves 130 octets available.</t>

        <t>G.9959 provides Segmentation And Reassembly for payloads up to 1350
        octets. Segmentation however adds further overhead. It is therefore
        desirable that datagrams can fit into a single G.9959 MAC PDU. IPv6
        Header Compression <xref target="RFC6282"/> improves the chances that
        a short IPv6 packet can fit into a single G.9959 frame.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Transmission status indications">
        <t>The G.9959 MAC layer provides native acknowledgement and
        retransmission of MAC PDUs. The G.9959 SAR layer does the same for
        larger datagrams. A mesh routing layer may provide a similar feature
        for routed communication. Acknowledgment and retransmission improves
        the transmission success rate and frees higher layers from the burden
        of implementing individual retransmission schemes. The feature may
        however introduce challenges to existing TCP rate control algorithms
        and it may mask problematic links from IP routing protocols.</t>

        <section title="IPv6 Socket interface considerations">
          <t>An IPv6 socket implementation communicating over G.9959 MUST have
          access to status indications such as link-layer delivery
          confirmation and Ack timeout from the MAC layer. If there is a mesh
          routing layer below the LoWPAN layer, the IPv6 socket implementation
          MUST have access to status indications such as delivery confirmation
          and Ack timeout from the mesh routing layer. This will allow the
          IPv6 socket implementation to adjust its transmissions to the
          available bandwidth of the G.9959 network; transmitting a new IPv6
          packet only when it positively knows that the previous transmission
          ended (with fail or success).</t>
        </section>

        <section title="IPv6 Routing protocol interface considerations">
          <t>An IPv6 routing stack communicating over G.9959 MUST have access
          to delivery status indications such as link-layer delivery
          confirmation and Ack timeout from the MAC layer. This will allow the
          IP routing stack to adjust its routing decisions or alternatively
          initiate route rediscovery based on status indications from the link
          layer.</t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section title="Transmission security">
        <t>G.9959 provides link-layer security based on a common network key.
        Mission critical applications such as door locks and meters SHOULD
        deploy additional application layer security measures for end-to-end
        authentication and encryption.</t>

        <t>Implementations claiming conformance with this specification MUST
        enable G.9959 common network key security.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="LoWPAN Adaptation Layer and Frame Format">
      <t>The LoWPAN encapsulation formats defined in this chapter are the
      payload in the G.9959 MAC PDU or the G.9959 SAR PDU. IPv6 header
      compression <xref target="RFC6282"/> MUST be supported by
      implementations of this specification.</t>

      <t>All LoWPAN datagrams transported over G.9959 are prefixed by a LoWPAN
      encapsulation header stack. The LoWPAN payload (e.g. an IPv6 packet)
      follows this encapsulation header. Each header in the header stack
      contains a header type followed by zero or more header fields. An IPv6
      header stack may contain, in the following order, addressing, hop-by-hop
      options, routing, fragmentation, destination options, and finally
      payload <xref target="RFC2460"/>. The LoWPAN header format is structured
      the same way. Currently only payload options are defined for the LoWPAN
      header format.</t>

      <t>The definition of LoWPAN headers consists of the dispatch value, the
      definition of the header fields that follow, and their ordering
      constraints relative to all other headers. Although the header stack
      structure provides a mechanism to address future demands on the LoWPAN
      adaptation layer, it is not intended to provide general purpose
      extensibility. This document specifies a small set of 6LoWPAN header
      types using the 6LoWPAN header stack for clarity, compactness, and
      orthogonality.</t>

      <section anchor="DispatchType" title="Dispatch Type and Header">
        <t>The dispatch type is defined by a zero bit as the first bit and a
        one bit as the second bit. The dispatch type and header are shown
        here:<vspace blankLines="1"/></t>

        <figure anchor="FigDispatchTypeAndHeader"
                title="Dispatch Type and Header">
          <artwork><![CDATA[  0                   1                   2                   3
  0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
 +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
 | LoWPAN CmdCls |0 1| Dispatch  |  Type-specific header         |
 +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+]]></artwork>
        </figure>

        <t>LoWPAN CmdCls: LoWPAN Command Class identifier, <xref
        target="G.9959"/>. Specifies that the following bits are a LoWPAN
        encapsulated datagram. Non-LoWPAN protocols MUST ignore the contents
        following the LoWPAN Command Class identifier. TBD: Explicit value to
        be assigned by Z-Wave Alliance before last call of this Internet
        Draft. Refer to <xref target="ZW-A_Considerations"/>.</t>

        <t>Dispatch: 6-bit selector. Identifies the header type immediately
        following the Dispatch Header.</t>

        <t>Type-specific header: A header determined by the Dispatch
        Header.</t>

        <t>The dispatch value may be treated as an unstructured namespace.
        Only a few symbols are required to represent current LoWPAN
        functionality. Although some additional savings could be achieved by
        encoding additional functionality into the dispatch byte, these
        measures would tend to constrain the ability to address future
        alternatives.</t>

        <t>Dispatch values used in this specification are compatible with the
        dispatch values defined by <xref target="RFC4944"/> and <xref
        target="RFC6282"/>.</t>

        <t><vspace blankLines="1"/></t>

        <figure anchor="FigDispatchValueBitPattern"
                title="Dispatch Value Bit Pattern">
          <artwork><![CDATA[+------------+------------------------------------------+-----------+
| Pattern    | Header Type                              | Reference |
+------------+------------------------------------------+-----------+
| 01  000000 | ESC         - Dispatch octet #2 follows  | [RFC6282] |
| 01  000001 | IPv6        - Uncompressed IPv6 Addresses| [RFC4944] |
|   ...      | reserved    - Defined or reserved        | [RFC4944] |
| 01  1xxxxx | LoWPAN_IPHC - LoWPAN_IPHC compressed IPv6| [RFC6282] |
| 1x  xxxxxx | reserved    - Defined or reserved        | [RFC4944] |
+------------+------------------------------------------+-----------+]]></artwork>
        </figure>

        <t>IPv6: Specifies that the following header is an uncompressed IPv6
        header.</t>

        <t>ESC: Specifies that the following header is a single 8-bit field
        for an additional Dispatch value. It allows support for Dispatch
        values larger than 63. Note: <xref target="RFC4944"/> assigns the
        value 01 111111 for ESC. That assignment was deprecated by <xref
        target="RFC6282"/>.</t>

        <t>LoWPAN_IPHC: IPv6 Header Compression. Refer to <xref
        target="RFC6282"/>.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="LowpanAddressing" title="LoWPAN addressing">
      <t>IPv6 addresses are derived from link-layer address information to
      save memory in devices and to facilitate efficient IP header
      compression.</t>

      <t>A G.9959 NodeID is 8 bits in length. NodeIDs are mapped into the
      restricted space of IEEE EUI-64 addresses by setting the middle 16 bits
      to 0xfffe, the bottom 8 bits to the NodeID, and all other bits to zero.
      As a result, an Interface Identifier (IID) generated from a NodeID has
      the form:<vspace blankLines="1"/></t>

      <figure>
        <artwork><![CDATA[   IID = 0000:00ff:fe00:00XX]]></artwork>
      </figure>

      <t>where XX carries the G.9959 NodeID. The universal/local bit is zero
      to indicate local scope.</t>

      <t/>

      <t>This mapping differs from that presented in Appendix A of [RFC4291].
      Using the restricted space ensures that there is no overlap with IIDs
      generated from unrestricted IEEE EUI-64 addresses. Also, including
      0xfffe in the middle of the IID helps avoid overlap with other locally
      managed IIDs. Further, the mapping enables efficient IP Header
      Compression as per <xref target="RFC6282"/>.</t>

      <section anchor="StatelessAddressAutoconfiguration"
               title="Stateless Address Autoconfiguration of routable IPv6 addresses">
        <t>The IID defined above MUST be used whether autoconfiguring a ULA
        IPv6 address <xref target="RFC4193"/> or a globally routable IPv6
        address <xref target="RFC3587"/> in G.9959 subnets.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="ChapterIPv6_LinkLocalAddress"
               title="IPv6 Link Local Address">
        <t>The IPv6 link-local address <xref target="RFC4291"/> for a G.9959
        interface is formed by appending the IID to the IPv6 link local prefix
        FE80::/64.</t>

        <t>The "Universal/Local" (U/L) bit MUST be set to zero in keeping with
        the fact that this is not a globally unique value <xref
        target="EUI64"/>.</t>

        <t>The resulting link local address is formed as follows:<vspace
        blankLines="1"/></t>

        <figure anchor="FigIPv6_LinkLocalAddress"
                title="IPv6 Link Local Address">
          <artwork><![CDATA[          10 bits            54 bits                  64 bits
       +----------+-----------------------+----------------------------+
       |1111111010|         (zeros)       | Interface Identifier (IID) |
       +----------+-----------------------+----------------------------+]]></artwork>
        </figure>

        <t><vspace blankLines="1"/></t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="UnicastAddressMapping" title="Unicast Address Mapping">
        <t>The address resolution procedure for mapping IPv6 unicast addresses
        into G.9959 link-layer addresses follows the general description in
        Section 7.2 of <xref target="RFC4861"/>. The Source/Target Link-layer
        Address option MUST have the following form when the link layer is
        G.9959.<vspace blankLines="1"/></t>

        <figure anchor="FigIPv6_UnicastAddressMapping"
                title="IPv6 Unicast Address Mapping">
          <artwork><![CDATA[                       0                   1
                       0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5
                      +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
                      |     Type      |    Length=1   |
                      +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
                      |  HomeID1 (MS) | HomeID2       |
                      +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
                      |  HomeID3      | HomeID4 (LS)  |
                      +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
                      |  0x00         | NodeID        |
                      +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+]]></artwork>
        </figure>

        <t><vspace blankLines="1"/>Option fields:</t>

        <t>Type: The value 1 signifies the Source Link-layer address. The
        value 2 signifies the Destination Link-layer address.</t>

        <t>Length: This is the length of this option (including the type and
        length fields) in units of 8 octets. The value of this field is always
        1 for G.9959 NodeIDs.</t>

        <t>HomeID: This is the G.9959 HomeID the actual interface currently
        responds to. The link-layer address may change if the interface joins
        another network at a later time.</t>

        <t>NodeID: This is the G.9959 NodeID the actual interface currently
        responds to. The link-layer address may change if the interface joins
        another network at a later time.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="HeaderCompression" title="Header Compression">
      <t>IPv6 header fields SHOULD be compressed. If IPv6 header compression
      is used, it MUST be according to <xref target="RFC6282"/>. This section
      will simply identify substitutions that should be made when interpreting
      the text of [RFC6282].</t>

      <t>In general the following substitutions should be made:</t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>Replace "802.15.4" with "G.9959"</t>

          <t>Replace "802.15.4 short address" with "G.9959 NodeID"</t>

          <t>Replace "802.15.4 PAN ID" with "G.9959 HomeID"</t>
        </list> When a 16-bit address is called for (i.e., an IEEE 802.15.4
      "short address") it MUST be formed by padding the G.9959 NodeID to the
      left with zeros:</t>

      <figure>
        <artwork><![CDATA[                       0                   1
                       0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5
                      +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
                      |      0x00     |    NodeID     |
                      +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+]]></artwork>
      </figure>

      <t><vspace blankLines="1"/>64 bit 802.15.4 address details should be
      ignored. This document only specifies the use of short addresses.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="IANA_Considerations" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>This document makes no request of IANA.</t>

      <t>Note to RFC Editor: this section may be removed on publication as an
      RFC.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="ZW-A_Considerations"
             title="Z-Wave Allliance Considerations">
      <t>This document requests that the Z-Wave Alliance assigns a Command
      Class identifier for the LoWPAN Command Class; refer to <xref
      target="DispatchType"/>.</t>

      <t>Note to RFC Editor: this section may be removed on publication as an
      RFC.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>The method of derivation of Interface Identifiers from 8-bit NodeIDs
      preserves uniqueness within the logical network. However, there is no
      protection from duplication through forgery. Neighbor Discovery in
      G.9959 links may be susceptible to threats as detailed in <xref
      target="RFC3756"/>. G.9959 networks may feature mesh routing. This
      implies additional threats due to ad hoc routing as per [KW03]. G.9959
      provides capability for link-layer security. G.9959 nodes MUST use
      link-layer security with a common key. Doing so will alleviate the
      majority of threats stated above. A sizeable portion of G.9959 devices
      is expected to always communicate within their PAN (i.e., within their
      subnet, in IPv6 terms). In response to cost and power consumption
      considerations, these devices will typically implement the minimum set
      of features necessary. Accordingly, security for such devices may rely
      on the mechanisms defined at the link layer by G.9959. G.9959 relies on
      the Advanced Encryption Standard (AES) for authentication and encryption
      of G.9959 frames and further employs challenge-response handshaking to
      prevent replay attacks.</t>

      <t>It is also expected that some G.9959 devices (e.g. billing and/or
      safety critical products) will implement coordination or integration
      functions. These may communicate regularly with IPv6 peers outside the
      subnet. Such IPv6 devices are expected to secure their end-to-end
      communications with standard security mechanisms (e.g., IPsec, TLS,
      etc).</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>Thanks to the authors of RFC 4944 and RFC6282 and members of the IETF
      6LoWPAN working group; this document borrows extensively from their
      work. Thanks to Kerry Lynn, Tommas Jess Christensen and Erez Ben-Tovim
      for useful discussions which helped shape this document.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4291"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4944"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6282"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2460"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2464"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4861"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4193"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3587"?>

      <reference anchor="G.9959">
        <front>
          <title>ITU-T G.9959: Low-Power, narrowband radio for control
          applications</title>

          <author fullname="">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <date day="1" month="January" year="2012"/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="EUI64">
        <front>
          <title>GUIDELINES FOR 64-BIT GLOBAL IDENTIFIER (EUI-64) REGISTRATION
          AUTHORITY</title>

          <author fullname="IEEE http:// standards.ieee.org/regauth/oui/tutorials/EUI64.html">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <date year=""/>
        </front>
      </reference>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3819"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3756"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6550"?>

      <reference anchor="P2P-RPL">
        <front>
          <title>IETF, I-D.ietf-roll-p2p-rpl-15, Reactive Discovery of
          Point-to-Point Routes in Low Power and Lossy Networks</title>

          <author fullname="M. Goyal" initials="M." surname="Goyal">
            <organization>University of Wisconsin</organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="E. Baccelli" initials="E." surname="Baccelli">
            <organization>INRIA</organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="M. Philipp" initials="M." surname="Philipp">
            <organization>INRIA</organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="A. Brandt" initials="A." surname="Brandt">
            <organization>Sigma Designs</organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="J. Martocci" initials="J." surname="Martocci">
            <organization>Johnson Controls</organization>
          </author>

          <date day="12" month="December" year="2012"/>
        </front>
      </reference>
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
