<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>

<!-- Use XML2RFC (http://xml.resource.org/) to parse this XML-formatted internet-draft. -->
<!-- Alternatively, use the rfc2629.xslt stylesheet to convert this document to HTML:
     e.g. xsltproc draft-urn-ogf.xml > draft-urn-ogf.html -->

<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc iprnotified="no" ?>  <!-- no known patent claims -->
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>  <!-- reduce white space; don't start sections on new page -->
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>  <!-- keep a blank link in lists -->
<?rfc comments="yes"?>  <!-- display the (cref) comments -->
<?rfc inline="yes" ?>  <!-- display comments inline -->

<rfc category="info" docName="draft-dijkstra-urn-ogf-06" ipr="trust200902" submissionType="independent">

  <front>

    <title abbrev="URN Namespace for the OGF">A URN Namespace for the Open Grid Forum (OGF)</title>
    
    <author fullname="Freek Dijkstra" initials="F." surname="Dijkstra">
      <organization>SARA</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Science Park 121</street>
          <code>1098 XG</code>
          <city>Amsterdam</city>
          <country>NL</country>
        </postal>
        <email>Freek.Dijkstra@sara.nl</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Richard Hughes-Jones" initials="R." surname="Hughes-Jones">
      <organization>DANTE</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>City House</street>
          <street>126-130 Hills Road</street>
          <city>Cambridge</city>
          <code>CB2 1PQ</code>
          <country>UK</country>
        </postal>
        <email>Richard.Hughes-Jones@dante.net</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date month="July" year="2011" />

    <!-- Meta-data Declarations -->

    <area>General</area>

    <keyword>urn</keyword>
    <keyword>ogf</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>This document describes a URN (Uniform Resource Name) namespace that
      is engineered by the Open Grid Forum (OGF) for naming persistent resources.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      
      <t>The Open Grid Forum (OGF) is a standardisation development organisation 
      in the field of distributed computing. The OGF produces documents such as 
      working drafts, specifications, and schemata. For more information, see 
      <eref target="http://www.ogf.org/">http://www.ogf.org/</eref></t>
      
      <t>Working groups in the OGF community have expressed the need for 
      global, distributed, persistent identifiers in working drafts and standards.
      Motivated by this need, the OGF would like to assign URNs to
      some resources in order to retain unique, permanent, 
      location-independent names for them.</t>
      
      <t>This namespace specification is for a formal namespace.</t>
      
      <section title="Requirements Language">
        <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
        "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
        document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
        target="RFC2119"/>.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="URN Specification for &quot;ogf&quot; NID">

      <section title="Namespace ID">
        <t>"ogf" requested.</t>
      </section>
      
      <section title="Registration Information">
        <t>
          Registration Version Number: 1<vspace />
          Registration Date: yyyy-mm-dd <cref anchor="RFC-Editor1">Please replace with the
            date of approval of this document for publication as an RFC</cref>
        </t>
      </section>
      
      <section title="Declared registrant of the namespace">
          <t>
            Technical Director<vspace />
            Open Grid Forum<vspace />
            P.O. Box 2326<vspace />
            Joliet, Illinois 60434<vspace />
            USA<vspace />
            http://www.ogf.org/<vspace />
            Email: urn@ogf.org
          </t>
          <t>The position of technical director is currently fulfilled by Joel Replogle.</t>
      </section>
      
      <section title="Declaration of syntactic structure">
        
        <t>The formal syntax definitions below are given in <xref target="RFC5234">ABNF</xref>.</t>
        
        <t>The NSS in the urn:ogf names hierarchy begins with a subnamespace
        identifier (SNID), followed by a delimiter and a subnamespace-dependent string</t>
        
        <figure><artwork type="abnf">
   OGF-URN  =  "urn:ogf:" SNID ":" SUBNAMESPACE-SPECIFIC-STRING</artwork></figure>
        
        <t>where &lt;SNID&gt; is a unique subnamespace identifier for the
        specification, and &lt;SUBNAMESPACE-SPECIFIC-STRING&gt; is a unique identifier 
        within the subnamespace identifier scope.</t>
        
        <t>&lt;SNID&gt; has the same syntax as a &lt;NID&gt; as defined in <xref target="RFC2141"/>:</t>
        
        <figure><artwork type="abnf">
   SNID  =  ( ALPHA / DIGIT )  *31( ALPHA / DIGIT / "-" )</artwork></figure>
        
        <t>ALPHA and DIGIT are defined in <eref target="http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc5234#appendix-B">Appendix B</eref> of <xref target="RFC5234"/>.</t>
        
        <t>The Technical Director at OGF (or their successors) assigns subnamespace identifiers (SNID).</t>
        
        <t>The syntax of &lt;SUBNAMESPACE-SPECIFIC-STRING&gt; is dependent on the &lt;SNID&gt;, and MUST be defined by a <xref target="GFD-SERIES">Grid Forum Document</xref>. This document does not pose any additional restrictions to the &lt;SUBNAMESPACE-SPECIFIC-STRING&gt; other than what is defined in the NSS syntax as defined by <xref target="RFC2141"/> or its successor:</t>
        
        <figure><artwork type="abnf">
   SUBNAMESPACE-SPECIFIC-STRING  =  1*&lt;URN chars&gt;
</artwork></figure>
        
        <t>&lt;URN chars&gt; is defined in <eref target="http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc2141#section-2.2">Section 2.2</eref> of <xref target="RFC2141"/>.</t>
        
      </section>
      
      <section title="Relevant ancillary documentation">
        
        <t>The Technical Director at OGF (or their successors) will keep a list of assigned subnamespace identifiers and associated documentation at <eref target="http://www.ogf.org/urn/">http://www.ogf.org/urn/</eref> <xref target="URN-OGF"/>.</t>
        
        <t>Information on the procedures how to register a subnamespace identifier can also be found at this website.</t>
        
      </section>
      
      <section title="Identifier uniqueness considerations">
        <t>Identifier uniqueness will be enforced by the Technical Director of the Open Grid Forum.</t>
        
        <t>The OGF Technical Director may sub-delegate part of the namespace to third parties.
        It will not be permissible, neither by the OGF Technical Director nor any third party, to
        re-assign previously assigned URNs. A practical consequence is that a previously assigned 
        subnamespace can not be re-assigned, unless additional arrangements are made to prevent 
        identifier re-assignements.</t>
      </section>
      
      <section title="Identifier persistence considerations">
        <t>The Technical Director will only assign subnamespace identifiers for persistent resources.</t>
        
        <t>In order to enforce identifier persistence for individual resources, each document defining subnamespace identifiers MUST contain a section on the type of resource that is specified (e.g. whether a URN in the subnamespace identifies a specific version of a resource, the latest version of a resource, a specific manifestation, or a more general concept)</t>
      </section>
      
      <section title="Process of identifier assignment">
        <t>Assignment of subnamespace identifiers is limited to the OGF and those 
        authorities that are specifically designated by the OGF Technical 
        Director. OGF may assign portions of its namespace (specifically, 
        those under designated subnamespace identifiers) for assignment by third
        parties.</t>
        
        <t>The details of this process is specified in <xref target="GFD-C.XXX"/>.<cref anchor="RFC-Editor2">Please hold publication of this RFC until the GFD-series number of this reference is assigned by the Open Grid Forum.</cref></t>
        
        <t>The syntax and semantics of each subnamespace MUST be defined by a <xref target="GFD-SERIES">Grid Forum Document</xref> before the corresponding subnamespace identifier (SNID) is assigned.</t>
      </section>
      
      <section title="Process of identifier resolution">
        <t>The OGF namespace is not currently listed with a Resolution
        Discovery System (RDS), but nothing about the namespace
        prohibits the future definition of appropriate resolution
        methods or listing with an RDS.</t>
        
        <t>The OGF will maintain an index of all subnamespace identifiers
        on its Web site, <eref target="http://www.ogf.org/urn/">http://www.ogf.org/urn/</eref>.
        This list may refer to known Resolution Discovery System(s).</t>
      </section>
      
      <section title="Rules for Lexical Equivalence">
        <t>The &lt;SNID&gt; part of URNs in the OGF hierarchy is case insensitive. Thus, the &lt;SNID&gt; MUST be case normalised before comparison.</t>
        
        <t>The rules for lexical equivalence of the &lt;SUBNAMESPACE-SPECIFIC-STRING&gt; part of URNs in the OGF hierarchy is specific for each SNID and MUST be defined when a SNID is assigned by the OGF Technical Director. These definitions MUST included information about case sensitivity, and in case %-escaped octets, MUST define the exact normalisation to use (e.g. interpret as octet, interpret as UTF-8, specify type of Unicode normalisation factor, etc.)</t>
      </section>
      
      <section title="Conformance with URN Syntax">
        <t>The intention of this document is to only restrict the syntax of the &lt;SNID&gt;. The syntax of the &lt;SUBNAMESPACE-SPECIFIC-STRING&gt; follows the general syntax of a URN:</t>
        
        <figure><artwork type="abnf">
   SUBNAMESPACE-SPECIFIC-STRING  =  1*&lt;URN chars&gt;
</artwork></figure>
        
        <t>Documents defining a subnamespace identifier SHOULD specify further syntactic 
          restrictions in &lt;SUBNAMESPACE-SPECIFIC-STRING&gt;.
          It is RECOMMENDED that these documents forbid the assignment of URNs containing 
          characters in the &lt;reserved&gt; set ("%", "/", "?", and "#") 
          as defined in <xref target="RFC2141"/>. 
          This is in accordance with section 2.2 of <xref target="RFC3986"/>.</t>
        
        <t>For forward compatibility, it is RECOMMENDED that software implementations 
          that don't validate subnamespace-specific strings, validate the syntax according 
          to the generic rules for validating URIs, as defined in <xref target="RFC3986"/>. 
          URIs may contain all characters defined in &lt;URN chars&gt;, including the 
          characters in &lt;reserved&gt; (albeit they have a special meaning), as well 
          the characters as "&amp;" and "~".</t>
        
      </section>
      
      <section title="Validation mechanism">
        <t>The validation mechanism of URNs in the OGF hierarchy is specific for each SNID and SHOULD be defined when a SNID is assigned by the OGF Technical Director.</t>
        
        <t>URNs in the OGF hierarchy without an assigned SNID are considered to be invalid.</t>
      </section>
      
      <section title="Scope">
        <t>Global URNs, relevant for the distributed computing community in general, and the Open Grid Forum in particular.</t>
      </section>
      
    </section>

    <section title="Examples (Informative)">
      
      <t>Since no subnamespace identifiers have been defined yet, no actual examples can be given. 
      Therefore, the following examples are not guaranteed to be real or even syntactically correct.</t>
      
      <t>Grid forum documents defining the "gfd" and "network" subnamespace identifiers may give the following examples.</t>
      
      <t><list style="symbols">
      <t>urn:ogf:gfd:136</t>
      <t>urn:ogf:network:canarie.ca:kisti-uninett-glif-001</t>
      </list></t>
      
    </section>

    <section title="Namespace Considerations">
      
      <t>The Open Grid Forum (OGF) is a standardisation development organisation 
      in the field of distributed computing.</t>
      
      <t>The use of the OGF hierarchy is expected to be broad, including but not limit to usage for:
        <list style="symbols">
          <t>Grid Forum Documents</t>
          <t>XML (Extensible Markup Language) Schemata</t>
          <t>RDF (Resource Description Framework) Schemata</t>
        </list>
      </t>
      
      <t>The Open Grid Forum is dedicated to openly publish all technical documentation related to URNs in the OGF hierarchy and allow unlimited distribution of these documents.</t>
      
    </section>

    <section title="Community Considerations">
      
      <t>Members of the distributed computing community will benefit from persistent and globally unique identifiers for use in protocols developed by the Open Grid Forum.</t>
      
      <t>Practical use of the urn:ogf namespace has been detected, 
        and a formal registration will allow the Open Grid Forum to 
        document this usage and enforce technical review of current practices.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>There are no additional security considerations other than those
      normally associated with the use and resolution of URNs in general.</t>
      
      <t>Implementers are recommended to check the OGF registry and 
      documentation <xref target="URN-OGF"/> before assuming that a 
      given identifier is valid or has a certain meaning.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">

      <t>IANA is kindly requested to register the "ogf" namespace identifier 
        (NID) at the <xref target="URN-NAMESPACES">URN Namespaces registry</xref>
        and refer to this document and/or the website <eref target="http://www.ogf.org/urn/">http://www.ogf.org/urn/</eref>.</t>

    </section>
    
    <section title="Acknowledgements">

      <t>The template and useful examples from <xref target="RFC3406"/> formed the basis for this document.  The authors would like to thank Joel Replogle and Andre Mersky for setting up the urn:ogf subnamespace registry.  Jeroen van der Ham, Peter Saint-Andre and Mykyta Yevstifeyev proof-read this document and provided valuable feedback.</t>

    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <!-- References split into informative and normative -->

    <references title="Normative References">
    
    <!-- References are included inline instead of referred to an external files, since that is not supported by XLST. -->
    
      <reference anchor='RFC2119'>
        <front>
          <title abbrev='RFC Key Words'>Key words for use in RFCs to Indicate Requirement Levels</title>
          <author initials='S.' surname='Bradner' fullname='Scott Bradner'>
            <organization>Harvard University</organization>
            <address>
              <postal>
                <street>1350 Mass. Ave.</street>
                <street>Cambridge</street>
                <street>MA 02138</street>
              </postal>
              <phone>- +1 617 495 3864</phone>
              <email>sob@harvard.edu</email>
            </address>
          </author>
          <date year='1997' month='March' />
          <area>General</area>
          <keyword>keyword</keyword>
          <abstract>
            <t>In many standards track documents several words are used to signify
            the requirements in the specification.  These words are often
            capitalised.  This document defines these words as they should be
            interpreted in IETF documents.  Authors who follow these guidelines
            should incorporate this phrase near the beginning of their document:
            <list><t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL
            NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED",  "MAY", and
            "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in
            RFC 2119.</t></list>
            </t>
            <t>Note that the force of these words is modified by the requirement
            level of the document in which they are used.</t>
          </abstract>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name='BCP' value='14' />
        <seriesInfo name='RFC' value='2119' />
        <format type='TXT' octets='4723' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc2119.txt' />
        <format type='HTML' octets='17491' target='http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/html/rfc2119.html' />
        <format type='XML' octets='5777' target='http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/xml/rfc2119.xml' />
      </reference>
      
      <reference anchor='RFC2141'>
        <front>
          <title>URN Syntax</title>
          <author initials='R.' surname='Moats' fullname='Ryan Moats'>
            <organization>AT&amp;T</organization>
            <address>
              <postal>
                <street>15621 Drexel Circle</street>
                <street>Omaha</street>
                <street>NE 68135-2358</street>
                <country>USA</country>
              </postal>
              <phone>+1 402 894-9456</phone>
              <email>jayhawk@ds.internic.net</email>
            </address>
          </author>
          <date year='1997' month='May' />
          <area>Applications</area>
          <keyword>URN</keyword>
          <keyword>uniform resource</keyword>
          <abstract>
            <t>Uniform Resource Names (URNs) are intended to serve as persistent,
            location-independent, resource identifiers. This document sets
            forward the canonical syntax for URNs.  A discussion of both existing
            legacy and new namespaces and requirements for URN presentation and
            transmission are presented.  Finally, there is a discussion of URN
            equivalence and how to determine it.</t>
          </abstract>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name='RFC' value='2141' />
        <format type='TXT' octets='14077' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc2141.txt' />
        <format type='HTML' octets='30670' target='http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/html/rfc2141.html' />
        <format type='XML' octets='17687' target='http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/xml/rfc2141.xml' />
      </reference>
      
      <reference anchor='RFC3986'>
        <front>
          <title abbrev='URI Generic Syntax'>Uniform Resource Identifier (URI): Generic Syntax</title>
          <author initials='T.' surname='Berners-Lee' fullname='Tim Berners-Lee'>
            <organization abbrev='W3C/MIT'>World Wide Web Consortium</organization>
            <address>
              <postal>
                <street>Massachusetts Institute of Technology</street>
                <street>77 Massachusetts Avenue</street>
                <city>Cambridge</city>
                <region>MA</region>
                <code>02139</code>
                <country>USA</country>
              </postal>
              <phone>+1-617-253-5702</phone>
              <facsimile>+1-617-258-5999</facsimile>
              <email>timbl@w3.org</email>
              <uri>http://www.w3.org/People/Berners-Lee/</uri>
            </address>
          </author>
          <author initials='R.' surname='Fielding' fullname='Roy T. Fielding'>
            <organization abbrev='Day Software'>Day Software</organization>
            <address>
              <postal>
                <street>5251 California Ave., Suite 110</street>
                <city>Irvine</city>
                <region>CA</region>
                <code>92617</code>
                <country>USA</country>
              </postal>
              <phone>+1-949-679-2960</phone>
              <facsimile>+1-949-679-2972</facsimile>
              <email>fielding@gbiv.com</email>
              <uri>http://roy.gbiv.com/</uri>
            </address>
          </author>
          <author initials='L.' surname='Masinter' fullname='Larry Masinter'>
            <organization abbrev='Adobe Systems'>Adobe Systems Incorporated</organization>
            <address>
              <postal>
                <street>345 Park Ave</street>
                <city>San Jose</city>
                <region>CA</region>
                <code>95110</code>
                <country>USA</country>
              </postal>
              <phone>+1-408-536-3024</phone>
              <email>LMM@acm.org</email>
              <uri>http://larry.masinter.net/</uri>
            </address>
          </author>
          <date year='2005' month='January' />
          <area>Applications</area>
          <keyword>uniform resource identifier</keyword>
          <keyword>URI</keyword>
          <keyword>URL</keyword>
          <keyword>URN</keyword>
          <keyword>WWW</keyword>
          <keyword>resource</keyword>
          <abstract>
            <t>
            A Uniform Resource Identifier (URI) is a compact sequence of characters
            that identifies an abstract or physical resource.  This specification
            defines the generic URI syntax and a process for resolving URI references
            that might be in relative form, along with guidelines and security
            considerations for the use of URIs on the Internet.
            The URI syntax defines a grammar that is a superset of all valid URIs,
            allowing an implementation to parse the common components of a URI
            reference without knowing the scheme-specific requirements of every
            possible identifier.  This specification does not define a generative
            grammar for URIs; that task is performed by the individual
            specifications of each URI scheme.
            </t>
          </abstract>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name='STD' value='66' />
        <seriesInfo name='RFC' value='3986' />
        <format type='TXT' octets='141811' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc3986.txt' />
        <format type='HTML' octets='213584' target='http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/html/rfc3986.html' />
        <format type='XML' octets='163534' target='http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/xml/rfc3986.xml' />
      </reference>
      
      <reference anchor='RFC5234'>
        <front>
          <title>Augmented BNF for Syntax Specifications: ABNF</title>
          <author initials='D.' surname='Crocker' fullname='D. Crocker'>
            <organization />
          </author>
          <author initials='P.' surname='Overell' fullname='P. Overell'>
            <organization />
          </author>
          <date year='2008' month='January' />
          <abstract>
            <t>Internet technical specifications often need to define a formal syntax.  
            Over the years, a modified version of Backus-Naur Form (BNF), called 
            Augmented BNF (ABNF), has been popular among many Internet specifications.  
            The current specification documents ABNF.  It balances compactness and 
            simplicity with reasonable representational power.  The differences between 
            standard BNF and ABNF involve naming rules, repetition, alternatives, 
            order-independence, and value ranges.  This specification also supplies 
            additional rule definitions and encoding for a core lexical analyzer of the 
            type common to several Internet specifications. [STANDARDS TRACK]</t>
          </abstract>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name='STD' value='68' />
        <seriesInfo name='RFC' value='5234' />
        <format type='TXT' octets='26359' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc5234.txt' />
      </reference>
      
      <reference anchor="GFD-C.XXX" target='http://www.ogf.org/documents/GFD.xxx.pdf'>
        <front>
          <title>Procedure for Registration of Subnamespace Identifiers in the URN:OGF Hierarchy</title>
          <author initials='F.' surname='Dijktra' fullname='F. Dijkstra'>
            <organization>SARA</organization>
          </author>
          <author initials='R.' surname='Hughes-Jones' fullname='Richard Hughes-Jones'>
            <organization>DANTE</organization>
          </author>
          <author initials='G.B.' surname='Newby' fullname='Gregory B. Newby'>
            <organization>Arctic Region Supercomputing Center</organization>
          </author>
          <author initials='J.' surname='Replogle' fullname='Joel Replogle'>
            <organization>Open Grid Forum</organization>
          </author>
          <date year='2011' month='XXX' />
          <abstract>
            <t>This document describes the procedure how to register subnamespace identifiers (&lt;snid&gt;) in the urn:ogf: namespace.</t>
          </abstract>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name='GFD' value='xxx' />
      </reference>
      
    </references>
    
    <references title="Informative References">
      
      <reference anchor='RFC3406'>
        <front>
          <title>Uniform Resource Names (URN) Namespace Definition Mechanisms</title>
          <author initials='L.' surname='Daigle' fullname='L. Daigle'>
            <organization />
          </author>
          <author initials='D.' surname='van Gulik' fullname='D. van Gulik'>
            <organization />
          </author>
          <author initials='R.' surname='Iannella' fullname='R. Iannella'>
            <organization />
          </author>
          <author initials='P.' surname='Faltstrom' fullname='P. Faltstrom'>
            <organization />
          </author>
          <date year='2002' month='October' />
          <abstract>
            <t>This document lays out general definitions of and mechanisms for establishing Uniform Resource Names (URN) "namespaces".  The URN WG has defined a syntax for URNs in RFC 2141, as well as some proposed mechanisms for their resolution and use in Internet applications in RFC 3401 and RFC 3405.  The whole rests on the concept of individual "namespaces" within the URN structure.  Apart from proof-of-concept namespaces, the use of existing identifiers in URNs has been discussed in RFC 2288.  This document specifies an Internet Best Current Practices for the Internet Community, and requests discussion and suggestions for improvements.</t>
          </abstract>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name='BCP' value='66' />
        <seriesInfo name='RFC' value='3406' />
        <format type='TXT' octets='43707' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc3406.txt' />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="URN-NAMESPACES" target="http://www.iana.org/assignments/urn-namespaces/">
        <front>
          <title>Official IANA Registry of URN Namespaces</title>
          <author>
            <organization>IANA</organization>
          </author>
        </front>
      </reference>
      
      <reference anchor="GFD-SERIES" target='http://www.ogf.org/documents/GFD.1.pdf'>
        <front>
          <title>GGF Document Series</title>
          <author initials='C.' surname='Catlett' fullname='C. Catlett'>
            <organization>Argonne National Laboratory</organization>
          </author>
          <date year='2002' month='April' />
          <abstract>
            <t>Among the most useful products of Global Grid Forum (GGF) efforts will be documents that provide information, guidance, or recommendations. This memo defines five types of GGF document and a set of development and review processes for these documents. The process borrows heavily from the Internet Engineering Task Force Request for Comments document process and is intended to complement that process.</t>
          </abstract>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name='GFD' value='1' />
      </reference>
      
      <reference anchor="URN-OGF" target="http://www.ogf.org/urn/">
        <front>
          <title>URN:OGF Hierarchy Registry and Documentation</title>
          <author>
            <organization>Open Grid Forum</organization>
          </author>
        </front>
      </reference>
      
    </references>

  </back>
</rfc>
