<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<rfc category="info" docName="draft-ietf-v6ops-mobile-device-profile-02"
     ipr="trust200902" updates="">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="IPv6 Profile for Cellular Devices">Internet Protocol
    Version 6 (IPv6) Profile for 3GPP Mobile Devices</title>

    <author fullname="David Binet" initials="D." surname="Binet">
      <organization>France Telecom</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>

          <city>Rennes</city>

          <region></region>

          <code></code>

          <country>France</country>
        </postal>

        <email>david.binet@orange.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Mohamed Boucadair" initials="M." surname="Boucadair">
      <organization>France Telecom</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>

          <city>Rennes</city>

          <region></region>

          <code>35000</code>

          <country>France</country>
        </postal>

        <email>mohamed.boucadair@orange.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Ales Vizdal" initials="A." surname="Vizdal">
      <organization>Deutsche Telekom AG</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>

          <city></city>

          <region></region>

          <country></country>
        </postal>

        <phone></phone>

        <email>ales.vizdal@t-mobile.cz</email>

        <uri></uri>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Cameron Byrne" initials="C." surname="Byrne">
      <organization>T-Mobile</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>

          <city></city>

          <region></region>

          <code></code>

          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>

        <phone></phone>

        <email>Cameron.Byrne@T-Mobile.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Gang Chen" initials="G." surname="Chen">
      <organization>China Mobile</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>

          <city></city>

          <region></region>

          <code></code>

          <country></country>
        </postal>

        <email>phdgang@gmail.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date day="23" month="April" year="2013" />

    <workgroup>V6OPS Working Group</workgroup>

    <abstract>
      <t>This document specifies an IPv6 profile for 3GPP mobile devices. It
      lists the set of features a 3GPP mobile device is to be compliant with
      to connect to an IPv6-only or dual-stack wireless network (including
      3GPP cellular network and IEEE 802.11 network).</t>

      <t>This document defines a different profile than the one for general
      connection to IPv6 cellular networks defined in <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-v6ops-rfc3316bis"></xref>. In particular, this document
      identifies also features to deliver IPv4 connectivity service over an
      IPv6-only transport.</t>

      <t>Both hosts and devices with capability to share their WAN (Wide Area
      Network) connectivity are in scope.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>IPv6 deployment in 3GPP mobile networks is the only perennial
      solution to the exhaustion of IPv4 addresses in those networks. Several
      mobile operators have already deployed IPv6 or are in the pre-deployment
      phase. One of the major hurdles encountered by mobile operators is the
      availability of non-broken IPv6 implementation in mobile devices.</t>

      <t><xref target="I-D.ietf-v6ops-rfc3316bis"></xref> lists a set of
      features to be supported by cellular hosts to connect to 3GPP mobile
      networks. In the light of recent IPv6 production deployments, additional
      features to facilitate IPv6-only deployments while accessing IPv4-only
      service are to be considered.</t>

      <t>This document defines a different profile than the one for general
      connection to IPv6 mobile networks defined in <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-v6ops-rfc3316bis"></xref>; in particular: <list
          style="symbols">
          <t>It lists an extended list of required features while <xref
          target="I-D.ietf-v6ops-rfc3316bis"></xref> identifies issues and
          explains how to implement basic IPv6 features in a cellular
          context.</t>

          <t>It identifies also features to ensure IPv4 service delivery over
          an IPv6-only transport.</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>This document specifies an IPv6 profile for mobile devices listing
      required specifications produced by various Standards Developing
      Organizations (in particular 3GPP and IETF). The objectives of this
      effort are:<list style="numbers">
          <t>List in one single document all requirements a mobile device is
          to comply with to connect to an IPv6 or dual-stack mobile network.
          These requirements cover various network types such as GPRS (General
          Packet Radio Service), EPC (Evolved Packet Core) or IEEE 802.11
          network.</t>

          <t>Help Operators with the detailed device requirement list
          preparation (to be exchanged with device suppliers). This is also a
          contribution to harmonize Operators&rsquo; requirements towards
          device vendors.</t>

          <t>Vendors to be aware of a minimal set of requirements to allow for
          IPv6 connectivity and IPv4 service continuity (over an IPv6-only
          transport).</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>Pointers to some requirements listed in <xref
      target="RFC6434"></xref> are included in this profile. The justification
      for using a stronger language compared to what is specified in <xref
      target="RFC6434"></xref> is provided for some requirements.</t>

      <t>The requirements do not include 3GPP release details. For more
      information on the 3GPP releases detail, the reader may refer to Section
      6.2 of <xref target="RFC6459"></xref>. </t>

      <t>Some of the features listed in this profile document require to
      activate dedicated functions at the network side. It is out of scope of
      this document to list these network-side functions.</t>

      <t>A detailed overview of IPv6 support in 3GPP architectures is provided
      in <xref target="RFC6459"></xref>.</t>

      <t>This document makes use of the terms defined in <xref
      target="RFC6459"></xref>. In addition, the following terms are
      used:<list style="symbols">
          <t>"3GPP cellular host" (or cellular host for short) denotes a 3GPP
          device which can be connected to 3GPP mobile networks or IEEE 802.11
          networks.</t>

          <t>"3GPP cellular device" (or cellular device for short) refers to a
          cellular host which supports the capability to share its WAN (Wide
          Area Network) connectivity.</t>

          <t>"Cellular host" and "mobile host" are used interchangeably.</t>

          <t>"Cellular device" and "mobile device" are used
          interchangeably.</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>PREFIX64 denotes an IPv6 prefix used to build IPv4-converted IPv6
      addresses <xref target="RFC6052"></xref>.</t>

      <section title="Scope">
        <t>A 3GPP mobile network can be used to connect various user
        equipments such as a mobile telephone, a CPE (Customer Premises
        Equipment) or a M2M (machine-to-machine) device. Because of this
        diversity of terminals, it is necessary to define a set of IPv6
        functionalities valid for any node directly connecting to a 3GPP
        mobile network. This document describes these functionalities.</t>

        <t>This document is structured to provide the generic IPv6
        requirements which are valid for all nodes, whatever their function or
        service (e.g., SIP <xref target="RFC3261"></xref>) capability. The
        document also contains, dedicated sections covering specific
        functionalities the specific device types must support (e.g.,
        smartphones, devices providing some LAN functions (mobile CPE or
        broadband dongles)).</t>

        <t>The requirements listed below are valid for both 3GPP GPRS and 3GPP
        EPS (Evolved Packet System) access. For EPS, PDN-Connection term is
        used instead of PDP-Context.</t>

        <t>This document identifies also some WLAN-related IPv6 requirements.
        Other non-3GPP accesses <xref target="TS.23402"></xref> are out of
        scope of this document. </t>
      </section>

      <section title="Special Language">
        <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
        "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
        document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
        target="RFC2119">RFC 2119</xref>.</t>

        <t>This document is not a standard. It uses the normative keywords
        only for precision.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="generic" title="Connectivity Requirements">
      <t></t>

      <t><list counter="" hangIndent="5" style="hanging">
          <t hangText="REQ#1:">The cellular host MUST be compliant with
          Section 5.9.1 (IPv6 Addressing Architecture) and Section 5.8 (ICMPv6
          support) of <xref target="RFC6434"></xref>.</t>

          <t hangText="REQ#2:">The cellular host MUST support both IPv6 and
          IPv4v6 PDP-Contexts. <list style="empty">
              <t>This allows each operator to select their own strategy
              regarding IPv6 introduction. Both IPv6 and IPv4v6 PDP-Contexts
              MUST be supported. IPv4, IPv6 or IPv4v6 PDP-Context request
              acceptance depends on the cellular network configuration.</t>
            </list></t>

          <t hangText="REQ#3:">The cellular host MUST comply with the behavior
          defined in <xref target="TS.23060"></xref> <xref
          target="TS.23401"></xref> <xref target="TS.24008"></xref> for
          requesting a PDP-Context type. In particular, the cellular host MUST
          request by default an IPv6 PDP-Context if the cellular host is
          IPv6-only and requesting an IPv4v6 PDP-Context if the cellular host
          is dual-stack or when the cellular host is not aware of connectivity
          types requested by devices connected to it (e.g., cellular host with
          LAN capabilities as discussed in <xref target="cpe"></xref>): <list
              style="symbols">
              <t>If the requested IPv4v6 PDP-Context is not supported by the
              network, but IPv4 and IPv6 PDP types are allowed, then the
              cellular host will be configured with an IPv4 address or an IPv6
              prefix by the network. It MUST initiate another PDP-Context
              activation in addition to the one already activated for a given
              APN (Access Point Name).</t>

              <t>If the requested PDP type and subscription data allows only
              one IP address family (IPv4 or IPv6), the cellular host MUST NOT
              request a second PDP-Context to the same APN for the other IP
              address family.</t>
            </list>The text above focuses on the specification part which
          explains the behavior for requesting IPv6-related PDP-Context(s).
          Understanding this behavior is important to avoid having broken IPv6
          implementations in cellular devices.</t>

          <t hangText="REQ#4:">The cellular host MUST support the PCO
          (Protocol Configuration Options) <xref target="TS.24008"></xref> to
          retrieve the IPv6 address(es) of the Recursive DNS server(s). <list
              style="empty">
              <t>In-band signaling is a convenient method to inform the
              cellular host about various services, including DNS server
              information. It does not require any specific protocol to be
              supported and it is already deployed in IPv4 cellular networks
              to convey such DNS information.</t>
            </list></t>

          <t hangText="REQ#5:">The cellular host MUST support IPv6 aware
          Traffic Flow Templates (TFT) <xref target="TS.24008"></xref>.<list
              style="empty">
              <t>Traffic Flow Templates are employing a packet filter to
              couple an IP traffic with a PDP-Context. Thus a dedicated
              PDP-Context and radio resources can be provided by the cellular
              network for certain IP traffic.</t>
            </list></t>

          <t hangText="REQ#6:">The device MUST support the Neighbor Discovery
          Protocol (<xref target="RFC4861"></xref> and <xref
          target="RFC5942"></xref>).<list style="empty">
              <t>This is a stronger form compared to what is specified in
              Section 5.2 and Section 12.2 of <xref
              target="RFC6434"></xref>.</t>

              <t>The support of Neighbor Discovery Protocol is mandatory in
              3GPP cellular environment as it is the only way to convey IPv6
              prefix towards the 3GPP cellular device.</t>

              <t>In particular, MTU (Maximum Transmission Unit) communication
              via Router Advertisement MUST be supported since many 3GPP
              networks do not have a standard MTU setting.</t>
            </list></t>

          <t hangText="REQ#7:">The cellular host MUST comply with Section
          5.6.1 of <xref target="RFC6434"></xref>. If the MTU used by cellular
          hosts is larger than 1280 bytes, they can rely on Path MTU discovery
          function to discover the real path MTU.</t>

          <t hangText="REQ#8:">The cellular host MUST support IPv6 Stateless
          Address Autoconfiguration (<xref target="RFC4862"></xref>) apart
          from the exceptions noted in <xref target="TS.23060"></xref> (3G)
          and <xref target="TS.23401"></xref> (LTE):<list style="empty">
              <t>Stateless mode is the only way to configure a cellular host.
              The GGSN must allocate a prefix that is unique within its scope
              to each primary PDP-Context.</t>

              <t>To configure its link local address, the cellular host MUST
              use the Interface Identifier conveyed in 3GPP PDP-Context setup
              signaling received from a GGSN/PGW. The cellular host may use a
              different Interface Identifiers to configure its global
              addresses (see also REQ#23 about privacy addressing
              requirement).</t>

              <t>For more details, refer to <xref target="RFC6459"></xref> and
              <xref target="I-D.ietf-v6ops-rfc3316bis"></xref>.</t>
            </list></t>

          <t hangText="REQ#9:">The cellular host MUST comply with Section 7.3
          of <xref target="RFC6434"></xref>.</t>

          <t hangText="REQ#10:">The cellular host MUST comply with Section
          7.2.1 of <xref target="RFC6434"></xref>.<list style="empty">
              <t>Stateless DHCPv6 is useful to retrieve other information than
              DNS.</t>

              <t>If <xref target="RFC6106"></xref> is not supported, the
              cellular host SHOULD retrieve DNS information using stateless
              DHCPv6 <xref target="RFC3736"></xref>.</t>
            </list></t>

          <t hangText="REQ#11:">If the cellular host receives the DNS
          information in several channels for the same interface, the
          following preference order MUST be followed:<list style="numbers">
              <t>PCO</t>

              <t>RA</t>

              <t>DHCPv6</t>
            </list></t>

          <t hangText="REQ#12:">The cellular host SHOULD support a method to
          locally construct IPv4-embedded IPv6 addresses <xref
          target="RFC6052"></xref>. A method to learn PREFIX64 SHOULD be
          supported by the cellular host. <list style="empty">
              <t>This solves the issue when applications use IPv4 referrals on
              IPv6-only access networks.</t>

              <t>In PCP-based environments, cellular hosts SHOULD follow <xref
              target="I-D.ietf-pcp-nat64-prefix64"></xref> to learn the IPv6
              Prefix used by an upstream PCP-controlled NAT64 device. If PCP
              is not enabled, the cellular host SHOULD implement the method
              specified in <xref
              target="I-D.ietf-behave-nat64-discovery-heuristic"></xref> to
              retrieve the PREFIX64.</t>
            </list></t>

          <t hangText="REQ#13:">The cellular host SHOULD implement the
          Customer Side Translator (CLAT, <xref target="RFC6877"></xref>)
          function which is compliant with <xref target="RFC6052"></xref><xref
          target="RFC6145"></xref><xref target="RFC6146"></xref>. <list
              style="empty">
              <t>CLAT function in the cellular host allows for IPv4-only
              application and IPv4-referals to work on an IPv6-only
              connectivity. CLAT function requires a NAT64 capability <xref
              target="RFC6146"></xref> in the core network.</t>
            </list></t>

          <t hangText="REQ#14:">The cellular device SHOULD embed a DNS64
          function <xref target="RFC6147"></xref>. <list style="empty">
              <t>Local DNS64 functionality allows for compatibility with DNS
              Security Extensions (DNSSEC, <xref target="RFC4033"></xref>,
              <xref target="RFC4034"></xref>, <xref target="RFC4035"></xref>).
              Means to configure or discover a PREFIX64 is also required on
              the cellular device as discussed in REQ#12.</t>
            </list></t>

          <t hangText="REQ#15:">The cellular host SHOULD support PCP <xref
          target="I-D.ietf-pcp-base"></xref>.<list style="empty">
              <t>The support of PCP is seen as a driver to save battery
              consumption exacerbated by keepalive messages. PCP also gives
              the possibility of enabling incoming connections to the cellular
              device. Indeed, because several stateful devices may be deployed
              in wireless networks (e.g., NAT and/or Firewalls), PCP can be
              used by the cellular host to control network-based NAT and
              Firewall functions which will reduce per-application signaling
              and save battery consumption.</t>
            </list></t>

          <t hangText="REQ#16:">When the cellular host is dual-stack connected
          (i.e., configured with an IPv4 address and IPv6 prefix), it SHOULD
          support means to prefer native IPv6 connection over connection
          established through translation devices (e.g., NAT44 and
          NAT64).<list style="empty">
              <t>When both IPv4 and IPv6 DNS servers are configured, a
              dual-stack host MUST contact first its IPv6 DNS server.</t>

              <t>Cellular hosts SHOULD follow the procedure specified in <xref
              target="RFC6724"></xref> for source address selection.</t>
            </list></t>

          <t hangText="REQ#17:">The cellular host SHOULD support Happy
          Eyeballs procedure defined in <xref target="RFC6555"></xref>.</t>

          <t hangText="REQ#18:">The cellular device MAY embed a BIH function
          <xref target="RFC6535"></xref> facilitating the communication
          between an IPv4 application and an IPv6 server.</t>
        </list></t>

      <section title="WLAN Connectivity Requirements">
        <t>It is increasingly common for cellular hosts have a WLAN interface
        in addition to their cellular interface. These hosts are likely to be
        connected to private or public hotspots. Below are listed some generic
        requirements:</t>

        <t><list hangIndent="7" style="hanging">
            <t hangText="REQ#19:">IPv6 MUST be supported on the WLAN
            interface. In particular, IPv6-only connectivity MUST be supported
            over the WLAN interface.<list style="empty">
                <t>Some tests revealed that IPv4 configuration is required to
                enable IPv6-only connectivity. Indeed, some cellular handsets
                can access a WLAN IPv6-only network by configuring first a
                static IPv4 address. Once the device is connected to the
                network and the wlan0 interface got an IPv6 global address,
                the IPv4 address can be deleted from the configuration. This
                avoids the device to ask automatically for a DHCPv4 server,
                and allows to connect to IPv6-only networks. Failing to
                configure an IPv4 address on the interface MUST NOT prohibit
                using IPv6 on the same interface.</t>

                <t>IPv6 Stateless Address Autoconfiguration (<xref
                target="RFC4862"></xref>) MUST be supported.</t>
              </list></t>

            <t hangText="REQ#20:">DHCPv6 client SHOULD be supported on WLAN
            interface.<list style="empty">
                <t>Refer to Section 7.2.1 of <xref
                target="RFC6434"></xref>.</t>
              </list></t>

            <t hangText="REQ#21:">WLAN interface SHOULD support Router
            Advertisement Options for DNS configuration (See Section Section
            7.3 of <xref target="RFC6434"></xref>).</t>

            <t hangText="REQ#22:">If the device receives the DNS information
            in several channels for the same interface, the following
            preference order MUST be followed: <list style="numbers">
                <t>RA</t>

                <t>DHCPv6</t>
              </list></t>
          </list></t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Advanced Requirements">
      <t></t>

      <t><list hangIndent="7" style="hanging">
          <t hangText="REQ#23:">The cellular host MUST be able to generate
          IPv6 addresses which preserve privacy. <list style="empty">
              <t>The activation of privacy extension (e.g., using <xref
              target="RFC4941"></xref>) makes it more difficult to track a
              host over time when compared to using a permanent Interface
              Identifier. Note, <xref target="RFC4941"></xref> does not
              require any DAD mechanism to be activated as the GGSN/PGW MUST
              NOT configure any global address based on the prefix allocated
              to the cellular host. </t>

              <t>Tracking a host is still possible based on the first 64 bits
              of the IPv6 address. Means to prevent against such tracking
              issues may be enabled in the network side. </t>
            </list></t>

          <t hangText="REQ#24:">The cellular host MUST support ROHC RTP
          Profile (0x0001) and ROHC UDP Profile (0x0002) for IPv6 (<xref
          target="RFC5795"></xref>). Other ROHC profiles MAY be
          supported.<list style="empty">
              <t>Bandwidth in cellular networks must be optimized as much as
              possible. ROHC provides a solution to reduce bandwidth
              consumption and to reduce the impact of having bigger packet
              headers in IPv6 compared to IPv4. </t>

              <t>"RTP/UDP/IP" ROHC profile (0x0001) to compress RTP packets
              and "UDP/IP" ROHC profile (0x0002) to compress RTCP packets are
              required for Voice over LTE (VoLTE) by IR.92.4.0 section 4.1
              <xref target="IR92"></xref>. Note, <xref target="IR92"></xref>
              indicates also the host must be able to apply the compression to
              packets that are carried over the radio bearer dedicated for the
              voice media.</t>
            </list></t>

          <t hangText="REQ#25:">The cellular host SHOULD support IPv6 Router
          Advertisement Flags Options (<xref target="RFC5175"></xref>).<list
              style="empty">
              <t>This is a stronger form compared to what is specified in
              <xref target="RFC6434"></xref>.</t>
            </list></t>

          <t hangText="REQ#26:">The cellular host MUST comply with Section 5.3
          of <xref target="RFC6434"></xref> and SHOULD support Router
          Advertisement extension for communicating default router preferences
          and more-specific routes as described in <xref
          target="RFC4191"></xref>.<list style="empty">
              <t>This function can be used for instance for traffic
              offload.</t>
            </list></t>
        </list></t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="cpe" title="Cellular Devices with LAN Capabilities">
      <t>This section focuses on cellular devices (e.g., CPE, smartphones or
      dongles with tethering features) which provide IP connectivity to other
      devices connected to them. In such case, all connected devices are
      sharing the same 2G, 3G or LTE connection. In addition to the generic
      requirements listed in <xref target="generic"></xref>, these cellular
      devices have to meet the requirements listed below.</t>

      <t><list hangIndent="7" style="hanging">
          <t hangText="REQ#27:">The cellular device MUST support Prefix
          Delegation capabilities <xref target="RFC3633"></xref> and MUST
          support Prefix Exclude Option for DHCPv6-based Prefix Delegation as
          defined in <xref target="RFC6603"></xref>. Particularly, it MUST
          behave as a Requesting Router. <list style="empty">
              <t>Cellular networks are more and more perceived as an
              alternative to fixed networks for home IP-based services
              delivery; especially with the advent of smartphones and 3GPP
              data dongles. There is a need for an efficient mechanism to
              assign shorter prefix than /64 to cellular hosts so that each
              LAN segment can get its own /64 prefix and multilink subnet
              issues to be avoided.</t>

              <t>In case a prefix is delegated to a cellular host using
              DHCPv6, the cellular device will be configured with two
              prefixes: <list style="empty">
                  <t>(1) one for 3GPP link allocated using SLAAC mechanism
                  and</t>

                  <t>(2) another one delegated for LANs acquired during Prefix
                  Delegation operation.</t>
                </list>Note that the 3GPP network architecture requires both
              the WAN (Wide Area Network) and the delegated prefix to be
              aggregatable, so the subscriber can be identified using a single
              prefix.</t>

              <t>Without the Prefix Exclude Option, the delegating router
              (GGSN/PGW) will have to ensure <xref target="RFC3633"></xref>
              compliancy (e.g., halving the delegated prefix and assigning the
              WAN prefix out of the 1st half and the prefix to be delegated to
              the terminal from the 2nd half).</t>
            </list></t>

          <t hangText="REQ#28:">The cellular device MUST be compliant with the
          CPE requirements specified in <xref target="RFC6204"></xref>.</t>

          <t hangText="REQ#29:">For deployments requiring to share the same
          /64 prefix, the cellular device SHOULD support <xref
          target="I-D.ietf-v6ops-64share"></xref> to enable sharing a /64
          prefix between the 3GPP interface towards the GGSN (WAN interface)
          and the LAN interfaces.</t>

          <t hangText="REQ#30:">The cellular device SHOULD support the
          Customer Side Translator (CLAT) <xref target="RFC6877"></xref>.
          <list style="empty">
              <t>Various IP devices are likely to be connected to cellular
              device, acting as a CPE. Some of these devices can be
              dual-stack, others are IPv6-only or IPv4-only. IPv6-only
              connectivity for cellular device does not allow IPv4-only
              sessions to be established for hosts connected on the LAN
              segment of cellular devices.</t>

              <t>In order to allow IPv4 sessions establishment initiated from
              devices located on LAN segment side and target IPv4 nodes, a
              solution consists in integrating the CLAT function in the
              cellular device. As elaborated in <xref
              target="generic"></xref>, the CLAT function allows also IPv4
              applications to continue running over an IPv6-only host.</t>
            </list></t>

          <t hangText="REQ#31:">If a RA MTU is advertised from the 3GPP
          network, the cellular device SHOULD relay that upstream MTU
          information to the downstream attached LAN devices in RA. <list
              style="empty">
              <t>Since 3GPP networks extensively use IP-in-IP/UDP GTP tunnels,
              the effective MTU is frequently effectively reduced to 1440
              bytes. While a host may generate packets with an MTU of 1500
              bytes, this results in undesirable fragmentation of the GTP
              IP/UDP packets.</t>

              <t>Receiving and relaying RA MTU values facilitates a more
              harmonious functioning of the mobile core network where end
              nodes transmit packets that do not exceed the MTU size of the
              mobile network&rsquo;s GTP tunnels.</t>

              <t><xref target="TS.23060"></xref> indicates providing a link
              MTU value of 1358 octets to the 3GPP cellular device will
              prevent the IP layer fragmentation within the transport network
              between the cellular device and the GGSN/PGW.</t>
            </list></t>
        </list></t>
    </section>

    <section title="APIs &amp; Applications">
      <t><list hangIndent="7" style="hanging">
          <t hangText="REQ#32:">Name resolution libraries MUST support both
          IPv4 and IPv6.<list style="empty">
              <t>In particular, the cellular host MUST support <xref
              target="RFC3596"></xref>.</t>
            </list></t>

          <t hangText="REQ#33:">Applications MUST be independent of the
          underlying IP address family.<list style="empty">
              <t>This means applications must be IP version agnostic.</t>
            </list></t>

          <t hangText="REQ#34:">Applications using URIs MUST follow <xref
          target="RFC3986"></xref>. For example, SIP applications MUST follow
          the correction defined in <xref target="RFC5954"></xref>.</t>
        </list></t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>The security considerations identified in <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-v6ops-rfc3316bis"></xref> and <xref
      target="RFC6459"></xref> are to be taken into account.</t>

      <t><list hangIndent="7" style="hanging">
          <t hangText="REQ#35:">If the cellular device provides LAN features,
          it SHOULD be compliant with the security requirements specified in
          <xref target="RFC6092"></xref>.</t>
        </list></t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="iana" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>This document does not require any action from IANA.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>Many thanks to H. Soliman, H. Singh, L. Colliti, T. Lemon, B.
      Sarikaya, M. Mawatari, M. Abrahamsson, P. Vickers, V. Kuarsingh, and J.
      Woodyatt for the discussion in the v6ops mailing list.</t>

      <t>Special thanks to T. Savolainen and J. Korhonen for the detailed
      review.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119"?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6434'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6106'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6052'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.4862'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.4941'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6145'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6146'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.3633'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6603'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.5175'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.4861'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.5954'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.3596'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6147'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.5795'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.5942'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.3736'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.4191'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.3986'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6724'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6535'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6555'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.3261'?>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6459'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6092'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6204'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.4033'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.4034'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.4035'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-v6ops-rfc3316bis'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-pcp-nat64-prefix64'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-behave-nat64-discovery-heuristic'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-pcp-base'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6877'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-v6ops-64share'?>

      <reference anchor="TS.23060" target="">
        <front>
          <title>General Packet Radio Service (GPRS); Service description;
          Stage 2</title>

          <author fullname="3GPP" surname="3GPP">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date day="0" month="September" year="2011" />
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="TS.24008" target="">
        <front>
          <title>Mobile radio interface Layer 3 specification; Core network
          protocols; Stage 3</title>

          <author fullname="3GPP" surname="3GPP">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date day="0" month="June" year="2011" />
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="TS.23401" target="">
        <front>
          <title>General Packet Radio Service (GPRS) enhancements for Evolved
          Universal Terrestrial Radio Access Network (E-UTRAN) access</title>

          <author fullname="3GPP" surname="3GPP">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date day="0" month="September" year="2011" />
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="TS.29060" target="">
        <front>
          <title>General Packet Radio Service (GPRS); GPRS Tunnelling Protocol
          (GTP) across the Gn and Gp interface</title>

          <author fullname="3GPP" surname="3GPP">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date day="0" month="September" year="2011" />
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="TS.29274" target="">
        <front>
          <title>3GPP Evolved Packet System (EPS); Evolved General Packet
          Radio Service (GPRS) Tunnelling Protocol for Control plane
          (GTPv2-C); Stage 3</title>

          <author fullname="3GPP" surname="3GPP">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date day="0" month="June" year="2011" />
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="TS.29281" target="">
        <front>
          <title>General Packet Radio System (GPRS) Tunnelling Protocol User
          Plane (GTPv1-U)</title>

          <author fullname="3GPP" surname="3GPP">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date day="0" month="September" year="2011" />
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="TS.23402" target="">
        <front>
          <title>Architecture enhancements for non-3GPP accesses</title>

          <author fullname="3GPP" surname="3GPP">
            <organization>UPnP Forum</organization>
          </author>

          <date day="0" month="September" year="2011" />
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="IR92"
                 target="http://www.gsma.com/newsroom/ir-92-v4-0-ims-profile-for-voice-and-sms">
        <front>
          <title>IR.92.V4.0 &ndash; IMS Profile for Voice and SMS</title>

          <author fullname="GSMA" surname="GSMA">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date day="0" month="March" year="2011" />
        </front>
      </reference>
    </references>

    <!--
-->
  </back>
</rfc>
