<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
     <!ENTITY rfc2104 PUBLIC ''
       'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2104.xml'>
     <!ENTITY rfc2119 PUBLIC ''
       'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml'>
     <!ENTITY rfc2406 PUBLIC ''
       'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2406.xml'>
     <!ENTITY rfc2407 PUBLIC ''
       'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2407.xml'>
     <!ENTITY rfc2409 PUBLIC ''
       'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2409.xml'>
     <!ENTITY rfc2410 PUBLIC ''
       'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2410.xml'>
     <!ENTITY rfc2412 PUBLIC ''
       'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2412.xml'>
     <!ENTITY rfc3979 PUBLIC ''
       'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3979.xml'>
     <!ENTITY rfc4879 PUBLIC ''
       'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4879.xml'>
     <!ENTITY rfc4301 PUBLIC ''
       'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4301.xml'>
     <!ENTITY rfc4306 PUBLIC ''
       'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4306.xml'>
     <!ENTITY rfc3264 PUBLIC ''
       'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3264.xml'>
     <!ENTITY rfc3394 PUBLIC ''
       'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3394.xml'>
     <!ENTITY rfc3548 PUBLIC ''
       'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3548.xml'>
     <!ENTITY rfc3550 PUBLIC ''
       'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3550.xml'>
     <!ENTITY rfc3610 PUBLIC ''
       'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3610.xml'>
     <!ENTITY rfc3602 PUBLIC ''
       'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3602.xml'>
     <!ENTITY rfc3686 PUBLIC ''
       'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3686.xml'>
     <!ENTITY rfc3830 PUBLIC ''
       'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3830.xml'>
     <!ENTITY rfc3711 PUBLIC ''
       'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3711.xml'>
     <!ENTITY rfc4563 PUBLIC ''
       'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4563.xml'>
     <!ENTITY rfc4753 PUBLIC ''
       'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4753.xml'>
     <!ENTITY rfc4754 PUBLIC ''
       'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4754.xml'>
     <!ENTITY rfc4771 PUBLIC ''
       'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4771.xml'>
     <!ENTITY rfc4568 PUBLIC ''
       'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4568.xml'>

     <!ENTITY rfc3686 PUBLIC ''
       'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3686.xml'>

     <!ENTITY rfc4106 PUBLIC ''
       'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4106.xml'>

     <!ENTITY rfc4303 PUBLIC ''
       'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4303.xml'>

     <!ENTITY rfc4543 PUBLIC ''
       'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4543.xml'>

     <!ENTITY rfc4868 PUBLIC ''
       'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4868.xml'>

     <!ENTITY rfc4869 PUBLIC ''
       'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4869.xml'>

     <!ENTITY rfc4835 PUBLIC ''
       'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4835.xml'>

     <!ENTITY rfc5282 PUBLIC ''
       'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5282.xml'>



     <!ENTITY I-D.wing-avt-dtls-srtp-key-transport SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.wing-avt-dtls-srtp-key-transport">
]>

<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>

<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc iprnotified="no" ?>
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?> 
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>

<rfc category="info" 
     docName="draft-mcgrew-esp-ah-algo-update-00.txt" 
     ipr="pre5378Trust200902" >

<front>
<title abbrev="IPsec Algorithms">
Updating ESP and AH Algorithm Requirements for Efficiency and Security
</title>

<author initials="D.A.M." surname="McGrew" fullname="David A. McGrew">
<organization>Cisco Systems</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street>510 McCarthy Blvd.</street>
<city>Milpitas</city>
<region>CA</region>
<code>95035</code>
<country>USA</country>
</postal>
<phone>(408) 525 8651</phone>
<email>mcgrew@cisco.com</email>
<uri>http://www.mindspring.com/~dmcgrew/dam.htm</uri>
</address>
</author>

<author initials="K." surname="Grewal" fullname="Ken Grewal">
<organization>Intel Corporation</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street>2111 NE 25th Avenue, JF3-232</street>
<city>Hillsboro </city>
<region>OR</region>
<code>97124</code>
<country>USA</country>
</postal>
<email>ken.grewal@intel.com</email>
</address>
</author>



<date month="February" year="2010" />

<area>Network</area>
<keyword>Cryptography</keyword>

<abstract>
<t>
This note defines an update to the ESP and AH algorithm requirements that
promotes efficiency, security, and interoperability, by recommending
the use of the Advanced Encryption Standard (AES) block cipher in the
Galois/Counter Mode (GCM) of operation.  It is an individual
submission, intended as input to future standards track work on
IPsec policy.
</t>
</abstract>
</front>
				
<middle>
<section title="Introduction">
<t>
This note describes and motivates a change to the "Cryptographic
Algorithm Implementation Requirements for Encapsulating Security
Payload (ESP) and Authentication Header (AH)",
<xref target="RFC4835"/>.  This note does not change the required algorithms;
rather, it replaces one SHOULD implement algorithm with another algorithm and
clarifies that a third algorithm (not mentioned in that RFC) is NOT RECOMMENDED.  
</t>
 <section title="Conventions Used In This Document">
<t>
The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
"SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
document are to be interpreted as described in <xref target="RFC2119"/>.
</t>
 </section>

</section>

<section title="New Algorithm Guidance">
<t>
This memo proposes the following guidance:
<list>
<t>
An ESP implementation SHOULD include AES-128-GCM.  The use of
HMAC-SHA-256, HMAC-SHA-384, or HMAC-SHA-512 is NOT RECOMMENDED.  An AH
implementation SHOULD include AES-182-GMAC, and the use of
HMAC-SHA-256, HMAC-SHA-384, or HMAC-SHA-512 is NOT RECOMMENDED.  This
guidance does not apply to uses of HMAC or SHA-2 outside of ESP or AH.
</t>
</list>
</t>
</section>

<section title="Rationale">
<t>
AES in Galois/Counter Mode of operation (AES-GCM)
<xref target="RFC4106"/> <xref target="RFC4543"/>
<xref target="RFC5282"/> should be recommended for use in ESP and AH,
because it provides higher efficiency than currently recommended
algorithms with equivalent security, and is required by newer IPsec
profiles <xref target="RFC4869"/>.
</t>
<t>
In order for ESP and AH implementations to realize the efficiency
benefits that GCM offers, it is important for IPsec to recognize the
sufficiency of that algorithm.  A major benefit of GCM is smaller
circuit size at high data rates.  However, this compactness will be
squandered if implementations have to additionally include the
circuits for less efficient algorithms.
</t>
<t>
Currently, AES in Counter Mode (AES-CTR) <xref target="RFC3686"/> is
recommended as a SHOULD in  <xref target="RFC4835"/>.  AES-CTR is a
useful algorithm because it admits efficient high speed
implementations.  However, it provides no authentication.  From
RFC3686: 
<list style="empty">
<t>
  "With AES-CTR, it is trivial to use a valid ciphertext to
  forge other (valid to the decryptor) ciphertexts. Thus, it is equally
  catastrophic to use AES-CTR without a companion authentication
  function. Implementations MUST use AES-CTR in conjunction with an
  authentication function, such as HMAC-SHA-1-96 [HMAC-SHA]."
</t>
</list>
Unfortunately, none of the authentication algorithms currently defined
for IPsec (HMAC, XCBC-MAC) admit efficient high speed implementations.
Thus the need for authentication undermines the efficiency of AES-CTR.
An unintended side effect is that users may be tempted to run AES-CTR
without authentication for performance reasons, even though the
standard says not to do so.
</t>
<t>
AES-GCM was designed specifically to overcome these problems.  It is a
"combined mode" in the ESP sense <xref target="RFC4303"/>, that
provides both encryption and authentication.  Internally, it combines
AES-CTR with an authentication mechanism that can be efficiently
implemented at high data rates.
</t>
<t>
At the time that RFC 4835 was published (April 2007), there was not
yet a stable normative reference for AES-GCM.  This may have motivated
the IPsec community to not put too much reliance on that algorithm in
its guidelines.  But November 2007 saw the publication of
"Recommendation for Block Cipher Modes of Operation: Galois/ Counter
Mode (GCM) and GMAC" <xref target="800-38D"/>, which removes any such
concern.  An additional change in favor of AES-GCM is its wide
adoption by cryptographic hardware and software suppliers.
</t>

<section title="Efficiency">
<t>
GCM can be efficiently implemented in hardware, because it can be
parallelized or fully pipelined with low latency, and it uses
relatively efficient GF(2^128) operations.   For more information
about performance in hardware, see the analysis of packet-processing
and hardware in Section 3 of <xref target="MV04"/>. 
</t>
<t>
Efficient software implementations are also possible.  With a modest
use of memory and a precomputed table, GCM can easily match the
performance of other encryption-and-authentication methods.  The
benchmarks of the popular Crypto++ library show that GCM with a 2Kb
table significantly outperforms the combination of HMAC-SHA-1 with any
AES encryption mode <xref target="DAI"/>.  (For the purposes of
comparison, one can consider GCM's authentication component, which is
called GMAC when used separately.  GMAC can be compared to HMAC-SHA-1,
SHA-256 and SHA-512.)
</t>
<t>
When specialized hardware or implementation techniques are available,
GCM is typically the most efficient alternative.  Kasper and Schwabe
recently published implementation strategies for modern CPUs that
include the most efficient software implementations of any
authentication encryption algorithm to date <xref target="KS09"/>.  A
recent report shows that AES-GCM can outperform the combination of
AES-CBC and HMAC-SHA-1 by over 40%, on platforms with cryptographic
instructions <xref target="AES-NI"/>.  The performance margin over
HMAC-SHA-256 or HMAC-SHA-512 would be even greater.
 </t>
</section>

<section title="HMAC-SHA-2">
<t>
The Secure Hash Standard, version 2 <xref target="FIPS-180-2"/>
defines the hash algorithms SHA-256, SHA-384, and SHA-512.  These
functions are similar to the SHA-1 hash function, but have higher
security goals.  These functions are unkeyed, but they can be used in
the HMAC algorithm <xref target="RFC2104"/> as a keyed message
authentication code.  The use of the hash function HASH in this manner
is denoted HMAC-HASH.
</t>
<t>
This memo suggests that IPsec explicitly put HMAC-SHA-256,
HMAC-SHA-384, and HMAC-SHA-512 in the "NOT RECOMMENDED for ESP or AH"
category, because those MACs neither necessary nor sufficient for
achieving the goals of efficiency, interoperability, and security.
There may be particular circumstances when these algorithms are
acceptable or even useful, but the full implications should be
understood and the case carefully weighed before implementing them.
Implications may include, e.g., higher power usage, higher circuit
cost, lower performance in software, and incompatibility with
implementations that do not, or can not, perform the additional
authentication due to their preference for more efficient algorithms.
This guidance applies only to the use of these algorithms in ESP and
AH; it does not apply to other uses described in
<xref target="RFC4868"/>.
</t>
<t>
AES-GCM is preferred over the use of AES-CTR with HMAC-SHA-256 for use
in ESP and AH, because the latter combination of algorithms is
considerably less efficient, and the former algorithm meets the
security requirements.  HMAC-SHA-1 is believed to be secure (recall
the "No Need for SHA-2" Open Letter <xref target="OL"/>), but as the
industry moves away from SHA1, HMAC-SHA-256 may be the first algorithm
that comes to mind for some users of IPsec.  A transition away from
SHA-1 for digital signatures is already underway; many users plan to
have that transition completed by the end of 2010 (see "Recommendation
for Applications Using Approved Hash Algorithms"
<xref target="800-107"/>, for example).
</t>
<t>
AES-CBC and HMAC-SHA1 are valuable because those algorithms are widely
implemented.  This suggests that it makes sense to rely on those
algorithms as mandatory-to-implement until the time comes when it
becomes necessary or desirable to stop using HMAC-SHA1.  AES-GCM could
be considered for use as a replacement to this combination of
algorithms, when that time comes.
</t>
</section>

</section>

<section title="Other Algorithms">
<t>
It may be desirable to revisit the advisability of other algorithms in
RFC 4835 such as HMAC-MD5-96.  However, these considerations are out
of scope of this note.
</t>
</section>

<section title="Security Considerations">
<t>
HMAC-SHA-256, HMAC-SHA-384, and HMAC-SHA-512 are believed 
to be secure.  The only reason that they are not recommended
is because they are less efficient.   No discredit to the
security of these functions should be inferred from
this guidance.
</t>
<t>
Internally, AES-GCM consists of AES-CTR encryption with an
authentication component that uses "universal hashing".  This
authentication method relies solely on well understood mathematical
properties of the hash function, rather than any unproven assumptions
about cryptographic properties.  In particular, AES-GCM makes no
cryptographic assumptions other than the suitability of AES as a
pseudorandom permutation, an assumption that is also shared by
AES-CTR.  Authentication using universal hashing is uncomplicated and
has been well understood in cryptographic theory for decades.  These
reasons have given confidence to the use of GCM in several standards,
including IEEE 802.1AE Ethernet MAC security, IEEE 1619 Security in
Storage, IPsec (ESP, AH, and IKE), and TLS.
</t>
<t>
GCM was in the vanguard of cryptographic standards that use universal
hashing for authentication.  While there was never any question about
the efficacy of universal hash based authentication, some commentators
pointed out system security aspects of GCM that are different than
those of other algorithms.  In particular, special care must be taken
to ensure the distinctness all of the nonce values used with a
particular GCM or GMAC key.  The standards describing the use of GCM
in ESP and AH already take these system security properties into
consideration; nonetheless, the interested reader can find more
background discussion in <xref target="MODES"/>.
</t>
<t>
An analysis of the security of GCM has been published
<xref target="MV04"/>; the reader interested in the precise security
claims is referred to that document.
</t>
</section>

<section title="IANA Considerations">
<t>
This note has no actions for IANA.  This section should be removed by
the RFC editor before publication as an RFC.
</t>
</section>

<!--
<section title="Acknowledgements">
<t>
Thanks to Ken Grewal and Paul Koning for constructive input.
</t>
</section>
-->

</middle>

<back>
  
  <references title="Normative References">
	
     <reference anchor="800-38D" 
		target="http://csrc.nist.gov/publications/nistpubs/800-38D/SP800-38D.pdf">
        <front>
          <title>Special Publication 800-38D: Recommendation for
                 Block Cipher Modes of Operation: Galois/Counter Mode
                 (GCM) and GMAC. </title>

          <author fullname="Morris Dworkin" initials="M." surname="Dworkin">
            <organization>U. S. National Institute of Standards and
            Technology (NIST)</organization>
          </author>

        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="U.S. National Institute of Standards and
              Technology (NIST) Special Publication (SP)"
		    value="800-38D"
                />
      </reference>

    &rfc2119;
    &rfc4106;
    &rfc4543;

    </references>

   <references title="Informative References">

    &rfc4835;
    &rfc4868;
    &rfc4869;
    &rfc5282;
    &rfc3686;
    &rfc2104;

     <reference anchor="FIPS-180-2" 
		target="http://csrc.nist.gov/publications/fips/fips180-2/fips180-2.pdf">
        <front>
          <title>
	    Announcing the SECURE HASH STANDARD 

	  </title>

          <author fullname="U. S. National Institute of Standards and Technology (NIST)" >
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

	  <date month="August" year="2002"/>
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="Federal Information Processing Standards (FIPS)"
		    value="180-2"
                />
      </reference>



	<reference anchor="800-107">
         <front>
           <title> Special Publication 800-107: Recommendation for
	     Applications Using Approved Hash Algorithms
	   </title>
	  <author fullname="Quynh Dang">
	      <organization/>
           </author>
	  <date year="2009"/>
         </front> <seriesInfo name="U.S. National Institute of
         Standards and Technology (NIST) Special Publication (SP)"
         value="800-107" />
        </reference>


        <reference anchor="MV04" target="http://eprint.iacr.org/2004/193">
        <front>
          <title>The Security and Performance of the Galois/Counter
          Mode (GCM)</title>
          <author initials="D.A." surname="McGrew" fullname="David A. McGrew">
              <organization/>
          </author>
          <author initials="J." surname="Viega" fullname="John Viega">
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <date month="December" year="2004"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="Proceedings of INDOCRYPT '04," value=""/>
        </reference>

	<reference anchor="KS09" target="http://www.cryptojedi.org/papers/aesbs-20090616.pdf">
         <front>
           <title> 
	     Faster and Timing-Attack Resistant AES-GCM
	   </title>
	  <author fullname="Emilia Kasper" surname="Kasper" initials="E.">
	      <organization/>
          </author>
	  <author fullname="Peter Schwabe" initials="P." surname="Schwabe">
	    <organization/>
          </author>
	  <date year="2009"/>
         </front> <seriesInfo name="Cryptographic Hardware and Embedded Systems -- CHES 2009"
         value="Spinger-Verlag Lecture Notes in Computer Science 5745"
         />
        </reference>

	<reference anchor="AES-NI">
         <front>
           <title> AES-NI: New Technology for Improving Encryption
          Efficiency and Enhancing Data Security in the Enterprise Cloud
	   </title>
	  <author fullname="Michael Kounavis" initials="M." surname="Kounavis">
	      <organization/>
           </author>
	  <date year="2009"/>
         </front> <seriesInfo name="Intel Developer Forum"
         value="https://intel.wingateweb.com/us09/scheduler/sessions.do?searchGroup=9&searchGroupID=10133&profileItem_id=10004"
         />
        </reference>

	<reference anchor="DAI" target="http://www.cryptopp.com/benchmarks.html">
         <front>
           <title> 
	     Crypto++ 5.6.0 Benchmarks
	   </title>
	  <author fullname="Wei Dai" initials="W." surname="Dai">
	      <organization/>
           </author>
	  <date year="2009"/>
         </front> <seriesInfo name="Web Page"
			      value="Speed Comparison of Popular Crypto Algorithms"
         />
        </reference>

	<reference anchor="OL" target="http://www.vpnc.org/ietf-ipsec/02.ipsec/msg01840.html">
         <front>
           <title> No Need for SHA-2
	   </title>
	  <author fullname="Russell Dietz, Editor"  surname="R. Dietz, Editor">
	      <organization/>
           </author>
	  <date year="2002"/>
         </front> <seriesInfo name="Open Letter to IPsec WG and Area Directors"
			      value="(email)"
         />
        </reference>


	<reference anchor="MODES" 
         target="http://csrc.nist.gov/groups/ST/toolkit/BCM/comments.html">
         <front>
           <title> Public Comments on the Draft GCM Specification, and
	     Comments on The Choice Between CWC or GCM
	   </title>
	  <author fullname="NIST Computer Security Division">
	      <organization/>
           </author>
	  <date year="2009"/>
         </front> <seriesInfo name="NIST Computer Security Division"
         value="Modes of Operation Comments"
         />
        </reference>

         &rfc4303;


   </references>


</back>
</rfc>
