<?xml version = '1.0'?>
<?rfc rfcedstyle='yes'?>
<?rfc rfcprocack='yes'?>
<?rfc toc='yes'?>
<?rfc symrefs='yes'?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "../xml2rfc-1.35pre1/rfc2629.dtd" [

      <!ENTITY rfc2119     PUBLIC '' '../rfc-bib/reference.RFC.2119.xml'>
      <!ENTITY rfc2865     PUBLIC '' '../rfc-bib/reference.RFC.2865.xml'>
      <!ENTITY rfc2866     PUBLIC '' '../rfc-bib/reference.RFC.2866.xml'>
      <!ENTITY rfc3268     PUBLIC '' '../rfc-bib/reference.RFC.3268.xml'>
      <!ENTITY rfc5176     PUBLIC '' '../rfc-bib/reference.RFC.5176.xml'>
      <!ENTITY rfc3588     PUBLIC '' '../rfc-bib/reference.RFC.3588.xml'>
      <!ENTITY rfc4279     PUBLIC '' '../rfc-bib/reference.RFC.4279.xml'>
      <!ENTITY rfc4346     PUBLIC '' '../rfc-bib/reference.RFC.4346.xml'>
      <!ENTITY rfc4985     PUBLIC '' '../rfc-bib/reference.RFC.4985.xml'>
      <!ENTITY rfc5246     PUBLIC '' '../rfc-bib/reference.RFC.5246.xml'>
      <!ENTITY rfc5280     PUBLIC '' '../rfc-bib/reference.RFC.5280.xml'>
      <!ENTITY radius-tcp  PUBLIC ''
'../i-d-bib/reference.I-D.dekok-radext-tcp-transport.xml'>
      <!ENTITY radius-dtls PUBLIC ''
'../i-d-bib/reference.I-D.draft-dekok-radext-dtls-02.xml'>
      <!ENTITY dyn-disc    PUBLIC ''
'../i-d-bib/reference.I-D.winter-dynamic-discovery.xml'>
    ]>
<rfc ipr='pre5378Trust200902' docName='draft-ietf-radext-radsec-07'
category='exp'>
  <front>
    <title abbrev="RADIUS over TLS" >TLS encryption for RADIUS</title>
    <author fullname="Stefan Winter" initials="S." surname="Winter" >
	<organization abbrev="RESTENA" >
		  Fondation RESTENA
	</organization>
	<address>
		<postal>
			<street>6, rue Richard Coudenhove-Kalergi</street>
			<city>Luxembourg</city>
			<code>1359</code>
			<country>LUXEMBOURG</country>
		</postal>
		<phone>+352 424409 1</phone>
		<facsimile>+352 422473</facsimile>
		<email>stefan.winter@restena.lu</email>
		<uri>http://www.restena.lu.</uri>
	</address>
    </author>
    <author fullname="Mike McCauley" initials="M." surname="McCauley" >
	    <organization abbrev="OSC" >
		    Open Systems Consultants
	    </organization>
	    <address>
		    <postal>
			    <street>9 Bulbul Place</street>
			    <city>Currumbin Waters</city>
			    <code>QLD 4223</code>
			    <country>AUSTRALIA</country>
		    </postal>
		    <phone>+61 7 5598 7474</phone>
		    <facsimile>+61 7 5598 7070</facsimile>
		    <email>mikem@open.com.au</email>
		    <uri>http://www.open.com.au.</uri>
	    </address>
    </author>
    <author fullname="Stig Venaas" initials="S." surname="Venaas" >
	<organization abbrev="UNINETT" >
		  UNINETT
	</organization>
	<address>
		<postal>
			<street>Abels gate 5 – Teknobyen</street>
			<city>Trondheim</city>
			<code>7465</code>
			<country>NORWAY</country>
		</postal>
		<phone>+47 73 55 79 00</phone>
		<facsimile>+47 73 55 79 01</facsimile>
		<email>stig.venaas@uninett.no</email>
		<uri>http://www.uninett.no.</uri>
	</address>
    </author>
    <author fullname="Klaas Wierenga" initials="K." surname="Wierenga" >
	    <organization abbrev="Cisco" >
		    Cisco Systems International BV
	    </organization>
	    <address>
		    <postal>
			    <street>Haarlerbergweg 13-19</street>
			    <city>Amsterdam</city>
			    <code>1101 CH</code>
			    <country>The Netherlands</country>
		    </postal>
		    <phone>+31 (0)20 3571752</phone>
		    <facsimile></facsimile>
		    <email>kwiereng@cisco.com</email>
		    <uri>http://www.cisco.com.</uri>
	    </address>
      </author>
    <date day="12" month="July" year="2010" />
    <area>Operations and Management Area</area>
    <workgroup>RADIUS Extensions Working Group</workgroup>
    <keyword>RADIUS</keyword>
    <keyword>AAA</keyword>
    <keyword>Security</keyword>
    <keyword>Reliability</keyword>
    <abstract>
	    <t>This document specifies security on the transport layer (TLS) for
the RADIUS protocol when transmitted over TCP. This enables dynamic trust
relationships between RADIUS servers.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>
  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction" anchor="intro">
	<t>The RADIUS protocol <xref target="RFC2865" /> is a widely deployed
authentication and authorisation protocol. The supplementary RADIUS Accounting
specification <xref target="RFC2866" /> also provides accounting mechanisms,
thus delivering a full AAA solution. However, RADIUS is experiencing several
shortcomings, such as its dependency on the unreliable transport protocol UDP
and the lack of security for large parts of its packet payload. RADIUS security
is based on the MD5 algorithm, which has been proven to be insecure.</t>
	
	<t>The main focus of RADIUS over TLS is to provide a means to secure the
communication between RADIUS/TCP peers on the transport layer. The most
important use of this specification lies in roaming environments where RADIUS packets need
to be transferred through different administrative domains and untrusted,
potentially hostile networks. An example for a world-wide roaming environment
that uses RADIUS over TLS to secure communication is "eduroam", see <xref
target="eduroam"/>.</t>
	
	<t>There are multiple known attacks on the MD5 algorithm which is used
in RADIUS to provide integrity protection and a limited confidentiality
protection (see <xref target="MD5-attacks" />). RADIUS over TLS wraps the entire RADIUS packet payload into a TLS stream and
thus mitigates the risk of attacks on MD5.</t> 
	
	<t>Because of the static trust establishment between RADIUS peers (IP
address and shared secret) the only scalable way of creating a massive
deployment of RADIUS-servers under control by different administrative entities
is to introduce some form of a proxy chain to route the access requests to their
home server. This creates a lot of overhead in terms of possible points of
failure, longer transmission times as well as middleboxes through which
authentication traffic flows. These middleboxes may learn privacy-relevant data
while forwarding requests. The new features in RADIUS over TLS obsolete the use of IP
addresses and shared MD5 secrets to identify other peers and thus allow the
dynamic establishment of connections to peers that are not previously
configured, and thus makes it possible to avoid aggregation-only RADIUS proxies
and reduce the number of middleboxes which can eavesdrop on traffic. One mechanism
to discover RADIUS over TLS peers with DNS is specified in <xref
target="I-D.winter-dynamic-discovery"/>.</t>
	<section title="Requirements Language" anchor="reqlang">
		<t>In this document, several words are used to signify the
requirements of the specification.  The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT",
"REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED",  "MAY",
and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in RFC 2119.
<xref target="RFC2119" /></t>
	</section>
	<section title="Terminology" anchor="terms">
		<t>RADIUS/TLS node: a RADIUS over TLS client or server</t>
		<t>RADIUS/TLS Client: a RADIUS over TLS instance which initiates a new
connection.</t>
		<t>RADIUS/TLS Server: a RADIUS over TLS instance which listens on a RADIUS over TLS
port and accepts new connections</t>
		<t>RADIUS/UDP: classic RADIUS transport over UDP as defined in <xref target="RFC2865" /></t>
	</section>
    </section>
    <section title="Normative: Transport Layer Security for RADIUS over TCP"
anchor="TLS">
	<section title="TCP port and packet types" anchor="ports">
		<t>The default destination port number for RADIUS over TLS is TCP/2083.
There are no separate ports for authentication, accounting and dynamic
authorisation changes. The source port is arbitrary.</t>
	</section>
	<section title="TLS negotiation" anchor="starttls">
		<t>RADIUS has no notion of negotiating TLS in an established connection. Servers and clients need to be preconfigured to use RADIUS/TLS for a given endpoint.</t>
	</section>
	<section title="Connection Setup" anchor="conn-setup">
		<t>RADIUS/TLS nodes
			<list style = "numbers">
				<t>establish TCP connections as per <xref
target="I-D.dekok-radext-tcp-transport" /></t>
				<t>immediately negotiate TLS sessions. The following restrictions apply:

according to <xref
target="RFC5246" /> or its predecessor TLS 1.1. The following restrictions
apply:
					<list style="symbols">
						<t>Support for TLS v1.1 <xref target="RFC4346"/> or later (e.g. TLS 1.2 <xref target="RFC5246"/>]) is REQUIRED.</t>
                                                <t>Support for certificate-based mutual authentication is REQUIRED.</t>
                                                <t>Negotiation of mutual authentication is REQUIRED.</t>
						<t>Negotiation of a ciphersuite providing for confidentiality as well as integrity protection is REQUIRED.</t>
						<t>Support for and negotiation of compression is OPTIONAL.</t>
						<t>Support for TLS-PSK mutual authentication <xref target="RFC4279"/> is OPTIONAL.</t>
						<t>RADIUS/TLS implementations MUST at a minimum support negotiation of the TLS_RSA_WITH_3DES_EDE_CBC_SHA), and SHOULD support TLS_RSA_WITH_RC4_128_SHA and TLS_RSA_WITH_AES_128_CBC_SHA as well (see <xref target="design-cipher" /> (1) ).</t>
						<t>In addition, RADIUS/TLS implementations MUST support negotiation of the mandatory-to-implement ciphersuites required by the versions of TLS that they support.</t>
					</list>
				</t>
				<t>
					If TLS is used in an X.509 certificate
based operation mode, the following list of certificate validation options
applies: <list style="symbols">
						<t>Implementations MUST allow to configure a list of acceptable Certification Authorities for incoming connections.  </t>
						<t>Certificate validation MUST include the verification rules as per <xref target="RFC5280" />.</t>
						<t>Implementations SHOULD indicate their acceptable Certification Authorities as per section 7.4.4 (server side) and x.y.z ["Trusted CA Indication"] (client side) of <xref target="RFC5246" />  (see <xref target="design-cert" />) </t>
						<t>
							Implementations SHOULD
allow to configure a list of acceptable certificates, identified via certificate
fingerprint. When a fingerprint configured, the fingerprint is prepended with an
  ASCII label identifying the hash function followed by a colon. Implementations
MUST support SHA-1 as the hash algorithm and use the ASCII label "sha-1" to
identify the SHA-1 algorithm.  The length of a SHA-1 hash is 20 bytes and the
length of the corresponding fingerprint string is 65 characters.  An example
certificate fingerprint is:    
sha-1:E1:2D:53:2B:7C:6B:8A:29:A2:76:C8:64:36:0B:08:4B:7A:F1:9E:9D
						</t>
						<t>
							Peer validation always
includes a check on whether the locally configured expected DNS name or IP
address of the server that is contacted matches its presented certificate. DNS
names and IP addresses can be contained in the Common Name (CN) or
subjectAltName entries. For verification, only one these entries is to be
considered. The following precedence applies: for DNS name validation,
subjectAltName:DNS has precedence over CN; for IP address validation,
subjectAltName:iPAddr has precedence over CN.
						</t>
						<t>
							Implementations SHOULD
allow to configure a set of acceptable values for subjectAltName:URI.
						</t>
					</list>
				</t>
				<t>
					start exchanging RADIUS datagrams. Note
<xref target="design-radius" /> (1) ). The shared secret to compute the
(obsolete) MD5 integrity checks and attribute encryption MUST be "radsec" (see
<xref target="design-radius" /> (2) ).
				</t>
			</list>
		</t>
	</section>
	<section title="Connecting Client Identity">
		<t>In RADIUS/UDP, clients are uniquely identified by their IP
address. The IP address alone does not permit the server to determine whether the connecting entity is a
NAS or a different server which proxies a request. When NAT is used on the path to
the server, it also does not permit to determine whether there is more than one
entity connecting from the same IP address.
		</t>
		<t>RADIUS/TLS makes it possible to preserve this traditional RADIUS
semantics by identifying a connecting client by the IP address which initiated
the TLS connection. In addition, it permits a much more fine-grained
identification. The parameters of the TLS connection can be attributed to the
RADIUS packets inside the TLS connection. An implementation of RADIUS/TLS
should expose as many details of the TLS connection which belongs to an incoming RADIUS packet as possible to the
application layer to allow the administrator to define the identification criteria
which are applicable to his desired operational model. In X.509 certificate operation, at least the following parameters of the TLS connection should be exposed:
		<list style= "symbols">
		  <t>Originating IP address</t>
		  <t>Certificate Fingerprint</t>
		  <t>Issuer</t>
		  <t>Subject</t>
		  <t>all X509v3 Extended Key Usage</t>
		  <t>all X509v3 Subject Alternative Name</t>
		  <t>all X509v3 Certificate Policies</t>
		</list>
In TLS-PSK operation, at least the following parameters of the TLS connection should be exposed:
		<list style= "symbols">
		  <t>Originating IP address</t>
		  <t>TLS Identifier</t>
		</list>
</t>
	</section>
	<section title="RADIUS Datagrams">
		<t>Authentication, Accounting and Authorization packets are sent
according to the following rules:</t>
		<t>RADIUS/TLS clients handle the following packet types from <xref
target="RFC2865" />, <xref target="RFC2866" />, <xref target="RFC5176" /> on the
connection they initiated (see <xref target="design-radius" /> (3) and (4) ):
			<list style= "symbols">
				<t>send Access-Request</t>
				<t>send Accounting-Request</t>
				<t>send Status-Server</t>
				<t>send Disconnect-ACK</t>
				<t>send Disconnect-NAK</t>
				<t>send CoA-ACK</t>
				<t>send CoA-NAK</t>
				<t>receive Access-Challenge</t>
				<t>receive Access-Accept</t>
				<t>receive Access-Reject</t>
				<t>receive Accounting-Response</t>
				<t>receive Disconnect-Request</t>
				<t>receive CoA-Request</t>
			</list></t>
		<t>RADIUS/TLS servers handle the following packet types from <xref
target="RFC2865" />, <xref target="RFC2866" />, <xref target="RFC5176" /> on the
connections they serve to clients:
			<list style= "symbols">
				<t>receive Access-Request</t>
				<t>receive Accounting-Request</t>
				<t>receive Status-Server</t>
				<t>receive Disconnect-ACK</t>
				<t>receive Disconnect-NAK</t>
				<t>receive CoA-ACK</t>
				<t>receive CoA-NAK</t>
				<t>send Access-Challenge</t>
				<t>send Access-Accept</t>
				<t>send Access-Reject</t>
				<t>send Accounting-Response</t>
				<t>send Disconnect-Request</t>
				<t>send CoA-Request</t>
			</list></t>
	</section>
</section>
	<section title="Informative: Design Decisions" anchor="design">
		<t>This section explains the design decisions that led to the
rules defined in the previous section.</t>
		<section title="X.509 Certificate Considerations"
anchor="design-cert">
			<t>
				(1) If a RADIUS/TLS client is in possession of
multiple certificates from different CAs (i.e. is part of multiple roaming
consortia) and dynamic discovery is used, the discovery mechanism possibly does
not yield sufficient information to identify the consortium uniquely (e.g. DNS
discovery). Subsequently, the client may not know by itself which client
certificate to use for the TLS handshake. Then it is necessary for the server to
signal which consortium it belongs to, and which certificates it expects. If
there is no risk of confusing multiple roaming consortia, providing this
information in the handshake is not crucial.
			</t>
			<t>
				(2) If a RADIUS/TLS server is in possession of
multiple certificates from different CAs (i.e. is part of multiple roaming
consortia), it will need to select one of its certificates to present to the
RADIUS/TLS client. If the client sends the Trusted CA Indication, this hint can make
the server select the appropriate certificate and prevent a handshake failure.
Omitting this indication makes it impossible to deterministically select the
right certificate in this case. If there is no risk of confusing multiple
roaming consortia, providing this indication in the handshake is not crucial.
			</t>
			<t>
				(3) If dynamic peer discovery as per <xref
target="I-D.winter-dynamic-discovery" /> is used, peer authentication alone is
not sufficient; the peer must also be authorised to perform user
authentications. In these cases, the trust fabric cannot depend on peer
authentication methods like DNSSEC to identify RADIUS/TLS nodes. The nodes
also need to be properly authorised. Typically, this can be achieved by adding
appropriate authorisation fields into a X.509 certificate. Such fields include
SRV authority <xref target="RFC4985" />, subjectAltNames, or a defined list of
certificate fingerprints. Operators of a RADIUS/TLS infrastructure should define
their own authorisation trust model and apply this model to the certificates.
The checks enumerated in <xref target="conn-setup" /> provide sufficient
flexibility for the implementation of authorisation trust models.
			</t>
	        </section>
		<section title="Ciphersuites and Compression Negotiation
Considerations" anchor="design-cipher">
			<t>Not all TLS ciphersuites in <xref target="RFC5246"/>
are supported by available TLS tool kits, and licenses may be required in some
cases. The existing implementations of RADIUS/TLS use OpenSSL as cryptographic
backend, which supports all of the ciphersuites listed in the rules in the
normative section.</t>
			<t>The TLS ciphersuite TLS_RSA_WITH_3DES_EDE_CBC_SHA is
mandatory-to-implement according to <xref target="RFC5246"/> and thus has to be
supported by RADIUS/TLS nodes.</t>
			<t>The two other ciphersuites in the normative section
are widely implemented in TLS toolkits and are considered good practice to
implement.</t>
	    </section>
	    <section title="RADIUS Datagram Considerations"
anchor="design-radius">
		    <t>(1) After the TLS session is established, RADIUS packet
payloads are exchanged over the encrypted TLS tunnel. In RADIUS/UDP, the
packet size can be determined by evaluating the size of the datagram that
arrived. Due to the stream nature of TCP and TLS, this does not hold true for
RADIUS/TLS packet exchange. Instead, packet boundaries of RADIUS packets that arrive
in the stream are calculated by evaluating the packet's Length field. Special
care needs to be taken on the packet sender side that the value of the Length
field is indeed correct before sending it over the TLS tunnel, because incorrect
packet lengths can no longer be detected by a differing datagram boundary. See
section 2.6.4 of <xref target="I-D.dekok-radext-tcp-transport" /> for more details.</t>
		    <t>(2) Within RADIUS <xref target="RFC2865"/>, a shared
secret is used for hiding of attributes such as User-Password, as well as in
computation of the Response Authenticator.  In RADIUS accounting <xref
target="RFC2866"/>, the shared secret is used in computation of both the Request
Authenticator and the Response Authenticator. Since TLS  provides integrity
protection and encryption sufficient to substitute for RADIUS application-layer
security, it is not necessary to configure a RADIUS shared secret. The use of a
fixed string for the obsolete shared secret eliminates possible node
misconfigurations.</t>
		    <t>(3) RADIUS <xref target="RFC2865" /> uses different UDP
ports for authentication, accounting and dynamic authorisation changes. RADIUS/TLS
allocates a single port for all RADIUS packet types. Nevertheless, in RADIUS/TLS the
notion of a client which sends authentication requests and processes replies
associated with it's users' sessions and the notion of a server which receives
requests, processes them and sends the appropriate replies is to be preserved.
The normative rules about acceptable packet types for clients and servers mirror
the packet flow behaviour from RADIUS/UDP.</t>
		    <t>(4) RADIUS <xref target="RFC2865" /> used negative ICMP
responses to a newly allocated UDP port to signal that a peer RADIUS server does
not support reception and processing of the packet types in <xref
target="RFC5176" />. These packet types are listed as to be received in RADIUS/TLS
implementations. Note well: it is not required for an implementation to actually
process these packet types. It is sufficient that upon receiving such a packet,
an unconditional NAK is sent back to indicate that the action is not
supported.</t>
		</section>
    </section>
    <section title="Compatibility with other RADIUS transports"
anchor="radius-compat">
	    <t>
		    Ongoing work in the IETF defines multiple alternative
transports to the classic UDP transport model as defined in <xref
target="RFC2865" />, namely RADIUS over TCP <xref
target="I-D.dekok-radext-tcp-transport" />, RADIUS over DTLS <xref
target="I-D.dekok-radext-dtls" /> and this present document on RADIUS over TLS.</t>
	    <t>
		    RADIUS/TLS does not specify any inherent backwards compatibility
to RADIUS/UDP or cross compatibility to the other transports, i.e. an
implementation which implements RADIUS/TLS only will not be able to receive or send
RADIUS packet payloads over other transports. An implementation wishing to be
backward or cross compatible (i.e. wishes to serve clients using other
transports than RADIUS/TLS) will need to implement these other transports along with the RADIUS/TLS
transport and be prepared to send and receive on all implemented transports,
which is called a multi-stack implementation.
	    </t>
	    <t>
		If a given IP device is able to receive RADIUS payloads on
multiple transports, this may or may not be the same instance of software, and
it may or may not serve the same purposes. It is not safe to assume that both
ports are interchangeable. In particular, it can not be assumed that state is
maintained for the packet payloads between the transports. Two such instances
MUST be considered separate RADIUS server entities.
	    </t>
	    <t>
		As a consequence, the selection of transports to communicate
from a client to a server is a manual administrative action. An automatic
fallback to RADIUS/UDP is NOT RECOMMENDED, as it may lead to down-bidding
attacks on the peer communication.
	    </t>
    </section>
    <section title="Diameter Compatibility" anchor="compat">
	    <t>
		    Since RADIUS/TLS is only a new transport profile for RADIUS,
compatibility of RADIUS/TLS - Diameter <xref target="RFC3588" /> vs. RADIUS/UDP <xref
target="RFC2865" /> - Diameter <xref target="RFC3588" /> is identical. The
considerations regarding payload size in <xref
target="I-D.dekok-radext-tcp-transport" /> apply.</t>
    </section>
    <section title="Security Considerations" anchor="security">
	    <t>
		    The computational resources to establish a TLS tunnel are
significantly higher than simply sending mostly unencrypted UDP datagrams.
Therefore, clients connecting to a RADIUS/TLS node will more easily create high load
conditions and a malicious client might create a Denial-of-Service attack more
easily.</t>
	    <t>
		    In the case of dynamic peer discovery as per <xref
target="I-D.winter-dynamic-discovery" />, a RADIUS/TLS node needs to be able to
accept connections from a large, not previously known, group of hosts, possibly
the whole internet. In this case, the server's RADIUS/TLS port can not be protected
from unauthorised connection attempts with measures on the network layer, i.e.
access lists and firewalls. This opens more attack vectors for Distributed
Denial of Service attacks, just like any other service that is supposed to serve
arbitrary clients (like for example web servers).
	    </t>
	    <t>
		    In the case of dynamic peer discovery as per <xref
target="I-D.winter-dynamic-discovery" />, X.509 certificates are the only proof
of authorisation for a connecting RADIUS/TLS nodes. Special care needs to be taken
that certificates get verified properly according to the chosen trust model
(particularly: consulting CRLs, checking critical extensions, checking
subjectAltNames etc.) to prevent unauthorised connections.
	    </t>
	    <t>
		    Some TLS ciphersuites only provide integrity validation of
their payload, and provide no encryption. This specification forbids the use of
such ciphersuites. Since the RADIUS payload's shared secret is fixed and
well-known, failure to comply with this requirement will expose the entire
datagram payload in plain text, including User-Password, to intermediate IP
nodes.
	    </t>
	    <t>
		    If peer communication between two devices is configured for
both RADIUS/TLS and RADIUS/UDP, a failover from TLS security to classic RADIUS security opens
the way for a down-bidding attack if an adversary can maliciously close the TCP
connection, or prevent it from being established. In this case, security of the
packet payload is reduced from the selected TLS cipher suite packet encryption
to the classic MD5 per-attribute encryption. Such an attack can be mitigated by
delisting the RADIUS/UDP client from the server configuration after successfully
migrating that client to RADIUS/TLS.
	    </t>
	    <t>
		    The RADIUS/TLS transport provides authentication and encryption
between RADIUS peers. In the presence of proxies, the intermediate proxies can
still inspect the individual RADIUS packets, i.e. "end-to-end" encryption is not
provided. Where intermediate proxies are untrusted, it is desirable to use other
RADIUS mechanisms to prevent RADIUS packet payload from inspection by such
proxies. One common method to protect passwords is the use of EAP methods which
utilize TLS.
	    </t>
    </section>
    <section title="IANA Considerations" anchor="iana">
	    <t>This document has no actions for IANA. The TCP port 2083 was
already previously assigned by IANA for RadSec, an early implementation of RADIUS/TLS. No new RADIUS attributes or
packet codes are defined.</t>
    </section>
    <section title="Acknowledgements" anchor="acks">
	    <t>RADIUS over TLS was first implemented as &quot;RADSec&quot; by Open Systems
Consultants, Currumbin Waters, Australia, for their &quot;Radiator&quot; RADIUS
server product (see <xref target="radsec-whitepaper" />).</t>
	    <t>Funding and input for the development of this Internet Draft was
provided by the European Commission co-funded project "GEANT2" <xref
target="geant2" /> and further feedback was provided by the TERENA Task Force
Mobility <xref target="terena" />.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>
  <back>
	  <references title="Normative References">
		  &rfc2119;
		  &rfc2865;
		  &rfc2866;
		  <!-- &rfc3268; -->
		  &rfc4279;
		  &rfc4346;
		  &rfc4985;
		  &rfc5280;
		  &rfc5176;
		  &rfc5246;
		  <!--	    <reference anchor="RFC4513">
			  <front>
				  <title>Lightweight Directory Access Protocol
(LDAP): Authentication Methods and Security Mechanisms</title>
				  <author initials="R." surname="Harrison"
fullname="Roger Harrison">
					  <organization abbrev="Novell">Novell,
Inc.</organization>
				  </author>
				  <date month="June" year="2006"/>
			  </front>
			  <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="4513" />
			  <format type="TXT" />
		  </reference> -->
		  <!--<reference anchor="draft-status-server"
target="http://www.ietf.org/internet-drafts/draft-dekok-radius-status-server-01.
txt">
			  <front>
				  <title>Use of Status-Server Packets in
RADIUS</title>
				  <author initials="A." surname="DeKok"
fullname="Alan DeKok">
					  <organization abbrev="FreeRADIUS">The
FreeRADIUS Server Project</organization>
				  </author>
				  <date month="February" year="2007"/>
			  </front>
			  <format type="TXT"
target="http://www.ietf.org/internet-drafts/draft-dekok-radius-status-server-01.
txt"/>
		  </reference>-->
		  &radius-tcp;
	  </references>
    <references title="Informative References">
	    &radius-dtls;
	    &dyn-disc;
	    &rfc3588;	
	<reference anchor="radsec-whitepaper"
target="http://www.open.com.au/radiator/radsec-whitepaper.pdf">
		<front>
			<title>RadSec - a secure, reliable RADIUS
Protocol</title>
			<author>
				<organization abbrev="OSC">Open System
Consultants</organization>
			</author>
			<date month="May" year="2005"/>
		</front>
		<format type="TXT"
target="http://www.open.com.au/radiator/radsec-whitepaper.pdf"/>
	</reference>
<reference anchor="MD5-attacks" target="http://www.springerlink.com/content/40867l85727r7084/">
                <front>
                        <title>A Study of the MD5 Attacks: Insights and Improvements</title>
                        <author initials="J." surname="Black" fullname="John Black">
                                <organization abbrev="Colorado">University of Colorado at Boulder, USA</organization>
                        </author>
			<author initials="M." surname="Cochran" fullname="Martin Cochran">
                                <organization abbrev="UColorado">University of Colorado at Boulder, USA</organization>
                        </author>
			<author initials="T." surname="Highland" fullname="Trevor Highland">
                                <organization abbrev="UTexas">University of Texas at Austin, USA</organization>
                        </author>
                        <date month="October" year="2006"/>
                </front>
                <format type="TXT" target="http://www.springerlink.com/content/40867l85727r7084/"/>
        </reference>
<!--	<reference anchor="radiator-manual"
target="http://www.open.com.au/radiator/ref.html">
		<front>
			<title>Radiator Radius Server - Installation and
Reference Manual</title>
			<author>
				<organization abbrev="OSC">Open System
Consultants</organization>
			</author>
			<date year="2006"/>
		</front>
		<format type="TXT"
target="http://www.open.com.au/radiator/ref.html"/>
	</reference> -->
<!--	<reference anchor="opendiameter" target="http://www.opendiameter.org/">
		<front>
			<title>Open Diameter</title>
			<author>
				<organization abbrev="ODP">Open Diameter
Project</organization>
			</author>
			<date year="2006"/>
		</front>
		<format type="TXT" target="http://www.opendiameter.org/"/>
	</reference>
	<reference anchor="jdiameter" target="https://jdiameter.dev.java.net/">
		<front>
			<title>JDiameter Project Homepage</title>
			<author initials="E." surname="Svenson" fullname="Erik
Svenson">
				<organization/>
			</author>
			<date year="2006"/>
		</front>
		<format type="TXT" target="https://jdiameter.dev.java.net/"/>
	</reference> -->
	<reference anchor="radsecproxy-impl"
target="http://software.uninett.no/radsecproxy/">
		<front>
			<title>radsecproxy Project Homepage</title>
			<author initials="S." surname="Venaas" fullname="Stig
Venaas">
				<organization
abbrev="UNINETT">UNINETT</organization>
			</author>
			<date year="2007"/>
		</front>
		<format type="TXT"
target="http://software.uninett.no/radsecproxy/"/>
	</reference>
	<reference anchor="eduroam" target="http://www.eduroam.org/">
		<front>
			<title>eduroam Homepage</title>
			<author>
				<organization abbrev="TERENA">Trans-European
Research and Education Networking Association</organization>
			</author>
			<date year="2007"/>
		</front>
		<format type="TXT" target="http://www.eduroam.org/"/>
	</reference>
	<reference anchor="geant2" target="http://www.geant2.net/">
		<front>
			<title>European Commission Information Society and
Media: GEANT2</title>
			<author>
				<organization abbrev="Dante">Delivery of
Advanced Network Technology to Europe</organization>
			</author>
			<date year="2008"/>
		</front>
		<format type="TXT" target="http://www.geant2.net/"/>
	</reference>
	<reference anchor="terena" target="http://www.terena.org/">
		<front>
			<title>Trans-European Research and Education Networking
Association</title>
			<author>
				<organization
abbrev="TERENA">TERENA</organization>
			</author>
			<date year="2008"/>
		</front>
		<format type="TXT" target="http://www.terena.org/"/>
	</reference>
    </references>	
    <section title="Implementation Overview: Radiator" anchor="radiator">
	    <t>Radiator implements the RadSec protocol for proxying requests
with the &lt;Authby RADSEC&gt; and &lt;ServerRADSEC&gt; clauses in the Radiator
configuration file.</t>
	    <t>The &lt;AuthBy RADSEC&gt; clause defines a RadSec client, and
causes Radiator to send RADIUS requests to the configured RadSec server using
the RadSec protocol.</t>
	    <t>The &lt;ServerRADSEC&gt; clause defines a RadSec server, and
causes Radiator to listen on the configured port and address(es) for connections
from &lt;Authby RADSEC&gt; clients. When an &lt;Authby RADSEC&gt; client
connects to a &lt;ServerRADSEC&gt; server, the client sends RADIUS requests
through the stream to the server. The server then handles the request in the
same way as if the request had been received from a conventional UDP RADIUS
client.</t>
	    <t>Radiator is compliant to version 2 of RadSec if the following
options are used:
	    	<list style="empty">
			<t>&lt;AuthBy RADSEC&gt;
				<list style="symbols">
					<t>Protocol tcp</t>
					<t>UseTLS</t>
					<t>TLS_CertificateFile</t>
					<t>Secret radsec</t>
				</list>
			</t>
			<t>&lt;ServerRADSEC&gt;
				<list style="symbols">
					<t>Protocol tcp</t>
					<t>UseTLS</t>
					<t>TLS_RequireClientCert</t>
					<t>Secret radsec</t>
				</list>
			</t>
		</list>
		As of Radiator 3.15, the default shared secret for RadSec
connections is configurable and defaults to "mysecret" (without quotes). For
compliance with this document, this setting needs to be configured for the
shared secret "radsec". The implementation uses TCP keepalive socket options,
but does not send Status-Server packets. Once established, TLS connections are
kept open throughout the server instance lifetime.
	    </t>
    </section>
    <section title="Implementation Overview: radsecproxy" anchor="radsecproxy">
	    <t>The RADIUS proxy named radsecproxy was written in order to allow
use of RadSec in current RADIUS deployments. This is a generic proxy that
supports any number and combination of clients and servers, supporting RADIUS
over UDP and RadSec. The main idea is that it can be used on the same host as a
non-RadSec client or server to ensure RadSec is used on the wire, however as a
generic proxy it can be used in other circumstances as well.</t>
	    <t>The configuration file consists of client and server clauses,
where there is one such clause for each client or server. In such a clause one
specifies either "type tls" or "type udp" for RadSec or UDP transport. For
RadSec the default shared secret "mysecret" (without quotes), the same as
Radiator, is used. For compliance with this document, this setting needs to be
configured for the shared secret "radsec". A secret may be specified by putting
say "secret somesharedsecret" inside a client or server clause.</t>
	    <t>In order to use TLS for clients and/or servers, one must also
specify where to locate CA certificates, as well as certificate and key for the
client or server. This is done in a TLS clause. There may be one or several TLS
clauses. A client or server clause may reference a particular TLS clause, or
just use a default one. One use for multiple TLS clauses may be to present one
certificate to clients and another to servers.</t>
	    <t>If any RadSec (TLS) clients are configured, the proxy will at
startup listen on port 2083, as assigned by IANA for the OSC RadSec
implementation. An alternative port may be specified. When a client connects,
the client certificate will be verified, including checking that the configured
FQDN or IP address matches what is in the certificate. Requests coming from a
RadSec client are treated exactly like requests from UDP clients.
	    </t>
	    <t>The proxy will at startup try to establish a TLS connection to
each (if any) of the configured RadSec (TLS) servers. If it fails to connect to
a server, it will retry regularly. There is some back-off where it will retry
quickly at first, and with longer intervals later. If a connection to a server
goes down it will also start retrying regularly. When setting up the TLS
connection, the server certificate will be verified, including checking that the
configured FQDN or IP address matches what is in the certificate. Requests are
sent to a RadSec server just like they would to a UDP server.</t>
	    <t>The proxy supports Status-Server messages. They are only sent to
a server if enabled for that particular server. Status-Server requests are
always responded to.</t>
	    <t>This RadSec implementation has been successfully tested together
with Radiator. It is a freely available open-source implementation. For source
code and documentation, see <xref target="radsecproxy-impl" />.</t>
</section>
  </back>
</rfc>
