<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY rfc2119 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc3261 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3261.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc3551 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3551.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc3761 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3761.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc3831 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3831.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc3840 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3840.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc3841 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3841.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc4103 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4103.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc4566 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4566.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc4975 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4975.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc5194 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5194.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.hellstrom-text-turntaking SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.hellstrom-text-turntaking.xml">
]>
<rfc category="bcp" docName="draft-hellstrom-txtgwy-02" ipr="trust200902">
  <?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>

  <?rfc toc="yes" ?>

  <!-- <?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
	<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?> -->

  <?rfc iprnotified="no" ?>

  <?rfc strict="yes" ?>

  <?rfc compact='yes'?>

  <front>
    <title abbrev="Real-time text in SIP gateway calls">Real-time text
    interworking between PSTN and IP networks</title>

    <author fullname="Gunnar Hellstrom" initials="G." surname="Hellstrom">
      <organization>Omnitor</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>

          <street>Box 92054</street>

          <code>120 06</code>

          <city>Stockholm</city>

          <region></region>

          <country>SE</country>
        </postal>

        <phone>+46-8-58900056</phone>

        <email>gunnar.hellstrom@omnitor.se</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Barry Dingle" initials="B." surname="Dingle">
      <organization></organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>3 Cosmo Court</street>

          <street></street>

          <code>3137</code>

          <city>Kilsyth</city>

          <region></region>

          <country>AU</country>
        </postal>

        <phone>+61-3-9725-3937</phone>

        <email>btdingle@gmail.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Arnoud van Wijk" initials="A.T." surname="van Wijk">
      <organization>Real-Time Text Taskforce (R3TF)</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>

          <street></street>

          <code></code>

          <city></city>

          <region></region>

          <country>NL</country>
        </postal>

        <phone></phone>

        <email>arnoud@realtimetext.org</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Guido Gybels" initials="G.G." surname="Gybels">
      <organization>RNID, Department of New Technologies</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>19-23 Featherstone Street</street>

          <street></street>

          <code>EC1Y 8SL</code>

          <city>London</city>

          <region></region>

          <country>UK</country>
        </postal>

        <phone>+44-20-7294 3713</phone>

        <email>guido.gybels@rnid.org</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date day="8" month="March" year="2010" />

    <abstract>
      <t>IP networks can support real-time text communication. SIP-based real-
      time text is called Text-over-IP or ToIP. PSTN networks support
      real-time text using textphones (or TTYs). When real-time text is
      supported by different networks, gateways are needed to provide
      interoperability. Real-time text capable gateways may also support
      real-time voice.</t>

      <t>This specification describes procedures for interworking between ToIP
      and PSTN textphones using a real-time text capable gateway (RTT
      gateway). It also describes ways to route calls to RTT gateways for
      several call scenarios.</t>

      <t>Procedures that support the phased introduction of RTT gateways and
      procedures that support the invocation of text channels at any time
      during the call are included. Interworking of PSTN textphones that do
      not support simultaneity of voice and text with IP User Agents that
      support simultaneous voice and text is also described.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

<middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
        <t>Real-time text can be a component in IP multimedia telephony and total conversation. Real-time
	  text can be transported in IP networks using standard IP protocols and
	  be used as a medium in a conversational service. IP devices such as multimedia
	  telephones, voicemail systems, IP phones, IVR systems or other devices,
	  may support the transmission of real-time text over IP networks. An IP
	  User Agent that supports real-time text over IP is called a ToIP User
	  Agent. A ToIP User Agent may also support text and voice.</t>

	<t>The control of IP real-time text calls is defined in SIP 
	  <xref target="RFC3261">RFC 3261</xref> and SDP 
	  <xref target="RFC4566">RFC 4566</xref>. 
	  <xref target="RFC4103">RFC 4103</xref>
	  specifies the carriage of real-time text in RTP packets between ToIP
	  devices in IP networks. RFC 5194 <xref target="RFC5194"> </xref> describes the implementation
	  aspects of ToIP using SIP.</t>
	
	<t>PSTN networks can support the transport of real-time text by
	  representing the text as audio. PSTN textphones (or TTYs) use modem
	  technology to carry the text encoded as tones. Some PSTN textphones can
	  support the transport of both voice and real-time text, but usually not
	  both at the same time. Some PSTN textphone protocols do not include
	  signalling to indicate whether or not the device is in text or voice
	  mode and therefore it is unclear if the audio signal is to be treated as
	  text or as voice.</t>
	
	<t>Interworking between the different forms of real-time text transport
	  and the different call control protocols requires a real-time text
	  capable gateway (RTT gateway). It supports ToIP (and possibly VoIP)
	  protocols on the IP side and textphone protocols on the PSTN side.</t>
	
	<t>PSTN textphones and multimedia IP User Agents usually support the
	  transport of both voice and real-time text. For calls that support both
	  voice and text media, the gateway needs to consider the lack of media
	  simultaneity imposed by some PSTN textphone protocols and include procedures
        to support medium interworking.</t>
	
	<t>The case where ToIP support is not provided at all PSTN/IP gateways that could be selected to
	  convey the call is also considered. It requires specific routing actions for calls that may contain text.</t>
    </section>
    
    <!-- If you use the the following keywords, add the following "Terminology" section. Don't forget to add the reference to RFC2119 -->

    <section title="Terminology">
        <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
	  "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
	  document are to be interpreted as described in 
	  <xref target="RFC2119">RFC 2119</xref>.</t>

        <section title="Abbreviations">
            <t>RTT real-time text</t>

            <t>ToIP text over IP</t>

            <t>PSTN public switched telephone network</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Definitions">
            <t>TTY: term used in some countries for PSTN textphone.</t>

	</section>
    </section>

    <section title="Functional goals of the procedures">
        <t>The procedures described in this specification are designed to meet
	  the following functional requirements. 
	  <list style="symbols">
            <t>The real-time text transport in the IP network shall use ToIP as
              specified by RFC 5194 <xref target="RFC5194"></xref>.</t>
	    
            <t>The text medium shall be able to be established at any time
              during the call for gateways that support text and voice.</t>
	    
            <t>The voice medium shall be able to be established at any time
              during the call for gateways that support text and voice.</t>
        </list></t>
    </section>
    
    <section title="Scope">
      <t>This specification describes the procedures for call routing, call
	control and media transport of real-time text calls between Text-over-
	IP (ToIP) User Agents and PSTN textphones (or TTYs) using real-time text
	capable (RTT) gateways. It specifies how to discover the RTT gateways
	from the PSTN and IP sides and how to invoke the text capability in
	them. It also specifies how to control media interaction between PSTN
	and IP for calls that involve both real-time text and voice.</t>
      
      <t></t>
    </section>
    
    <section title="Locating RTT gateways ">
        <t></t>
      
        <section title="Types of RTT gateways">
            <t>Text capable gateways can be located in at least the following
              distinctively different locations:</t>

            <t>
	        <list style="numbers">
		    <t>a residential text capable gateway with PSTN terminals
		      directly connected to it</t>

		    <t>a network text capable gateway that has PSTN technology on
		      one side and IP technology on the other</t>
		    
		    <t>a network text capable gateway that is in the IP network
		      that has text transported to it from the PSTN that is still in
		      audio (modem tones) format but carried by IP transport (e.g. G.711
		      <xref target="RFC3551"></xref> A-law encoded audio) and with high QoS.</t>
                </list>
	    </t>
	</section>
	<section title="Locating a gateway">
            <t></t>
            <section title="From the IP side">
                <t>A call to a PSTN number will require the use of a gateway. If not
		  all PSTN/IP gateways are text capable, then some means of routing to
		  a RTT gateway is required. The methods resulting in one step calling
		  should be preferred. The following mechanisms are possible:</t>
		
		<t>Option 1: Indications are used in the SIP header to indicate that
		  text capability may be required. RFC 3840 <xref target="RFC3840"></xref> and RFC 3841 <xref target="RFC3841"></xref>
		  provide a means of doing that.</t>
		
		<t>Option 2: ENUM RFC 3761 <xref target="RFC3761"></xref> procedures may be used to identify
		  and route to RTT gateways.</t>
		
		<t>Option 3: Addressing is used consisting of the PSTN number as the
		  user name and the RTT gateway as the SIP domain address on the form
		  number@gateway_domain.</t>
		
		<t>Option 4: Dial a special RTT gateway address. The gateway answers
		  in text mode. Then enter the destination number when requested by
		  the RTT gateway using text.</t>
            </section>

            <section title="From the PSTN side">
                <t></t>
		
		<t>If a PSTN textphone is not directly connected to a RTT gateway or
              if not all PSTN/IP gateways that are candidates for handling the call
              are text capable, then some means of routing to a RTT gateway is
              required. Most PSTN textphone calls appear as ordinary audio telephone
              calls and do not provide an indication that a call could involve text.
              A means of indicating the possible need to support real-time text to
              the PSTN routing procedures is required. Several options are
              available, the ones resulting in a one-step procedure should be
              preferred</t>
	    
            <t>Option 1 - Use a prefix to destination number (e.g. 18001 +
              'destination number')</t>
	    
            <t>Option 2 - Dial a special RTT gateway address. The gateway answers
              in text mode. Then enter the destination number or address when
              requested by the RTT gateway using text.</t>
	    
            <t>Option 3 - A PSTN line marking of 'text' that is carried by the
              signalling</t>
	    
            <t>Option 4 - The call routing made after number analysis that results 
in that a call to a real-time text user is routed through the text gateway located in the IP network.</t>
	    
            <t>Option 5 - The destination SIP subscriber has an indication on SIP registration level or call control level that
              text support is required.</t>
	    
            <t></t>

            </section>
	    
            
	</section>
    </section>
    
    <section title="SIP Call control">
        <t></t>
      
	<section title="SIP and SDP text indicators">
            <t>SIP User Agents and RTT gateways SHALL announce support for
              real-time text in the Contact field according to RFC 3840 <xref target="RFC3840"></xref> by sending the following in an INVITE:</t>
	    
            <t>
	      <list style="empty">
	          <t>Contact: &lt;uri&gt;;text</t>
            </list>
	    </t>

            <t>A calling ToIP User Agent that does not want to give priority to
              text can indicate an interest to use text according to RFC 3841 <xref target="RFC3841"></xref> by
              sending the following in a Response to an INVITE:</t>
	    
            <t>
	        <list style="empty">
		    <t>Accept-Contact: *;text</t>
		</list>
	    </t>
	    
            <t>A calling ToIP User Agent should indicate priority to establishing
              a text connection according to RFC 3841 <xref target="RFC3841"></xref> by sending the following
              in a Response to an INVITE:</t>
	    
        <t>
	    <list style="empty">
                <t>Accept-Contact: *;text;require</t>
            </list>
	</t>

        <t>PSTN textphones can support alternating text and audio during the
          call. If this capability is known, the RTT gateway can indicate it
          according to RFC 3840 <xref target="RFC3840"></xref> by sending an indication in the call setup as specified in draft-hellstrom-text-turntaking <xref
        target="I-D.hellstrom-text-turntaking"></xref>.</t>
	
        <t>This indication will allow ToIP User Agents to inform users of the
          need to communicate in a turn-taking manner.</t>
	
        <t></t>
	</section>
	
	<section title="SIP/SDP Call procedures">
            <t>The decision to include text when offering the call may be
              because:</t>
	  
            <t>a. textphone tones have already been detected by the gateway on the PSTN line.</t>
	    
            <t>b. the gateway may be configured to be a dedicated RTT gateway.</t>
	    
            <t>c. it is known by subscription or other external means that the
              PSTN user has preference for text</t>
	    
            <t>d. it is simpler to offer text initially.</t>
	    
            <t>Note - the examples below do not include all SIP and SDP fields.
              They concentrate on the fields needed for ToIP operation and VoIP
              operation (if required).</t>
	    
            <t>The audio medium description in the examples assumes ITU-T G.711
              A-law encoding.</t>
	    
            <section title="Calls from the PSTN">
              <t></t>
	      
                <section title="Text-only call">
		    <t></t>
		    
		    <t>When a RTT gateway has information that indicates that only a
		  text medium is required, it SHALL include specifications in line
		  with this example in an INVITE:</t>
		
		<t><list style="empty">
		  <t>Contact: &lt;sip:gw-uri&gt;;text</t>
		  
		  <t>...</t>
		  
		  <t>m=text 7202 RTP/AVP 99 98</t>
		  
		  <t>a=rtpmap:98 t140/1000</t>
		  
		  <t>a=rtpmap:99 red/1000</t>
		  
              <t>a=fmtp:99 98/98/98</t>
              </list></t>

		<t>The answering ToIP User Agent SHALL accept the text medium by
		  including specifications according to this example in its
		  Response:</t>
		
		<t><list style="empty">
		    <t>Contact: &lt;sip:term-uri&gt;;text</t>
		    
		    <t>...</t>
		    
		    <t>m=text 7202 RTP/AVP 99 98</t>
		    
              <t>a=rtpmap:98 t140/1000</t>

              <t>a=rtpmap:99 red/1000</t>

              <t>a=fmtp:99 98/98/98</t>
            </list></t>

          <t></t>

		</section>
	      
		

          <section title="Call with text and voice">
            <t>If the RTT gateway has an indication that voice and text media
            are required in the call, it SHALL include a media line for audio
            and a media line for text in an INVITE in line with the following
            example:</t>

            <t><list style="empty">
                <t>Accept-Contact: *;text;require</t>

                <t>Contact: &lt;sip:gw-uri&gt;;text</t>

                <t>...</t>

                <t>m=audio 7200 RTP/AVP 0</t>

                <t>m=text 7202 RTP/AVP 99 98</t>

                <t>a=rtpmap:98 t140/1000</t>

                <t>a=rtpmap:99 red/1000</t>

                <t>a=fmtp:99 98/98/98</t>
              </list></t>

            <t>The answering ToIP device can accept the audio and the text
            media by sending the following in the Response:</t>

            <t><list style="empty">
                <t>Contact: &lt;sip:term-uri&gt;;text</t>

                <t>...</t>

                <t>m=audio 7200 RTP/AVP 0</t>

                <t>m=text 7202 RTP/AVP 99 98</t>

                <t>a=rtpmap:98 t140/1000</t>

                <t>a=rtpmap:99 red/1000</t>

                <t>a=fmtp:99 98/98/98</t>
              </list></t>
          </section>

          <section title="Voice call with text added later">
            <t>A RTT gateway that wishes to establish an audio medium and
            indicate support for text but does not wish to establish a text
            medium immediately e.g. in order to avoid spending resources for
            text transport on calls that do not carry text at all, SHOULD send
            an INVITE with contents in line with the following example:</t>

            <t><list style="empty">
                <t>Contact: &lt;sip:gw-uri&gt;;text</t>

                <t>....</t>

                <t>m=audio 7200 RTP/AVP 0</t>
              </list></t>

            <t>The answering ToIP device can indicate text support and accept
            the audio medium by including lines in line with the following
            example in the Response to the INVITE:</t>

            <t><list style="empty">
                <t>Contact: &lt;sip:term-uri&gt;;text</t>

                <t>.....</t>

                <t>m=audio 7200 RTP/AVP 0</t>
              </list></t>

            <t>Then the text medium can be added later in the call.</t>
          </section>

        </section>

        <section title="Call from a ToIP User Agent">
          <t></t>

          <section title="Text-only call">
            <t>A calling ToIP User Agent can indicate that a text medium is
            required in the call by sending an INVITE based on the following
            example:</t>

            <t><list style="empty">
                <t>Contact: &lt;sip:term-uri&gt;;text</t>

                <t>Accept-Contact: *;text;require</t>

                <t>...</t>

                <t>m=text 7202 RTP/AVP 99 98</t>

                <t>a=rtpmap:98 t140/1000</t>

                <t>a=fmtp:98 cps=20</t>

                <t>a=rtpmap:99 red/1000</t>

                <t>a=fmtp:99 98/98/98</t>
              </list> The network will route the call to a RTT gateway if the
            destination address is in the PSTN and the Contact indicates
            'text'. The RTT gateway should then commence call establishment
            procedures on the PSTN side.</t>

            <t>The RTT gateway can accept the text request by sending the
            following in the Response:</t>

            <t><list style="empty">
                <t>Contact: &lt;sip:gw-uri&gt;;text</t>

                <t>....</t>

                <t>m=text 7202 RTP/AVP 99 98</t>

                <t>a=rtpmap:98 t140/1000</t>

                <t>a=fmtp:98 cps=20</t>

                <t>a=rtpmap:99 red/1000</t>

                <t>a=fmtp:99 98/98/98</t>
              </list></t>
          </section>

          <section title="Text and voice call">
            <t>A calling ToIP User Agent can request a text medium and a voice
            medium in a call by including a media line for audio and a media
            line for text in an INVITE as follows:</t>

            <t><list style="empty">
                <t>Contact: &lt;sip:term-uri&gt;;text</t>

                <t>Accept-Contact: *;text;require</t>

                <t>...</t>

                <t>m=audio 7200 RTP/AVP 0</t>

                <t>m=text 7202 RTP/AVP 99 98</t>

                <t>a=rtpmap:98 t140/1000</t>

                <t>a=fmtp:98 cps=20</t>

                <t>a=rtpmap:99 red/1000</t>

                <t>a=fmtp:99 98/98/98</t>
              </list></t>

            <t>The network will route the call to a RTT gateway if the
            destination address is in the PSTN.</t>

            <t>The answering RTT gateway can accept the text medium and the
            audio medium by sending the following in the Response:</t>

            <t><list style="empty">
                <t>Contact: &lt;sip:gw-uri&gt;;text</t>

                <t>Accept-Contact: *;text;require</t>

                <t>...</t>

                <t>m=audio 7200 RTP/AVP 0</t>

                <t>m=text 7202 RTP/AVP 99 98</t>

                <t>a=rtpmap:98 t140/1000</t>

                <t>a=rtpmap:99 red/1000</t>

                <t>a=fmtp:99 98/98/98</t>
              </list></t>
          </section>

          <section title="Voice call with text added later">
            <t>If a calling ToIP device user is not depending on text, but
            wants to have it available for occasional use, the INVITE that is
            sent could include the following:</t>

            <t><list style="empty">
                <t>Contact: &lt;sip:term-uri&gt;;text</t>

                <t>Accept-Contact: *;text</t>

                <t>...</t>

                <t>m=audio 7200 RTP/AVP 0</t>

                <t>m=text 7202 RTP/AVP 99 98</t>

                <t>a=rtpmap:98 t140/1000</t>

                <t>a=fmtp:98 cps=20</t>

                <t>a=rtpmap:99 red/1000</t>

                <t>a=fmtp:99 98/98/98</t>
              </list></t>

            <t>The RTT gateway may decide to not establish the text channel
            initially, but should indicate its text capability in the Contact
            header of the Response as follows:</t>

            <t><list style="empty">
                <t>Contact: &lt;gwy-uri&gt;;text</t>

                <t>Accept-Contact: *;text</t>

                <t>....</t>

                <t>m=audio 7200 RTP/AVP 0</t>

                <t>m=text 0 RTP/AVP 99 98</t>
              </list></t>

            <t>During a call, if either party starts text activity, a text
            channel can be added to the session by sending a re-Invite
            according to RFC 3261 <xref target="RFC3261"></xref>. This procedure can be executed even if
            no text capability was expressed from the ToIP User Agent
            initially. A re-INVITE from the gateway could include the
            following:</t>

            <t><list style="empty">
                <t>Contact: &lt;uri&gt;;text</t>

                <t>...</t>

                <t>m=audio 7200 RTP/AVP 0</t>

                <t>m=text 7202 RTP/AVP 99 98</t>

                <t>a=rtpmap:98 t140/1000</t>

                <t>a=fmtp:98 cps=20</t>

                <t>a=rtpmap:99 red/1000</t>

                <t>a=fmtp:99 98/98/98</t>
              </list></t>

            <t>The receiving device should answer with a Response that
            includes the following:</t>

            <t><list style="empty">
                <t>Contact: &lt;uri&gt;;text</t>

                <t>...</t>

                <t>m=audio 7200 RTP/AVP 0</t>

                <t>m=text 7202 RTP/AVP 99 98</t>

                <t>a=rtpmap:98 t140/1000</t>

                <t>a=fmtp:98 cps=20</t>

                <t>a=rtpmap:99 red/1000</t>

                <t>a=fmtp:99 98/98/98</t>
              </list></t>
          </section>
        </section>


      </section>

      <section title="Procedure for RFC 4103 and other real-time text transports">
        <t>In the case where a User Agent implements both <xref
        target="RFC4103">RFC 4103</xref> and other codecs for text transport,
        the procedures in this specification can be complemented with the
        other transport establishment. When establishing a call, a ToIP device
        may advertise support for real-time text in accordance with other
        transport methods, and for real-time Text over IP according to the
        procedures described above.</t>

        <t>The capabilities of the other party in the call setup will lead to
        the establishment of text transport according to either <xref
        target="RFC4103">RFC 4103</xref> or the other transport method, or both.</t>

        <t></t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Text medium interworking">
      <t>Many PSTN textphones can support both voice and text on the one
      analog 'voice' channel. The voice and the text make use of the channel
      in an alternating fashion. This direction dependence is however a usage
      convention, while the transmission can be made in either direction. In
      most cases, voice is used in one direction and text in the other
      direction, for example a hearing impaired user talks to an relay
      operator, who then replies in text.</t>

      <t>ITU-T V.18 <xref target="V.18">V.18</xref> specifies a range of PSTN textphone protocols that
      could be supported. On the IP side, text and voice are carried in
      separate text and voice media.</t>

      <t>The RTT gateway must be able to:</t>

      <t>a) indicate to the ToIP User Agent if the PSTN textphone operates in
      an alternating text and voice mode so that the IP User can be informed
      and communicate appropriately, and</t>

      <t>b) indicate to the ToIP User Agent if turntaking of text in one
      direction and text in the other direction is required by the PSTN
      textphone. The RTT gateway shall decode the characters received and
      transmit them to the ToIP User Agent.</t>

      <t>Determining the type of PSTN textphone device in use is the
      responsibility of the RTT gateway. The ToIP User Agent need not concern
      itself with what kind of PSTN textphone device is connected to the RTT
      gateway.</t>

      <t>When the ToIP User Agent first has characters to send to the RTT
      gateway the ToIP device shall open the text channel if it was not opened
      before. The ToIP device shall then transmit the characters to the RTT
      gateway. The RTT gateway shall perform any required signaling on the
      PSTN termination if the type of PSTN textphone s needed to be known by
      the RTT gateway. While connecting, the RTT gateway shall buffer any
      characters received from the ToIP User Agent and transmit them when the
      RTT gateway has connected to the PSTN textphone. The size of the
      character buffer should be sufficient to hold the characters that may
      come from one side in a connection before a response is expected.</t>

      <t>If the RTT gateway does not support the modulation used by the PSTN
      textphone device, the RTT gateway may:</t>

      <t>a) transmit the received textphone signals via Voiceband Data (VBD)
      or the audio stream, depending on the capabilities of the ToIP User
      Agent.</t>

      <t>b) discard characters received from the ToIP User Agent.</t>

      <t>c) transmit the received characters to the PSTN textphone based on a
      pre-provisioned indication of the modulation.</t>

      <t></t>

      <section title="Handling of alternating text and audio">
        <t>Many PSTN textphones support alternating voice and real-time text.
        Some PSTN textphones can only handle text transmission in one
        direction at a time. Most ToIP User Agents can send text and voice
        simultaneously and in both directions at the same time. When bridging
        between these two environments, turn-taking schemes must be introduced
        both by the human users and by the RTT gateways. The following
        procedures should be applied:</t>

        <t></t>

        <section title="Non-continuous carrier PSTN textphones">
          <t>For these PSTN textphones, audio is transmitted through the RTT
          gateway between the PSTN circuit and the audio stream of the ToIP
          User Agent. This is done as long as there is no text to transmit or
          receive on the PSTN side. Text transmission and reception has
          priority over audio transmission.</t>
        </section>


        <section title="Continuous-carrier PSTN textphones">
          <t>For these PSTN textphones, the recommended procedure is:</t>

          <t>As long as carrier is maintained from the PSTN textphone, it is
          maintained from the RTT gateway, and text transmission can occur. If
          carrier is dropped from the PSTN textphone, the RTT gateway shall
          transmit any remaining characters to the PSTN textphone and then
          drop the carrier and transmit audio.</t>

          <t>When carrier is received again from the PSTN textphone and if
          text is to be transmitted to the PSTN textphone, carrier
          transmission will be resumed from the gateway and text may be
          transmitted.</t>

          <t>If, during a period of audio transmission, text is received from
          the ToIP device, then audio transmission will be interrupted,
          carrier re- established and the text transmitted.</t>

          <t>If, during a period of carrier or text transmission, the
          Interrupt command (INT) is received in the <xref
          target="T.140">T.140</xref> stream from the ToIP User Agent, the
          carrier should be dropped and transmission of audio through the
          gateway established. In most cases the control of the carrier can be
          left to the PSTN textphone user.</t>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>TBD.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Security Considerations">
      <t>TBD</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <reference anchor="T.140">
        <front>
          <title>Recommendation T.140, Protocol for Multimedia Application
          Text Conversation and Addendum 1</title>

          <author fullname="" initials="" surname="">
            <organization>ITU-T</organization>
          </author>

          <date month="February" year="2000" />
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="V.18">
        <front>
          <title>Operational and interworking requirements for DCEs operating in the text telephone mode</title>
          <author fullname="" initials="" surname="">
            <organization>ITU-T</organization>
          </author>
          <date month="November" year="2000" />
        </front>
      </reference>
      
      &rfc2119;
      
      &rfc3261;

	&rfc3551;

      &rfc3761;
      
      &rfc3840;
      
      &rfc3841; 
      
      &rfc4103;
      
      &rfc4566;
      
      &rfc4975;
      
      &rfc5194;

      &I-D.hellstrom-text-turntaking;


    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
