<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">

<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>

<?rfc strict='yes'?>
<?rfc toc='yes'?>
<?rfc symrefs='yes'?>
<?rfc sortrefs='yes'?>
<?rfc iprnotified="no" ?>
<?rfc compact='yes'?>
<?rfc subcompact='no'?>

<rfc ipr="trust200902" docName="draft-masinter-dated-uri-08" category="info">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="The 'tdb' and 'duri' URI schemes">The 'tdb' and 'duri' URI schemes, based on dated URIs</title>
    <author initials="L." surname="Masinter" fullname="Larry Masinter">
      <organization>Adobe</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>345 Park Ave</street>
          <city>San Jose</city><region>CA</region>
          <code>95110</code>
          <country>US</country>
        </postal>
        <phone>+1 408 536 3024</phone>
        <email>LMM@acm.org</email>
        <uri>http://larry.masinter.net</uri>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date year="2011" />
    <area>Applications</area>
    
    <abstract>
    <t> This document defines two URI schemes. The first,
   'duri' (standing for "dated URI"), identifies a resource
   as of a particular time. This allows explicit
   reference to the "time of retrieval", similar to the way
   in which bibliographic references containing URIs are often written.
   </t><t>The second scheme, 'tdb' ( standing for
   "Thing Described By"), provides a way of
   minting URIs for something by the means of 
   identifying a description as of a particular time.
</t>
    </abstract>
    <note title="Note">

  <t> This document is not a product of any working group. Many of the
  ideas here have been discussed since 2001. Versions of this document
  have been discussed on the mailing list &lt;uri@w3.org&gt;. Previous
  versions have couched 'tdb' and 'tdb' as URN namespaces, used
  different syntax for timestamps, and handled URIs with fragment
  identifiers differently.
  </t>
    </note>
  </front>
  <middle>
    
<section anchor="overview" title="Overview and Requirements">

<t>This document is not a product of any working group. Many of the
  ideas here have been discussed since 2001. The practical application
  of the URI schemes defined here is uncertain, but enough interest
  has been expressed in having a stable reference for these concepts
  that it seems worthwhile to publish these.
</t>

<t>Versions of this document have been discussed on the mailing list
  &lt;uri@w3.org&gt; and &lt;www-tag@w3.org&gt;. Previous versions
  have couched 'tdb' and 'tdb' as URN namespaces, used different
  syntax for timestamps, and handled URIs with fragment identifiers
  differently.
</t>

<t>The URI schemes defined here address several related problems:</t>

<section title="Persistent identifiers">

<t> <xref target="RFC1737"/> defined several requirements for Uniform
  Resource Names. In particular, it requires "persistence":

  <list style="empty">

   <t>
     Persistence: It is intended that the lifetime of a URN be
     permanent.  That is, the URN will be globally unique forever, and
     may well be used as a reference to a resource well beyond the
     lifetime of the resource it identifies or of any naming authority
     involved in the assignment of its name.
  </t>
  </list>

 </t>
  <t>  Many people have wondered how to create globally unique and
  persistent identifiers. There are a number of URI schemes and URN
  namespaces already registered. However, guarantees of
  both uniqueness and persistence are difficult.
  </t><t>
  In some cases, the guarantee of persistence comes through a promise
  of good management practice, such as is encouraged in <xref 
  target="COOL">"Cool URIs don't change"</xref>.
  </t>
<t>
  A primary design goal for URIs is that they are intended to mean the
  same thing, no matter in what context they appear: that is the "Uniform"
  of "Uniform Resource Identifier". 
  However, even when URIs have "Uniform" meaning
  independent of the context of use, they don't usually
  guarantee stability over time. Despite best efforts and intentions,
  the mechanisms of resolution are subject to change in unpredictable ways:
  domain names can disappear or be reassigned, name resolving organizations
  can change in structure or responsibility, can disappear, merge, or change
   in other unpredictable ways.
  </t>
  
  <t>
  The interpretation of most URNs depend significantly on the reliable
  behavior of name assignment and resolution authorities. The authorities
  are usually individuals or organizations trusted initially first to insure 
  the uniqueness of assignment (so that the same name is not
  latter assigned for a different resource), and secondly to
   reliably maintain the link between the name and the named.
  </t>
  
  <t>
  However, assignment and resolution authorities (whether individuals
  or organizations) have a lifetime. The functioning of identifiers as
  unique holders of meaning depends on having a reliable
  infrastructure for the authority to maintain records, and for anyone
  to contact the authority or the authority's records to determine the
  thing identified.
  </t>
  
</section>
<section title="URIs for anything">
<t>

 The description of URIs <xref target="RFC3986" /> describes a
  range for 'Resource' that is quite broad:
<list style="empty">
 <t>
     This specification does not limit the scope of what might be a
      resource; rather, the term "resource" is used in a general sense
      for whatever might be identified by a URI.  Familiar examples
      include an electronic document, an image, a source of information
      with a consistent purpose (e.g., "today's weather report for Los
      Angeles"), a service (e.g., an HTTP-to-SMS gateway), and a
      collection of other resources.
   A resource is not necessarily
      accessible via the Internet; e.g., human beings, corporations, and
      bound books in a library can also be resources.  Likewise,
      abstract concepts can be resources, such as the operators and
      operands of a mathematical equation, the types of a relationship
      (e.g., "parent" or "employee"), or numeric values (e.g., zero,
      one, and infinity).

 </t>
</list>
  However, no means is given for constructing URIs with such
  a range. How, then, might one construct a URI that identifies
  a human being, a corporation, or the value 'zero'?
</t>
<t>
  One might wish to use a URI such as 'mailto' URI to identify
  a person, or use a 'http' URI to identify an abstract concept,
  with the indirection determined by context. 

  Doing so, however, leaves the open the question of how one might
  identify, within the same context, both the system mailbox
   and the person to which it is assigned; both the resource
  reached via the HTTP protocol as determined by the 'http' URI
  and also the concept that resource describes.
</t><t>
   The 'tdb' URI scheme allows one to mint a
  URIs for things that are distinguished from the media
  content that describes them.
  The 'tdb' URI scheme attempts to provide a mechanism which is, at the same time:
<list style="hanging">
<t hangText="permanent:" > The meaning of the URI doens't change over time.
</t>

<t hangText="objective:" > What's meant by the URI, or how it's to be
interpreted, is explicit in the URI.
</t>

<t hangText="useful for non-networked things: ">
 Allows identification of resources outside the network:
      people, organizations, places, things, even abstract concepts.
</t>
<t hangText="no long-term administration requirement: ">

 The mechanism does not depend on administrative processes of
 authorities for reliable interpretation over time.
</t>
 
</list>
</t>

</section>
</section>

<section anchor="syntax" title="Syntax">
<t>A 'duri' URI takes the form:</t>
<figure>
<artwork>     duri:&lt;timestamp&gt;:&lt;embeddedURI&gt;
</artwork>
</figure>
<t> and A 'tdb' URI takes a similar form:</t>
<figure>
<artwork>     tdb:&lt;timestamp&gt;:&lt;embeddedURI&gt;
</artwork>
</figure>

<t>&lt;embeddedURI&gt; is an absoluteURI (as defined in <xref target="RFC3986"/>).</t>

<t>Note that the &lt;embeddedURI&gt; in duri and tdb URIs does not allow embedded fragment identifiers.</t>

<t>A &lt;timestamp&gt; in these URI schemes consists of a restricted
  subset of date times, as per <xref target="RFC3339" />.</t>

<figure><artwork>
  timestamp = date [ "T" time "Z" ]
  date       =date-fullyear [ "-" date-month [ "-" date-mday ]]
  time       = time-hour  [ ":" time-minute 
               [ ":" time-second [ time-secfrac ]]]
</artwork></figure>

<t>where non-terminals "date-fullyear", "date-month", "date-mday",
 "time-hour", "time-minute", "time-second", "time-secfrac"
are taken from <xref target="RFC3339" />.

 The goal is to allow relatively short
  expressions with no ambiguity, but also allow arbitrary
  precision. While shorter forms are available (e.g.,
  year-only timestamps), it is possible to use forms that 
  are exactly compatible with <xref target="RFC3339" /> "date-time"
  non-terminal.
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="semantics" title="Semantics">

<section anchor="duri-meaning" title="'duri' Semantics">
  

<t>  The meaning of a 'duri' URI is "the resource that was
  identified by the &lt;embeddedURI&gt; at the
  the time given".
</t><t>
  
  For example, "duri:2001:http://www.ietf.org" is a persistent
  identifier to the resource identified by "http://www.ietf.org"
   as of (the end of) 2001. 
</t>
</section>
<section anchor="tdb-meaning" title="'tdb' Semantics">
<t>
  The 'tdb' URI scheme is intended to be useful
  for describing entities, concepts, abstractions, and other things
  which may not themselves be network accessible resources, but
  are (or at least have been at some point) described by network
  accessible resources.
</t>
  
<t>
  Thus, a 'tdb' URI is most useful when the &lt;embeddedURI&gt;
  identifies a 'document' of some sort (something a person could read, peruse,
  understand), and where the document thus identified describes some
  thing or concept. The 'tdb' URI itself then identifies the subject
  of that document. This is similar to the common practice of giving a 
  reference for a concept by including a pointer to a document
  phrase that defines the concept.
</t>
  
<t>
  For example, one might use "tdb:2009:http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/IETF" as
  a persistent identifier for the Internet Engineering Task
  Force (at least as described by the Wikipedia article as of
  2009).
</t>
<t>
   The 'tdb' URI scheme can be thought of as giving
  a way to invoke a level of semantic indirection to URI resolution.
</t>
<t>Expressed in RDF, one might consider 
<figure><artwork>
    &lt;duri:T:U;&gt; foaf:primaryTopic &lt;tdb:T:U&gt;
</artwork></figure>
where '-- foaf:primaryTopic --' is read '-- has, as its primary topic, --' (<xref target="FOAF" /> term "primaryTopic").
</t>
</section>
  
<section anchor="timestamp-semantics" title="Timestamp Semantics">
<t>
  It is conventional in references and citations in printed
  works to include the date of publication; this practice
  provides important context.   <xref target="MANSTYLE" />.
</t>


  <t>One can use 'tdb' without a date;  doing so does leave
  the possibility that a reference that is unambiguous at one time
  might become ambiguous at some other time. There are two ways that
  the date is useful for 'tdb' URIs: it fixes the time of access of
  the resource (and thus time variations of the description), and it
  fixes the time of interpretation, for descriptions whose meaning
  might vary. Thus, timestamps are useful in 'tdb' even when the
  resource identification does not vary (as with 'data' URIs).
</t>

<t>
While normally, in a literary work in natural language which makes
a reference to another work, both the reference itself and the
work referenced are dated, e.g., a footnote in an article
written in 1967 might talk about a "private communication" which
itself had a date. The difference between a URI and a conventional
literary reference is the desire to be able to extract the URI
from its context and still retain its meaning.
</t>


<t>
  The meaning of a timestamp is the interval specified by the
  granularity of the time range indicated, in the UTC time zone,
  as described in <xref target="RFC3339" />.
   If necessary, timestamps can
  include times and even fractional times, so that a generator of
  'duri' or 'tdb' URIs can be arbitrarily precise.
</t><t>
 If there is any ambiguity of the resource within the range of 
 time indicated (for example, if the timestamp consists only of
 a year, and the resource changes over the course of the year), then
 the last available resource state within the the range
 indicated should be used.
</t>
  
<t>Timestamps are allowed to be specified with as much precision as
needed. This keeps most 'duri' and 'tdb' URIs relatively short.</t>

</section>

</section>
<section title="Use as a Locator">
  
<t>  A 'duri' URI is not directly useful as a resource locator,
 since many resources vary their content over time.
</t>
  
<t> A 'tdb' URI is not a resource locator in a practical sense,
since it explicitly requires interpretation of the description.
However, it allows one to know that  a resource was described at some
point in time; whether the description is still available,
or whether that description is still meaningful, is not guaranteed.
</t>
</section>

<section title="Hierarchy">
<t>
  For 'tdb', the "thing described by" a resource may bear little
  relationship to the "thing described by" a relative pointer,
  so the 'tdb' URI scheme seems to have no use cases for
  using "/" as a hierarchical delimiter.
</t>
<t>
  However, 'duri' URIs can often be used with
  relative URI references with some amount of reliability. 
</t>

</section>

<section anchor="additional" title="Additional Considerations">
<section title="Embedded URI schemes">
<t>

  The 'tdb' scheme is primarily useful when the &lt;embeddedURI&gt;
  identifies an "information resources".
</t>

<t>
  For example, a 'http' URI might refer to a web
  page or the subject of a web as it was described at the given time.
  This can be a way of referring to a web site at some time in the
  past, or an organization that has changed, merged, split, or
  disappeared.
</t>

<t>
  A 'file' URI with a known-to-be unique host name might also be used 
  within a 'tdb' URI, for example, </t>
<figure><artwork>
    tdb:2001-08-14T14:23:27Z:file://this.example.com/c|/temp/test.txt
</artwork></figure>
  <t>This use is primarily focused on providing a unique way of
  identifying something, even if the referent 
  is not widely known. (Using 'file' URIs in this way without a fully
  qualified domain name as the authority would not be appropriate,
   because the interpretation is not uniform even at any particular
   instant.)
</t>
<t>
  One might consider using 'tdb' with a 'data' URI to designate concepts
  that can be described uniquely with brief inline text. For example, </t>
<figure><artwork>
     tdb:2001:data:,The%20US%20president
</artwork></figure>
  
  <t> names the concept described by the (text/plain) string "The US
  president" at the end of 2001. Of
  course, this practice is only useful if the referent of the data is
  (or was at the time) unique. Since a 'data' URI does not
  contain a way to designate content-language, the string in question
  should be unambiguous as to its language.  In the case of
  'data' URIs, there is no assigning authority at all; the interpretation
  of the 'tdb' depend on the interpreting community.
</t>

<t> Using 'duri' with an embedded 'urn' might not seem to be too useful,
  but it might be useful where the assignment of names in a URN
  namespace are not, in practice, permanent, and one wants to
  refer to the assignment as of a given date. In this case, it is
  possible to use a "urn" within a 'duri', e.g., </t>
<figure><artwork>
      duri:2000:urn:ietf:std:50
</artwork></figure>
 <t>  might be used to refer to "the document that the IETF considered to be STD 50, at the end of 2000".

</t><t>
  For use with 'tdb', many URIs identify resources which do not clearly describe
  anything at all. Even when there is a description of something, care should be given; for example,
  the home page for an organization might not be
  as good a resource to use to describe an organization
  as the organization's "about" page or an external authority's
  description of the organization. It is up to the minter
  of a 'tdb' URI to choose wisely.
</t>
</section>

<section title="Useful timestamps">

<t>
  Timestamps in the future are suspect, because the future
  content of a description resource cannot usually
  be reliably predicted.  Timestamps which preceed
  the availability of the description resource should
  not be used either.  For example, using a http URI with
  a timestamp before the description resource has been
  created is also   not recommended.
</t><t>
  
  However, although these practices are not recommended, there is no
  assurance that they haven't been used; by itself, a 'tdb' URI by
  itself does not constitute an assertion that the description
  resource was available or assigned at the date specified.
  
</t><t>
  Note that the use of the "last available state" allows for the 
  conventional bibliographic convention that a work published
  in 2009 can use "2009" as the date string, to refer to the
  work in the year of publication.  

</t>
</section>
<section title="Free assignment">
<t>
  Because of the many possible schemes that can be used in the
  embedded URI, there should be no difficulty in almost any
  computational process being able to assign 'duri' or 'tdb' URIs at will. Of
  course, it is necessary for there to be some resource which is
  available at some point in time, and to have a clock which is
  accurate to the granularity of the frequency of assignment.
  
</t>
</section>
<section anchor="resolution" title="Resolution">
<t>
  There are no direct resolution servers or processes for 'duri' or
  'tdb' URIs. However, a 'duri' URI might be "resolvable" in the sense
  that a resource that was accessed at a point in time might have the
  result of that access cached or archived in an Internet archive
  service. See, for example, the "Internet Archive" project <xref
  target="archive" />. And a 'tdb' URI is "resolvable" to the extent
  that the description resource can be accessed and interpreted.
</t>
  
<t> Clients without access to an Internet archive service might take
  the embedded URI of a 'duri' and attempt resolution
  of that identifier. This will give an approximation whose
  reliability depends on the what has happened in the time since the
  date indicated.
</t>

</section>
<section anchor="ambiguousResources" title="Ambiguous Resources">
<t>
There are many URIs which are, unfortunately, not particularly
"uniform", in the sense that two clients can observe
completely different content for the same resource, at exactly the
same time.  These resources are not so useful with 'tdb' URIs, since
time alone is not adequate to identify precisely because the
results of access depends on other details of the observation (e.g., IP address, cookies, HTTP request headers, which physical server responded, etc.).
That is, for 'tdb' URIs, there are two possible sources of instability, the URI to resource
mapping and the resource to representation relationship, since
the "description" is carried in a representation. </t>

<t> 
Non uniform-resources are also problematic with 'duri' URIs, because
archival services are unlikely to preserve all of the variants
and conditions of variability.
</t>

</section>

<section anchor="whysemantics" title="Why Names with Semantics?">
<t>    
  The 'tdb' URI scheme differs from other URI or URN methods for
  identifying abstractions because the designation of what is actually
  identified by the 'tdb' doesn't depend on knowing the intention of
  the assigner of the identifier. Unlike the 'tag' <xref
  target='RFC4151'/>, 'info' <xref target='RFC4452' />, 'cid' or 'mid'
  <xref target='RFC2392'/> schemes, for example, the identification
  does not depend on any authority or process not reusing the same
  identifier at some later point for a different concept, or
  maintaining any records or meaning.
  
  In these other schemes, the assigning authority only insures
  uniqueness at the time of minting, 
  with some other agent or process or context providing the
  authority to interpret the meaning of the identifier in the
  future. 
  In this sense, 'duri' and 'tdb' are different, in that 
  it is the agreement between the describer (the agent creating
  the URI) and the receiver of the URI (the agent interpreting
  the URI) to agree upon the semantics without any reference
  to any third party.
</t>
</section>
<section title="Avoiding MetaData">
<t>
  One might consider the timestamp in a 'duri' or 'tdb' URI to be just one piece of
  additional metadata about the URI, and consider adding other
  pieces of metadata as annotation.
</t><t>
  However, the use of the timestamp is intended primarily as a
  mechanism of accomplishing uniqueness over time. No other bit of
  metadata or description readily fills that purpose. Further, the date
  is not descriptive (an assertion about the URI) but merely
  refining.
</t>
</section>
<section title="Avoiding 'duri' and 'tdb'">
<t>
  Many applications of URIs already provide a context of timestamp. For
  example, one could imagine a hypertext system where the URIs contained
  within a document were intended to refer to the resources as of the
  date of the enclosing document. This would be a reasonable
  interpretation of URIs within an Internet archive system, for example.
  
</t><t>
  Some applications of URIs already implicitly use the level of
  interpretive indirection that is explicit with 'tdb', For example,
  within an ontology language definition, the URIs used for abstract
  concepts, individuals and so forth are generally considered 
  the "thing described by" the URI.
</t><t>
  In addition, the 'application/rdf+xml' Media Type
  <xref target="RFC3870"/> uses the fragment identifier resolution
  as an explicit way of identifying things that are
  described by an RDF document.
</t>
</section>

<section title="Persistent Domains">
<t>A design issue writeup <xref target="PDOMAINS" /> also explored
the problem space with a focus on the 
lack of persistence of DNS domain name assignments as one of the
primary contributions to instability of "http:" URIs. While
the solution explored there (persistent year-dated domain names)
might resolve some of the issues, it leaves open the possibility
that "http:" itself might not be the primary access method for
networked resources in one-hundred years, or the difficulty of
assuring any of the organizational guarantees that might be
expected of such an assignment -- that the webmasters of all 
organizations with persistent domains will always maintain
URIs which were promised to be stable.
</t>
</section>

<section title="'tdb' and levels of indirection">
<t>
  
  The 'tdb' scheme introduces a level of semantic indirection. The
  puzzles and confusions about use and mention, name and reference,
  and levels of indirection have been puzzling and amusing for quite a
  while.
  
 <list style="empty">
  <t>"It's long," said the Knight, "but it's very, very beautiful. Everybody that hears me sing it--either it brings tears into their eyes, or else--"<vspace />
"Or else what?" said Alice, for the Knight had made a sudden pause. <vspace />
"Or else it doesn't, you know. The name of the song is called 'Haddock's Eyes.'" <vspace />
    "Oh, that's the name of the song, is it?" Alice said, trying to
     feel interested. <vspace />
    "No, you don't understand," the knight said, looking a little
     vexed. "That's what the name is called. The name really is 'The
     Aged Aged Man.'" <vspace />
"Then I ought to have said 'That's what the song is called'?" Alice corrected herself.<vspace />
"No, you oughtn't: that's quite another thing! The song is called 'Ways and Means': but that's only what it's called, you know!" <vspace />
"Well, what is the song, then?" said Alice, who was by this time completely bewildered.<vspace />
"I was coming to that," the Knight said. "The song really is 'A-sitting On A Gate': and the tune's my own invention."

 <xref target="LOOK" />
</t></list>

</t>

</section>
</section>
<section anchor="spec" title="URI Specification Templates">

<section anchor="durispec" title="'duri' Scheme Template">
<t>

<list style="hanging">

<t hangText="URI scheme name:">
      duri
</t><t hangText="Status:">
      permanent

</t><t hangText="URI scheme syntax:">
        The syntax is described in detail in <xref target="syntax"/>
        of this document.
      Briefly, the syntax is  <vspace />
          duri:&lt;timestamp&gt;:&lt;embeddedURI&gt;  <vspace />
      where &lt;timestamp&gt; is year, year-month or date taken from
      <xref target="RFC3339"/>, and &lt;embeddedURI&gt; is
      an &lt;absoluteURI&gt; from <xref target="RFC3986"/>.
</t><t hangText="URI scheme semantics:">
      A URI as of a particular time.
      Semantics are described in detail in this document.
</t><t hangText="Encoding considerations:">
      'duri' URIs consist of a prefix followed by
      another URI, and should have the same 
      encoding considerations as others.
</t><t hangText="Applications/protocols that use this URI scheme name:">
      Limited: this scheme was originally developed 
      as a "thought experiment", although there is some
      discussion of using it with Memento <xref target="MEMENTO" />. 

</t><t hangText="Interoperability considerations:">
      The actual interoperability with Internet archiving
      services needs further exploration.
</t><t hangText="Security considerations:">
      See <xref target="security" /> of this document.
</t><t hangText="Contact:">
     Larry Masinter
     tdb:2010:http://larry.masinter.net
</t><t hangText="Author/Change controller:">
     Contact, as above.
</t><t hangText="References:">
      See References of this document.
</t>
</list>
</t>

</section>
<section anchor="tdbspec" title="'tdb' Scheme Template">
<t>

<list style="hanging">

<t hangText="URI scheme name:">
      tdb
</t><t hangText="Status:">
      permanent

</t><t hangText="URI scheme syntax:">
      The syntax is described in detail in <xref target="syntax"/>
      of this document.
      Briefly, the syntax is  <vspace />
          tdb:&lt;timestamp&gt;:&lt;embeddedURI&gt;  <vspace />
      where &lt;timestamp&gt; is year, year-month or date taken from
      <xref target="RFC3339"/>, and &lt;embeddedURI&gt; is
      an &lt;absoluteURI&gt; from <xref target="RFC3986"/>.

</t><t hangText="URI scheme semantics:">
      Semantic indirection at indicated date.
      Semantics are described in detail in this document.
</t><t hangText="Encoding considerations:">
      'tdb' URIs consist of a prefix followed by
      another URI, and should have the same 
      encoding considerations as others.
</t><t hangText="Applications/protocols that use this URI scheme name:">
      Limited:  This scheme was originally designed 
      as a "thought experiment", as a way resolve some of the
      use/mention ambiguities in semantic web applications
      that wish to "denote" concepts and other ideas
      and not just access resources over the Internet.

</t><t hangText="Interoperability considerations:">
      Existing semantic web applications may have other
      means of fixing meaning at a particular time or
      semantic indirection, and do not fix description
      by time.
</t><t hangText="Security considerations:">
      See <xref target="security" /> of this document.
</t><t hangText="Contact:">
     Larry Masinter
     tdb:2010:http://larry.masinter.net
</t><t hangText="Author/Change controller:">
     as above
</t><t hangText="References:">
      See References of this document.
</t>
</list>
</t>
</section>
</section>
<section anchor="iana" title="IANA considerations">
<t>
  This document includes two URI scheme registrations (<xref
  target="spec" /> that should be entered into the IANA registry of
  URI schemes as a permanent registration (once approved).

</t>
</section>
<section anchor="security" title="Security Considerations">
<t>
  'tdb' identifiers are not any more reliable because they 
  have dates.  URIs don't contain enough information to supply the
  authority for deciding what was or wasn't at a given URI at a given
  date.
</t>
</section>
<section anchor="acks" title="Acknowledgements">
<t>
  There have been many discussions over several years on the relationship of URLs, URNs, URIs, resources and resource identifiers, with many contributions.
   Particular thanks to those who have severely critiqued various versions of
   this document in the past, including Jonathan Rees, Nathan, Alan Ruttenberg, Alfred Hines, Herbert Van de Sompel, Al Gilman, Aaron Swartz, Brian McBride,
   Stuart Williams, Michael Mealling, Ray Denenberg and Pat Hayes.
</t>
</section>
</middle>
<back>

<references title="Normative References">


  

<reference anchor="RFC3339">
<front>
 <title>Date an Time on the Internet: Timestamps</title>
 <author initials='G.' surname='Klyne' fullname='Graham Klyne'>
    <organization /></author>
 <author initials='C.' surname='Newman'>
    <organization /></author>
 <date month='July' year='2002' />
 </front>
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='3339' />
</reference>


<reference anchor="RFC3986">
 <front>
  <title>Uniform Resource Identifiers (URI): Generic Syntax</title>
  <author initials='T.' surname='Berners-Lee' fullname='Tim Berners-Lee'>
   <organization />
  </author>
  <author initials='R.T.' surname='Fielding' fullname='Roy T. Fielding'>
   <organization />
  </author>
  <author initials='L.' surname='Masinter' fullname='Larry Masinter'>
   <organization />
  </author>
  <date month='January' year='2005' />
 </front>
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='3986' />
</reference>

</references>
<references title="Informative References">
 
<reference anchor="PDOMAINS" target="http://www.w3.org/DesignIssues/PersistentDomains">
<front>
<title>Persistent Domains - Strawman ideas on Web Architecture</title>
<author initials="T." surname="Berners-Lee">
  <organization /> </author>
<date year='2000' month='October' />
</front>
</reference>


<reference anchor='MANSTYLE' target="http://www.chicagomanualofstyle.org/tools_citationguide.html">
 
<front>
<title>The Chicago Manual Of Style Online: Chicago-Style Citation Quick Guide</title>
<author>
<organization>The University of Chicago</organization>
</author>
<date year='2010' />
</front>

</reference>
 
  <reference anchor='RFC4452'>

<front>
<title>The "info" URI Scheme for Information Assets with Identifiers in Public Namespaces</title>
<author initials='H.' surname='Van de Sompel' fullname='H. Van de Sompel'>
<organization /></author>
<author initials='T.' surname='Hammond' fullname='T. Hammond'>
<organization /></author>
<author initials='E.' surname='Neylon' fullname='E. Neylon'>
<organization /></author>
<author initials='S.' surname='Weibel' fullname='S. Weibel'>
<organization /></author>
<date year='2006' month='April' />
</front>

<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='4452' />
<format type='TXT' octets='36408' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc4452.txt' />
</reference>
  
<reference anchor='RFC2392'>
<front>
<title abbrev='Message- &amp; Content-ID URLs'>Content-ID and Message-ID Uniform Resource Locators</title>
<author initials='E.' surname='Levinson' fullname='Edward Levinson'>
<organization />
  
</author>
<date year='1998' month='August' />
<area>Applications</area>
<keyword>content-type</keyword>
<keyword>encapsulate</keyword>
<keyword>hypertext markup language</keyword>
<keyword>multipurpose internet mail extensions</keyword>
<keyword>uniform resource</keyword>

</front>

<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='2392' />
<format type='TXT' octets='11141' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc2392.txt' />
<format type='HTML' octets='23113' target='http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/html/rfc2392.html' />
<format type='XML' octets='12024' target='http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/xml/rfc2392.xml' />
</reference>

<reference anchor='RFC4151'>

<front>
<title>The 'tag' URI Scheme</title>
<author initials='T.' surname='Kindberg' fullname='T. Kindberg'>
<organization /></author>
<author initials='S.' surname='Hawke' fullname='S. Hawke'>
<organization /></author>
<date year='2005' month='October' />
</front>

<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='4151' />
<format type='TXT' octets='22555' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc4151.txt' />
</reference>


  <reference anchor="RFC3870">
<front>
 <title>application/rdf+xml Media Type Registration</title>
 <author initials='A.' surname='Swartz' fullname='Aaron Swartz'>
    <organization /></author>
 <date month='September' year='2004' />
 </front>
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='3870' />
</reference
>


<reference anchor="MEMENTO" target="http://mementoweb.org/">
<front>
   <title>Memento: Adding Time to the Web</title>
   <author>
     <organization>Memento Development Group</organization>
   </author>
  <date month="" year="2010" />
  </front>
 </reference>


<reference anchor="COOL" target="http://www.w3.org/Provider/Style/URI.html">
<front>
  <title>Cool URIs don't change</title>
  <author initials="T." surname="Berners-Lee">
   <organization>W3C</organization>
   </author>
  <date month="" year="1998" />
 </front>
</reference>
<reference anchor="RFC1737">
<front>
 <title>Functional Requirements for Uniform Resource Names</title>
  <author initials="K." surname="Sollins">
  <organization></organization> </author>
  <date month="December" year="1994" />
  </front>
 <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="1737" />
</reference>
  
<reference anchor="archive" target="http://www.sciam.com/0397issue/0397kahle.html">
  <front>
<title>Preserving the Internet</title>
<author initials="B." surname="Kahle" fullname="Brewster Kahle">
<organization>Alexa Internet</organization></author>
  <date month='March' year='1997' />
  
</front>
 <seriesInfo name="Scientific American" value="" />
</reference>

<reference anchor="LOOK" target="http://www.literature.org/authors/carroll-lewis/through-the-looking-glass/chapter-08.html">
<front>
<title>Through the Looking Glass</title>
<author initials="L." surname="Carroll" fullname="Lewis Carroll"><organization /></author>
<date month='' year='1872' />
</front>
</reference>
<reference anchor="FOAF" target="http://xmlns.com/foaf/spec/#term_primaryTopic">
<front>
<title> FOAF Vocabulary Specification 0.98</title>
<author initials="D." surname="Brickley">
<organization /></author> 
<date month='August' year='2010' />
</front>
</reference>

</references>

</back>
</rfc>
