<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">

<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>


<?rfc strict='yes'?>
<?rfc toc='yes'?>
<?rfc symrefs='yes'?>
<?rfc sortrefs='yes'?>
<?rfc iprnotified="no" ?>
<?rfc compact='yes'?>
<?rfc subcompact='no'?>

<rfc ipr="trust200902" docName="draft-masinter-dated-uri-07" category="info">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="The 'tdb' and 'duri' URI schemes">The 'tdb' and 'duri' URI schemes, based on dated URIs</title>
    <author initials="L." surname="Masinter" fullname="Larry Masinter">
      <organization>Adobe</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>345 Park Ave</street>
          <city>San Jose</city><region>CA</region>
          <code>95110</code>
          <country>US</country>
        </postal>
        <phone>+1 408 536 3024</phone>
        <email>LMM@acm.org</email>
        <uri>http://larry.masinter.net</uri>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date day="22" month="October" year="2010" />
    <area>Applications</area>
    
    <abstract>
    <t> This document defines two URI schemes. The first,
   'duri' (standing for "dated URI"), allows indicating a URI
   as of a particular date (and time). This allows explicit
   reference to the "time of retrieval", similar to the way
   in which bibliographic references containing URIs are used.
   </t><t>The second scheme, 'tdb' ( standing for
   "Thing Described By"), provides a way of using a way of
   minting URIs for anything that can be described, with the
   ability to fix  the description to a given date or time.
  The 'tdb' URI scheme may reduce the need to define 
  define new URN namespaces merely for the purpose of creating stable
  identifiers for concepts or abstractions:  it provides a ready means
   for identifying
  "non-information resources" by semantic indirection -- a way
  of creating a URI for anything.
</t>
    </abstract>
    <note title="Note">
  <t> This document is not a product of any working group. Many of
  the ideas here have been discussed since 2001. This document has
  been discussed on the mailing list &lt;uri@w3.org&gt;. Previous
  versions have couched 'tdb' and 'tdb' as URN namespaces.
  </t>
    </note>
  </front>
  <middle>
    
<section anchor="overview" title="Overview and Requirements">

<t>  The URI schemes defined here address several related problems:
</t>

<section title="Persistent identifiers">

<t>  <xref target="RFC1737" />
 defines several requirements for Uniform Resource
  Names. In particular, it requires "persistence":
  <list style="empty">
   <t>
     Persistence: It is intended that the lifetime of a URN be
     permanent.  That is, the URN will be globally unique forever, and
     may well be used as a reference to a resource well beyond the
     lifetime of the resource it identifies or of any naming authority
     involved in the assignment of its name.
  </t>
  </list>
 </t>
  <t>  Many people have wondered how to create globally unique and
  persistent identifiers. There are a number of URI schemes and URN
  namespaces already registered. However, an absolute guarantee of
  both uniqueness and persistence is very difficult.
  </t><t>
  In some cases, the guarantee of persistence comes through a promise
  of good management practice, such as is encouraged in <xref 
  target="COOL">"Cool URLs
  don't change"</xref>.  However, relying on promise of good
  management practice is not the same as having a design that
  guarantees reliability independent of actual administrative
  practice.
  </t>
<t>
  A primary design goal for URIs is that they are intended to mean the
  same thing, no matter in what context they appear: a "Uniform" way
  to Identify a Resource. However, even when URIs have Uniform meaning
  from the point of view of the source of the reference, they don't
  guarantee stability over time. Despite best efforts and intentions,
  identifying information can change in unpredictable ways: domain
  names can disappear or be reassigned, name assigning organizations
  can change structure, responsibility, disappear, merge, or change in
  unpredictable ways.
  </t>
  <t>
  There is a significant dependence in the interpretation of many URNs
  with the concept of "naming authority". The authority is presumably
  some individual or organization both to insure uniqueness of
  assignment and also to help with understanding the meaning of the
  link between the name and the named.
  </t><t>
  However, authorities, whether individuals or organizations, have a
  lifetime, and must be consulted at some point to understand the
  bindings. The functioning of names as unique identifiers and holders
  of meaning depends on having a reliable infrastructure of consulting
  the authority or the authorities records to determine the thing
  referenced.
  </t>
</section>
<section title="URIs for abstractions">
<t>

 The description of URIs <xref target="RFC3986" /> describes a
  range for 'Resource' that is quite broad:
<list style="empty">
 <t>
     This specification does not limit the scope of what might be a
      resource; rather, the term "resource" is used in a general sense
      for whatever might be identified by a URI.  Familiar examples
      include an electronic document, an image, a source of information
      with a consistent purpose (e.g., "today's weather report for Los
      Angeles"), a service (e.g., an HTTP-to-SMS gateway), and a
      collection of other resources.
   A resource is not necessarily
      accessible via the Internet; e.g., human beings, corporations, and
      bound books in a library can also be resources.  Likewise,
      abstract concepts can be resources, such as the operators and
      operands of a mathematical equation, the types of a relationship
      (e.g., "parent" or "employee"), or numeric values (e.g., zero,
      one, and infinity).

 </t>
</list>
</t>
<t>
  One might use a URI such as "mailto:" email address to identify
  a person, or a "http:" URI to identify an abstract comment.
  However, this leaves the question of how one might identify, within
  the same context, both the system mailbox and the person to which
  it is assigned, or the web page at a http URI and the
  concept it describes. The 'tdb' URI scheme allows ready assignment
  of URIs for abstractions that are distinguished from the media
  content that describes them.
</t><t>
  The goal, then, of the 'tdb' URI scheme is to
  provide a mechanism which is, at the same time:
<list style="hanging">
<t> permanent: The identity of the resource identified
      is not subject to reinterpretation over time.
</t>
<t>explicitly bound: The mechanism by which the identified
      resource can be determined is explicitly included in
      the URI.
</t>
<t>useful for non-networked items:
 Allows identification of resources outside the network:
      people, organizations, abstract concepts.
</t>
<t>no administration:
 The mechanism does not depend on reliable administrative processes
      of authorities for either assignment or interpretation.
</t>
</list>
</t>

</section>
</section>

<section anchor="syntax" title="Syntax">
<section anchor="duri-syntax" title="'duri' Syntax">
<t>A 'duri' URI takes the form:</t>

<figure>
<artwork>     duri:&lt;timestamp&gt;:&lt;encoded-URI&gt;
</artwork>
</figure>
<t> where &lt;timestamp&gt; is s sequence of digits representing
a date and time (<xref target="timestamp-syntax"/>) and &lt;encoded-URI&gt; is
an absolute URI-reference <xref target="RFC3986" />  in
  which any reserved character other than "/" have been percent-encoded 
  (<xref target="encoding" />). Note that the URI which has been
   encoded MAY include a fragment identifier.</t>
</section>
<section anchor="tdb-syntax" title="tdb Syntax">
<t>A 'tdb' URI takes a similar form:</t>
<figure>
<artwork>     tdb:&lt;timestamp&gt;:&lt;encoded-URI&gt;
</artwork>
</figure>
<t> with the same syntax.
</t>
</section>
<section anchor="encoding" title="encoded-URI encoding">
<t>The following characters must be encoded within &lt;encoded-URI&gt;:
<list style="symbols">
   <t> The character "#" <vspace />
     Note that the URI encoded by &lt;encoded-URI&gt; can include a
    fragment identifier; the "#" character used to delimit it must
    be encoded. This feature is intended for use with 'tdb', where
    the fragment identified might contain the description. Including
    an encoded "#" with a 'duri' is not as useful, since the fragment
    identifier might as well be applied to the 'duri' itself.
  </t>
  <t> The character "%" <vspace />
    The encoded-URI can itself contain encoded characters, which are
    encoded with the same method. To insure that decoding happens at
   the right level of processing, the "%" itself must be encoded.
    Unfortunately, this means there are cases where there is a double
    encoding of characters, first to construct the embedded URI
    itself and second to then embed the URI within the 'tdb' or
    'duri' URI.
 </t>
</list>
</t>
</section>
<section anchor="timestamp-syntax" title="Timestamp syntax">
<t>
  A timestamp in these URI schemes consists of a restricted
  subset of date times, as per <xref target="RFC3339" />.

  The goal is to allow relatively short
  expressions with no ambiguity, but also with arbitrary
  precision.

</t>
<figure>
<artwork>
  timestamp = date [ "T" time "Z" ]
  date       =date-fullyear [ "-" date-month [ "-" date-mday ]]
  time       = time-hour  [ ":" time-minute 
               [ ":" time-second [ time-secfrac ]]]
</artwork>
</figure>
<t>where non-terminals "date-fullyear", "date-month", "date-mday",
 "time-hour", "time-minute", "time-second", "time-secfrac"
are taken from <xref target="RFC3339" />.

The goal was to minimize the amount of precision needed, while
retaining the possibility of generating timestamps that are
exactly compatible with <xref target="RFC3339" /> "date-time"
non-terminal.
</t>
</section>

</section>

<section anchor="semantics" title="Semantics">

<section anchor="duri-meaning" title="'duri' Semantics">
<t>
  It is traditional in convention references and citations in printed
  works to include the date of publication; this practice serves the
  important purpose that the context of the naming can be determined.
</t>
<t>  The meaning of a 'duri' URI is "the resource that was
  identified by the &lt;encoded-URI&gt; (after hex decoding) at
  the date(time) given".
</t><t>
  
  For example, "duri:2001:http://www.ietf.org" is a persistent
  identifier to "http://www.ietf.org" as of 2001. 
  A 'duri' URI may not be a resource locator in a practical
  sense: the time of location has not yet arrived or has
  passed. 
</t>
</section>
<section anchor="tdb-meaning" title="'tdb' Semantics">
<t>
  The 'tdb' URI scheme is intended to be useful
  for describing entities, concepts, abstractions, and other items
  which may not themselves be network accessible resources, but have been
  at some point described by network accessible resources.
</t>

<t>

  A 'tdb' URI is intended to be used where the &lt;encoded-URI&gt;
  identifies a 'document' (something a person could read, peruse,
  understand) or a fragment thereof, where the document describes some
  thing or concept. The 'tdb' URI itself then identifies the subject
  of that document. It is common practice to give a reference for a
  concept by including a pointer to a document, segment, phrase that
  defines the concept; 'tdb' attempts to capture this practice in URI
  space.
</t>
  
<t>
  For example, one might use "tdb:2008:http://www.ietf.org" as
  a persistent identifier for the Internet Engineering Task
  Force, as described by the "http://www.ietf.org" in 2008. 
</t>
<t>
  
  The 'tdb' URI scheme differs from other URI or URN methods for
  identifying abstractions because the designation of what is actually
  identified by the 'tdb' doesn't depend on knowing the intention of
  the "assigner" of the identifier. Unlike "tag", "info", "cid", "mid"
  or related schemes, the identification is not dependent on the
  context of use.  The 'tdb' URI scheme can be thought of as giving
  a way to invoke a level of semantic indirection to URI resolution.
  
</t>
  
<t>While one could imagine using 'tdb' without a date, it would leave
  the possibility that a reference that is unambiguous at one time
  might become ambiguous at some other time. There are two ways that
  the date is useful for 'tdb' URIs: it fixes the time of access of
  the resource, for variable descriptions, and it fixes the time of
  interpretation, for descriptions whose meaning (in natural language)
  might vary.
</t>
</section>
<section anchor="timestamp-semantics" title="Timestamp Semantics">
<t>
  It is traditional in convention references and citations in printed
  works to include the date of publication; this practice serves the
  important purpose that the context of the naming can be determined.
</t>

<t>While one could imagine using 'tdb'
  without a timestamp, it would leave the possibility that a reference that
  is unambiguous at one time might become ambiguous at some other
  time. There are two ways that the date is useful for 'tdb':
  it fixes the time of access of the resource, for variable descriptions,
  and it fixes the time of interpretation, for descriptions whose
  meaning (in natural language) might vary. 
While normally, in a literary work in natural language which makes
a reference to another work, both the reference itself and the
work referenced are dated, e.g., a footnote in an article
written in 1967 might talk about a "private communication" which
itself had a date. The difference between a URI and a conventional
literary reference is the desire to be able to extract the URI
from its context and still retain its meaning.
</t>

<t>
  The meaning of a timestamp is the interval specified by the
  granularity of the time range indicated, in the UTC time zone,
  as described in <xref target="RFC3339" />.
   If necessary, timestamps can
  include times and even fractional times, so that a generator of
  'duri' or 'tdb' URIs can be arbitrarily precise.
</t><t>
 If there is any ambiguity of the resource within the range of 
 time indicated (for example, if the timestamp consists only of
 a year, and the resource changes over the course of the year), then
 the resource state as of the very last instant of the range
 indicated should be used.
</t>
<t>Timestamps are allowed to be specified with as much precision as
needed. This keeps most 'duri' and 'tdb' URIs relatively short.</t>

</section>

</section>
<section title="Use as a Locator">
<t>  A 'duri' URI is not directly useful as a resource locator,
 since many resources vary their content over time.
</t>
<t> A 'tdb' URI is not a resource locator in a practical sense,
since it explicitly requires human interpretation.
However, it allows one to know that  a resource was described at some
point in time; whether the description is still available,
or whether that description is still meaningful, is not guaranteed.
</t>
</section>

<section title="Hierarchy">
<t>
  For 'tdb', the "thing described by" a resource may bear little
  relationship to the "thing described by" a relative pointer,
  so the 'tdb' URI scheme seems to have no use cases for
  using "/" as a hierarchical delimiter.
</t>
<t>
  However, 'duri' URIs can often be used with
  relative URI references with some amount of reliability. Note,
  however, that double-encoding of previously encoded URI
  characters will cause some problems.
</t>

</section>

<section anchor="additional" title="Additional Considerations">
<section title="Embedded URI schemes">
<t>

  The intent of 'duri' and 'tdb' is to use them with embedded URI
  references that identify documents or document fragments. That is,
  they are most useful for "information resources".
</t>

<t>
  For example, use with a "http" URI can be used to refer to a web
  page or the subject of a web as it was described at the given time.
  This can be a way of referring to a web site at some time in the
  past, or an organization that has changed, merged, split, or
  disappeared.
</t>

<t>
  Local systems that have known-to-be unique host names can use "file" URIs
  with 'tdb', for example, </t>
<figure><artwork>
    tdb:20010814142327:file://this.example.com/c|/temp/test.txt
</artwork></figure>
  <t> since this use is primarily focused on providing a unique way of
  identifying an abstraction, even if the referent of the abstraction
  is not widely known. (Using 'file:' URIs in this way without a fully
  qualified domain name would not be appropriate, because the interpretation
  is not uniform.)
</t>
<t>
  One might consider using 'tdb' with a "data" URI to designate concepts
  that can be described uniquely briefly inline. For example, </t>
<figure><artwork>
     tdb:2001:data:,The%20US%20president
</artwork></figure>
  
  <t> names the concept described by the (text/plain) string "The US
  president" at the very last instant of 2001. Of
  course, this practice is only useful if the referent of the data is
  (or was at the time) completely unique. Since "data" does not
  contain a way to designate content-language, the string in question
  would have to not be ambiguous as to its language.  In the case of
  'data', there is no assigning authority at all; the interpretation
  of the 'tdb' depend on the interpreting community.

</t><t> Using 'tdb'
  or 'duri' with an embedded 'urn:' might not seem to be too useful,
  But it might be useful where the assignment of names in a URN
  namespace are not, in practice, permanent, or that one might want to
  refer to the assignment as of a given date. In this case, it is
  possible to use a "urn" within a 'duri', e.g., </t>
  
<figure><artwork>
      duri:2000:urn:ietf:std:50
</artwork></figure>
 <t>  might be used to refer to "the document that the IETF considered to be STD 50, as
  of the last instant of 2000".

</t><t>
  For 'tdb', many URIs identify resources which do not clearly describe
  anything at all. The "home page" for an organization isn't
  nearly as good a resource to use to describe an organization
  as the organization's "about" page. But it is up to the minter
  of the 'tdb' URI to choose wisely.
</t>
</section>

<section title="Useful timestamps">

<t>
  Timestamps far in the future are suspect, because the future
  content of a description resource cannot usually
  be reliably predicted.  Timestamps which preceed
  the availability of the description resource should
  not be used either.  For example, using a http URI with
  a timestamp before the description resource is also
  not recommended.
</t><t>
  However, although these practices are not recommended, there is no
  assurance that they haven't been used; by itself, a 'tdb' URI by itself does not
  constitute an assertion that the description resource was available or
  assigned at the date specified.
</t><t>
  Note that the use of the "very last instant" allows for the 
  conventional bibliographic convention that a work published
  in 2009 can use "2009" as the date string, to refer to the
  work in the year of publication. 
</t>
</section>
<section title="Free assignment">
<t>
  
  Because of the many possible schemes that can be used in the
  &lt;encoded-URI&gt; portion, there should be no difficulty in almost any
  computational process being able to assign 'duri' or 'tdb' URIs at will. Of
  course, it is necessary for there to be some resource which is
  available at some point in time, and to have a clock which is
  accurate to the granularity of the frequency of assignment.
  
</t>
</section>
<section anchor="resolution" title="Resolution">
<t>
  There are no direct resolution servers or processes for 'duri' or
  'tdb' URIs. However, a 'duri' URI might be "resolvable" in the sense
  that a resource that was accessed at a point in time might have the
  result of that access cached or archived in an Internet archive
  service. See, for example, the "Internet Archive" project <xref
  target="archive" />. And a 'tdb' URI is "resolvable" in the sense
  that the description resource can be accessed and interpreted.
</t>
  
<t> Clients without access to an Internet archive service might take
  the decoded &lt;encoded-URI&gt; of a 'duri' and attempt resolution
  of *that* identifier. This will give an approximation whose
  reliability depends on the what has happened in the time since the
  date indicated.
</t>

</section>
<section title="Why Names with Semantics?">
<t>
  
  There are a number of URI and URN schemes that create otherwise
  unbound "names", where the scheme only provides for uniqueness,
  with some other agent or process or context providing the
  authority to interpret the meaning of the identifier at
  some point in the future. 'duri' and 'tdb' is different, in that 
  it is the agreement between the describer (the agent creating
  the URI) and the receiver of the URI (the agent interpreting
  the URI) to agree upon the semantics without any reference
  to any third party.
</t>
</section>
<section title="Avoiding MetaData">
<t>
  One might consider the timestamp in a 'duri' or 'tdb' URI to be just one piece of
  additional metadata about the URI, and consider adding other
  pieces of metadata as annotation.
</t><t>
  However, the use of the timestamp is intended primarily as a
  mechanism of accomplishing uniqueness over time. No other bit of
  metadata or description readily fills that purpose. Further, the date
  is not descriptive (an assertion about the URI) but merely
  refining.
</t>
</section>
<section title="Avoiding 'duri' and 'tdb'">
<t>
  Many applications of URIs already provide a context of timestamp. For
  example, one could imagine a hypertext system where the URIs contained
  within a document were intended to refer to the resources as of the
  date of the enclosing document. This would be a reasonable
  interpretation of URIs within an Internet archive system, for example.
  
</t><t>
  Some applications of URIs already implicitly use the level of
  interpretive indirection that is explicit with 'tdb', For example,
  within an ontology language definition, the URIs used for abstract
  concepts, individuals and so forth are generally considered 
  the "thing described by" the URI.
</t><t>
  In addition, the 'application/rdf+xml' Media Type
  <xref target="RFC3870"/> uses the fragment identifier resolution
  as an explicit way of identifying abstract concepts that are
  described by an RDF document.
</t>
</section>

<section title="'tdb' and levels of indirection">
<t>
  
  The 'tdb' scheme introduces a level of semantic indirection. The
  puzzles and confusions about use and mention, name and reference,
  and levels of indirection have been puzzling and amusing for quite a
  while.
  
 <list style="empty">
  <t>"It's long," said the Knight, "but it's very, very beautiful. Everybody that hears me sing it--either it brings tears into their eyes, or else--"<vspace />
"Or else what?" said Alice, for the Knight had made a sudden pause. <vspace />
"Or else it doesn't, you know. The name of the song is called 'Haddock's Eyes.'" <vspace />
    "Oh, that's the name of the song, is it?" Alice said, trying to
     feel interested. <vspace />
    "No, you don't understand," the knight said, looking a little
     vexed. "That's what the name is called. The name really is 'The
     Aged Aged Man.'" <vspace />
"Then I ought to have said 'That's what the song is called'?" Alice corrected herself.<vspace />
"No, you oughtn't: that's quite another thing! The song is called 'Ways and Means': but that's only what it's called, you know!" <vspace />
"Well, what is the song, then?" said Alice, who was by this time completely bewildered.<vspace />
"I was coming to that," the Knight said. "The song really is 'A-sitting On A Gate': and the tune's my own invention."

 <xref target="LOOK" />
</t></list>

</t>

</section>
</section>
<section anchor="spec" title="URI Specification Templates">

<section anchor="durispec" title="'duri' Scheme Template">
<t>

<list style="hanging">

<t hangText="URI scheme name:">
      duri
</t><t hangText="Status:">
      permanent

</t><t hangText="URI scheme syntax:">
      Briefly, the syntax is  <vspace />
          tdb:&lt;timestamp&gt;:&lt;encoded-URI&gt;  <vspace />
      The syntax is described in this document.

</t><t hangText="URI scheme semantics:">
      A URI as of a particular time.
      Semantics are described in detail in this document.
</t><t hangText="Encoding considerations:">
      'duri' URIs consist of a prefix followed by
      another URI, and should have the same 
      encoding considerations as others. Note discussion
      of double-encoding.
</t><t hangText="Applications/protocols that use this URI scheme name:">
      Limited: this scheme was originally developed 
      as a "thought experiment", although there is some
      discussion of using it with Memento <xref target="MEMENTO" />. 

</t><t hangText="Interoperability considerations:">
      The actual interoperability with Internet archiving
      services needs further exploration.
</t><t hangText="Security considerations:">
      See <xref target="security" /> of this document.
</t><t hangText="Contact:">
     Larry Masinter
     tdb:2010:http://larry.masinter.net
</t><t hangText="Author/Change controller:">
     as above
</t><t hangText="References:">
      See References of this document.
</t>
</list>
</t>

</section>
<section anchor="tdbspec" title="tdb Scheme Template">
<t>

<list style="hanging">

<t hangText="URI scheme name:">
      tdb
</t><t hangText="Status:">
      permanent

</t><t hangText="URI scheme syntax:">
      Briefly, the syntax is  <vspace />
          tdb:&lt;timestamp&gt;:&lt;encoded-URI&gt;  <vspace />
      The syntax is described in this document.

</t><t hangText="URI scheme semantics:">
      Semantic indirection at indicated date.
      Semantics are described in detail in this document.
</t><t hangText="Encoding considerations:">
      'tdb' URIs consist of a prefix followed by
      another URI, and should have the same 
      encoding considerations as others.
      Note discussion of double-encoding possibilities.
</t><t hangText="Applications/protocols that use this URI scheme name:">
      Limited:  This scheme was originally designed 
      as a "thought experiment", as a way resolve some of the
      use/mention ambiguities in semantic web applications
      that wish to "denote" concepts and other ideas
      and not just access resources over the Internet.

</t><t hangText="Interoperability considerations:">
      Existing semantic web applications may have other
      means of fixing meaning at a particular time or
      semantic indirection, and do not fix description
      by time.
</t><t hangText="Security considerations:">
      See <xref target="security" /> of this document.
</t><t hangText="Contact:">
     Larry Masinter
     tdb:2010:http://larry.masinter.net
</t><t hangText="Author/Change controller:">
     as above
</t><t hangText="References:">
      See References of this document.
</t>
</list>
</t>
</section>
</section>
<section anchor="iana" title="IANA considerations">
<t>
  This document includes two URI scheme registrations (<xref
  target="spec" /> that should be entered into the IANA registry of
  URI schemes as a permanent registration (once approved).

</t>
</section>
<section anchor="security" title="Security Considerations">
<t>
  'tdb' identifiers are not any more reliable because they 
  have dates.  URIs don't contain enough information to supply the
  authority for deciding what was or wasn't at a given URI at a given
  date.
</t>
</section>
<section anchor="acks" title="Acknowledgements">
<t>
  There have been many discussions over several years on the relationship of URLs, URNs, URIs, resources and resource identifiers, with many contributions.
   Particular thanks to Alfred Hines, Herbert Van de Sompel, Al Gilman, Aaron Swartz, Brian McBride,
   Stuart Williams, Michael Mealling, Ray Denenberg and Pat Hayes.
</t>
</section>
</middle>
<back>

<references title="Normative References">


<reference anchor="RFC3339">
<front>
 <title>Date an Time on the Internet: Timestamps</title>
 <author initials='G.' surname='Klyne' fullname='Graham Klyne'>
    <organization /></author>
 <author initials='C.' surname='Newman'>
    <organization /></author>
 <date month='July' year='2002' />
 </front>
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='3339' />
</reference>


<reference anchor="RFC3986">
 <front>
  <title>Uniform Resource Identifiers (URI): Generic Syntax</title>
  <author initials='T.' surname='Berners-Lee' fullname='Tim Berners-Lee'>
   <organization />
  </author>
  <author initials='R.T.' surname='Fielding' fullname='Roy T. Fielding'>
   <organization />
  </author>
  <author initials='L.' surname='Masinter' fullname='Larry Masinter'>
   <organization />
  </author>
  <date month='January' year='2005' />
 </front>
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='3986' />
</reference>

<reference anchor="namespaces" target="http://www.w3.org/TR/REC-xml-names">
<front>
<title>Namespaces in XML</title>
    <author initials="T." surname="Bray" fullname="Tim Bray">
  <organization /> </author>
    <author initials="D." surname="Hollander" fullname="Dave Hollander">
   <organization /> </author>
    <author initials="A." surname="Layman" fullname="Andrew Layman">
   <organization /> </author>

<date month='January' year='1999' />
</front>
  <seriesInfo name="W3C Recommendation" value="REC-xml-names"/>
</reference>

</references>
<references title="Informative References">

  <reference anchor="RFC3870">
<front>
 <title>application/rdf+xml Media Type Registration</title>
 <author initials='A.' surname='Swartz' fullname='Aaron Swartz'>
    <organization /></author>
 <date month='September' year='2004' />
 </front>
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='3870' />
</reference
>


<reference anchor="MEMENTO" target="http://mementoweb.org/">
<front>
   <title>Memento: Adding Time to the Web</title>
   <author>
     <organization>Memento Development Group</organization>
   </author>
  <date month="" year="2010" />
  </front>
 </reference>


<reference anchor="COOL" target="http://www.w3.org/Provider/Style/URI.html">
<front>
  <title>Cool URIs don't change</title>
  <author initials="T." surname="Berners-Lee">
   <organization>W3C</organization>
   </author>
  <date month="" year="1998" />
 </front>
</reference>
<reference anchor="RFC1737">
<front>
 <title>Functional Requirements for Uniform Resource Names</title>
  <author initials="K." surname="Sollins">
  <organization></organization> </author>
  <date month="December" year="1994" />
  </front>
 <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="1737" />
</reference>
  
<reference anchor="archive" target="http://www.sciam.com/0397issue/0397kahle.html">
  <front>
<title>Preserving the Internet</title>
<author initials="B." surname="Kahle" fullname="Brewster Kahle">
<organization>Alexa Internet</organization></author>
  <date month='March' year='1997' />
  
</front>
 <seriesInfo name="Scientific American" value="" />
</reference>

<reference anchor="LOOK" target="http://www.literature.org/authors/carroll-lewis/through-the-looking-glass/chapter-08.html">
<front>
<title>Through the Looking Glass</title>
<author initials="L." surname="Carroll" fullname="Lewis Carroll"><organization /></author>
<date month='' year='1872' />
</front>
</reference>
</references>

</back>
</rfc>
