<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">

<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>

<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>

<rfc category="info" docName="draft-masinter-mime-web-info-02" ipr="trust200902">

  <!-- category values: std, bcp, info, exp, and historic
     you can add the attributes updates="NNNN" and obsoletes="NNNN" 
     they will automatically be output with "(if approved)" -->

  <front>

    <title abbrev="MIME and the Web">MIME and the Web</title>

    <author fullname="Larry Masinter" initials="L." 
            surname="Masinter">
      <organization>Adobe</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>345 Park Ave.</street>
          <city>San Jose</city>
          <region></region>
          <code>95110</code>

          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>

        <phone>+1 408 536 3024</phone>

        <email>masinter@adobe.com</email>
        <uri>http://larry.masinter.net</uri>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date year="2011" />

    <area>Applications</area>

    <workgroup>Internet Engineering Task Force</workgroup>

    <keyword>MIME</keyword>
    <keyword>Internet Media Types</keyword>
    <keyword>charset</keyword>
    <keyword>Web</keyword>
    <keyword>HTTP</keyword>

    <abstract>
<t>This document describes some of the ways in which parts of the MIME system,
   originally designed for electronic mail, have been used in the Web,
     and some of the ways in which those uses have resulted in difficulties.

 Given this background and justification, this document then goes on to outline requirements for changes to MIME registries and practices for their use within W3C and IETF, in order to address those difficulties.

Within IETF, it is expected that a companion Best Current Practice document will make specific changes to the Internet Media Types and Charset registries, among others.
</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>

<section title="Introduction">

<t>This document was prompted by discussions about
Web architecture and the difficulties surrounding evolution of the
Web, Internet Media types, multiple specifications for a single media
type, and related discussions.</t>

<t>The document gives some of the history of MIME and its introduction
and use in the Web <xref target="history" />. It then describes some
of the current difficulties with the use of MIME in the Web context
<xref target="problems" />.  This background and context is then
followed by a description of changes which would reduce some of those
difficulties; the changes involve specifications, practices, and
registries within IETF and W3C <xref target="changes"/>. In
particular, changes to the registry and maintenance procedures for
MIME-related registries maintained by IANA are describes.</t>

<t>Currently, discussion of this document is suggested on the mailing
list www-tag@w3c.org (mailing list open for subscription to all),
archives at http://lists.w3.org/Archives/Public/www-tag/.</t>

</section>
     
<section title="History" anchor="history">
     
<section title="Origins of MIME">

<t>MIME ("Multipurpose Internet Mail Extensions") was invented
originally for email, based on general principles of "messaging" (a
foundational architecture framework). The role of MIME was to extend
Internet email messaging from ASCII-only plain text, to include other
character sets, images, rich documents, etc.)  <xref target="RFC1521"
/>, <xref target="RFC1522" />.

The basic architecture of complex content messaging is:

<list style="symbols">

<t>Message sent from A to B. </t>

<t>Message includes some data. Sender A includes standard 'headers'
telling recipient B enough information that recipient B knows how
sender A intends the message to be interpreted. </t>

<t>Recipient B gets the message, interprets the headers for the data
and uses it as information on how to interpret the data. </t>

</list>
</t>

<t>MIME is a "tagging and bagging" specification:

<list style="hanging">

<t hangText="tagging:">How to label content so the intent of how the
content should be interpreted is known.</t>

<t hangText="bagging:">How to wrap the content so the label is clear,
or, if there are multiple parts to a single message, how to combine
them.</t>

</list>
</t>

<t>"MIME types" (renamed "Internet Media Types" in later specs <xref
target='RFC2046' />) are part of the "tagging" -- a way to describe
the content of a message so that it could be used to initiate
interpretation of a message. The "Internet Media Type registry" (MIME
type registry) is where someone can tell the world what a particular
label means, as far as the sender's intent of how recipients should
process a message of that type, and the description of a recipients
capability and ability for senders.  </t></section>

<section title="Introducing MIME into the Web">

<t>The original World Wide Web (the 0.9 version of HTTP, see <xref
target='RFC1945' />) didn't have "tagging and bagging" -- everything
sent via HTTP was assumed to be HTML.

However, at the time (early 1990's) other distributed information
access systems, including Gopher (distributed menu system) and WAIS
(remote access to document databases) were adding capabilities for
accessing many things other text and hypertext and the WWW folks were
considering type tagging.  It was agreed that HTTP should use MIME as
the vocabulary for talking about file types and character sets.  The
result was that HTTP 1.0 added the "content-type" header, following
(more or less) MIME. Later, for content negotiation, additional uses
of this technology (in 'Accept' headers) were also added.
</t>

<t>

The differences between the use of Internet Media Types between email
and HTTP have minor:

 <list style="symbols">
<t>default charset: HTTP originally specified ISO-8859-1 as the default character set, not US-ASCII ((NEED REF TO HTTP ISSUE see http://trac.tools.ietf.org/wg/httpbis/trac/ticket/20; the text that it refers to currently is here: 
http://greenbytes.de/tech/webdav/draft-ietf-httpbis-p3-payload-11.html#rfc.section.2.3.1 ))
  </t>
 <t> requirement for CRLF in plain text: in practice, Web clients didn't
   restrict content to use CRLF in text/* MIME bodies.</t>
</list></t>
<t>These minor differences have caused a lot of trouble.
</t>
</section>
     
<section title="Distributed Extensibility">
<texttable>

   <preamble>The real advantage of using Internet Media Types to label
   content meant that the Web was no longer restricted to a single
   format. This one addition meant expanding from Global Hypertext to
   Global Hypermedia (as suggested in <xref target="connolly92">a 1992
   email</xref>)</preamble>

   <ttcol align="left" />

   <c>The Internet currently serves as the backbone for a global
   hypertext. FTP and email provided a good start, and the gopher,
   WWW, or WAIS clients and servers make wide area information
   browsing simple. These systems even interoperate, with email
   servers talking to FTP servers, WWW clients talking to gopher
   servers, on and on.</c>

  <c>This currently works quite well for text.  But what should WWW
  clients do as Gopher and WAIS servers begin to serve up pictures,
  sounds, movies, spreadsheet templates, postscript files, etc.? It
  would be a shame for each to adopt its own multimedia typing
  system.</c>

<c>If they all adopt the MIME typing system (and as many other
features from MIME as are appropriate), we can step from global
hypertext to global hypermedia that much easier.</c>
 
</texttable>

<t>The fact that HTTP could reliably transport images of different
formats, for example, allowed NCSA to add &lt;img&gt; to HTML. MIME
allowed other document formats (Word, PDF, Postscript) and other kinds
of hypermedia, as well as other applications, to be part of the
Web. MIME was arguably the most important extensibility mechanism in
the Web.  </t></section>

</section>

<section title="Problems with application to the Web" anchor="problems">

<t>Unfortunately, while the use of Internet Media Types for the Web
added incredible power, a number of problems have arisen.</t>

<section title="Lack of clarity">

<t> Many people are confused about the purpose of MIME in the Web, its
uses, the meaning of Internet Media Types. Many W3C specifications TAG
findings and Internet Media Type registrations make what are incorrect
assumptions about the meaning and purposes of a Internet Media Type
registration.
</t>

</section>
<section title="Differences between email and Web delivery">

<t>Some of the differences between the application contexts of email
and Web delivery determine different requirements:

<list style="symbols">

<t>
In the Web, the transfer of data is initiated differently than in
email: the "messages" with labeled content are usually HTTP responses
to a specific (GET) request (although the request is itself a message,
GET has no content). In the most common case, then, the receiver knows
more about the data before it has been sent. </t>

<t> Clients would like to know more about the content before they
retrieve it. The "tagging" is often not sufficient to know, for
example, "can I interpret this if I retrieve it", because of
versioning, capabilities, or dependencies on things like screen size
or interaction capabilities of the recipient. </t>

<t> Some content isn't delivered over the HTTP (files on local file
system), or there is no opportunity for tagging (data delivered over
FTP) and in those cases, some other ways are needed for determining
file type.  </t>

</list></t>

<t>Operating systems use (and continued to evolve) different systems
to determine the 'type' of something, different from the MIME tagging
and bagging:

<list style="symbols">

<t>'magic numbers': in many contexts, file types can be guessed
by looking for some unique string, number or pattern, which only
appears in files of that type. In circumstances where this was
a unique number, it was called a "magic number", although this
concept has been extended to other textual patterns. </t>

<t>Originally MAC OS had a 4 character 'file type' and another 4
character 'creator code' for file types. </t>

<t> Windows evolved to use the "file extension" -- 3 letters (and then
more) at the end of the file name -- as the initial determination of
the oveall type of a file. This practice has now extended to other
systems.</t>

</list></t>

<t>Information about these other ways of determining type (rather than
by the content-type label) were gathered for the Internet Media Type
registry; those registering types are encouraged to also describe
'magic numbers', Mac file type, common file extensions. However, since
there was no formal use of that information, the quality of that
information in the registry is haphazard.</t>

<t>Finally, there was the fact that tagging and bagging might be OK
for unilaterally initiated (one-way) messaging, you might want to know
whether you could handle the data before reading it in and
interpreting it, but the Internet Media Types weren't enough to tell.

</t>
</section>
     
<section title="The Rules Weren't Quite Followed">
     
<t> The behavior of the community when the Internet Media Type
registry was designed hasn't matched expectations:

<list style="symbols">
  <t> Lots of file types aren't registered (no entry in IANA for file
types)</t>
  <t>For many file types that are registration, the registration is incomplete or incorrect (people
  doing registration didn't understand 'magic number' or other
  fields).</t>

  <t>The actual content deployed or created by deployed software doesn't
  match the registration.</t>
</list>
</t>
     

<t>These problems arise for various reason, for example:
<list style="symbols"> 

  <t>The benefit of registration to the
  organization that designed the file type is unclear compared
  to the overhead of sheperding the registration through the process.</t>
  <t>Registration requires announcing product plans in advance
  of product release. </t>
  <t>Orgnaizations are unaware of the registration process or misinformed.</t>

</list>
</t>

<t>In particular, Web implementations of Internet Media Types diverged
from expected behavior:
     
<list style="symbols">    

<t>Browser implementors would be liberal in what they accepted, and
use what looked like a file extension in the URL and/or magic number
or other "sniffing" techniques to decide file type, without assuming
content-label was authoritative. This was necessary anyway for files
that weren't delivered by HTTP. </t>

<t>HTTP server implementors and administrators didn't supply ways of
easily associating the 'intended' file type label with the file,
resulting in files frequently being delivered with a label other than
the one they would have chosen if they'd thought about it, and if
browsers *had* assumed content-type was authoritative.  Some popular
servers had default configuration files that treated any unknown type
as "text/plain" (plain ext in ASCII). Since it didn't matter (the
browsers worked anyway), it was hard to get this fixed. </t>

</list>

</t>
     
<t>Thus, in many situations, because of poor control over server
administration or weak file-type detection in popular web
server technology, receivers might find that 'magic number'
scanning was more reliable than the actual labeled content-type.</t>

<t>Incorrect senders coupled with liberal readers wind up feeding a
negative feedback loop based on the robustness principle (<xref
target='WikiRobust' />, <xref target='RFC3117' />).</t>


<t>In addition, since the "magic number" technology is heuristic,
it is possible to have different formats all with the same "magic number" 
or more generally, more than one different format that might 
be reasonably "sniffed".</t>

<t>For example, there are cases where the reuse of one file
type's magic number for another file type is intentional -- deliberate
"puns", attempts to usurp ownership of another vendor, group, or standards
organization's control over a file format, for example.</t>
<t>Secondly, there are cases where a single file might match
more than one 'magic number' or recognition pattern, and different
recievers apply heuristics differently.</t>

<t>Finally, there are simple cases where the labeled type
(text/plain, application/octet-stream) is more general and
could reasonably be used with content which might otherwise
match other patterns. </t>

<t>For example, the sniffing that's done by some web browsers
text/plain.  If you serve it the perfectly 
valid text file with the content:</t>

<figure><artwork>
&lt;?xml version="1.0"?&gt;
&lt;animals&gt;
  &lt;dog&gt;Rufus&lt;/fish&gt;
  &lt;cat&gt;Kitty&lt;/elephant&gt;
&lt;/animals&gt;
</artwork></figure>


<t>
the browser will not display it (there are intentionally mismatched tags on the 3rd line).  Something like this might come up, for example, if you had a bug
database, with links to the text of documents that caused problems.  This 
buggy XML, served as text/plain, should render, but it does not in browsers that incorrectly guess "application/xml".
</t>

<t>The "&lt;?xml" is treated as a "magic number", and the wrong thing is
happening.  The browser thinks "surely it's XML"; the bug tracking app
knows "on the contrary, I'm serving it as text precisely because I
know it's not".</t>

</section>

<section title="Consequences">

<t>The result, alas, is that increased unreliability, in that 

<list style="symbols">
<t>servers sending responses to browsers don't have a good guarantee that the browser won't "sniff" the content and decide to do something other than treat it as it is labeled</t>

<t>browsers receiving content don't have a good guarantee that the content isn't mis-labeled </t>

<t>intermediaries (gateways, proxies, caches, and other pieces of the Web infrastructure) don't have a good way of telling what the conversation means.  </t>
</list></t>

<t>This ambiguity and 'sniffing' also applies to the W3C developed Widget Packaging and Configuration <xref target='Widgets'/> (a kind of 'bagging' using ZIP rather than MIME multipart).</t>

</section>

<section title="The Down Side of Extensibility">

<t> Extensibility adds great power, and allows the Web to evolve without
committee approval of every extension. For some (those who want to
extend and their clients who want those extensions), this is power!
For others (those who are building Web components or infrastructure),
extensibility is a drawback -- it adds to the unreliability and
difference of the Web experience. When senders use extensions
recipients aren't aware of, implement incorrectly or incompletely,
then communication often fails.  With messaging, this is a serious
problem, although most 'rich text' documents are still delivered in
multiple forms (using multipart/alternative).</t>

<t>
If your job is to support users of a popular browser, however, where each user has installed a different configuration of file handlers and extensibility mechanisms, MIME may appear to add unnecessary complexity and variable experience for users of all but the most popular types.

</t>
</section>
</section>
     
<section title="Additional considerations">
<t>This section notes some additional considerations.</t>     
<section title="There are related problems with charsets">
     
<t>MIME includes provisions not only for file 'types', but also, importantly the "character encoding" used by text types: for example, simple US ASCII, Western European ISO-8859-1, Unicode UTF8. A similar vicious cycle also happened with character set labels: mislabeled content happily processed correctly by liberal browsers encouraged more and more sites to proliferate text with  mis-labeled character sets, to the point where browsers feel they *have* to guess the wrong label. (NEEDS EXPANSION)</t>
<t>There are sites that intentionally label content as
iso-2022-jp or euc-jp when it is in fact one of the Microsoft extension
charsets (e.g., for access to circled digits. This is an intentional
misuse of the definitions of the charsets themselves -- definitions which
originated at the national standards body level.
</t>

</section>


<section title="Embedded, downloaded, launch independent application">

<t>
The type of a document might be determined not only for entire documents "HTML" vs "Word" vs "PDF", but also to embedded components of documents, "JPEG image" vs. "PNG image". However, the use cases, requirements and likely operational impact of MIME handling is likely different for those use cases.
</t>

</section>

<section title="Additional Use Cases: Polyglot and Multiview">
<t>
There are some interesting additional use cases which add to the design requirements:
<list style="symbols">
<t> "Polyglot" documents:  A 'polyglot' document is one which is some data which can be treated as two different Internet Media Types, in the case where the meaning of the data is the same. This is part of a transition strategy to allow content providers (senders) to manage, produce, store, deliver the same data, but with two different labels, and have it work equivalently with two different kinds of receivers (one of which knows one Internet Media Type, and another which knows a second one.) This use case was part of the transition strategy from HTML to an XML-based XHTML, and also as a way of a single service offering both HTML-based and XML-based processing (e.g., same content useful for news articles and Web pages. </t>

<t>"Multiview" documents: This use case seems similar but it's quite different. In this case, the same data has very different meaning when served as two different content-types, but that difference is intentional; for example, the same data served as text/html is a document, and served as an RDFa type is some specific data. </t>
</list>
</t>
</section>
     
<section title="Evolution, Versioning, Forking">
     
<t>The subject of format/language/type evolution is complex; this section is a litle terse.</t>

<t>Formats and their specifications evolve over time. There are several reasons for the evolution: innovation, compatibility with other implementations, attempts to gain control.  </t>

<t>Some times new evolutions are "compatible", although compatibility has several variations. It is part of the responsibility of the designer of a new version of a file type to try to insure both forward and backward compatibility: new documents work reasonably (with some fallback) with old viewers and that old documents work reasonably with new viewers. In some cases this is accomplished, others not; in some cases, "works reasonably" is softened to "either works reasonably or gives clear warning about nature of problem (version mismatch)." </t>

<t>In MIME, the 'tag', the Internet Media Type, corresponds to the versioned series. Internet Media Types do not identify a particular version of a file format. Rather, the general idea is that the Internet Media Type identifies the family, and also how you're supposed to otherwise find version information on a per-format basis. Many (most) file formats have an internal version indicator, with the idea that you only need a new Internet Media Type to designate a completely incompatible format. The notion of an "Internet Media Type" is very course-grained. The general approach to this has been that the actual Media Type includes provisions for version indicator(s)  embedded in the content itself to determine more precisely the nature of how the data is to be interpreted.  That is, the message itself contains further information. </t>

<t>Unfortunately, lots has gone wrong in this scenario as well -- processors ignoring version indicators encouraging content creators to not be careful to supply correct version indicators, leading to lots of content with wrong version indicators. </t>

<t>Those updating an existing Internet Media Type registration to account for new versions are admonished to not make previously conforming documents non-conforming. This is harder to enforce than would seem, because the previous specifications are not always accurate to what the Internet Media Type was used for in practice.</t>

<t>In addition, there are situations where there are simultaneously multiple, different specifications which all claim to authoritatively define the same internet media type; one might be couched as 'newer' or 'better', or the specifications might be 'forked'.
</t>
</section>

<section title="Content Negotiation">
<t> The general idea of content negotiation is when party A communicates to party B, and the message can be delivered in more than one format (or version, or configuration), there can be some way of allowing some negotiation, some way for A to communication to B the available options, and for B to be able to accept or indicate preferences.
</t>

<t>
Content negotiation happens all over. When one fax machine twirps to another when initially connecting, they are negotiating resolution, compression methods and so forth. In Internet mail, which is a one-way communication, the "negotiation" consists of the sender preparing and sending multiple versions of the message, one in text/html, one in text/plain, for example, in sender-preference order. The recipient then chooses the first version it can understand.
</t>

<t>
HTTP added "Accept" and "Accept-language" to allow content negotiation in HTTP GET, based on Internet Media Types, and there are other methods explained in the HTTP spec.
</t>

</section>

<section title="Fragment identifiers">

<t> The Web added the notion of being able to address part of a
content and not the whole content by adding a 'fragment identifier' to
the URL that addressed the data. Of course, this originally made sense
for the original Web with just HTML, but how would it apply to other
content. The URL spec glibly noted that "the definition of the
fragment identifier meaning depends on the Internet Media Type", but
unfortunately, few of the Internet Media Type definitions included this
information, and practices diverged greatly.</t>

<t>If the interpretation of fragment identifiers depends on the MIME
type, though, this really crimps the style of using fragment
identifiers differently if content negotiation is wanted.</t>

</section>
</section>

<section title="Recommendations" anchor="changes">

<t>This section outlines the kinds of changes needed to bring the MIME
system in line with current practice and to address the problems
outlined above. The purpose of this text is not to specify the exact
details of how changes can be accomplished, but rather to find broad
aggreement.</t>

<t>We need a clear direction on how to make the Web more reliable, not
less. We need a realistic transition plan from the unreliable Web to
the more reliable one. Part of this is to encourage senders (Web
servers) to mean what they say, and encourage recipients (browsers) to
give preference to what the senders are sending.</t>

<t>We should try to create specifications for protocols and best
practices that will lead the Web to more reliable and secure
communication. To this end, we give an overall architectural approach
to use of MIME, and then specific specifications, for HTTP clients and
servers, Web Browsers in general, proxies and intermediaries, which
encourage behavior which, on the one hand, continues to work with the
already deployed infrastructure (of servers, browsers, and
intermediaries), but which advice, if followed, also improves the
operability, reliability and security of the Web.</t>

<t>This section outlines requirements for standards and practices intended to address some of the difficulties. This is an early version, which mainly  contains "strawman" proposals for changes. It is intended to stimulate discussion -- however, the hope is that we can get agreement about the nature of the problems and current situation before focusing in detail about possible solutions. However, having at least strawman proposals seems to be helpful. For some problems, additional changes to IETF and W3C specifications are also be advisable; the expectations are briefly outlined here.</t>

<section title="Internet Media Type registration">
<t>Update the Internet Media Type registry and registration process.</t>
     
<section title="MIME registry magic numbers for sniffing">
     
     <t>Be clearer about relationship of 'magic numbers' to sniffing;
     review Internet Media Types already registered and update. </t>
</section>

<section title="Scripting and scriptable content safety">

     <t>Be clearer about requiring Security Considerations to address
     risks of sniffing </t>
</section>

<section title="Fragment identifiers">
<t>Problem: MIME type definitions don't talk about fragment identifiers.</t>
<t>require definition of fragment identifier applicability; add fragID semantics </t>
</section>

<section title="Application info">
<t>Problem: Most often, the original conception of MIME for email "attachments"
    was that each content body was really a separate communication; however
    some Internet Media Types do not have that characteristic. </t>
     <t>Could the 'applications that use this type' section to be
     clearer about whether the media type is intended to be 
     piece of self-contained content (it is sensible to store the
     MIME data as a file and later launch a separate application to
     view or interact with it) or whether it is (always, most often,
     not really appropriate) to do so, and instead this content
     is intended or embedding or processing as a part of a larger
     context or application.  Of course there may be situations where
     either holds with the same media type.
     </t>
</section>

<section title="File extensions in registry">
 <t>Problem: Sniffing needs to use file extensions too; signify which file extensions are useful for sniffing.</t>
     <t>Be clearer about file extension use and relationship of file
     extensions to MIME handlers </t>
</section>
</section>

<section title="Sniffing">

<t>Various new specifications discuss, promote or mandate the use of 'sniffing' -- using the content of the data to supplement or even override the declared content-type or charset. Update these specifications.</t>

<section title="Sniffing uses Media Type magic number">
<t> Update the proposed Media Type sniffing document (<xref target='mime-sniff' />) so that sniffing uses MIME registry for 'magic numbers.</t>
</section>

<section title="Sniffing when there are multiple different definitions">
<t>Address issue of sniffing when there are multiple independent definitions of the same MIME type.</t>
</section>

<section title="Sniffing charsets">
<t> Update sniffing of charsets in HTML5 (<xref target='HTML5-charset'/> to use the charset reference info. </t>
</section>

<section title="Sniffing security uses scriptability info">
<t>If the Internet Media Type registry is more explicit about which kinds of content contain what kind of scriptability access, then the specifications for sniffing can reference the Internet Media Type registry to determine what kinds of sniffing constitute a 'privelege upgrade'.</t>

<t>Note that all sniffing can be a priviledge upgrade, if there is a buggy recipient, although bugs can be fixed, but spec violations are a problem.</t>

</section>
</section>

<section title="Changes to IANA processes for MIME registries">

<t>Problem: Internet Media Type registries are hard to update, and there can be different definitions of the same MIME type. </t>

<t>STRAWMAN: Allow commenting or easier update; not all Internet Media Type owners
     need or have all the information the internet needs. Wiki for
     Internet Media Types as well as formal registry? Ability to add comments
     about deployed senders, deployed content, deployed recievers. </t>

</section>

<section title="FTP specification">
<t>Do FTP clients also change rules about guessing file types based on OS of FTP server? 
</t>
</section>

<section title="Update some URI definitions">
<t>ftp, file, need sniffing, http sometimes does; data defaults to text/plain rather than sniffing. Should this info be in the URI definitions.</t>
</section>

<section title="Changes to W3C findings, processes">
<t> Update Tag finding on authoritative metadata:     is it possible to remove 'authority'?
   </t>
<t>new:  MIME and Internet Media Type section to WebArch, referencing this  memo </t>

  <t>New: Add a W3C Web architecture material on MIME in HTML to W3C site, referencing this memo </t>

<t> Reconsider other extensibility mechanisms (namespaces, for example): should they use MIME or something like it? </t>

</section>
</section>
 <section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>This document is the result of discussions among many 
         individuals in the IETF and W3C. Special thanks to
         Alexey Melnikov, Noah Mendelsohn. </t>

 </section>

<section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>This document includes no specific changes to IANA registries
      or processes. However, it outlines several considerations
        for future explicit recommendations to IANA,
     to change Internet Media Type and Charset registries
     and the processes around their maintenance.
     IANA evaluation of the feasibility of these changed
     processes is required.

</t>
</section>

<section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>This document discusses some of the security issues
         resulting from use (and mis-use) of MIME content types
         in the Web.</t>
</section>

</middle>

  <back>
    <!-- References split into informative and normative -->




<references title="Informative References">

<reference anchor='RFC3117' target='http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc3117'> 
<front>
<title>On the Design of Application Protocols</title>
<author initials='M.T.' surname='Rose' fullname='Marshall T. Rose'>
<organization>Dover Beach Consulting, Inc.</organization>
</author>
<date year='2001' month='November' />
</front>
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='3117' />
</reference>


<reference anchor='WikiRobust' target='http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robustness_principle'>
<front>
<title>Robustness principle</title>
<author fullname="Wikipedia" />
<date year='2010' />
</front>
</reference>

<reference anchor='Widgets' target='http://www.w3.org/TR/widgets/'>
<front>
<title>Widget Packaging and Configuration</title>
<author initials='M.' surname='Cáceres' fullname='Marcos Cáceres'>
<organization>Opera Software ASA</organization>
</author>
</front>
</reference>

<reference anchor='RFC1521' target='http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc5521'>
<front>
<title abbrev='MIME'>MIME (Multipurpose Internet Mail Extensions) Part One: Mechanisms for Specifying and Describing the Format of Internet Message Bodies</title>
<author initials='N.S.' surname='Borenstein' fullname='Nathaniel S. Borenstein'>
<organization>Bellcore</organization>
</author>
<author initials='N.' surname='Freed' fullname='Ned Freed'>
<organization>Innosoft International, Inc.</organization>
</author>
</front>
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='1521' />
</reference>

<reference anchor='RFC1522' target="http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc1522">

<front>
<title abbrev='MIME Part Two'>MIME (Multipurpose Internet Mail Extensions) Part Two: Message Header Extensions for Non-ASCII Text</title>
<author initials='K.' surname='Moore' fullname='Keith Moore'>
<organization>University of Tennessee</organization>
</author>
<date year='1993' month='September' />
</front>
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='1522' />
</reference>

<reference anchor='RFC1945' target='http://tools.ietf.org/rfc/rf1945'>
<front>
<title abbrev='HTTP/1.0'>Hypertext Transfer Protocol -- HTTP/1.0</title>
<author initials='T.' surname='Berners-Lee' fullname='Tim Berners-Lee'>
<organization>MIT, Laboratory for Computer Science</organization>
</author>

<author initials='R.T.' surname='Fielding' fullname='Roy T. Fielding'>
<organization>University of California, Irvine, Department of Information and Computer Science</organization>

</author>
<author initials='H.F.' surname='Nielsen' fullname='Henrik Frystyk Nielsen'>
<organization>W3 Consortium, MIT Laboratory for Computer Science</organization>
</author>
<date year='1996' month='May' />
</front>

<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='1945' />
</reference>

<reference anchor='RFC2046' target="http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc2046">
<front>
<title abbrev='Media Types'>Multipurpose Internet Mail Extensions (MIME) Part Two: Media Types</title>
<author initials='N.' surname='Freed' fullname='Ned Freed'>
<organization>Innosoft International, Inc.</organization>
</author>
<author initials='N.' surname='Borenstein' fullname='Nathaniel S. Borenstein'>
<organization>First Virtual Holdings</organization>
</author>
<date year='1996' month='November' />
</front>
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='2046' />
</reference>

<reference anchor="HTML5-charset" target="http://www.w3.org/TR/html5/parsing.html#determining-the-character-encoding">
<front>
<title>HTML5: A vocabulary and associated APIs for HTML and XHTML (8.2.2.1 Determining the character encoding)</title>
<author initials='I.' surname='Hickson' />
</front>
</reference>

 <reference anchor="mime-sniff" target="http://tools.ietf.org/html/draft-ietf-websec-mime-sniff">
    <front><title>Media Type Sniffing</title>
     <author initials="A." surname="Barth">
       <organization>Google, Inc.</organization>
     </author>
     <author initials="I." surname="Hickson">
       <organization>Google, Inc.</organization>
     </author>

     <date month="December" day="29" year="2010" />
    </front>
    </reference>

    <reference anchor="connolly92" target="http://lists.w3.org/Archives/Public/www-talk/1992SepOct/0024.html">
          <front>
            <title>Global Hypermedia</title>
            <author fullname="Dan Connolly" initials="D." surname="Connolly">
             <organization>pixel.convex.com</organization>
            </author>
            <date month="Oct" day="21" year="1992" />
          </front>
   </reference>

    </references>

  </back>
</rfc>


