<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="no" ?>
<rfc category="exp" ipr="trust200902" 
  docName="draft-ietf-hip-reload-instance-09">
<front>
    <title abbrev="HIP BONE Instance Spec for RELOAD">
       Host Identity Protocol-Based Overlay Networking Environment (HIP BONE)
        Instance Specification for REsource LOcation And Discovery (RELOAD)
    </title>

    <author fullname="Ari Keranen" initials="A." surname="Keranen">      
      <organization abbrev="Ericsson">Ericsson</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Hirsalantie 11</street>
          <city>02420 Jorvas</city>
          <country>Finland</country>
        </postal>
        <email>Ari.Keranen@ericsson.com</email>        
      </address>
    </author>

    <author initials="G." surname="Camarillo" fullname="Gonzalo Camarillo">
      <organization>Ericsson</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Hirsalantie 11</street>
          <code>02420</code> 
          <city>Jorvas</city> 
          <country>Finland</country>
        </postal>
        <email>Gonzalo.Camarillo@ericsson.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author initials="J." surname="Maenpaa" fullname="Jouni Maenpaa">
      <organization>Ericsson</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Hirsalantie 11</street>
          <code>02420</code> 
          <city>Jorvas</city> 
          <country>Finland</country>
        </postal>
        <email>Jouni.Maenpaa@ericsson.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>


    <date year="2013" /> 
    <area>Internet</area>
    <workgroup>HIP Working Group</workgroup>
    <keyword>HIP, overlay, P2P</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t> This document is the Host Identity Protocol-Based Overlay Networking
      Environment (HIP BONE) instance specification for the REsource LOcation
      And Discovery (RELOAD) protocol. The document provides the details needed
      to build a RELOAD-based overlay that uses HIP. </t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t> The Host Identify Protocol-Based Overlay Networking
      Environment (HIP BONE) specification <xref target="RFC6079"/>
      provides a high-level framework for building HIP-based <xref
      target="RFC5201"/> overlays. The HIP BONE framework leaves the
      specification of the details on how to combine a particular peer
      protocol with HIP to build an overlay up to documents referred
      to as HIP BONE instance specifications. As discussed in <xref
      target="RFC6079"/>, a HIP BONE instance specification needs to
      define, minimally: </t>
      
      <t> <list style="symbols">
          <t> the peer protocol to be used. </t>

          <t>what kind of Node IDs are used and how they are derived. </t>

          <t> which peer protocol primitives trigger HIP messages. </t>

          <t> how the overlay identifier is generated. </t>

        </list> </t>
      
      <t> This document addresses all the previous items and provides
      additional details needed to built RELOAD-based HIP BONEs,
      referred to here as RELOAD HIP BONEs. The details on how
      different RELOAD modules would be integrated to a HIP
      implementation and what kind of APIs are used between them are
      left as implementation details or to be defined by other
      documents. </t>

    </section>
    
    <section title="Terminology">
      <t> The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
      document are to be interpreted as described in RFC 2119 <xref
      target="RFC2119"/>. In addition, this document uses the terms defined in
      <xref target="RFC5201"/>, <xref target="RFC6079"/>, <xref
      target="RFC6028"/>, and <xref target="I-D.ietf-p2psip-base"/>.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section title="Peer Protocol">
      <t> The peer protocol to be used is REsource LOcation And
      Discovery (RELOAD) <xref target="I-D.ietf-p2psip-base"/>.  When
      used with RELOAD, HIP replaces the RELOAD's Forwarding and Link
      Management Layer (described in Section 6.5 of <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-p2psip-base"/>). </t>
    </section>

    <section title="Node ID Generation" anchor="sec-id-generation">
      <t> This document specifies two modes for generating Node and
      Resource IDs. Which mode is used in an actual overlay is defined
      by the overlay configuration. Both of the modes are based on
      16-byte ID mode of RELOAD, and hence only 16-byte RELOAD Node
      and Resource IDs MUST be used in a RELOAD HIP BONE. </t>

      <t> HIP uses 128-bit Overlay Routable Cryptographic Hash
      Identifiers (ORCHIDs) <xref target="RFC4843"/> as
      identifiers. In a RELOAD HIP BONE a peer's ORCHID can be used as
      such as a RELOAD Node ID (the "ORCHID" mode). In this mode all
      the RELOAD IDs, including Resource IDs, are prefixed with the
      ORCHID prefix and the lower 100 bits of the IDs defined by
      RELOAD usage documents are used after the prefix. </t>

      <t> In the other Node ID mode, namely "RELOAD", all 128 bits are
      generated as defined in <xref target="I-D.ietf-p2psip-base"/>
      resulting in a larger usable address space. The downside of not
      using the ORCHID prefix is that such Node IDs can not be used
      with legacy applications and APIs, as discussed in Section 5.1
      of <xref target="RFC6079"/>.</t>

    </section>

    <section title="Mapping between Protocol Primitives and HIP Messages">

      <t> RELOAD HIP BONE replaces the RELOAD protocol primitives
      taking care of connection establishment with the HIP base
      exchange, whereas the rest of the RELOAD messages are conveyed
      within HIP messages. The Forwarding and Link Management Layer
      functionality of RELOAD, including all the NAT traversal
      functionality, is replaced by HIP, existing extensions of HIP,
      and the extensions defined in this document. </t>

      <t> The standard RELOAD messages consist of three parts:
      Forwarding Header, Message Contents and the Security Block. When
      RELOAD messages are sent in a RELOAD HIP BONE overlay, the
      RELOAD Message Contents are used as such within HIP DATA <xref
      target="RFC6078"/> messages, but the functionality of the
      Forwarding Header and Security Block are replaced with HIP
      header, HIP Destination and Via lists <xref target="RFC6028"/>,
      and CERT <xref target="RFC6253"/>, TRANSACTION_ID <xref
      target="RFC6078"/>, OVERLAY_ID and OVERLAY_TTL <xref
      target="RFC6079"/> parameters, as defined in the following
      sections. </t>

      <section title="Forwarding Header">
        <t> The RELOAD Forwarding Header is used for forwarding
        messages between peers and to their final destination. The
        Forwarding Header's overlay field value MUST be used as such
        in an OVERLAY_ID parameter and the transaction_id field in a
        TRANSACTION_ID parameter. That is, all RELOAD HIP BONE
        messages MUST contain these parameters and the length of the
        OVERLAY_ID parameter's identifier field is 4 and the length of
        the TRANSACTION_ID parameter is 8 octets. HIP Destination and
        Via lists are used for the same purpose as the
        destination_list and via_list in the Forwarding Header, with
        the exception that all Resource IDs MUST be of the same length
        as Node IDs and compressed IDs MUST NOT be used. The TTL value
        in the OVERLAY_TTL parameter is used like the ttl field in the
        Forwarding Header. </t>

        <t> The functionality of the fragment and length fields are
        provided by the HIP headers. The relo_token, version, and
        max_response_length are not needed with HIP and options field,
        if needed eventually for some extensions, can be replaced with
        additional HIP parameters. </t>
      </section>

      <section title="Security Block">
        <t> The RELOAD Security Block contains certificates and digital
        signatures of the message. All the HIP DATA messages are digitally
        signed by the originator of the message and contain the HOST_ID
        parameter with the identifier that can be used for verifying the
        signature. Certificates are delivered in a HIP CERT parameter as
        defined in <xref target="RFC6253"/> or stored to the overlay
        using the RELOAD Certificate Storage Usage. </t>

        <t> Note that when the RELOAD mode for Node ID generation is used, the
        certificate certifying that a host is allowed to use a certain Node ID
        MUST contain host's Node ID instead of HIT in the "Subject Alternative
        Name" of the certificate as described in Section 11.3 of <xref
        target="I-D.ietf-p2psip-base"/> while the "Subject" field contains the
        HIT calculated from the Host Identity. </t>
      </section>

      <section title="Replaced RELOAD Messages">
        <t> The Attach procedure in RELOAD establishes a connection between two
        peers. This procedure is performed using the AttachReq and AttachAns
        messages. When HIP is used, the Attach procedure is performed by using
        a HIP base exchange. That is, peers send HIP I1 messages instead of
        RELOAD AttachReq messages. This behavior replaces the one described in
        Section 6.5 of <xref target="I-D.ietf-p2psip-base"/>. </t>

        <t> The AppAttach procedure in RELOAD is used for creating a connection
        for other applications than RELOAD. Also the AppAttach procedure is
        replaced with HIP base exchange and, after the base exchange, peers can
        exchange any application layer data using the normal transport layer
        ports over the NAT traversing IPsec connection. </t>

        <t> This specification does not support flooding of configuration
        files, so ConfigUpdate requests and responses (Section 6.5.4 of <xref
        target="I-D.ietf-p2psip-base"/>) MUST NOT be sent in the
        overlay. RELOAD Ping messages (Section 6.5.3 of <xref
        target="I-D.ietf-p2psip-base"/>) MAY be used.</t>

        <t> For all other RELOAD messages the Message Contents are used as such
        within HIP DATA messages. </t>
      </section>

    </section>

    <section title="Securing Communication">

      <t> RELOAD uses TLS <xref target="RFC5246"/> connections for securing the
      hop-by-hop messaging and certificates and signatures for providing
      integrity protection for the overlay messages and for the data stored in
      the overlay.</t>

      <t> With a RELOAD HIP BONE, instead of using TLS connections as
      defined in <xref target="I-D.ietf-p2psip-base"/>, all HIP
      overlay messages SHOULD be either sent using encrypted
      connections (such as IPsec ESP tunnel between two peers <xref
      target="RFC6261"/>) or the contents of the messages SHOULD be in
      an ENCRYPTED parameter (see Section 5.2.15 of <xref
      target="RFC5201"/>). Use of encrypted connections is RECOMMENDED
      since that provides confidentiality also for the HIP
      headers. </t>

      <t> The data objects stored in the RELOAD HIP BONE overlay are
      signed and the signatures are stored as defined in <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-p2psip-base"/> with the exception that
      SignerIdentity is carried in the HIP DATA message's HOST_ID
      parameter instead of using the RELOAD SecurityBlock. Where
      certificates are needed, they are sent using the HIP CERT
      parameter. </t>

    </section>


    <section title="Routing HIP Messages via the Overlay" anchor="routing-hip">
      <t> If a host has no valid locator for the receiver of a new HIP packet,
      and the receiver is part of a RELOAD HIP BONE overlay the host is
      participating in, the host can send the HIP packet to the receiver using
      the overlay routing. </t>

      <t> When sending a HIP packet via the overlay, the host MUST add an empty
      ROUTE_VIA parameter <xref target="RFC6028"/> to the packet with
      the SYMMETRIC and MUST_FOLLOW flags set and an OVERLAY_ID parameter
      containing the identifier of the right overlay network. The host consults
      the RELOAD Topology Plugin for the next hop and sends the HIP packet to
      that host. </t>

      <t> An intermediate host receiving a HIP packet with the
      OVERLAY_ID parameter checks if it is participating in that
      overlay, and SHOULD drop packets sent to unknown overlays. If
      the host is not the final destination of the packet (i.e., the
      Receiver HIT in the HIP header does not match to any of its
      HITs), it checks if the packet contains a ROUTE_DST
      parameter. Such packets are forwarded to the next hop as
      specified in <xref target="RFC6028"/>. If the packet does not
      contain a ROUTE_DST parameter, the host finds the next hop from
      the RELOAD Topology Plugin and forwards the packet there.  As
      specified in <xref target="RFC6028"/>, the host adds the HIT it
      uses on the HIP association with the next hop host to the end of
      the ROUTE_VIA parameter, if present. </t>
      
      <t> When the final destination host receives the HIP packet, the host
      processes it as specified in <xref target="RFC5201"/> and in case of HIP
      DATA packet, the contents are processed as specified in <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-p2psip-base"/>. If the HIP packet generates a response,
      the response is routed back on the same path using the ROUTE_DST
      parameter as specified in <xref target="RFC6028"/>. </t>

    </section>

    <section title="Enrollment and Bootstrapping">
      <t>The RELOAD HIP BONE instance uses the enrollment and bootstrap 
      procedure defined by RELOAD <xref target="I-D.ietf-p2psip-base"/> with 
      the exceptions listed below.</t>

      <t><list style="symbols"> 

	<t>In RELOAD, a node wishing to enroll in an overlay starts
	with obtaining a configuration document as explained in <xref
	target="I-D.ietf-p2psip-base"/>. This specification extends
	the RELOAD overlay configuration document as defined in <xref
	target="sec-config"/>. </t>

        <t>The X.509 certificates used by the RELOAD HIP BONE instance are 
        similar to those of RELOAD except that they contain HITs instead of 
        RELOAD URIs. The HITs are included in the SubjectAltName field of the 
        certificate as described in <xref target="RFC6253"/>.</t>
          
        <t> When contacting a bootstrap node, instead of forming a DTLS or TLS
        connection, the host MUST perform a HIP base exchange with the
        bootstrap node. The base exchange MAY be performed using a HIP
        rendezvous or relay server. </t>

        </list></t>

      <t> </t>

    </section>
    
    <section title="NAT Traversal">

      <t> RELOAD relies on the Forwarding and Link Management Layer providing
      NAT traversal capabilities. Thus, the RELOAD HIP BONE instance
      implementations MUST implement some reliable NAT traversal mechanism. To
      maximize interoperability, all implementations SHOULD implement at least
      <xref target="RFC5770"/>. </t>

      <t> HIP relay servers are not necessarily needed with this HIP BONE
      instance since the overlay network can be used for relaying the Base
      Exchange and further HIP signaling can be done directly between the
      peers. However, if it is possible that a bootstrap peer is behind a NAT,
      it MUST register with a HIP relay so that there is a reliable way to
      connect to it. </t>

    </section>


    <section title="RELOAD Overlay Configuration Document Extension" 
      anchor="sec-config">

      <t> This document modifies the bootstrap-node element of the RELOAD 
      overlay configuration document. The modified bootstrap-node element 
      contains the following attributes: </t>

      <t><list style="hanging">
        <t hangText="address:">The locator of the bootstrap node.</t>
        <t hangText="port:">The HIP port of the bootstrap node.</t>
        <t hangText="hit:">The HIT of the bootstrap node.</t>
      </list></t>

      <t> If the bootstrap-node element does not contain a HIT, the
      opportunistic mode (as specified in <xref target="RFC5201"/>)
      SHOULD be used for contacting the bootstrap node. If the element
      does not contain a port number, the bootstrap node SHOULD be
      contacted by starting the base exchange as defined in <xref
      target="RFC5201"/>.  Otherwise, the base exchange MUST be
      started UDP-encapsulated as defined in <xref target="RFC5770"/>
      using the given port as the destination port number. </t>

      <t> A RELOAD HIP BONE overlay MUST use Overlay Link Protocol
      type "HIP" in the configuration document's overlay-link-protocol
      element. The enrolling node MUST check the overlay-link-protocol
      element and proceed with procedures defined in this document
      only if "HIP" link type is found. </t>

      <t> This document also adds a new element inside the
      configuration element that defines which mode (see <xref
      target="sec-id-generation"/>) is used for generating the Node
      and Resource IDs. The name of the element is "hipbone-id-mode"
      and the content is the identifier of the mode: "ORCHID" for the
      ORCHID prefixed IDs and "RELOAD" for the IDs that use the whole
      128 bits as defined by the RELOAD specification.  The
      NodeIdLength MUST be set to 16 in the configuration document and
      the 16 bytes are used, depending on the generation mode, as
      defined in <xref target="sec-id-generation"/>. </t>
    </section>

    <section title="Security Considerations" anchor="sec-security">
      <t> The security considerations of RELOAD (Section 13 of <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-p2psip-base"/>), with the exception of TLS specific
      features, apply also to RELOAD HIP BONE instances. </t>

      <t> The option to send overlay messages unencrypted makes it possible for
      hosts that are not part of the overlay to inspect the contents of the
      messages and thus should be avoided when possible. If the ENCRYPTED
      parameter is used instead of encrypted connections, the HIP header
      remains visible but the contents are protected. </t>

      <t> Limiting the Node ID and Resource ID space into 128 bits (or 100 bits
      with ORCHID prefixes) results in a higher probability for ID collisions,
      both unintentional and intentional, than using larger address
      spaces. </t>
    </section>

    <section title="IANA Considerations" anchor="sec-iana">
      <t> This section is to be interpreted according to <xref
      target="RFC5226"/>. </t>

      <t> IANA is requested to update the "Overlay Link Protocol"
      registry <xref target="I-D.ietf-p2psip-base"/> by assigning new
      Overlay Link Protocol type "HIP" (see <xref
      target="sec-config"/>). </t>
    </section>

    <section title="Acknowledgements" anchor="sec-acks">
      <t> Tom Henderson and Christer Holmberg have provided valuable
      reviews and comments on the draft. </t>
    </section>

  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4843" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5201" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5226" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5770" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6028" ?> 
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6078" ?>     
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6079" ?>      
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6253" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6261" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.I-D.ietf-p2psip-base" ?>
    </references>

    <references title="Informational References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5246" ?>
    </references>

  </back>
  
</rfc>
