<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc toc="yes" symrefs="no" ?>
<rfc docName="draft-xu-homenet-traffic-class-00" ipr="pre5378Trust200902">
	<front>
		<title abbrev="Traffic Class Routing in HomeNet">Traffic Class Routing Protocol in Home Networks</title>
		<author initials='M.' surname='Xu' fullname='Mingwei Xu'>
			<organization abbrev='Tsinghua University'>Tsinghua University</organization>
			<address>
				<postal>
	        <street>Department of Computer Science, Tsinghua University</street>
	        <city>Beijing</city>
	        <code>100084</code>
	        <country>P.R. China</country>
	    	</postal>
	    	<phone>+86-10-6278-5822</phone>
	    	<email>xmw@csnet1.cs.tsinghua.edu.cn</email>
	    </address>
		</author>
		<author initials='S.' surname='Yang' fullname='Shu Yang'>
			<organization abbrev='Tsinghua University'>Tsinghua University</organization>	
				<address>
				<postal>
	      				  <street>Department of Computer Science, Tsinghua University</street>
	       				 <city>Beijing</city>
	      				  <code>100084</code>
	      				  <country>P.R. China</country>
	    			</postal>
	    				<phone>+86-10-6278-5822</phone>
	    				<email>yangshu@csnet1.cs.tsinghua.edu.cn</email>
	   			 </address>
		</author>
		<author initials="J." surname="Wu" fullname="Jianping Wu">
		  <organization abbrev="Tsinghua University">Tsinghua University</organization>
		  <address>
		    <postal>
		      <street>
			Department of Computer Science, Tsinghua University
		      </street>
		      <city>Beijing</city>
		      <code>100084</code>
		      <country>P.R. China</country>
		    </postal>
		    <phone>+86-10-6278-5983</phone>
		    <email>jianping@cernet.edu.cn</email>
		  </address>
		</author>
		<author initials="F." surname="Baker" fullname="Fred Baker">
		  <organization abbrev="Cisco Systems">Cisco Systems</organization>
		  <address>
		    <postal>
		      <street> </street>
		      <city>Santa Barbara, California</city>
		      <code>93117</code>
		      <country>USA</country>
		    </postal>
		    
		    <email>fred@cisco.com</email>
		  </address>
		</author>

		<date month="July" year="2013" />

		<abstract>
			<t>Home IT staff is generally unfamiliar with network operations, making it desirable to provide a configuration-free mode of operation. Policy-based routing (in the sense of configuring one router to redirect traffic to another based on access control) and multi-topology routing both require configuration, making them undesirable.
			 </t>
			<t>
			  In this document, we propose a configuration-free mechanism, in which packets will be routed towards
			  the corresponding upstream ISPs based on both destination and source addresses.

			 </t>
		</abstract>
	</front>

<middle>
<section title="Introduction">
	<t>Home networks are growing both in device count and in complexity. Today they generally contain both wired and wireless components, and may require routing to place audio/visual entertainment traffic one one path, office services on another, and wireless LANs (both IEEE-style and 4G/LTE-style) on a third. Traditionally, we have simplified networks using a single exit router and a default route. Today, we might have multiple routers to wired upstream networks, and by separate paths LTE services, "Smart Grid" services, or health network services. Increasingly, such networks are multihomed, and multihomed using diverse access network technologies.</t>

	<t>Traditionally, routing protocols make routing decisions solely based on destination IP addresses, packets towards
	the same destination will be delivered to the same next hop no matter where they come from. These protocols work well with simple
	home networks that have only one egress router. However, in the multi-homing scenario, packets may be dropped if forwarded
	only based on destination addresses <xref target="RFC3704"></xref>. </t>

	<t>Although many patch-like solutions, like policy-based routing (PBR), multi-topology routing (MTR) and layer-3 VPN can solve the problem, they complex the configurations in home networks, and are not suitable for home IT staffs. We need a configuration-free solution to help operators set up their home networks in the multi-homing scenario.</t>

	<t>In this document, we propose a configuration-free mechanism - traffic class routing, based on OSPFv3, such that home networks can route packets towards the corresponding upstream ISPs, according to both destination and source addresses.</t>

</section>

<section title="Terminology">
	<t>Terminology used in this document:</t>
        <t><list style="symbols">
	  
	  <t>Traffic Class (TC): Identified by (destination prefix, source prefix), all packets falling in the domain belong to the traffic
	  class.</t>
	  <t>TC-Route: Identified by (destination prefix, source prefix, value), where value is the administrative value applied to the
	  traffic class (destination prefix, source prefix). </t>
	  <t>TC-LSA: Link state advertisement that communicates the reachability for a traffic classes.</t>
	</list>
	</t>
</section>

<section title="Overview">
<t>
In a home network, traditionally, egress routers obtain delegated prefixes from upstream ISPs using DHCPv6 with prefix options <xref target="RFC3633"></xref>. The egress routers will then assign longer sub-prefixes to the other links in the home network. Each router inside the home network will act as standard OSPFv3 router, and forward packets based on their destination addresses.
</t>

<t>
With traffic class routing, after obtaining delegated prefixes and assigning sub-prefixes, egress routers will populate traffic classes (with extended LSAs), rather than destination address only, into the home network. Each router inside the home network will flood these traffic classes information. When calculating the path towards a destination address, routers will take the traffic classes into considerations. Intrinsically, in traditional routing model, the object being routed to is a destination prefix; in our routing model, the object being routed might be a destination prefix given that the packet sports a certain source prefix.
</t>

<t>
Each traffic class is associated with a cost, which is a single dimensionless metric.
</t>

<t>
For example, a site is connected to the Internet through two ISPs, ISP1 and ISP2. ISP1 delegates prefix P1 to the site, and ISP2 delegates prefix P2 to the site. After being delegated with P1, the egress router E1 of the site will advertise a traffic class - {::/0, P1}, into the site. After being delegated with P2, the egress router E2 of the site will advertise a traffic class - {::/0, P2}, into the site. Receiving these advertisements, interior router I1 will compute two paths towards ::/0, one through router E1 for traffic from P1, the other through E2 for traffic from P2.  
</t>


		<figure title="Figure 1: Multi-homing Scenario in Home Networks">
		  <artwork>
			<![CDATA[
            +---------------+                  +-----------------+
            |               |                  |                 |
            |   ISP1: P1    |                  |    ISP2: P2     |
            |               |                  |                 |
            +--------+------+                  +-----+-----------+
                     |                               |
                  +--+---+                        +--+---+
                  |Router|                        |Router|
                  | BR1  |                        | BR2  |
                  +---+--+                        +---+--+
                ------+----------          -----------+-----
                      |                               |        
                  +---+--+                        +---+--+
                  |Router|                        |Router|
                  |  E1  |                        |  E2  |
                  +------+       +------+         +------+
                        -+-------+Router+---------+-
                                 |  I1  |
                                 +--+---+
                                 +--+---+  Address A in P1
                                 | Host |  
                                 +------+  Address B in P2
			]]>
		  </artwork>
		</figure>
  
  </section>

<section title = "Router Behavior">
<t>
  All routers behave like traditional OSPFv3 routers, however, the following behaviors are different with traditional OSPFv3 routers.
  </t>
  <section title = "Egress Router Behavior">
    <t>
    After obtaining delegated prefixes using DHCPv6 with prefix options, an egress router should originate TC-LSAs, i.e., extended LSAs with source prefixes appended. Egress routers then will advertise these TC-LSAs into the home network.
    </t>
    <t>
    Note that an egress router behaves like an interior router if it receives a TC-LSA from other egress routers. 
    </t>
    </section>
  <section title = "Interior Router Behavior">
    <t>
      Receiving TC-LSAs from egress routers, an interior router should store the TC-LSAs into its LSDB, and flood it to other routers. 
      After calculating a path to an egress router advertising reachability, i.e., a destination prefix, the interior router should
      decide which traffic class can follow this path towards the egress router. If a traffic class can travel through two different paths,
      then interior router should compare their costs, and select the path with the lowest cost.
      </t>
    <t>
      Interior routers contains a routing table that contains all necessary information to forward an IP packet following
      the path of a traffic class. After computing the path towards a traffic class, interior routers should update the entry
      in the routing table if necessary, e.g., change the next hop towards the traffic class. The routing table structure
      will be described in Section 6. Calculation of routing table will be illustrated in Section 7.
      </t>
    <t>
      At last, interior routers should update the Forwarding Information Base (FIB), which will be discussed in the next version of this document.
      </t>
  </section>
  </section>

<section title = "TC-LSA Format">
  <t>
    TC-LSA adds TLV extensions, which contains source prefix information, based on original OSPFv3 LSA. We follow the TLV format
    in <xref target="I-D.baker-ipv6-ospf-dst-src-routing"></xref> and extended LSA format in <xref target="I-D.acee-ospfv3-lsa-extend"></xref>. 
    </t>

  <t>
    Each extended LSA includes the traditional LSA part in <xref target="RFC5340"></xref>, and one or more TLVs defined in <xref target="I-D.baker-ipv6-ospf-dst-src-routing"></xref>. But we do not need all LSAs to be extended, the LSAs need
    to be extended are as follows:</t>
    <t><list style="symbols">
      <t> Intra-Area-Prefix-LSA: The extended LSA has type 0x2029.</t> 
    </list></t>

  <t>
    The extended LSA format for Intra-Area-Prefix-LSA in multi-homing is as follows: 
    </t>
  <t>
    <figure title="Figure 1: Multi-homing Scenario in Home Networks">
      <artwork>
	<![CDATA[
       
       0                   1                   2                   3
       0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
      +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
      |           LS Age              |0|0|1|       LSA Type          |
      +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
      |                      Link State ID                            |
      +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
      |                   Advertising Router                          |
      +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
      |                   LS Sequence Number                          |
      +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
      |        LS Checksum            |          LSA Length           |
      +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
      |       # Prefixes              |     Referenced LS Type        |
      +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
      |                  Referenced Link State ID                     |
      +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
      |               Referenced Advertising Router                   |
      +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
      |  PrefixLength | PrefixOptions |          Metric               |
      +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
      |                        Address Prefix                         |
      |                             ...                               |
      +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
      |                             ...                               |
      +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
      |  PrefixLength | PrefixOptions |          Metric               |
      +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
      |                        Address Prefix                         |
      |                             ...                               |
      +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
      |           TLV Type            |        TLV Length             |
      +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
      | SPrefixLength | SPrefixOptions|               0               |
      +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
      |                  Source Address Prefix                        |
      |                             ...                               |
      +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
      |                             ...                               |
      +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
      |           TLV Type            |        TLV Length             |
      +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
      | SPrefixLength | SPrefixOptions|               0               |
      +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
      |                  Source Address Prefix                        |
      |                             ...                               |
      +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
	]]>
      </artwork>
    </figure>
    </t>
  <t>
    All LSA header fields are the same as defined in <xref target="RFC5340"></xref>, except the following:
    </t>

  <t><list style="symbols">
    <t> LSA type: The LSA type value is 0x2029, according to <xref target="I-D.acee-ospfv3-lsa-extend"></xref>;</t> 
    <t> LSA length: The length of the whole LSA header, including the TLVs; </t>
    <t> TLV type: The type of IPv6 source prefix TLV, assigned by IANA;</t>
    <t> TLV length: The value is 20 as defined in <xref target="I-D.baker-ipv6-ospf-dst-src-routing"></xref>;</t>
    <t> SPrefixLength, SPrefixOptions, Source Address Prefix: Representation of the IPv6 address prefix, which is delegated from the upstream ISP providers;</t>
  </list></t>

  <t>
    In the extended LSA, suppose there are n destination prefix d1, d2, ..., dn, and m source prefix s1, s2, ..., sm, then the LSA
    carries n*m TC-route announcement, (d1, s1, v1), (d1, s2, v1), ..., (d1, sm, v1), (d2, s1, v2), (d2, s2, v2), ..., (dn, sm, vn),
    where vi is the metric associated with destination prefix di.
    </t>
  </section>		

<section title = "Routing Table Structure">
  <t>
    For traditional routing, the routing table structure contains all needed information to forward IP
    packets to the right destination. For example, destination prefixes are commonly structured into a prefix trie, 
    where each trie nodes contain the necessary information. Routers can lookup and
    update the prefix trie. 
    </t>
  <t>
    With traffic classes, the routing table structure must contain all needed information to forward IP
    packets following the right traffic class, i.e., towards the related destination and from the related
    source. For each routing table entry, there are two additional fields other than the fields mentioned
    in <xref target="RFC5340"></xref>:
    </t>
  <t><list style="symbols">
    <t> Source IP Address: The IP address of the source in traffic class.</t> 
    <t> Source Address Mask: If the source is a subnet, then it is referred to as the subnet mask.</t>
  </list></t>

  <t>The routing table must provide interface for update and lookup in it. For example, traffic classes
  can be structured into a two dimensional (or two level) trie, where each trie node in the first dimension
  points to a sub-trie in the second dimension. The trie nodes in the second dimension contain the necessary
  information to forward IP packets following the right traffic class.
    </t>
  </section>

<section title = "Calculation of the Routing Table">
  <t>
    The fundamental algorithm in OSPFv3 doesn't change. The algorithm uses the SPF approach to 
    calculate a path to the router advertising reachability, and then uses the reachability advertisement 
    to decide what traffic should follow that route. What we are changing is the reachability advertisement,
    in traiditional OSPFv3, the advertisements, which is one or several kinds of LSAs, represent destination prefixes;
    in this document, the advertisements, which is one or several kinds of TC-LSAs, represent traffic classes.
    </t>
  <t>
    Note that we do not have to change router-LSA and network-LSA in <xref target="RFC5340"></xref>. Thus, the first stage of
    Section 4.8.1 in <xref target="RFC5340"></xref> remains the same in this document. However, the second stage of Section 4.8.1 in
    <xref target="RFC5340"></xref> should change by a little bit. Instead of examining the list of the intra-area-prefix-LSAs,
    the list of extended intra-area-prefix-LSAs is examined. The cost of any advertised traffic class is the sum
    of the class' advertised metric plus the cost of the transit vertex (either router or transit network) indentified
    by extended intra-area-prefix-LSAs' referenced LS type, referenced link state ID, and referenced advertising 
    router field. 
    </t>
  </section>

<section title = "Matching Rule">
  <t>
  We also adopt the LMF (longest match first) rule when a packet matches multiple routing entries. However, traffic class has
  two dimensions, there might exist ambiguity. For example, if there exists two routing entries, (d1, s1, nexthop1), (d2, s2,
  nexthop2), where d1 is longer than d2 and s2 is longer than s1, then none entry is longer than the other in both dimensions. 
  
  In this situation, we must insert an additional entry into the routing table, e.g., (d1, s2, nexthop1) in the above 
  example. The entry directs to nexthop1 rather than nexthop2, because we must guarantee reachability according to 
  the destination prefix.
  </t>
</section>

<section title = "Compatibility">
  <t>
    Routers can also announce the traditional destination-based LSAs at the same time. In this case, routers have to keep two
    routing tables, one for destination prefix only, and the other for traffic classes. When a packet arrives, routers first
    lookup in the routing table storing traffic classes; If none entry matches, then routers lookup in the routing table storing
    destination prefixes.
    </t>
  </section>

		
<section title="IANA Considerations">
	<t>
		The newly LSA types and TLVs should be assigned by IANA, please refer to <xref target="I-D.baker-ipv6-ospf-dst-src-routing"></xref> and <xref target="I-D.acee-ospfv3-lsa-extend"></xref>. 
		</t>
</section>

<section title="Acknowledgments">
<t>Zheng Liu and Gautier Bayzelon provided useful input into this document.</t>
</section>
</middle>

<back>
	<references title="Normative References">
		<?rfc include="reference.RFC.3704" ?>
		<?rfc include="reference.RFC.3633" ?>
		<?rfc include="reference.RFC.5340" ?>
		
	</references>

	<references title="Informative References">
                <?rfc include="reference.I-D.draft-ietf-homenet-arch-07" ?>
		<?rfc include="reference.I-D.draft-baker-ipv6-ospf-dst-src-routing-02" ?>
		<?rfc include="reference.I-D.draft-acee-ospfv3-lsa-extend-00" ?>
		<?rfc include="reference.I-D.draft-baker-fun-routing-class-00" ?>
	</references>
</back>
</rfc>
