<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc toc='yes'?>
<?rfc tocdepth='4'?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>

<rfc category="info" docName="draft-kyzivat-siprec-conference-use-cases-00" ipr="trust200902">
	<front>
		<title abbrev="Use Cases for Multimedia Conf Rec">Multimedia Conference Recording Use Cases and Requirements</title>
		<author initials="P." surname="Kyzivat" fullname="Paul H. Kyzivat">
			<organization>Huawei</organization>
			<address>
				<email>pkyzivat@alum.mit.edu</email>
			</address>
		</author>
		<author initials="M." surname="Yan" fullname="Michael Yan">
			<organization>Huawei</organization>
			<address>
				<email>michael.yan@huawei.com</email>
			</address>
		</author>
		<author initials="S P." surname="Romano" fullname="Simon Pietro Romano">
			<organization>University of Napoli</organization>
			<address>
				<email>spromano@unina.it</email>
			</address>
		</author>

		<date day="13" month="September" year="2013"/>
                  <area>RAI</area>
		<workgroup>SIPREC</workgroup>

		<abstract>
            <t>The current work of SIPREC will soon finish. As conferences are the key requirement for some environments, it is worth to explore several extensions and additional functionalities to support multimedia conference recording. SIPREC is not sufficient to record all the conference sessions via certain interactive media channels, like multi-user chat or screen sharing.</t> 
            <t>This draft tries to show the use cases for multimedia conference recording and the requirements for how to work well under SIPREC mechanism.</t>
		</abstract>

		<note title="Requirements Language">
			<t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in <xref target="RFC2119">RFC 2119</xref>.</t>
		</note>
	</front>

	<middle>
		<section title="Introduction">
            <t>In general, a basic video conference has participants with video channels, audio channels and DTMF ability. An advanced multimedia conference would have extended channels like text, interactive text and presentation graphics <xref target="RFC4597"/>. These extended channels recording have the same strong needs as audio or video, especially in some conference use cases. The conference's host and participants, even nonparticipants, would like to play back the recordings in real-time or non-real-time for different purposes, like editing  summary, reviewing outlines or monitoring process. The recordings should have the ability to reconstruct the conference richly, with adequate media and metadata recorded, which are not only audio/video but also IM, shared data and even floor negotiation information via BFCP. Such an exhaustive reconstruction could give audiences more information and a better experience.</t>
        </section>

		<section title="Multimedia Conference Recording Overview">
	        <t>There is one use case (use case 11) covering the recording of a multi-channel and multimedia session in the existing use case document <xref target="RFC6341"/>. Aside from audio, video and text (as defined by <xref target="RFC4103"/>), it does not include other interactive channels. The limitations to the multi-channel types leads to poor support for recording multimedia conference. A multimedia conference has various channels, including audio, video, IM, data sharing(screen/document/application), etc. SIPREC is mostly capable of recording any sort of RTP media sessions, including voice, DTMF, video, and text <xref target="RFC6341"/> with SDP negotiation <xref target="I-D.ietf-siprec-protocol"/> and certain metadata <xref target="I-D.ietf-siprec-metadata"/>. But it is not evident how to support the remaining media, like multi-user chat or screen sharing.</t>

            <t>Multi-user chat session is one of key cases about the IM session in CS of multimedia conference. A multi-user chat or simple-chat session is to handle the media to relay instant messages received from one participant to the rest of the participants in the conference <xref target="I-D.ietf-simple-chat"/>, especially for the MSRP session. The host and participants in conference might start MSRP sessions among each others for public group chat, sidebar chat or whisper chat. These MSRP content could be replicated by SRC (might be the MSRP switch or certain MSRP replay or MSRP client) to deliver to SRS via a special RS channel. The replicated content could be the Message/CPIM message that contains text, HTML and Image, etc. Recording XMPP based IM in CS is out of the scope for this document.</t>

	        <t>The data sharing, known as content sharing or content streams as well, in a multimedia conference's CS has functionalities as screen sharing, application sharing, document sharing, etc. These data streams of them could be managed as still images (snapshots with increments) or as dynamic streams (video streams) to carry details like slide presentation, annotating, direct editing or page turning. Especially, the screen sharing would have different ways to get its data streams, like the video streams directly offered from VGA port or codec by application on peer's client or turned from multiple screenshots, or even the still images carried by MSRP channels. </t>

			<t>One way for a conference focus to record a conference is introduced in <xref target="I-D.ietf-siprec-architecture"/>. This defines how the conference focus works as a SRC to deliver RTP streams and associate recording metadata to SRS. It may choose the recording RTP stream type, separated or mixed. There are more details about how to use SDP, RTP for recording by participant or by media type in <xref target="I-D.ietf-siprec-protocol"/>. The focus may setup different recording sessions for different media streams recorded separately, or one recording session for a mixed media stream created by the SRC, or even multiplexing different media streams in a single RTP recording session<xref target="I-D.ietf-siprec-protocol"/>.</t>

			<t>But more is needed to support other media streams in a multimedia conference. There is need for MSRP switch/relay/client as SRC to replicate MSRP session to the recorder, with a new "media stream" type in RS for delivering MSRP based streams or contents. There is another need for a new type of "media stream" for data sharing, distinct from the main video streams, with different m-lines or metadata. There is also need of a mechanism for the SRC to bound the number of media streams to be recorded, especially when the participant number in a conference is extremely large. </t>
        </section>

        <section title="Definitions">
            <t>Instant Message Stream: instant message stream refers to the streams transferred by messages between users in near real-time <xref target="RFC3248"/>.</t>

            <t>Data Sharing: Data sharing is to use a content channel for collaboratively working on documents, files, images, desktops, etc in real time. It is also called as content sharing, including application sharing, screen sharing, document sharing, etc.</t>

            <t>Application Sharing: application sharing is the sharing
of the graphical user-interface of an application amongst multiple users simultaneously in real time. The slide sharing could be one of special case.</t>

            <t>Screen Sharing: screen sharing is the sharing of a computer desktop amongst multiple users simultaneously in real time, also called desktop sharing. Comparing to application sharing, which is always a single one, screen sharing is for the a whole screen.</t>

            <t>Document Sharing: document sharing is the sharing to help multiple users working simultaneously on a single document or file to achieve a single final version. It is also called as file sharing or document collabration.</t>

            <t>Audio/Video Conference: Audio/video conference is one sort of various conferences. In SIP, an audio/video conference is an instance of a multi-party conversation that followed the definition in <xref target="RFC4353"/> and the framework in <xref target="RFC5239"/>, with the media channels as audio and video.</t>

            <t>Chat Conference: a synonym for a multi-party chat conference <xref target="I-D.ietf-simple-chat"/>.</t>

            <t>Multimedia Conference: multimedia conference is the multi-party conversation include any combination of different media types such as audio, video, text, interactive text, or presentation graphics <xref target="RFC4597"/>.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Use cases">
		<section title="Instant Message Stream Recording">
            <t>Use Case 1: Instant Message Stream Recording.</t>
            <t>Instant message is the function offered to chat between/among peers. There are page mode and session mode <xref target="RFC6914"/>. Here especially means the instant message session happened in the point to point call using session mode, which consider instant message as a media type.</t> 
            <t>For example, in a call center or emergency (first-responder) center, a customer could use the web client to start a chat with an agent about his questions or describing the situation happened around him. Call center or emergency center would need to record those chat sessions between customers and agents.</t>              
        </section>

		<section title="Screen Sharing Stream Recording">
            <t>Use Case 2: Screen Sharing Stream Recording.</t>
            <t>This is also well known as desktop sharing or remote sharing between peers. This function could be also used in a point to point call directly. </t>
            <t>In an enterprise, the softphone calls between colleagues would choose screen sharing to illustrate their views clearly if the voice discussing is not enough. The enterprise would ask to record those screen sharing session for security check. </t>
            <t>Another example is the remote education training, it need to record the screen to keep the integrality of training class.</t>
        </section>

		<section title="Application Sharing Stream Recording">
            <t>Use Case 3: Application Sharing Stream Recording.</t>
            <t>Users would choose application sharing instead of screen sharing to avoid exposing the privacy content on their computer desktop, when have the point-to-point call with others or have a conference call. And the recorded streams are the content of applications shown in CS. </t>
        </section>

		<section title="Document Sharing Stream Recording">
            <t>Use Case 4: Document Sharing Stream Recording.</t>
            <t>Users would work on one document simultaneously in real time. The content of document would be recorded which is close to use case 3.</t>
        </section>

		<section title="Audio/Video Conference Recording">
		 	<t>Use Case 5: Audio/Video conference Recording.</t>
            <t>The recording for audio/video conference is basic. All the channels in conference would be recorded as one mixed streams or separated streams by participants. It has been supported by current SIPREC mechanism.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Chat Conference Recording">
		 	<t>Use Case 6: Chat Conference Recording.</t>
			<t>There is another type conference known as multi-user chat conference or chat-rooms. The chat conference would have participants to chat or message each other in conference with nicknames and provide private chat using the Message Session Relay Protocol (MSRP) <xref target="I-D.ietf-simple-chat"/>. There would have needs to record the chat content and details like nichnames.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Multimedia Conference Recording">
            <t>Use Case 7: Multimedia Conference Recording.</t>
            <t>This is a special use case to indicate the multimedia conference recording environment. When there is a common education class or skill training conference, the audiences who are not in the conference session would prefer replaying the conference in real-time with professor or lecturer's voice with their slides, better include the video of  if available. The recording of this education conferences need to record audio, video from hosts and data sharing of theirs.</t>
            <t>While the audiences(out-conference) need to know what the audiences(in-conference) feedback to the training, they might also want to know what those audiences(in-conference) have been discussing in IM session. Thus the recording need record the IM sessions.</t>
        </section>

        </section>

        <section title="Requirements">
        <section title="REQ-001">
            <t>REQ-001: The mechanism MUST support MSRP stream recording. This requirement could derive from use case 1,6,7. </t>
        </section>

        <section title="REQ-002">
            <t>REQ-002: The mechanism MUST support screen sharing stream recording. This requirement could derive from use case 2,7.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="REQ-003">
            <t>REQ-004: The mechanism MUST support application sharing stream recording. This requirement could derive from use case 3,7.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="REQ-004">
            <t>REQ-003: The mechanism MUST support document sharing stream recording. This requirement could derive from use case 4,7.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="REQ-005">
            <t>REQ-005: The mechanism MUST support metadata or SDP to separate the main video stream to data/content video stream. This requirement could derive from use case 3,4,5,7.</t>
        </section>
		</section>

		<section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
			<t>This document contains no IANA considerations.</t>
		</section>
		<section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
			<t>Not explicitly covered in this version.</t>
		</section>
	</middle>
	<back>

   		<references title="Normative References">
                   <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119"?>
                   <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3261"?>
                   <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6341"?>
                   <?rfc include="reference.I-D.ietf-siprec-architecture"?>
                   <?rfc include="reference.I-D.ietf-siprec-protocol"?>
                   <?rfc include="reference.I-D.ietf-siprec-metadata"?>
                   <?rfc include="reference.I-D.kyzivat-siprec-webconf-use-case"?>
                   <?rfc include="reference.I-D.ietf-simple-chat"?>
		</references>

		<references title="Informative References">
                   <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3248"?>  
                   <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4103"?>  
                   <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4353"?>
                   <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4597"?>
                   <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4975"?>
                   <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5239"?>
  				   <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6914"?>  
		</references>
	</back>
</rfc>
