<?xml version="1.0"?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd"[
<!ENTITY W3C.REC-html401-19991224 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml4/reference.W3C.REC-html401-19991224.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC1939 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1939.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC2119 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC2743 SYSTEM
         "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2743.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3501 SYSTEM
         "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3501.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6120 SYSTEM
         "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6120.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4422 SYSTEM
         "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4422.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3986 SYSTEM
         "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3986.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3987 SYSTEM
         "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3987.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC2606 SYSTEM
         "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2606.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC2616 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2616.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4959 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4959.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5246 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5246.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5280 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5280.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5587 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5587.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5801 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5801.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6125 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6125.xml">
]>

<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>

<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="no" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<?rfc linkmailto="yes" ?>

<rfc ipr="trust200902" docName="draft-ietf-kitten-sasl-openid-08" category="std">

  <front>
    <title abbrev="SASL &amp; GSS-API Mechanism for OpenID">
      A SASL &amp; GSS-API Mechanism for OpenID
    </title>
    <author fullname="Eliot Lear" initials="E." surname="Lear">
      <organization>Cisco Systems GmbH</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Richtistrasse 7</street>
          <city>Wallisellen</city>
          <code>CH-8304</code>
          <region>ZH</region>
          <country>Switzerland</country>
        </postal>
        <phone>+41 44 878 9200</phone>
        <email>lear@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author initials="H." surname="Tschofenig" fullname="Hannes Tschofenig">
      <organization>Nokia Siemens Networks</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Linnoitustie 6</street>
          <city>Espoo</city>
          <code>02600</code>
          <country>Finland</country>
        </postal>
        <phone>+358 (50) 4871445</phone>
        <email>Hannes.Tschofenig@gmx.net</email>
        <uri>http://www.tschofenig.priv.at</uri>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author initials="H." surname="Mauldin" fullname="Henry Mauldin">
      <organization>Cisco Systems, Inc.</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>170 West Tasman Drive</street>
          <city>San Jose</city>
          <region>CA</region>
          <code>95134</code>
          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>
        <phone>+1 (800) 553-6387</phone>
        <email>hmauldin@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

        <author initials="S." surname="Josefsson" fullname="Simon Josefsson">
            <organization>SJD AB</organization>
            <address>
                <postal>
                    <street>Hagagatan 24</street>
                    <city>Stockholm</city>
                    <code>113 47</code>
                    <country>SE</country>
                </postal>
                <email>simon@josefsson.org</email>
                <uri>http://josefsson.org/</uri>
            </address>
        </author>

    <date year="2012"/>

    <abstract>
      <t>OpenID has found its usage on the Internet for Web Single Sign-On. Simple Authentication
        and Security Layer (SASL) and the Generic Security Service Application Program Interface (GSS-API) are application frameworks to generalize authentication. This
        memo specifies a SASL and GSS-API mechanism for OpenID that allows the integration of existing OpenID
        Identity Providers with applications using SASL and GSS-API.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>
        <xref target="OpenID">OpenID</xref> is a web-based three-party protocol that provides a
        means for a user to offer identity assertions and other attributes to a web server (Relying
        Party) via the help of an identity provider. The purpose of this system is to provide a way
        to verify that an end user controls an identifier.</t>
      <t>
        <xref target="RFC4422">Simple Authentication and Security
        Layer (SASL)</xref>  (SASL) is used by application protocols
        such <xref target="RFC3501">IMAP</xref>, <xref target="RFC1939">POP</xref>
        and <xref target="RFC6120">XMPP</xref>,
        with the goal of modularizing authentication and security
        layers, so that newer mechanisms can be added
        as needed. This memo specifies just such a
        mechanism. </t>

      <t>The <xref target="RFC2743">Generic Security Service
          Application Program Interface (GSS-API)</xref> provides a
          framework for applications to support multiple
          authentication mechanisms through a unified interface.  This
        document defines a pure SASL mechanism for OpenID, but it
        conforms to the new bridge between SASL and the GSS-API
        called <xref target="RFC5801">GS2</xref>.  This
        means that this document defines both a SASL mechanism and
        a GSS-API mechanism.  Implementors of the SASL component MAY
        implement the GSS-API interface as well.
      </t>

      <t>This mechanism specifies
        interworking between SASL and OpenID in order to assert
        identity and other attributes to relying parties. As such,
        while SASL servers (as relying parties) will advertise SASL
        mechanisms, clients will select the OpenID mechanism. </t>
      <t>The OpenID mechanism described in this memo aims to re-use
        the OpenID mechanism to the maximum extent and therefore does
        not establish a separate authentication, integrity and
        confidentiality mechanism. It is anticipated that existing
        security layers, such as <xref target="RFC5246">Transport
        Layer Security (TLS)</xref>, continue to be used.
        Minimal changes are required to non-web applications, as most
        of the transaction occurs through a normal web browser.
        Hence, this specification is only appropriate for use when
        such a browser is available.

</t>

      <t><xref target="overview"/> describes the interworking between
        OpenID and SASL.  This document
        requires enhancements to the Relying Party and to the Client (as the two SASL communication
        end points) but no changes to the OpenID Provider (OP) are necessary. To accomplish this goal
        indirect messaging required by the OpenID specification is tunneled through the SASL/GSS-API mechanism.</t>
      <t>
        <figure anchor="overview" title="Interworking Architecture">
          <artwork><![CDATA[
                                 +-----------+
                                 |  Relying  |
                                >|  Party /  |
                               / |   SASL    |
                             //  |  Server   |
                           //    +-----------+
                         //            ^
                OpenID //           +--|--+
                     //             | O|  | G
                    /             S | p|  | S
                  //              A | e|  | S
                //                S | n|  | A
              //                  L | I|  | P
            //                      | D|  | I
          </                        +--|--+
   +------------+                      v
   |            |                 +----------+
   |  OpenID    |   OpenID        |          |
   |  Provider  |<--------------->|  Client  |
   |            |                 |          |
   +------------+                 +----------+
]]></artwork>
        </figure>
      </t>

    <section anchor="terminology" title="Terminology">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT",
        "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in
        RFC 2119 <xref target="RFC2119"/>.</t>
      <t>The reader is assumed to be familiar with the terms used in the OpenID 2.0
      specification.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="applicability" title="Applicability">

      <t>Because this mechanism transports information that should not
        be controlled by an attacker, the OpenID mechanism MUST only
        be used over channels protected
        by TLS, and the client MUST
        successfully validate the server certificate. <xref target="RFC5280" /><xref target="RFC6125" /></t>

    </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Applicability for application protocols other than
    HTTP">
      <t>OpenID was originally envisioned for <xref target="RFC2616">HTTP</xref> and <xref target="W3C.REC-html401-19991224">HTML</xref> based communications, and with the associated
        semantic, the idea being that the user would be redirected by the Relying Party to an identity provider who
        authenticates the user, and then sends identity information and other attributes (either directly or indirectly) to the
        Relying Party.  The identity provider in
   the OpenID specifications is referred to as an OpenID Provider
        (OP). The actual protocol flow can be found in Section 3 of
        the <xref target="OpenID">OpenID 2.0 specification</xref>.
        The reader is strongly encouraged to be familiar with the
        specification before continuing.
</t>
      <t>When considering that flow in the context of SASL, we note
        that while the RP and the client both need to change their code
        to implement this SASL mechanism, it is a design constraint
        that the OP behavior remain untouched, in order for
        implementations to interoperate with existing IdPs.  Hence, an
        analog flow that
        interfaces the three parties needs to be created.  In the
        analog, we note that unlike a web server, the SASL server
        already has some sort of session
        (probably a TCP connection) established with the client.
        However, it may be necessary for a SASL client to invoke
        to another application.  This will be discussed below.  By
        doing so, we externalize much of the authentiction from SASL.
</t><t>
      The steps are listed below:</t>
      <t>
        <list style="numbers">
          <t>The SASL server advertises support for
          the SASL OpenID mechanism to the client. </t>
          <t>The client initiates a SASL authentication and transmits
          the User-Supplied Identifier as its first response.  The
          SASL mechanism is client-first, and as explained in <xref
          target="RFC4422"/> the server will send an empty challenge
          if needed.</t>
          <t>After normalizing the User-Supplied Identifier as
            discussed in <xref target="OpenID" />, the Relying Party performs discovery on
            it and establishes the OP Endpoint URL that the end user uses for authentication.</t>
          <t>The Relying Party and the OP optionally establish an association -- a shared secret
            established using Diffie-Hellman Key Exchange. The OP uses
            an association to validate
            those messages through the use of an HMAC; this removes the
            need for subsequent direct requests to verify the
            signature after each authentication request/response. </t>
          <t>The Relying Party transmits an authentication request to the OP to obtain an assertion
            in the form of an indirect request. These messages are passed through the client rather
            than directly between the RP and the OP. OpenID defines two methods for indirect
            communication, namely HTTP redirects and HTML form submission. Both mechanisms are not
            directly applicable for usage with SASL. To ensure that a standard OpenID 2.0 capable OP
            can be used a new method is defined in this document that requires the OpenID message
            content to be encoded using
            a <xref target="RFC3986">Universal Resource Idenitifier
            (URI).</xref>  Note that any Internationalized Resource
            Identifiers (IRIs) must be normalized to URIs by the SASL
            client, as specified in <xref target="RFC3987" />, prior
            to transmitting them to the SASL server.
            </t>
          <t>The SASL client now sends an response consisting of "=", to indicate that
          authentication continues via the normal OpenID flow.
</t><t>
             At this point the client application MUST construct a URL containing
            the content received in the previous message from the
             RP. This URL is transmitted to the OP either by
             the SASL client application or an appropriate handler, such
             as a browser.</t>
          <t>Next the client optionally authenticates to the OP and
            then approves or disapproves authentication to the Relying
            Party.  For reasons of its own the OP has the option of
            not authenticating a request.
The manner in which the end user is authenticated
            to their respective OP and any
            policies surrounding such authentication is out of scope of OpenID and and hence also
            out of scope for this specification. This step happens
            out of band from SASL.</t>
          <t>The OP will convey information about the success or failure of the
            authentication phase back to the RP, again using an indirect
            response via the client browser or handler.
            The client transmits over HTTP/TLS the redirect of the OP
          result to the RP.  This step happens out of band from
            SASL.</t>
          <t>The RP MAY send an OpenID check_authentication request
          directly to the OP, if no association has been established,
          and the OP should respond.  Again this step
          happens out of band from SASL.</t>
          <t>The SASL server sends an appropriate SASL response to the
          client, with optional Open Simple Registry (SREG) attributes. </t>
        </list>
      </t>
<t>
        <figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[
      SASL Serv.       RP/Client       OP
         |>-----(1)----->|              | Advertisement
         |               |              |
         |<-----(2)-----<|              | Initiation
         |               |              |
         |> - - (3) - - - - - - - - - ->| Discovery
         |                              |
         |>- - -(4)- - - - - - - - - - >| Association
         |<- - -(4)- - - - - - - - - - <|
         |               |              |
         |>-----(5)----->|              | Indirect Auth Request
         |               |              |
         |<-----(6)-----<|              | Client "=" Response
         |               |               |
         |               |>- - (7)- - ->| Client GET to the OP (ext)
         |               |              |
         |               |<- - (8)- - ->| Client / OP Auth. (ext.)
         |               |              |
         |<- - -(9)- - - + - - - - - - <| HTTPs Indirect id_res
         |               |              |
         |<- - -(10)- - - - - - - - - ->| Optional check_authenticate
         |               |              |
         |>-----(11)---->|              | SASL completion with status

     ----- = SASL
     - - - = HTTPS
]]>
</artwork></figure>
</t>
<t>Note the directionality in SASL is such that the client MUST send the "="
  response.  Specifically, the SASL client processes the redirect and
  then awaits a final SASL decision, while the rest of the OpenID
  authentication process continues.
</t>
<section title="Binding SASL to OpenID in the Relying Party" >
<t>
  OpenID is meant to be used in serial within the web, where browser
  cookies are easily accessible.  As such,
  there are no transaction-ids within the protocol.
  To ensure that a specific request is bound, and in particular to
  ease interprocess communication,  the relying
  party MUST encode a nonce or transaction-id in the URIs it
  transmits through the client for success or failure, either as a
  base URI or fragment component to the "return_to" URI.  This value
  is to be used to uniquely identify each authentication transaction.
  The nonce value MUST be at least 2^32 large and large enough to
  handle well in excess of the number of concurrent transactions a
  SASL server shall see.
</t>
</section>
<section title="Discussion">
<t>
As mentioned above OpenID is primarily designed to interact with
web-based applications.  Portions of the authentication stream are
only defined in the crudest sense.  That is, when one is prompted to
approve or disapprove an authentication, anything that one might find
on a browser is allowed, including JavaScript, fancy style-sheets,
etc.  Because of this lack of structure, implementations will need to
invoke a fairly rich browser in order to ensure that the
authentication can be completed.
</t>
<t>Once there is an outcome, the SASL server needs to know about it.
  The astute will hopefully by now have noticed an "=" client SASL
  response.  This is not to say that nothing is happening, but rather
  that authentication flow has shifted from SASL and the client
  application to OpenID within the browser, and
  will return to the client application when the server has an outcome
  to hand to the client.
  The alternative to this flow would be some sort of signal from the
  HTML browser to the SASL client of the results that would in turn be
  passed to the SASL server.  The inter-process communication issue
  this raises is substantial.  Better, we conclude, to externalize the
  authentication to the browser, and have an "=" client response.
</t>
</section>
</section>

<section title="OpenID SASL Mechanism Specification">
      <t>This section specifies the details of the OpenID SASL
      mechanism.  Recall section 5 of <xref target="RFC4422"/> for
      what needs to be described here.</t>

      <t>The name of this mechanism &quot;OPENID20&quot;.  The
      mechanism is capable of transferring an authorization identity
      (via "gs2-header").  The mechanism does not offer a security
      layer.</t>

      <t>The mechanism is client-first.  The first mechanism message
      from the client to the server is the "initial-response"
      described below.  As described in <xref target="RFC4422"/>, if
      the application protocol does not support sending a
      client-response together with the authentication request, the
      server will send an empty server-challenge to let the client
      begin.</t>

      <t>The second mechanism message is from the server to the
      client, the "authentication_request" described below.</t>

      <t>The third mechanism message is from client to the server, and
      is the fixed message consisting of "=".</t>

      <t>The fourth mechanism message is from the server to the
      client, described below as "outcome_data" (with SREG
      attributes), sent as additional data when indicating a
      successful outcome.</t>

      <section title="Initiation" anchor="initiation">
        <t>A client initiates an OpenID authentication with SASL by
        sending the GS2 header followed by the URI, as
        specified in the OpenID specification.</t>
     <figure>
      <artwork><![CDATA[
    initial-response = gs2-header Auth-Identifier
    Auth-Identifier = Identifier ; authentication identifier
    Identifier = URI       ;  Identifier is specified in
                           ;  Sec. 7.2 of the OpenID 2.0 spec.


]]></artwork>
        </figure>

     <t>The syntax and semantics of the "gs2-header" are specified in
     <xref target="RFC5801"/>, and we use it here with the following
     limitations:  The "gs2-nonstd-flag" MUST NOT be
     present.  The "gs2-cb-flag" MUST be "n" because channel binding
     is not supported by this mechanism.</t>
<t>
     URI is specified in <xref target="RFC3986" />. <xref target="XRI2.0">XRIs MUST NOT be used.</xref>
        </t>
      </section>
      <section title="Authentication Request" anchor="request">

        <t>The SASL Server sends the URL resulting from the OpenID
        authentication request, containing an &quot;openid.mode&quot;
        of either &quot;checkid_immediate&quot; or
        &quot;checkid_setup&quot;, as specified in Section 9.1 of the
        OpenID 2.0 specification.</t>

     <figure>
      <artwork><![CDATA[
       authentication-request = URI
]]></artwork>
        </figure>

        <t>As part of this request, the SASL server MUST append a
        unique transaction id to the &quot;return_to&quot; portion of
        the request.  The form of this transaction is left to the RP
        to decide, but SHOULD be large enough to be resistant to being
        guessed or attacked.
        </t>
        <t>The client now sends that request via an HTTP GET to the
        OP, as if redirected to do so from an HTTP server.</t>

        <t>The client MUST handle both user authentication to the OP
        and confirmation or rejection of the authentiation by the
        RP via this SASL mechanism.</t>

        <t>After all authentication has been completed by the OP, and
        after the response has been sent to the client, the client
        will relay the response to the Relying Party via HTTP/TLS, as
        specified previously in the transaction ("return_to").  </t>
      </section>

      <section title="Server Response" anchor="response2">

        <t>The Relying Party now validates the response it received
        from the client via HTTP/TLS, as specified in the OpenID
        specification, using the "return_to" URI given previsiously in
        the transaction.</t>

        <t>The response by the Relying Party constitutes a SASL
        mechanism outcome, and SHALL be used to set state in the
        server accordingly, and it SHALL be used by the server to
        report that state to the SASL client as described in [RFC4422]
        Section 3.6.  In the additional data, the server MAY include
        OpenID Simple Registry (SREG) attributes that are listed in
        Section 4 of <xref target="SREG1.0" />.SREG
        attributes are encoded as
        follows:</t>

        <t>
          <list style="numbers">
            <t>Strip &quot;openid.sreg.&quot; from each attribute name.</t>
            <t>Treat the concatentation of results as URI parameters that are
            separated by an ampersand (&amp;) and encode as one would a URI,
            absent the scheme, authority, and the question mark.
            </t>
          </list>
        </t>
        <t>
        </t>
        <t>
          For example: email=lear@example.com&amp;fullname=Eliot%20Lear
        </t>
        <t>More formally:
        <figure><artwork><![CDATA[

      outcome-data = [ sreg-avp *( "," sreg-avp ) ]
      sreg-avp     = sreg-attr "=" sreg-val
      sreg-attr    = sreg-word
      sreg-val     = sreg-word
      sreg-word    = 1*( unreserved / pct-encoded )
                     ; pct-encoded from Section 2.1 of RFC 3986
                     ; unreserved from Section 2.3 of RFC 3986

                     ]]></artwork></figure>
        </t>

        <t>A client who does not support SREG MUST ignore SREG attributes
        sent by the server.  Similarly, a client MUST ignore unknown
        attributes.
        </t>
        <t>In the case of failures, the response MUST follow this syntax:
        <figure><artwork><![CDATA[
     outcome_data = "openid.error" "=" sreg_val *( "," sregp_avp )
     ]]></artwork></figure>
</t>
      </section>
      <section title="Error Handling">
        <t>
          <xref target="RFC4422" /> Section 3.6 explicitly prohibits
          additional information in an unsuccessful authentication
          outcome.  Therefore, the openid.error and openid.error_code
          are to be sent as an additional challenge in the event of an
          unsuccessful outcome.  In this case, as the protocol is lock
          step,  the client will follow with an additional exchange
          containing "=", after which the server will respond with an
          application-level outcome.
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="OpenID GSS-API Mechanism Specification">

      <t>This section and its sub-sections and appropriate
        references of it not referenced elsewhere in this document are
        not required for SASL implementors, but this section MUST be
        observed to implement the GSS-API mechanism discussed below.</t>


      <t>The OpenID SASL mechanism is actually also a GSS-API
      mechanism.  The OpenID user takes the role of the GSS-API
      Initiator and the OpenID Relying Party takes the role of the
      GSS-API Acceptor.  The OpenId Provider does not have a role in
      GSS-API, and is considered an internal matter for the OpenID
      mechanism.  The messages are the same, but a) the GS2 header on
      the client's first message and channel binding data is excluded
      when OpenID is used as a GSS-API mechanism, and b) the RFC2743
      section 3.1 initial context token header is prefixed to the
      client's first authentication message (context token).</t>

      <t>The GSS-API mechanism OID for OpenID is OID-TBD (IANA to
      assign: see IANA considerations).
        </t>

      <t>OpenID security contexts MUST have the mutual_state flag
        (GSS_C_MUTUAL_FLAG) set to TRUE.  OpenID does not support
        credential delegation, therefore OpenID security contexts
        MUST have the deleg_state flag (GSS_C_DELEG_FLAG) set to
        FALSE.
      </t>

      <t>The mutual authentication property of this mechanism relies
      on successfully comparing the TLS server identity with the
      negotiated target name.  Since the TLS channel is managed by the
      application outside of the GSS-API mechanism, the mechanism
      itself is unable to confirm the name while the application is
      able to perform this comparison for the mechanism.  For this
      reason, applications MUST match the TLS server identity with the
      target name, as discussed in <xref target="RFC6125" />.</t>

      <t>The OpenID mechanism does not support per-message tokens or
      GSS_Pseudo_random.</t>

      <t>The <xref target="RFC5587" /> mechanism attributes for this
      mechanism are GSS_C_MA_MECH_CONCRETE, GSS_C_MA_ITOK_FRAMED, and
      GSS_C_MA_AUTH_INIT.</t>

      <section title="GSS-API Principal Name Types for OpenID">

        <t>OpenID supports standard generic name syntaxes for
          acceptors such as GSS_C_NT_HOSTBASED_SERVICE (see
          <xref target="RFC2743" />, Section 4.1).</t>

        <t>OpenID supports only a single name type for initiators:
          GSS_C_NT_USER_NAME.  GSS_C_NT_USER_NAME is the default name
          type for OpenID.</t>

        <t>OpenID name normalization is covered by the OpenID
          specification, see <xref target="OpenID" /> section 7.2.</t>

        <t>The query, display, and exported name syntaxes for OpenID
          principal names are all the same.  There are no
          OpenID-specific name syntaxes -- applications should use
          generic GSS-API name types such as GSS_C_NT_USER_NAME and
          GSS_C_NT_HOSTBASED_SERVICE (see <xref target="RFC2743" />,
          Section 4).  The exported name token does, of course,
          conform to <xref target="RFC2743" />, Section 3.2, but the
          "NAME" part of the token should be treated as a potential
          input string to the OpenID name normalization rules.
          For example, the OpenID identifier "https://openid.example/" will
          have a GSS_C_NT_USER_NAME value of
          "https://openid.example/".
</t>
        <t>GSS-API name attributes may be defined in the future to
          hold the normalized OpenID Identifier.</t>

      </section>

    </section>

    <section title="Example">
      <t>Suppose one has an OpenID of https://openid.example, and
      wishes to authenticate his IMAP connection to mail.example
      (where .example is the top level domain specified in
      <xref target="RFC2606"/>).  The user would input his Openid into
      his mail user agent, when he configures the account.  In this
      case, no association is attempted between the OpenID RP
      and the OP.  The client will make use of the return_to attribute
      to capture results of the authentication to be redirected to the
      server.   Note the use of <xref target="RFC4959" /> for initial
      response. The authentication on the wire would then look
      something like the following:
      </t>
<figure><artwork>
<![CDATA[
    (S = IMAP server; C = IMAP client)

    C: < connects to IMAP port>
    S: * OK
    C: C1 CAPABILITY
    S: * CAPABILITY IMAP4rev1 SASL-IR SORT [...] AUTH=OPENID20
    S: C1 OK Capability Completed
    C: C2 AUTHENTICATE OPENID biwsaHR0cHM6Ly9vcGVuaWQuZXhhbXBsZS8=
    [  This is the base64 encoding of "n,,https://openid.example/".
       Server performs discovery on http://openid.example/ ]
    S: + aHR0cHM6Ly9vcGVuaWQuZXhhbXBsZS9vcGVuaWQvP29wZW5pZC5ucz1
         odHRwOi8vc3BlY3Mub3BlbmlkLm5ldC9hdXRoLzIuMCZvcGVuaWQucm
         V0dXJuX3RvPWh0dHBzOi8vbWFpbC5leGFtcGxlL2NvbnN1bWVyLzFlZ
         jg4OGMmb3BlbmlkLmNsYWltZWRfaWQ9aHR0cHM6Ly9vcGVuaWQuZXhh
         bXBsZS8mb3BlbmlkLmlkZW50aXR5PWh0dHBzOi8vb3BlbmlkLmV4YW1
         wbGUvJm9wZW5pZC5yZWFsbT1pbWFwOi8vbWFpbC5leGFtcGxlJm9wZW
         5pZC5tb2RlPWNoZWNraWRfc2V0dXA=

    [ This is the base64 encoding of "https://openid.example/openid/
          ?openid.ns=http://specs.openid.net/auth/2.0
          &openid.return_to=https://mail.example/consumer/1ef888c
          &openid.claimed_id=https://openid.example/
          &openid.identity=https://openid.example/
          &openid.realm=imap://mail.example
          &openid.mode=checkid_setup"
       with line breaks and spaces added here for readibility.
    ]
    C: PQ==
    [ The client now sends the URL it received to a browser for
      processing. The user logs into https://openid.example, and
      agrees to authenticate imap://mail.example.  A redirect is
      passed back to the client browser who then connects to
      https://imap.example/consumer via SSL with the results.
      From an IMAP perspective, however, the client sends the "="
      response, and awaits mail.example.
      Server mail.example would now contact openid.example with an
      openid.check_authenticate message.  After that...
    ]
    S: + ZW1haWw9bGVhckBtYWlsLmV4YW1wbGUsZnVsbG5hbWU9RWxp
         b3QlMjBMZWFy
      [ Here the IMAP server has returned an SREG attribute of
        email=lear@mail.example,fullname=Eliot%20Lear.
        Line break in response added in this example for clarity. ]
    C: 
      [ In IMAP client must send a blank response after receiving the
        SREG data. ]
    S: C2 OK
]]></artwork></figure>
<t>
In this example, the SASL server / RP has made use of a transaction id
1ef888c.
</t>
    </section>
    <section title="Security Considerations">
<t>
This section will address only security considerations associated with
the use of OpenID with SASL and GSS-API.  For considerations relating
to OpenID in general, the reader is referred to the OpenID
specification and to other literature
<eref target="http://sites.google.com/site/openidreview/resources" />.
Similarly, for general <xref target="RFC4422">SASL</xref>
and <xref target="RFC5801">GSS-API</xref> Security Considerations, the reader is referred to those
specifications.
</t>
<section title="Binding OpenIDs to Authorization Identities">
<t>As specified in <xref target="RFC4422" />, the server is
  responsible for binding credentials to a specific authorization
  identity.  It is therefore necessary that a
  registration process takes place in advance that binds specific
  OpenIDs to specific authorization identities, or that only specific
  trusted OpenID Providers be allowed, where a mapping is predefined.
  For example, it could be pre-arranged between an IdP and RP that
  "https://example.com/user" maps to "user" for purposes of authorization.
</t>
</section>
<section title="RP redirected by malicious URL to take an improper action">
<t>
In the initial SASL client response a user or host can transmit a
malicious response to the RP for purposes of
taking advantage of weaknesses in the RP's OpenID implementation.
It is possible to add port numbers to the URL so that the outcome is
the RP does a port scan of the site.
The URL could contain an unauthorized host or even the
local host.  The URL could contain a protocol other than http or
https, such as file or ftp.
</t>
<t> One mitigation would be for RPs to have a list of authorized
  URI bases. OPs SHOULD only redirect to RPs with the same domain
  component of the base URI.  RPs MUST NOT automatically retry on failed
  attempts.  A log of those sites that fail SHOULD be kept, and
  limitations on queries from clients SHOULD be imposed, just as with
  any other authentication attempt.  Applications SHOULD NOT invoke
  browsers to communicate with OPs that they are not themselves
  configured with.
</t>
</section>
<!--
<section title="Man-in-the-middle attack">
<t>
The optional establishment of an association between the OP and the RP
uses the Diffie-Hellman key exchange.  The Diffie-Hellman key exchange
is vulnerable to interception attacks.  Using Diffie-Hellman without
proper authentication introduces the possibility of OP Massqurade.
</t>
<t>The appropriate mitigation is to make use of OPs that support
  SSL.
</t>
</section>
-->
<!--
<section title="Phishing of the OP site">
<t>
There are two common phishing attacks.
<list style="symbols">
<t>Phished OP Page: The normal flow has the RP redirecting the user to
an OP for authentication.  A malicious RP could redirect the user to
identically looking, but phished OP page with the intent to steal the
user's credentials.  The appropriate mitigation is for some form of
  secondary mutual authentication to take place on the OP, such as
  branding, client-side authentication, or a record of legitimate site
  being associated with a given identity.  The latter would probably
  require substantial client extensions.
</t>
<t>Realm Spoofing: A malicious RP can create an authentication request
with an openid.realm set to a trusted domain and the return_to
pointing back to itself.  If the OP does not do a Realm return_to
validation, then the OP will assert to the user that they are signing
into a trusted domain.  However, the user is in reality being
redirected back to the malicious RP. XXX mitigation?
</t>
</list>
</t>
</section>
<section title="Session Swapping (Cross-Site Request Forgery)">
<t>
There is no defined mechanism in the OpenID protocol to bind the
OpenID session to the user's browser.  An attacker may forge a
cross-site request in the log-in form, which has the user logging into
a proper RP as the attacker.  The user would not recognize they are
logged into the site as the attacker, and so may reveal information at
the RP.  Cross-site request forgery is a widely exploited
vulnerability at web sites.  This is only concern in the context SASL
in as much as the client is not configured with the Relying Party
(e.g., SASL server) in a safe manner.
</t>
</section>
<section title="Use of DNS poisoning attack to impersonate user at RP">
<t>
If not using a secure https identifier, an attacker can use a DNS
poisoning attack to impersonate the user on some RP by tricking the RP
into thinking the attacker is hosting the user's IdP.  XXX is this
solved by SSL or DNSSEC?
</t>
</section>
-->
<section title="User Privacy">
<t>
The OP is aware of each RP that a user logs into.  There
is nothing in the protocol to hide this information from the OP.  It
is not a requirement to track the visits, but there is nothing that
prohibits the collection of information.  SASL servers should be aware
that OpenID Providers will be able to track - to some extent - user access to
their services and any additional information that OP provides.
</t>
</section>
<!-- <section title="Collusion between RPs">
<t>
It is possible for RPs to link data that they have collected on principals.
By using the same identifier to log into every RP, collusion between
RPs is possible.  In OpenID 2.0, directed identity was introduced.
Directed identity allows the OP to transform the identifier the user
typed in to another identifier.  This way the RP would never see the
actual user identifier, but a randomly generated identifier.  This is
an option the user has to understand and decide to use if the OP is
supporting it.
</t>
</section>
-->
</section>

    <section title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>The IANA is requested to update the SASL Mechanism Registry
      using the following template, as described in <xref
      target="RFC4422"/>.</t>
      <t/>
      <t>SASL mechanism name: OPENID20</t>
      <t>Security Considerations: See this document</t>
      <t>Published specification: See this document</t>
      <t>Person &amp; email address to contact for further information:
      Authors of this document</t>
      <t>Intended usage: COMMON</t>
      <t>Owner/Change controller: IETF</t>
      <t>Note: None</t>

      <t>The IANA is further requested to assign an OID for this GSS
      mechanism in the SMI numbers registry, with the prefix of
      iso.org.dod.internet.security.mechanisms (1.3.6.1.5.5) and to
      reference this specification in the registry.
      </t>

    </section>
    <section title="Acknowledgments">
      <t>The authors would like to thank Alexey Melnikov, Joe
      Hildebrand, Mark Crispin, Chris Newman, Leif Johansson, Sam
      Hartman, Nico Williams, Klaas Wierenga, Stephen Farrell,
      and Stephen Kent for their review and contributions.
      </t>
    </section>
  </middle>
  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <reference anchor="OpenID">
        <front>
          <title>OpenID Authentication 2.0 - Final</title>
          <author>
            <organization>OpenID Foundation</organization>
            <address>
              <uri>http://www.openid.net</uri>
            </address>
          </author>
          <date month="December" day="5" year="2007" />
        </front>
        <format type="HTML"
        target="http://specs.openid.net/auth/2.0" />
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="SREG1.0">
        <front>
          <title>OpenID Simple Registration Extension version
          1.0</title>
          <author>
            <organization>OpenID Foundation</organization>
            <address>
              <uri>http://www.openid.net</uri>
              </address>
            </author>
          <date year="2006" month="June" day="30" />
        </front>
        <format type="HTML"
        target="http://openid.net/sreg/1.0" />
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="XRI2.0">
        <front>
          <title>Extensible Resource Identifier (XRI) Syntax
          V2.0</title>
          <author fullname="Drummond Reed" initials="D."
          surname="Reed">
            <organization>Cordance</organization>
            <address>
              <email>drummond.reed@cordance.net</email>
            </address>
          </author>
          <author fullname="Dave McAlpin" initials="D." surname="McAlpin">
            <organization>Epok</organization>
            <address>
              <email>dave.mcalpin@epokinc.com</email>
            </address>
          </author>
          <date year="2005" month="September" day="14" />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="OASIS Standard" value="xri-syntax-V2.0-cs"
        />
        <format type="HTML"
        target="http://www.oasis-open.org/committees/download.php/15376/xri-syntax-V2.0-cs.html"
        />
      </reference>
      &RFC2119;
      &RFC2743;
      &RFC4422;
      &RFC2606;
      &RFC2616;
      &RFC3986;
      &RFC3987;
      &RFC5246;
      &RFC5280;
      &RFC5587;
      &RFC5801;
      &RFC6125;
    </references>
<references title="Informative References">
  &W3C.REC-html401-19991224;
  &RFC1939;
  &RFC3501;
  &RFC6120;
  &RFC4959;
</references>
    <section title="Changes">
      <t>This section to be removed prior to publication.</t>
      <t>
        <list style="symbols">
          <t>04 - 07 04 - 07 address LC and review comments,
          including those of Stephen Farrell, Steve Kent, and Brian
          Carpenter.
          </t>
          <t>03 Clarifies messages and ordering, and replace the empty
          message with a "=" message.</t>
          <t>02 Address all WGLC comments.</t>
          <t>01 Specific text around possible improvements for OOB
          browser control in security considerations.  Also talk about
          transaction id.</t>
          <t>00 WG -00 draft.  Slight wording modifications abou
          design constraints per Alexey.</t>
          <t>02 Correct single (significant) error on mechanism name.</t>
          <t>01 Add nonce discussion, add authorized identity, explain
             a definition. Add gs2 support.</t>
          <t>00 Initial Revision. </t>
        </list>
      </t>
    </section>
  </back>
</rfc>
