<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!-- This is built from a template for a generic Internet Draft. Suggestions for
     improvement welcome - write to Brian Carpenter, brian.e.carpenter @ gmail.com -->

<!-- This can be converted using the Web service at http://xml.resource.org/experimental.html
     (which supports the latest, sometimes undocumented and under-tested, features.) -->

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [

<!-- You need one entry like the following for each RFC referenced -->

<!ENTITY RFC2119 PUBLIC ''
  'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml'>
<!ENTITY RFC2629 PUBLIC ''
  'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2629.xml'>
<!ENTITY RFC3986 PUBLIC ''
  'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3986.xml'>
<!ENTITY RFC4007 PUBLIC ''
  'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4007.xml'>
<!ENTITY RFC5952 PUBLIC ''
  'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5952.xml'>
<!ENTITY RFC5234 PUBLIC ''
  'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5234.xml'>
<!ENTITY RFC3493 PUBLIC ''
  'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3493.xml'>
<!ENTITY RFC4001 PUBLIC ''
  'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4001.xml'>




<!-- You need one entry like the following for each I-D referenced -->

<!ENTITY DRAFT-3697bis SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-6man-flow-3697bis.xml">
]>


<?rfc toc="yes"?>            <!-- You want a table of contents -->
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>        <!-- Use symbolic labels for references -->
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>       <!-- This sorts the references -->
<?rfc iprnotified="no" ?>    <!-- Change to "yes" if someone has disclosed IPR for the draft -->
<?rfc compact="yes"?>


<!-- This defines the specific filename and version number of your draft (and inserts the appropriate IETF boilerplate -->
<rfc ipr="trust200902" docName="draft-carpenter-6man-uri-zoneid-01" category="std" updates="3986, 4007">


<front>
<title abbrev="IPv6 Zone ID in URI">Representing IPv6 Zone Identifiers in Uniform Resource Identifiers</title>


<author initials="B. E." surname="Carpenter" fullname="Brian Carpenter">
    <organization abbrev="Univ. of Auckland"></organization>
    <address>
      <postal>
        <street>Department of Computer Science</street>
        <street>University of Auckland</street>
        <street>PB 92019</street>
        <city>Auckland</city>
        <region></region>
        <code>1142</code>
        <country>New Zealand</country>
      </postal>
      
      <email>brian.e.carpenter@gmail.com</email>
    </address>
</author>

<author initials="R.M." surname="Hinden"
            fullname="Robert M. Hinden">
    <organization abbrev="Check Point">
        Check Point Software Technologies, Inc.
    </organization>
  <address>
    <postal>
        <street>800 Bridge Parkway</street>
        <city>Redwood City</city> <region>CA</region>
        <code>94065</code>
        <country>US</country>
    </postal>

    <email>bob.hinden@gmail.com</email>
  </address>
</author>

<date day="8" month="February" year="2012" />

<area>Internet</area>
<workgroup>6MAN</workgroup>

 


<abstract>

<t>This document describes how the Zone Identifier of an IPv6 scoped address can be represented in a Uniform Resource Identifier 
that includes a literal IPv6 address. It updates RFC 3986 and RFC 4007.
</t>
    
</abstract>
</front>

<middle>
<section anchor="intro" title="Introduction">

<t><xref target="RFC3986"/> defined how a literal IPv6 address can be represented in the "host" 
part of a Uniform Resource Identifier (URI). Subsequently, <xref target="RFC4007"/> extended
the text representation of limited-scope IPv6 addresses such that a zone identifier may be concatenated
to an address, for purposes described in that RFC. Zone identifiers are especially
useful in contexts where literal addresses are typically used, for example during fault diagnosis,
when it may be essential to specify which interface is used for sending to a link local address. 
It should be noted that zone identifiers have purely local meaning within the host where
they are defined, and they are completely meaningless for any other host. </t>

<t>RFC 4007 does not specify how zone identifiers are to be represented
in URIs. Practical experience has shown that this feature is useful, in particular when using a
web browser for debugging with link local addresses, but as it is undefined,
it is not implemented consistently in URI parsers or in browsers. </t>

<t>This document updates <xref target="RFC3986"/> by adding syntax to allow a zone identifier
to be included in a literal IPv6 address. It also clarifies some statements in <xref target="RFC4007"/>. </t>

<t>It should be noted that in other contexts than a user interface, a zone identifier is mapped into
a numeric zone index or interface number. The MIB textual convention <xref target="RFC4001"/> and the
socket interface <xref target="RFC3493"/> define this as a 32 bit unsigned integer. The mapping
between the human-readable zone identifier string and the numeric value is a host-specific
function that varies between operating systems. The present document is concerned only
with the human-readable string. </t>



<t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
   "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
   document are to be interpreted as described in <xref target="RFC2119"/>.</t>


</section> <!-- intro -->

<section anchor="spec" title="Specification">
<t>According to RFC 4007, a zone identifier is attached to the textual representation of an IPv6
address by concatenating "%" followed by &lt;zone_id>, where &lt;zone_id> is a string identifying the zone of the address.
However, RFC 4007 gives no precise definition of the character set allowed in &lt;zone_id>.
There are no rules or de facto standards for this. For example, the first Ethernet interface in a host
might be called %0, %1, %en1, %eth0, or whatever the implementer happened to choose.</t>

<t>In a URI, a literal IPv6 address is always embedded between "[" and "]". 
This document specifies that &lt;zone_id> may contain any ASCII character classified in RFC 3986
as "unreserved", which conveniently excludes "]" in order to simplify parsing. </t>

<t>There is an additional complication in that "%" is always treated as an escape
character in a URI, and according to RFC 3986 it MUST therefore itself be escaped in a URI, in the
form "%25". Thus, the scoped address fe80::a%en1 would appear in a produced URI as http://[fe80::a%25en1].
</t>

<t>If an operating system uses any other characters in zone or interface identifiers that are not in the
"unreserved" character set, they too MUST be escaped with a "%" sign according to RFC 3986. </t>

<t>
In RFC 3986, the IPv6 literal format is formally defined in ABNF <xref target="RFC5234"/> by the following rule:
<figure><artwork>
   IP-literal = "[" ( IPv6address / IPvFuture  ) "]"
</artwork></figure>
</t>

<t>To provide support for a zone identifier, 
the existing syntax of IPv6address is retained, and a zone identifier may be
added optionally to any literal address. This allows flexibility for unknown future
uses. The rule quoted above from RFC 3986 is replaced by three rules:

<figure><artwork>
   IP-literal = "[" ( IPv6addrz / IPvFuture  ) "]"

   ZoneID = 1*unreserved
   
   IPv6addrz = IPv6address [ "%" ZoneID ]
</artwork></figure></t>

<t>The rules in <xref target="RFC5952"/> SHOULD be applied in producing URIs.
The user MUST replace "%" by "%25" when manually constructing such a URI, and
similarly for any other characters that are not in the "unreserved" character set
of RFC 3986. </t>

<t>The 6man WG discussed and rejected an alternative in which
the existing syntax of IPv6address would be extended by an option
to add the ZoneID only for the case of link-local addresses. It
was felt that the present solution offers more flexibility for
future uses and is more straightforward to implement.
</t>

<t>RFC 4007 offers guidance on how the ZoneID affects interface/address selection
inside the IPv6 stack. Note that the behaviour of an IPv6 stack if passed a non-zero
zone index for an address other than link-local is undefined. </t>


</section> <!-- spec  -->


<section anchor="security" title="Security Considerations">

<t>The security considerations of  <xref target="RFC3986"/> and <xref target="RFC4007"/> apply. 
In particular, this URI format creates a specific pathway by which a deceitful zone
index might be communicated, as mentioned in the final security consideration of RFC 4007.
It is emphasised that the format is intended only for debugging purposes, but of course
this intention does not prevent misuse. </t>

<t>To limit this risk, implementations SHOULD NOT allow use of this format except for
well-defined usages such as sending to link local addresses under prefix fe80::/10. </t>

<t>An HTTP server or proxy MUST ignore any ZoneID attached to an incoming URI, as it only has
local significance at the sending host. </t>

</section> <!-- security -->


<section anchor="iana" title="IANA Considerations">
   <t>This document requests no action by IANA. </t>
</section> <!-- iana -->




<section anchor="ack" title="Acknowledgements">

<t>
The lack of this format was pointed out by Kerry Lynn. Valuable comments and contributions were made by
Karl Auer,
Brian Haberman,
Tatuya Jinmei,
Tom Petch,
Tomoyuki Sahara,
and
Juergen Schoenwaelder.
 </t>

<t>This document was produced using the xml2rfc tool
<xref target="RFC2629"/>.</t>

</section> <!-- ack -->


<section anchor ="changes" title="Change log [RFC Editor: Please remove]">

<t>draft-carpenter-v6ops-label-balance-01: chose Option 2, removed 15 character limit, added explanation of ID/number mapping
and other clarifications, 2012-02-08.</t>

<t>draft-carpenter-v6ops-label-balance-00: original version, 2011-12-07.</t>


</section> <!-- changes -->

</middle>

<back>

<references title="Normative References">

&RFC3986;
&RFC4007;
&RFC5952;
&RFC2119;
&RFC5234;


</references>

<references title="Informative References">

&RFC2629;
&RFC3493;
&RFC4001;
 
</references>


</back>
</rfc>

