<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<!-- Expand crefs and put them inline -->
<?rfc comments='yes' ?>
<?rfc inline='yes' ?>
<rfc category="std" docName="draft-santos-smtpgrey-02" ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="SMTPGREY">SMTP Service Extension for Greylisting
    Operations</title>

    <author fullname="Hector Santos" initials="H." role="editor"
            surname="Santos">
      <organization>Santronics Software, Inc.</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>15600 SW 158 ST Suite #306</street>

          <city>Homestead, Florida</city>

          <region>FL</region>

          <code>33033</code>

          <country>United States of America</country>
        </postal>

        <email>hsantos@santronics.com</email>

        <uri>http://www.santronics.com</uri>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Evan Harris" initials="E." surname="Harris">
      <organization>puremagic.com</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>

          <street></street>

          <city></city>

          <code></code>

          <country></country>
        </postal>

        <email>eharris@puremagic.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date day="26" month="April" year="2012" />

    <abstract>
      <t>GREYLIST is a SMTP extension to formalize the widely supported
      Greylisting mail filtering method and to help support SMTP rejected
      transports by following a new formal structured 4yz server temporary
      rejection response by including a "retry=time-delay" tag string which
      SMTP clients can use to optimize the rescheduling of the mail delivery
      attempts. With adoption, network overhead reduction in wasteful mail
      delivery attempts will be realized.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>In 2003, a non-IETF technology called GreyListing was invented by
      <xref target="HARRIS">Evan Harris</xref> as a very effective method of
      enhancing the abilities of <xref target="RFC5321">SMTP</xref> mail
      systems to limit the amount of unwanted, abusive mail that they receive
      and deliver to their users. Mail systems supporting GreyListing has
      grown over the years to become a "pseudo standard" among many SMTP
      operations.</t>

      <t>This specification provides a formal IETF specification to the
      Greylisting framework, learned practices and introduces a SMTP extension
      to reduce the network, traffic overheads and mail delivery delays
      associated with SMTP Greylisting operations.</t>

      <section title="Background">
        <t>Greylisting was originally tested on a few small scale mail hosts
        (less than 100 users, though with a fairly diverse set of senders from
        all over the world, and volumes over 10,000 email attempts a day).
        Currently, Greylisting is in use on many mail servers, including ones
        processing several millions of messages per day. It was designed to be
        scalable and marginal impact to both administrators and users, and
        should be acceptable for use on a wide range of systems. Of course,
        performance issues are very dependent on implementation details.</t>

        <t><spanx>How does Greylisting work?</spanx></t>

        <t>Greylisting works by leveraging the standard SMTP client design
        expectation to retry sending mail after an initial 4yz temporary
        rejection response is issued by the server. When the greylisted
        recorded SMTP client reschedules and retries the same transaction, the
        GreyListing server will allow the greylisted recorded sender to
        continue with the transaction.</t>

        <t>While the idea of using an intentional 4yz rejection to force SMTP
        clients to retry sending mail would naturally be considered a radical
        concept for the IETF purist and most likely would not have been
        endorsed as an IETF standard protocol, the proof of concept has long
        been established as a very effective means to control certain types of
        malicious and abusive mail senders and today, Greylisting is a widely
        recognized mail filtering method and Greylisting SMTP Servers are
        widely implemented by many in the IETF mail community.</t>

        <t><spanx xml:space="preserve">What sort of mail senders does Greylisting address?</spanx></t>

        <t>By leveraging the SMTP retry expectation for clients, Greylisting
        is very effective against mail senders who anonymously and randomly
        perform a "Single Shot" mail sending attempt and will never repeat the
        same transaction after the sender has been initially rejected. The
        high payoff has been the nearly 100% of all mail senders behaving as
        "single shot" mail senders are abusive and/or malicious in nature.</t>

        <t>Greylisting can not address abusive mail senders using compliant
        SMTP mail clients. However, it has been observed that many abusive
        mail senders will retry again and often immediately within a short
        time delay. Hence, the Greylisting concept includes the idea of using
        a "Blocking Time" factor where a greylisted recorded mail sender is
        blocked for a certain time period. Only when the blocking time has
        expired, will the GreyListing server finally allow the mail sender to
        continue with the transaction.</t>

        <t><spanx>What sort of impact has Greylisting had with Mail Delivery?</spanx></t>

        <t>Greylisting has been designed since its conception to satisfy
        certain criteria:</t>

        <t><list hangIndent="" style="symbols">
            <t>Enforce SMTP compliance with expected SMTP retry
            strategies,</t>

            <t>Limit abusive mail senders ability to circumvent the
            blocking,</t>

            <t>Have minimal impact on users, and</t>

            <t>Require minimal maintenance at both the user and administrator
            level.</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>The first immediate impact are the increasing delays in mail
        delivery due to the wide range in Greylisting blocking time values
        which can be seconds, minutes to hours. Since SMTP has a standard
        recommendation to implement a Progressive Retry queuing strategy (see
        section 4.5.4.1 in <xref target="RFC5321">RFC5321</xref>) where the
        first few attempts have short delays (i.e. two attempts within the
        first hour) with a progressive back off longer delay before the
        maximum attempts (i.e. over 4-5 days) are exhausted, there are
        increasing wasted attempts and foremost higher delays in delivering
        mail. When a SMTP client implements an initial retry lower than the
        remote GreyListing Server blocking time, the SMTP client will have
        increasing wasted attempts overhead. When the SMTP client implements
        an initial retry delay higher than the remote GreyListing Server
        blocking time, the SMTP client will have unnecessary wasted mail
        delays in delivering mail.</t>

        <t>With the increasing deployment of Greylisting mail servers, the
        second impact is such that even the SMTP server who does not employ
        Greylisting, will more than likely increasingly connect to a remote
        mail server that does employ Greylisting and will experience the
        temporary rejection overhead requiring additional mail sending
        retries.</t>

        <t>The third impact is that many GreyListing servers now use the
        rejection idea at the connection level using a 421 greeting response
        which may be a different retry condition than a 45z rejection response
        issued at the MAIL FROM or DATA state. Since many MTA clients see a
        421 as a possible loading limit, it may use this to immediately
        reschedule a retry using a different MX/IP host..</t>

        <t>Overall, Greylisting was designed to address the high abuse of
        "single shot" anonymous mail senders, however it was done at the
        expense of legitimate mail senders experiencing wasted mail attempts
        and increasing delivery delays and with improper GreyListing server
        and client settings, SMTP clients may now have to revisit their
        queuing strategies to address the Greylisting overhead related
        issues.</t>

        <t>This specification provides insights into preparing a low impact
        Greylisting Server by providing some recommendations for blocking
        delays and defining a formal structure GreyListing server to
        optionally include a suggested "retry=time-delay" information in the
        server's 4yz temporary text responses.</t>

        <t>This specification does not attempt to alter existing IETF standard
        SMTP and non-IETF standard Greylisting protocols other than to provide
        augmented Greylisting techniques to help alleviate the overhead
        associated with Greylisting in the client/server SMTP transport
        process. SMTP servers supporting this extension will only be altering
        4yz greylisting responses which is out of scope in RFC5321.
        Greylisting is not part of SMTP and is implemented as an "add-on"
        component. SMTP clients supporting this extension will only be
        factoring in a new time factor for their existing retry and queuing
        method where the exact retry and queuing methods in placed is also out
        of scope in RFC5321.</t>

        <t>The Greylisting method specified in this document is a
        complementary method to any other existing mail filtering control
        systems, and is not intended as a replacement for those other methods.
        In fact, it is expected that abusive mail senders will eventually try
        to minimize the effectiveness of this method of blocking, and
        Greylisting is designed to limit options available to the mail senders
        when attempting to do so. The positive outcome of Greylisting is that
        the only methods of circumventing it will tend to make other mail
        filtering control techniques just that much more effective (primarily
        DNS and other methods of blacklisting based on IP address) even after
        any adaptation by the abusive mail senders has occurred.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Document Conventions">
        <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
        "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
        document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
        target="RFC2119">RFC 2119</xref>.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Definitions and Acronyms">
        <t><list hangIndent="5" style="hanging">
            <t hangText="MTA">Mail Transfer Agent. Sender or Receiver of mail.
            Generally viewed as a router within a MSA intra-network where
            there is a inherent authentication.<vspace blankLines="1" /></t>

            <t hangText="MUA">Mail User Agent. Online or offline mail
            reader/writer software. Typically has its own MTA component for
            sending mail.<vspace blankLines="1" /></t>

            <t hangText="MSA">Mail Submission Agent. Generally associated with
            a MUA sending message to a ISP or ESP where there is an authorized
            or authenticated association with the MUA.<vspace
            blankLines="1" /></t>

            <t hangText="MDA">Mail Destination Agent. Generally associated as
            the final destination of the message where the message is
            typically targeted for a local user. If the MDA is going to route
            the mail, then its behaving more as a MSA or MTA.<vspace
            blankLines="1" /></t>
          </list></t>
      </section>

      <section title="Syntactic Notation">
        <t>This specification uses the Augmented Backus-Naur Form (<xref
        target="RFC5234">ABNF</xref>) notation for the formal definition of
        the syntax for the "retry=time-delay" hint.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Out of Scope Considerations">
        <t>The following are out of scope considerations in this
        specification:</t>

        <t></t>

        <t><list style="empty">
            <t>o how Greylisting information is recorded in databases,</t>

            <t>o what additional mail information is recorded in databases
            beyond the Triplet recording, and</t>

            <t>o server reasons for an 4yz response outside a Greylisting
            reason, such as SMTP Traffic Control concepts.</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Greylisting Basic Framework">
      <t>The basic idea of GreyListing is:</t>

      <t><list style="numbers">
          <t>MTA Client initiates a mail delivery attempt to a remote
          GreyListing compliant mail receiver (MDA),<vspace
          blankLines="1" /></t>

          <t>The GreyListing Server collects first time session information
          about the sender such as connection IP, MAIL FROM and RCPT TO called
          the Triplet.<vspace blankLines="1" /></t>

          <t>If the Triplet was never recorded before, the Triplet is recorded
          and a 4yz rejection server response with a recommended
          "retry=time-delay" hint is issued where the time reflects the
          blocking time the sender can attempt again and proceed with the
          transaction.<vspace blankLines="1" /></t>

          <t>If the Triplet was recorded, a check is performed to determine if
          the blocking time has expired. If not, another 4yz rejection
          response with a new "retry=time-delay" hint reflecting the new
          blocking time is issued.<vspace blankLines="1" /></t>

          <t>When the sender tries again with the same recorded information
          after the blocking time has expired, then the sender has passed the
          server's greylist test and is allowed to proceed to send the
          mail.</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>One of the essential goals of this specification is to reduce the
      network and communications overhead in sender attempts and to reduce
      mail delivery delays by implementing the server "retry=time-delay" hints
      in the 4yz greylist responses.</t>

      <section title="Greylist Recording Parameters">
        <t>Greylisting Server implementations vary in ways which may include
        many factors including how senders are traced, accepted, how record
        expires, the history of sender transactions and including but not
        limited to how senders are temporarily or permanently white listed.
        The original <xref target="HARRIS">Harris</xref> Greylisting
        specifications offers a range of ideas that are considered.</t>

        <t>This specification concentrate on the three principle parameters
        that make up the fundamental backgound of a Greylist system:</t>

        <t><list>
            <t>Sender Triplet</t>

            <t>Blocking Time Delay</t>

            <t>Triplet Expiration Time</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>

      <section title="Recording Sender Information (Triplet)">
        <t>In the classic Greylisting protocol described in <xref
        target="HARRIS">HARRIS</xref>, a Triplet is the unique combination of
        connection IP, the reverse address (MAIL FROM) and the forwarding
        address (RCPT TO) used to track the sender. When the sender retries
        with the same triplet, a lookup can be perform to determine its
        Greylist status. However, depending on the Greylist server
        implementation, it can reject at different points in the SMTP state
        machine and may not collect the entire triplet information.</t>

        <t>While it is out of scope how a SMTP session Triplet is collected
        and what SMTP session data points it contains, the key point is a
        specific Triplet used to track the MTA for an initial transaction
        attempt and subsequent retries in order to control it during the
        Greylisting Server blocking time.</t>

        <t>The following is an implementation example for triplet
        recording:</t>

        <figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[Sender-Triplet = triplet-alg(CIP, RPATH, FPATH)

where

   CIP          is the connection IP address of the client,
   RPATH        is the MAIL FROM reverse-address or domain,
   FPATH        is the RCPT TO forwarding address
   triplet-alg  is the algorithm used to generate a database
                tracking key.]]></artwork>
        </figure>

        <t>One example of a triplet-alg is using a standard hashing algorithm
        as such SHA1 with BASE64 encoding.</t>

        <t><list>
            <t>BASE64(SHA1(CIP, RPATH, FPATH))</t>
          </list>Other tracking methods such as index keys in SQL database
        tables are often common with Greylisting server implementations. This
        specification does not define an formal triple-alg method. Any SMTP
        data can be used as long as it represents Greylisting servers method
        for consistent tracking transactions , its initial rejection and
        subsequent acceptance with expected retries.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="SMTP Server Rejection Points">
        <t>Greylisting assumes a triplet recording (IP, FROM and TO), however
        a Greylisting server can reject at any point in the SMTP state machine
        by recording less information about the sender. This specification
        hopes to assist the MTA to determine when a temporary rejection is
        greylist related apart from other reasons which can be a factor in how
        an MTA client will reschedule new attempts.</t>

        <section title="Connection Greeting">
          <t>Many SMTP servers will use a 421 response during the greeting as
          a way to limit connections and control load.</t>

          <t>A GreyListing server deciding to greylist a client at the
          connection greeting MUST use a 421 reply code and SHOULD include a
          "retry=time-delay" hint as part of the text response.</t>

          <t>The "retry=time-delay" hint will help the MTA decide what sort of
          rejection was imposed by distinguishing between loading limit or
          greylist rejection. Without the "retry=time-delay" hint, a MTA can
          try an alternative MX immediately (without delay) and the rejection
          may still occur. Including the "retry=time-delay" hint will assist
          the MTA to better reschedule the retry.</t>

          <t>A GreyListing Server rejecting at the connection level is
          recording only the connection IP to track the sender.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="EHLO/HELO">
          <t>A GreyListing server deciding to greylist a client as a response
          to the EHLO or HELO command SHOULD use a 451 reply code and SHOULD
          include a "retry=time-delay" hint as part of the text response. The
          hint will help the MTA decide when a new attempt should be
          attempted.</t>

          <t>A GreyListing Server rejecting at the EHLO is recording the
          connection IP and EHLO/HELO machine host name.</t>

          <t>Note: The editor has no information on the existence of
          Greylisting servers that perform a 4yz rejection at the EHLO or HELO
          command for greylisting reasons.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="MAIL FROM">
          <t>A GreyListing server deciding to greylist a client as a response
          to the MAIL FROM command SHOULD use a 451 reply code and SHOULD
          include a "retry=time-delay" hint as part of the text response. The
          hint will help the MTA decide when a new attempt should be
          attempted.</t>

          <t>A GreyListing Server rejecting at the MAIL FROM is recording the
          connection IP and MAIL FROM sender address.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="RCPT TO">
          <t>A GreyListing server deciding to greylist a client as a response
          to the RCPT TO command SHOULD use a 451 reply code and SHOULD
          include a "retry=time-delay" hint as part of the text response. The
          hint will help the MTA decide when a new attempt should be
          attempted.</t>

          <t>A GreyListing Server rejecting at the RCPT TO is recording the
          connection IP, MAIL FROM and RCPT TO addresses.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="DATA">
          <t>A GreyListing server deciding to greylist a client as a response
          to the DATA End of Data (EOD) SHOULD use a 451 reply code and SHOULD
          include a "retry=time-delay" hint as part of the text response. The
          hint will help the MTA decide when a new attempt should be
          attempted.</t>

          <t>Generally, a GreyListing server will allow the DATA command in
          order to capture the actual <xref target="RFC5322">RFC5322</xref>
          message before a greylist response is issued. The reasons are beyond
          the scope of this specification.</t>

          <t>A GreyListing Server rejecting at the DATA may be recording more
          information besides the triplet information, i.e. Message-Id
          header.</t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section title="4yz Format Structure">
        <t>Many current Greylisting Servers use varying text responses with
        informal language try again time text information. The following are
        known forms of existing Greylisting Servers which expose a form of
        time hints within the text response:</t>

        <t><list>
            <t>421 This server implements greylisting, please try again in #
            seconds</t>

            <t>450 4.7.1 &lt;RCPT&gt;: Recipient address rejected: Greylisted
            for # minutes</t>

            <t>450 4.7.1 &lt;RCPT&gt;: Recipient address rejected: Greylisted
            for # seconds</t>

            <t>451 4.7.1 Greylisting in action, please come back in
            HH:MM:SS</t>

            <t>451 Greylisted for # seconds</t>

            <t>451 Greylisted, please try again in # seconds</t>

            <t>451 Greylisting enabled, try again in # minutes</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>It is possible for existing MTA clients currently supporting the
        parsing and extraction of the time factor with the known informal
        responses from existing Greylisting servers and this specification
        does not attempt to limit specific MTA client implementations which
        may already exist.</t>

        <t>This specification offers a formal structure the Greylisting Server
        MAY use within their 4yz responses and the MTA client MAY use to
        detect and extract the retry information consistently without error
        using a single format within the 4yz response containing the following
        structured "retry=time-delay" tag:</t>

        <t><list>
            <t>retry=[DD-]HH:MM:SS</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>The [DD-]HH:MM:SS part is the time delay the MTA SHOULD wait before
        attempting to send the mail again. It is not a specific time of day,
        but rather the amount of GreyListing Server blocking time expected by
        the server before the client SHOULD try again. An MTA client ignoring
        this information, attempting again before the blocking time has
        expired, is a wasted attempt and can delay the mail delivery well
        beyond the GreyListing server blocking time.</t>

        <t>In <xref target="RFC5234">ABNF</xref>, GreyListing server response
        syntax is:</t>

        <figure>
          <artwork type="abnf"><![CDATA[
Reply-Line  = ( Reply-Code [ SP textstring ] CRLF ) /
                ( Reply-Code "-" [ SP textstring ] CRLF
                  *( Reply-Code "-" [ textstring ] CRLF )
                  Reply-Code [ SP textstring ]  CRLF )

Reply-Code  = "421" / "450" / "451"

textstring  = 1*(%x09 / %x20-7E) [SP retryhint [ SP expirehint ] ]

retryhint   = "retry=" time-delay

expirehint  = "expire=" time-expire

time-delay  = ( [days "-"] hours ":" minutes ":" seconds) / totalsecs

time-expire = ( [days "-"] hours ":" minutes ":" seconds) / totalsecs

days        = 2DIGIT   ; 00-99

hours       = 2DIGIT   ; 00-23

minutes     = 2DIGIT   ; 00-59

seconds     = 2DIGIT   ; 00-59

totalsecs   = 6*DIGIT  ; 0-999999]]></artwork>
        </figure>

        <t>Examples:</t>

        <figure>
          <artwork type=""><![CDATA[
Single line responses:

  450 4.7.1. Greylist enabled. retry=00:02:00
  451 Temporary rejection. retry=00:00:30
  450 4.7.1. Temporary Greylist rejection. retry=01-00:10:00
  451 TempFail Retry=00:00:55
  421 Your connection is greylisted. Please try again later (retry=00:01:00)

Multiple lines response:

  451-Greylisted. See policy http://example.com/GreyList-Policy
  451 Retry=00:02:00]]></artwork>
        </figure>

        <t>For multiple lines responses, the retryhint MUST be provided in the
        last line of the response.</t>

        <section title="421 vs 45z Reply Codes">
          <t>GreyListing Servers may issue 421 or 45z responses at any point
          in the SMTP session. However, RFC5321 recommends 421 be used at the
          greeting and for server interruption events. This specification
          recommends keeping with the SMTP RFC5321 recommendations for 421 and
          only use 45z for non-Greeting rejections responses. All SMTP
          compliant MTA will always follow 4yz for scheduling a retry, but the
          difference is a 421 can trigger an immediate retry attempt without
          delay at the next MX IP address, if any, where a GreyListing server
          will most likely reject the new attempt due to the blocking
          time.</t>

          <t><list>
              <t>IMPLEMENTATION NOTE: RFC5321 recommends a specific 450 reply
              code for temporary rejections related to local policy reasons.
              HARRIS used 451 to make it distinctive as a greylist response.
              This specification recommends using 450, however, it is
              recognized that many existing Greylisting servers already use
              451 as the reply code. MTA MUST NOT depend on 450 or 451 to make
              retry decisions. All 4yz responses MUST be interpreted as a
              temporary rejection.</t>
            </list>When the "retry=time-delay" hint is implemented in the
          response, compliant MTA will be able to determine the difference
          between a load restriction and a greylisted rejection to
          appropriately reschedule a new attempt at the GreyListing server's
          suggested time hint.</t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section title="Recommended Blocking Times">
        <t>This specification does not impose any specific blocking delay
        value when 4yz rejections are issued by servers, other than to suggest
        that timely delivery of mail to users remains to be an inherent
        expectation by SMTP clients and SMTP servers.</t>

        <t>The GreyListing server blocking times vary greatly in practice, but
        there is empirical evidence a majority of systems use a 1 to 5 minute
        delay. Many use 10 minutes or 15 minutes. Many use less than 1 minute,
        like 30 to 55 seconds. The latter tend to be systems who wish to lower
        impact with immediate and timely mail delivery delays. However, this
        can be wasteful attempts when the MTA is operating blindly with
        unknown blocking times imposed by Greylisting Servers.</t>

        <t>When it comes to a recommendation, there is no GreyListing logic to
        suggest that long delays be use when the goal of Greylisting senders
        is to address the anonymous random "single shot" senders where their
        triplet will never be the same. Delaying good SMTP senders for
        extended unreasonable periods defeats the goal of Greylisting.</t>

        <t>Since there is no clear recommendation for a blocking time delay
        (other than to keep it short as possible), this specification offers
        the "retry=time-delay" hint as a method to alleviate the uncertainty
        in the wasted attempts and delays in timely mail delivery.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="SMTP Service Keyword">
      <t>GREYLIST is a new <xref target="RFC1651">ESMTP</xref> service
      keyword. The GreyListing Server MAY add this optional keyword as a
      response to EHLO command. EHLO response Format:</t>

      <t>250-GREYLIST [server-options]</t>

      <t>If the GREYLIST keyword is presented as part of the EHLO response, it
      means the server has Greylisting implemented and 4yz responses are
      possible due to a Greylist decision by the server to impose on the
      client. The keyword is not necessary and the server can still provide
      4yz temporary rejections.</t>

      <t>The optional server-options provides space separated attributes
      reflecting the server Greylisting information the server wishes to
      expose. Currently the following optional attributes are defined:</t>

      <t><list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="RETRY">means that 4yz responses related to GreyListing
          will have "retry=time-delay" information. The attribute is optional
          and not required to issue 4yz responses with "retry=time-delay"
          hints.</t>
        </list></t>

      <section title="SMTP Client/Server Implementation">
        <section title="SMTP Server Implementation">
          <t>The SMTP server MAY add support for the GREYLIST service keyword
          in the EHLO response. If the SMTP server adds the GREYLIST service
          keyword without the RETRY attribute, it MAY add the
          "retry=time-delay" hint to 4yz responses. If the SMTP server adds
          the GREYLIST service keyword with the RETRY attribute, it MUST add
          the "retry=time-delay" hint to to 4yz responses.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="SMTP Client Implementation">
          <t>The SMTP client MAY read the GREYLIST service keyword exposed by
          the EHLO response and it MAY support the usage of the
          "retry=time-delay" hint in 4yz responses and are not obligated to
          honor the SMTP servers recommended retry delay.</t>

          <t>If the SMTP server offers the GREYLIST keyword with the RETRY
          attribute, the SMTP client SHOULD consider supporting the usage of
          the server's recommended retry delay in 4yz responses with
          "retry=time-delay" hints.</t>

          <t>If a SMTP client is rejected by the Greylisting Server during the
          session, the client SHOULD NOT attempt to start a new transaction
          during the same session and SHOULD immediately issue a QUIT command
          to end the session. Its been observed that some mail senders will
          hold the connection for 1-5 minutes and retry the same mail
          transaction or a new transaction. The SMTP server rejecting the
          initial transaction MAY stop accepting any new transactions attempts
          during the same session.</t>

          <t>If a SMTP server offers a "retry=time-delay" hint which results
          in a wasted 2nd attempt and requires additional attempts, the SMTP
          client MAY begin to ignore the server's "retry=time-delay" hint
          after the 2nd wasted retry. The SMTP client implementation can
          decide what limits to place on honoring "retry=time-delay" hints and
          wasted attempts it provides.</t>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Examples">
      <t>Example with no extended codes:</t>

      <figure>
        <artwork><![CDATA[
S: serverdomain.com, welcome ESMTP v2.0
C: EHLO mail.clientdomain.com
S: 250-GREYLIST
S: 250-HELP
C: MAIL FROM:<jqpublic@emaildomain.com>
S: 250 User OK
C: RCPT TO:<localuser@serverdomain.com>
S: 451 Greylisted. Please Disconnect now. retry=00:01:00
C: QUIT
S: 221 Goodbye
      ]]></artwork>
      </figure>

      <t>In the above example, the client can extract the "retry=00:01:00"
      information and rechedule a 2nd mail delivery attempt at the current
      attempt time plus 1 minute later and not before. It can reschedule at a
      later time it if chooses to do so.</t>

      <t>Example with extended codes:</t>

      <figure>
        <artwork><![CDATA[
S: serverdomain.com, welcome ESMTP v2.0
C: EHLO mail.clientdomain.com
S: 250-ENHANCEDSTATUSCODES
S: 250-GREYLIST
S: 250-HELP
C: MAIL FROM:<jqpublic@emaildomain.com>
S: 250 2.1.0 User OK
C: RCPT TO:<localuser@serverdomain.com>
S: 450 4.7.1 Greylisted. Please Disconnect now. retry=00:10:00 expire=02-00:00:00
C: QUIT
S: 221 2.3.0 Goodbye]]></artwork>
      </figure>

      <t>In the above example, the client can extract the "retry=00:05:00"
      information and rechedule a 2nd mail delivery attempt at the current
      attempt time plus 10 minutes and not before. It can reschedule at a
      later time, however since a "expire=time-expire" hint was provide, it
      should complete the new attempts before the indicated 2 days expiration.
      If the attempt is done after 2 days, the server will greylist reject the
      MTA again.</t>

      <t>Example of connection rejection:</t>

      <figure>
        <artwork><![CDATA[
S: 421 4.7.1 Greylist enabled. Try again later. retry=00:10:00]]></artwork>
      </figure>

      <t></t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>This document makes no request of IANA.</t>

      <t>Note to RFC Editor: this section may be removed on publication as an
      RFC.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>One possible security concern envisioned is a DoS attack when
      "retry=time-delay" information is exposed by the GreyListing server
      where by a malicious sender may attempt to overwhelm the server during
      the server's retry time exposing a time window when the server has
      indicated system availability for mail acceptability. However, since
      security measures to mitigate DoS is a required operational factor, a
      GreyListing Server will inherently be prepared for DoS attacks with
      managed loading limits with or without "retry=time-delay" Greylist
      responses, thus there is no expected technical concern by exposing
      Greylist "retry=time-delay" hints. With or without this specification,
      all SMTP servers SHOULD be prepared for DoS attacks of all kinds.</t>

      <t>Another arguable security concern is related to the idea a formal
      SMTP extension can possibly lower the effectiveness of Greylisting when
      abusive mail senders adapt to the server's suggested retry times. This
      concern does not seem to have weight since adaptation can occur with or
      without the extension simply by complying to SMTP retry recommendations.
      Greylisting remains effective because legacy abusive systems do not
      adapt. In fact, a "retry=time-delay" hint implementation provides a
      means to help avoid abusive redundancy and reduced random overloading of
      connections at unmanaged random times by MTA clients of all flavors. A
      "retry=time-delay" hint may actually be purposely calculated to provide
      a time window when there is less loading for legitimate and abusive
      senders.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>The following individuals contributed input and guidance in the
      production of this specification:</t>

      <t><list>
          <t>Claus Assmann, Frank Ellerrman, Tim Kehres, John Klensin, S.
          Moonesamy, Keith Moore, Ken Raeburn, Paul Smith.</t>
        </list>Please note acknowledgement does not imply any specific
      endorsement of this specification other than they have provided
      important pros and cons input which helped mold the specification.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.1651"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3463"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4408"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4871"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5234"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5321"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5322"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5672"?>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <reference anchor="HARRIS"
                 target="http://projects.puremagic.com/greylisting/whitepaper.html">
        <front>
          <title>The Next Step in the Spam Control War: Greylisting</title>

          <author fullname="E. Harris" initials="E." surname="Harris"></author>

          <date year="2003" />
        </front>
      </reference>
    </references>

    <section title="Additional Greylist Parameters">
      <t>Greylisting Server implementations vary in ways which may include
      many factors including how senders are traced, accepted, how record
      expires, the history of sender transactions and including but not
      limited to how senders are temporarily or permanently white listed. The
      original <xref target="HARRIS">Harris</xref> Greylisting specifications
      offers a range of ideas that are considered. The following are just of a
      few of additional parameters that are considered by servers:</t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>Whitelist Record Expiration:<vspace blankLines="1" />Whitelist
          Record Expiration is used to allow a previous greylisted sender a
          time window where it can be temporarily or permanently whitelisted
          depending on the implementation. This is a local policy
          consideration, however, it should be noted that redundant
          greylisting of a common MTA is not considered reasonable. At some
          point, the MTA is a trusted source of mail and the MTA SHOULD be
          permanently whitelisted. The main idea with a temporary whitelisting
          is that its possible a future transaction can be a compromised user
          transaction.<vspace blankLines="1" /></t>

          <t>Class C IP Address Tracking:<vspace blankLines="1" />Class C IP
          Address Tracking allows a Greylisting server to control a greylisted
          MTA who retries using a different class C address. This is typical
          in larger outbound farms where many machines are used to send mail.
          If Class C is not considered, MTAs using a different IP will be
          unnecessarily rejected after delaying within a blocked time.</t>
        </list></t>
    </section>

    <section title="Augmenting Other Standard Email Filters Methods">
      <t>It is possible for a GreyListing server to combine other mail
      filtering techniques, methods and session information to determine if a
      sender should be greylisted. While the augmentation of these additional
      methods is out of the scope, the following are some suggestions that may
      help minimize a GreyListing Server impact. on MTAs.</t>

      <t><list hangIndent="5" style="hanging">
          <t hangText="SPF"><xref target="RFC4408">SPF (Sender Policy
          Framework)</xref> can be used to help validate a sender's IP
          association with the return path domain. A SPF SOFTFAIL or FAIL (if
          not used for rejection) result could be used to help decide when
          Greylisting should be employed on the sender. While a PASS result is
          not a trusted condition, a local policy may use a PASS to skip
          Greylisting mail checks.</t>

          <t hangText="DKIM"><xref target="RFC5672">DKIM (Domain Key
          Identified Mail)</xref> can be used to help authenticate the
          transactions from trusted DKIM mail signers. If the signer is
          considered is trusted source, this can help eliminate the need to
          greylist the sender.</t>
        </list></t>
    </section>

    <section title="TO DO LIST">
      <t><list style="numbers">
          <t>Possible section showing real proof of concept examples.<vspace
          blankLines="1" /></t>

          <t>Review the SMTP Service Keyword and determine how SHOULD|MAY|MUST
          is applied.<vspace blankLines="1" /></t>
        </list></t>
    </section>
  </back>
</rfc>