<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY rfc3986 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3986.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc4395 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4395.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc2119 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc5234 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5234.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc2609 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2609.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc2683 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2683.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc2822 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2822.xml">
<!ENTITY pbasu-intentional SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.pbasu-dtnrg-naming.xml">
]>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<rfc category="info" docName="draft-davies-dtnrg-uri-find-00.txt"
     ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="Adding find opname to dtn: URI">Adding the "find" Operation
    to the dtn: URI Scheme</title>

    <author fullname="Elwyn B. Davies" initials="E.B." surname="Davies">
      <organization>Folly Consulting</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>

          <city>Soham</city>

          <region>Cambs</region>

          <code></code>

          <country>UK</country>
        </postal>

        <phone>+44 7889 488 335</phone>

        <email>elwynd@dial.pipex.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Avri Doria" initials="A.D." surname="Doria">
      <organization>LTU</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>

          <street></street>

          <city>Lulea</city>

          <region></region>

          <code>971 87</code>

          <country>Sweden</country>
        </postal>

        <phone>+1 401 663 5024</phone>

        <email>avri@acm.org</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date day="09" month="October" year="2009" />

    <area>IRTF</area>

    <keyword>Delay Tolerant Networking Research Group</keyword>

    <keyword>Request for Comments</keyword>

    <keyword>I-D</keyword>

    <keyword>IRTF</keyword>

    <keyword>DTN</keyword>

    <keyword>URI</keyword>

    <keyword>EID</keyword>

    <keyword>Service Naming</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>This document discusses the addition of a new operation to the
      proposed dtn: URI (Uniform Resource Identifier) scheme. The new "find"
      operation would provide support for DTN anycast services.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>This document describes the addition of an extra operation to the
      proposed dtn: URI (Uniform Resource Identifier) scheme documented in
      <xref target="I-D.irtf-dtnrg-dtn-uri-scheme"></xref>.</t>

      <t>The purpose of the "find" operation is to allow DTN nodes to access
      services that they do not or cannot support through exchange of DTN
      bundles. In the spirit of DTN operation, nodes expect to be able to
      operate independently and may not know exactly where such a service is
      implemented, but has a reasonable expectation that such a service is
      provided by another node accessible using DTN.</t>

      <t>In order for the "find" operation to work satisfactorily, the routing
      service, whether static or dynamic, would need to collect and propagate
      information about the "services" offered by the nodes to which it was
      able to route bundles. With the help of this information, the DTN
      routing system could offer a form of "anycast" service that delivered
      appropriately addressed bundles to one or more nodes that offer the
      services requested in the "find" adressing format. Especially in the
      dynamic case, service announcements will need to be propagated in the
      DTN network. The mechanism to be used to provide these announcements
      requires further study. Where services are provided by gateway nodes at
      the edge of the Internet static configuration in some DTN nodes may be
      sufficient.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Requirements Notation">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
      document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
      target="RFC2119"></xref>.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Changes to &quot;dtn&quot; Scheme Syntax and Rules">
      <section title="Syntax">
        <t>The general syntax of a dtn URI as defined in <xref
        target="I-D.irtf-dtnrg-dtn-uri-scheme"></xref> is unchanged except for
        the addition of "find" to opname. The revised ABNF <xref
        target="RFC5234"></xref> is:</t>

        <t>dtnURI = "dtn:" ("none" / nontrivialSSP)</t>

        <t>where:</t>

        <t>nontrivialSSP = dtnURIelt *("!" dtnURIelt)</t>

        <t>dtnURIelt = [opname] ":" URI ; URI as defined in RFC 3986 [*]</t>

        <t>opname = "push" / "pop" / "next" / "flood" / "exec"/ "find"</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Changes to Resolution of DTN Endpoint IDs">
        <t>Section 2.2 of <xref target="I-D.irtf-dtnrg-dtn-uri-scheme"></xref>
        contains defintions of the various operations listed under "opname" in
        the ABNF. For the "find" operation the following definition should be
        added after thedefinition of "exec":</t>

        <t><list hangIndent="3" style="hanging">
            <t hangText="find:">When the operation name is "find", the bundle
            agent SHOULD use information accumulated by the DTN routing system
            in use to forward the bundle towards one or more nodes that are
            able to deliver the requested service or would be better able to
            forward the bundle towards such a node. However, the node MAY
            determine that it is able to deliver the bundle locally to an
            agent that can provide the requested service: in this case the
            operation is equivalent to the "pop" operation. If the node is
            unable to determine a suitable target it MAY drop the bundle.</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Examples">
      <section title="dtn:find:mailto:another@example.org,second@example.org">
        <t>Citing this EID as the destination of a bundle causes the bundle to
        be delivered to a node that provides an (outgoing) email server that
        can forward the payload of the bundle as an email to the specified
        address(es) in the mailto URI or local account(s) to which the email
        can be delivered. In this case the bundle payload is expected to
        contain one or more emails in <xref target="RFC2822"></xref>
        format.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="dtn:find:service:printer?printer-color-supported=true">
        <t>Citing this EID as the destination of a bundle causes the bundle to
        be delivered to a node that provides a printing service. The specified
        attribute requests that a color capable printer be used to print the
        payload carried in the bundle. This example uses the service: URI
        template "printer.2.0.en" <eref
        target="http://www.iana.org/assignments/svrloc-templates/printer.2.0.en"></eref>
        that conforms to the specification in <xref
        target="RFC2609"></xref>.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="dtn:find:service:fax?destination=+4416324960123">
        <t>Citing this EID as the destination of a bundle is intended to cause
        the bundle to be delivered to a node that provides a telephone
        facsimile (fax) service. Note that this would require the definition
        of a new service: URI template for a fax delivery service which
        provided the "destination" attribute that would be the telephone
        number called. The payload of the bundle would be sent as a fax to the
        specified destination.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="httpproxy1"
               title="dtn:find:service:httpproxy:http://example.com/somepage.html?depth=3">
        <t>Citing this EID as the destination of a bundle is intended to cause
        the bundle to be delivered to a node that provides a (caching) web
        proxy service. As with the previous example, this proposes the use of
        a yet-to-be created service: URI template for a web proxy service that
        would access the specified URI using the HTTP protocol. Typically the
        HTML in the page returned from the initial request would require
        additional accesses to build up the entire displayed page (c.f., the
        GNU "wget" tool that returns content from web servers <eref
        target="http://www.gnu.org/software/wget/"></eref>). The "depth"
        parameter controls the depth of recursion of such accesses. The suite
        of returned HTML documents would be combined into a single bundle that
        would be returned to the requestor. The complete service would provide
        additional parameters to control the behavior of the service and
        possibly cause repeated operation on a timed basis.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="dtn:find:service:httpproxy:http:?telephone+number+example, &amp;width=5,&amp;depth=3">
        <t>This example is similar to the previous example in <xref
        target="httpproxy1"></xref>, except that the intention is to have the
        service access a suitable web search engine (to be chosen by the
        service provider) to look up information according to the query (in
        this case information about example numbers to be used when describing
        a telephone service) with parameters that control the number of
        returned results (&amp;width parameter) to be examined in more detail
        by accessing the returned URIs recursively to the value of the
        &amp;depth parameter. Again the complete set of results would be
        returned as a single bundle and additional parameters could be
        defined.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="dtn:find:intent#role(?E,coffee),location(?E,Loc),within(100,(1,3),Loc)">
        <t>The concept of intentional naming is described in <xref
        target="I-D.pbasu-dtnrg-naming"></xref>. An example of the naming
        scheme used with the GRAIN (Gradient-Based Algorithm for Intentional
        Naming) salgorithm to locate nodes that satisfy the intentional naming
        specification is given at the end of Section 5.5 of the draft. The
        mechanism needs additional support from the dtn: URI scheme to be
        usable in a DTN network. We suggest that the "find" operation could be
        used in the way illustrated in this example to direct bundles to
        appropriate nodes using an intentional naming scheme. We also note
        that it would also be possible to specify the intentional naming
        mechanism through a service: URI service template which would allow it
        to be used in the wider Internet instead of defined a separate
        "intent" URI scheme restricted to DTN.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Security Considerations">
      <t>The addition of the "find" operation does not appear to introduce any
      extra security issues beyind the considerable challenges already facing
      DTN security.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>It is intended that the "find" operation will be folded into the dtn:
      URI scheme being defined in <xref
      target="I-D.irtf-dtnrg-dtn-uri-scheme"></xref> which will be registered
      in the URI registry defined in <xref target="RFC4395"></xref>.</t>

      <t>The "find" operation expects to use URIs following the service: URI
      scheme (<xref target="RFC2609"></xref>) and possibly other existing
      schemes. It may require the definition of new service templates
      according to the service: URI definition.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Acknowledgments"></section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      &rfc3986;

      &rfc4395;

      &rfc2119;

      &rfc5234;

      <reference anchor="I-D.irtf-dtnrg-dtn-uri-scheme">
        <front>
          <title>The DTN URI Scheme</title>

          <author fullname="Kevin Fall" initials="K" surname="Fall">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="Scott Burleigh" initials="S" surname="Burleigh">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="Avri Doria" initials="A" surname="Doria">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="Joerg Ott" initials="J" surname="Ott">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date day="31" month="March" year="2009" />

          <abstract>
            <t>This document describes the "dtn" Uniform Resource Identifier
            (URI) scheme. DTN URIs are used as DTN endpoint identifiers
            (EIDs).</t>
          </abstract>
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft"
                    value="draft-irtf-dtnrg-dtn-uri-scheme-00" />

        <format target="http://www.ietf.org/internet-drafts/draft-irtf-dtnrg-dtn-uri-scheme-00.txt"
                type="TXT" />
      </reference>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      &rfc2609;

      &rfc2683;

      &rfc2822;

      &pbasu-intentional;
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>