<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY rfc1757 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1757.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc2021 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2021.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc2863 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2863.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc3418 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3418.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc2119 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc2578 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2578.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc2579 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2579.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc2580 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2580.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc3410 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3410.xml">
]>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<?rfc strict="no"?>
<?rfc rfcedstyle="yes"?>
<rfc category="std" docName="draft-cole-manet-report-mib-01" ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="The REPORT-MIB">Definition of Managed Objects for
    Performance Reporting</title>

    <author fullname="Robert G. Cole" initials="R.G." surname="Cole">
      <organization>Johns Hopkins University</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>11100 Johns Hopkins Road, Room 257</street>

          <city>Laurel</city>

          <region>Maryland</region>

          <code>21073</code>

          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>

        <phone>+1 443 778 6951</phone>

        <email>robert.cole@jhuapl.edu</email>

        <uri>http://www.cs.jhu.edu/~rgcole/</uri>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Joseph Macker" initials="J.M." surname="Macker">
      <organization>Naval Research Laboratory</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>
          <city>Washington</city>

          <region>D.C.</region>

          <code>20375</code>

          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>

        <email>macker@itd.nrl.navy.mil</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Al Morton" initials="A." surname="Morton">
      <organization>AT&T Laboratories</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>
          <city>Middletown</city>

          <region>N.J.</region>

          <code>07724</code>

          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>

        <email>amorton@att.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>


    <date />

    <area>Operations and Management</area>

    <workgroup>Internet Engineering Task Force</workgroup>

    <keyword>Network Management</keyword>

    <keyword>Management Information Base</keyword>

    <keyword>MIB</keyword>

    <keyword>SMIv2</keyword>

    <keyword>Reporting</keyword>

    <keyword>MANET</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>This memo defines a portion of the Management Information Base (MIB)
      for use with network management protocols in the Internet community. In
      particular, it describes objects for configuring autonomous
      report generation on any device that supports MIBs containing
      counter and gauge objects for performance monitoring.  This allows a management station
      to instruct a device to build off-line reports to be collected asynchronously by
      the management station.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>This memo defines a portion of the Management Information Base (MIB)
      for use with network management protocols in the Internet community. In
      particular, it describes objects for configuring autonomous, off-line report
      generation for performance monitoring on any device supporting 
      MIBs containing variables that resolve to type Integer32 
      (i.e., Integer32, Counter, Gauge, or TimeTicks).  
      This should be useful to devices or networks where efficient use
      of bandwidth is of concern or where intermittent connectivity
      is common.  Hence, the REPORT-MIB is useful for devices managed over
      some Mobile Ad-Hoc Networks (MANETs) or Disruption Tolerant Networks (DTNs).</t>

      <t>The REPORT-MIB offers to types of off-line reporting.  One type offering
      reports which present statistical analysis of the objects being
      tracked; found within the reportStatsGroup.  The second offering
      reports which present (collect) raw data values from the objects
      being tracked; found within the reportUsrHistoryGroup.</t>

      <t>For statistical reporting, the REPORT-MIB borrows 
      from the RMON <xref target="RFC1757"></xref> ReportsControl and Reports Tables.
      Here the ReportsControlTable specifies the report metric, the
      Object ID to monitor and other aspects of the report development
      and storage.  For raw data collection, the REPORT-MIB
      reproduces the capabilities originally developed and found within
      RMON2 <xref target="RFC2021"></xref>.  The REPORT-MIB defines
      various compliance groups which allow for development of
      only raw data collection reports, or only statistical data
      reports, or both.</t>

    </section>

    <section title="The Internet-Standard Management Framework">
      <t>For a detailed overview of the documents that describe the current
      Internet-Standard Management Framework, please refer to section 7 of RFC
      3410 <xref target="RFC3410"></xref>.</t>

      <t>Managed objects are accessed via a virtual information store, termed
      the Management Information Base or MIB. MIB objects are generally
      accessed through the Simple Network Management Protocol (SNMP). Objects
      in the MIB are defined using the mechanisms defined in the Structure of
      Management Information (SMI). This memo specifies a MIB module that is
      compliant to the SMIv2, which is described in STD 58, RFC 2578 <xref
      target="RFC2578"></xref>, STD 58, RFC 2579 <xref
      target="RFC2579"></xref> and STD 58, RFC 2580 <xref
      target="RFC2580"></xref>.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Conventions">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
      document are to be interpreted as described in RFC 2119 <xref
      target="RFC2119"></xref>.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Overview">
      <t>The Reporting MIB ...
      and notifications.</t>

      <section title="REPORT-MIB Management Model">
        <t>This section describes the management model for the Reporting
        MIB process.  First, the model for the reportStatsGroup is presented.
        Then the model for the reportUsrHistoryGroup is presented.</t>

        <t>Figure 1 illustrates a potential use of the REPORT-MIB
           for the generation of off-line, remotely generated reports.
           The management station on the left hand side of the illustration
           instructs the remote device to create reports through manipulation
           of the ReportCntrl Objects in the REPORT-MIB resident on the
           remote device.  The reports instruct the device to monitor the
           status of specified counters (on other MIBs) periodically
           and to generate a set of metrics describing the temporal
           behavior of those counter values.  The reports are stored locally
           until the management station decides to pull them off the
           device.  The figure shows a case where the REPORT-MIB generates
           a notification that Report_2 has completed, prompting the management
           station to pull Report_2 from the device.</t>

      <figure>
         <preamble />
            <artwork><![CDATA[
Mgmt       Device
Station
                       REPORT-MIB         MIB_1
                       +---------+        +-----+
                       |         |        |     |
 Build_Rep_1           |+-------+|        +--+  |
    +----------------->||cntrl_1||<------>|PC|  |
                       |+-------+|<-+     +--+--+
                       |         |  |
                       |         |  |     MIB_2
                       |         |  |     +-----+
                       |            |     |     |
                       |         |  |     +--+  |
                       |         |  +---->|PC|  |
 Build_Rep_2           |+-------+|    +-->+--+--+
    +----------------->||cntrl_2||<---+
                       |+-------+|
                       |         |
                       |         |
 Build_Rep_3           |+-------+|
    +----------------->||cntrl_3||<---+   MIB_n
                       |+-------+|    |   +-----+
                       |         |    |   |     |
                       |+-----+  |    |   +--+  |
                       ||Rep_1|  |    +-->|PC|  |
                       |+-----+  |        +--+--+
                       |         |
                       |+-----+  |
    <------------------||Rep_2|  |
 Notf_Rep_2            |+-----+  |
                       |         |
                       |+-----+  |
                       ||Rep_3|  |
                       |+-----+  |
 Get_Rep_2             |         |
    +----------------->|         |
                       |         |
    <-----------------+|         |
 Send_Rep_2            +---------+


Figure 1: REPORT-MIB front-end report generation process.
           ]]></artwork>
         <postamble />
      </figure>

      <t>The REPORT-MIB's reportStatsGroup defines specifically a set of metrics which are
         computed within all reports.  It also allows for the specification
         of metric extensions which are local to the specific implementation
         of the REPORT-MIB.  These are identified in the reportStatsCapabilitiesGroup
         metricExtension Table.</t>

      <t>Each metric has an associated Object ID of type counter associated
         with it.  The control table specifies a report interval and a
         bin interval.  The report interval is an integral multiple
         of the bin interval.  For each bin interval, the device
         identifies the change in the counter value over the bin interval (called x_i)
         and then computes the associated metric, e.g., sum, sum of the square,
         etc, over the set {x_i}.  It maintains the sum of these computations within the metric
         objects in the 'reportStatsDataTable'.  Once the report interval
         is complete, the management station has enough information
         to compute a set of interesting and useful statistics.</t>

      <t>The computational model of the reportStatsGroup of the
         REPORT-MIB is illustrated in the figure below.
         The important controls are a) the contrlInterval, b) the cntrlBinInterval,
         c) the specific counterObjectId, and d) the metric.  In the figure
         x_i represents the ith value of the counter change, i.e.,
         x_i = counterValue(t_i+1) - counterValue(t_i).  The metrics reported
         are then computed from the set (x_i).  Three examples are identified
         in the figure, e.g., StatSumX, StatSumSq and StatMaxX.  Other existing and
         potential metrics are discussed below.</t>

      <figure>
         <preamble />
            <artwork><![CDATA[

|
|<--------------------- cntrlInterval ---------------------------->|
|                                                                  |

|     |     |     |     |                              |     |     |
| x_0 | x_1 | x_2 | x_3 |            ...               |x_n-2|x_n-1|
+-----+-----+-----+-----+---                        ---+-----+-----+

^     ^     ^     ^     ^                              ^     ^     ^
t_0   t_1   t_2   t_3   t_4                            t_n-2 t_n-1 t_n


where t_i - t_i-1 = cntrlBinInterval
      n = cntrlInterval / cntrlBinInterval

      StatSumX = Sum(x_i)  from i=0, ..., n-1
      StatSumSq = Sum((x_i)^2) from i=0, ..., n-1
      StatMaxX = Max(x_i) for i=0, ..., n-1


Figure 2: REPORT-MIB statistical analysis computation process.
           ]]></artwork>
         <postamble />
      </figure>


      <t>The following observations and analysis techniques are not all
         inclusive.  Rather these are the ones we have come up with at the
         time of writing this document.</t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
         <t>Number - </t>

         <t>Frequency - </t>

         <t>The time interval is that specified in the control table.  It
            is not a metric datum, but it is associated with the metric
            sample - </t>

         <t>Maximum - </t>

         <t>Minimum - </t>

         <t>Range - </t>

         <t>Arithmetic Mean - </t>

         <t>Root Mean Square - </t>

         <t>Variance - </t>

         <t>Standard Deviation - </t>

         <t>Slope of a least-squares line - </t>

         <t>These are accessible from the statistical datum provided by this MIB
            module.</t>
      </list></t>

      <t>The REPORT-MIB also provide for the collection of raw data
         instead of statistical data.  It does this by importing (copying)
         the usrHistory group from RMON2 
         <xref target="RFC2021"></xref> which allows for the
         generation of reports collecting the raw object values binned
         for the purpose of aggregation and efficiency of collection.
         These are defined within the reportUsrHistoryGroup.  The model
         used for this type of report generation is based upon three
         tables.  The reportUsrHistoryControlTable defines aspects of the
         report generation related to duration of the reporting interval,
         the bin (or bucket) sizes for the report, and the number of object
         values collected for each bucket.  The reportUsrHistoryObjectTable
         identifies the specific MIB objects whose values and binned
         within the report.  And the reportUsrHistoryDataTable contains
         the binned data values collected for the report.</t>

      </section>

      <section title="Terms">
        <t>The following definitions apply throughout this document:</t>

        <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>Capabilities - Objects related to the capabilities of the device and
             MIB implemented on the device.  Some objects are explicitly defined
             within the REPORT-MIB.  Other capabilities can be exposed through
             the REPORT-MIB, but which are not explicitly defined within this
             document.  These later capabilities include objects, e.g., for
             new metrics.</t>

          <t>Control - Objects defined within this document which set the
             parameters for specific reports to be generated offline on the
             the remote managed device.</t>

          <t>Data - Objects which hold the report data, either statistical data
             or raw history data.</t>
        </list></t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Structure of the MIB Module">
      <t>This section presents the structure of the REPORT-MIB module. The
      objects are arranged into the following groups:</t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
        <t>reportMIBNotifications - defines the notifications associated with the
        REPORT-MIB.</t>

        <t>reportMIBObjects - defines the objects forming the basis for the REPORT
        MIB. These objects are divided up by function into the following
        groups:</t>

        <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>Statistics Group - This group contains the objects which
          support the generation of reports of a statistical nature.</t>

          <t>Usr History Group - This group contains the objects which
          support the generation (collection) of historical reports exposing
          raw data values.</t>
        </list></t>

        <t>reportMIBConformance - Defines a variety of conformance of
        implementations of this REPORT-MIB.</t>
      </list></t>

      <section title="Textual Conventions">
        <!--Generic and Common Textual Conventions 
        can be found summarized at 
        http://www.ops.ietf.org/mib-common-tcs.html-->

        <t>The textual conventions used in the REPORT-MIB are as follows. The
        RowStatus textual convention is imported from 
        RFC 2579 <xref target="RFC2579" />.</t>

        <!--The ReportInterfaceOperStatus is defined within the REPORT-MIB.
           This contains the current operational status of the
           REPORT interface.</t>-->
      </section>

      <section title="The Statistics Group">
        <t>The REPORT-MIB device has a ....</t>

        <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>StatsCapabilities - ...</t>
          <t>StatsControl - ...</t>
          <t>StatsData - ...</t>
        </list></t>

        <t> The reportStatsCapabilitiesGroup contains .....</t>

        <t> The reportStatsControlGroup contains .....</t>

        <t>The reportStatsDataGroup contains ...
           As and example of how the metrics are to be computed
           within the REPORT-MIB, consider the standard metric
           object 'reportStatsDataStatSumX'.  For each bin interval
           defined by the object reportCntrlReportsBinInterval, the
           change in the value of the counter pointed to by the Object ID
           reportCntrlReportsPriObjID is calculated.  Then this (delta) value
           is added to the current value of the value contained in the
           object 'reportStatsDataStatSumX'.  Then, if interested in
           computing the average change in this object (sampled each
           bin interval) for the duration of the report, the management
           station simply divides reportStatsDataStatSumX by
           reportStatsDataStatN.  Although this is a trivial
           example because the value of reportAggrReportStatSumX
           is simple the difference in the counter reportCntrolReportsPriObjID
           at the start and the end of the total report interval, the
           other metrics defined are not as trivial.</t>

        <t>The objects 'reportStatsDataOverflowStatSumX' and
           'reportStatsDataHCSumX' are borrowed from RMON and
           exist to handle integer overflow situations where, e.g., 
           'reportStatsDataStatSumX' overruns its maximum vary
           numerous times.</t>

        <t>Computations and utility of the other standard metrics are
           as follows:</t>

        <t><list style="symbols">
            <t>reportStatsDataStatSumXSq - </t>

            <t>reportStatsDataStatMaximum - </t>

            <t>reportStatsDataStatMinimum - </t>

            <t>reportStatsDataStatSumSq - </t>

            <t>reportStatsDataStatSumIX - </t>

            <t>reportStatsDataStatSumIXSq - </t>
        </list></t>
      </section>

      <section title="The User History Group">
        <t>The User History Group contains tables which ....</t>

        <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>reportUsrHistoryControlTable - </t>
          <t>reportUsrHistoryObjectTable - </t>
          <t>reportUsrHistoryDataTable - </t>
        </list></t>

        <t> The reportUsrHistoryControlTable contains .....</t>

        <t> The reportUsrHistoryObjectsTable contains .....</t>

        <t> The reportUsrHistoryDataTable contains .....</t>
      </section>


      <section title="The Notifications Group">
        <t>The Notifications Subtree contains the list of notifications
        supported within the REPORT-MIB and their intended purpose or utility.
        This group is currently empty.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Relationship to Other MIB Modules">
      <t>[TODO]: The text of this section specifies the relationship of the
      MIB modules contained in this document to other standards, particularly
      to standards containing other MIB modules. Definitions imported from
      other MIB modules and other MIB modules that SHOULD be implemented in
      conjunction with the MIB module contained within this document are
      identified in this section.</t>

      <section title="Relationship to the SNMPv2-MIB">
        <t>The 'system' group in the SNMPv2-MIB <xref target="RFC3418"></xref>
        is defined as being mandatory for all systems, and the objects apply
        to the entity as a whole. The 'system' group provides identification
        of the management entity and certain other system-wide data. The
        REPORT-MIB does not duplicate those objects.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Relationship to the IF-MIB">
        <t>[TODO] This section is included as an example; If the MIB module is
        not an adjunct of the Interface MIB, then this section should be
        removed.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="MIB modules required for IMPORTS">
        <t>[TODO]: Citations are not permitted within a MIB module, but any
        module mentioned in an IMPORTS clause or document mentioned in a
        REFERENCE clause is a Normative reference, and must be cited someplace
        within the narrative sections. If there are imported items in the MIB
        module, such as Textual Conventions, that are not already cited, they
        can be cited in text here. Since relationships to other MIB modules
        should be described in the narrative text, this section is typically
        used to cite modules from which Textual Conventions are imported.</t>

        <t>The following REPORT-MIB module IMPORTS objects from SNMPv2-SMI <xref
        target="RFC2578"></xref>, SNMPv2-TC <xref target="RFC2579"></xref>,
        SNMPv2-CONF <xref target="RFC2580"></xref>, and IF-MIB <xref
        target="RFC2863"></xref></t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <!-- Definitions section -->

    <!-- This section contains the MIB module(s) defined by the specification.
         These MIB modules MUST be written in SMIv2 [RFC2578] [RFC2579]
         [RFC2580].

         See Section 4 of RFC 4181 for guidelines on SMIv2 usage.

	 See Appendix C of RFC 4181 for suggested naming conventions

         A list of tools that can help automate the process of 
         checking mib definitions can be found at 
         http://www.ops.ietf.org/mib-review-tools.html
    -->

    <section title="Definitions">
      <t></t>

      <figure>
        <artwork><![CDATA[

REPORT-MIB DEFINITIONS ::= BEGIN

IMPORTS

   ZeroBasedCounter32
      FROM RMON2-MIB                           -- [RFC2021]

   MODULE-IDENTITY, OBJECT-TYPE, NOTIFICATION-TYPE,
   Counter32, Gauge32, Unsigned32, Integer32, mib-2
      FROM SNMPv2-SMI                          -- [RFC2578]

   TEXTUAL-CONVENTION, RowStatus, TruthValue, 
   TimeStamp, StorageType
      FROM SNMPv2-TC                           -- [RFC2579]

   MODULE-COMPLIANCE, OBJECT-GROUP, 
   NOTIFICATION-GROUP
      FROM SNMPv2-CONF                         -- [RFC2580]

   OwnerString
      FROM RMON-MIB                            -- [RFC2819]

   InterfaceIndexOrZero
      FROM IF-MIB                              -- [RFC2863]

   ZeroBasedCounter64
      FROM HCNUM-TC                            -- [RFC2856]

   SnmpAdminString
      FROM SNMP-FRAMEWORK-MIB                  -- [RFC3411]

   InetAddress, InetAddressType,
   InetAddressPrefixLength
      FROM INET-ADDRESS-MIB                    -- [RFC4001]

   SspmClockSource, SspmClockMaxSkew,
   SspmMicroSeconds
      FROM SSPM-MIB                           -- [RFC4149]
   ;

reportMIB MODULE-IDENTITY
   LAST-UPDATED "200910251300Z"  -- October 25, 2009
   ORGANIZATION "IETF MANET Working Group"
   CONTACT-INFO
      "WG E-Mail: manet@ietf.org

       WG Chairs: ian.chakeres@gmail.com
                  jmacker@nrl.navy.mil


       Editors:   Robert G. Cole
                  Johns Hopkins University
                  Applied Physics Lab and
                  Department of Computer Science
                  11000 Johns Hopkins Road
                  Room 02-257
                  Laurel, MD 22014
                  USA
                  +1 443 778-6951
                  robert.cole@jhuapl.edu

                  Joseph Macker
                  Naval Research Laboratory
                  Washington, D.C. 20375
                  USA
                  macker@itd.nrl.navy.mil

                  Al Morton
                  AT&T Laboratories
                  Middletown, N.J. 07724
                  USA
                  amorton@att.com"
   DESCRIPTION
      "This MIB module contains managed object definitions for
       the autonmous reporting of performance object counters.  
       Copyright (C) The IETF Trust (2009). This version
       of this MIB module is part of RFC xxxx; see the RFC
       itself for full legal notices."

     -- Revision History
     REVISION    "200910251300Z"   -- October 25, 2009
     DESCRIPTION
        "The second draft of this MIB module published as
         draft-cole-manet-report-mib-01.txt.  Significant
         revisions to this draft include a) the inclusion of
         raw data collection borrow blatently from the
         usrHistory Group within RMON2, b) the deletion of
         the CurrentHistoryTable from version -00, 
         c) modifications to the overall structure of the
         MIB, and d) the definition of various Compliance
         options for implementations related to this MIB."
     REVISION    "200904281300Z"   -- April 28, 2009
     DESCRIPTION
        "Initial draft of this MIB module published as
         draft-cole-manet-report-mib-00.txt."
     -- RFC-Editor assigns XXXX
     ::= { mib-2 998 }   -- to be assigned by IANA



-- TEXTUAL CONVENTIONs

   ReportMetricDefID ::= TEXTUAL-CONVENTION
       DISPLAY-HINT "d"
       STATUS       current
       DESCRIPTION
           "An index that identifies through reference to a specific
           statistical metrics.
           "
       SYNTAX       Unsigned32 (1..2147483647)



--
-- Top-Level Object Identifier Assignments
--

reportMIBNotifications OBJECT IDENTIFIER ::= { reportMIB 0 }
reportMIBObjects       OBJECT IDENTIFIER ::= { reportMIB 1 }
reportMIBConformance   OBJECT IDENTIFIER ::= { reportMIB 2 }

-- Then, the reportMIBObjects Assignments:
--      reportStatsGroup           - 1
--      reportUsrHistoryGroup      - 2


reportStatsGroup       OBJECT IDENTIFIER ::= { reportMIBObjects 1 }

-- Then, the reportStatsGroup assignments are :
--      reportStatsCapabilitiesGroup    - 1
--      reportStatsControlGroup         - 2   
--      reportStatsDataGroup            - 3


-- reportStatsCapabilitiesGroup
--    This group contains the REPORT objects that identify specific
--    capabilities within this device related to REPORT functions.


reportCapabilitiesGroup  OBJECT IDENTIFIER ::= { reportStatsGroup 1 }

reportClockResolution  OBJECT-TYPE
    SYNTAX      SspmMicroSeconds
    MAX-ACCESS  read-only
    STATUS      current
    -- UNITS       Microseconds
    DESCRIPTION
        "A read-only variable indicating the resolution
         of the measurements possible by this device."
    ::= { reportCapabilitiesGroup 1 }

reportClockMaxSkew  OBJECT-TYPE
    SYNTAX      SspmClockMaxSkew
    MAX-ACCESS  read-only
    STATUS      current
    -- UNITS       Seconds
    DESCRIPTION
        "A read-only variable indicating the maximum
         offset error due to skew of the local clock
         over the time interval 86400 seconds, in seconds."
    ::= { reportCapabilitiesGroup 2 }

reportClockSource  OBJECT-TYPE
    SYNTAX      SspmClockSource
    MAX-ACCESS  read-only
    STATUS      current
    DESCRIPTION
        "A read-only variable indicating the source of the clock.
         This is provided to allow a user to determine how accurate
         the timing mechanism is compared with other devices."
    ::= { reportCapabilitiesGroup 3 }

reportMetricDirLastChange  OBJECT-TYPE
    SYNTAX      TimeStamp
    MAX-ACCESS  read-only
    STATUS      current
    DESCRIPTION
        "The value of sysUpTime at the time the
        reportTransMetricDirTable was last modified, through
        modifications of the reportTransMetricDirConfig object."
    ::= { reportCapabilitiesGroup 4 }


-- REPORT Metric Extensions Definition Table

reportMetricExtDefTable  OBJECT-TYPE
    SYNTAX      SEQUENCE OF ReportMetricExtDefEntry
    MAX-ACCESS  not-accessible
    STATUS      current
    DESCRIPTION
        "The reportMetricExtDefTable describes the metrics
        available to the REPORT-MIB.  The reportMetricExtDefTable
        can define metrics by referencing existing IETF,
        ITU, and other standards organizations' documents,
        including enterprise-specific documents.
        Examples of appropriate references include the
        ITU-T Recommendation Y.1540 [Y.1540] on IP
        packet transfer performance metrics and the
        IETF documents from the IPPM WG; e.g., RFC2681
        on the round trip delay metric [RFC2681] or
        RFC3393 on the delay variation metric [RFC3393].
        Other examples include RFC2679 [RFC2679], RFC2680
        [RFC2680], and RFC3432 [RFC3432].  Although no
        specific metric is mandatory, implementations
        should, at a minimum, support a round-trip delay
        and a round-trip loss metric.

        This table contains one row per metric supported by this
        agent, and it should be populated during system
        initialization."
    ::= { reportCapabilitiesGroup 5 }

reportMetricExtDefEntry  OBJECT-TYPE
    SYNTAX      ReportMetricExtDefEntry
    MAX-ACCESS  not-accessible
    STATUS      current
    DESCRIPTION
        "Information about a particular metric."
    INDEX   { reportMetricExtDefID }
    ::= { reportMetricExtDefTable 1 }

ReportMetricExtDefEntry ::= SEQUENCE {
      reportMetricExtDefID             ReportMetricDefID,
      reportMetricExtDefType           INTEGER,
      reportMetricExtDefName           SnmpAdminString,
      reportMetricExtDefOperation      SnmpAdminString,
      reportMetricExtDefReference      SnmpAdminString
    }

reportMetricExtDefID OBJECT-TYPE
    SYNTAX      ReportMetricDefID
    MAX-ACCESS  not-accessible
    STATUS      current
    DESCRIPTION
        "The index for this entry.  This object identifies
         the particular metric in this MIB module."
    ::= { reportMetricExtDefEntry 1 }

reportMetricExtDefType  OBJECT-TYPE
    SYNTAX      INTEGER  {
                          other(1),
                          singleObjMetric(2),
                          multipleObjMetric(3)
                }
    MAX-ACCESS  read-only
    STATUS      current
    DESCRIPTION
        "The basic type of metric indicated by this entry.

        The value 'other(1)' indicates that this metric cannot be
        characterized by any of the remaining enumerations specified
        for this object.

        The value 'connectMetric(2)' indicates that this metric
        measures connectivity characteristics.

        The value 'delayMetric(3)' indicates that this metric
        measures delay characteristics.
        "
    ::= { reportMetricExtDefEntry 2 }

reportMetricExtDefName  OBJECT-TYPE
    SYNTAX      SnmpAdminString
    MAX-ACCESS  read-only
    STATUS      current
    DESCRIPTION
       "The textual name of this metric.  For example, if
        this reportMetricDefEntry identified the IPPM metric for
        round trip delay, then this object should contain
        the value, e.g., 'Type-P-Round-Trip-Delay'."
    ::= { reportMetricExtDefEntry 3 }

reportMetricExtDefOperation  OBJECT-TYPE
    SYNTAX      SnmpAdminString
    MAX-ACCESS  read-only
    STATUS      current
    DESCRIPTION
        "The textual description of the operations necessary
        to compute this metric.  For example, if
        this reportMetricDefEntry identified the IPPM metric for
        round trip delay, then this object should contain
        the value, e.g., 'Type-P-Round-Trip-Delay'."
    ::= { reportMetricExtDefEntry 4 }

reportMetricExtDefReference  OBJECT-TYPE
    SYNTAX      SnmpAdminString
    MAX-ACCESS  read-only
    STATUS      current
    DESCRIPTION
        "This object contains a reference to the document that
        defines this metric.  If this document is available online
        via electronic download, then a de-referencable URL
        should be specified in this object.  The implementation
        must support an HTTP URL type and may support additional
        types of de-referencable URLs such as an FTP type.

        For example, if this reportMetricDefName identified the IPPM
        metric 'Type-P-Round-Trip-Delay', then this object should
        contain the value, e.g.,
        'http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc2681.txt'."
    ::= { reportMetricExtDefEntry 5 }



-- Stats Control Group
--     This and the following tables are modeled
--     after the report control and collection
--     capabilities found in RMON II, RFC XXXX  

reportStatsControlGroup OBJECT IDENTIFIER ::= {reportStatsGroup 2}

reportStatsControlTable  OBJECT-TYPE
    SYNTAX      SEQUENCE OF ReportStatsControlEntry
    MAX-ACCESS  not-accessible
    STATUS      current
    DESCRIPTION
        "The reportStatsControlTable is the controlling entry
        that manages the population of studies in the
        Report for selected time intervals.

        Note that this is not like the typical RMON
        controlTable and dataTable in which each entry creates
        its own data table.  Each entry in this table enables the
        creation of multiple data tables on a study basis.  For each
        interval, the study is updated in place, and the current
        data content of the table becomes invalid.

        The control table entries are persistent across
        system reboots."
    ::= { reportStatsControlGroup 1 }

reportStatsControlEntry  OBJECT-TYPE
    SYNTAX      ReportStatsControlEntry
    MAX-ACCESS  not-accessible
    STATUS      current
    DESCRIPTION
        "A conceptual row in the reportStatsControlTable.

        An example of the indexing of this entry is
        reportGenReportCntrInterval.1"
    INDEX { reportStatsControlIndex }
    ::= { reportStatsControlTable 1 }

ReportStatsControlEntry ::= SEQUENCE {
    reportStatsControlIndex          Unsigned32,
    reportStatsControlInterval       Unsigned32,
    reportStatsControlBinInterval    Unsigned32,
    reportStatsControlPriObjID       OBJECT IDENTIFIER,
    reportStatsControlSecObj1ID      OBJECT IDENTIFIER,
    reportStatsControlSecObj2ID      OBJECT IDENTIFIER,
    reportStatsControlSecObj3ID      OBJECT IDENTIFIER,
    reportStatsControlSecObj4ID      OBJECT IDENTIFIER,
    reportStatsControlSecObj5ID      OBJECT IDENTIFIER,
    reportStatsControlMetricExt1     ReportMetricDefID,
    reportStatsControlMetricExt2     ReportMetricDefID,
    reportStatsControlMetricExt3     ReportMetricDefID,
    reportStatsControlMetricExt4     ReportMetricDefID,
    reportStatsControlMetricExt5     ReportMetricDefID,
    reportStatsControlReqReports     Unsigned32,
    reportStatsControlGrantedReports Unsigned32,
    reportStatsControlStartTime      TimeStamp,
    reportStatsControlReportNumber   Unsigned32,
    reportStatsControlInsertsDenied  Counter32,
    reportStatsControlOwner          OwnerString,
    reportStatsControlStorageType    StorageType,
    reportStatsControlStatus         RowStatus
}

reportStatsControlIndex  OBJECT-TYPE
    SYNTAX      Unsigned32 (1..65535)
    MAX-ACCESS  not-accessible
    STATUS      current
    DESCRIPTION
        "An index that uniquely identifies an entry in the
        reportStatsControlTable.  Each such entry defines a unique
        report whose results are placed in the reportGenReportTable 
        on behalf of this reportStatsControlEntry."
    ::= { reportStatsControlEntry 1 }


reportStatsControlInterval  OBJECT-TYPE
    SYNTAX      Unsigned32
    UNITS       "Seconds"
    MAX-ACCESS  read-create
    STATUS      current
    DESCRIPTION
       "The interval in seconds over which data is accumulated before
        being aggregated into a report in the reportGenReportTable.
        All reports with the same reportStatsControlIndex will be
        based on the same interval.

        The value of the reportStatsControlInterval should be
        an integral multiple of the value of the
        reportStatsControlBinInterval.

        This object may not be modified if the associated
        reportStatsControlStatus object is equal to active(1)."
    DEFVAL { 3600 }
    ::= { reportStatsControlEntry 2 }

reportStatsControlBinInterval  OBJECT-TYPE
    SYNTAX      Unsigned32
    UNITS       "Seconds"
    MAX-ACCESS  read-create
    STATUS      current
    DESCRIPTION
       "The interval in seconds between which the value of the
        reportStatsControlPriObjID and SecObjIDs are polled
        for the purpose of generating the metric values associated
        with this report.  All reports with the same 
        reportStatsControlIndex will be based on the 
        same bin interval.

        This object may not be modified if the associated
        reportStatsControlStatus object is equal to active(1)."
    DEFVAL { 3600 }
    ::= { reportStatsControlEntry 3 }

reportStatsControlPriObjID  OBJECT-TYPE
    SYNTAX      OBJECT IDENTIFIER
    MAX-ACCESS  read-create
    STATUS      current
    DESCRIPTION
        "This identifies the primary counter object to be
        monitored within this report.

        This object may not be modified if the associated
        reportStatsControlStatus object is equal to active(1)."
    ::= { reportStatsControlEntry 4 }   

reportStatsControlSecObj1ID  OBJECT-TYPE
    SYNTAX      OBJECT IDENTIFIER
    MAX-ACCESS  read-create
    STATUS      current
    DESCRIPTION
        "This identifies the secondary counter object to be
        monitored within this report associated with the 
        specified reportStatsControlMetricExt1.  If the
        reportStatsControlMetricExt1 is a simple metric, then
        the value of this reportStatsControlSecObj1ID is
        set to '0'.

        This object may not be modified if the associated
        reportStatsControlStatus object is equal to active(1)."
    ::= { reportStatsControlEntry 5 }   

reportStatsControlSecObj2ID  OBJECT-TYPE
    SYNTAX      OBJECT IDENTIFIER
    MAX-ACCESS  read-create
    STATUS      current
    DESCRIPTION
        "This identifies the secondary counter object to be
        monitored within this report associated with the 
        specified reportStatsControlMetricExt2.  If the
        reportStatsControlMetricExt2 is a simple metric, then
        the value of this reportStatsControlSecObj2ID is
        set to '0'.

        This object may not be modified if the associated
        reportStatsControlStatus object is equal to active(1)."
    ::= { reportStatsControlEntry 6 }   

reportStatsControlSecObj3ID  OBJECT-TYPE
    SYNTAX      OBJECT IDENTIFIER
    MAX-ACCESS  read-create
    STATUS      current
    DESCRIPTION
        "This identifies the secondary counter object to be
        monitored within this report associated with the 
        specified reportStatsControlMetricExt3.  If the
        reportStatsControlMetricExt3 is a simple metric, then
        the value of this reportStatsControlSecObj3ID is
        set to '0'.

        This object may not be modified if the associated
        reportStatsControlStatus object is equal to active(1)."
    ::= { reportStatsControlEntry 7 }   

reportStatsControlSecObj4ID  OBJECT-TYPE
    SYNTAX      OBJECT IDENTIFIER
    MAX-ACCESS  read-create
    STATUS      current
    DESCRIPTION
        "This identifies the secondary counter object to be
        monitored within this report associated with the 
        specified reportStatsControlMetricExt4.  If the
        reportStatsControlMetricExt4 is a simple metric, then
        the value of this reportStatsControlSecObj4ID is
        set to '0'.

        This object may not be modified if the associated
        reportStatsControlStatus object is equal to active(1)."
    ::= { reportStatsControlEntry 8 }   

reportStatsControlSecObj5ID  OBJECT-TYPE
    SYNTAX      OBJECT IDENTIFIER
    MAX-ACCESS  read-create
    STATUS      current
    DESCRIPTION
        "This identifies the secondary counter object to be
        monitored within this report associated with the 
        specified reportStatsControlMetricExt5.  If the
        reportStatsControlMetricExt5 is a simple metric, then
        the value of this reportStatsControlSecObj5ID is
        set to '0'.

        This object may not be modified if the associated
        reportStatsControlStatus object is equal to active(1)."
    ::= { reportStatsControlEntry 9 }   

reportStatsControlMetricExt1  OBJECT-TYPE
    SYNTAX      ReportMetricDefID
    MAX-ACCESS  read-create
    STATUS      current
    DESCRIPTION
        "This identifies the first metric extension placed
        in the reportGenReportTable.  If no metric extension
        is requested, then this object value is set to '0'.

        If this metric is defined on a single counter object,
        then only the reportStatsControlPriObjID is set, while
        the value of the reportStatsControlSecObjID is
        set to '0'.  Else, the reportStatsControlSecObjID
        is set in accoradance with the instruction in the
        definition of the metric extension found in the
        reportCapabilitiesMetwircExtTable above.

        This object may not be modified if the associated
        reportStatsControlStatus object is equal to active(1)."
    ::= { reportStatsControlEntry 10 }

reportStatsControlMetricExt2  OBJECT-TYPE
    SYNTAX      ReportMetricDefID
    MAX-ACCESS  read-create
    STATUS      current
    DESCRIPTION
        "This identifies the first metric extension placed
        in the reportGenReportTable.  If no metric extension
        is requested, then this object value is set to '0'.

        If this metric is defined on a single counter object,
        then only the reportStatsControlPriObjID is set, while
        the value of the reportStatsControlSecObjID is
        set to '0'.  Else, the reportStatsControlSecObjID
        is set in accoradance with the instruction in the
        definition of the metric extension found in the
        reportCapabilitiesMetwircExtTable above.

        This object may not be modified if the associated
        reportStatsControlStatus object is equal to active(1)."
    ::= { reportStatsControlEntry 11 }

reportStatsControlMetricExt3  OBJECT-TYPE
    SYNTAX      ReportMetricDefID
    MAX-ACCESS  read-create
    STATUS      current
    DESCRIPTION
        "This identifies the first metric extension placed
        in the reportGenReportTable.  If no metric extension
        is requested, then this object value is set to '0'.

        If this metric is defined on a single counter object,
        then only the reportStatsControlPriObjID is set, while
        the value of the reportStatsControlSecObjID is
        set to '0'.  Else, the reportStatsControlSecObjID
        is set in accoradance with the instruction in the
        definition of the metric extension found in the
        reportCapabilitiesMetwircExtTable above.

        This object may not be modified if the associated
        reportStatsControlStatus object is equal to active(1)."
    ::= { reportStatsControlEntry 12 }

reportStatsControlMetricExt4  OBJECT-TYPE
    SYNTAX      ReportMetricDefID
    MAX-ACCESS  read-create
    STATUS      current
    DESCRIPTION
        "This identifies the first metric extension placed
        in the reportGenReportTable.  If no metric extension
        is requested, then this object value is set to '0'.

        If this metric is defined on a single counter object,
        then only the reportStatsControlPriObjID is set, while
        the value of the reportStatsControlSecObjID is
        set to '0'.  Else, the reportStatsControlSecObjID
        is set in accoradance with the instruction in the
        definition of the metric extension found in the
        reportCapabilitiesMetwircExtTable above.

        This object may not be modified if the associated
        reportStatsControlStatus object is equal to active(1)."
    ::= { reportStatsControlEntry 13 }

reportStatsControlMetricExt5  OBJECT-TYPE
    SYNTAX      ReportMetricDefID
    MAX-ACCESS  read-create
    STATUS      current
    DESCRIPTION
        "This identifies the first metric extension placed
        in the reportGenReportTable.  If no metric extension
        is requested, then this object value is set to '0'.

        If this metric is defined on a single counter object,
        then only the reportStatsControlPriObjID is set, while
        the value of the reportStatsControlSecObjID is
        set to '0'.  Else, the reportStatsControlSecObjID
        is set in accoradance with the instruction in the
        definition of the metric extension found in the
        reportCapabilitiesMetwircExtTable above.

        This object may not be modified if the associated
        reportStatsControlStatus object is equal to active(1)."
    ::= { reportStatsControlEntry 14 }


reportStatsControlReqReports  OBJECT-TYPE
    SYNTAX      Unsigned32 (1..65535)
    MAX-ACCESS  read-create
    STATUS      current
    DESCRIPTION
        "The number of saved reports requested to be allocated on
        behalf of this entry.

        This object may not be modified if the associated
        reportStatsControlStatus object is equal to active(1)."
    ::= { reportStatsControlEntry 15 }

reportStatsControlGrantedReports  OBJECT-TYPE
    SYNTAX      Unsigned32 (0..65535)
    MAX-ACCESS  read-only
    STATUS      current
    DESCRIPTION
        "The number of saved reports the agent has allocated based
        on the requested amount in reportStatsControlReqReports.
        Because each report can have many entries, the total number
        of entries allocated will be this number multiplied by the
        value of reportStatsControlGrantedSize, or by 1 if that
        object doesn't exist.

        When the associated reportStatsControlReqReports object is
        created or modified, the agent should set this object as
        closely to the requested value as is possible for the
        particular implementation and available resources.  When
        considering available resources, the agent must consider its
        ability to allocate this many reports, each with the number
        of entries represented by reportStatsControlGrantedSize, or
        by 1 if that object doesn't exist.

        Note that although the storage required for each report may
        fluctuate due to changing conditions, the agent must continue
        to have storage available to satisfy the full report size for
        all reports, when necessary.  Further, the agent must not
        lower this value except as a result of a set to the
        associated reportStatsControlReqSize object."
    ::= { reportStatsControlEntry 16 }

reportStatsControlStartTime  OBJECT-TYPE
    SYNTAX      TimeStamp
    MAX-ACCESS  read-only
    STATUS      current
    DESCRIPTION
        "The value of sysUpTime when the system began processing the
        report in progress.  Note that the report in progress is not
        available.

        This object may be used by the management station to figure
        out the start time for all previous reports saved for this
        reportStatsControlEntry, as reports are started at fixed
        intervals."
    ::= { reportStatsControlEntry 17 }

reportStatsControlReportNumber  OBJECT-TYPE
    SYNTAX      Unsigned32
    MAX-ACCESS  read-only
    STATUS      current
    DESCRIPTION
        "The number of the report in progress.  When an
        reportStatsControlEntry is activated, the first report will
        be numbered zero."
    ::= { reportStatsControlEntry 18 }

reportStatsControlInsertsDenied  OBJECT-TYPE
    SYNTAX      Counter32
    MAX-ACCESS  read-only
    STATUS      current
    DESCRIPTION
        "The number of attempts to add an entry to reports for
        this ReportStatsControlEntry that failed because the 
        number of entries would have exceeded 
        reportStatsControlGrantedSize.

        This number is valuable in determining if enough 
        entries have been allocated for reports 
        in light of fluctuating network
        usage.  Note that an entry that is denied will 
        often be attempted again, so this number will 
        not predict the exact number of additional entries 
        needed, but it can be used to
        understand the relative magnitude of the problem.

        Also note that there is no ordering specified for 
        the entries in the report; 
        thus, there are no rules for which entries
        will be omitted when not enough entries are available.  
        As a consequence, the agent is not required 
        to delete 'least valuable' entries first."
    ::= { reportStatsControlEntry 19 }

reportStatsControlOwner  OBJECT-TYPE
    SYNTAX      OwnerString
    MAX-ACCESS  read-create
    STATUS      current
    DESCRIPTION
        "The entity that configured this entry and is
        therefore using the resources assigned to it.

        This object may not be modified if the associated
        reportStatsControlStatus object is equal to active(1)."
    ::= { reportStatsControlEntry 20 }

reportStatsControlStorageType  OBJECT-TYPE
    SYNTAX      StorageType
    MAX-ACCESS  read-create
    STATUS      current
    DESCRIPTION
        "The storage type of this reportStatsControlEntry.  If the
        value of this object is 'permanent', no objects in this row
        need to be writable."
    ::= { reportStatsControlEntry 21 }

reportStatsControlStatus  OBJECT-TYPE
    SYNTAX      RowStatus
    MAX-ACCESS  read-create
    STATUS      current
    DESCRIPTION
        "The status of this performance control entry.

        An entry may not exist in the active state unless each
        object in the entry has an appropriate value.

        Once this object is set to active(1), no objects in the
        reportStatsControlTable can be changed.

        If this object is not equal to active(1), all associated
        entries in the reportGenReportTable shall be deleted."
    ::= { reportStatsControlEntry 22 }




-- Stats Data Group 

reportStatsDataGroup  OBJECT IDENTIFIER ::= { reportStatsGroup 3 }


-- Report Stats Data Table

reportStatsDataTable  OBJECT-TYPE
    SYNTAX      SEQUENCE OF ReportStatsDataEntry
    MAX-ACCESS  not-accessible
    STATUS      current
    DESCRIPTION
        "This table contains completed
        studies for each of the control table entries in
        reportAggrReportCntrlTable.  These studies are
        provided based on the selections and parameters
        found for the entry in the
        reportAggregateReportsCntrlTable.

        The performance statistics are specified in the
        reportTransMetricDirTable associated with the
        application in question and indexed by
        appLocalIndex and reportTransMetricIndex."
    ::= { reportStatsDataGroup 1 }

reportStatsDataEntry  OBJECT-TYPE
    SYNTAX      ReportStatsDataEntry
    MAX-ACCESS  not-accessible
    STATUS      current
    DESCRIPTION
        "A conceptual row in the reportStatsDataTable.

        The reportStatsControlIndex value in the 
        index identifies the reportStatsControlEntry 
        on whose behalf this entry was created.

        The reportStatsDataIndex value in the index 
        identifies which report 
        (in the series of reports) this entry is a part of.

        The reportStatsDataServerAddress value in the 
        index identifies the network layer address of the 
        device generatung this report.

        An example of the indexing of this entry is
        reportStatsDataStatN.3.15.34.262.18.4.128.2.6.7.3256521"
    INDEX { reportStatsControlIndex,
            reportStatsDataIndex
          }
    ::= { reportStatsDataTable 1 }

ReportStatsDataEntry ::= SEQUENCE {
    reportStatsDataIndex                Unsigned32,
    reportStatsDataServerAddress        OCTET STRING,
    reportStatsDataStatN                ZeroBasedCounter32,
    reportStatsDataStatSumX             ZeroBasedCounter32,
    reportStatsDataOverflowStatSumX     ZeroBasedCounter32,
    reportStatsDataHCStatSumX           ZeroBasedCounter64,
    reportStatsDataStatMaximum          ZeroBasedCounter32,
    reportStatsDataStatMinimum          ZeroBasedCounter32,
    reportStatsDataStatSumSq            ZeroBasedCounter32,
    reportStatsDataOverflowStatSumSq    ZeroBasedCounter32,
    reportStatsDataHCStatSumSq          ZeroBasedCounter64,
    reportStatsDataStatSumIX            ZeroBasedCounter32,
    reportStatsDataOverflowStatSumIX    ZeroBasedCounter32,
    reportStatsDataHCStatSumIX          ZeroBasedCounter64,
    reportStatsDataStatSumIXSq          ZeroBasedCounter32,
    reportStatsDataOverflowStatSumIXSq  ZeroBasedCounter32,
    reportStatsDataHCStatSumIXSq        ZeroBasedCounter64,
    reportStatsDataStatMetricExt1       ZeroBasedCounter32,
    reportStatsDataStatMetricExt2       ZeroBasedCounter32,
    reportStatsDataStatMetricExt3       ZeroBasedCounter32,
    reportStatsDataStatMetricExt4       ZeroBasedCounter32,
    reportStatsDataStatMetricExt5       ZeroBasedCounter32 
}

reportStatsDataIndex  OBJECT-TYPE
    SYNTAX      Unsigned32 (1..2147483647)
    MAX-ACCESS  not-accessible
    STATUS      current
    DESCRIPTION
        "The value of reportAggrReportCntrlNumber for the report to
        which this entry belongs."
    ::= { reportStatsDataEntry 1 }

-- [Note: Need to revisit the syntax for this object of type 'address'.]
reportStatsDataServerAddress  OBJECT-TYPE
    SYNTAX      OCTET STRING (SIZE (0..108))
    MAX-ACCESS  not-accessible
    STATUS      current
    DESCRIPTION
        "The network layer address of the server host in this
        conversation.

        This is represented as an octet string with specific
        semantics and length as identified by the
        protocolDirLocalIndex component of the index.

        Because this object is an index variable, it is encoded in
        the index according to the index encoding rules.  For
        example, if the protocolDirLocalIndex indicates an
        encapsulation of IPv4, this object is encoded as a length
        octet of 4, followed by the 4 octets of the IPv4 address,
        in network byte order.

        If the associated reportAggrReportCntrlAggrType is equal to
        application(4) or client(2), then this object will be a null
        string and will be encoded simply as a length octet of 0."
    ::= { reportStatsDataEntry 2 }

reportStatsDataStatN  OBJECT-TYPE
    SYNTAX      ZeroBasedCounter32
    MAX-ACCESS  read-only
    STATUS      current
    DESCRIPTION
        "The count of the total number of data points for the
        specified metric.  This number is simply the value of
        reportCntrlReportsInterval divided by the value of
        reportCntrlReportsBinInterval, which should be integer
        valued.
        "
    ::= { reportStatsDataEntry 3 }

reportStatsDataStatSumX  OBJECT-TYPE
    SYNTAX      ZeroBasedCounter32
    MAX-ACCESS  read-only
    STATUS      current
    DESCRIPTION
        "The sum of all the data point values for the specified
        metric.  This number always represents the total values
        of the statistical datum analyzed.  Each metric
        specifies the exact meaning of this object.
        This value represents the results of one metric and is
        related directly to the specific parameters of the metric
        and the Server and Client addresses involved."
    ::= { reportStatsDataEntry 4 }

reportStatsDataOverflowStatSumX  OBJECT-TYPE
    SYNTAX      ZeroBasedCounter32
    MAX-ACCESS  read-only
    STATUS      current
    DESCRIPTION
        "The number of times the associated
        reportAggrReportStatSumX counter has overflowed.
        Note that this object will only be instantiated if the
        associated reportAggrReportHCStatSumX object is also
        instantiated for a particular dataSource."
    ::= { reportStatsDataEntry 5 }

reportStatsDataHCStatSumX  OBJECT-TYPE
    SYNTAX      ZeroBasedCounter64
    MAX-ACCESS  read-only
    STATUS      current
    DESCRIPTION
        "The high-capacity version of reportAggrReportStatSumX.
        Note that this object will only be instantiated if the
        agent supports High Capacity monitoring for a particular
        dataSource."
    ::= { reportStatsDataEntry 6 }

reportStatsDataStatMaximum  OBJECT-TYPE
    SYNTAX      ZeroBasedCounter32
    MAX-ACCESS  read-only
    STATUS      current
    DESCRIPTION
        "The single maximum data point value observed during the
        study period for the specified metric.  This number always
        represents the maximum value of any single statistical
        datum analyzed.  Each metric specifies the exact meaning
        of this object.

        This value represents the results of one metric and is
        related directly to the specific parameters of the metric
        and the Server and Client addresses involved."
    ::= { reportStatsDataEntry 7 }

reportStatsDataStatMinimum  OBJECT-TYPE
    SYNTAX      ZeroBasedCounter32
    MAX-ACCESS  read-only
    STATUS      current
    DESCRIPTION
        "The single minimum data point value observed during the
        study period for the specified metric.  This number always
        represents the minimum value of any single statistical
        datum analyzed.  Each metric specifies the exact meaning
        of this object.

        This value represents the results of one metric and is
        related directly to the specific parameters of the metric
        and the Server and Client addresses involved."
    ::= { reportStatsDataEntry 8 }

reportStatsDataStatSumSq  OBJECT-TYPE
    SYNTAX      ZeroBasedCounter32
    MAX-ACCESS  read-only
    STATUS      current
    DESCRIPTION
        "The sum of all the squared data point values for the
        specified metric.  This number always represents the
        total of the squared values of the statistical datum
        analyzed.  Each metric specifies the exact meaning of
        this object.

        This value represents the results of one metric and is
        related directly to the specific parameters of the metric
        and the Server and Client addresses involved."
    ::= { reportStatsDataEntry 9 }

reportStatsDataOverflowStatSumSq  OBJECT-TYPE
    SYNTAX      ZeroBasedCounter32
    MAX-ACCESS  read-only
    STATUS      current
    DESCRIPTION
        "The number of times the associated
        reportAggrReportStatSumSq counter has overflowed.
        Note that this object will only  be instantiated if
        the associated reportAggrReportHCStatSumSq object
        is also instantiated for a particular dataSource."
    ::= { reportStatsDataEntry 10 }

reportStatsDataHCStatSumSq  OBJECT-TYPE
    SYNTAX      ZeroBasedCounter64
    MAX-ACCESS  read-only
    STATUS      current
    DESCRIPTION
        "The high-capacity version of reportAggrReportStatSumSq.
        Note that this object will only be instantiated if the
        agent supports High Capacity monitoring for a particular
        dataSource."
    ::= { reportStatsDataEntry 11 }

reportStatsDataStatSumIX  OBJECT-TYPE
    SYNTAX      ZeroBasedCounter32
    MAX-ACCESS  read-only
    STATUS      current
    DESCRIPTION
        "For each interval, each data point is associated with a
        value I, I = 1..N where N is the number of data points;
        reportAggrReportStatSumIX is the multiplication of the
        data point value with the current I.  This value
        along with the other statistics values allow the
        calculation of the slope of the least-squares line
        through the data points."
    ::= { reportStatsDataEntry 12 }

reportStatsDataOverflowStatSumIX  OBJECT-TYPE
    SYNTAX      ZeroBasedCounter32
    MAX-ACCESS  read-only
    STATUS      current
    DESCRIPTION
        "The number of times the associated
        reportAggrReportStatSumIX counter has overflowed.
        Note that this object will only be instantiated if the
        associated reportAggrReportHCStatSumIX object is also
        instantiated for a particular dataSource."
    ::= { reportStatsDataEntry 13 }

reportStatsDataHCStatSumIX  OBJECT-TYPE
    SYNTAX      ZeroBasedCounter64
    MAX-ACCESS  read-only
    STATUS      current
    DESCRIPTION
        "The high-capacity version of reportAggrReportStatSumIX.
        Note that this object will only be instantiated if the
        agent supports High Capacity monitoring for a particular
        dataSource."
    ::= { reportStatsDataEntry 14 }

reportStatsDataStatSumIXSq  OBJECT-TYPE
    SYNTAX      ZeroBasedCounter32
    MAX-ACCESS  read-only
    STATUS      current
    DESCRIPTION
        "For each interval, each data point is associated with a
        value I, I = 1..N where N is the number of data points;
        reportAggrReportStatSumIXSq is the multiplication
        of the data point value squared with the current I.
        This value along with the other statistics
        values allow the calculation of the slope of
        the least-squares line through the data points."
    ::= { reportStatsDataEntry 15 }

reportStatsDataOverflowStatSumIXSq  OBJECT-TYPE
    SYNTAX      ZeroBasedCounter32
    MAX-ACCESS  read-only
    STATUS      current
    DESCRIPTION
        "The number of times the associated
        reportAggrReportStatSumIXSq counter has overflowed.
        Note that this object will only be instantiated if the
        associated reportAggrReportHCStatSumIXSq object is also
        instantiated for a particular dataSource."
    ::= { reportStatsDataEntry 16 }

reportStatsDataHCStatSumIXSq  OBJECT-TYPE
    SYNTAX      ZeroBasedCounter64
    MAX-ACCESS  read-only
    STATUS      current
    DESCRIPTION
        "The high-capacity version of reportAggrReportStatSumIXSq.
        Note that this object will only be instantiated if the
        agent supports High Capacity monitoring for a particular
        dataSource."
    ::= { reportStatsDataEntry 17 }

reportStatsDataStatMetricExt1  OBJECT-TYPE
    SYNTAX      ZeroBasedCounter32
    MAX-ACCESS  read-only
    STATUS      current
    DESCRIPTION
        "The .... for the MetricExt1.
        "
    ::= { reportStatsDataEntry 18 }

reportStatsDataStatMetricExt2  OBJECT-TYPE
    SYNTAX      ZeroBasedCounter32
    MAX-ACCESS  read-only
    STATUS      current
    DESCRIPTION
        "The .... for the MetricExt2.
        "
    ::= { reportStatsDataEntry 19 }

reportStatsDataStatMetricExt3  OBJECT-TYPE
    SYNTAX      ZeroBasedCounter32
    MAX-ACCESS  read-only
    STATUS      current
    DESCRIPTION
        "The .... for the MetricExt3.
        "
    ::= { reportStatsDataEntry 20 }

reportStatsDataStatMetricExt4  OBJECT-TYPE
    SYNTAX      ZeroBasedCounter32
    MAX-ACCESS  read-only
    STATUS      current
    DESCRIPTION
        "The .... for the MetricExt4.
        "
    ::= { reportStatsDataEntry 21 }

reportStatsDataStatMetricExt5  OBJECT-TYPE
    SYNTAX      ZeroBasedCounter32
    MAX-ACCESS  read-only
    STATUS      current
    DESCRIPTION
        "The .... for the MetricExt5.
        "
    ::= { reportStatsDataEntry 22 }



-- The reportCurDataTable
-- [Note: Need to revisit the logic of the reportCurDataTable.]



reportUsrHistoryGroup       OBJECT IDENTIFIER ::= { reportMIBObjects 2 }

--      Then, the reportUsrHistoryGroup assignments are :
--             reportUsrHistoryControlTable    - 1
--             reportUsrHistoryObjectTable     - 2   
--             reportUsrHistoryDataTable       - 3


-- REPORT-MIB Editors' Note: 
-- The reportUsrHistoryGroup is copied from the usrHistory
-- group documented in RMON2 [RFC2021].  We have perserved all of
-- the annotations and object descriptions, as any changes would
-- only diminish the quality of the development.  The only changes
-- made were to the naming of the objects themselves.  Here we have
-- merely prefixed the original names with 'report'.
-- The remainder of this group development is copied from [RFC2021]:

--
-- User History Collection Group (usrHistory)
--
-- The usrHistory group combines mechanisms seen in the alarm and
-- history groups to provide user-specified history collection,
-- utilizing two additional control tables and one additional data
-- table. This function has traditionally been done by NMS
-- applications, via periodic polling.  The usrHistory group allows
-- this task to be offloaded to an RMON probe.
--
-- Data (an ASN.1 INTEGER based object) is collected in the same
-- manner as any history data table (e.g. etherHistoryTable) except
-- that the user specifies the MIB instances to be collected. Objects
-- are collected in bucket-groups, with the intent that all MIB
-- instances in the same bucket-group are collected as atomically as
-- possible by the RMON probe.
--
-- The usrHistoryControlTable is a one-dimensional read-create table.
-- Each row configures a collection of user history buckets, much
-- the same as a historyControlEntry, except that the creation of a
-- row in this table will cause one or more associated instances in
-- the usrHistoryObjectTable to be created. The user specifies the
-- number of bucket elements (rows in the usrHistoryObjectTable)
-- requested, as well as the number of buckets requested.
--
-- The usrHistoryObjectTable is a 2-d read-write table.
-- Each row configures a single MIB instance to be collected.
-- All rows with the same major index constitute a bucket-group.
--
-- The usrHistoryTable is a 3-d read-only table containing
-- the data of associated usrHistoryControlEntries. Each
-- entry represents the value of a single MIB instance
-- during a specific sampling interval (or the rate of
-- change during the interval).
--
-- A sample value is stored in two objects - an absolute value and
-- a status object. This allows numbers from -(2G-1) to +4G to be
-- stored.  The status object also indicates whether a sample is
-- valid. This allows data collection to continue if periodic
-- retrieval of a particular instance fails for any reason.
--
-- Row Creation Order Relationships
--
-- The static nature of the usrHistoryObjectTable creates
-- some row creation/modification issues. The rows in this
-- table need to be set before the associated
-- usrHistoryControlEntry can be activated.
--
-- Note that the usrHistoryObject entries associated with a
-- particular usrHistoryControlEntry are not required to
-- be active before the control entry is activated. However,
-- the usrHistory data entries associated with an inactive
-- usrHistoryObject entry will be inactive (i.e.
-- usrHistoryValStatus == valueNotAvailable).
--

reportUsrHistoryControlTable OBJECT-TYPE
    SYNTAX SEQUENCE OF UsrHistoryControlEntry
    MAX-ACCESS not-accessible
    STATUS current
    DESCRIPTION
        "A list of data-collection configuration entries."
    ::= { reportUsrHistoryGroup 1 }

reportUsrHistoryControlEntry OBJECT-TYPE
    SYNTAX UsrHistoryControlEntry
    MAX-ACCESS not-accessible
    STATUS current
    DESCRIPTION
        "A list of parameters that set up a group of user-defined
        MIB objects to be sampled periodically (called a
        bucket-group).

        For example, an instance of reportUsrHistoryControlInterval
        might be named reportUsrHistoryControlInterval.1"
    INDEX { reportUsrHistoryControlIndex }
    ::= { reportUsrHistoryControlTable 1 }

UsrHistoryControlEntry ::= SEQUENCE {
    reportUsrHistoryControlIndex             Integer32,
    reportUsrHistoryControlObjects           Integer32,
    reportUsrHistoryControlBucketsRequested  Integer32,
    reportUsrHistoryControlBucketsGranted    Integer32,
    reportUsrHistoryControlInterval          Integer32,
    reportUsrHistoryControlOwner             OwnerString,
    reportUsrHistoryControlStatus            RowStatus
}

reportUsrHistoryControlIndex OBJECT-TYPE
    SYNTAX Integer32 (1..65535)
    MAX-ACCESS not-accessible
    STATUS current
    DESCRIPTION
        "An index that uniquely identifies an entry in the
        reportUsrHistoryControlTable.  Each such entry defines a
        set of samples at a particular interval for a specified
        set of MIB instances available from the managed system."
    ::= { reportUsrHistoryControlEntry 1 }

reportUsrHistoryControlObjects OBJECT-TYPE
    SYNTAX Integer32 (1..65535)
    MAX-ACCESS read-create
    STATUS current
    DESCRIPTION
        "The number of MIB objects to be collected
        in the portion of reportUsrHistoryTable associated with this
        reportUsrHistoryControlEntry.

        This object may not be modified if the associated instance
        of reportUsrHistoryControlStatus is equal to active(1)."
    ::= { reportUsrHistoryControlEntry 2 }

reportUsrHistoryControlBucketsRequested OBJECT-TYPE
    SYNTAX Integer32 (1..65535)
    MAX-ACCESS read-create
    STATUS current
    DESCRIPTION
        "The requested number of discrete time intervals
        over which data is to be saved in the part of the
        reportUsrHistoryTable associated with this 
        reportUsrHistoryControlEntry.

        When this object is created or modified, the probe
        should set reportUsrHistoryControlBucketsGranted as closely to
        this object as is possible for the particular probe
        implementation and available resources."
    DEFVAL { 50 }
    ::= { reportUsrHistoryControlEntry 3 }

reportUsrHistoryControlBucketsGranted OBJECT-TYPE
    SYNTAX Integer32 (1..65535)
    MAX-ACCESS read-only
    STATUS current
    DESCRIPTION
        "The number of discrete sampling intervals
        over which data shall be saved in the part of
        the reportUsrHistoryTable associated with this
        reportUsrHistoryControlEntry.

        When the associated reportUsrHistoryControlBucketsRequested
        object is created or modified, the probe should set
        this object as closely to the requested value as is
        possible for the particular  probe implementation and
        available resources.  The probe must not lower this
        value except as a result of a modification to the associated
        reportUsrHistoryControlBucketsRequested object.

        The associated reportUsrHistoryControlBucketsRequested object
        should be set before or at the same time as this object
        to allow the probe to accurately estimate the resources
        required for this reportUsrHistoryControlEntry.

        There will be times when the actual number of buckets
        associated with this entry is less than the value of
        this object.  In this case, at the end of each sampling
        interval, a new bucket will be added to the 
        reportUsrHistoryTable.

        When the number of buckets reaches the value of this object
        and a new bucket is to be added to the reportUsrHistoryTable,
        the oldest bucket associated with this 
        reportUsrHistoryControlEntry shall be deleted by the agent 
        so that the new bucket can be added.

        When the value of this object changes to a value less than
        the current value, entries are deleted from the
        reportUsrHistoryTable associated with this 
        reportUsrHistoryControlEntry.  Enough of the oldest 
        of these entries shall be deleted by the
        agent so that their number remains less than or equal to the
        new value of this object.

        When the value of this object changes to a value greater
        than the current value, the number of associated 
        reportUsrHistory entries may be allowed to grow."
    ::= { reportUsrHistoryControlEntry 4 }


reportUsrHistoryControlInterval OBJECT-TYPE
    SYNTAX Integer32 (1..2147483647)
    MAX-ACCESS read-create
    STATUS current
    DESCRIPTION
        "The interval in seconds over which the data is
        sampled for each bucket in the part of the reportUsrHistory
        table associated with this reportUsrHistoryControlEntry.

        Because the counters in a bucket may overflow at their
        maximum value with no indication, a prudent manager will
        take into account the possibility of overflow in any of
        the associated counters. It is important to consider the
        minimum time in which any counter could overflow on a
        particular media type and set the 
        reportUsrHistoryControlInterval object to a value less 
        than this interval.

        This object may not be modified if the associated
        reportUsrHistoryControlStatus object is equal to active(1)."
    DEFVAL { 1800 }
    ::= { reportUsrHistoryControlEntry 5 }

reportUsrHistoryControlOwner OBJECT-TYPE
    SYNTAX OwnerString
    MAX-ACCESS read-create
    STATUS current
    DESCRIPTION
        "The entity that configured this entry and is
        therefore using the resources assigned to it."
    ::= { reportUsrHistoryControlEntry 6 }

reportUsrHistoryControlStatus OBJECT-TYPE
    SYNTAX RowStatus
    MAX-ACCESS read-create
    STATUS current
    DESCRIPTION
        "The status of this variable history control entry.

        An entry may not exist in the active state unless all
        objects in the entry have an appropriate value.

        If this object is not equal to active(1), all associated
        entries in the reportUsrHistoryTable shall be deleted."
    ::= { reportUsrHistoryControlEntry 7 }


-- Object table

reportUsrHistoryObjectTable OBJECT-TYPE
    SYNTAX SEQUENCE OF UsrHistoryObjectEntry
    MAX-ACCESS not-accessible
    STATUS current
    DESCRIPTION
        "A list of data-collection configuration entries."
    ::= { reportUsrHistoryGroup 2 }

reportUsrHistoryObjectEntry OBJECT-TYPE
    SYNTAX UsrHistoryObjectEntry
    MAX-ACCESS not-accessible
    STATUS current
    DESCRIPTION
        "A list of MIB instances to be sampled periodically.

        Entries in this table are created when an associated
        reportUsrHistoryControlObjects object is created.

        The reportUsrHistoryControlIndex value in the index is
        that of the associated reportUsrHistoryControlEntry.

        For example, an instance of reportUsrHistoryObjectVariable 
        might be reportUsrHistoryObjectVariable.1.3"
    INDEX { reportUsrHistoryControlIndex, reportUsrHistoryObjectIndex }
    ::= { reportUsrHistoryObjectTable 1 }

UsrHistoryObjectEntry ::= SEQUENCE {
    reportUsrHistoryObjectIndex             Integer32,
    reportUsrHistoryObjectVariable          OBJECT IDENTIFIER,
    reportUsrHistoryObjectSampleType        INTEGER
}

reportUsrHistoryObjectIndex OBJECT-TYPE
    SYNTAX Integer32 (1..65535)
    MAX-ACCESS not-accessible
    STATUS current
    DESCRIPTION
        "An index used to uniquely identify an entry in the
        reportUsrHistoryObject table.  Each such entry defines a
        MIB instance to be collected periodically."
    ::= { reportUsrHistoryObjectEntry 1 }


reportUsrHistoryObjectVariable OBJECT-TYPE
    SYNTAX OBJECT IDENTIFIER
    MAX-ACCESS read-create
    STATUS current
    DESCRIPTION
        "The object identifier of the particular variable to be
        sampled.

        Only variables that resolve to an ASN.1 primitive type of
        Integer32 (Integer32, Counter, Gauge, or TimeTicks) may be
        sampled.

        Because SNMP access control is articulated entirely in terms
        of the contents of MIB views, no access control mechanism
        exists that can restrict the value of this object to identify
        only those objects that exist in a particular MIB view.
        Because there is thus no acceptable means of restricting the
        read access that could be obtained through the user history
        mechanism, the probe must only grant write access to this
        object in those views that have read access to all objects on
        the probe.

        During a set operation, if the supplied variable name is not
        available in the selected MIB view, a badValue error must be
        returned.

        This object may not be modified if the associated
        reportUsrHistoryControlStatus object is equal to active(1)."
    ::= { reportUsrHistoryObjectEntry 2 }

reportUsrHistoryObjectSampleType OBJECT-TYPE
    SYNTAX INTEGER {
               absoluteValue(1),
               deltaValue(2)
           }
    MAX-ACCESS read-create
    STATUS current
    DESCRIPTION
        "The method of sampling the selected variable for storage in
        the reportUsrHistoryTable.

        If the value of this object is absoluteValue(1), the value of
        the selected variable will be copied directly into the history
        bucket.

        If the value of this object is deltaValue(2), the value of the
        selected variable at the last sample will be subtracted from
        the current value, and the difference will be stored in the
        history bucket. If the associated reportUsrHistoryObjectVariable
        instance could not be obtained at the previous sample
        interval, then a delta sample is not possible, and the value
        of the associated reportUsrHistoryValStatus object for this
        interval will be valueNotAvailable(1).

        This object may not be modified if the associated
        reportUsrHistoryControlStatus object is equal to active(1)."
    ::= { reportUsrHistoryObjectEntry 3 }


-- data table

reportUsrHistoryTable OBJECT-TYPE
    SYNTAX SEQUENCE OF UsrHistoryEntry
    MAX-ACCESS not-accessible
    STATUS current
    DESCRIPTION
        "A list of user defined history entries."
    ::= { reportUsrHistoryGroup 3 }

reportUsrHistoryEntry OBJECT-TYPE
    SYNTAX UsrHistoryEntry
    MAX-ACCESS not-accessible
    STATUS current
    DESCRIPTION
        "A historical sample of user-defined variables.  This sample
        is associated with the reportUsrHistoryControlEntry which set 
        up the parameters for a regular collection of these samples.

        The reportUsrHistoryControlIndex value in the index identifies
        the reportUsrHistoryControlEntry on whose behalf this entry 
        was created.

        The reportUsrHistoryObjectIndex value in the index identifies
        the reportUsrHistoryObjectEntry on whose behalf this entry 
        was created.

        For example, an instance of reportUsrHistoryAbsValue, which 
        represents the 14th sample of a variable collected as 
        specified by reportUsrHistoryControlEntry.1 and 
        reportUsrHistoryObjectEntry.1.5, would be named 
        reportUsrHistoryAbsValue.1.14.5"
    INDEX { reportUsrHistoryControlIndex, reportUsrHistorySampleIndex,
            reportUsrHistoryObjectIndex }
    ::= { reportUsrHistoryTable 1 }

UsrHistoryEntry ::= SEQUENCE {
    reportUsrHistorySampleIndex   Integer32,
    reportUsrHistoryIntervalStart TimeStamp,
    reportUsrHistoryIntervalEnd   TimeStamp,
    reportUsrHistoryAbsValue      Gauge32,
    reportUsrHistoryValStatus     INTEGER
}

reportUsrHistorySampleIndex OBJECT-TYPE
    SYNTAX     Integer32 (1..2147483647)
    MAX-ACCESS not-accessible
    STATUS     current
    DESCRIPTION
        "An index that uniquely identifies the particular sample this
        entry represents among all samples associated with the same
        reportUsrHistoryControlEntry. This index starts at 1 and
        increases by one as each new sample is taken."
    ::= { reportUsrHistoryEntry 1 }

reportUsrHistoryIntervalStart OBJECT-TYPE
    SYNTAX TimeStamp
    MAX-ACCESS read-only
    STATUS current
    DESCRIPTION
        "The value of sysUpTime at the start of the interval over
        which this sample was measured.  If the probe keeps track of
        the time of day, it should start the first sample of the
        history at a time such that when the next hour of the day
        begins, a sample is started at that instant.

        Note that following this rule may require the probe to delay
        collecting the first sample of the history, as each sample
        must be of the same interval. Also note that the sample which
        is currently being collected is not accessible in this table
        until the end of its interval."
    ::= { reportUsrHistoryEntry 2 }

reportUsrHistoryIntervalEnd OBJECT-TYPE
    SYNTAX TimeStamp
    MAX-ACCESS read-only
    STATUS current
    DESCRIPTION
        "The value of sysUpTime at the end of the interval over which
        this sample was measured."
    ::= { reportUsrHistoryEntry 3 }

reportUsrHistoryAbsValue OBJECT-TYPE
    SYNTAX Gauge32
    MAX-ACCESS read-only
    STATUS current
    DESCRIPTION
        "The absolute value (i.e. unsigned value) of the
        user-specified statistic during the last sampling period. The
        value during the current sampling period is not made available
        until the period is completed.

        To obtain the true value for this sampling interval, the
        associated instance of reportUsrHistoryValStatus must 
        be checked, and reportUsrHistoryAbsValue adjusted as necessary.

        If the MIB instance could not be accessed during the sampling
        interval, then this object will have a value of zero and the
        associated instance of reportUsrHistoryValStatus will be set to
        'valueNotAvailable(1)'."
    ::= { reportUsrHistoryEntry 4 }


reportUsrHistoryValStatus OBJECT-TYPE
    SYNTAX INTEGER {
        valueNotAvailable(1),
        valuePositive(2),
        valueNegative(3)
    }
    MAX-ACCESS read-only
    STATUS current
    DESCRIPTION
        "This object indicates the validity and sign of the data in
        the associated instance of reportUsrHistoryAbsValue.

        If the MIB instance could not be accessed during the sampling
        interval, then 'valueNotAvailable(1)' will be returned.

        If the sample is valid and actual value of the sample is
        greater than or equal to zero then 'valuePositive(2)' is
        returned.

        If the sample is valid and the actual value of the sample is
        less than zero, 'valueNegative(3)' will be returned. The
        associated instance of reportUsrHistoryAbsValue should be
        multiplied by -1 to obtain the true sample value."
    ::= { reportUsrHistoryEntry 5 }

-- REPORT-MIB Editors' Note:  This ends the copy of definitions from
-- the usrHistory group from RMON2 [RFC 2021]. 



--
-- Notifications
--

-- Note:  What notifications do we want for this MIB?
--        Checkout what is done in the APM-MIB for Notifications?


--
-- Compliance Statements
--

-- [Note: Current thoughts on Conformance follow:
--    Mandatory for Stats will include no extensions, 
--    or high capacity objects.  
--    Hence, the reports will have only the hard-coded statistics.
--    Optional for Stats will be extensions definition table and high 
--    capacity objects.
--
--    Mandatory for UsrHistory will include all.]


reportCompliances  OBJECT IDENTIFIER ::= { reportMIBConformance 1 }
reportMIBGroups    OBJECT IDENTIFIER ::= { reportMIBConformance 2 }

reportStatsBasicCompliance  MODULE-COMPLIANCE
   STATUS current
   DESCRIPTION "The Stats basic implementation requirements for 
                managed network entities that implement
                the REPORT process." 
   MODULE  -- this module
   MANDATORY-GROUPS {reportStatsCapabilitiesBaseObjectsGroup,
                     reportStatsControlBaseObjectsGroup,
                     reportStatsDataBaseObjectsGroup }
::= { reportCompliances 1 }  

reportStatsHCCompliance MODULE-COMPLIANCE
   STATUS current
   DESCRIPTION "The HC implementation requirements for
                managed network entities that implement
                the REPORT process."
   MODULE  -- this module
   MANDATORY-GROUPS {reportStatsCapabilitiesBaseObjectsGroup,
                     reportStatsControlBaseObjectsGroup,
                     reportStatsDataBaseObjectsGroup,
                     reportStatsDataHCObjectsGroup }
::= { reportCompliances 2 }  

reportStatsExtendedMetricsCompliance MODULE-COMPLIANCE
   STATUS current
   DESCRIPTION "The extended metrics implementation requirements for
                managed network entities that implement
                the REPORT process."
   MODULE  -- this module
   MANDATORY-GROUPS {reportStatsCapabilitiesBaseObjectsGroup,
                     reportStatsControlBaseObjectsGroup,
                     reportStatsDataBaseObjectsGroup,
                     reportStatsExtendedMetricsCapabilitiesObjectsGroup,
                     reportStatsExtendedMetricsControlObjectsGroup,
                     reportStatsExtendedMetricsDataObjectsGroup }
::= { reportCompliances 3 }  

reportUsrHistoryBasicCompliance  MODULE-COMPLIANCE
   STATUS current
   DESCRIPTION "The Stats basic implementation requirements for 
                managed network entities that implement
                the REPORT process." 
   MODULE  -- this module
   MANDATORY-GROUPS {reportStatsCapabilitiesBaseObjectsGroup,
                     reportUsrHistoryControlBaseObjectsGroup,
                     reportUsrHistoryObjectIDBaseObjectsGroup,
                     reportUsrHistoryDataBaseObjectsGroup }
::= { reportCompliances 4 }  



-- Units of Conformance

reportStatsCapabilitiesBaseObjectsGroup OBJECT-GROUP
   OBJECTS {
            reportClockResolution,
            reportClockMaxSkew,
            reportClockSource
   }
   STATUS  current
   DESCRIPTION
      "Set of REPORT configuration objects implemented
       in this module."
::= { reportMIBGroups 1 }

reportStatsControlBaseObjectsGroup OBJECT-GROUP
   OBJECTS {
            reportStatsControlInterval,
            reportStatsControlBinInterval,
            reportStatsControlPriObjID,
            reportStatsControlReqReports,
            reportStatsControlGrantedReports,
            reportStatsControlStartTime,
            reportStatsControlReportNumber,
            reportStatsControlInsertsDenied,
            reportStatsControlOwner,
            reportStatsControlStorageType,
            reportStatsControlStatus
   }
   STATUS  current
   DESCRIPTION
      "Set of REPORT Stats Control base objects implemented
       in this module."
::= { reportMIBGroups 2 }

reportStatsDataBaseObjectsGroup  OBJECT-GROUP
   OBJECTS {
            reportStatsDataServerAddress,
            reportStatsDataStatN,
            reportStatsDataStatSumX,
            reportStatsDataOverflowStatSumX,
            reportStatsDataStatMaximum,
            reportStatsDataStatMinimum,
            reportStatsDataStatSumSq,
            reportStatsDataOverflowStatSumSq,
            reportStatsDataStatSumIX,
            reportStatsDataOverflowStatSumIX,
            reportStatsDataStatSumIXSq,
            reportStatsDataOverflowStatSumIXSq
   }
   STATUS  current
   DESCRIPTION
      "Set of REPORT state objects implemented
       in this module."
::= { reportMIBGroups 3 }
reportStatsDataHCObjectsGroup  OBJECT-GROUP
   OBJECTS {
            reportStatsDataHCStatSumX,
            reportStatsDataHCStatSumSq,
            reportStatsDataHCStatSumIX,
            reportStatsDataHCStatSumIXSq
   }
   STATUS  current
   DESCRIPTION
      "Set of REPORT state objects implemented
       in this module."
::= { reportMIBGroups 4 }

reportStatsExtendedMetricsCapabilitiesObjectsGroup  OBJECT-GROUP
   OBJECTS {
            reportMetricExtDefType,
            reportMetricExtDefName,
            reportMetricExtDefOperation,
            reportMetricExtDefReference,
            reportMetricDirLastChange
   }
   STATUS  current
   DESCRIPTION
      "Set of REPORT state objects implemented
       in this module."
::= { reportMIBGroups 5 }

reportStatsExtendedMetricsControlObjectsGroup  OBJECT-GROUP
   OBJECTS {
            reportStatsControlSecObj1ID,
            reportStatsControlSecObj2ID,
            reportStatsControlSecObj3ID,
            reportStatsControlSecObj4ID,
            reportStatsControlSecObj5ID,
            reportStatsControlMetricExt1,
            reportStatsControlMetricExt2,
            reportStatsControlMetricExt3,
            reportStatsControlMetricExt4,
            reportStatsControlMetricExt5
   }
   STATUS  current
   DESCRIPTION
      "Set of REPORT state objects implemented
       in this module."
::= { reportMIBGroups 6 }

reportStatsExtendedMetricsDataObjectsGroup  OBJECT-GROUP
   OBJECTS {
            reportStatsDataStatMetricExt1,
            reportStatsDataStatMetricExt2,
            reportStatsDataStatMetricExt3,
            reportStatsDataStatMetricExt4,
            reportStatsDataStatMetricExt5
   }
   STATUS  current
   DESCRIPTION
      "Set of REPORT state objects implemented
       in this module."
::= { reportMIBGroups 7 }

reportUsrHistoryControlBaseObjectsGroup  OBJECT-GROUP
   OBJECTS {
            reportUsrHistoryControlObjects,
            reportUsrHistoryControlBucketsRequested,
            reportUsrHistoryControlBucketsGranted,
            reportUsrHistoryControlInterval,
            reportUsrHistoryControlOwner,
            reportUsrHistoryControlStatus
   }
   STATUS  current
   DESCRIPTION
      "Set of REPORT state objects implemented
       in this module."
::= { reportMIBGroups 8 }

reportUsrHistoryObjectIDBaseObjectsGroup  OBJECT-GROUP
   OBJECTS {
            reportUsrHistoryObjectVariable,
            reportUsrHistoryObjectSampleType
   }
   STATUS  current
   DESCRIPTION
      "Set of REPORT state objects implemented
       in this module."
::= { reportMIBGroups 9 }

reportUsrHistoryDataBaseObjectsGroup  OBJECT-GROUP
   OBJECTS {
            reportUsrHistoryIntervalStart,
            reportUsrHistoryIntervalEnd,
            reportUsrHistoryAbsValue,
            reportUsrHistoryValStatus
   }
   STATUS  current
   DESCRIPTION
      "Set of REPORT state objects implemented
       in this module."
::= { reportMIBGroups 10 }


END

	]]></artwork>
      </figure>
    </section>

    <section title="Security Considerations">
      <!--[TODO] Remember to consider security from the start. -->

      <t>[TODO] Each specification that defines one or more MIB modules MUST
      contain a section that discusses security considerations relevant to
      those modules. This section MUST be patterned after the latest approved
      template (available at http://www.ops.ietf.org/mib-security.html).
      Remember that the objective is not to blindly copy text from the
      template, but rather to think and evaluate the risks/vulnerabilities and
      then state/document the result of this evaluation.</t>

      <t></t>

      <t>[TODO] if you have any read-write and/or read-create objects, please
      include the following boilerplate paragraph.</t>

      <t>There are a number of management objects defined in this MIB module
      with a MAX-ACCESS clause of read-write and/or read-create. Such objects
      may be considered sensitive or vulnerable in some network environments.
      The support for SET operations in a non-secure environment without
      proper protection can have a negative effect on network operations.
      These are the tables and objects and their
      sensitivity/vulnerability:</t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>[TODO] writable MIB objects that could be especially disruptive
          if abused MUST be explicitly listed by name and the associated
          security risks MUST be spelled out; RFC 2669 has a very good
          example.</t>

          <t>[TODO] list the writable tables and objects and state why they
          are sensitive.</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>[TODO] else if there are no read-write objects in your MIB module,
      use the following boilerplate paragraph.</t>

      <t>There are no management objects defined in this MIB module that have
      a MAX-ACCESS clause of read-write and/or read-create. So, if this MIB
      module is implemented correctly, then there is no risk that an intruder
      can alter or create any management objects of this MIB module via direct
      SNMP SET operations.</t>

      <t>[TODO] if you have any sensitive readable objects, please include the
      following boilerplate paragraph.</t>

      <t>Some of the readable objects in this MIB module (i.e., objects with a
      MAX-ACCESS other than not-accessible) may be considered sensitive or
      vulnerable in some network environments. It is thus important to control
      even GET and/or NOTIFY access to these objects and possibly to even
      encrypt the values of these objects when sending them over the network
      via SNMP. These are the tables and objects and their
      sensitivity/vulnerability: <list style="symbols">
          <t>[TODO] you must explicitly list by name any readable objects that
          are sensitive or vulnerable and the associated security risks MUST
          be spelled out (for instance, if they might reveal customer
          information or violate personal privacy laws such as those of the
          European Union if exposed to unauthorized parties)</t>

          <t>[TODO] list the tables and objects and state why they are
          sensitive.</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>[TODO] discuss what security the protocol used to carry the
      information should have. The following three boilerplate paragraphs
      should not be changed without very good reason. Changes will almost
      certainly require justification during IESG review.</t>

      <t>SNMP versions prior to SNMPv3 did not include adequate security. Even
      if the network itself is secure (for example by using IPSec), even then,
      there is no control as to who on the secure network is allowed to access
      and GET/SET (read/change/create/delete) the objects in this MIB
      module.</t>

      <t>It is RECOMMENDED that implementers consider the security features as
      provided by the SNMPv3 framework (see <xref target="RFC3410"></xref>,
      section 8), including full support for the SNMPv3 cryptographic
      mechanisms (for authentication and privacy).</t>

      <t>Further, deployment of SNMP versions prior to SNMPv3 is NOT
      RECOMMENDED. Instead, it is RECOMMENDED to deploy SNMPv3 and to enable
      cryptographic security. It is then a customer/operator responsibility to
      ensure that the SNMP entity giving access to an instance of this MIB
      module is properly configured to give access to the objects only to
      those principals (users) that have legitimate rights to indeed GET or
      SET (change/create/delete) them.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>[TODO] In order to comply with IESG policy as set forth in
      http://www.ietf.org/ID-Checklist.html, every Internet-Draft that is
      submitted to the IESG for publication MUST contain an IANA
      Considerations section. The requirements for this section vary depending
      what actions are required of the IANA. see RFC4181 section 3.5 for more
      information on writing an IANA clause for a MIB module document.</t>

      <t>[TODO] select an option and provide the necessary details.</t>

      <t>Option #1:</t>

      <figure>
        <preamble></preamble>

        <artwork><![CDATA[
     The MIB module in this document uses the following IANA-assigned
     OBJECT IDENTIFIER values recorded in the SMI Numbers registry: 
      
     Descriptor        OBJECT IDENTIFIER value
     ----------        -----------------------

     sampleMIB  { mib-2 XXX }
      	]]></artwork>

        <postamble></postamble>
      </figure>

      <t></t>

      <t>Option #2:</t>

      <t>Editor's Note (to be removed prior to publication): the IANA is
      requested to assign a value for "XXX" under the 'mib-2' subtree and to
      record the assignment in the SMI Numbers registry. When the assignment
      has been made, the RFC Editor is asked to replace "XXX" (here and in the
      MIB module) with the assigned value and to remove this note.</t>

      <t>Note well: prior to official assignment by the IANA, a draft document
      MUST use placeholders (such as "XXX" above) rather than actual numbers.
      See RFC4181 Section 4.5 for an example of how this is done in a draft
      MIB module.</t>

      <t>Option #3:</t>

      <!-- If no IANA work is required, an explicit note must be included.-->

      <t>This memo includes no request to IANA.</t>
    </section>

    <!-- The Author's Addresses section will be generated 
         automatically by XML2RFC from the front information -->

    <section title="Contributors">
      <t>This MIB document uses the template authored by D. Harrington which
      is based on contributions from the MIB Doctors, especially Juergen
      Schoenwaelder, Dave Perkins, C.M.Heard and Randy Presuhn.</t>

      <t><!--[TODO] Change this section to mention contributors to your 
             MIB module document.--></t>
    </section>

    <section title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>We would like to thank Bert Wijnen and Andy Bierman for
         pointing out the existence of the usrHistory group within
         RMON2.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <!-- References Section -->

    <!-- Section 4.7f of [RFC2223bis] specifies the requirements for the
   references sections.  In particular, there MUST be separate lists of
   normative and informative references, each in a separate section.
   The style SHOULD follow that of recently published RFCs.

   The standard MIB boilerplate available at
   http://www.ops.ietf.org/mib-boilerplate.html includes lists of
   normative and informative references that MUST appear in all IETF
   specifications that contain MIB modules.  If items from other MIB
   modules appear in an IMPORTS statement in the Definitions section,
   then the specifications containing those MIB modules MUST be included
   in the list of normative references.  When items are imported from an
   IANA-maintained MIB module the corresponding normative reference
   SHALL point to the on-line version of that MIB module.  It is the
   policy of the RFC Editor that all references must be cited in the
   text;  such citations MUST appear in the overview section where
   documents containing imported definitions (other those already
   mentioned in the MIB boilerplate) are required to be mentioned (cf.
   Section 3.2).

In general, each normative reference SHOULD point to the most recent
version of the specification in question.
-->

    <references title="Normative References">

      &rfc2863;

      &rfc3418;

      <!--  <t>[TODO] rfc2119, 2578, 2579, and 2580 are required to support MIB
      module boilerplate text.</t> -->

      &rfc2119;

      &rfc2578;

      &rfc2579;

      &rfc2580;

      <!--  <t>[TODO]: Add your own normative references.</t>-->
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <!-- <t>[TODO] RFC3410 is required to support the boilerplate text.</t>-->

      &rfc3410;

      <!-- <t>[TODO] Add your own informative references</t>-->
      &rfc1757;

      &rfc2021;

      &smf;


    </references>

    <!--
<section anchor="appendix" title="Appendix A">
	<t>You can add appendices just as regular sections, the only
difference is that they go under "back" element, and get letters 
instead of numbers</t>
</section>
-->

    <section title="Change Log ">
      <t>Changes from -00 to -01 draft.</t>

      <t>
        <list style="numbers">
          <t>Added (copied) the usrHistory group from RMON2 into the REPORT-MIB.</t>
          <t>Restructured the MIB to account for the inclusion of the
             reportUsrHistoryGroup.</t>
          <t>Dropped the reportCurReportsTable as this did not make sense within the
             context of the REPORT-MIB.</t>
          <t>Added the Compliance and Conformance material.  Defined several Compliance
             Groups to all for base implementations of the REPORT-MIB for only statistical
             reports, for only historical reports or for both.  Allow for enhanced
             implementations to address higher capacity issues and 
             extension to metric reporting for statistical reporting.</t>
          <t>Ran the MIB through the smilint checker and in the process corrected numerous
             typos, ommisions, TEXTUAL CONVENTIONS, IMPORTS, etc.</t>
          <t>Updated main text to reflect changes.</t>
        </list>
      </t>
    </section>

    <section title="Open Issues">
      <t>This section contains the set of open issues related to the
      development and design of the REPORT-MIB. This section will not be present
      in the final version of the MIB and will be removed once all the open
      issues have been resolved.</t>

      <t>
        <list style="numbers">
          <t>Specify the set of metrics for default support.</t>

          <t>Clean up the Table indexing.  Specifically, what uniquely defines a report?</t>

          <t>Complete notification group.</t>

          <t>Complete conformance group.</t>

          <t>Work on the relationship to other MIBs, IF-MIB, NHDP-MIB.</t>

          <t>Update the text of the document to reflect the final state of the MIB.</t>

          <t>Identify all objects requiring non-volatile storage in their
          DESCRIPTION clauses.</t>

          <t>Incorporate parameter relationship conditions into their
          DESCRIPTION clauses.</t>

          <t>Complete the security analysis and section.</t>

          <t>Cleanup all the [TODOs] from the MIB template.</t>
        </list>
      </t>
    </section>

    <section title="">
       <figure>
          <preamble />

             <artwork><![CDATA[
***************************************************************
* Note to the RFC Editor (to be removed prior to publication) *
*                                                             *
* 1) The reference to RFCXXXX within the DESCRIPTION clauses  *
* of the MIB module point to this draft and are to be         *
* assigned by the RFC Editor.                                 *
*                                                             *
* 2) The reference to RFCXXX2 throughout this document point  *
* to the current draft-ietf-manet-report-xx.txt.  This        *
* need to be replaced with the XXX RFC number.                *
*                                                             *
***************************************************************
              ]]></artwork>
           <postamble></postamble>
        </figure>
     </section>

  </back>
</rfc>
