<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc tocindent="no"?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc tocindent="no"?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY rfc2119 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc5996 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5996.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc3526 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3526.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc5114 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5114.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc5903 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5903.xml">
]>
<rfc docName="draft-ietf-ipsecme-dh-checks-01" ipr="trust200902" category="std" updates="5996">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="DH Tests">Additional Diffie-Hellman Tests for IKEv2</title>
    <author initials="Y." surname="Sheffer" fullname="Yaron Sheffer">
      <organization abbrev="Porticor">Porticor</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>10 Yirmiyahu St.</street>
          <city>Ramat HaSharon</city>
          <code>47298</code>
          <country>Israel</country>
        </postal>
        <email>yaronf.ietf@gmail.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author initials="S." surname="Fluhrer" fullname="Scott Fluhrer">
      <organization abbrev="Cisco">Cisco Systems</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>1414 Massachusetts Ave.</street>
          <city>Boxborough</city>
          <region>MA</region>
          <code>01719</code>
          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>
        <email>sfluhrer@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date month="April" year="2013"/>
    <workgroup>
ipsecme
</workgroup>
    <keyword>Internet-Draft</keyword>
    <abstract>
      <t>
This document adds a small number of mandatory tests required for the secure operation of IKEv2 with elliptic curve groups. No change is required to IKE implementations that use modular exponential groups, other than a few rarely used so-called DSA groups. This document updates the IKEv2 protocol, RFC 5996.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>
  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction" anchor="d1e350">
      <t>
IKEv2 <xref target="RFC5996"/> consists of the establishment of a shared secret using the Diffie-Hellman (DH) protocol, followed by authentication of the two peers. Existing implementations typically use modular exponential (MODP) DH groups, such as those defined in <xref target="RFC3526"/>.</t>
      <t>
IKEv2 does not require that any tests be performed by a peer receiving a public Diffie-Hellman key from the other peer. This is fine for the common case of MODP groups. For other DH groups, when peers reuse DH values across multiple IKE sessions, the lack of tests by the recipient results in a potential vulnerability (see  <xref target="sub_DH_Key_Reuse"/> for more details). In particular, this is true for elliptic curve groups whose use is becoming ever more popular. This document defines such tests for several types of DH groups.</t>
      <section title="Conventions used in this document" anchor="d1e377">
        <t>
The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in <xref target="RFC2119"/>.</t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section title="Group Membership Tests" anchor="d1e393">
      <t>
This section describes the tests that need to be performed by IKE peers receiving a Key Exchange (KE) payload. The tests are RECOMMENDED for all implementations, but only REQUIRED for those that reuse DH secret keys (as defined in <xref target="RFC5996"/>, Sec. 2.12). The tests are listed here according to the DH group being used.</t>
      <section title="Regular MODP Groups" anchor="sub_Regular_MODP_Groups_">
        <t>
These are currently the most commonly used groups; all these groups have the property that (p-1)/2 is also prime; this section applies to any such MODP group. Each recipient MUST verify that the peer's public value r is in the legal range (1 &lt; r &lt; p-1). According to <xref target="Menezes"/>, Sec 2.2, even with this check there remains the possibility of leaking a single bit of the secret exponent when DH keys are reused; this amount of leakage is insignificant.</t>
        <t>
See  <xref target="sec_IANA_Considerations"/> for the specific groups covered by this section.</t>
      </section>
      <section title="MODP Groups with Small Subgroups" anchor="sub_MODP_Groups_with">
        <t><xref target="RFC5114"/> defines modular exponential groups with small subgroups; these are modular exponential groups with comparatively small subgroups, and all have (p-1)/2 composite. Sec. 2.1 of <xref target="Menezes"/> describes some informational leakage from a small subgroup attack on these groups, if the DH private value is reused. </t>
        <t>
This leakage can be prevented if the recipient performs a test on the peer's public value, however this test is expensive (approximately as expensive as what reusing DH private values saves). In addition, the NIST standard <xref target="NIST-800-56A"/> requires that test (see section 5.6.2.4), hence anyone needing to conform to that standard will need to implement the test anyway.</t>
        <t>
Because of the above, the IKE implementation MUST choose between one of the following two options:</t>
        <t>
          <list style="symbols">
            <t>
It MUST check both that the peer's public value is in range (1 &lt; r &lt; p-1) and that r**q = 1 mod p (where q is the size of the subgroup, as listed in the RFC). DH private values MAY then be reused. This option is appropriate if conformance to <xref target="NIST-800-56A"/> is required.</t>
            <t>
It MUST NOT reuse DH private values (that is, the DH private value for each DH exchange MUST be generated from a fresh output of a cryptographically secure random number generator), and it MUST check that the peer's public value is in range (1 &lt; r &lt; p-1). This option is more appropriate if conformance to <xref target="NIST-800-56A"/> is not required. </t>
          </list>
        </t>
        <t>
See  <xref target="sec_IANA_Considerations"/> for the specific groups covered by this section.</t>
      </section>
      <section title="Elliptic Curve Groups" anchor="sub_Elliptic_Curve_Groups_">
        <t>
IKEv2 can be used with elliptic curve groups defined over a field GF(p) <xref target="RFC5903"/> <xref target="RFC5114"/>. According to <xref target="Menezes"/>, Sec. 2.3, there is some informational leakage possible. A receiving peer MUST check that its peer's public value is valid; that is, it is not the point-at-infinity, and that the x and y parameters from the peer's public value satisfy the curve equation, that is, y**2 = x**3 + ax + b mod p (where for groups 19, 20, 21, a=-3, and all other values of a, b and p for the group are listed in the RFC).</t>
        <t>
See  <xref target="sec_IANA_Considerations"/> for the specific groups covered by this section.</t>
      </section>
      <section title="Transition" anchor="d1e527">
        <t>
Existing implementations of IKEv2 with ECDH groups MAY be modified to include the tests described in the current document, if they do not reuse DH keys with multiple peers. The tests can be considered as sanity checks, and will prevent the code having to handle inputs that it may not have been designed to handle.</t>
        <t>
ECDH implementations that do reuse DH keys MUST be enhanced to include the above tests.</t>
      </section>
      <section title="Protocol Behavior" anchor="sub_Protocol_Behavior">
        <t>
The recipient of a DH public key that fails one of the above tests can assume that the sender either is truly malicious or else it has a bug in its implementation. The recipient MAY respond with an unauthenticated INVALID_SYNTAX notification, and MUST immediately drop the IKE SA.</t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section title="Security Considerations" anchor="d1e550">
      <t>
This entire document is concerned with the IKEv2 security protocol and the need to harden it in some cases.</t>
      <section title="DH Key Reuse and Multiple Peers" anchor="sub_DH_Key_Reuse">
        <t>
This section describes the attack prevented by the tests defined here.</t>
        <t>
Suppose that IKE peer Alice maintains IKE security associations with peers Bob and Eve. Alice uses the same secret ECDH key for both SAs, which is allowed with some restrictions. If Alice does not implement these tests, Eve will be able to send a malformed public key, which would allow her to efficiently determine Alice's secret key (as described in Sec. 2 of <xref target="Menezes"/>). Since the key is shared, Eve will be able to obtain Alice's shared IKE SA key with Bob.</t>
      </section>
      <section title="Groups not covered by this RFC" anchor="d1e580">
        <t>
There are a number of group types that are not specifically addressed by this RFC. A document that defines such a group MUST describe the tests required by that group.</t>
        <t>
One specific type of group would be an even-characteristic elliptic curve group. Now, these curves have cofactors greater than 1; this leads to a possibility of some information leakage. There are several ways to address this information leakage, such as performing a test analogous to the test in section 2.2, or adjusting the ECDH operation to avoid this leakage (such as "ECC CDH", where the shared secret really is hxyG). Because the appropriate test depends on how the group is defined, we cannot document it in advance.</t>
      </section>
      <section title="Behavior Upon Test Failure" anchor="d1e592">
        <t>
The behavior recommended in  <xref target="sub_Protocol_Behavior"/> is in line with generic error treatment during the IKE_SA_INIT exchange, Sec. 2.21.1 of <xref target="RFC5996"/>. The sender is not required to send back an error notification, and the recipient cannot depend on this notification because it is unauthenticated. Thus, the notification is only useful to debug implementation errors.</t>
        <t>
On the other hand, the error notification is secure, in the sense that no secret information is leaked. All IKEv2 Diffie-Hellman groups are publicly known, and none of the tests defined here depend on any secret key. In fact the tests can all be performed by an eavesdropper.</t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section title="IANA Considerations" anchor="sec_IANA_Considerations">
      <t>
This document requests that IANA should add a column named “Recipient Tests” to the IKEv2 DH Group Transform IDs Registry <xref target="IANA-DH-Registry"/>.</t>
      <t>
This column should initially be populated as per the following table.</t>
      <texttable>
        <ttcol align="center">
Number</ttcol>
        <ttcol align="center">
Recipient Tests</ttcol>
        <c>
1, 2, 5, 14, 15, 16, 17, 18</c>
        <c>
[current], Sec. 2.1</c>
        <c>
22, 23, 24</c>
        <c>
[current], Sec. 2.2</c>
        <c>
19, 20, 21, 25, 26</c>
        <c>
[current], Sec. 2.3</c>
      </texttable>
      <t>
Note to RFC Editor: please replace [current] by the RFC number assigned to this document.</t>
      <t>
Future documents that define new DH groups for IKEv2 are REQUIRED to provide this information for each new group, possibly by referring to the current document.</t>
    </section>
    <section title="Acknowledgements" anchor="d1e696">
      <t>
We would like to thank Dan Harkins who initially raised this issue on the ipsec mailing list. Thanks to Tero Kivinen and Rene Struik for their useful comments.</t>
      <t>
The document was prepared using the lyx2rfc tool, created by Nico Williams.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>
  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">&rfc2119;
&rfc5996;
</references>
    <references title="Informative References">&rfc3526;
&rfc5114;
&rfc5903;

<reference anchor="NIST-800-56A"><front><title>Recommendation for Pair-Wise Key Establishment Schemes Using Discrete Logarithm Cryptography (Revised)</title><author><organization>National Institute of Standards and Technology (NIST) </organization></author><date month="March" year="2007"/></front><seriesInfo name="NIST" value="PUB 800-56A"/></reference>
<reference anchor="Menezes" target="http://www.cacr.math.uwaterloo.ca/techreports/2008/cacr2008-24.pdf"><front><title>On Reusing Ephemeral Keys In Diffie-Hellman Key Agreement Protocols</title><author initials="A." surname="Menezes" fullname="A. Menezes"><organization/></author><author initials="B." surname="Ustaoglu" fullname="B. Ustaoglu"><organization/></author><date year="2008" month="December"/></front></reference> 
<reference anchor="IANA-DH-Registry" target="http://www.iana.org/assignments/ikev2-parameters/ikev2-parameters.xml#ikev2-parameters-8"><front><title>Internet Key Exchange Version 2 (IKEv2) Parameters, Transform Type 4 - Diffie-Hellman Group Transform IDs</title><author><organization>IANA</organization></author><date month="Jan." year="2005"/></front></reference>
</references>
    <section title="Appendix: Change Log" anchor="d1e790">
      <t>
Note to RFC Editor: please remove this section before publication.</t>
      <section title="-01" anchor="d1e799">
        <t>
          <list style="symbols">
            <t>
Corrected an author's name that was misspelled.</t>
            <t>
Added recipient behavior if a test fails, and the related security considerations.</t>
          </list>
        </t>
      </section>
      <section title="-00" anchor="d1e812">
        <t>
          <list style="symbols">
            <t>
First WG document.</t>
            <t>
Clarified IANA actions.</t>
            <t>
Discussion of potential future groups not covered here.</t>
            <t>
Clarification re: practicality of recipient tests for DSA groups.</t>
          </list>
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>
  </back>
</rfc>
