<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!-- This template is for creating an Internet Draft using xml2rfc,
     which is available here: http://xml.resource.org. -->
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!-- One method to get references from the online citation libraries.
     There has to be one entity for each item to be referenced. 
     An alternate method (rfc include) is described in the references. -->
<!ENTITY RFC2119 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC2629 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2629.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3552 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3552.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.narten-iana-considerations-rfc2434bis SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.narten-iana-considerations-rfc2434bis.xml">
<!--
<!ENTITY I-D.draft-mcgrew-standby-cipher SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.draft-mcgrew-standby-cipher-00.xml">
-->
]>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<!-- used by XSLT processors -->
<!-- For a complete list and description of processing instructions (PIs), 
     please see http://xml.resource.org/authoring/README.html. -->
<!-- Below are generally applicable Processing Instructions (PIs) that most I-Ds might want to use.
     (Here they are set differently than their defaults in xml2rfc v1.32) -->
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<!-- give errors regarding ID-nits and DTD validation -->
<!-- control the table of contents (ToC) -->
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<!-- generate a ToC -->
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<!-- the number of levels of subsections in ToC. default: 3 -->
<!-- control references -->
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<!-- use symbolic references tags, i.e, [RFC2119] instead of [1] -->
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<!-- sort the reference entries alphabetically -->
<!-- control vertical white space 
     (using these PIs as follows is recommended by the RFC Editor) -->
<?rfc compact="no"?>
<!-- do not start each main section on a new page -->
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<!-- keep one blank line between list items -->
<!-- end of list of popular I-D processing instructions -->
<rfc category="std" docName="draft-ietf-ipsecme-esp-ah-reqts-00"
     ipr="trust200902">
  <!-- category values: std, bcp, info, exp, and historic
     ipr values: full3667, noModification3667, noDerivatives3667
     you can add the attributes updates="NNNN" and obsoletes="NNNN" 
     they will automatically be output with "(if approved)" -->

  <!-- ***** FRONT MATTER ***** -->

  <front>
    <!-- The abbreviated title is used in the page header - it is only necessary if the 
         full title is longer than 39 characters -->

    <title abbrev="Requirements and Guidance for ESP and AH">Cryptographic
    Algorithm Implementation Requirements and Usage Guidance for Encapsulating
    Security Payload (ESP) and Authentication Header (AH)</title>

    <!-- add 'role="editor"' below for the editors if appropriate -->

    <!-- Another author who claims to be an editor -->

    <author fullname="David McGrew" initials="D." surname="McGrew">
      <organization>Cisco Systems</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>13600 Dulles Technology Drive</street>

          <!-- Reorder these if your country does things differently -->

          <city>Herndon</city>

          <region>Virginia</region>

          <code>20171</code>

          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>

        <phone>408 525 8651</phone>

        <email>mcgrew@cisco.com</email>

        <!-- uri and facsimile elements may also be added -->
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Wajdi Feghali" initials="W." surname="Feghali">
      <organization>Intel Corp.</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>75 Reed Road</street>

          <!-- Reorder these if your country does things differently -->

          <city>Hudson</city>

          <region>Massachusetts</region>

          <code/>

          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>

        <phone/>

        <email>wajdi.k.feghali@intel.com</email>

        <!-- uri and facsimile elements may also be added -->
      </address>
    </author>

    <date day="11" month="March" year="2013"/>

    <!-- If the month and year are both specified and are the current ones, xml2rfc will fill 
         in the current day for you. If only the current year is specified, xml2rfc will fill 
	 in the current day and month for you. If the year is not the current one, it is 
	 necessary to specify at least a month (xml2rfc assumes day="1" if not specified for the 
	 purpose of calculating the expiry date).  With drafts it is normally sufficient to 
	 specify just the year. -->

    <!-- Meta-data Declarations -->

    <area>General</area>

    <workgroup>Internet Engineering Task Force</workgroup>

    <!-- WG name at the upperleft corner of the doc,
         IETF is fine for individual submissions.  
	 If this element is not present, the default is "Network Working Group",
         which is used by the RFC Editor as a nod to the history of the IETF. -->

    <keyword>template</keyword>

    <!-- Keywords will be incorporated into HTML output
         files in a meta tag but they have no effect on text or nroff
         output. If you submit your draft to the RFC Editor, the
         keywords will be used for the search engine. -->

    <abstract>
      <t>This Internet Draft is standards track proposal to update to
      the Cryptographic Algorithm Implementation Requirements for ESP
      and AH; it also adds usage guidance to help in the selection of
      these algorithms. </t>

      <t>The Encapsulating Security Payload (ESP) and Authentication Header
      (AH) protocols makes use of various cryptographic algorithms to provide
      confidentiality and/or data origin authentication to protected data
      communications in the IP Security (IPsec) architecture. To ensure
      interoperability between disparate implementations, the IPsec standard
      specifies a set of mandatory-to- implement algorithms. This document
      specifies the current set of mandatory-to-implement algorithms for ESP
      and AH, specifies algorithms that should be implemented because they may
      be promoted to mandatory at some future time, and also recommends
      against the implementation of some obsolete algorithms. Usage guidance
      is also provided to help the user of ESP and AH best achieve their
      security goals through appropriate choices of cryptographic algorithms.
      </t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>The Encapsulating Security Payload (ESP) <xref target="RFC4303"/> and
      the Authentication Header (AH) <xref target="RFC4302"/> are the
      mechanisms for applying cryptographic protection to data being sent over
      an IPsec Security Association (SA) <xref target="RFC4301"/>. </t>

      <t>To ensure interoperability between disparate implementations, it is
      necessary to specify a set of mandatory-to-implement algorithms. This
      ensures that there is at least one algorithm that all implementations
      will have in common. This document specifies the current set of
      mandatory-to-implement algorithms for ESP and AH, specifies algorithms
      that should be implemented because they may be promoted to mandatory at
      some future time, and also recommends against the implementation of some
      obsolete algorithms. Usage guidance is also provided to help the user of
      ESP and AH best achieve their security goals through appropriate choices
      of mechanisms. </t>

      <t>The nature of cryptography is that new algorithms surface
      continuously and existing algorithms are continuously attacked. An
      algorithm believed to be strong today may be demonstrated to be weak
      tomorrow. Given this, the choice of mandatory-to-implement algorithm
      should be conservative so as to minimize the likelihood of it being
      compromised quickly. Thought should also be given to performance
      considerations as many uses of IPsec will be in environments where
      performance is a concern. </t>

      <t>The ESP and AH mandatory-to-implement algorithm(s) may need to change
      over time to adapt to new developments in cryptography. For this reason,
      the specification of the mandatory-to-implement algorithms is not
      included in the main IPsec, ESP, or AH specifications, but is instead
      placed in this document. Ideally, the mandatory-to-implement algorithm
      of tomorrow should already be available in most implementations of IPsec
      by the time it is made mandatory. To facilitate this, this document
      identifies such algorithms, as they are known today. There is no
      guarantee that the algorithms that we believe today may be mandatory in
      the future will in fact become so. All algorithms known today are
      subject to cryptographic attack and may be broken in the future. </t>

      <t/>

      <section title="Requirements Language">
        <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
        "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
        document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
        target="RFC2119">RFC 2119</xref>. </t>

        <t>Following <xref target="RFC4835"/>, we define some additional key
        words: </t>

        <t><list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="MUST-"> This term means the same as MUST. However, we
            expect that at some point in the future this algorithm will no
            longer be a MUST. </t>

            <t hangText="SHOULD+"> This term means the same as SHOULD.
            However, it is likely that an algorithm marked as SHOULD+ will be
            promoted at some future time to be a MUST. </t>

            <t hangText="SHOULD-"> This term means the same as SHOULD.
            However, it is likely that an algorithm marked as SHOULD- will be
            deprecated to a MAY or worse in a future version of this document.
            </t>

            <t hangText="SHOULD NOT+">This term means the same as SHOULD NOT.
            However, it is likely that an algorithm marked as SHOULD NOT+ will
            be deprecated to a MUST NOT in a future version of this document.
            </t>
          </list>
	</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Document History">
	<t>
	  This is the initial version of this draft. It is based on an
	  earlier individual submission <xref
	  target="draft-mcgrew-ipsec-me-esp-ah-reqts"/>, and
	  incorporates feedback provided during the last IPsec ME
	  meeting at IETF85. 
	  Triple-DES is now a MAY (instead of SHOULD NOT)
          and HMAC-MD5 is now ignored (instead of a SHOULD NOT),
          and "MAY" is no longer called out, except for algorithms that
          were previously listed as SHOULD, SHOULD+, or MUST.  
	  </t>
	  <t>
	  This revision also adds a section discussing
	  algorithm diversity, and references to new work on
	  the selection of future cryptographic standards <xref
	  target="draft-mcgrew-standby-cipher"/> and technical work
	  showing the insecurity of 64-bit block ciphers (such as the
	  Triple-DES algorithm) used to encrypt more than a gigabyte
	  of data <xref target="M13"/>.
	</t>

      </section>

    </section>

    <section title="Implementation Requirements">
      <t>This section specifies the cryptographic algorithms that MUST be
      implemented, and provides guidance about ones that SHOULD or SHOULD NOT
      be implemented.
      </t>

      <section title="ESP Authenticated Encryption (Combined Mode Algorithms)">
        <t>ESP combined mode algorithms provide both confidentiality and
        authentication services; in cryptographic terms, these are
        authenticated encryption algorithms <xref target="RFC5116"/>.
        Authenticated encryption transforms are listed in the ESP encryption
        transforms IANA registry. </t>

        <figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[
        Requirement    Authenticated Encryption Algorithm
        -----------    ----------------------------------
        SHOULD+        AES-GCM [RFC4106]
        MAY            AES-CCM [RFC4309]]]></artwork>
        </figure>

        <t/>
      </section>

      <section title="ESP Encryption Algorithms">
        <t/>

        <figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[        Requirement    Encryption Algorithm
        -----------    --------------------------
        MUST           NULL [RFC2410] 
        MUST           AES-128-CBC [RFC3602]
        MAY            AES-CTR [RFC3686]
        MAY            TripleDES-CBC [RFC2451]
        SHOULD NOT+    DES-CBC [RFC2405] ]]></artwork>
        </figure>
      </section>

      <section title="ESP Authentication Algorithms">
        <t/>

        <figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[        Requirement    Authentication Algorithm (notes)
        -----------    -----------------------------
        MUST           HMAC-SHA1-96 [RFC2404]
        SHOULD+        AES-GMAC [RFC4543]
        SHOULD         AES-XCBC-MAC-96 [RFC3566]
        MAY            NULL [RFC4303]]]></artwork>
        </figure>
<!--
        SHOULD NOT     HMAC-MD5-96 [RFC2403]
        MAY            HMAC-SHA-256 [RFC4868]
        MAY            HMAC-SHA-384 [RFC4868]
        MAY            HMAC-SHA-512 [RFC4868]
-->
      </section>

      <section title="AH Authentication Algorithms">
        <t>The requirements for AH are the same as for ESP Authentication
        Algorithms, except that NULL authentication is inapplicable. </t>
      </section>

      <section title="Summary of Changes">
        <t><figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[      Old            New
      Requirement    Requirement      Algorithm (notes)
      ----           -----------      -----------------
      MAY            SHOULD+          AES-GCM [RFC4106]
      MAY            SHOULD+          AES-GMAC [RFC4543]
      MUST-          MAY              TripleDES-CBC [RFC2451]
      SHOULD+        SHOULD           AES-XCBC-MAC-96 [RFC3566] 
      SHOULD         MAY              AES-CTR [RFC3686]]]></artwork>
          </figure></t>
	  <!--
	      MAY            SHOULD NOT       HMAC-MD5-96 [RFC2403]
	      
	  -->
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Usage Guidance">
      <t>Since ESP and AH can be used in several different ways, this note
      provides guidance on the best way to utilize these mechanisms. </t>

      <t>ESP can provide confidentiality, data origin authentication, or the
      combination of both of those security services. AH provides only data
      origin authentication. Background information on those security services
      is available <xref target="RFC4949"/>. In the following, we shorten
      `data origin authentication&rsquo; to `authentication&rsquo;. </t>

      <t>Both confidentiality and authentication SHOULD be provided. If
      confidentiality is not needed, then authentication MAY be provided.
      Confidentiality without authentication is not effective <xref
      target="DP07"/> and SHOULD NOT be used. We describe each of these cases
      in more detail below.</t>

      <t>To provide confidentiality and authentication, an authenticated
      encryption transform SHOULD be used in ESP, in conjunction with NULL
      authentication. Alternatively, an ESP encryption transform and ESP
      authentication transform MAY be used together (provided that neither
      transform is NULL). If authentication on the IP header is needed in
      conjunction with confidentiality of higher-layer data, then AH SHOULD be
      used in addition to the transforms recommended above. It is NOT
      RECOMMENDED to use ESP with NULL authentication in conjunction with AH;
      some configurations of this combination of services have been shown to
      be insecure <xref target="PD10"> </xref>. </t>

      <t>To provide authentication without confidentiality, an authentication
      transform MUST be used in either ESP or AH. It is not possible to
      provide effective confidentiality without authentication, because the
      lack of authentication undermines the efficacy of encryption <xref
      target="B96"/><xref target="V02"/>. An encryption transform MUST NOT be
      used with a NULL authentication transform (unless the encryption
      transform is an authenticated encryption transform). </t>

      <t>
	Triple-DES SHOULD NOT be used in any scenario in which
	multiple gigabytes of data will be encrypted with a single
	key.  As a 64-bit block cipher, it leaks information about
	plaintexts above that "birthday bound" <xref target="M13"/>.
	Triple-DES CBC is listed as a MAY implement for the sake of
	backwards compatibility, but its use is discouraged.
      </t>

    </section>

    <section title="Rationale">
      <t>This section explains the principles behind the implementation
      requirements described above. </t>


<t>
      The algorithms listed as MAY-implement are not meant to be
      endorsed over other non-standard alternatives.  All of the
      algorithms that appeared in <xref target="RFC4835"/> are
      included in this note, for the sake of continuity.  In some
      cases, these algorithms have moved from being SHOULD-implement
      to MAY-implement algorithms.
</t>

      <section title="Authenticated Encryption">
        <t>This note encourages the use of authenticated encryption algorithms
        because they can provide significant efficiency and throughput
        advantages, and the tight binding between authentication and
        encryption can be a security advantage <xref target="RFC5116"/>.</t>

        <t> AES-GCM [RFC4106] brings significant performance benefits <xref
        target="KKGEGD"/>, has been incorporated into IPsec recommendations
        <xref target="RFC6379"/> and has emerged as the preferred
        authenticated encryption method in IPsec and other standards.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="3des" title="Encryption Transforms">
        <t>Since ESP encryption is optional, support for the "NULL" algorithm
        is required to maintain consistency with the way services are
        negotiated. Note that while authentication and encryption can each be
        "NULL", they MUST NOT both be "NULL" <xref target="RFC4301"/> <xref
        target="H10"/>. </t>

        <t>AES Counter Mode (AES-CTR) is an efficient encryption method, but
        it provides no authentication capability. The AES-GCM authenticated
        encryption method has all of the advantages of AES-CTR, while also
        providing authentication. Thus this note moves AES-CTR from a SHOULD
        to a MAY. </t>

        <t>The Triple Data Encryption Standard (TDES) is obsolete
        because of its small block size; as with all 64-bit block
        ciphers, it SHOULD NOT be used to encrypt more than one
        gigabyte of data with a single key <xref target="M13"/>.  Its
        key size is smaller than that of the Advanced Encryption
        Standard (AES), while at the same time its performance and
        efficiency is worse.  Thus, its use in new implementations is
        discouraged.</t>

        <t>The Data Encryption Standard (DES) is obsolete because of its small
        key size and small block size. There have been publicly demonstrated
        and open-design special-purpose cracking hardware. Therefore, its use
        is discouraged. </t>
      </section>

      <section title="Authentication Transforms">
        <t>AES-GMAC provides good security along with performance advantages,
        even over HMAC-MD5. In addition, it uses the same internal components
        as AES-GCM and is easy to implement in a way that shares components
        with that authenticated encryption algorithm. </t>

        <t>The MD5 hash function has been found to not meet its goal of
        collision resistance; it is so weak that its use in digital signatures
        is highly discouraged <xref target="RFC6151"/>. There have been
        theoretical results against HMAC-MD5, but that message authentication
        code does not seem to have a practical vulnerability. Thus, it may not
        be urgent to remove HMAC-MD5 from the existing protocols.
	<!-- however,
        since MD5 must not be used for digital signatures, HMAC-MD5 should not
        be included in new implementations.
	-->
	</t>

        <t>SHA-1 has been found to not meet its goal of collision resistance.
        However, HMAC-SHA-1 does not rely on this property, and HMAC-SHA-1 is
        believed to be secure.</t>

        <t>The HMAC-SHA-256, HMAC-SHA-384, and HMAC-SHA-512 are believed to
        provide a good security margin, and they perform adequately on many
        platforms. However, these algorithms are not recommended for implementation
        in this note, because HMAC-SHA-1 support is widespread and its
        security is good, AES-GMAC provides good security with better
        performance, and Authenticated Encryption algorithms do not need any
        authentication methods.</t>

        <t>AES-XCBC has not seen widespread deployment, despite being
        previously being recommended as a SHOULD+ in RFC4305. Thus this draft
        lists it only as a SHOULD. </t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Algorithm Diversity">
      <t>
	When the AES cipher was first adopted, it was decided to
	continue encouraging the implementation of Triple-DES, in
	order to provide algorithm diversity.  But the passage of time
	has eroded the viability of Triple-DES as an alternative to
	AES.  As it is a 64-bit block cipher, its security is
	inadequate at high data rates (see <xref target="3des"/>).
	Its performance in software and FPGAs is considerably worse
	than that of AES.  Since it would not be possible to use
	Triple-DES as an alternative to AES in high data rate
	environments, or in environments where its performance could
	not keep up the requirements, the rationale of retaining Triple-DES
	to provide algorithm diversity is disappearing.  (Of course,
	this does not change the rationale of retaining Triple-DES
	in IPsec implementations for backwards compability.) 
      </t>
      <t>
	It may be prudent to begin considering the selection of a
	different cipher that could provide algorithm diversity in
	IPsec and other IETF standards.  There are many important
	criteria to consider, which are out of scope for this note.
	These issues have been taken up in recent work <xref
	target="draft-mcgrew-standby-cipher"/>.
      </t>
      <t>
	It is important to bear in mind that it is very highly
	unlikely that an exploitable flaw will be found in AES (e.g.,
	a flaw that required less than a terabyte of known plaintext,
	when AES is used in a conventional mode of operation).  The
	only reason that algorithm diversity deserves any
	consideration is because the problems that would be caused if
	such a flaw were found would be so large.   
      </t>
    </section>

    <!-- This PI places the pagebreak correctly (before the section title) in the text output. -->

    <?rfc needLines="8" ?>

    <section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>Much of the wording herein was adapted from <xref target="RFC4835"/>,
      the parent document of this document. That RFC itself borrows from <xref
      target="RFC4305"/>, which borrows in turn from <xref target="RFC4307"/>.
      RFC4835, RFC4305, and RFC4307 were authored by Vishwas Manral, Donald
      Eastlake, and Jeffrey Schiller respectively. </t>

      <t>Thanks are due to Scott Fluhrer, Dan Harkins, Brian Weis, and Cheryl
      Madson for insightful feedback on this draft. </t>
    </section>

    <!-- Possibly a 'Contributors' section ... -->

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>This memo includes no request to IANA.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>The security of a system that uses cryptography depends on both the
      strength of the cryptographic algorithms chosen and the strength of the
      keys used with those algorithms. The security also depends on the
      engineering and administration of the protocol used by the system to
      ensure that there are no non-cryptographic ways to bypass the security
      of the overall system. </t>

      <t>This document concerns itself with the selection of cryptographic
      algorithms for the use of ESP and AH, specifically with the selection of
      mandatory-to-implement algorithms. The algorithms identified in this
      document as "MUST implement" or "SHOULD implement" are not known to be
      broken at the current time, and cryptographic research so far leads us
      to believe that they will likely remain secure into the foreseeable
      future. However, this is not necessarily forever. We would therefore
      expect that new revisions of this document will be issued from time to
      time that reflect the current best practice in this area. </t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <!--  *****BACK MATTER ***** -->

  <back>
    <!-- References split into informative and normative -->

    <!-- There are 2 ways to insert reference entries from the citation libraries:
     1. define an ENTITY at the top, and use "ampersand character"RFC2629; here (as shown)
     2. simply use a PI "less than character"?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119.xml"?> here
        (for I-Ds: include="reference.I-D.narten-iana-considerations-rfc2434bis.xml")

     Both are cited textually in the same manner: by using xref elements.
     If you use the PI option, xml2rfc will, by default, try to find included files in the same
     directory as the including file. You can also define the XML_LIBRARY environment variable
     with a value containing a set of directories to search.  These can be either in the local
     filing system or remote ones accessed by http (http://domain/dir/... ).-->

    <references title="Normative References">
      <!--?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"?-->

      &RFC2119;

      <reference anchor="RFC2403">
        <front>
          <title> The Use of HMAC-MD5-96 within ESP and AH </title>

          <author initials="C" surname="Madson">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <author initials="R" surname="Glenn">
            <organization/>

            <address>
              <postal>
                <street/>

                <city/>

                <region/>

                <code/>

                <country/>
              </postal>

              <phone/>

              <facsimile/>

              <email/>

              <uri/>
            </address>
          </author>

          <date year="1998"/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RFC2404">
        <front>
          <title>The Use of HMAC-SHA-1-96 within ESP and AH</title>

          <author initials="C" surname="Madson">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <author initials="R" surname="Glenn">
            <organization/>

            <address>
              <postal>
                <street/>

                <city/>

                <region/>

                <code/>

                <country/>
              </postal>

              <phone/>

              <facsimile/>

              <email/>

              <uri/>
            </address>
          </author>

          <date year="1998"/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RFC2405">
        <front>
          <title> The ESP DES-CBC Cipher Algorithm With Explicit IV</title>

          <author initials="C" surname="Madson">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <author initials="N" surname="Doraswamy">
            <organization/>

            <address>
              <postal>
                <street/>

                <city/>

                <region/>

                <code/>

                <country/>
              </postal>

              <phone/>

              <facsimile/>

              <email/>

              <uri/>
            </address>
          </author>

          <date year="1998"/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RFC2410">
        <front>
          <title> The NULL Encryption Algorithm and Its Use With IPsec
          </title>

          <author initials="R" surname="Glenn">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <author initials="S" surname="Kent">
            <organization/>

            <address>
              <postal>
                <street/>

                <city/>

                <region/>

                <code/>

                <country/>
              </postal>

              <phone/>

              <facsimile/>

              <email/>

              <uri/>
            </address>
          </author>

          <date year="1998"/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RFC3566">
        <front>
          <title> The AES-XCBC-MAC-96 Algorithm and Its Use With IPsec
          </title>

          <author initials="S" surname="Frankel">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <author initials="H" surname="Herbert">
            <organization/>

            <address>
              <postal>
                <street/>

                <city/>

                <region/>

                <code/>

                <country/>
              </postal>

              <phone/>

              <facsimile/>

              <email/>

              <uri/>
            </address>
          </author>

          <date year="2003"/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RFC3602">
        <front>
          <title> The AES-CBC Cipher Algorithm and Its Use with IPsec </title>

          <author initials="S" surname="Frankel">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <author initials="R" surname="Glenn">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <author initials="S" surname="Kelly">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <date year="2003"/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RFC3686">
        <front>
          <title> Using Advanced Encryption Standard (AES) Counter Mode With
          IPsec Encapsulating Security Payload (ESP)</title>

          <author initials="R" surname="Housley">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <date year="2004"/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RFC4301">
        <front>
          <title> Security Architecture for the Internet Protocol </title>

          <author initials="S" surname="Kent">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <author initials="K" surname="Seo">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <date year="2005"/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RFC4302">
        <front>
          <title>IP Authentication Header</title>

          <author initials="S" surname="Kent">
            <organization>K</organization>
          </author>

          <date year="2005"/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RFC4303">
        <front>
          <title>IP Encapsulating Security Payload</title>

          <author initials="S" surname="Kent">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <date year="2005"/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RFC4106">
        <front>
          <title> The Use of Galois/Counter Mode (GCM) in IPsec Encapsulating
          Security Payload (ESP)</title>

          <author initials="J" surname="Viega">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <author initials="D" surname="McGrew">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <date year="2005"/>
        </front>
      </reference>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <!-- Here we use entities that we defined at the beginning. -->



      <reference anchor="RFC4305">
        <front>
          <title> Cryptographic Algorithm Implementation Requirements for
          Encapsulating Security Payload (ESP) and Authentication Header
          (AH)</title>

          <author initials="D" surname="Eastlake">
            <organization>E</organization>
          </author>

          <date/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RFC4307">
        <front>
          <title> Cryptographic Algorithms for Use in the Internet Key
          Exchange Version 2 (IKEv2)</title>

          <author initials="J" surname="Schiller">
            <organization>S</organization>
          </author>

          <date year="2005"/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RFC4309">
        <front>
          <title> Using Advanced Encryption Standard (AES) CCM Mode with IPsec
          Encapsulating Security Payload (ESP)</title>

          <author initials="R" surname="Housley">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <date year="2005"/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RFC4835">
        <front>
          <title>Cryptographic Algorithm Implementation Requirements for
          Encapsulating Security Payload (ESP) and Authentication Header
          (AH)</title>

          <author initials="V" surname="Manral">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <date/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RFC4949">
        <front>
          <title> Internet Security Glossary, Version 2 </title>

          <author initials="R" surname="Shirley">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <date year="2007"/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RFC5116">
        <front>
          <title> An Interface and Algorithms for Authenticated Encryption
          </title>

          <author initials="D" surname="McGrew">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <date year="2008"/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="B96">
        <front>
          <title>Problem areas for the IP security protocols (Proceedings of
          the Sixth Usenix Unix Security Symposium)</title>

          <author fullname="" initials="S" surname="Bellovin">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <date year="1996"/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="DP07">
        <front>
          <title>Attacking the IPsec Standards in Encryption-only
          Configurations (IEEE Symposium on Privacy and Security)</title>

          <author initials="J." surname="Degabriele">
            <organization/>

            <address>
              <postal>
                <street/>

                <city/>

                <region/>

                <code/>

                <country/>
              </postal>

              <phone/>

              <facsimile/>

              <email/>

              <uri/>
            </address>
          </author>

          <author initials="K." surname="Paterson">
            <organization>P</organization>
          </author>

          <date year="2007"/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="PD10">
        <front>
          <title>On the (in)security of IPsec in MAC-then-encrypt
          configurations (ACM Conference on Computer and Communications
          Security, ACM CCS)</title>

          <author initials="K." surname="Paterson">
            <organization>P</organization>
          </author>

          <author initials="J." surname="Degabriele">
            <organization/>

            <address>
              <postal>
                <street/>

                <city/>

                <region/>

                <code/>

                <country/>
              </postal>

              <phone/>

              <facsimile/>

              <email/>

              <uri/>
            </address>
          </author>

          <date year="2010"/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="V02">
        <front>
          <title>Security Flaws Induced by CBC Padding - Applications to SSL,
          IPSEC, WTLS ... (EUROCRYPT)</title>

          <author initials="S" surname="Vaudenay">
            <organization>Va</organization>
          </author>

          <date year="2002"/>
        </front>
      </reference>



      <reference anchor="draft-mcgrew-standby-cipher">
        <front>
          <title>  
	    Selection of Future Cryptographic Standards
	  </title>

          <author initials="D" surname="McGrew">
            <organization>Va</organization>
          </author>

          <author initials="A" surname="Grieco">
            <organization>Va</organization>
          </author>

          <author initials="Y" surname="Sheffer">
            <organization>Va</organization>
          </author>

          <date year="2013"/>
        </front>
      </reference>


      <reference anchor="draft-mcgrew-ipsec-me-esp-ah-reqts">
        <front>
          <title>  
	    Cryptographic Algorithm Implementation Requirements and Usage Guidance
	    for Encapsulating Security Payload (ESP) and Authentication Header (AH)
	  </title>

          <author initials="D" surname="McGrew">
            <organization>Va</organization>
          </author>

          <date year="2012"/>
        </front>
      </reference>


      <reference anchor="M13">
        <front>
          <title>  
	    Impossible plaintext cryptanalysis and probable-plaintext collision attacks of 64-bit block cipher modes
	  </title>

          <author initials="D" surname="McGrew">
            <organization>Va</organization>
          </author>

          <date year="2012"/>
        </front>
      </reference>


      <reference anchor="KKGEGD">
        <front>
          <title>Encrypting the Internet (SIGCOMM)</title>

          <author initials="M" surname="Kounavis">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <author initials="X" surname="Kang">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <author initials="K" surname="Grewal">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <author initials="M" surname="Eszenyi">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <author initials="S" surname="Gueron">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <author initials="D" surname="Durham">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <date year="2010"/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="H10">
        <front>
          <title>Using Intel AES New Instructions and PCLMULQDQ to
          Significantly Improve IPSec Performance on Linux </title>

          <author initials="A" surname="Hoban">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <date year="2010"/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RFC6379">
        <front>
          <title> Suite B Cryptographic Suites for IPsec </title>

          <author initials="L" surname="Law">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <author initials="J" surname="Solinas">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <date year="2011"/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RFC6151">
        <front>
          <title> Updated Security Considerations for the MD5 Message-Digest
          and the HMAC-MD5 Algorithms</title>

          <author initials="S" surname="Turner">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <author initials="L" surname="Chen">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <date year="2011"/>
        </front>
      </reference>
    </references>

    <!-- Based on XML2RFC template-->
  </back>
</rfc>
