<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='./rfc2629.xslt' ?>

<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="no"?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<?rfc linkmailto="yes" ?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" >
    
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<rfc ipr="trust200902" docName="draft-ietf-ipsecme-failure-detection-07" category="std">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="Quick Crash Detection">A Quick Crash Detection Method for IKE</title>
    <author initials="Y." surname="Nir" fullname="Yoav Nir" role="editor">
      <organization abbrev="Check Point">Check Point Software Technologies Ltd.</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>5 Hasolelim st.</street>
          <city>Tel Aviv</city>
          <code>67897</code>
          <country>Israel</country>
        </postal>
        <email>ynir@checkpoint.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author initials="D." surname="Wierbowski" fullname="David Wierbowski">
      <organization abbrev="IBM">International Business Machines</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>1701 North Street</street>
          <city>Endicott</city>
          <region>New York</region>
          <code>13760</code>
          <country>United States</country>
        </postal>
        <email>wierbows@us.ibm.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <!-- Do Pratima and Frederic want to be co-authors?  Guess so. -->
    <author initials="F." surname="Detienne" fullname="Frederic Detienne">
      <organization abbrev="Cisco">Cisco Systems, Inc.</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>De Kleetlaan, 7</street>
          <city>Diegem</city>
          <code>B-1831</code>
          <country>Belgium</country>
        </postal>
        <phone>+32 2 704 5681</phone>
        <email>fd@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author initials="P." surname="Sethi" fullname="Pratima Sethi">
      <organization abbrev="Cisco">Cisco Systems, Inc.</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>O'Shaugnessy Road, 11</street>
          <city>Bangalore</city>
          <region>Karnataka</region>
          <code>560027</code>
          <country>India</country>
        </postal>
        <phone>+91 80 4154 1654</phone>
        <email>psethi@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date year="2011"/>
    <area>Security Area</area>
    <workgroup>IPsecME Working Group</workgroup>
    <keyword>Internet-Draft</keyword>
    <abstract>
      <t> This document describes an extension to the IKEv2 protocol that allows for faster 
        detection of Security Association (SA) desynchronization using a saved token.</t>
      <t> When an IPsec tunnel between two IKEv2 peers is disconnected due to a restart of one peer,
        it can take as much as several minutes for the other peer to discover that the reboot has 
        occurred, thus delaying recovery. In this text we propose an extension to the protocol, 
        that allows for recovery immediately following the restart.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>
  <middle>
    <!-- ====================================================================== -->
    <section anchor="introduction" title="Introduction">
      <t> IKEv2, as described in <xref target="RFC5996"/> and its predecessor RFC 4306, has a 
        method for recovering from a reboot of one peer. As long as traffic flows in both 
        directions, the rebooted peer should re-establish the tunnels immediately. However, in many 
        cases the rebooted peer is a VPN gateway that protects only servers, so all traffic is 
        inbound.  In other cases, the non-rebooted peer has a dynamic IP address, so the rebooted 
        peer cannot initiate IKE because its current IP address is unknown. In such cases, the 
        rebooted peer will not be able to re-establish the tunnels. <xref target="SCR"/> describes 
        how recovery works under RFC 5996, and explains why it may take several minutes.</t> 
      <t> The method proposed here, is to send an octet string, called a "QCD token" in the 
        IKE_AUTH exchange that establishes the tunnel. That token can be stored on the peer as part 
        of the IKE SA. After a reboot, the rebooted implementation can re-generate the token, and 
        send it to the peer, so as to delete the IKE SA. Deleting the IKE SA results in a quick 
        establishment of new IPsec tunnels. This is described in <xref target="outline"/>.</t>
      <section anchor="mustshouldmay" title="Conventions Used in This Document">
        <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT",
          "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described
          in <xref target="RFC2119"/>.</t>
        <t> The term "token" refers to an octet string that an implementation can generate using 
          only the properties of a protected IKE message (such as IKE SPIs) as input. A conforming 
          implementation MUST be able to generate the same token from the same input even after 
          rebooting.</t>
        <t> The term "token maker" refers to an implementation that generates a token and sends it
          to the peer as specified in this document.</t>
        <t> The term "token taker" refers to an implementation that stores such a token or a digest
          thereof, in order to verify that a new token it receives is identical to the old token it
          has stored.</t>
        <t> The term "non-volatile storage" in this document refers to a data storage module, that
          persists across restarts of the token maker. Examples of such a storage module include an
          internal disk, an internal flash memory module, an external disk and an external 
          database. A small non-volatile storage module is required for a token maker, but a larger
          one can be used to enhance performance, as described in <xref target="operation_esp"/>.</t>
      </section>
      </section>
      <section anchor="SCR" title="RFC 5996 Crash Recovery">
        <t> When one peer loses state or reboots, the other peer does not get any notification, so 
          unidirectional IPsec traffic can still flow. The rebooted peer will not be able to 
          decrypt it, however, and the only remedy is to send an unprotected INVALID_SPI 
          notification as described in section 3.10.1 of <xref target="RFC5996"/>.  That section 
          also describes the processing of such a notification:</t>
        <figure><artwork><![CDATA[
      "If this Informational Message is sent outside the
  context of an IKE_SA, it should be used by the recipient
  only as a "hint" that something might be wrong (because it
  could easily be forged)."
        ]]></artwork></figure>
        <t> Since the INVALID_SPI can only be used as a hint, the non-rebooted peer has to determine
          whether the IPsec SA, and indeed the parent IKE SA are still valid.  The method of doing 
          this is described in section 2.4 of <xref target="RFC5996"/>. This method, called 
          "liveness check" involves sending a protected empty INFORMATIONAL message, and awaiting a 
          response. This procedure is sometimes referred to as "Dead Peer Detection" or DPD.</t>
        <t> Section 2.4 does not mandate how many times the liveness check message should be 
          retransmitted, or for how long, but does recommend the following:</t>
        <figure><artwork><![CDATA[
                                                            "It is
 suggested that messages be retransmitted at least a dozen times over
 a period of at least several minutes before giving up on an SA..."
        ]]></artwork></figure>
        <t> Those "at least several minutes" are a time during part of which both peers are active, 
          but IPsec cannot be used.</t>
        <t> Especially in the case of a reboot (rather than fail-over or administrative clearing of 
          state), the peer does not recover immediately. Reboot, depending on the system, may take 
          from a few seconds to a few minutes. This means that at first the peer just goes silent, 
          i.e., does not send or respond to any messages. IKEv2 implementations can detect this 
          situation and follow the rules given in section 2.4:</t>
        <figure><artwork><![CDATA[
         If there has only been outgoing traffic on all of
  the SAs associated with an IKE SA, it is essential to confirm
  liveness of the other endpoint to avoid black holes.  If no
  cryptographically protected messages have been received on an IKE 
  SA or any of its Child SAs recently, the system needs to perform a
  liveness check in order to prevent sending messages to a dead peer.
   ]]></artwork></figure>
        <t> <xref target="RFC5996"/> does not mandate any time limits, but it is possible that the
          peer will start liveness checks even before the other end is sending 
          INVALID_SPI notification, as it detected that the other end is not sending any packets 
          anymore while it is still rebooting or recovering from the situation.</t>
        <t> This means that the several minutes recovery period is overlaping the actual recover 
          time of the other peer, i.e., if the security gateway requires several minutes to boot up 
          from the crash then the other peers have already finished their liveness checks before 
          the crashing peer even has a chance to send INVALID_SPI notifications.</t>
        <t> There are cases where the peer loses state and is able to recover immediately; in those
          cases it might take several minutes to recreate the IPsec SAs.</t>
        <t> Note that the IKEv2 specification specifically gives no guidance for the number of 
          retries or the length of timeouts, as these do not affect interoperability. This means 
          that implementations are allowed to use the hints provided by the INVALID_SPI messages to 
          shorten those timeouts (i.e., different environment and situation requiring different 
          rules).</t>
        <t> Some existing IKEv2 implementations already do that (i.e., both shorten timeouts or 
          limit number of retries) based on these kind of hints and also start liveness checks 
          quickly after the other end goes silent. However, see <xref target="shortwait"/> for a
          discussion of why this may not be enough.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="outline" title="Protocol Outline">
        <t> Supporting implementations will send a notification, called a "QCD token", as described
          in <xref target="format_notif"/> in the first IKE_AUTH exchange messages. These are the 
          first IKE_AUTH request and final IKE_AUTH response that contain the AUTH payloads.  The 
          generation of these tokens is a local matter for implementations, but considerations are 
          described in <xref target="tokengen"/>. Implementations that send such a token will be
          called "token makers".</t>
        <t> A supporting implementation receiving such a token MUST store it (or a digest thereof)
          along with the IKE SA. Implementations that support this part of the protocol will be 
          called "token takers". <xref target="operation_who"/> has considerations for which 
          implementations need to be token takers, and which should be token makers. 
          Implementations that are not token takers will silently ignore QCD tokens.</t>
        <t> When a token maker receives a protected IKE request message with unknown IKE SPIs, it 
          SHOULD generate a new token that is identical to the previous token, and send it to the 
          requesting peer in an unprotected IKE message as described in <xref target="format_info"/>.</t>
        <t> When a token taker receives the QCD token in an unprotected notification, it MUST verify 
          that the TOKEN_SECRET_DATA matches the token stored with the matching IKE SA. If the 
          verification fails, or if the IKE SPIs in the message do not match any existing IKE SA,
          it SHOULD log the event. If it succeeds, it MUST silently delete the IKE SA associated 
          with the IKE_SPI fields, and all dependent child SAs. This event MAY also be logged. The 
          token taker MUST accept such tokens from any IP address and port combination, so as to 
          allow different kinds of high-availability configurations of the token maker.</t>
        <t> A supporting token taker MAY immediately create new SAs using an Initial exchange, 
          or it may wait for subsequent traffic to trigger the creation of new SAs.</t>
        <t> See <xref target="int_resume"/> for a short discussion about this extensions&apos;s 
          interaction with IKEv2 Session Resumption (<xref target="RFC5723"/>).</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="format" title="Formats and Exchanges">
        <section anchor="format_notif" title="Notification Format">
          <t> The notification payload called "QCD token" is formatted as follows:</t>
          <figure><artwork><![CDATA[
                         1                   2                   3
     0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
    ! Next Payload  !C!  RESERVED   !         Payload Length        !
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
    !  Protocol ID  !   SPI Size    ! QCD Token Notify Message Type !
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
    !                                                               !
    ~                       TOKEN_SECRET_DATA                       ~
    !                                                               !
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
          ]]></artwork></figure>
          <t><list style="symbols">
            <t>Protocol ID (1 octet) MUST be 1, as this message is related to an IKE SA.</t>
            <t>SPI Size (1 octet) MUST be zero, in conformance with section 3.10 of 
              <xref target="RFC5996"/>.</t>
            <t>QCD Token Notify Message Type (2 octets) - MUST be xxxxx, the value assigned for QCD
              token notifications. TBA by IANA.</t>
            <t>TOKEN_SECRET_DATA (variable) contains a generated token as described in 
              <xref target="tokengen"/>.</t>
          </list></t>
        </section>
        <section anchor="format_auth" title="Passing a Token in the AUTH Exchange">
          <t> For brevity, only the EAP version of an AUTH exchange will be presented here. The 
            non-EAP version is very similar. The figures below are based on appendix C.3 of
            <xref target="RFC5996"/>.</t>
          <figure><artwork><![CDATA[
 first request       --> IDi,
                         [N(INITIAL_CONTACT)],
                         [[N(HTTP_CERT_LOOKUP_SUPPORTED)], CERTREQ+],
                         [IDr],
                         [N(QCD_TOKEN)]
                         [CP(CFG_REQUEST)],
                         [N(IPCOMP_SUPPORTED)+],
                         [N(USE_TRANSPORT_MODE)],
                         [N(ESP_TFC_PADDING_NOT_SUPPORTED)],
                         [N(NON_FIRST_FRAGMENTS_ALSO)],
                         SA, TSi, TSr,
                         [V+]

 first response      <-- IDr, [CERT+], AUTH,
                         EAP,
                         [V+]

                   / --> EAP
 repeat 1..N times |
                   \ <-- EAP

 last request        --> AUTH

 last response       <-- AUTH,
                         [N(QCD_TOKEN)]
                         [CP(CFG_REPLY)],
                         [N(IPCOMP_SUPPORTED)],
                         [N(USE_TRANSPORT_MODE)],
                         [N(ESP_TFC_PADDING_NOT_SUPPORTED)],
                         [N(NON_FIRST_FRAGMENTS_ALSO)],
                         SA, TSi, TSr,
                         [N(ADDITIONAL_TS_POSSIBLE)],
                         [V+]
          ]]></artwork></figure>
          <t> Note that the QCD_TOKEN notification is marked as optional because it is not required
            by this specification that every implementation be both token maker and token taker. 
            If only one peer sends the QCD token, then a reboot of the other peer will not be 
            recoverable by this method. This may be acceptable if traffic typically originates from 
            the other peer.</t>
          <t> In any case, the lack of a QCD_TOKEN notification MUST NOT be taken as an indication
            that the peer does not support this standard. Conversely, if a peer does not understand 
            this notification, it will simply ignore it. Therefore a peer may <!-- changed from MAY
            at Scott C Moonen's email --> send this notification 
            freely, even if it does not know whether the other side supports it.</t>
          <t> The QCD_TOKEN notification is related to the IKE SA and should follow the AUTH payload
            and precede the Configuration payload and all payloads related to the child SA.</t>
        </section>
        <section anchor="format_rekey" title="Replacing Tokens After Rekey or Resumption">
          <t> After rekeying an IKE SA, the IKE SPIs are replaced, so the new SA also needs to have
            a token.  If only the responder in the rekey exchange is the token maker, this can be
            done within the CREATE_CHILD_SA exchange. If the initiator is a token maker, then we 
            need an extra informational exchange.</t>
          <t> The following figure shows the CREATE_CHILD_SA exchange for rekeying the IKE SA. Only
            the responder sends a QCD token.</t>
          <figure><artwork><![CDATA[
   request             --> SA, Ni, [KEi]

   response            <-- SA, Nr, [KEr], N(QCD_TOKEN)            
          ]]></artwork></figure>
          <t> If the initiator is also a token maker, it SHOULD initiate an INFORMATIONAL exchange 
            immediately after the CREATE_CHILD_SA exchange as follows:</t>
          <figure><artwork><![CDATA[
   request             --> N(QCD_TOKEN)

   response            <--             
          ]]></artwork></figure>
          <t> For session resumption, as specified in <xref target="RFC5723"/>, the situation is 
            similar. The responder, which is necessarily the peer that has crashed, SHOULD send a 
            new ticket within the protected payload of the IKE_SESSION_RESUME exchange. If the 
            Initiator is also a token maker, it needs to send a QCD_TOKEN in a separate 
            INFORMATIONAL exchange.</t>
          <t> The INFORMATIONAL exchange described in this section can also be used if QCD tokens
            need to be replaced due to a key rollover. However, since token takers are required to
            verify at least 4 QCD tokens, this is only necessary if secret QCD keys are rolled over
            more than four times as often as IKE SAs are rekeyed. See <xref target="tg1"/> 
            for an example method that uses secret keys which may require rollover.</t>
        </section>
        <section anchor="format_mob" title="Replacing the Token for an Existing SA">
          <t> With some token generation methods, such as that described in <xref target="tg2"/>,
            a QCD token may sometimes become invalid, although the IKE SA is still perfectly valid.</t>
          <t> In such a case, the token maker MUST send the new token in a protected message under
            that IKE SA. That exchange could be a simple INFORMATIONAL, such as in the last figure 
            in the previous section, or else it can be part of a MOBIKE INFORMATIONAL exchange such
            as in the following figure taken from section 2.2 of <xref target="RFC4555"/> and
            modified by adding a QCD_TOKEN notification:</t>
          <figure><artwork><![CDATA[
  (IP_I2:4500 -> IP_R1:4500)
  HDR, SK { N(UPDATE_SA_ADDRESSES),
            N(NAT_DETECTION_SOURCE_IP),
            N(NAT_DETECTION_DESTINATION_IP) }  -->

                        <-- (IP_R1:4500 -> IP_I2:4500)
                            HDR, SK { N(NAT_DETECTION_SOURCE_IP),
                                 N(NAT_DETECTION_DESTINATION_IP) }

                        <-- (IP_R1:4500 -> IP_I2:4500)
                            HDR, SK { N(COOKIE2), [N(QCD_TOKEN)] }

  (IP_I2:4500 -> IP_R1:4500)
  HDR, SK { N(COOKIE2), [N(QCD_TOKEN)] }  -->
          ]]></artwork></figure>
          <t> A token taker MUST accept such gratuitous QCD_TOKEN notifications as long as they are
            carried in protected exchanges. A token maker SHOULD NOT generate them unless it is
            no longer able to generate the old QCD_TOKEN.</t>
        </section>
        <section anchor="format_info" title="Presenting the Token in an Unprotected Message">
          <t> This QCD_TOKEN notification is unprotected, and is sent as a response to a protected
            IKE request, which uses an IKE SA that is unknown.</t>
          <figure><artwork><![CDATA[
         message             --> N(INVALID_IKE_SPI), N(QCD_TOKEN)+
          ]]></artwork></figure>
          <t> If child SPIs are persistently mapped to IKE SPIs as described in 
            <xref target="operation_esp"/>, a token taker may get the following unprotected message 
            in response to an ESP or AH packet.</t>
          <figure><artwork><![CDATA[
         message             --> N(INVALID_SPI), N(QCD_TOKEN)+
          ]]></artwork></figure>
          <t> The QCD_TOKEN and INVALID_IKE_SPI notifications are sent together to support both 
            implementations that conform to this specification and implementations that don&apos;t. 
            Similar to the description in section 2.21 of <xref target="RFC5996"/>, the IKE SPI and 
            message ID fields in the packet headers are taken from the protected IKE request.</t>
          <t> To support a periodic rollover of the secret used for token generation, the token 
            taker MUST support at least four QCD_TOKEN notifications in a single packet. The token
            is considered verified if any of the QCD_TOKEN notifications matches. The token maker 
            MAY generate up to four QCD_TOKEN notifications, based on several generations of keys.</t>
          <t> If the QCD_TOKEN verifies OK, the receiver MUST silently discard the IKE SA and all
            associated child SAs. If the QCD_TOKEN cannot be validated, a response MUST NOT be 
            sent, and the event may be logged. <xref target="tokengen"/> defines token 
            verification.</t>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section anchor="tokengen" title="Token Generation and Verification">
        <t> No token generation method is mandated by this document. Two methods are documented in
          the following sub-sections, but they only serve as examples.</t>
        <t> The following lists the requirements for a token generation mechanism:<list style="symbols">
          <t> Tokens MUST be at least 16 octets long, and no more than 128 octets long, to 
            facilitate storage and transmission. Tokens SHOULD be indistinguishable from random data.</t>
          <t> It should not be possible for an external attacker to guess the QCD token generated
            by an implementation. Cryptographic mechanisms such as PRNG and hash functions are
            RECOMMENDED.</t>
          <t> The token maker MUST be able to re-generate or retrieve the token based on the 
            IKE SPIs even after it reboots.</t>
          <t> The method of token generation MUST be such that a collision of QCD tokens between 
            different pairs of IKE SPI will be highly unlikely.</t>
        </list></t>
        <section anchor="tg1" title="A Stateless Method of Token Generation">
          <t> The following describes a stateless method of generating a token. In this case, 
            'stateless' means not maintaining any per-tunnel state, although there is a small amount 
            of non-volatile storage required.<list style="symbols">
            <t> At installation or immediately after the first boot of the token maker, 32 random 
              octets are generated using a secure random number generator or a PRNG.</t>
            <t> Those 32 bytes, called the "QCD_SECRET", are stored in non-volatile storage on 
              the machine, and kept indefinitely.</t>
            <t> If key rollover is required by policy, the implementation MAY periodically generate
              a new QCD_SECRET and keep up to 3 previous generations. When sending an unprotected 
              QCD_TOKEN, as many as 4 notification payloads may be sent, each from a different
              QCD_SECRET.</t>
            <t> The TOKEN_SECRET_DATA is calculated as follows:</t></list></t>
          <figure><artwork><![CDATA[
            
         TOKEN_SECRET_DATA = HASH(QCD_SECRET | SPI-I | SPI-R)

          ]]></artwork></figure>
        </section>
        <section anchor="tg2" title="A Stateless Method with IP addresses">
          <t> This method is similar to the one in the previous section, except that the IP 
            address of the token taker is also added to the block being hashed. This has the 
            disadvantage that the token needs to be replaced (as described in 
            <xref target="format_mob"/>) whenever the token taker changes its address.</t>
          <t> See <xref target="sec_trans"/> for a discussion of a use-case for this method.
            When using this method, the TOKEN_SECRET_DATA field is calculated as follows:</t>
          <figure><artwork><![CDATA[
            
      TOKEN_SECRET_DATA = HASH(QCD_SECRET | SPI-I | SPI-R | IPaddr-T)

          ]]></artwork></figure>
          <t> The IPaddr-T field specifies the IP address of the token taker. Secret rollover 
            considerations are similar to those in the previous section.</t>
          <t> Note that with a multi-homed token taker, the QCD token matches just one of the token
            taker IP addresses. Usually this is not a problem, as packets sent to the token maker 
            come out the same IP address. If for some reason this changes, then the token maker can
            replace the token as described in section 4.4.</t>
          <t> There is a corner case where the token taker begins using a different IP address 
            (because of multi-homing, roaming or normal network operations) and the token maker 
            loses state before replacing the token. In that case, it will send a correct QCD token,
            but the token taker will still have the old token. In that case the extension will not
            work, and the peers will revert to RFC 5996 recovery.</t>
        </section>
        <section anchor="toklifetime" title="Token Lifetime">
          <t> The token is associated with a single IKE SA, and SHOULD be deleted by the token taker
            when the SA is deleted or expires. More formally, the token is associated with the pair 
            (SPI-I, SPI-R).</t>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section anchor="backupgw" title="Backup Gateways">
        <t> Making crash detection and recovery quick is a worthy goal, but since rebooting a 
          gateway takes a non-zero amount of time, many implementations choose to have a stand-by 
          gateway ready to take over as soon as the primary gateway fails for any reason. 
          <xref target="cluster"/> describes considerations for such clusters of gateways with 
          synchronized state, but the rest of this section is relevant even when there is no 
          synchronized state.</t>
        <t> If such a configuration is available, it is RECOMMENDED that the stand-by gateway be
          able to generate the same token as the active gateway. if the method described in 
          <xref target="tg1"/> is used, this means that the QCD_SECRET field is identical in both 
          gateways. This has the effect of having the crash recovery available immediately.</t>
        <t> Note that this refers to "high availability" configurations, where only one gateway is
          active at any given moment. This is different from "load sharing" configurations where
          more than one gateway is active at the same time. For load sharing configurations, please 
          see <xref target="sec_trans"/> for security considerations.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="int_resume" title="Interaction with Session Resumption">
        <t> Session resumption, specified in <xref target="RFC5723"/>, allows the setting up of a 
          new IKE SA to consume less computing resources. This is particularly useful in the case 
          of a remote access gateway that has many tunnels. A failure of such a gateway requires 
          all these many remote access clients to establish an IKE SA either with the rebooted 
          gateway or with a backup. This tunnel re-establishment occurs within a short period of 
          time, creating a burden on the remote access gateway. Session resumption addresses this 
          problem by having the clients store an encrypted derivative of the IKE SA for quick 
          re-establishment.</t>
        <t> What Session Resumption does not help is the problem of detecting that the peer gateway
          has failed.  A failed gateway may go undetected for an arbitrarily long time, because 
          IPsec does not have packet acknowledgement, and applications cannot signal the IPsec 
          layer that the tunnel "does not work".  Section 2.4 of RFC 5996 does not specify how long 
          an implementation needs to wait before beginning a liveness check, and only says "not 
          recently" (see full quote in Section 2). In practice some mobile devices wait a very long 
          time before beginning liveness check, in order to extend battery life by allowing parts 
          of the device to remain in low-power modes.</t>
        <t> QCD tokens provide a way to detect the failure of the peer in the case where liveness 
          check has not yet ended (or begun).</t>
        <t> A remote access client conforming to both specifications will store QCD tokens, as well
          as the Session Resumption ticket, if provided by the gateway. A remote access gateway 
          conforming to both specifications will generate a QCD token for the client. When the 
          gateway reboots, the client will discover this in either of two ways:<list style="numbers">
          <t> The client does regular liveness checks, or else the time for some other IKE exchange
            has come. Since the gateway is still down, the IKE exchange times out after several 
            minutes. In this case QCD does not help.</t>
          <t> Either the primary gateway or a backup gateway (see <xref target="backupgw"/>) 
            is ready and sends a QCD token to the client. In that case the client will quickly
            re-establish the IPsec tunnel, either with the rebooted primary gateway or the backup
            gateway as described in this document.
            </t></list></t>
          <t> The full combined protocol looks like this:</t>
          <figure><artwork><![CDATA[
     Initiator                Responder
     -----------              -----------
    HDR, SAi1, KEi, Ni  -->

                        <--    HDR, SAr1, KEr, Nr, [CERTREQ]

    HDR, SK {IDi, [CERT,] 
    [CERTREQ,] [IDr,]
    AUTH, N(QCD_TOKEN)
    SAi2, TSi, TSr, 
    N(TICKET_REQUEST)}  -->
                        <--    HDR, SK {IDr, [CERT,] AUTH, 
                               N(QCD_TOKEN), SAr2, TSi, TSr, 
                               N(TICKET_LT_OPAQUE) } 

             ---- Reboot -----

    HDR, {}             -->
                        <--  HDR, N(QCD_TOKEN)
                        
    HDR, [N(COOKIE),]
    Ni, N(TICKET_OPAQUE)
    [,N+]               -->
                        <--  HDR, Nr [,N+]
                            
          ]]></artwork></figure>
      </section>
    <section anchor="operation" title="Operational Considerations">
      <section anchor="operation_who" title="Who should implement this specification">
        <t> Throughout this document, we have referred to reboot time alternatingly as the time that 
          the implementation crashes and the time when it is ready to process IPsec packets and IKE 
          exchanges. Depending on the hardware and software platforms and the cause of the reboot, 
          rebooting may take anywhere from a few seconds to several minutes. If the implementation
          is down for a long time, the benefit of this protocol extension is reduced. For this reason
          critical systems should implement backup gateways as described in 
          <xref target="backupgw"/>.</t>
        <t> Implementing the "token maker" side of QCD makes sense for IKE implementation where protected
          connections originate from the peer, such as inter-domain VPNs and remote access gateways.
          Implementing the "token taker" side of QCD makes sense for IKE implementations where protected
          connections originate, such as inter-domain VPNs and remote access clients.</t>
        <t> To clarify the this discussion: <list style="symbols"> 
          <t> For remote-access clients it makes sense to implement the token taker role.</t>
          <t> For remote-access gateways it makes sense to implement the token maker role.</t>
          <t> For inter-domain VPN gateways it makes sense to implement both roles, because it can't
            be known in advance where the traffic originates.</t>
          <t> It is perfectly valid to implement both roles in any case, for example when using a 
            single library or a single gateway to perform several roles.</t></list></t>
        <t> In order to limit the effects of DoS attacks, a token taker SHOULD limit the rate
          of QCD_TOKENs verified from a particular source. </t>
        <t> If excessive amounts of IKE requests protected with unknown IKE SPIs arrive at a token
          maker, the IKE module SHOULD revert to the behavior described in section 2.21 of 
          <xref target="RFC5996"/> and either send an INVALID_IKE_SPI notification, or ignore it 
          entirely.</t>
        <t> <xref target="sec_trans"/> requires that token makers never send a QCD token in the 
          clear for a valid IKE SA, and describes some configurations where this could occur.
          Implementations that may be installed in such configurations SHOULD automatically detect 
          this and disable this extension in unsafe configurations, and MUST allow the user to 
          control whether the extension is enabled or disabled.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="operation_esp" title="Response to unknown child SPI">
        <t> After a reboot, it is more likely that an implementation receives IPsec packets than 
          IKE packets. In that case, the rebooted implementation will send an INVALID_SPI
          notification, triggering a liveness check.  The token will only be sent in a response to
          the liveness check, thus requiring an extra round-trip.</t>
        <t> To avoid this, an implementation that has access to enough non-volatile storage MAY 
          store a mapping of child SPIs to owning IKE SPIs, or to generated tokens. If such a 
          mapping is available and persistent across reboots, the rebooted implementation SHOULD 
          respond to the IPsec packet with an INVALID_SPI notification, along with the appropriate 
          QCD_Token notifications. A token taker SHOULD verify the QCD token that arrives with an 
          INVALID_SPI notification the same as if it arrived with the IKE SPIs of the parent IKE 
          SA.</t>
        <t> However, a persistent storage module might not be updated in a timely manner, and 
          could be populated with tokens relating to IKE SPIs that have already been rekeyed. A 
          token taker MUST NOT take an invalid QCD Token sent along with an INVALID_SPI 
          notification as evidence that the peer is either malfunctioning or attacking, but it 
          SHOULD limit the rate at which such notifications are processed.</t>
      </section>
    </section>
      <section anchor="security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t> The extension described in this document must not reduce the security of IKEv2 or IPsec.
        Specifically, an eavesdropper must not learn any non-public information about the peers.</t>
      <t> The proposed mechanism should be secure against attacks by a passive MITM (eavesdropper). 
        Such an attacker must not be able to disrupt an existing IKE session, either by resetting 
        the session or by introducing significant delays. This requirement is especially 
        significant, because this document introduces a new way to reset an IKE SA.</t>
      <t> The mechanism need not be similarly secure against an active MITM, since this type of 
        attacker is already able to disrupt IKE sessions.</t>
      <section anchor="sec_handling" title="QCD Token Generation and Handling">
        <t> Tokens MUST be hard to guess. This is critical, because if an attacker can guess the 
          token associated with an IKE SA, they can tear down the IKE SA and associated tunnels at
          will. When the token is delivered in the IKE_AUTH exchange, it is encrypted. When it is
          sent again in an unprotected notification, it is not, but that is the last time this
          token is ever used.</t>
        <t> An aggregation of some tokens generated by one maker together with the related IKE SPIs
          MUST NOT give an attacker the ability to guess other tokens. Specifically, if one taker 
          does not properly secure the QCD tokens and an attacker gains access to them, this
          attacker MUST NOT be able to guess other tokens generated by the same maker. This is the
          reason that the QCD_SECRET in <xref target="tg1"/> needs to be sufficiently long.</t>
        <t> The token taker MUST store the token in a secure manner. No attacker should be able to
          gain access to a stored token.</t>
        <t> The QCD_SECRET MUST be protected from access by other parties. Anyone gaining
          access to this value will be able to delete all the IKE SAs for this token maker.</t>
        <t> The QCD token is sent by the rebooted peer in an unprotected message. A message like 
          that is subject to modification, deletion and replay by an attacker. However, these 
          attacks will not compromise the security of either side. Modification is meaningless
          because a modified token is simply an invalid token. Deletion will only cause the 
          protocol not to work, resulting in a delay in tunnel re-establishment as described in
          <xref target="SCR"/>. Replay is also meaningless, because the IKE SA has been deleted
          after the first transmission.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="sec_trans" title="QCD Token Transmission">
        <t> A token maker MUST NOT send a valid QCD token in an unprotected message for an existing 
          IKE SA.</t>
        <t> This requirement is obvious and easy in the case of a single gateway. However, some 
          implementations use a load balancer to divide the load between several physical gateways.
          It MUST NOT be possible even in such a configuration to trick one gateway into sending a 
          valid QCD token for an IKE SA which is valid on another gateway.  This is true whether 
          the attempt to trick the gateway uses the token taker's IP address or a different IP 
          address.</t>
    	<t> IPsec Failure Detection is not applicable to deployments where the QCD secret is shared 
    	  by multiple gateways and the gateways cannot assess whether the token can be legitimately 
    	  sent in the clear while another gateway may actually still own the SA's. Load balancer 
    	  configurations typically fall in this category.  In order for a load balancing 
    	  configuration of IPsec gateways to support this specification, all members MUST be able 
    	  to tell whether a particular IKE SA is active anywhere in the cluster.  One way to do 
    	  this is to synchronize a list of active IKE SPIs among all the cluster members.</t>
    	<t> Because it includes the token taker's IP address in the token generation, the method in 
    	  <xref target="tg2"/> can (under certain conditions) prevent revealing the QCD token for 
    	  an existing pair of IKE SPIs to an attacker who is using a different IP address, even in
    	  a load-sharing cluster without state synchronization. That method does not prevent 
    	  revealing the QCD token to an active attacker who is spoofing the token taker's IP 
    	  address. Such an attacker may attempt to direct messages to a cluster member other than 
    	  the member responsible for the IKE SA in an attempt to trick that gateway into sending a 
    	  QCD token for a valid IKE SA. That method should not be used unless the load balancer 
    	  guarantees that IKE packets from the same source IP address always go to the same cluster 
    	  member.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="sec_enum" title="QCD Token Enumeration">
        <t> An attacker may try to attack QCD if the generation algorithm described in 
          <xref target="tg1"/> is used. The attacker will send several fake IKE requests to the
          gateway under attack, receiving and recording the QCD Tokens in the responses. This will
          allow the attacker to create a dictionary of IKE SPIs to QCD Tokens, which can later be
          used to tear down any IKE SA.</t>
        <t> Three factors mitigate this threat:<list style="symbols">
          <t> The space of all possible IKE SPI pairs is huge: 2^128, so making such a dictionary
            is impractical. Even if we assume that one implementation always generates predictable 
            IKE SPIs, the space is still at least 2^64 entries, so making the dictionary is 
            extremely hard. To ensure this, token makers MUST generate unpredictable IKE SPIs by 
            using a cryptographically strong pseudo-random number generator.</t>
          <t> Throttling the amount of QCD_TOKEN notifications sent out, as discussed in 
            <xref target="operation_who"/>, especially when not soon after a crash will limit the 
            attacker&apos;s ability to construct a dictionary.</t>
          <t> The methods in <xref target="tg1"/> and <xref target="tg2"/> allow for a periodic 
            change of the QCD_SECRET. Any such change invalidates the entire dictionary.</t></list></t>
      </section>
      </section>
      <section anchor="iana" title="IANA Considerations">
        <t> IANA is requested to assign a notify message type from the status types range
          (16406-40959) of the "IKEv2 Notify Message Types" registry with name 
          "QUICK_CRASH_DETECTION".</t>
      </section>      
      <section anchor="ack" title="Acknowledgements">
        <t> We would like to thank Hannes Tschofenig and Yaron Sheffer for their comments about
          Session Resumption.</t>
       <!-- Since Pratima and Frederic are back as co-authors, they don't get acknowledged.
        <t> Frederic D&apos;etienne and Pratima Sethi contributed the ideas in 
          <xref target="operation_with_ip"/> and <xref target="tg2"/>.</t>
       -->
        <t> Others who have contributed valuable comments are, in alphabetical order, Lakshminath 
          Dondeti, Paul Hoffman, Tero Kivinen, Scott C Moonen, Magnus Nystrom, and Keith 
          Welter.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="history" title="Change Log">
        <t> This section lists all changes in this document</t>
        <t> NOTE TO RFC EDITOR : Please remove this section in the final RFC</t>
        <section anchor="history12" title="Changes from draft-ietf-ipsecme-failure-detection-05">
          <t> <list style="symbols">
            <t> Some clarifications suggested by Magnus Nystrom.</t></list></t>
        </section>
        <section anchor="history11" title="Changes from draft-ietf-ipsecme-failure-detection-04">
          <t> <list style="symbols">
            <t> Some more rephrasing of section 9.2 based on suggestions by Tero Kivinen and Dave
              Wierbowski.</t></list></t>
        </section>
        <section anchor="history10" title="Changes from draft-ietf-ipsecme-failure-detection-03">
          <t> <list style="symbols">
            <t> Merged section 9.4 into section 9.2.</t>
			<t> Multiple typos discovered by Scott Moonen, Keith Welter and Yaron.</t></list></t>
        </section>
        <section anchor="history09" title="Changes from draft-ietf-ipsecme-failure-detection-02">
          <t> <list style="symbols">
            <t> Moved section 7 to Appendix A. Also changed some wording.</t>
            <t> Fixed some language in the "interaction with session resumption" section to 
              say that although liveness check MUST be done, there are no time limits to how long
              an implementation takes before starting liveness check, or ending it.</t></list></t>
        </section>
        <section anchor="history08" title="Changes from draft-ietf-ipsecme-failure-detection-01">
          <t> <list style="symbols">
            <t> Fixed the language requiring random IKE SPIs.</t>
            <t> Some better explanation of the reasons to choose the methods in <xref target="tg2"/>
              and the method in <xref target="tg1"/>, to close issue #193.</t>
            <t> Added text to the beginning of <xref target="security"/> to accomodate issue #194.
              </t></list></t>
        </section>
        <section anchor="history07" title="Changes from draft-ietf-ipsecme-failure-detection-00">
          <t><list style="symbols">
            <t> Nits pointed out by Scott and Yaron.</t>
            <t> Pratima and Frederic are back on board.</t>
            <t> Changed IKEv2bis draft reference to RFC 5996.</t>
            <t> Resolved issues #189, #190, #191, and #192:<list style="symbols">
              <t> Renamed section 4.5 and removed the requirement to send an acknowledgement for 
                the unprotected message.</t>
              <t> Moved the QCD token from the last to the first IKE_AUTH request.</t>
              <t> Added a MUST to <xref target="sec_enum"/> to require that IKE SPIs be randomly 
                generated.</t>
              <t> Changed the language in <xref target="operation_who"/>, to not use RFC 2119
                terminology.</t>
              <t> Moved the section describing why one would want the method dependant on IP 
                addresses (in <xref target="tg2"/> from operational considerations to security
                considerations.</t></list></t>
          </list></t>
        </section>
        <section anchor="history06" title="Changes from draft-nir-ike-qcd-07">
          <t><list style="symbols">
            <t> First WG version.</t>
            <t> Addressed Scott C Moonen&apos;s concern about collisions of QCD tokens.</t>
            <t> Updated references to point to IKEv2bis instead of RFC 4306 and 4718. Also 
              converted draft reference for resumption to RFC 5723.</t>
            <t> Added Dave Wiebrowski as author, and removed Pratima and Frederic.</t>
          </list></t>
        </section>
        <section anchor="history05" title="Changes from draft-nir-ike-qcd-03 and -04">
          <t>Mostly editorial changes and cleaning up.</t>
        </section>
        <section anchor="history04" title="Changes from draft-nir-ike-qcd-02">
          <t><list style="symbols">
            <t> Described QCD token enumeration, following a question by Lakshminath Dondeti.</t>
            <t> Added the ability to replace the QCD token for an existing IKE SA.</t>
            <t> Added tokens dependent on peer IP address and their interaction with MOBIKE.</t>
          </list></t>
        </section>
        <section anchor="history03" title="Changes from draft-nir-ike-qcd-01">
          <t><list style="symbols">
            <t> Removed stateless method.</t>
            <t> Added discussion of rekeying and resumption.</t>
            <t> Added discussion of non-synchronized load-balanced clusters of gateways in the 
              security considerations.</t>
            <t> Other wording fixes.</t>
          </list></t>
        </section>
        <section anchor="history02" title="Changes from draft-nir-ike-qcd-00">
          <t><list style="symbols">
            <t> Merged proposal with draft-detienne-ikev2-recovery</t>
            <t> Changed the protocol so that the rebooted peer generates the token. This has the
              effect, that the need for persistent storage is eliminated.</t>
            <t> Added discussion of birth certificates.</t> 
          </list></t>
        </section>
        <section anchor="history01" title="Changes from draft-nir-qcr-00">
          <t><list style="symbols">
            <t> Changed name to reflect that this relates to IKE. Also changed from quick crash 
              recovery to quick crash detection to avoid confusion with IFARE.</t>
            <t> Added more operational considerations. </t>
            <t> Added interaction with IFARE.</t>
            <t> Added discussion of backup gateways.</t>
          </list></t>
        </section>
      </section>
  </middle>
  <!-- ====================================================================== -->
  <back>
    <references title="Normative References"> 
      <reference anchor='RFC2119'>
        <front>
          <title abbrev='RFC Key Words'>Key words for use in RFCs to Indicate Requirement Levels</title>
          <author initials='S.' surname='Bradner' fullname='Scott Bradner'>
            <organization>Harvard University</organization>
            <address>
              <postal>
                <street>1350 Mass. Ave.</street>
                <street>Cambridge</street>
                <street>MA 02138</street>
              </postal>
              <phone>- +1 617 495 3864</phone>
              <email>sob@harvard.edu</email>
            </address>
          </author>
          <date year='1997' month='March' />
          <area>General</area>
          <keyword>keyword</keyword>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name='BCP' value='14' />
        <seriesInfo name='RFC' value='2119' />
        <format type='TXT' octets='4723' target='ftp://ftp.isi.edu/in-notes/rfc2119.txt' />
        <format type='HTML' octets='16553' target='http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/html/rfc2119.html' />
        <format type='XML' octets='5703' target='http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/xml/rfc2119.xml' />
      </reference>
      <reference anchor='RFC5996'>
        <front>
          <title>Internet Key Exchange Protocol: IKEv2</title>
          <author initials='C' surname='Kaufman' fullname='Charlie Kaufman'>
            <organization>Microsoft</organization>
          </author>
          <author initials='P' surname='Hoffman' fullname='Paul Hoffman'>
            <organization>VPN Consortium</organization>
          </author>
          <author initials='Y' surname='Nir' fullname='Yoav Nir'>
            <organization>Check Point</organization>
          </author>
          <author initials='P' surname='Eronen' fullname='Pasi Eronen'>
            <organization>Nokia</organization>
          </author>
          <date month='September' year='2010' />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name='RFC' value='5996' />
        <format type='TXT' target='http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc5996.txt' />
        <format type='HTML' target='http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/html/rfc5996.html' />
        <format type='XML' target='http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/xml/rfc5996.xml' />
      </reference>
      <reference anchor='RFC4555'>
        <front>
          <title>IKEv2 Mobility and Multihoming Protocol (MOBIKE)</title>
          <author initials='P.' surname='Eronen' fullname='P. Eronen'>
            <organization>Nokia</organization></author>
          <date year='2006' month='June' />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name='RFC' value='4555' />
        <format type='TXT' target='http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc4555.txt' />
        <format type='HTML' target='http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/html/rfc4555.html' />
        <format type='XML' target='http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/xml/rfc4555.xml' />
      </reference>
    </references>
    <references title="Informative References"> 
      <reference anchor='RFC5723'>
        <front>
          <title>IKEv2 Session Resumption</title>
          <author initials='Y.' surname='Sheffer' fullname='Y. Sheffer'>
            <organization>Check Point</organization></author>
          <author initials='H.' surname='Tschofenig' fullname='H. Tschofenig'>
            <organization>Nokia Siemens Networks</organization></author>
          <date year='2010' month='January' />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name='RFC' value='5723' />
        <format type='TXT' target='http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc5723.txt' />
        <format type='HTML' target='http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/html/rfc5723.html' />
        <format type='XML' target='http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/xml/rfc5723.xml' />
       </reference>
       <reference anchor='recovery'>
        <front>
          <title>Safe IKE Recovery</title>
          <author initials='F.' surname='Detienne' fullname='Frederic Detienne'>
            <organization>Cisco</organization></author>
          <author initials='P.' surname='Sethi' fullname='Pratima Sethi'>
            <organization>Cisco</organization></author>
          <author initials='Y.' surname='Nir' fullname='Yoav Nir'>
            <organization>Check Point</organization></author>
          <date year='2010' month='January' />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name='Internet-Draft' value='draft-detienne-ikev2-recovery' />
        <format type='TXT'
          target='http://tools.ietf.org/id/draft-detienne-ikev2-recovery' />
        <format type='HTML'
          target='http://tools.ietf.org/html/draft-detienne-ikev2-recovery' />
       </reference>
       <reference anchor='cluster'>
        <front>
          <title>IPsec Cluster Problem Statement</title>
          <author initials='Y.' surname='Nir' fullname='Yoav Nir' role="editor">
            <organization>Check Point</organization></author>
          <date year='2010' month='July' />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name='Internet-Draft' value='draft-ietf-ipsecme-ipsec-ha' />
        <format type='TXT'
          target='http://tools.ietf.org/id/draft-ietf-ipsecme-ipsec-ha' />
        <format type='HTML'
          target='http://tools.ietf.org/html/draft-ietf-ipsecme-ipsec-ha' />
       </reference>
    </references>
    <section title="The Path Not Taken" anchor="whynot">
      <section anchor="newikesa" title="Initiating a new IKE SA">
        <t> Instead of sending a QCD token, we could have the rebooted implementation start an 
          Initial exchange with the peer, including the INITIAL_CONTACT notification. This would
          have the same effect, instructing the peer to erase the old IKE SA, as well as establishing
          a new IKE SA with fewer rounds.</t>
        <t> The disadvantage here, is that in IKEv2 an authentication exchange MUST have
          a piggy-backed Child SA set up. Since our use case is such that the rebooted implementation
          does not have traffic flowing to the peer, there are no good selectors for such a Child
          SA.</t>
        <t> Additionally, when authentication is asymmetric, such as when EAP is used, it is not 
          possible for the rebooted implementation to initiate IKE.</t>
        </section>
        <section anchor="sir" title="SIR">
          <t> Another proposal that was considered for this work item is the SIR extension,
            which is described in <xref target="recovery"/>. Under that proposal, the non-rebooted 
            peer sends a non-protected query to the possibly rebooted peer, asking whether the IKE
            SA exists. The peer replies with either a positive or negative response, and the
            absence of a positive response, along with the existence of a negative response is 
            taken as proof that the IKE SA has really been lost.</t>
          <t> The working group preferred the QCD proposal to this one.</t>
        </section>
        <section anchor="bcerts" title="Birth Certificates">
          <t> Birth Certificates is a method of crash detection that has never been formally
            defined. Bill Sommerfeld suggested this idea in a mail to the IPsec mailing list on 
            August 7, 2000, in a thread discussing methods of crash detection:</t>
          <figure><artwork><![CDATA[
    If we have the system sign a "birth certificate" when it 
    reboots (including a reboot time or boot sequence number), 
    we could include that with a "bad spi" ICMP error and in 
    the negotiation of the IKE SA.
          ]]></artwork></figure>
          <t> We believe that this method would have some problems. First, it requires Alice to
            store the certificate, so as to be able to compare the public keys. That requires more
            storage than does a QCD token. Additionally, the public-key operations needed to verify 
            the self-signed certificates are more expensive for Alice.</t>
          <t> We believe that a symmetric-key operation such as proposed here is more light-weight
            and simple than that implied by the Birth Certificate idea.</t>
        </section>
        <section anchor="shortwait" title="Reducing Liveness Check Length">
          <t> Some implementations require fewer retransmissions over a shorter period of time for 
            cases of liveness check started because of an INVALID_SPI or INVALID_IKE_SPI 
            notification.</t>
          <t> We believe that the default retransmission policy should represent a good balance 
            between the need for a timely discovery of a dead peer, and a low probability of false 
            detection.  We expect the policy to be set to take the shortest time such that this 
            probability achieves a certain target.  Therefore, we believe that reducing the elapsed 
            time and retransmission count may create an unacceptably high probability of false 
            detection, and this can be triggered by a single INVALID_IKE_SPI notification.</t>
          <t> Additionally, even if the retransmission policy is reduced to, say, one minute, it is
            still a very noticeable delay from a human perspective, from the time that the gateway 
            has come up (i.e., is able to respond with an INVALID_SPI or INVALID_IKE_SPI 
            notification) and until the tunnels are active, or from the time the backup gateway has 
            taken over until the tunnels are active.  The use of QCD tokens can reduce this delay.</t>
        </section>
    </section>
    <!-- ====================================================================== -->
  </back>
</rfc>
