<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">

<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc strict="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>

<rfc ipr="trust200902" docName="draft-ietf-sunset4-gapanalysis-00"
  category="info">

  <front>

    <title abbrev="IPv4 Sunsetting Analysis">Gap Analysis for IPv4 Sunset</title>

    <author initials="JP." surname="Dionne" fullname="Jean-Philippe Dionne">
      <organization>Viagénie</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>246 Aberdeen</street>
          <city>Québec</city>
          <region>QC</region>
          <code>G1R 2E1</code>
          <country>Canada</country>
        </postal>
        <phone>+1 418 656 9254</phone>
        <email>jean-philippe.dionne@viagenie.ca</email>
        <uri>http://viagenie.ca</uri>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author initials="S." surname="Perreault" fullname="Simon Perreault">
      <organization>Viagénie</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>246 Aberdeen</street>
          <city>Québec</city>
          <region>QC</region>
          <code>G1R 2E1</code>
          <country>Canada</country>
        </postal>
        <phone>+1 418 656 9254</phone>
        <email>simon.perreault@viagenie.ca</email>
        <uri>http://viagenie.ca</uri>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author initials="T." surname="Tsou" fullname="Tina Tsou">
      <organization>Huawei Technologies (USA)</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>2330 Central Expressway</street>
          <city>Santa Clara</city>
          <region>CA</region>
          <code>95050</code>
          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>
        <phone>+1 408 330 4424</phone>
        <email>tina.tsou.zouting@huawei.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date/>

    <abstract>
      <t>Sunsetting IPv4 refers to the process of turning off IPv4 definitively.
        It can be seen as the final phase of the migration to IPv6.
        This memo analyses difficulties arising when sunsetting IPv4, and
        identifies the gaps resulting in additional work.</t>
    </abstract>

  </front>

  <middle>

    <section title="Introduction">

      <t>The final phase of the migration to IPv6 is the sunset of IPv4, that is
        turning off IPv4 definitively on the attached networks and on the upstream networks. </t>

      <t>Some current implementations behavior make it hard to sunset IPv4. Additionally, some
        new features could be added to IPv4 to make its sunsetting easier. This
        document analyzes the current situation and proposes new work in this
        area.</t>
</section>
 <section title="Related Work">
      <t><xref target="RFC3789"/>, <xref target="RFC3790"/>,<xref target="RFC3791"/>, <xref target="RFC3792"/>, <xref target="RFC3793"/>, <xref target="RFC3794"/>, <xref target="RFC3795"/> and <xref target="RFC3796"/> contain surveys of IETF protocols with their IPv4 dependencies.</t>

    </section>

    <section title="Remotely Disabling IPv4">
      <section title="Indicating that IPv4 connectivity is unavailable">
        <t>
          <list style="format PROBLEM %d:" counter="problems">
            <t>When an IPv4 node boots and requests an IPv4 address (e.g., using
              DHCP), it typically interprets the absence of a response as a
              failure condition even when it is not.</t>
            <t>Home router devices often identify themselves as default routers
              in DHCP responses that they send to requests coming from the LAN,
              even in the absence of IPv4 connectivity on the WAN.</t>
          </list>
        </t>
        <t>One way to address these issues is to send a signal
          to an dual-stack node that IPv4 connectivity is unavailable. Given that IPv4 shall be off, the message must be delivered through IPv6.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Disabling IPv4 in the LAN">
        <t>
          <list style="format PROBLEM %d:" counter="problems">
            <t>IPv4-enabled hosts inside an IPv6-only LAN can auto-configure
              IPv4 addresses <xref target="RFC3927"/> and enable various
              protocols over IPv4 such as mDNS <xref
                target="I-D.cheshire-dnsext-multicastdns"/> and LLMNR <xref
                target="RFC4795"/>. This can be undesirable for operational or
              security reasons, since in the absence of IPv4, no monitoring or logging of IPv4 will be in place.</t>
            <t>IPv4 can be completely disabled on a link by filtering it on the
              L2 switching device. However, this may not be possible in all cases or complex to deploy. For example, an ISP is often not able to control the L2 switching device in the subscriber home network.</t>
          </list>
        </t>
        <t>One way to address these issues is to send a signal
          to an dual-stack node that auto-configuration of IPv4 addresses is
          undesirable, or that direct IPv4 communications between nodes on the
          same link should not take place.</t>
        <t>This problem was described in <xref target="RFC2563"/>, which
          standardized a DHCP option to disable IPv4 address auto-configuration.
          However, using this option requires running an IPv4 DHCP server, which
          is contrary to the goal of IPv4 sunsetting. 
          An equivalent way of signalling this over IPv6 is necessary,,
          using either Router Advertisements or DHCPv6. </t>
        <t>Furthermore, it could be
          useful to have L2 switches snoop this signalling and automatically
          start filtering IPv4 traffic as a consequence.</t>
        <t>Finally, it could be useful to publish guidelines on how to safely
          block IPv4 on an L2 switch.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Client Connection Establishment Behavior">
      <t>
        <list style="format PROBLEM %d:" counter="problems">
          <t>Happy Eyeballs <xref target="RFC6555"/> refers to the multiple
            approaches to dual-stack client implementations that try to reduce
            connection setup delays by trying both IPv4 and IPv6 paths
            simultaneously. Some implementations introduce delays which provide
            an advantage to IPv6, while others do not <xref
              target="Huston2012"/>. The latter will pick the fastest path, no
            matter whether it is over IPv4 or IPv6, directing more traffic over
            IPv4 than the other kind of implementations. This can prove
            problematic in the context of IPv4 sunsetting, especially for
            Carrier-Grade NAT phasing out.</t>
          <t>getaddrinfo() <xref target="RFC3493"/> sends DNS queries for both A
            and AAAA records regardless of the state of IPv4 or IPv6
            availability. The AI_ADDRCONFIG flag can be used to change this
            behavior, but it relies on programmers using the getaddrinfo()
            function to always pass this flag to the function. The current
            situation is that in an IPv6-only environment, many useless A
            queries are made.</t>
        </list>
      </t>
      <t>Recommendations on client connection establishment behavior that would
        facilitate IPv4 sunsetting is therefore appropriate.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Disabling IPv4 in Operating System and Applications">
      <t>
        <list style="format PROBLEM %d:" counter="problems">
          <t>Completely disabling IPv4 at runtime often reveals implementation
            bugs. Hard-coded dependencies on IPv4 abound, such as on the
            127.0.0.1 address assigned to the loopback interface. It is
            therefore often operationally impossible to completely disable IPv4
            on individual nodes.</t>
          <t>In an IPv6-only world, legacy IPv4 code in operating systems and
            applications incurs a maintenance overhead and can present security
            risks.</t>
        </list>
      </t>
      <t>It is possible to completely remove IPv4 support from an operating
        system as has been shown by the work of Bjoern Zeeb on FreeBSD. <xref
          target="Zeeb"/> Removing IPv4 support in
        the kernel revealed many IPv4 dependencies in libraries and
        applications.</t>
      <t>It would be useful for the IETF to provide guidelines to programmers on
        how to avoid creating dependencies on IPv4, how to discover existing
        dependencies, and how to eliminate them. Having programs and operating
        systems that behave well in an IPv6-only environment is a prerequisite
        for IPv4 sunsetting.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>None.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Security Considerations">
      <t>TODO</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>TODO</t>
    </section>

  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Informative References">

      <reference anchor='RFC2563'>

        <front>
          <title abbrev='DHCP Auto-Configuration Option'>DHCP Option to Disable Stateless Auto-Configuration in IPv4 Clients</title>
          <author initials='R.' surname='Troll' fullname='Ryan Troll'>
            <organization>@Home Network</organization>
            <address>
              <postal>
                <street>425 Broadway</street>
                <city>Redwood City</city>
                <region>CA</region>
                <code>94063</code>
                <country>US</country></postal>
              <phone>+1 650 556 6031</phone>
              <email>rtroll@corp.home.net</email></address></author>
          <date year='1999' month='May' />
          <abstract>
            <t>Operating Systems are now attempting to support ad-hoc networks of
              two or more systems, while keeping user configuration at a minimum.
              To accommodate this, in the absence of a central configuration
              mechanism (DHCP), some OS's are automatically choosing a link-local
              IP address which will allow them to communicate only with other hosts
              on the same link.  This address will not allow the OS to communicate
              with anything beyond a router.  However, some sites depend on the
              fact that a host with no DHCP response will have no IP address.  This
              document describes a mechanism by which DHCP servers are able to tell
              clients that they do not have an IP address to offer, and that the
              client should not generate an IP address it's own.</t></abstract></front>

        <seriesInfo name='RFC' value='2563' />
        <format type='TXT' octets='17838' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc2563.txt' />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor='RFC3493'>

        <front>
          <title>Basic Socket Interface Extensions for IPv6</title>
          <author initials='R.' surname='Gilligan' fullname='R. Gilligan'>
            <organization /></author>
          <author initials='S.' surname='Thomson' fullname='S. Thomson'>
            <organization /></author>
          <author initials='J.' surname='Bound' fullname='J. Bound'>
            <organization /></author>
          <author initials='J.' surname='McCann' fullname='J. McCann'>
            <organization /></author>
          <author initials='W.' surname='Stevens' fullname='W. Stevens'>
            <organization /></author>
          <date year='2003' month='February' />
          <abstract>
            <t>The de facto standard Application Program Interface (API) for TCP/IP applications is the "sockets" interface.  Although this API was developed for Unix in the early 1980s it has also been implemented on a wide variety of non-Unix systems.  TCP/IP applications written using the sockets API have in the past enjoyed a high degree of portability and we would like the same portability with IPv6 applications.  But changes are required to the sockets API to support IPv6 and this memo describes these changes.  These include a new socket address structure to carry IPv6 addresses, new address conversion functions, and some new socket options.  These extensions are designed to provide access to the basic IPv6 features required by TCP and UDP applications, including multicasting, while introducing a minimum of change into the system and providing complete compatibility for existing IPv4 applications.  Additional extensions for advanced IPv6 features (raw sockets and access to the IPv6 extension headers) are defined in another document.  This memo provides information for the Internet community.</t></abstract></front>

        <seriesInfo name='RFC' value='3493' />
        <format type='TXT' octets='82570' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc3493.txt' />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor='RFC3789'>

        <front>
          <title>Introduction to the Survey of IPv4 Addresses in Currently Deployed IETF Standards Track and Experimental Documents</title>
          <author initials='P.' surname='Nesser' fullname='P. Nesser'>
            <organization /></author>
          <author initials='A.' surname='Bergstrom' fullname='A. Bergstrom'>
            <organization /></author>
          <date year='2004' month='June' />
          <abstract>
            <t>This document is a general overview and introduction to the v6ops IETF workgroup project of documenting all usage of IPv4 addresses in IETF standards track and experimental RFCs.  It is broken into seven documents conforming to the current IETF areas.  It also describes the methodology used during documentation, which types of RFCs have been documented, and provides a concatenated summary of results.  This memo provides information for the Internet community.</t></abstract></front>

        <seriesInfo name='RFC' value='3789' />
        <format type='TXT' octets='22842' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc3789.txt' />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor='RFC3790'>

        <front>
          <title>Survey of IPv4 Addresses in Currently Deployed IETF Internet Area Standards Track and Experimental Documents</title>
          <author initials='C.' surname='Mickles' fullname='C. Mickles'>
            <organization /></author>
          <author initials='P.' surname='Nesser' fullname='P. Nesser'>
            <organization /></author>
          <date year='2004' month='June' />
          <abstract>
            <t>This document seeks to document all usage of IPv4 addresses in currently deployed IETF Internet Area documented standards.  In order to successfully transition from an all IPv4 Internet to an all IPv6 Internet, many interim steps will be taken.  One of these steps is the evolution of current protocols that have IPv4 dependencies.  It is hoped that these protocols (and their implementations) will be redesigned to be network address independent, but failing that will at least dually support IPv4 and IPv6.  To this end, all Standards (Full, Draft, and Proposed) as well as Experimental RFCs will be surveyed and any dependencies will be documented.  This memo provides information for the Internet community.</t></abstract></front>

        <seriesInfo name='RFC' value='3790' />
        <format type='TXT' octets='102694' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc3790.txt' />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor='RFC3791'>

        <front>
          <title>Survey of IPv4 Addresses in Currently Deployed IETF Routing Area Standards Track and Experimental Documents</title>
          <author initials='C.' surname='Olvera' fullname='C. Olvera'>
            <organization /></author>
          <author initials='P.' surname='Nesser' fullname='P. Nesser'>
            <organization /></author>
          <date year='2004' month='June' />
          <abstract>
            <t>This investigation work seeks to document all usage of IPv4 addresses in currently deployed IETF Routing Area documented standards.  In order to successfully transition from an all IPv4 Internet to an all IPv6 Internet, many interim steps will be taken.  One of these steps is the evolution of current protocols that have IPv4 dependencies.  It is hoped that these protocols (and their implementations) will be redesigned to be network address independent, but failing that will at least dually support IPv4 and IPv6.  To this end, all Standards (Full, Draft, and Proposed) as well as Experimental RFCs will be surveyed and any dependencies will be documented.  This memo provides information for the Internet community.</t></abstract></front>

        <seriesInfo name='RFC' value='3791' />
        <format type='TXT' octets='27567' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc3791.txt' />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor='RFC3792'>

        <front>
          <title>Survey of IPv4 Addresses in Currently Deployed IETF Security Area Standards Track and Experimental Documents</title>
          <author initials='P.' surname='Nesser' fullname='P. Nesser'>
            <organization /></author>
          <author initials='A.' surname='Bergstrom' fullname='A. Bergstrom'>
            <organization /></author>
          <date year='2004' month='June' />
          <abstract>
            <t>This document seeks to document all usage of IPv4 addresses in currently deployed IETF Security Area documented standards.  In order to successfully transition from an all IPv4 Internet to an all IPv6 Internet, many interim steps will be taken.  One of these steps is the evolution of current protocols that have IPv4 dependencies.  It is hoped that these protocols (and their implementations) will be redesigned to be network address independent, but failing that will at least dually support IPv4 and IPv6.  To this end, all Standards (Full, Draft, and Proposed) as well as Experimental RFCs will be surveyed and any dependencies will be documented.  This memo provides information for the Internet community.</t></abstract></front>

        <seriesInfo name='RFC' value='3792' />
        <format type='TXT' octets='46398' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc3792.txt' />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor='RFC3793'>

        <front>
          <title>Survey of IPv4 Addresses in Currently Deployed IETF Sub-IP Area Standards Track and Experimental Documents</title>
          <author initials='P.' surname='Nesser' fullname='P. Nesser'>
            <organization /></author>
          <author initials='A.' surname='Bergstrom' fullname='A. Bergstrom'>
            <organization /></author>
          <date year='2004' month='June' />
          <abstract>
            <t>This document seeks to document all usage of IPv4 addresses in currently deployed IETF Sub-IP Area documented standards.  In order to successfully transition from an all IPv4 Internet to an all IPv6 Internet, many interim steps will be taken.  One of these steps is the evolution of current protocols that have IPv4 dependencies.  It is hoped that these protocols (and their implementations) will be redesigned to be network address independent, but failing that will at least dually support IPv4 and IPv6.  To this end, all Standards (Full, Draft, and Proposed) as well as Experimental RFCs will be surveyed and any dependencies will be documented.  This memo provides information for the Internet community.</t></abstract></front>

        <seriesInfo name='RFC' value='3793' />
        <format type='TXT' octets='11624' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc3793.txt' />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor='RFC3794'>

        <front>
          <title>Survey of IPv4 Addresses in Currently Deployed IETF Transport Area Standards Track and Experimental Documents</title>
          <author initials='P.' surname='Nesser' fullname='P. Nesser'>
            <organization /></author>
          <author initials='A.' surname='Bergstrom' fullname='A. Bergstrom'>
            <organization /></author>
          <date year='2004' month='June' />
          <abstract>
            <t>This document seeks to document all usage of IPv4 addresses in currently deployed IETF Transport Area documented standards.  In order to successfully transition from an all IPv4 Internet to an all IPv6 Internet, many interim steps will be taken.  One of these steps is the evolution of current protocols that have IPv4 dependencies.  It is hoped that these protocols (and their implementations) will be redesigned to be network address independent, but failing that will at least dually support IPv4 and IPv6.  To this end, all Standards (Full, Draft, and Proposed) as well as Experimental RFCs will be surveyed and any dependencies will be documented.  This memo provides information for the Internet community.</t></abstract></front>

        <seriesInfo name='RFC' value='3794' />
        <format type='TXT' octets='60001' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc3794.txt' />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor='RFC3795'>

        <front>
          <title>Survey of IPv4 Addresses in Currently Deployed IETF Application Area Standards Track and Experimental Documents</title>
          <author initials='R.' surname='Sofia' fullname='R. Sofia'>
            <organization /></author>
          <author initials='P.' surname='Nesser' fullname='P. Nesser'>
            <organization /></author>
          <date year='2004' month='June' />
          <abstract>
            <t>This document describes IPv4 addressing dependencies in an attempt to clarify the necessary steps in re-designing and re-implementing specifications to become network address independent, or at least, to dually support IPv4 and IPv6.  This transition requires several interim steps, one of them being the evolution of current IPv4 dependent specifications to a format independent of the type of IP addressing schema used.  Hence, it is hoped that specifications will be re-designed and re-implemented to become network address independent, or at least to dually support IPv4 and IPv6.  To achieve that step, it is necessary to survey and document all IPv4 dependencies experienced by current standards (Full, Draft, and Proposed) as well as Experimental RFCs.  Hence, this document describes IPv4 addressing dependencies that deployed IETF Application Area documented Standards may experience.  This memo provides information for the Internet community.</t></abstract></front>

        <seriesInfo name='RFC' value='3795' />
        <format type='TXT' octets='92584' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc3795.txt' />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor='RFC3796'>

        <front>
          <title>Survey of IPv4 Addresses in Currently Deployed IETF Operations &amp; Management Area Standards Track and Experimental Documents</title>
          <author initials='P.' surname='Nesser' fullname='P. Nesser'>
            <organization /></author>
          <author initials='A.' surname='Bergstrom' fullname='A. Bergstrom'>
            <organization /></author>
          <date year='2004' month='June' />
          <abstract>
            <t>This document seeks to record all usage of IPv4 addresses in currently deployed IETF Operations &amp;amp; Management Area accepted standards.  In order to successfully transition from an all IPv4 Internet to an all IPv6 Internet, many interim steps will be taken.  One of these steps is the evolution of current protocols that have IPv4 dependencies.  It is hoped that these protocols (and their implementations) will be redesigned to be network address independent, but failing that will at least dually support IPv4 and IPv6.  To this end, all Standards (Full, Draft, and Proposed), as well as Experimental RFCs, will be surveyed and any dependencies will be documented.  This memo provides information for the Internet community.</t></abstract></front>

        <seriesInfo name='RFC' value='3796' />
        <format type='TXT' octets='78400' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc3796.txt' />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor='RFC3927'>

        <front>
          <title>Dynamic Configuration of IPv4 Link-Local Addresses</title>
          <author initials='S.' surname='Cheshire' fullname='S. Cheshire'>
            <organization /></author>
          <author initials='B.' surname='Aboba' fullname='B. Aboba'>
            <organization /></author>
          <author initials='E.' surname='Guttman' fullname='E. Guttman'>
            <organization /></author>
          <date year='2005' month='May' />
          <abstract>
            <t>To participate in wide-area IP networking, a host needs to be configured with IP addresses for its interfaces, either manually by the user or automatically from a source on the network such as a Dynamic Host Configuration Protocol (DHCP) server. Unfortunately, such address configuration information may not always be available. It is therefore beneficial for a host to be able to depend on a useful subset of IP networking functions even when no address configuration is available. This document describes how a host may automatically configure an interface with an IPv4 address within the 169.254/16 prefix that is valid for communication with other devices connected to the same physical (or logical) link.&lt;/t>&lt;t> IPv4 Link-Local addresses are not suitable for communication with devices not directly connected to the same physical (or logical) link, and are only used where stable, routable addresses are not available (such as on ad hoc or isolated networks). This document does not recommend that IPv4 Link-Local addresses and routable addresses be configured simultaneously on the same interface. [STANDARDS-TRACK]</t></abstract></front>

        <seriesInfo name='RFC' value='3927' />
        <format type='TXT' octets='83102' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc3927.txt' />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor='RFC4795'>

        <front>
          <title>Link-local Multicast Name Resolution (LLMNR)</title>
          <author initials='B.' surname='Aboba' fullname='B. Aboba'>
            <organization /></author>
          <author initials='D.' surname='Thaler' fullname='D. Thaler'>
            <organization /></author>
          <author initials='L.' surname='Esibov' fullname='L. Esibov'>
            <organization /></author>
          <date year='2007' month='January' />
          <abstract>
            <t>The goal of Link-Local Multicast Name Resolution (LLMNR) is to enable name resolution in scenarios in which conventional DNS name resolution is not possible.  LLMNR supports all current and future DNS formats, types, and classes, while operating on a separate port from DNS, and with a distinct resolver cache.  Since LLMNR only operates on the local link, it cannot be considered a substitute for DNS.  This memo provides information for the Internet community.</t></abstract></front>

        <seriesInfo name='RFC' value='4795' />
        <format type='TXT' octets='71969' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc4795.txt' />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor='RFC6555'>

        <front>
          <title>Happy Eyeballs: Success with Dual-Stack Hosts</title>
          <author initials='D.' surname='Wing' fullname='D. Wing'>
            <organization /></author>
          <author initials='A.' surname='Yourtchenko' fullname='A. Yourtchenko'>
            <organization /></author>
          <date year='2012' month='April' />
          <abstract>
            <t>When a server's IPv4 path and protocol are working, but the server's IPv6 path and protocol are not working, a dual-stack client application experiences significant connection delay compared to an IPv4-only client.  This is undesirable because it causes the dual- stack client to have a worse user experience.  This document specifies requirements for algorithms that reduce this user-visible delay and provides an algorithm. [STANDARDS-TRACK]</t></abstract></front>

        <seriesInfo name='RFC' value='6555' />
        <format type='TXT' octets='34048' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc6555.txt' />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor='I-D.cheshire-dnsext-multicastdns'>
        <front>
          <title>Multicast DNS</title>

          <author initials='S' surname='Cheshire' fullname='Stuart Cheshire'>
            <organization />
          </author>

          <author initials='M' surname='Krochmal' fullname='Marc Krochmal'>
            <organization />
          </author>

          <date month='December' day='9' year='2011' />

          <abstract><t>As networked devices become smaller, more portable, and more ubiquitous, the ability to operate with less configured infrastructure is increasingly important. In particular, the ability to look up DNS resource record data types (including, but not limited to, host names) in the absence of a conventional managed DNS server is useful.  Multicast DNS (mDNS) provides the ability to perform DNS-like operations on the local link in the absence of any conventional unicast DNS server. In addition, mDNS designates a portion of the DNS namespace to be free for local use, without the need to pay any annual fee, and without the need to set up delegations or otherwise configure a conventional DNS server to answer for those names.  The primary benefits of mDNS names are that (i) they require little or no administration or configuration to set them up, (ii) they work when no infrastructure is present, and (iii) they work during infrastructure failures.</t></abstract>

        </front>

        <seriesInfo name='Internet-Draft' value='draft-cheshire-dnsext-multicastdns-15' />
        <format type='TXT'
          target='http://www.ietf.org/internet-drafts/draft-cheshire-dnsext-multicastdns-15.txt' />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor='Huston2012'>
        <front>
          <title>RIPE 64: Analysing Dual Stack Behaviour and IPv6 Quality</title>
          <author initials='G.' surname='Huston'
            fullname='Geoff Huston'>
            <organization abbrev='APNIC'>APNIC</organization>
          </author>
          <author initials='G.' surname='Michaelson'
            fullname='George Michaelson'>
            <organization abbrev='APNIC'>APNIC</organization>
          </author>
          <date month='April' year='2012' />
        </front>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="Zeeb" target="http://wiki.freebsd.org/IPv6Only">
        <front>
          <title>FreeBSD Snapshots without IPv4 support</title>
          <author/>
        </front>
      </reference>
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>

