<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
  <!ENTITY RFC1034  PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1034.xml'>
  <!ENTITY RFC2119  PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml'>
  <!ENTITY RFC2460  PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2460.xml'>
  <!ENTITY RFC2782  PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2782.xml'>
  <!ENTITY RFC2822  PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2822.xml'>
  <!ENTITY RFC2827  PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2827.xml'>
  <!ENTITY RFC3123  PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3123.xml'>
  <!ENTITY RFC4033  PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4033.xml'>
  <!ENTITY RFC4034  PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4034.xml'>
  <!ENTITY RFC4291  PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4291.xml'>
  <!ENTITY RFC4408  PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4408.xml'>
  <!ENTITY RFC4941  PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4941.xml'>
  <!ENTITY RFC4954  PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4954.xml'>
  <!ENTITY RFC5321  PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5321.xml'>
  <!ENTITY RFC5322  PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5322.xml'>
  <!ENTITY RFC5451  PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5451.xml'>
  <!ENTITY RFC6376  PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6376.xml'>
  <!ENTITY RFC6530  PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6530.xml'>
  <!ENTITY RFC6531  PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6531.xml'>
  <!ENTITY RFC6532  PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6532.xml'>
  <!ENTITY RFC6577  PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6577.xml'>
  <!ENTITY RFC6686  PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6686.xml'>
  <!ENTITY I-D.kucherawy-dmarc-base  PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.kucherawy-dmarc-base.xml'>
  <!ENTITY I-D.ietf-spfbis-4408bis  PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-spfbis-4408bis.xml'>
]>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes" ?>
<?rfc tocdepth="2" ?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc iprnotified="no" ?>
<rfc category="info" docName="draft-otis-spfbis-macros-nixed-00" ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="Macros Nixed">Macros Nixed by Major Providers</title>
    <author fullname="Douglas Otis" initials="D." surname="Otis">
      <organization>Trend Micro</organization>
      <address>
         <postal>
           <street>10101 N. De Anza Blvd</street>
           <city>Cupertino</city>
           <region>CA</region>
           <code>95014</code>
           <country>USA</country>
         </postal>
         <phone>+1.408.257-1500</phone>
         <email>doug_otis@trendmicro.com</email>
       </address>
    </author>
    <author fullname="Dave Rand" initials="D." surname="Rand">
      <organization>Trend Micro</organization>
      <address>
         <postal>
           <street>10101 N. De Anza Blvd</street>
           <city>Cupertino</city>
           <region>CA</region>
           <code>95014</code>
           <country>USA</country>
         </postal>
         <phone>+1.408.257-1500</phone>
         <email>dave_rand@trendmicro.com</email>
       </address>
    </author>
    <date day="16" month="May" year="2013"/>
    <area>Internet Area</area>
    <workgroup>Individual</workgroup>
    <keyword>rfc4408, rfc5321, rfc5322, rfc6376, rfc5451, spf, apl, reverse mapping, mta,
      submission, domain, authorize, email, results, security</keyword>
    <abstract>
      <t>SPF is a popular tool for managing email blocking issues. It has also helped reduce
        backscatter related with Non-Delivery Notifications as was intended. A practically unused
        feature is SPF macro capability that SPFbis still in part retains. This feature greatly
        diminishes SPF's utility and actually threatens email interchange, especially when used in
        conjunction with secondary policy layers while also being ignored by major providers. The
        macro mechanism is also unable to cope with internationalization, and is found in virtually
        none of the published resource records. It is counter productive to retain the largely
        unused and often unsupported macro feature, despite efforts expended to develop the macro
        language.</t>
    </abstract>
    <note title="Requirements Language">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT",
        "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in
          <xref target="RFC2119"/>.</t>
    </note>
  </front>
  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>Checking reverse DNS <xref target="RFC1034"/> entries per SMTP <xref target="RFC5321"/>
        connection requires queries against the entire IP address. SPF <xref
          target="I-D.ietf-spfbis-4408bis"/> macros may go a step further of searching for address
        matches with the SMTP client resolved from reverse DNS PTR record sets in a manner similar
        to address matches with the 'MX' mechanism hostname list. For IPv6, reverse DNS checks by
        SMTP servers may inadvertently induce DDoS effects against the DNS managed by the sender's
        network provider while at the same time consuming the receiving SMTP server's connection
        resources waiting for the subsequent DNS responses. Prior IPv4 mapping of reverse DNS is
        often used to avoid wasting of resources resulting from reverse DNS, but this strategy is
        not possible with IPv6. Use of reverse DNS is seldom practical simply due to network
        resource considerations. While use of SPF 'PTR' mechanism and the {%p} macro now offers 'do
        not use' advice, it is unfortunate similar considerations for uninvolved DNS servers that
        can be similarly burdened by local-part macros or various macro expansions of SMTP client
        addresses were not offered the same advice.</t>
      <t>At least reasonable limits were placed on the number of NX domain responses. Unfortunately
        even that strategy is undermined by a technique growing in popularity of using synthetic
        domains to act as an alternative for web cookies where the resulting responses actually
        increases the level of amplification. There is no justification to use macros that are able
        to impose queries constructed of odd elements of the email-address local-part or that of the
        SMTP client IP address.</t>
      <t>Windows, OS X, iOS, Linux employ IPv6 privacy extensions <xref target="RFC4941"/> where any
        problematic IP address is likely to be reassigned different addresses regularly and remain
        valid beyond the reassignment interval. Since a major portion of spam originates from
        compromised residential systems, any attempts to handle or cache this highly diverse
        information should not be considered practical.</t>
    </section>
    <section title="SMTP Internationalization">
      <t>It should also be pointed out use of macros may not function when <xref target="RFC6531"/>
        permits international email addresses that includes both local-part and domain portions of
        the email address. Tests and comments by large email providers show an understandable
        reluctance to process SPF macros where often they simply do not implement the macro portion
        of SPF.</t>
      <t>The SPF review documented in <xref target="RFC6686"/> failed to provide a breakdown on
        macro use. SPF's macros can prove hazardous, especially with IPv6. Rather than permitting
        receivers to decide their acceptance methods, an SPF resource record based on the Mail From
        parameter can induce 100 DNS transactions using labels constructed from random strings found
        in the message local-part. While recent changes made in the current version of SPF
        recommends against its use, to process the reverse namespace may place an extreme burden on
        DNS, its cache, and the SMTP server's connection resources. Too bad unrelated DNS providers
        where not afforded similar consideration.</t>
      <t>SPF macros have not anticipated the use of internationalized email addresses and lacks any
        negotiation with respect to this type of email. A fair amount of problematic repair
        regarding construction of DNS queries based on internationalized email-addresses can be
        avoided by simply acknowledging currently SPF macros are seldom used and often not
        implemented.</t>
    </section>
    <section title="Mail From Parameter and SPF">
      <t>Access to an outbound SMTP servers may or may not restrict use of the Mail From Parameter.
        An alternative mitigation strategy may rely upon rate limits and denial of access subsequent
        to abuse reports. Reasons for publishing SPF records might be to mitigate backscatter based
        on records that offer Non-Delivery-Notifications (NDNs) authorization by the Mail From
        parameter where the loss of some of these notifications is considered acceptable. When used
        to authorize bulk senders, or provide results that are independent of the SMTP client, the
        process will not offer a status safely associated with any particular message.</t>
      <t>SPF failure rates of even a few percent are too high for it to offer a solid basis for
        either acceptance or rejection. There are some policy strategies for specific domains <xref
          target="I-D.kucherawy-dmarc-base"/> that attempt to combine SPF <xref
          target="I-D.ietf-spfbis-4408bis"/> and DKIM <xref target="RFC6376"/> where when either of
        their related domains manage to pass, only then is the message to be placed in the
        in-box.</t>
      <t>Domains that reference SPF resource records should not be considered authenticated because
        the SPF process authorized the SMTP client. Often an SMTP client is shared by many domains.
        As such, it would be incorrect to assume SPFv1 records that authorize a provider by way of
        the Mail From Parameters is only permitted by authenticated accounts from that domain.</t>
      <t>As a result, no domain information in SPF or DKIM, under current circumstances, can be used
        as a domain reference for either acceptance or reputation.</t>
    </section>
    <section title="IPv6 and SPF with PTR or local-part Macros">
      <t>When IPv6 becomes more commonly used, some will attempt white-listing IP addresses as a
        practical albeit non-scalable method to deal with the highly increased address range
        confronted when dealing with IPv6. There are currently no practical solutions able to scale
        to the challenging range of IP addresses that might be controlled by malefactors.</t>
      <t>Unlike most DNS resources that segregate IPv4 and IPv6 datasets, SPF consolidates both IPv4
        and IPv6 addresses into a common list comprised of a chain of DNS transactions. In addition
        to explicit chaining, SPF expects receivers to process the first SPF resource record which
        may contain 10 SPF mechanisms. Each mechanism may then require an additional 10 DNS
        transactions to resolve the mechanism's status. According to <xref target="spf-all.com"/>
        out of 112,311,175 domains, 24,073,182 (21.4 %) publish SPF records where only 12,768
        (0.053%) employ macros. Even the 0.053% figure overstates use since many represent
        questionable server farm deployments. These are questionable since many major providers do
        not process SPF records that contain macros. Non-implementation of macros is very good from
        a security and reliability perspective, but problematic for email's integrity when used.</t>
      <section title="Problems with Macros">
        <section title="Use of SPF Macros Ignored">
          <t>When SPF was first introduced, AOL claimed they used SPF to create IP address
            white-lists based upon domains with whom they collaborate. White-listing would be less
            effective if macros were used in SPF records to modify results based upon variables such
            as the IP address of the client or the local-part of the email address. Ask a group of
            email providers about SPF, and you'll likely hear SPF is used to identify IP addresses
            used by a domain to send email. With this information, they can then check these
            addresses against popular reputation services to determine where problems are apparent.
            Silent discard or placement into spam folders reduces delivery status integrity and
            makes supporting unreliable delivery difficult.</t>
          <t>The information returned in the Authentication-Results header does not always clarify
            whether the SPF records were actually processed. In speaking with some of these
            providers about potential network amplification concerns along with resource
            consumption, they made assurances they do not process SPF macros and they have not had
            any complaints. It seems these providers are also aware of path registration failure
            rates associated with SPF, and do not reject email on the basis of SPF failure.</t>
          <t><xref target="I-D.kucherawy-dmarc-base"/> Changes the importance of SPF records being
            processed, as they will come into play during message acceptance and not be limited to
            just deciding whether a NDN is safe to send. As such, both 'do not use' and 'do not
            process' macros offers improved interchange and security. SPF's intent is to constrain
            the number of invalid NDNs being returned when someone spoofs their domain. Evidence of
            this intent might be denoted by SPF record's ending or providers overriding them with
            "?all". This approach better supports DMARC's efforts at improving delivery rates with
            improved policy enforcement. Because DMARC may actually convince a provider to refuse
            messages based upon SPF failures, it is important that it is not used for messages that
            are sent to mailing-lists for example.</t>

          <t><xref target="I-D.ietf-spfbis-4408bis"/> purports to be documenting current use. It
            dropped the SPF resource record (99) due to sparse use and recommends against reverse
            PTR use. If a similar threshold were applied, all the SPF macro expansion aspects of
            this protocol would be removed as well. Several large providers have offered their
            assurance that their SPF libraries had these macros removed. Any effort hoping to define
            current use MUST carefully reconsider the inclusion of this ill-considered macro
            feature. Otherwise, it can not be suggested SPF-bis simply documents current use.</t>
          <t>Danger imposed by the use of the local-part macro is inherent in the query required to
            support both an IPv6 expansion, in conjunction with the expansion of local-part macros
            induced by possibly cached SPF records. The local-part, along with a range of IP
            addresses made readily possible by IPv6, can be manipulated to induce a flurry of large
            DNS transactions directed toward any otherwise uninvolved domain, all directed by cached
            DNS records that contain active content.</t>
          <t>It is never a good idea to allow free attacks enabled through foreign scripts. The SPF
            local-part macro would allow a cached DNS record to be repeatedly exploited by a spam
            campaign with an attacker consuming little of their resources beyond what they already
            use in the campaign. In this case, their recipients change the domains queried on behalf
            of the attackers based upon the same SPF resource record. High levels of amplification
            still apply if SPF specifications are not changed and resulting implementation are then
            assumed part of some greater security requirement and are no longer deemed experimental.
            The SPF macro DOS overview demonstrated in 2006 <xref target="otis-spf-dos-exploit"/>
            did not consider IPv6 use which offers higher gain, where the gain achieved sending a
            single 1KB message to a single recipient offered a 1:156 reflected gain over IPv4 that
            can never be filtered or blocked by using BCP38 <xref target="RFC2827"/>. When made
            against a wildcard record, even higher gains can be achieved.</t>
          <t>Logically, local-part macros would not safely provide positive results without the
            query being combined with an IP address list of SMTP clients in some form. A list
            structure would need to be repeated for each user. Rcpt To using schemes like BATV
            provides an expedient way where the purported sender determines whether a NDN can be
            returned without the risk associated with active content placed within DNS resource
            records. Several parsers ignore local-part macro expansion since they rarely play any
            role in providing positive results.</t>
          <t>The <xref target="I-D.ietf-spfbis-4408bis"/> Addendum E indicates a possible use of SPF
            macros such as exists:{%l}._spf.{%d} or exists:{%i}_spf.{%d} can be used in
            "specialized" DNS servers able to understand encrypted local-parts or react to
            inordinate query rates which suggests use of resource records having extremely short
            TTLs. Such an approach can add a sizeable burden on recipients and targeted DNS servers.
            Such a scheme represents a poor alternative to providing authenticated domain
            identifiers. The general intent and purpose of SPF is to offer Non-Delivery Notification
            authorization where no macros are required and by most practical measure are not being
            used.</t>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section title="'do not use' Advice Assumes Senders Cooperate">
        <t>Problems related to various types of network abuse made possible by SPF macro extensions
          are not prevented by assuming corrective behavior is obtained through advice given to
          senders. In general, it is the sender not to be trusted. Only by giving the advice 'do not
          use and do not implement' is both security and interchange ensured.</t>
      </section>
      <section title="Retain SPF Type (99)">
        <t>Upon greater reflection regarding deprecation of the SPF type (99) record, this was a
          mistake. When overlaying the TXT resource record was originally proposed, many strongly
          objected. Studies then showed scant use of TXT records which convinced those in the then
          MARID WG they could adopt the TXT record at the domain apex as belonging to SPF as their
          means to support wildcard use. Although support of unknown RR types has improved, the
          vendor that made adoption of a different RR type problematic still persists with their
          related name service extensions imposing barriers. SPF Type (99) should be retained to
          better ensure extensions to DNS retain an ability to cope with unknown RR types.</t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section title="Domains as a Basis for Managing Traffic">
      <t>A manageable basis for assessments can leverage a smaller number of related domains,
        compared to IPv6 or even IPv4 addresses. Although technically the domain name space can be
        larger than the massively large IPv6 address space, in practice it is not. One hundred
        thousand domains control 90% of Internet traffic out of approximately 100 million domains
        active each month. The top 150 domains control 50% of the traffic, and the top 2,500 domains
        control 75%. This level of domain consolidation permits effective fast-path white-listing.
        Improvements achieved using domains to consolidate the threat landscape can easily justify
        added cryptographic authentication burdens. Even APL resource records <xref target="RFC3123"
        /> can authenticate EHLO using a single DNS transaction, but this would not allow IPv6 email
        to be more easily managed, which cryptographic technology can offer.</t>
    </section>
    <section title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>This document requires no IANA consideration.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Security Considerations">
      <t>This draft intends to describe serious security and interchange concerns with use of SPF
        macros. The contained recommendations are expected to reduce these concerns. Greater caution
        is warranted before making assumptions about DNS activity. Due to high volumes of traffic,
        rarely is this traffic logged directly by the server. Some items might be triggered while
        passing through firewalls, but without being given the item to watch, discovering a well
        orchestrated attack is analogous to discovering a needle in the proverbial haystack.</t>
      <t>Many administrators overlook a serious problem made much worse by chatty protocols that
        impose processing delays. Examining server logs will not reveal any problem either, because
        the limited resource being consumed is the number of outstanding connections TCP is able to
        support. Reaching this limit will prevent new connections from being instantiated but this
        is not logged as an event. Over time administrators may hear complaints email is not being
        delivered or just see an ever growing percentage of spam.</t>
      <t>Add language clearly indicating BOTH the implementation or use of SPF macro features is
        hereby deprecated. Any such use provides a neutral result. In addition, restore SPF type 99
        to better insure the future health of DNS.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>
  <back>
    <references title="References - Informative"> &RFC1034; &RFC2119; &RFC2460; &RFC2782;&RFC2822;
      &RFC2827; &RFC3123; &RFC4033; &RFC4034; &RFC4291; &RFC4941; &RFC4408; &RFC4954; &RFC5321;
      &RFC5322; &RFC5451; &RFC6376; &RFC6530; &RFC6531; &RFC6532; &RFC6577; &RFC6686;
      &I-D.ietf-spfbis-4408bis; &I-D.kucherawy-dmarc-base; <reference anchor="otis-spf-dos-exploit">
        <front>
          <title abbrev="SPF DoS Exploit">Otis SPF DoS Exploitation</title>
          <author fullname="Douglas Otis">
            <organization>http://tools.ietf.org/html/draft-otis-spf-dos-exploit-01</organization>
          </author>
          <date month="June" day="27" year="2006"/>
          <abstract>
            <t>This document describes an email induced Denial of Service threat from SPF script
              used to evaluate the association of a source domain-name with the sending-system. The
              SPF script attempts to establish the domain-name association through the construction
              of an extensive IP address list of all sending-systems. Expectations of an association
              have become problematic, as message handling might be negatively affected without an
              apparent domain-name relationship discovered between the sending-system and either the
              message envelope or the message itself.</t>
          </abstract>
        </front>
        <format type="html" target="http://tools.ietf.org/html/draft-otis-spf-dos-exploit-01.html"/>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="spf-all.com">
        <front>
          <title abbrev="SPF Stats">SPF-all.com Stats</title>
          <author fullname="Greg Hewgill">
            <organization>http://spf-all.com/stats.html</organization>
          </author>
          <date month="May" day="8" year="2013"/>
          <abstract>
            <t>Website dedicated to SPF by Greg Hewgill of Hewgill Networks.</t>
          </abstract>
        </front>
        <format type="html" target="http://spf-all.com/stats.html"/>
      </reference>
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
