<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<rfc category="std" docName="draft-ietf-ippm-rt-loss-05" ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="Round-trip Loss">Round-trip Packet Loss Metrics</title>

    <author fullname="Al Morton" initials="A." surname="Morton">
      <organization>AT&amp;T Labs</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>200 Laurel Avenue South</street>

          <city>Middletown,</city>

          <region>NJ</region>

          <code>07748</code>

          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>

        <phone>+1 732 420 1571</phone>

        <facsimile>+1 732 368 1192</facsimile>

        <email>acmorton@att.com</email>

        <uri>http://home.comcast.net/~acmacm/</uri>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date day="8" month="May" year="2012" />

    <abstract>
      <t>Many user applications (and the transport protocols that make them
      possible) require two-way communications. To assess this capability, and
      to achieve test system simplicity, round-trip loss measurements are
      frequently conducted in practice. The Two-Way Active Measurement
      Protocol specified in RFC 5357 establishes a round-trip loss measurement
      capability for the Internet. However, there is currently no metric
      specified according to the RFC 2330 framework.</t>

      <t>This memo adds round-trip loss to the set of IP Performance Metrics
      (IPPM).</t>
    </abstract>

    <note title="Requirements Language">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
      document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
      target="RFC2119">RFC 2119</xref>.</t>

      <t></t>
    </note>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>This memo defines a metric to quantify an IP network's ability to
      transfer packets in both directions from one host to another host.
      Two-way communication is almost always needed, thus failure to transfer
      a packet in either direction constitutes a round-trip packet loss.</t>

      <t>This memo defines a metric for round-trip packet loss on Internet
      paths. It builds on the notions and conventions introduced in the IP
      Performance Metrics (IPPM) framework <xref target="RFC2330"></xref>.
      Also, the specifications of the One-way Packet Loss Metric for IPPM
      <xref target="RFC2680"></xref> and the Round-trip Delay Metric for IPPM
      <xref target="RFC2681"></xref> are frequently referenced and modified to
      match the round-trip circumstances addressed here. However, this memo
      assumes that the reader is familiar with the references, and does not
      repeat material as was done in <xref target="RFC2681"></xref>.</t>

      <t>This memo uses the terms "two-way" and "round-trip" synonymously.</t>

      <section title="Motivation">
        <t>Many user applications and the transport protocols that make them
        possible require two-way communications. For example, the TCP
        SYN-&gt;, &lt;-SYN-ACK, ACK-&gt; three-way handshake attempted
        billions of times each day cannot be completed without two-way
        connectivity in a near-simultaneous time interval. Thus, measurements
        of Internet round-trip packet loss performance provide a basis to
        infer application performance more easily.</t>

        <t>Measurement system designers have also recognized advantages of
        system simplicity when one host simply echoes or reflects test packets
        to the sender. Round-trip packet loss measurements are frequently
        conducted and reported in practice. The ubiquitous "ping" tools allow
        the measurement of round-trip packet loss and delay, but usually
        require ICMP Echo-Request/Reply support, and ICMP packets may
        encounter exceptional treatment on the measurement path (see Section
        2.6 of <xref target="RFC2681"></xref>). The Two-Way Active Measurement
        Protocol (TWAMP) specified in <xref target="RFC5357"></xref>
        establishes a round-trip packet loss measurement capability for the
        Internet. However, there is currently no round-trip packet loss metric
        specified according to the <xref target="RFC2330"></xref>
        framework.</t>

        <t><xref target="RFC2681"></xref> indicates that round-trip
        measurements may sometimes encounter "asymmetric" paths. When loss is
        observed using a round-trip measurement, there is often a desire to
        ascertain which of the two directional paths "lost" the packet. Under
        some circumstances, it is possible to make this inference. The
        round-trip measurement method raises a few complications when
        interpreting the embedded one-way results, and the user should be
        aware of them.</t>

        <t><xref target="RFC2681"></xref> also points out that loss
        measurement conducted sequentially in both directions of a path and
        reported as a round-trip result may be exactly the desired metric. On
        the other hand, it may be difficult to derive the state of round-trip
        packet loss from one-way measurements conducted in each direction
        unless a method to match the appropriate one-way measurements has been
        pre-arranged.</t>

        <t>Finally, many measurement systems report statistics on a
        conditional delay distribution, where the condition is packet arrival
        at the destination. This condition is encouraged in <xref
        target="RFC3393"></xref>, <xref target="RFC5481"></xref>, and
        [draft-ietf-ippm-reporting-metrics]. As a result, lost packets need to
        be reported separately, according to a standardized metric. This memo
        defines such a metric.</t>

        <t>See Section 1.1 of<xref target="RFC2680"></xref> for additional
        motivation of the packet loss metric.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Scope">
      <t>This memo defines a round-trip packet loss metric using the
      conventions of the IPPM framework <xref target="RFC2330"></xref>.</t>

      <t>The memo defines a singleton metric, a sample metric, and a
      statistic, as per <xref target="RFC2330"></xref>. The <xref
      target="RFC2330"></xref> framework is for active measurement methods.
      Although this metric MAY be applicable in passive measurement as well,
      discussion of additional considerations for the passive scenario are
      beyond the normative scope of this memo.</t>

      <t>The memo also investigates the topic of one-way loss inference from a
      two-way measurement, and lists some key considerations.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Common Specifications for Round-trip Metrics">
      <t>To reduce the redundant information presented in the detailed metrics
      sections that follow, this section presents the specifications that are
      common to two or more metrics. The section is organized using the same
      subsections as the individual metrics, to simplify comparisons.</t>

      <section title="Name: Type-P-*">
        <t>All metrics use the Type-P convention as described in <xref
        target="RFC2330"></xref>. The rest of the name is unique to each
        metric.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Metric Parameters">
        <t><list style="symbols">
            <t>Src, the IP address of a host</t>

            <t>Dst, the IP address of a host</t>

            <t>T, a time (start of test interval)</t>

            <t>Tf, a time (end of test interval)</t>

            <t>lambda, a rate in reciprocal seconds (for Poisson Streams)</t>

            <t>incT, the nominal duration of inter-packet interval, first bit
            to first bit (for Periodic Streams)</t>

            <t>T0, a time that MUST be selected at random from the interval
            [T, T+dT] to start generating packets and taking measurements (for
            Periodic Streams)</t>

            <t>TstampSrc, the wire time of the packet as measured at MP(Src)
            as it leaves for Dst.</t>

            <t>TstampDst, the wire time of the packet as measured at MP(Dst),
            assigned to packets that arrive within a "reasonable" time (less
            than Tmax).</t>

            <t>Tmax, a maximum waiting time for packets to arrive at Src, set
            sufficiently long to disambiguate packets with long delays from
            packets that are discarded (lost).</t>

            <t>M, the total number of packets sent between T0 and Tf</t>

            <t>N, the total number of packets received at Dst (sent between T0
            and Tf)</t>

            <t>Type-P, as defined in <xref target="RFC2330"></xref>, which
            includes any field that may affect a packet's treatment as it
            traverses the network</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>

      <section title="Metric Definition">
        <t>This section is specific to each metric.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Metric Units">
        <t>The metric units are logical (1 or 0) when describing a single
        packet's loss performance, where a 0 indicates successful packet
        transmission and a 1 indicates packet loss.</t>

        <t>Units of time are as specified in <xref
        target="RFC2330"></xref>.</t>

        <t>Other units used are defined in the associated section.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="A Singleton Round-trip Loss Metric">
      <t></t>

      <section title="Name: Type-P-Round-trip-Loss">
        <t></t>
      </section>

      <section title="Metric Parameters">
        <t>See section 3.2.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Definition and Metric Units">
        <t>Type-P-Round-trip-Loss SHALL be represented by the binary logical
        values (or their equivalents) when the following conditions are
        met:</t>

        <t>Type-P-Round-trip-Loss = 0:<list style="symbols">
            <t>Src sent the first bit of a Type-P packet to Dst at wire-time
            TstampSrc,</t>

            <t>that Dst received that packet,</t>

            <t>the Dst sent a Type-P packet back to the Src as quickly as
            possible (certainly less than Tmax, and fast enough for the
            intended purpose), and</t>

            <t>that Src received the last bit of the reflected packet prior to
            wire-time TstampSrc + Tmax.</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>Type-P-Round-trip-Loss = 1:<list style="symbols">
            <t>Src sent the first bit of a Type-P packet to Dst at wire-time
            TstampSrc,</t>

            <t>that Src did not receive the last bit of the reflected packet
            before the waiting time lapsed at TstampSrc + Tmax.</t>
          </list>Possible causes for the Loss = 1 outcome are:</t>

        <t><list style="symbols">
            <t>the Dst did not receive that packet,</t>

            <t>the Dst did not send a Type-P packet back to the Src, or</t>

            <t>the Src did not receive a reflected Type-P packet sent from the
            Dst.</t>
          </list>Following the precedent of Section 2.4 of<xref
        target="RFC2681"></xref>, we make the simplifying assertion, that
        Round-trip loss measured between two hosts is equal regardless of the
        host that originates the test:</t>

        <t>Type-P-Round-trip-Loss(Src-&gt;Dst-&gt;Src) =
        Type-P-Round-trip-Loss(Dst-&gt;Src-&gt;Dst)</t>

        <t>(and agree with the rationale presented there, that the ambiguity
        introduced is a small price to pay for measurement efficiency).</t>

        <t>Therefore, each singleton can be represented by pairs of elements
        as follows: <list style="symbols">
            <t>TstampSrc, the wire time of the packet at the Src (beginning
            the round-trip journey).</t>

            <t>L, either zero or one (or some logical equivalent), where L=1
            indicates loss and L=0 indicates successful round-trip arrival
            prior to TstampSrc + Tmax.</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>

      <section title="Discussion and other details">
        <t>See <xref target="RFC2680"></xref> and <xref
        target="RFC2681"></xref> for extensive discussion, methods of
        measurement, errors and uncertainties, and other fundamental
        considerations that need not be repeated here.</t>

        <t>We add the following guidance regarding the responder process to
        "send a Type-P packet back to the Src as quickly as possible".</t>

        <t>A response that was not generated within Tmax is inadequate for any
        realistic test, and the Src will discard such responses. A responder
        that serves typical round-trip packet loss testing (which is relevant
        to higher-layer application performance) SHOULD produce a response in
        1 second or less. A responder that is unable to satisfy this
        requirement SHOULD log the fact so that an operator can adjust the
        load and priorities as necessary. Analysis of responder time-stamps
        <xref target="RFC5357"></xref> that finds responses are not generated
        in a timely fashion SHOULD result in operator notification, and the
        operator SHOULD suspend tests to the responder since it may be
        overloaded. Additional measurement considerations are described in
        Section 8, below.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="A Sample Round-trip Loss Metric">
      <t>Given the singleton metric Type-P-Round-trip-Loss, we now define one
      particular sample of such singletons. The idea of the sample is to
      select a particular binding of the parameters Src, Dst, and Type-P, then
      define a sample of values of parameter TstampSrc. This can be done in
      several ways, including:<list style="numbers">
          <t>Poisson: a pseudo-random Poisson process of rate lambda, whose
          values fall between T and Tf. The time interval between successive
          values of TstampSrc will then average 1/lambda, as per Section 11.1
          of <xref target="RFC2330"></xref>.</t>

          <t>Periodic: a periodic stream process with pseudo-random start time
          T0 between T and dT, and nominal inter-packet interval incT, as per
          <xref target="RFC3432"></xref>.</t>
        </list>In the metric name, the variable &lt;Sample&gt; SHALL be
      replaced with the process used to define the sample, using one of the
      above processes (or another sample process meeting the criteria in
      Section 11.1 of <xref target="RFC2330"></xref>, the details of which
      MUST be reported with the results if used).</t>

      <section title="Name: Type-P-Round-trip-Loss-&lt;Sample&gt;-Stream">
        <t></t>
      </section>

      <section title="Metric Parameters">
        <t>See section 3.2.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Definition and Metric Units">
        <t>Given one of the methods for defining the test interval, the sample
        of times (TstampSrc) and other metric parameters, we obtain a sequence
        of Type-P-Round-trip-Loss singletons as defined in section 4.3.</t>

        <t>Type-P-Round-trip-Loss-&lt;Sample&gt;-Stream SHALL be a sequence of
        pairs with elements as follows: <list style="symbols">
            <t>TstampSrc, as above</t>

            <t>L, either zero or one (or some logical equivalent), where L=1
            indicates loss and L=0 indicates successful round-trip arrival
            prior to TstampSrc + Tmax.</t>
          </list>and where &lt;Sample&gt; SHALL be replaced with "Poisson",
        "Periodic", or an appropriate term to designate another sample method
        as described in Section 5 above.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Discussion and other details">
        <t>See <xref target="RFC2680"></xref> and <xref
        target="RFC2681"></xref> for extensive discussion, methods of
        measurement, errors and uncertainties, and other fundamental
        considerations that need not be repeated here. However, when these
        references were approved, the packet reordering metrics in <xref
        target="RFC4737"></xref> had not yet been defined, nor had reordering
        been addressed in IPPM methodologies.</t>

        <t><xref target="RFC4737"></xref> defines packets that arrive "late"
        with respect to their sending order as reordered. For example, when
        packets arrive with sequence numbers 4, 7, 5, 6, then packets 5 and 6
        are reordered, and they are obviously not lost because they have
        arrived within some reasonable waiting time threshold. The presence of
        reordering on a round-trip path has several likely effects on the
        measurement.<list style="numbers">
            <t>Methods of measurement should continue to wait the specified
            time for packets, and avoid prematurely declaring round-trip
            packet loss when a sequence gap or error is observed.</t>

            <t>The time distribution of the singletons in the sample has been
            significantly changed.</t>

            <t>Either the original packet stream or the reflected packet
            stream experienced path instability, and the original conditions
            may no longer be present.</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>Measurement implementations MUST address the possibility for packet
        reordering and avoid related errors in their processes.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Round-trip Loss Statistic">
      <t>This section gives the primary and overall statistic for loss
      performance. Additional statistics and metrics originally prepared for
      One-way loss MAY also be applicable.</t>

      <section title="Type-P-Round-trip-Loss-&lt;Sample&gt;-Ratio">
        <t>Given a Type-P-Round-trip-Loss-&lt;Sample&gt;-Stream, the average
        of all the logical values, L, in the Stream is the
        Type-P-Round-trip-Loss-&lt;Sample&gt;-Ratio. This ratio is in units of
        lost packets per round-trip transmissions actually attempted.</t>

        <t>In addition, the Type-P-Round-trip-Loss-&lt;Sample&gt;-Ratio is
        undefined if the sample is empty.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Round-trip Testing and One-way Reporting">
      <t>This section raises considerations for results collected using a
      round-trip measurement architecture, such as in TWAMP <xref
      target="RFC5357"></xref>.</t>

      <t>The sampling process for the reverse path (Dst-&gt;Src) is a
      conditional process that depends on successful packet arrival at the Dst
      and correct operation at the Dst to generate the reflected packet.
      Therefore, the sampling process for the reverse path will be
      significantly affected when appreciable loss occurs on the Src-&gt;Dst
      path, making an attempt to assess the reverse path performance invalid
      (for loss or possibly any metric).</t>

      <t>Further, the sampling times for the reverse path (Dst-&gt;Src) are a
      random process that depends on the original sample times (TstampSrc),
      the one-way-delay for successful packet arrival at the Dst, and time
      taken at the Dst to generate the reflected packet. Therefore, the
      sampling process for the reverse path will be significantly affected
      when appreciable delay variation occurs on the Src-&gt;Dst path, making
      an attempt to assess the reverse path performance invalid (for loss or
      possibly any metric).</t>

      <t>As discussed above in Section 5.4, packet reordering is always a
      possibility. In addition to the severe delay variation that usually
      accompanies it, reordering on the Src-&gt;Dst path will cause a
      mis-alignment of sequence numbers applied at the Dst when compared to
      the sender numbers. Measurement implementations MUST address this
      possible outcome.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Measurement Considerations and Calibration">
      <t>Prior to conducting this measurement, the participating hosts MUST be
      configured to send and receive test packets of the chosen Type-P.
      Standard measurement protocols are capable of this task <xref
      target="RFC5357"></xref>, but any reliable method is sufficient (e.g.,
      if the issues with ICMP discussed in Section 2.6 of<xref
      target="RFC2681"> </xref> can be alleviated, and the requirements of
      Section 4.3 and Section 4.4 above are met, then ICMP could be used).</t>

      <t>Two key features of the host that receives test packets and returns
      them to the originating host are described in section 4.2 of <xref
      target="RFC5357"></xref> . Every received test packet MUST result in a
      responding packet, and the response MUST be generated as quickly as
      possible. This implies that interface buffers will be serviced promptly,
      and that buffer discards will be extremely rare. These features of the
      measurement equipment MUST be calibrated according to Section 3.7.3 of
      <xref target="RFC2679"></xref>, when operating under a representative
      measurement load (as defined by the user). Both unexpected test packet
      discards, and the systematic and random errors and uncertainties, MUST
      be recorded.</t>

      <t>We note that Section 4.2.1 of <xref target="RFC5357"></xref>
      specifies a method to collect all four significant time-stamps needed to
      describe a packet's round-trip delay <xref target="RFC2681"></xref> and
      remove the processing time incurred at the responding host. This
      information supports the measurement of the corresponding One-way Delays
      encountered on the round-trip path, which can identify path asymmetry or
      unexpected processing time at the responding host.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Security Considerations">
      <t></t>

      <section title="Denial of Service Attacks">
        <t>This metric requires a stream of packets sent from one host
        (source) to another host (destination) through intervening networks,
        and back. This method could be abused for denial of service attacks
        directed at the destination and/or the intervening network(s).</t>

        <t>Administrators of source, destination, and the intervening
        network(s) should establish bilateral or multi-lateral agreements
        regarding the timing, size, and frequency of collection of sample
        metrics. Use of this method in excess of the terms agreed between the
        participants may be cause for immediate rejection or discard of
        packets or other escalation procedures defined between the affected
        parties.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="User Data Confidentiality">
        <t>Active use of this method generates packets for a sample, rather
        than taking samples based on user data, and does not threaten user
        data confidentiality. Passive measurement must restrict attention to
        the headers of interest. Since user payloads may be temporarily stored
        for length analysis, suitable precautions MUST be taken to keep this
        information safe and confidential. In most cases, a hashing function
        will produce a value suitable for payload comparisons.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Interference with the metrics">
        <t>It may be possible to identify that a certain packet or stream of
        packets is part of a sample. With that knowledge at the destination
        and/or the intervening networks, it is possible to change the
        processing of the packets (e.g. increasing or decreasing delay) in a
        way that may distort the measured performance. It may also be possible
        to generate additional packets that appear to be part of the sample
        metric. These additional packets are likely to perturb the results of
        the sample measurement.</t>

        <t>Authentication or encryption techniques, such as digital
        signatures, MAY be used where appropriate to guard against injected
        traffic attacks. <xref target="RFC5357"></xref> includes both
        authentication and encryption features.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>Metrics previously defined in IETF were registered in the IANA IPPM
      METRICS REGISTRY, however this process was discontinued when the
      registry structure was found to be inadequate, and the registry was
      declared Obsolete <xref target="RFC6248"></xref>.</t>

      <t>Although the metrics in this draft may be considered for some form of
      registration in the future, no IANA Action is requested at this
      time.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>The author thanks Tiziano Ionta for his careful review of this memo,
      primarily resulting in the development of measurement considerations
      using TWAMP <xref target="RFC5357"></xref> as an example method. The
      reviews of Adrian Farrel and Benoit Claise also contributed to the
      clarity of the memo.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc ?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2330"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2679"?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.2680'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.3393'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.3432'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.2681'?>

      <?rfc ?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.4737'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.5357'?>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <?rfc ?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.5481'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6248'?>

      <?rfc ?>
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>