<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM 'rfc2629.dtd'[
<!ENTITY RFC2026 SYSTEM
"/IETF/xml2rfc-1.35/bibxml/reference.RFC.2026.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC2119 SYSTEM
"/IETF/xml2rfc-1.35/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC2327 SYSTEM
"/IETF/xml2rfc-1.35/bibxml/reference.RFC.2327.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3261 SYSTEM
"/IETF/xml2rfc-1.35/bibxml/reference.RFC.3261.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3264 SYSTEM
"/IETF/xml2rfc-1.35/bibxml/reference.RFC.3264.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3266 SYSTEM
"/IETF/xml2rfc-1.35/bibxml/reference.RFC.3266.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3312 SYSTEM
"/IETF/xml2rfc-1.35/bibxml/reference.RFC.3312.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3388 SYSTEM
"/IETF/xml2rfc-1.35/bibxml/reference.RFC.3388.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3550 SYSTEM
"/IETF/xml2rfc-1.35/bibxml/reference.RFC.3550.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3605 SYSTEM
"/IETF/xml2rfc-1.35/bibxml/reference.RFC.3605.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3830 SYSTEM
"/IETF/xml2rfc-1.35/bibxml/reference.RFC.3830.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3890 SYSTEM
"/IETF/xml2rfc-1.35/bibxml/reference.RFC.3890.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4091 SYSTEM
"/IETF/xml2rfc-1.35/bibxml/reference.RFC.4091.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4145 SYSTEM
"/IETF/xml2rfc-1.35/bibxml/reference.RFC.4145.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4566 SYSTEM
"/IETF/xml2rfc-1.35/bibxml/reference.RFC.4566.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4567 SYSTEM
"/IETF/xml2rfc-1.35/bibxml/reference.RFC.4567.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4568 SYSTEM
"/IETF/xml2rfc-1.35/bibxml/reference.RFC.4568.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4572 SYSTEM
"/IETF/xml2rfc-1.35/bibxml/reference.RFC.4572.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4574 SYSTEM
"/IETF/xml2rfc-1.35/bibxml/reference.RFC.4574.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4583 SYSTEM
"/IETF/xml2rfc-1.35/bibxml/reference.RFC.4583.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4796 SYSTEM
"/IETF/xml2rfc-1.35/bibxml/reference.RFC.4796.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5027 SYSTEM
"/IETF/xml2rfc-1.35/bibxml/reference.RFC.5027.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5411 SYSTEM
"/IETF/xml2rfc-1.35/bibxml/reference.RFC.5411.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5683 SYSTEM
"/IETF/xml2rfc-1.35/bibxml/reference.RFC.5683.xml">
]>


<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>

<rfc category="info" ipr="trust200902" docName="draft-greevenbosch-mmusic-hitchhikersguide-sdp-00">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="Hitchhiker's guide to SDP">Hitchhiker's guide to the Session Description Protocol (SDP)</title>
    <author initials="B." surname="Greevenbosch" fullname="Bert Greevenbosch">
      <organization abbrev="Huawei Technologies">Huawei Technologies Co., Ltd.</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Huawei Industrial Base</street>
          <street>Bantian, Longgang District</street>
          <city>Shenzhen</city>
          <code>518129</code>
          <country>P.R. China</country>
        </postal>
        <phone>+86-755-28978088</phone>
        <email>bert.greevenbosch@huawei.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date month="April" year="2012"/>
    <area>Real-time Applications and Infrastructure</area>
    <workgroup>mmusic</workgroup>
    <abstract>
      <t>
         The Session Initiation Protocol (SDP) is the subject of numerous
         specifications that have been produced by the IETF.  It can be
         difficult to locate the right document, or even to determine the set
         of Request for Comments (RFC) about SDP.  This specification serves
         as a guide to the SDP RFC series.  It lists a current snapshot of the
         specifications under the SDP umbrella, briefly summarises each, and
         groups them into categories.
      </t>
    </abstract>
    <note title="Note">
      <t>
        Discussion and suggestions for improvement are requested, 
        and should be sent to mmusic@ietf.org.
      </t>
    </note>
  </front>
  <middle>
    <section title="Requirements notation">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL",
        "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY",
        and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as
        described in <xref target="RFC2119"/>.
      </t>
    </section>
    <section title="Introduction">
       <t>
          The Session Description Protocol (SDP) <xref target="RFC4566"/> 
          is the subject of numerous specifications that have been produced by the IETF.  
          It can be difficult to locate the right document, 
          or even to determine the set of Request for Comments (RFC) about SDP.          
       </t>
       <t>
          This specification serves as a guide to the SDP RFC series.  
          It is a current snapshot of the specifications under the SDP umbrella at the time of publication.  
          It is anticipated that this document itself will be regularly updated as SDP specifications mature.  
          Furthermore, it references many specifications, which, 
          at the time of publication of this document, 
          were not yet finalised, 
          and may eventually be completed or abandoned.  
          Therefore, the enumeration of specifications here is a work-in-progress and subject to change.
      </t>
      <t>
         For each specification, 
         a paragraph or so description is included that summarises the purpose of the specification.
         Each specification also includes a letter that designates its category in the Standards Track <xref target="RFC2026"/>.  
         These values are:
         <list>
           <t>S: Standards Track (Proposed Standard, Draft Standard, or Standard)</t>
           <t>E: Experimental</t>
           <t>B: Best Current Practice</t>
           <t>I: Informational</t>
         </list>
      </t>
      <t>
         The specifications are grouped together by topic.  The topics are:
         <list style="hanging">
         
            <t hangText="Core:">
               The SDP specifications that are expected to be utilised for
               each session or registration an endpoint participates in.
            </t>

            <t hangText="General Purpose Infrastructure:">
               General purpose extensions to SDP, 
               but the ones that are not expected to always be used.
            </t>

            <t hangText="NAT Traversal:">
               Specifications to deal with firewall and NAT traversal.
            </t>

            <t hangText="Quality of Service:">
               Specifications related to multimedia quality of service (QoS).
            </t>

            <t hangText="Operations and Management:">
               Specifications related to configuration
               and monitoring of SDP deployments.
            </t>

            <t hangText="Minor Extensions:">
               Specifications that solve a narrow problem space or provide an optimisation.
            </t>

            <t hangText="Security Mechanisms:">
               Specifications providing security functionality for SDP.
            </t>

            <t hangText="Conferencing:">            
              Specifications for multimedia conferencing.
            </t>

         </list>
      </t>
      <t>
         Typically, SDP extensions fit naturally into topic areas, and
         implementors interested in a particular topic often implement many or
         all of the specifications in that area.  There are some
         specifications that fall into multiple topic areas, 
         but generally they will be listed only once.
      </t>
      <t>
         This document itself is not an update to <xref target="RFC4566"/> or an extension to SDP.  
         It is an informational document, meant to guide newcomers, implementers, 
         and deployers to the many specifications associated with SDP.
       </t>
    </section>
    <section title="Core SDP specifications">
       <t>
          <list style="hanging">
             <t hangText="RFC 2327,">
                Session Description Protocol (S):
                <xref target="RFC2327"/> defines the original SDP protocol.
                The RFC has been obsoleted by its successor <xref target="RFC4566"/>.
             </t>
             <t hangText="RFC 3264,">
               An Offer/Answer Model with the Session Description Protocol (S):  
               <xref target="RFC3264"/> defines how SDP is used with 
               SIP <xref target="RFC3261"/> 
               to negotiate the parameters of a media session.  
               It is in widespread usage and an integral part of the
               behaviour of SIP.
             </t>
             <t hangText="RFC 4566,">
                Session Description Protocol (S):  <xref target="RFC4566"/> defines a
                format for representing multimedia sessions.  SDP objects are
                carried in the body of SIP messages and, based on the offer/answer
                model, are used to negotiate the media characteristics of a
                session between users.
             </t>
          </list>
       </t>
    </section>
    <section title="General purpose infrastructure extensions">
       <t>
          <list style="hanging">
             <t hangText="RFC 3266,">
                Support for IPv6 in Session Description Protocol (SDP) (S): 
                <xref target="RFC3266"/> describes the use of Internet Protocol Version 6 (IPv6)
   				addresses in conjunction with the Session Description Protocol (SDP).
   				The document clarifies existing text in SDP in regard to the syntax of IPv6 addresses.
             </t>
             <t hangText="RFC 3388,">
                Grouping of Media Lines in the Session Description Protocol (S):  
                <xref target="RFC3388"/> defines a framework for grouping together
                media streams in an SDP message.  Such a grouping allows
                relationships between these streams, such as which stream is the
                audio for a particular video feed, to be expressed.
             </t>
             <t hangText="RFC 4091,">
                The Alternative Network Address Types (ANAT) Semantics for
                the Session Description Protocol (SDP) Grouping Framework (S):
                <xref target="RFC4091"/> defines a mechanism for including both IPv4 and IPv6
                addresses to establish a media stream.  This mechanism has been
                deprecated in favor of ICE [ICE].
             </t>
             <t hangText="RFC 4145,">
                TCP-Based Media Transport in the Session Description
                Protocol (SDP) (S):  <xref target="RFC4145"/> defines an extension to SDP for
                setting up TCP-based sessions between user agents.  It defines who
                sets up the connection and how its lifecycle is managed.  It has
                seen relatively little usage due to the small number of media
                types to date that use TCP.
             </t>
          </list>          
       </t>
    </section>
    <section title="NAT Traversal">
       <t>
          <list style="hanging">
             <t hangText = "RFC3605,">
                Real Time Control Protocol (RTCP) Attribute in the Session
      			Description Protocol (SDP) (S):  
      			<xref target="RFC3605"/> defines a way to
                explicitly signal, within an SDP message, the IP address and port
                for RTCP, rather than using the port+1 rule in the Real Time
                Transport Protocol (RTP)
                <xref target="RFC3550"/>.  It is needed for devices
                behind NAT, and the specification is required by ICE.
             </t>
          </list>         
       </t>
    </section>
    <section title="Minor extensions">
      <t>
        <list style="hanging">
           <t hangText="RFC3890,">
              A Transport Independent Bandwidth Modifier for the Session
              Description Protocol (SDP) (S):  
              <xref target="RFC3890"/> specifies an SDP
              extension that allows for the description of the bandwidth for a
              media session that is independent of the underlying transport
              mechanism.
            </t>
            <t hangText="RFC 4796,"> The SDP (Session Description Protocol) Content Attribute (S):  
               <xref target="RFC4796"/> defines an SDP attribute for describing the
               purpose of a media stream.  Examples include a slide view, the
               speaker, a sign language feed, and so on.
            </t>
         </list>
      </t>
    </section>
    <section title="Security mechanisms">
      <t>
        <list style="hanging">
           <t hangText="RFC4567,">    
              Key Management Extensions for Session Description Protocol
              (SDP) and Real Time Streaming Protocol (RTSP) (S):  
              <xref target="RFC4567"/>
              defines extensions to SDP that allow tunneling of a key management
              protocol, namely MIKEY <xref target="RFC3830"/>, 
              through offer/answer exchanges.
              This mechanism is one of three Secure Realtime Transport Protocol
              (SRTP) keying techniques specified for SIP, with Datagram
              Transport Layer Security (DTLS)-SRTP <xref target="RFC5683"/> having been
              selected as the final solution.
            </t>
            <t hangText="RFC4568,">
               Session Description Protocol (SDP) Security Descriptions
               for Media Streams (S):  
               <xref target="RFC4568"/>
               defines extensions to SDP that
               allow for the negotiation of keying material directly through
               offer/answer, without a separate key management protocol.  This
               mechanism, sometimes called sdescriptions, has the drawback that
               the media keys are available to any entity that has visibility to
               the SDP.  It is one of three SRTP keying techniques specified for
               SIP, with DTLS-SRTP <xref target="RFC5683"/> having been selected as the final
               solution.
            </t>
            <t hangText="RFC4572,">
               Connection-Oriented Media Transport over the Transport
               Layer Security (TLS) Protocol in the Session Description Protocol
               (SDP) (S):  
               <xref target="RFC4572"/> specifies a mechanism for signaling TLS-
               based media streams between endpoints.  It expands the TCP-based
               media signaling parameters defined in <xref target="RFC4145"/> to include
               fingerprint information for TLS streams so that TLS can operate
               between end hosts using self-signed certificates.
            </t>
            <t hangText="RFC5027,">
               Security Preconditions for Session Description Protocol
      		   Media Streams (S):  
               <xref target="RFC5027"/> 
               defines a precondition for use with
               the preconditions framework 
               <xref target="RFC3312"/>.  The security precondition
               prevents a session from being established until a security media
               stream is set up.
            </t>
         </list>
      </t>
    </section>
    
    <section title="Conferencing">
      <t>
         <list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="RFC4574,">    
               The SDP (Session Description Protocol) Label Attribute
               (S):  <xref target="RFC4574"/> defines an SDP attribute for providing an opaque
               label for media streams.  These labels can be referred to by
               external documents, and in particular, by conference policy
               documents.  This allows a UA to tie together documents it may
               obtain through conferencing mechanisms to media streams to which
               they refer.
            </t>
            <t hangText="RFC4583,">
               Session Description Protocol (SDP) Format for Binary Floor
               Control Protocol (BFCP) Streams (S):  
               <xref target="RFC4583"/> defines a
               mechanism in SDP to signal floor control streams that use BFCP.
               It is used for push-to-talk and conference floor control.
            </t>
         </list>
      </t>
    </section>

    <section title="Documents left to handle">       
       <section title="RFCs">
          <t>
            3108,
            3890,
            4317,
            4570,            
            4583,
            4585,
            5104,
            5432,
            5547,
            5576,
            5583,            
            5888,
            5898,
            5939,
            6236.
         </t>
      </section>
      <section title="Working group drafts">
         <t>
            draft-ietf-mmusic-media-loopback-16,
            draft-ietf-mmusic-parallax-attribute-00,
            draft-ietf-mmusic-rfc4566bis-04,
            draft-ietf-mmusic-sdp-cs-09,
            draft-ietf-mmusic-sdp-media-capabilities-12,
            draft-ietf-mmusic-traffic-class-for-sdp-00,     
            draft-ietf-mmusic-signal-3d-format-00,
            draft-ietf-payload-rtp-mvc.
         </t>
      </section>
      <section title="Individual drafts">
         <t>
            draft-boucadair-mmusic-altc-04,
            draft-boucadair-mmusic-ipv6-use-cases-00,
            draft-boulton-mmusic-sdp-control-package-attribute-07,
            draft-holmberg-mmusic-sdp-bundle-negotiation-00,
            draft-lennox-mmusic-sdp-source-selection-03,
            draft-petithuguenin-mmusic-ice-attributes-level-02,
            draft-westerlund-mmusic-sdp-bw-attribute-00.
         </t>
      </section>	   
    </section>
    <section title="Security Considerations">
       <t>
          This specification is an overview of existing specifications and does
   	      not introduce any security considerations on its own.
   	   </t>
    </section>
    <section title="Acknowledgements">
       <t>
          The author would like to thank Jonathan Rosenberg, 
          the author of "A Hitchhiker's guide to the Session Initiation Protocol (SIP)" <xref target="RFC5411"/>, 
          which served as basis for this document,
          and from which much text was copied. 
       </t>
       <t>
          The title of this document was inspired by the "The Hitchhiker's Guide to the Galaxy" <xref target="HGTTG"/>.
       </t>
    </section>
  </middle>
  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
       &RFC2026;
       &RFC2119;
       &RFC2327;
       &RFC3261;
       &RFC3264;
       &RFC3266;
       &RFC3312;
       &RFC3388;
       &RFC3550;
       &RFC3605;
       &RFC3830;
       &RFC3890;
       &RFC4091;
       &RFC4145;
       &RFC4566;
       &RFC4567;
       &RFC4568;
       &RFC4572;
       &RFC4574;
       &RFC4583;
       &RFC4796;
       &RFC5027;
       &RFC5411;
       &RFC5683;
       <reference anchor="HGTTG">
         <front>
           <title>The Hitchhiker's Guide to the Galaxy</title>
           <author initials="D." surname="Adams"/>                       
           <date month="September" year="1979"/>
         </front>
         <seriesInfo name="TS" value="26.234 v5.3.0"/>
       </reference>
    </references>
    
  </back>

</rfc>