<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>

<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<?rfc strict="no"?>
<?rfc rfcedstyle="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY rfc2119 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc2743 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2743.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc2865 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2865.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc3748 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3748.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc4279 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4279.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc4401 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4401.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc4559 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4559.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc5246 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5246.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc5247 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5247.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.ietf-abfab-gss-eap SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-abfab-gss-eap.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.ietf-radext-radsec SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-radext-radsec.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.ietf-emu-chbind SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-emu-chbind.xml">
]>

<rfc category="info" docName="draft-howlett-radsec-knp-02" ipr="trust200902">
    <front>
        <title abbrev="KNP">Key Negotiation Protocol (KNP)</title>
        <author initials="J." surname="Howlett" fullname="Josh Howlett">
            <organization>JANET(UK)</organization>
            <address>
                <postal>
                    <street>Lumen House, Library Avenue, Harwell</street>
                    <city>Oxford</city>
                    <code>OX11 0SG</code>
                    <country>UK</country>
                </postal>
                <phone>+44 1235 822363</phone>
                <email>Josh.Howlett@ja.net</email>
            </address>
        </author>
        <author initials="S." surname="Hartman" fullname="Sam Hartman">
            <organization>Painless Security</organization>
            <address>
                <email>hartmans-ietf@mit.edu</email>
            </address>
        </author>

        <date  year="2011" />
        <area>Security Area</area>
        <keyword>Internet-Draft</keyword>
        <keyword>Federated Authentication</keyword>
        <keyword>RADIUS</keyword>
        <keyword>RADIUS</keyword>
        <keyword>GSS-API</keyword>
        <keyword>EAP</keyword>

        <abstract>
            <t>
		The Key Negotiation Protocol enables an untrusting RADIUS client and RADIUS server to derive
		a key by reference to a mutually trusted actor called the Introducer. This key may subsequently 
		be used for one of two purposes. First, it can credential a TLS PSK ciphersuite applied to a 
		RadSec connection between the RADIUS client and RADIUS server; or secondly, to establish a 
		trust relationship between the RADIUS client and a second Introducer that is trusted by the first Introducer.
	    </t>
	    <t>
		The composition of these capabilities enables a RADIUS client to establish a RadSec connection with
		any RADIUS server with whom it shares a direct or indirect trust relationship via one or more Introducers.
	    </t>
        </abstract>
    </front>

    <middle>
        <section title="Introduction">
            <t>
                TLS encryption for RADIUS (RadSec) <xref target="I-D.ietf-radext-radsec" />
                provides a mechanism for securing the communication between a RADIUS <xref target="RFC2865" /> client and 
		server on the transport layer by using TLS <xref target="RFC5246" />.
            </t>
            <t>
                RadSec mandates the use of one of the <xref target="RFC5246" /> ciphersuites and
                recommends the use of two other ciphersuites specified in that document. However any
                ciphersuite, including the TLS Pre-Shared Key (PSK) ciphersuites <xref target="RFC4279" />,
                may be used providing that it supports encryption.
            </t>
            <t>
		The Key Negotiation Protocol enables an untrusting RADIUS client 
		and RADIUS server to derive a key by means of a mutually trusted actor called the Introducer. 
		This key may subsequently for two purposes.
	    </t>
	    <t>
		First, the key can be used to credential a TLS PSK ciphersuite when applied to a RadSec connection between the RADIUS client and 
		RADIUS server, permitting a trusted exchange of RADIUS messages in the absence of a pre-existing
		relationship between the RADIUS client and RADIUS server. This is described as "Credentialing".
	    </t>
	    <t>
		Secondly, the key can used as a credential by a RADIUS client to establish a trust relationship
		with a second Introducer that happens to be trusted by the first Introducer. This is described as 
		"Introduction".
            </t>
	    <t>
		The composition of Credentialing and Introduction enables a RADIUS client to establish a RadSec connection with
		any RADIUS server with whom it shares an indirect trust relationship via one or more Introducers.
	    </t>
        </section>

        <section title="Motivation">
            <t>
                The KNP is motivated by the following requirements:
                <list style="symbols">
                    <t>
			In the case of a non-federated RADIUS environment where a RADIUS client and RADIUS §server shares a direct 
			trust relationship, a shared secret credential is used as the trust anchor between these
			systems. In transitioning to the use of RadSec, it may be more convenient if these systems are 
			able to continue using the existing credential technology rather than introduce a new credential
			technology (such as X.509 certificates), as this may impose significant changes to operational 
			practices (such as deploying a Public Key Infrastructure).
                    </t>
                    <t>
			In the case of a federated RADIUS environment where RADIUS clients and RADIUS servers are associated
			with different domains, transitioning to the use of RadSec may impose a requirement to distribute
			and manage multiple trust anchors. It may be more convenient if the systems within these domains were able to
			use a single trust anchor for RADIUS systems in all other domains, in addition to those systems
			within its own domain. This may facilitate the scaling of large heterogeneous RADIUS environments
                        where it may be difficult - for technical and/or administrative reasons - to impose support for even
			a small set of trust anchors.
                    </t>
		    <t> 
			The use of multiple trust anchors within complex federated environments may impede 
			essential trust management functions such as timely revocation. Reducing the number of trust anchors
			may therefore improve trust management within these environments, particularly if it can be
			reduced to a single trust anchor. 
                    </t>
                </list>
            </t>
        </section>

	<section title="Overview">
	    <t>
                The Key Negotiation Protocol (KNP) enables a RADIUS client and RADIUS server that do not share a
		direct trust relationship to derive a shared key by virtue of both systems having a trust relationship with an
		EAP server called the Introducer. This key may be used for the following purposes:
                <list style="numbers">
            	    <t>
			Credentialing: the RADIUS client and RADIUS server can use the key to credential a TLS PSK ciphersuite
			applied to a RadSec connection.
                    </t>
                    <t>
			Introduction: a credential can be derived from the key that can be used to authenticate the RADIUS 
			client against a second Introducer that is trusted by the first Introducer.
                    </t>
                </list>
            </t>
            <t>
                The composition of these capabilities enables a RADIUS client to derive a key that can be used to credential
		a RadSec connection with any other RADIUS server with whom it shares a common Introducer and, through transitivity,
		any number of intermediate Introducers.
            </t>
            <t>
                This transitivity of trust between a RADIUS client and RADIUS server across a chain of intermediate Introducers may 
		appear very similar to the use of RADIUS proxies to establish a chain of trust between a RADIUS client and 
		RADIUS server. There is however a very significant difference:
		<list style="symbols">
		    <t>
		        In the case of RADIUS proxy, the RADIUS messages emitted by the RADIUS client and RADIUS 
			server must transit through the intermediate RADIUS proxy(ies). There is no end-to-end
			relationship between the RADIUS client and RADIUS server, either in terms of connectivity or trust.
		    </t>
		    <t>
			In the case of KNP, the RADIUS messages are able to transit directly between RADIUS client 
			and RADIUS server. The path of transmissions between these systems is therefore entirely 
			decoupled from the path of trust . There is an end-to-end relationship between the RADIUS
			client and RADIUS server, both in terms of connectivity and trust.
		    </t>
		</list>
	    </t>
	    <t>
		The use of RADIUS Proxies and Introducers are not mutually exclusive; deployers may choose to use both.
	    </t>
	</section>

        <section title="Conventions used in this document">
            <t>
                The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", 
		"RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in 
		RFC 2119 <xref target="RFC2119" />.
            </t>
        </section>
        
        <section title="The KNP Actors">
            <t>
                In the KNP, the RADIUS client and RADIUS server do not initially share a trust relationship. 
		Instead, these actors share a trust relationship with a mutually trusted 
		third party known as the "Introducer".
            </t>
            <t>
                Figure 1 below depicts the trust relationships for a RADIUS client, RADIUS server and 
		Introducer before the KNP has been invoked.
            </t>
            <figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[
                                Introducer
                                    /\
                                   /  \
                                  /    \
                            RADIUS      RADIUS
                            Client      Server

                                Figure 1
            ]]></artwork>
            </figure>
            <t>
                Figure 2 below depicts the new trust relationship between the RADIUS client, RADIUS server 
		and Introducer after the KNP has been invoked.
            </t>
            <figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[
                                Introducer
                                    /\
                                   /  \
                                  /    \
                            RADIUS------RADIUS
                            Client      Server

                                Figure 2
            ]]></artwork>
            </figure>
            <t>
                Figure 3 below depicts the flow of RADIUS packets from the RADIUS client to the RADIUS 
		server using the new trust relationship.
            </t>
            <figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[
                                Introducer



                            RADIUS ---> RADIUS
                            Client      Server

                                Figure 3
            ]]></artwork>
            </figure>
	    <t>
		Note that the RADIUS messages are not routed by the Introducer, as they would in the case
		of a RADIUS Proxy. Instead, they flow directly from RADIUS client to RADIUS server.
	    </t>
        </section>

        <section title="Relationships With Other Protocols">
            <t>
                The KNP builds on a variety of protocols. This section describes the relationship of KNP to these.
            </t>
            <section title="Relationship to EAP">
                <t>
		    In the KNP the RADIUS client assumes the role of an EAP peer. In this role, it attempts to authenticate
		    against a RADIUS server that assumes the role of a pass-through EAP authenticator. An EAP
		    server acts as the Introducer.
                </t>
                <t>
                    The KNP enables all three actors - RADIUS client (EAP peer), RADIUS server (EAP authenticator) 
		    and Introducer (EAP server) - to establish a common view of their mutual relationships as 
		    described by the EAP names and keys that the EAP exchange yields, using the norms established 
		    by the EAP Key Management Framework <xref target="RFC5247" />.
                </t>
                <t>
                    The RADIUS client must possess an EAP credential for the Introducer, allowing mutual 
		    authentication of both parties.
                </t>
                <t>
                    Figure 4 below depicts the relationships between these actors:
                </t>
                <figure>
                <artwork><![CDATA[
                                Introducer
                                    /\
                                   /  \
                                  /    \
                            RADIUS      RADIUS
                            Client      Server
                (possessing an EAP
                    credential for
                   the Introducer)

                                Figure 4
                ]]></artwork>
                </figure>
            </section>

            <section title="Relationship to RADIUS">
               <t>
                    The RADIUS server uses the RADIUS protocol to forward the EAP transaction to the Introducer.
                </t>
                <t>
                    The RADIUS server must share a RADIUS secret with the Introducer, allowing mutual 
		    authentication of both actors.
                </t>
                <t>
                    Figure 5 below depicts the relationships between these actors:
                </t>
                <figure>
                <artwork><![CDATA[
                               Introducer
                                    /\
                                   /  \
                                  /    \
                            RADIUS      RADIUS
                            Client      Server
                (possessing an EAP      (possessing a RADIUS
                    credential for      secret for
                   the Introducer)      the Introducer)

                                Figure 5
                ]]></artwork>
                </figure>
            </section>

            <section title="Relationship to the GSS API">
                <t>
                    The KNP builds on the GSS API <xref target="RFC2743" /> framework by using the GSS EAP mechanism 
		    <xref target="I-D.ietf-abfab-gss-eap" /> and EAP <xref target="RFC3748" />. The GSS EAP tokens
                    are transported between the RADIUS client and RADIUS server using the HTTP Negotiate authentication scheme 
		    <xref target="RFC4559" />.
                </t>
            </section>
            <section title="Relationship to the HTTP">
                <t>
		    The KNP uses HTTP to transport its request and response protocol messages between the RADIUS Client
		    and RADIUS server.
                </t>
            </section>

        </section>
          
        <section title="Key Negotiation Protocol">
	    <t>
		As described previously, the KNP provides two operations: Credentialing and Introduction.
	    </t>
            <t>
		The KNP provides these operations using a common protocol pattern. This
		pattern is applied against two types of Target actor, depending on the operation in question:
	 	<list style="symbols">
		    <t>
			In the case of Credentialing, the Target actor is a RADIUS server. If Credentialing is 
			successful, the RADIUS client and RADIUS server will derive a common PSK that can be 
			applied with a TLS-PSK ciphersuite and RadSec.
		    </t>
		    <t>
			In the case of Introduction, the Target actor is an Introducer. If an Introduction is
			successful, the RADIUS client and Introducer will derive an EAP credential that can
			subsequently be used for subsequent Credentialing or Introduction operations.
		    </t>
		</list>
            </t>
            <t>
                For both operations it is essential that all three actors - RADIUS Client, Introducer and 
		Target (whether a RADIUS server, in the case of Credentialing, or another Introducer, in the
		case of Introduction) - are able to authorise the claims that the other actors make about their
		respective names. These claims are validated using different processes for each relationship; 
		these are summarised in Figure 6 below.
            </t>
            <figure>
                <artwork><![CDATA[
+===============+===============+==================+===============+
|    Subject    | Relying Party |     Process      | Evidence from |
+===============+===============+==================+===============+
| RADIUS Client |  Introducer   |     GSS EAP      |  EAP method   |
+---------------+---------------+  authentication  | w/ qualifying |
|  Introducer   | RADIUS Client |                  |Security Claims|
+===============+===============+==================+===============+
|  Introducer   |     Target    |      RADIUS      |     RADIUS    |
+---------------+---------------+  authentication  |     shared    |
|    Target     |  Introducer   |                  |     secret    |
+===============+===============+==================+===============+
|    Target     |     RADIUS    | Channel bindings | Assertion by  |
|               |     Client    |                  |  Introducer   |
+---------------+---------------+------------------+---------------+
|    RADIUS     |     Target    | RADIUS attribute | Assertion by  |
|    Client     |               |                  |  Introducer   |
+===============+===============+==================+===============+
                            Figure 6
                ]]></artwork>
                </figure>
                
                <section title="Operation Independent Flow" anchor="KNP_Operation">
                    <t>
			The RADIUS Client invokes the KNP by establishing an HTTP connection with the Target's
			KNP end-point.
                    </t>
                    <t>
			The RADIUS Client MUST use the GSS EAP mechanism <xref target="I-D.ietf-abfab-gss-eap" /> 
			to authenticate to the Introducer, requesting mutual authentication from the GSS layer.
                    </t>
		    <t>
			The RADIUS Client, Target and Introducer MUST support EAP channel bindings 
			<xref target="I-D.ietf-emu-chbind" />. The Introducer MUST use validate the EAP channel bindings 
			<xref target="I-D.ietf-emu-chbind" /> provided by the RADIUS Client. If the 
			channel binding verification fails, the Introducer MUST reject the authentication.
                    </t>
                    <t>
                        The completion of the EAP method exchange results in the derivation of an EAP MSK known only 
		        to the RADIUS Client and Introducer and Peer-Id(s) and Server-Id(s) identifying these respectively. The 
		        Introducer MUST replicate the keying material and Server-Id to the Target.
                    </t>
                    <t>
                        The RADIUS Client and Target, in possession of the EAP MSK, create a GSS-API security 
    		        context as described in section 6 of <xref target="I-D.ietf-abfab-gss-eap" />.
                    </t>
		    <t>
			The RADIUS Client POSTs a key negotiation request, encoded as an HTML form dataset, to the 
			Target. This request contains a set of operation-specific controls that specifies key negotiation parameters.
			A key negotiation request MUST contain the following controls:
			<list style="symbols">
			    <t>Version: the version of the KNP.</t>
			    <t>Request-Identifier: a unique alphanumeric identifier for the request.</t>
			    <t>Requestor-Name: the requestor's GSS EAP initiator name.</t>
			    <t>Operation-Type: the type of operation.</t>
			    <t>Authenticator-Type: message authentication algorithm.</t>
			    <t>Authenticator-Value: message authenticator value.</t>
			</list>
                    </t>
                    <t>
			The Target extracts the key negotiation parameters and assesses their compliance to 
			the Target's key negotiation policies. The Target MUST return an operation-specific document 
			providing information about the resulting key negotiation context.
			<list style="symbols">
			    <t>Version: the version of the KNP.</t>
			    <t>Request-Identifier: the identifier for the request that this is a reponse to.</t>
			    <t>Responder-Name: the requestor's GSS EAP acceptor name.</t>
			    <t>Operation-Type: the type of operation.</t>
			    <t>Status-Code: a status code.</t>
			    <t>Expires-After: a timestamp indicating the time of expiration.</t>
			    <t>Authenticator-Type: message authentication algorithm.</t>
			    <t>Authenticator-Value: message authenticator value.</t>
			</list>
		    </t>
		    <t>
			TODO: consider use of SAML authentication assertion instead?
		    </t>
            	    <t>
                	The RADIUS server and client SHOULD cache the GSS context until expiry of the GSS context. However, 
			either party MAY delete a GSS context at any time. If a GSS context is deleted, 
			any operation-specific derived materials SHOULD also be deleted, although such materials MAY be retained
			for auditing purposes.
            	    </t>
                </section>
            
            	<section title="The Credentialing Operation">
		    <t>
		        This section describes the Credentialing operation-specific extensions to the general KNP flow.
		    </t>
		    <t>
			The RADIUS Client MUST specify the following control values within the key negotiation request:
			<list style="symbols">
			    <t>Operation-Type: Credentialing</t>
			</list>
		    </t>
                    <t>
                        The PSK identity and value shall be outputs of GSS_Pseudo_random() <xref target="RFC4401" /> 
		        using the Pseudo-Random Function defined for the GSS EAP mechanism <xref target="I-D.ietf-abfab-gss-eap" />.
                    </t>
                    <t>
                        For the PSK identity, the prf_in input string MUST be prepended with the string 
		        "tls-psk-knp-identity"; desired_out_len MUST be set to 128 octets.
                    </t>
                    <t>
                        For the PSK value, the prf_in input string MUST be prepended with the string "tls-psk-knp-value"; 
		        desired_out_len MUST be set to 64 octets.
                    </t>
                    <t>
                        Note: these output values should use base64 encoding
                    </t>
                </section>

                <section title="The Introduction Operation">
		    <t>
		        This section describes the Introduction operation-specific extensions to the general KNP flow.
		    </t>
		    <t>
			The RADIUS Client MUST specify the following control values within the key negotiation request:
			<list style="symbols">
			    <t>Operation-Type: Introduction"</t>
			</list>
		    </t>
                    <t>
                        The EAP identity and credential shall be outputs of GSS_Pseudo_random() <xref target="RFC4401" /> 
		        using the Pseudo-Random Function defined for the GSS EAP mechanism <xref target="I-D.ietf-abfab-gss-eap" />.
                    </t>
                    <t>
                        For the EAP identity, the prf_in input string MUST be prepended with the string 
		        "tls-psk-eap-identity"; desired_out_len MUST be set to 128 octets. The output string MUST
			be appended with the realm of the Introducer to form an NAI.
                    </t>
                    <t>
                        For the EAP credential, the prf_in input string MUST be prepended with the string "tls-psk-eap-psk"; 
		        desired_out_len MUST be set to 64 octets.
                    </t>
                    <t>
                        Note: these output values should use base64 encoding.
                    </t>
                </section>
            </section>

        <section title="Security Considerations">
            <t>
                TODO
            </t>
        </section>
        
        <section title="IANA Considerations">
            <t>
		TODO
            </t>
        </section>        

        <section title="Acknowledgements">
            <t>
                TODO
            </t>
        </section>        
        
    </middle>

    <back>
        <references title="Normative References">
            &rfc2119;
            &rfc2743;
            &rfc2865;
            &rfc3748;
            &rfc4279;
            &rfc4401;
            &rfc4559;
            &rfc5246;
            &rfc5247;
            &I-D.ietf-abfab-gss-eap;
            &I-D.ietf-radext-radsec;
            &I-D.ietf-emu-chbind;
        </references>

        </back>
</rfc>
