<?xml version="1.0" encoding="us-ascii"?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
  <!ENTITY rfc5890 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5890.xml">
]>

<?rfc compact="yes" ?>

<rfc category="std" docName="draft-yoneya-dns-variant-label-rr-00" ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="VL RR">Variant Label Resource Record</title>

    <author fullname="Yoshiro Yoneya" initials="Y" surname="Yoneya">
      <organization>JPRS</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Chiyoda First Bldg. East 13F</street>
          <street>3-8-1 Nishi-Kanda</street>
          <city>Chiyoda-ku</city>
          <region>Tokyo</region>
          <code>101-0065</code>
          <country>Japan</country>
        </postal>
        <phone>+81 3 5215 8451</phone>
        <email>yoshiro.yoneya@jprs.co.jp</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date day="18" month="February" year="2013"/>

    <abstract>
      <t>
        Definition and operation of variant domain names are differ
        from zone administrators, and there is no generic rules,
        therefore, in general, it is hard to guess variant labels for
        end users and / or applications.  Meanwhile, zone
        administrators are understanding all variant labels list
        because they generate variant labels and activate them
        according to rules they defined.  Thus, if there is a
        mechanism that end users and / or applications can obtain
        variant labels list from zone administrators, then it would be
        useful.  The Variant Labels Resource Record (VL RR) provides
        such variant labels list for that purpose.
      </t>
    </abstract>

  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>
        Some of the zone administrators such as TLD registries that
        accepting IDNs are bundling variants as a package.  Also, in
        conjunction with the deployment of IDN TLDs, consideration of
        Variant IDN TLD is in progress.  It is hard to guess variant
        labels list from short string that does not have context like
        domain name, because definition of variants are differ from
        languages even though using the same script.  The zone
        administrators such as registries have complete list of
        variant labels for a label, so if they have mechanism to
        provide the list, end users and / or applications can obtain
        variant labels list without guessing.  The Variant Labels
        Resource Record (VL RR) is a new DNS RR that provides variant
        labels for a label.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section title="Definition of VL RR">
      <t>
        VL RR format is as follows:
      </t>
      <figure><artwork><![CDATA[
variant1 TTL IN VL priority1 variant1.
                   priority2 variant2.
                   priority3 variant3.
      ]]></artwork></figure>
      <t>
        Here, the variant1 is a variant label in a query name, the
        variant1, variant2 and the variant3 are the list of variant
	labels for the variant1.  The values of right hand side can be
	listed multiple times as RRset like other RRs.  Period at the
	end can't be omitted.  If the variant label is IDN, then it
	must be written in A-label <xref target="RFC5890"/>.  The
	priority1, priority2 and priority3 are the integer numbers
	which indicate priorities for the variant1, variant2 and
	variant3 respectively.  The smallest number means that the
	variant label is the canonical label.
      </t>
      <t>
        All variant labels must be defined inside of one zone, and
        they can't refer labels outside of the zone.
      </t>
      <t>
        The VL RR can't set to the zone apex.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section title="Behaviour of full resolvers">
      <t>
        The full resolvers send VL RR query to the authoritative DNS
        server(s) for the FQDN which is generated from the query name
        omitting most left label (parent zone authoritative DNS
        server(s)) and get response.  The full resolvers may cache the
        response during the TTL time.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section title="Behaviour of authoritative DNS servers">
      <t>
        The authoritative DNS servers must ignore VL RR which is set
        to the zone apex.  The authoritative DNS servers respond
        NXDOMAIN for queries to non-existent label.  The authoritative
        DNS servers respond VL RRset for queries to existing label if
        it has VL RRs, or respond NOERROR for queries to existing
        label if it does not have VL RRs.
      </t>
      <t>
        The full resolvers which is not VL RR capable can't send
        queries to the parent zone's authoritative DNS server(s),
        therefore, it can't obtain VL RR for the zone apex actively.
        Thus, parent zone's authoritative DNS server(s) should respond
        VL RRset in additional section when it respond NS RRset.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section title="Behaviour of applications">
      <t>
        The applications treat a label with most small number priority
        as a canonical label from list of variant labels obtained by
        the query.  Other labels may be displayed to the users as list
        of variant labels.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section title="Issues of VL RR">
      <t>
        The VL RR increases volume of large zone such as TLD
        registries have.  This will impact zone generation and / or
        zone transfer.
      </t>
      <t>
        Deployment of VL RR aware applications will increases queries
        to Root zone or TLD zones.  This will impact Root / TLD
        authoritative servers in performance and / or bandwidth.
      </t>
      <t>
        The zone administrators who will introduce VL RR are
        recommended to have enough assessment previously with
        recognition above.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>
        IANA is required to assign VL RR type and number.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section title="Security Considerations">
      <t>
        Because the VL RR can set many variant labels, it can be a source of DNS
        amplifier attack.  The zone administrators can avoid this
        issue by suppressing number of activating variant labels
        appropriately.
      </t>
    </section>

  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative references">
      &rfc5890;
    </references>

  </back>
</rfc>
