<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
	  <!ENTITY RFC2119 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
	  <!ENTITY RFC2865 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2865.xml">
	  <!ENTITY RFC3484 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3484.xml">
	  <!ENTITY RFC4291 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4291.xml">
	  <!ENTITY RFC5969 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5969.xml">
	  <!ENTITY RFC6146 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6146.xml">
	  <!ENTITY RFC6219 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6219.xml">
	  <!ENTITY I-D.ietf-softwire-dual-stack-lite SYSTEM
		   "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-softwire-dual-stack-lite.xml"> 
		<!ENTITY I-D.ietf-behave-v4v6-bih SYSTEM
		   "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-behave-v4v6-bih.xml"> 
		<!ENTITY I-D.ietf-softwire-ds-lite-tunnel-option SYSTEM
		   "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-softwire-ds-lite-tunnel-option.xml"> 
	  <!ENTITY I-D.zhang-behave-nat64-load-balancing SYSTEM
		   "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.zhang-behave-nat64-load-balancing.xml"> 
	  ]>


<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt'?>
<?rfc strict="yes"?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>

<rfc category="info" docName="draft-li-v6ops-load-balancing-requirement-00"
     ipr="trust200902">

  <front>
    <title abbrev="Load Balancing in IPv4/IPv6 Transition">
      Analysis on Load Balancing Requirement in IPv4/IPv6 Transition
    </title>

    <author initials="Z" surname="Li" fullname="Zhenqiang Li">
      <organization>China Mobile</organization>
      <address><postal>
	  <street>
	    Unit2, Dacheng Plaza, No. 28 Xuanwumenxi Ave, Xicheng District
	  </street>  
	  <city>Beijing</city><code>100053</code><country>P.R. China</country>
	</postal>
	<email>lizhenqiang@chinamobile.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

   <author initials="Q" surname="Zhao" fullname="Qin Zhao">
      <organization>Beijing University of Posts and Telecommunications</organization>
      <address><postal>
	  <street>Information Network Center, No. 10 Xitucheng Road, Haidian District
    </street>
	  <city>Beijing</city><code>100876</code><country>P.R. China</country>
	</postal>
	<email>zhaoqin@bupt.edu.cn</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    
    <author initials="X" surname="Huang" fullname="Xiaohong Huang">
      <organization>Beijing University of Posts and Telecommunications</organization>
      <address><postal>
	  <street>Information Network Center, No. 10 Xitucheng Road, Haidian District
    </street>
	  <city>Beijing</city><code>100876</code><country>P.R. China</country>
	</postal>
	<email>huangxh@bupt.edu.cn</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author initials="Y" surname="Ma" fullname="Yan Ma">
      <organization>Beijing University of Posts and Telecommunications</organization>
      <address><postal>
	  <street>Information Network Center, No. 10 Xitucheng Road, Haidian District
    </street>
	  <city>Beijing</city><code>100876</code><country>P.R. China</country>
	</postal>
	<email>mayan@bupt.edu.cn</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    
    <author initials="X" surname="Xu" fullname="Xiaohu Xu">
      <organization>Huawei Technologies Co.,Ltd</organization>
      <address><postal>
	  <street>KuiKe Building, No.9 Xinxi Rd., Haidian District
    </street>
	  <city>Beijing</city><code>100085</code><country>P.R. China</country>
	</postal>
	<email>xuxiaohu@huawei.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
     
    <date month="July" day="4" year="2011"/>
    <area>Operations and Management Area</area>
    <workgroup>v6ops</workgroup>
    <abstract>
      <t>
	This document first analyzes the critical issues of bottlenecks in existing tunneling and
   translation technologies, which can be solved by proper
   load balancing mechanisms(e,g., scalability, availability, and single point of failure). 
   Then, several key factors in designing a valid load
   balancing mechanism are described.  Solutions to specific load
   balancing requirements can be drawn out by considering these factors.
   At last, current efforts about load balancing are introduced.
      </t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section anchor="intro" title="Introduction">
      <t>
  Since the depletion of IPv4 address, IPv6 is being introduced into existing networks and IPv4 will be gradually replaced by IPv6.
      </t>
      
      <t>
	The Current Internet is almost fully built on IPv4. IPv6 is fundamentally incompatible with IPv4. The smooth and incremental transition from IPv4 to IPv6 is vital to IPv6's success. IPv6 transition technologies are generally classified into three catigories: dual stack, tunneling (e.g., 6RD<xref target='RFC5969'/>, DS-Lite<xref target='I-D.ietf-softwire-dual-stack-lite'/>) and translation (e.g. , NAT64<xref target='RFC6146'/>, IVI<xref target='RFC6219'/>, BIH<xref target='I-D.ietf-behave-v4v6-bih'/>).
      </t>

      <t>
	Dual stack technology can gradually steer traffic from IPv4 network to IPv6 network by using the address selection policy that generally "IPv6 prior to IPv4", as specified in <xref target='RFC3484'/>.
      </t>

 <t>
	Both tunneling and translation technologies introduce traffic concentration points, the tunnel end-point in tunneling technology and the translation gateway in translation technology. When the scope of IPv6 deployment continuously expands and the traffic of IPv6 business gradually grows, traffic concentration points usually bare very heavy work load. These concentration points will become bottlenecks and the sources of the single point of failure. To address such issues,load balancing mechanism should be considered.
      </t>
      
       <t>
	This document firstly analyzes these problems caused by the centralized points imposed in the current tunneling and translation solutions. These problems are expected to be solved by proper load balancing mechanisms. Secondly, several key factors in designing such load balancing mechanisms are analyzed. Finally, current efforts about load balancing are analyzed and concluded.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section title="Requirements Language">
      <t>
	The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
	"SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in
	this document are to be interpreted as described in
	<xref target='RFC2119'/>. 
      </t>
    </section>

    <section title="Terminology">
      <t>
	The terminology used in this document is consistent with 6rd<xref target='RFC5969'/>, NAT64<xref target='RFC6146'/>, IVI<xref target='RFC6219'/>, DS-Lite<xref target='I-D.ietf-softwire-dual-stack-lite'/>. Besides, the following terminology is defined.
      </t>

      <t>
	Load-balancer: A system which distributes users’ workload across multiple devices providing identical services.
      </t>
      
      <t>
	Target Device: The device to which a load-balancer distributes workload. That is the concentration points of the tunneling and translation technologies.
      </t>
      
      <t>
	Selection policy: The Policy by which the load-balancer selects target device.
      </t>
      
      <t>
	Transport protocol: The protocol the load balancer uses to delivery information of selected target device to user.
      </t>				
    </section>

    <section title="Problems of Bottlenecks">
      <t>
	During the coexistence of IPv4 and IPv6, more and more IPv6 traffic will be carried on IPv4 network or IPv4 Internet in the form of 6in4 tunnel such as 6RD<xref target='RFC5969'/>. Similarly, more and more IPv4 traffic will be guided to IPv6 network or IPv6 Internet in the form of 4in6 tunnel such as DS-Lite <xref target='I-D.ietf-softwire-dual-stack-lite'/>. Both DS-Lite and 6RD concentrate all the tunnel traffic at the tunnel end-points in the service provider network. These tunnel end-points are traffic concentration points which are potential bottlenecks.
      </t>
      
      <t>
	During the evolution from IPv4 to IPv6, IPv6 users will communicate with IPv4 network or IPv4 Internet in the form of 6->4 translation such as NAT64<xref target='RFC6146'/>. Similarly, some IPv4 users will visit IPv6 network or IPv6 Internet in the form of 4->6 translation such as IVI<xref target='RFC6219'/>. Both NAT64 and IVI convert all the translation traffic at the translation gateways in service provider network. These translation gateways are traffic concentration points or potential bottlenecks.
      </t>
      
      <t>
	There are many problems about bottlenecks.
	<list>
	  <t>
	    1. The performance of a single concentration point cannot satisfy the increasing workload.
	  </t>
	  <t>
	    2. Drive traffic through roundabout path.
	  </t>
	  <t>
	    3. Involve a single point of failure.
	  </t>
	</list>
      </t>
 
    <t>
	    In order to avoid becoming bottleneck, traffic concentration point should be distributed to multiple parallel points. Each parallel point performs the same operations. There must be some load-balancing mechanisms to make parallel points collaborate with one another stably, smartly and efficiently.
	  </t>     
    </section>

 <section title="Keys To the Load-balancing Solutions">
      <t>
	In order to keep transition technology always available when traffic growing from small to large scale, some load balancing approaches should be applied at IPv4/IPv6 conjunction points. There are four categories requirements for load balancing scheme. Different solutions or mechanisms may be concluded when necessary to meet the requirements of each. The four categories requirements are: Target Device, Selection policy, Transport protocol and Load-balancer location.	
      </t>
      
      <section  title="Target Device">
        <t>
        As mentioned above, the target device can be tunnel end-point or translation gateway in service provider network.
        </t>
        
        <section  title="Tunnel End-Point">
	        <t>
	        In DS-Lite, such device is AFTR (Address Family Transition Router element) which is 4in6 tunnel concentration point and NAPT44 address port translator. In 6RD, such device is BR (Border Relay) which is only a 6in4 tunnel concentration point.
	        </t>      
         </section>
         
         <section  title="Translation Gateway">
	        <t>
	        In NAT64, such device is stateful NAT64 device which is IPv6 to IPv4 protocol address translator. In IVI, such device is IVI translator which is the mapping and translation gateway.
	        </t>      
         </section>
      </section>
      
      <section  title="Selection Policy">
        <t>
        <xref target='I-D.zhang-behave-nat64-load-balancing'/> has proposed some kinds of prefix64 selection policies for NAT64 load balancing. Those policies can also be applied to general load balancing selection policy in addition to Subscriber-Based Policy.
        </t>
        
        <section  title="Anycast-Based Selection Policy">
	        <t>
	        It requires a load-balancer to select target device according to whether target device and involved routers support anycast<xref target='RFC4291'/>.
	        </t>      
         </section>
         
         <section  title="Source-Based Selection Policy">
	        <t>
	        It requires a load-balancer to select target device according to the IPv6 address of user device.
	        </t>      
         </section>
         
         <section  title="Destination-Based Selection Policy">
	        <t>
	        It requires a load-balancer to choose target device according to e.g., the FQDN, the IPv4/IPv6 address, or other identifiers of destination servers.
	        </t>      
         </section>
         
         <section  title="Round-Robin Selection Policy">
	        <t>
	        It requires a load-balancer to select target device and destination servers circularly according to the arrival request.
	        </t>      
         </section>
         
          <section  title="Subscriber-Based Policy">
	        <t>
	        It requires a load-balancer to choose target device according to the subscriber's information, which can be stored in AAA servers, for example.
	        </t>      
         </section>
         
         <section  title="Dynamic Selection Policy">
	        <t>
	        It requires a load-balancer to select target device according to the real-time status of target device.
	        </t>      
         </section>
      </section>
      
      <section  title="Transport Protocol">
        <t>
        According to the selection policy, one or more target devices may be chosen by load-balancer. There are different protocols can be used to transport the results to user device.
        </t>
        
        <section  title="DNS">
	        <t>
	        DNS protocol carries response results to DNS queries. If result is IPv6 address with network specific IPv6 prefix, traffic can be lead to relevant translation gateway. If result is IPv6 address of tunnel end-point in service provider network, traffic can be lead to relevant tunnel concentration point.
	        </t>      
         </section>
         
         <section  title="DHCP">
	        <t>
	        DHCPv4 or DHCPv6 protocol sends network configuration parameters to user device. The parameters may contain network specific IPv6 prefix or tunnel end-point address.
	        </t>      
         </section>
         
         <section  title="ICMPv6">
	        <t>
	        ICMPv6 protocol can broadcast RA (Router Advertisement) message and options to user device. The options may contain network specific IPv6 prefix or tunnel end-point address.
	        </t>      
         </section>
         
         <section  title="RADIUS">
	        <t>
	        RADIUS protocol<xref target='RFC2865'/>] can transport subscriber's information to network servers such as DHCP or DNS server. The subscriber's information may contain selected network specific IPv6 prefix or tunnel end-point address. The network servers then can distribute the prefix or address to user device.
	        </t>      
         </section>
      </section>
      
      <section  title="Load-balancer Location">
        <t>
        The load-balancer can be implemented in different locations or different devices.
        </t>
        
        <section  title="Terminal/Host">
	        <t>
	        Terminal/Host can be modified to balance the load to target devices. The terminal/host should use the selection policy in 5.2 to choose a target device and make its traffic go through it.
	        </t>      
         </section>
         
         <section  title="Access Gateway">
	        <t>
	        Access gateway can be modified to balance the load on target devices. The access gateway should use the selection policy in 5.2 to choose a target device and make user traffic go through it.
	        </t>      
         </section>
         
         <section  title="Network Servers">
	        <t>
	        Network servers include DHCP server, DNS server, RADIUS server and so on. They should use the selection policy in 5.2 to choose a target device. Then, they delivery the results to user device and user device will make its traffic go through the target device.
	        </t>      
         </section>
      </section>
    </section>
    
     <section title="Where Are We Now">
      <t>
	At present, some transition technologies have specified their own load balancing solutions, some transition technologies' load balancing solutions are in discussion and the others' are still waiting to be focused on.	
      </t>
      
        <section  title="Work Done"> 
        		<section  title="6RD">
		        <t>Target Device is BR, the tunnel end-point. </t>    
		        <t>Selection Policy is Anycast.</t>   
		        <t>Transport Protocol can be DNS, DHCPv4, PPP, or manual configuration etc. DHCPv4 is recommended in <xref target='RFC5969'/>.</t>   
		        <t>Load-balancer Location is in network server. DHCPv4 server is recommended in <xref target='RFC5969'/>.</t>     
         </section>
	         
	         <section  title="BIH">
	        <t>
		        BIH is described in <xref target='I-D.ietf-behave-v4v6-bih'/>.Since BIH is NOT REOMMENDED to use together with a NAT64, there is no traffic concentration point for the BIH per se. So BIH does not need any load-balancing mechanism.
		        </t>      
         </section>
        </section>
        
        <section  title="Work In Progress">
	        <section  title="NAT64">
	        <t>Target Device is the NAT64 translator.</t> 
	        <t>
<xref target='I-D.zhang-behave-nat64-load-balancing'/> is considering NAT64 load-balancing mechanism. But no solution is recommended at present.
	        </t>      
         </section>     
         </section>
         
         <section  title="Work To Be Done">
	        <section  title="IVI">
	        <t>Target Device is the IVI translator.</t>
	        <t>The load-balancing mechanism is not mentioned in the specification of IVI<xref target='RFC6219'/>.</t>      
         </section>
         
         <section  title="DS-Lite">
	        <t>Target Device is AFTR, the tunnel end-point.</t>
	        <t>Although the load-balancing of AFTR can be done by using the FQDN option defined in <xref target='I-D.ietf-softwire-ds-lite-tunnel-option'/> and DNS, this point is not explicitly described in the specification of DS-lite <xref target='I-D.ietf-softwire-dual-stack-lite'/>.</t>      
         </section>
         </section>
      
    </section>
    
    <section anchor="security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>
	The potential security problem should be considered in the specific load balancing mechanism designed for the specific transition technology.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>
	This document makes no request of IANA.
      </t>
       <t>
Note to RFC Editor: this section may be removed on publication as an RFC.
      </t>
    </section>
    
    <section title="Contributors">
      <t>
	The following individuals have contributed to this document:
      </t>
       
       <t>
	Dacheng Zhang<vspace blankLines="0" />
	Huawei Technologies Co.,Ltd<vspace blankLines="0" />
KuiKe Building, No.9 Xinxi Rd.,Haidian District<vspace blankLines="0" />
 Beijing 100085<vspace blankLines="0" />
P.R. China<vspace blankLines="0" />
</t>
			
			<t>Email: zhangdacheng@huawei.com </t>
    </section>

  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Informative References">
      
      &I-D.ietf-softwire-dual-stack-lite;
      &I-D.ietf-behave-v4v6-bih;
      &I-D.ietf-softwire-ds-lite-tunnel-option;
      &I-D.zhang-behave-nat64-load-balancing;
      &RFC2119;
      &RFC2865;
      &RFC3484;
      &RFC4291;
      &RFC5969;
			&RFC6146;
			&RFC6219;
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>

