<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- edited with XMLSPY v5 rel. 3 U (http://www.xmlspy.com)
     by Daniel M Kohn (private) -->
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY rfc2119 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
]>
<rfc category="info" docName="draft-ietf-avtcore-monarch-16.txt"
     ipr="trust200902">
  <?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>

  <?rfc toc="yes" ?>

  <?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>

  <?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>

  <?rfc iprnotified="no" ?>

  <?rfc strict="yes" ?>

  <front>
    <title abbrev="RTP Monitoring Framework">Guidelines for Use of the RTP
    Monitoring Framework</title>

    <author fullname="Qin Wu" initials="Q." role="editor" surname="Wu">
      <organization>Huawei</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>101 Software Avenue, Yuhua District</street>

          <city>Nanjing</city>

          <region>Jiangsu</region>

          <code>210012</code>

          <country>China</country>
        </postal>

        <email>sunseawq@huawei.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Geoff Hunt" initials="G." surname="Hunt">
      <organization>Unaffiliated</organization>

      <address>
        <email>r.geoff.hunt@gmail.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Philip Arden" initials="P.J." surname="Arden">
      <organization abbrev="BT">BT</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Orion 3/7 PP4</street>

          <street>Adastral Park</street>

          <street>Martlesham Heath</street>

          <city>Ipswich</city>

          <region>Suffolk</region>

          <code>IP5 3RE</code>

          <country>United Kingdom</country>
        </postal>

        <phone>+44 1473 644192</phone>

        <email>philip.arden@bt.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date year="2012" />

    <area>Real-time Applications and Infrastructure Area</area>

    <workgroup>Audio/Video Transport Working Group</workgroup>

    <keyword>RFC</keyword>

    <keyword>Request for Comments</keyword>

    <keyword>I-D</keyword>

    <keyword>Internet-Draft</keyword>

    <keyword>Real Time Control Protocol</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>This memo proposes an extensible RTP monitoring framework for
      extending RTP Control Protocol (RTCP) with a new RTCP Extended Reports
      (XR) (RFC3611) block type to report new metrics regarding media
      transmission or reception quality, following RTCP guidelines established
      in RFC5968. This memo suggests that a new block should contain a single
      metric or a small number of metrics relevant to a single parameter of
      interest or concern, rather than containing a number of metrics which
      attempt to provide full coverage of all those parameters of concern to a
      specific application. Applications may then "mix and match" to create a
      set of blocks which covers their set of concerns. Where possible, a
      specific block should be designed to be re-usable across more than one
      application, for example, for all of voice, streaming audio and
      video.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section anchor="intro" title="Introduction">
      <t>Multimedia services using the Real-Time Protocol (RTP) are seeing
      increased use. Standard methods for gathering RTP performance metrics
      from these applications are needed to manage uncertainties in the
      behavior and availability of their services. Standards , such as RTP
      Control Protocol Extended Reports (RTCP XR)<xref
      target="RFC3611"></xref> and other RTCP extension to Sender Reports
      (SR), Receiver Reports (RR) <xref target="RFC3550"></xref> are being
      developed for the purpose of collecting and reporting performance
      metrics from endpoint devices that can be used to correlate the metrics,
      provide end to end service visibility and measure and monitor Quality of
      Experience (QoE) <xref target="RFC6390"></xref>.</t>

      <t>However the proliferation of RTP/RTCP specific metrics for transport
      and application quality monitoring has been identified as a potential
      problem for interoperability when using RTP/RTCP to communicate all the
      parameters of concern to a specific application. Given that different
      applications layered on RTP may have some monitoring requirements in
      common, these metrics should be satisfied by a common design.</t>

      <t>The objective of this document is to define an extensible RTP
      monitoring framework to provide a small number of re-usable Quality of
      Service (QoS)/QoE metrics which facilitate reduced implementation costs
      and help maximize inter-operability. The "Guidelines for Extending the
      RTP Control Protocol (RTCP)" <xref target="RFC5968"></xref> has stated
      that, where RTCP is to be extended with a new metric, the preferred
      mechanism is by the addition of a new RTCP XR <xref
      target="RFC3611"></xref> block. This memo assumes that any requirement
      for a new metric to be transported in RTCP will use a new RTCP XR
      block.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Terminology">
      <t>This memo is informative and as such contains no normative
      requirements.</t>

      <t>In addition, the following terms are defined:</t>

      <t><list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="Transport level metrics"><vspace blankLines="1" />A set
          of metrics which characterise the three transport impairments of
          packet loss, packet delay, and packet delay variation. These metrics
          should be usable by any application which uses RTP transport.<vspace
          blankLines="1" /></t>

          <t hangText="Application level metrics"><vspace blankLines="1" />
          Metrics relating to application specific parameters or QoE related
          parameters. Application specific parameters are measured at the
          application level and focus on quality of content rather than
          network performance. QoE related parameters reflect the end-to-end
          performance at the services level and are ususally measured at the
          user endpoint. One example of such metrics is the QoE Metric
          specified in QoE metric reporting Block <xref target="QOE"></xref>.
          <vspace blankLines="1" /></t>

          <t hangText="End System metrics"><vspace blankLines="1" />Metrics
          relating to the way a terminal deals with transport impairments
          affecting the incident RTP stream. These may include de-jitter
          buffering, packet loss concealment, and the use of redundant streams
          (if any) for correction of error or loss.<vspace
          blankLines="1" /></t>

          <t hangText="Direct metrics"><vspace blankLines="1" />Metrics that
          can be directly measured or calculated and are not dependent on
          other metrics.<vspace blankLines="1" /></t>

          <t hangText="Composed metrics"><vspace blankLines="1" />Metrics that
          are not measured directly but rather are derived by algorithmically
          combining one or more measured metrics. An example is a metric
          derived based on direct metrics that have been measured.<vspace
          blankLines="1" /></t>

          <t hangText="Interval metrics"><vspace blankLines="1" />Metrics
          measured over the course of a single reporting interval between two
          successive report blocks. This may be the most recent RTCP reporting
          interval (<xref target="RFC3550"></xref>, section 6.2) or some other
          interval signalled using an RTCP Measurement Information XR Block
          <xref target="MEASI"></xref>. An example interval metric is the
          count of the number of RTP packets lost over the course of the last
          RTCP reporting interval. <vspace blankLines="1" /></t>

          <t hangText="Cumulative metrics"><vspace blankLines="1" />Metrics
          measured over several reporting intervals for accumulating
          statistics. The time period over which measurements are accumulated
          can be the complete RTP session, or some other interval signalled
          using an RTCP Measurement Information XR Block <xref
          target="MEASI"></xref>. An example cumulative metric is the total
          number of RTP packets lost since the start of the RTP
          session.<vspace blankLines="1" /></t>

          <t hangText="Sampled metrics"><vspace blankLines="1" />Metrics
          measured at a particular time instant and sampled from the values of
          a continuously measured or calculated metric within a reporting
          interval (generally the value of some measurement as taken at the
          end of the reporting interval). An example is the inter-arrival
          jitter reported in RTCP SR and RR packets, which is continually
          updated as each RTP data packet arrives, but only reported based on
          a snapshot of the value which is sampled at the instant the
          reporting interval ends. <vspace blankLines="1" /></t>
        </list></t>
    </section>

    <section title="RTP Monitoring Framework">
      <t>There are many ways in which the performance of an RTP session can be
      monitored. These include RTP-based mechanisms such as the RTP SNMP MIB
      <xref target="RFC2959"></xref>, or the SIP event package for RTCP
      summary reports <xref target="RFC6035"></xref>, or non-RTP mechanisms
      such as generic MIBs, NetFlow, IPFix, and so on. Together, these provide
      useful mechanisms for exporting data on the performance of an RTP
      session to non-RTP network management systems. It is desirable to also
      perform in-session monitoring of RTP performance. RTCP provides the
      means to do this. In the following, we review the RTP Monitoring
      Framework, and give guidance for using and extending RTCP for monitoring
      RTP sessions. One major benefit of such framework is ease of integration
      with other RTP/RTCP mechanisms.</t>

      <section title="Overview of the RTP Monitoring Framework">
        <t>The RTP monitoring Framework comprises the following two key
        functional components shown below:<list style="symbols">
            <t>RTP Monitor</t>

            <t>RTP Metric Block</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>RTP Monitor is the functional component defined in the Real-time
        Transport Protocol <xref target="RFC3550"></xref>. It acts as a
        repository of information gathered for monitoring purposes.</t>

        <t>According to the definition of monitor in the RTP Protocol <xref
        target="RFC3550"></xref>, the end system that runs an application
        program that sends or receives RTP data packets, an
        intermediate-system that forwards RTP packets to End-devices or a
        third party that observes the RTP and RTCP traffic but does not make
        itself visible to the RTP Session participants can play the role of
        the RTP monitor within the RTP monitoring Framework. As shown in <xref
        target="fig1"></xref>, the third party RTP monitor can be a passive
        monitor that sees the RTP/RTCP stream pass it, or a system that gets
        sent RTCP reports but not RTP and uses that to collect information.
        The third party RTP monitor should be placed on the RTP/RTCP path
        between the sender, intermediate and the receiver.</t>

        <t>The RTP Metric Block (MB) conveys real time Application QoS/QoE
        metric information and is used by the RTP monitor to exchange with
        other RTP monitors in the appropriate report block format. The
        information contained in the RTP MBs is collected by RTP monitors and
        can be formulated as various types of metrics, e.g., direct
        metrics/composed metrics or interval metrics/ cumulative
        metrics/sampled metrics, etc. Both the RTCP or RTCP XR can be extended
        to transport these metrics, e.g., the basic RTCP Reception Report (RR)
        <xref target="RFC3550"></xref> that conveys reception statistics
        (i.e., transport level statistics) for multiple RTP media streams, the
        RTCP XRs <xref target="RFC3611"></xref> that supplement the existing
        RTCP packets and provide more detailed feedback on reception quality
        and RTCP NACK <xref target="RFC4585"></xref> that provides feedback on
        the RTP sequence numbers for a subset of the lost packets or all the
        currently lost packets. Ultimately the metric information collected by
        RTP monitors within the RTP monitoring framework may go to the network
        management tools beyond the RTP monitoring framework, e.g., as shown
        <xref target="fig1"></xref>, the RTP monitors may export the metric
        information derived from the RTP monitoring framework to the
        management system using non-RTP means.</t>

        <t><figure align="center" anchor="fig1"
            title="Example showing the components of the RTP monitoring framework">
            <artwork>
               +-----------+                  +----------+
               |Third Party|                  |Management|
               |RTP Monitor|          &gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;|  System  |&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt;
               +-----------+          ^       +----------+    ^
                   :   ^              ^                       ^
                   :   |              ^                       ^
+---------------+  :   |       +-------------+        +-------------+
| +-----------+ |  :   |       |+-----------+|        |+-----------+|
| |RTP Monitor| |..:...|.......||RTP Monitor||........||RTP Monitor||
| +-----------+ |      |       |+-----------+|        |+-----------+|
|               |------+------&gt;|             |-------&gt;|             |
| RTP Sender    |              |RTP Mixer or |        |RTP Receiver |
|               |              |Translator   |        |             |
+---------------+              +-------------+        +-------------+

----&gt; RTP media traffic
..... RTCP control channel
&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt; Non-RTP/RTCP management flows
</artwork>
          </figure></t>

        <t>RTP may be used with multicast groups, both Any Source Multicast
        (ASM) and Source Specific Multicast (SSM). These groups can be
        monitored using RTCP. In the ASM case, the RTP monitor is a member of
        the multicast group and listens to RTCP reports from all members of
        the ASM group. In the SSM case, there is a unicast feedback target
        that receives RTCP feedback from receivers and distributes it to other
        members of the SSM group (see figure 1 of <xref
        target="RFC5760"></xref> ). The RTP monitor will need to be co-located
        with the feedback target to receive all feedback from the receivers
        (this may also be an intermediate system). In both ASM and SSM
        scenarios, receivers can send RTCP reports to enhance the reception
        quality reporting.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Location of RTP Monitors">
        <t>As shown in the <xref target="fig1"></xref>, there are several
        possible locations from where RTP sessions can be monitored. These
        include end-systems that terminate RTP sessions, intermediate-systems
        that are an active part of an RTP session, and third-party devices
        that passively monitor an RTP session. Not every RTP sessions will
        include monitoring, and those sessions that are monitored will not all
        include each type of monitor. The performance metrics collected by RTP
        monitors can be divided into end system metrics, application level
        metrics, and transport level metrics. Some of these metrics may be
        specific to the measurement point of the RTP monitor, or depend on
        where the RTP monitors are located in the network, while others are
        more general and can be collected in any monitoring location.</t>

        <t>End-system monitoring is monitoring that is deployed on devices
        that terminate RTP flows. Flows can be terminated in user equipment,
        such as phones, video conferencing systems, or IPTV set-top boxes.
        Alternatively, they can be terminated in devices that gateway between
        RTP and other transport protocols. Transport and end system metrics,
        application level metrics that don’t reflect end to end user
        experience may be collected at all types of end system, but some
        application level metrics (i.e.,quality of experience (QoE) metrics)
        may only be applicable for user-facing end systems.</t>

        <t>RTP sessions can include intermediate-systems that are an active
        part of the system. These intermediate-systems include RTP mixers and
        translators, MCUs, retransmission servers, etc. If the
        intermediate-system establishes separate RTP sessions to the other
        participants, then it must act as an end system in each of those
        separate RTP sessions for the purposes of monitoring. If a single RTP
        session traverses the intermediate-system, then the
        intermediate-system can be assigned an SSRC in that session which it
        can use for it's reports. Transport level metrics may be collected at
        such intermediate-system.</t>

        <t>Third-party monitors may be deployed that passively monitor RTP
        sessions for network management purposes. Third-party monitors often
        do not send reports into the RTP session being monitored, but instead
        collect transport and end system metrics, application level metrics
        that are reported via some network management application. In some
        cases, however, third-party monitors can send reports to some or all
        participants in the session being monitored. For example, in a media
        streaming scenario, third-party monitors may be deployed that
        passively monitor the session and send reception quality reports to
        the media source, but not to the receivers.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Issues with reporting metric block using RTCP XR extension">
      <t>The following sections discuss four issues that have come up in the
      past with reporting metric block using RTCP XR extensions.</t>

      <section title="Using compound metrics block">
        <t>A compound metrics block is designed to contain a large number of
        parameters from different classes for a specific application in a
        single block. For example, the RTCP Extended Reports (XRs) <xref
        target="RFC3611"></xref> defines seven report block formats for
        network management and quality monitoring. Some of these block types
        defined in the RTCP XRs <xref target="RFC3611"></xref> are only
        specifically designed for conveying multicast inference of network
        characteristics (MINC) or voice over IP (VoIP) monitoring. However
        different applications layered on RTP may have different monitoring
        requirements. Designing compound metrics block only for specific
        applications may increase implementation cost and minimize
        interoperability.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Correlating RTCP XR with the non-RTP data">
        <t>Canonical End-Point Identifier SDES Item (CNAME), defined in the
        RTP Protocol <xref target="RFC3550"></xref>, is an example of an
        existing tool that allows binding a Synchronization source (SSRC) that
        may change to a name that is fixed within one RTP session. CNAME may
        be also fixed across multiple RTP sessions from the same source.
        However there may be situations where RTCP reports are sent to other
        participating endpoints using non-RTP protocol in a session. For
        example, as described in the SIP RTCP Summary Report Protocol <xref
        target="RFC6035"></xref>, the data contained in RTCP XR VoIP metrics
        reports <xref target="RFC3611"></xref> are forwarded to a central
        collection server systems using SIP. In such case, there is a large
        portfolio of quality parameters that can be associated with real time
        application, e.g., VOIP application, but only a minimal number of
        parameters are included on the RTCP-XR reports. With these minimal
        number of RTCP statistics parameters mapped to non-RTCP measurements,
        it is hard to provide accurate measures of real time application
        quality, conduct detailed data analysis and creates alerts timly to
        the users. Therefore correlation between RTCP XR and non-RTP data
        should be provided.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Measurement Information duplication">
        <t>We may set a measurement interval for the session and monitor RTP
        packets within one or several consecutive report intervals. In such
        case, the extra measurement information (e.g., extended sequence
        number of 1st packet, measurement period) may be expected. However if
        we put such extra measurement information into each metric block,
        there may be situations where an RTCP XR packet containing multiple
        metric blocks, reports on the same streams from the same source. In
        other words, duplicated data for the measurement is provided multiple
        times, once in every metric block. Though this design ensures immunity
        to packet loss, it may bring more packetization complexity and the
        processing overhead is not completely trivial in some cases. Therefore
        compromise between processing overhead and reliability should be taken
        into account.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Consumption of XR block code points">
        <t>The RTCP XR block namespace is limited by the 8-bit block type
        field in the RTCP XR header. Space exhaustion may be a concern in the
        future. Anticipating the potential need to extend the block type
        space, it is noted that Block Type 255 is reserved for future
        extensions in <xref target="RFC3611"></xref>.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Guidelines for reporting metric block using RTCP XR">
      <section anchor="smallblock"
               title="Contain the single metrics in the Metric Block">
        <t>Different applications using RTP for media transport certainly have
        differing requirements for metrics transported in RTCP to support
        their operation. For many applications, the basic metrics for
        transport impairments provided in RTCP SR and RR packets <xref
        target="RFC3550"></xref> (together with source identification provided
        in RTCP SDES packets) are sufficient. For other applications
        additional metrics may be required or at least sufficiently useful to
        justify the overhead, both of processing in endpoints and of increased
        session bandwidth. For example an IPTV application using Forward Error
        Correction (FEC) might use either a metric of post-repair loss or a
        metric giving detailed information about pre-repair loss bursts to
        optimise payload bandwidth and the strength of FEC required for
        changing network conditions. However there are many metrics available.
        It is likely that different applications or classes of applications
        will wish to use different metrics. Any one application is likely to
        require metrics for more than one parameter but if this is the case,
        different applications will almost certainly require different
        combinations of metrics. If larger blocks are defined containing
        multiple metrics to address the needs of each application, it becomes
        likely that many different such larger blocks are defined, which
        becomes a danger to interoperability.</t>

        <t>To avoid this pitfall, this memo recommends the definition of
        metrics blocks containing a very small number of individual metrics
        characterizing only one parameter of interest to an application
        running over RTP. For example, at the RTP transport layer, the
        parameter of interest might be packet delay variation, and
        specifically the metric "IP Packet Delay Variation (IPDV)" defined by
        <xref target="Y1540"></xref>. See <xref target="example"></xref> for
        architectural considerations for a metrics block, using as an example
        a metrics block to report packet delay variation. Further, it is
        appropriate to not only define report blocks separately, but also to
        do so in separate documents where possible. This makes it easier to
        evolve the reports (i.e., to update each type of report block
        separately), and also makes it easier to require compliance with a
        particular report block.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Include the payload type in the Metric Block">
        <t>There are some classes of metrics that can only be interpreted with
        knowledge of the media codec that is being used (audio mean opinion
        scores (MOS) were the triggering example, but there may be others). In
        such cases the correlation of RTCP XR with RTP data is needed. Report
        blocks that require such correlation need to include the payload type
        of the reported media. In addition, it is necessary to signal the
        details and parameters of the payload format to which that payload
        type is bound using some out-of-band means (e.g., as part of an SDP
        offer/answer exchange).</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Use RTCP SDES to correlate XR reports with non-RTP data">
        <t>There may be situations where more than one media transport
        protocol is used by one application to interconnect to the same
        session in the gateway. For example, one RTCP XR Packet is sent to the
        participating endpoints using non-RTP-based media transport (e.g.,
        using SIP) in a VOIP session. One crucial factor lies in how to handle
        their different identities that are corresponding to different media
        transport.</t>

        <t>This memo recommends an approach to facilitate the correlation of
        the RTCP Session with other session-related non-RTP data. That is to
        say if there is a need to correlate RTP sessions with non-RTP
        sessions, then the correlation information needed should be conveyed
        in a new RTCP Source Description (SDES) item, since such correlation
        information describes the source, rather than providing a quality
        report. An example use case is for a participant endpoint may convey a
        call identifier or a global call identifier associated with the SSRC
        of measured RTP stream. In such case, the participant endpoint uses
        the SSRC of source to bind the call identifier using SDES item in the
        SDES RTCP packet and send such correlation to the network management
        system. A flow measurement tool that is configured with the 5-tuple
        and not call-aware then forward the RTCP XR reports along with the
        SSRC of the measured RTP stream which is included in the XR Block
        header and 5-tuple to the network management system. Network
        management system can then correlate this report using SSRC with other
        diagnostic information such as call detail records.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Reduce Measurement information repetition across metric blocks">
        <t>When multiple metric blocks are carried in one RTCP XR packet,
        reporting on the same stream from the same source for the same time
        period, RTCP should use the SSRC to identify and correlate the
        multiple metric blocks between metric blocks. This memo proposes to
        define a new XR Block (i.e., the Measurement information block <xref
        target="MEASI"></xref>) that will be used to convey the common time
        period and the number of packets sent during this period. If the
        measurement interval for a metric is different from the RTCP reporting
        interval, then this measurement duration in the Measurement
        information block should be used to specify the interval. When there
        may be multiple measurements information blocks with the same SSRC in
        one RTCP XR compound packet, the measurement information block should
        be put in order and followed by all the metric blocks associated with
        this measurement information block. New RTCP XR metric blocks that
        rely on the Measurement information block <xref target="MEASI"></xref>
        must specify the response in case the new RTCP XR metric block is
        received without an associated measurement information block. In most
        cases, it is expected that the correct response is to discard the
        received metric. In order to reduce measurement information repetition
        in one RTCP XR compound packet containing multiple metric blocks, the
        measurement information shall be sent before the related metric blocks
        that are from the same reporting interval. Note that for packet loss
        robustness if the report blocks for the same interval span over more
        than one RTCP packet, then each must have the measurement identity
        information even though they will be the same.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="example" title="An example of a metric block">
      <t>This section uses the example of an existing proposed metrics block
      to illustrate the application of the principles set out in <xref
      target="smallblock"></xref>.</t>

      <t>The example <xref target="PDV"></xref> is a block to convey
      information about packet delay variation (PDV) only, consistent with the
      principle that a metrics block should address only one parameter of
      interest. One simple metric of PDV is available in the RTCP RR packet as
      the "interarrival jitter" field. There are other PDV metrics with a
      certain similarity in metric structure which may be more useful to
      certain applications. Two such metrics are the IPDV metric (<xref
      target="Y1540"></xref>, <xref target="RFC3393"></xref>) and the mean
      absolute packet delay variation 2 (MAPDV2) metric <xref
      target="G1020"></xref>. Use of these metrics is consistent with the
      principle in Section 5 of RTCP guideline <xref target="RFC5968"></xref>
      that metrics should usually be defined elsewhere, so that RTCP standards
      define only the transport of the metric rather than its nature. The
      purpose of this section is to illustrate the architectural consideration
      using the example of <xref target="PDV"></xref> rather than to document
      the design of the PDV metrics block or to provide a tutorial on PDV in
      general.</t>

      <t>Given the availability of at least three metrics for PDV, there are
      design options for the allocation of metrics to RTCP XR blocks:</t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>provide an RTCP XR block per metric</t>

          <t>provide a single RTCP XR block which contains all three
          metrics</t>

          <t>provide a single RTCP block to convey any one of the three
          metrics, together with a identifier to inform the receiving RTP
          system of the specific metric being conveyed</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>In choosing between these options, extensibility is important,
      because additional metrics of PDV may well be standardized and require
      inclusion in this framework. The first option is extensible but only by
      use of additional RTCP XR blocks, which may consume the limited
      namespace for RTCP XR blocks at an unacceptable rate. The second option
      is not extensible, so could be rejected on that basis, but in any case a
      single application is quite unlikely to require transport of more than
      one metric for PDV. Hence the third option was chosen. This implies the
      creation of a subsidiary namespace to enumerate the PDV metrics which
      may be transported by this block, as discussed further in <xref
      target="PDV"></xref>.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="topologies" title="Application to RFC 5117 topologies">
      <t>The topologies specified in <xref target="RFC5117"></xref> fall into
      two categories. The first category relates to the RTP system model
      utilizing multicast and/or unicast. The topologies in this category are
      specifically Topo-Point-to-Point, Topo- Multicast, Topo-Translator (both
      variants, Topo-Trn-Translator and Topo-Media-Translator, and
      combinations of the two), and Topo-Mixer. These topologies use RTP end
      systems, RTP mixers and RTP translators defined in the RTP protocol
      <xref target="RFC3550"></xref>. For purposes of reporting connection
      quality to other RTP systems, RTP mixers and RTP end systems are very
      similar. Mixers resynchronize packets and do not relay RTCP reports
      received from one cloud towards other cloud(s). Translators do not
      resynchronize packets and should forward certain RTCP reports between
      clouds. In this category, the RTP system (end system, mixer or
      translator) which originates, terminates or forwards RTCP XR blocks is
      expected to handle RTCP, including RTCP XR, according to the RTP
      protocol <xref target="RFC3550"></xref>. Provided this expectation is
      met, an RTP system using RTCP XR is architecturally no different from an
      RTP system of the same class (end system, mixer, or translator) which
      does not use RTCP XR. The second category relates to deployed system
      models used in many H.323 <xref target="H323"></xref> video conferences.
      The topologies in this category are Topo-Video-Switch-MCU and
      Topo-RTCP-terminating-MCU. Such topologies based on systems (e.g.,MCUs)
      do not behave according to the RTP protocol <xref
      target="RFC3550"></xref>.</t>

      <t>Considering the translator and MCU are two typical
      intermediate-systems in these two categories mentioned above, this
      document will take them as two typical examples to explain how RTCP XR
      report works in different RFC5117 topologies.</t>

      <section anchor="txlat" title="Applicability to Translators">
        <t>Section 7.2 of the RTP protocol <xref target="RFC3550"></xref>
        describes processing of RTCP by translators. RTCP XR is within the
        scope of the recommendations of the RTP protocol <xref
        target="RFC3550"></xref>. Some RTCP XR metrics blocks may usefully be
        measured at, and reported by, translators. As described in the RTP
        protocol <xref target="RFC3550"></xref> this creates a requirement for
        the translator to allocate an SSRC for the monitor collocated with
        itself so that the monitor may populate the SSRC in the RTCP XR packet
        header as packet sender SSRC and send it out(although the translator
        is not a Synchronisation Source in the sense of originating RTP media
        packets). It must also supply this SSRC and the corresponding CNAME in
        RTCP SDES packets.</t>

        <t>In RTP sessions where one or more translators generate any RTCP
        traffic towards their next-neighbour RTP system, other translators in
        the session have a choice as to whether they forward a translator's
        RTCP packets. Forwarding may provide additional information to other
        RTP systems in the connection but increases RTCP bandwidth and may in
        some cases present a security risk. RTP translators may have
        forwarding behaviour based on local policy, which might differ between
        different interfaces of the same translator.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Applicability to MCU">
        <t>Topo-Video-Switch-MCU and Topo-RTCP-terminating-MCU, suffer from
        the difficulties described in <xref target="RFC5117"></xref>. These
        difficulties apply to systems sending, and expecting to receive, RTCP
        XR blocks as much as to systems using other RTCP packet types. For
        example, a participant RTP end system may send media to a video switch
        MCU. If the media stream is not selected for forwarding by the switch,
        neither RTCP RR packets nor RTCP XR blocks referring to the end
        system's generated stream will be received at the RTP end system.
        Strictly the RTP end system can only conclude that its RTP has been
        lost in the network, though an RTP end system complying with the
        robustness principle of <xref target="RFC1122"></xref> should survive
        with essential functions (i.e.,media distribution) unimpaired.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>There is no IANA action in this document.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Security Considerations">
      <t>This document focuses on the RTCP reporting extension using RTCP XR
      and should not give rise to any new security vulnerabilities beyond
      those described in RTCP XRs <xref target="RFC3611"></xref>. However it
      also describes the architectural framework to be used for monitoring at
      RTP layer. The security issues with monitoring needs to be
      considered.</t>

      <t>In RTP sessions, a RTP system may use its own SSRC to send its
      monitoring reports towards its next-neighbour RTP system. Other RTP
      system in the session may have a choice as to whether they forward this
      RTP system's RTCP packets. This present a security issue since the
      information in the report may be exposed by the other RTP system to any
      malicious node. Therefore if the information is considered as sensitive,
      the monitoring report should be encrypted.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Acknowledgement">
      <t>The authors would also like to thank Colin Perkins, Charles Eckel,
      Robert Sparks, Salvatore Loreto, Graeme Gibbs, Debbie Greenstreet, Keith
      Drage, Dan Romascanu, Ali C. Begen, Roni Even, Magnus Westerlund for
      their valuable comments and suggestions on the early version of this
      document.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Informative References">
      <reference anchor="RFC1122">
        <front>
          <title>Requirements for Internet Hosts -- Communication
          Layers</title>

          <author initials="R." surname="Braden">
            <organization>USC/ISI</organization>
          </author>

          <date month="October" year="1989" />
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="1122" />

        <format type="TXT" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RFC3393">
        <front>
          <title>IP Packet Delay Variation Metric for IP Performance Metrics
          (IPPM)</title>

          <author fullname="Carlo Demichelis" initials="C."
                  surname="Demichelis">
            <organization>Telecomitalia Lab</organization>
          </author>

          <date month="November" year="2002" />
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="3393" />

        <format type="TXT" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RFC6390">
        <front>
          <title>Guidelines for Considering New Performance Metric
          Development</title>

          <author fullname="A.Clark" initials="A." surname="Clark">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="B. Claise" initials="B." surname="Claise">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date month="October" year="2011" />
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="6390" />

        <format type="TXT" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RFC3550">
        <front>
          <title>RTP: A Transport Protocol for Real-Time Applications</title>

          <author fullname="Henning Schulzrinne" initials="H."
                  surname="Schulzrinne">
            <organization>Columbia University</organization>
          </author>

          <date month="July" year="2003" />
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="3550" />

        <format type="TXT" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RFC3611">
        <front>
          <title>RTP Control Protocol Extended Reports (RTCP XR)</title>

          <author fullname="Timur Friedman" initials="T. (Ed)"
                  surname="Friedman">
            <organization>Paris 6</organization>
          </author>

          <date month="November" year="2003" />
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="3611" />

        <format type="TXT" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RFC5117">
        <front>
          <title>RTP Topologies</title>

          <author fullname="Magnus Westerlund" initials="M."
                  surname="Westerlund">
            <organization>Ericsson Research</organization>
          </author>

          <date month="January" year="2008" />
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="5117" />

        <format type="TXT" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RFC5968">
        <front>
          <title>Guidelines for Extending the RTP Control Protocol
          (RTCP)</title>

          <author fullname="Joerg Ott" initials="J." surname="Ott">
            <organization>Helsinki University of Technology</organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="C. Perkins" initials="C." surname="Perkins">
            <organization>University of Glasgow</organization>
          </author>

          <date month="September" year="2010" />
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="5968" />

        <format type="TXT" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RFC4585">
        <front>
          <title>Extended RTP Profile for Real-time Transport Control Protocol
          (RTCP)-Based Feedback (RTP/AVPF)</title>

          <author fullname="Joerg Ott" initials="J." surname="Ott">
            <organization>Helsinki University of Technology</organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="S. Wenger" initials="S." surname="Wenger">
            <organization>Nokia</organization>
          </author>

          <date month="July" year="2006" />
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="4585" />

        <format type="TXT" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RFC6035">
        <front>
          <title>Session Initiation Protocol Event Package for Voice Quality
          Reporting</title>

          <author fullname="A. Pendleton" initials="A." surname="Pendleton">
            <organization>Telchemy Incorporated</organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="A. Clark" initials="A." surname="Clark">
            <organization>Telchemy Incorporated</organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="A. Johnston" initials="A." surname="Johnston">
            <organization>Avaya</organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="H. Sinnreich" initials="H." surname="Sinnreich">
            <organization>Unaffiliated</organization>
          </author>

          <date month="November" year="2010" />
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="6035" />

        <format type="TXT" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RFC2959">
        <front>
          <title>Real-Time Transport Protocol Management Information
          Base</title>

          <author fullname="M. Baugher" initials="M." surname="Baugher">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="B. Strahm" initials="B." surname="Strahm">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="I. Suconick" initials="I." surname="Suconick">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date month="October" year="2000" />
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="2959" />

        <format type="TXT" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RFC5760">
        <front>
          <title>RTP Control Protocol (RTCP) Extensions for Single-Source
          Multicast Sessions with Unicast Feedback</title>

          <author fullname="Joerg Ott" initials="J." surname="Ott">
            <organization>Helsinki University of Technology</organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="Julian Chesterfield" initials="J."
                  surname="Chesterfield">
            <organization>University of Cambridge</organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="Eve Schooler" initials="E." surname="Schooler">
            <organization>Intel Research / CTL</organization>
          </author>

          <date month="February" year="2010" />
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="5760" />

        <format type="TXT" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="PDV">
        <front>
          <title>RTCP XR Report Block for Packet Delay Variation Metric
          Reporting</title>

          <author fullname="Geoff Hunt" initials="G." surname="Hunt">
            <organization>BT</organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="Alan Clark " initials="A." surname="Clark">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="Qin Wu" initials="Q." surname="Wu">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date month="May" year="2012" />
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="ID" value="draft-ietf-xrblock-rtcp-xr-pdv-03" />

        <format type="TXT" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="MEASI">
        <front>
          <title>Measurement Identity and information Reporting using SDES
          item and XR Block</title>

          <author fullname="Qin Wu" initials="Q." surname="Wu">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date month="June" year="2012" />
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="ID"
                    value="draft-ietf-xrblock-rtcp-xr-meas-identity-07" />

        <format type="TXT" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="QOE">
        <front>
          <title>RTCP XR Blocks for QoE Metric Reporting</title>

          <author fullname="G.Hunt" initials="G." surname="Hunt">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="A.Clark" initials="A." surname="Clark">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="Qin Wu" initials="Q." surname="Wu">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="Roland Schott" initials="R." surname="Schott">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="Glen Zorn" initials="G." surname="Zorn">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date month="May" year="2012" />
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="ID" value="draft-ietf-xrblock-rtcp-xr-qoe-01" />

        <format type="TXT" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="P.NAMS">
        <front>
          <title>Non-intrusive parametric model for the Assessment of
          performance of Multimedia Streaming</title>

          <author>
            <organization>ITU-T</organization>
          </author>

          <date month="November" year="2009" />
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="ITU-T Recommendation" value="P.NAMS" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="G1020">
        <front>
          <title>ITU-T Rec. G.1020, Performance parameter definitions for
          quality of speech and other voiceband applications utilizing IP
          networks</title>

          <author>
            <organization>ITU-T</organization>
          </author>

          <date month="July" year="2006" />
        </front>

        <format type="TXT" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="Y1540">
        <front>
          <title>ITU-T Rec. Y.1540, IP packet transfer and availability
          performance parameters</title>

          <author fullname="" initials="" surname="">
            <organization>ITU-T</organization>
          </author>

          <date month="November" year="2007" />
        </front>

        <format type="TXT" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="H323">
        <front>
          <title>ITU-T Rec. H.323, Packet-based multimedia communications
          systems</title>

          <author fullname="" initials="" surname="">
            <organization>ITU-T</organization>
          </author>

          <date month="June" year="2006" />
        </front>

        <format type="TXT" />
      </reference>
    </references>

    <section title="Change Log">
      <t>Note to the RFC-Editor: please remove this section prior to
      publication as an RFC.</t>

      <section title="draft-ietf-avtcore-monarch-16">
        <t>The following are the major changes compared to 15: <list
            style="symbols">
            <t>A few modification to the figure 1.</t>

            <t>Change RTCP XR reports into RTCP reports in the section
            3.1.</t>

            <t>References Update.</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>

      <section title="draft-ietf-avtcore-monarch-15">
        <t>The following are the major changes compared to 14: <list
            style="symbols">
            <t>Add figure 1 in section 3 to describe RTP monitoring
            framework.</t>

            <t>Change the title as Guidelines for Use of the RTP Monitoring
            Framework.</t>

            <t>Other editorial change to get in line with the title change in
            the section 3.</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>

      <section title="draft-ietf-avtcore-monarch-14">
        <t>The following are the major changes compared to 13: <list
            style="symbols">
            <t>Incorporate the key points in the section 3.2 into overview
            section.</t>

            <t>Remove the figure 1 and use the description instead.</t>

            <t>Add description in the section 3.3 to discuss the possible
            location of the monitors and the types of metric at that
            location.</t>

            <t>Add the description to make the definition of Interval
            metrics/cumulative metrics/sampled metrics clear.</t>

            <t>Editorial Changes.</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>

      <section title="draft-ietf-avtcore-monarch-13">
        <t>The following are the major changes compared to 12: <list
            style="symbols">
            <t>Editorial Changes.</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>

      <section title="draft-ietf-avtcore-monarch-12">
        <t>The following are the major changes compared to 11: <list
            style="symbols">
            <t>Editorial Changes based on Charles' Comments.</t>

            <t>Reference update.</t>

            <t>Add one new section 5.2 to discuss Correlating RTCP XR with RTP
            data.</t>

            <t>Add text in section 5.1 to highlight it is more appropriate to
            define each block in a separate draft.</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>

      <section title="draft-ietf-avtcore-monarch-11">
        <t>The following are the major changes compared to 10: <list
            style="symbols">
            <t>Editorial Changes.</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>

      <section title="draft-ietf-avtcore-monarch-10">
        <t>The following are the major changes compared to 09: <list
            style="symbols">
            <t>Discuss what exist already for monitoring in section 3.1.</t>

            <t>Provide benefit using RTCP XR based monitoring in section
            3.1.</t>

            <t>add one new paragraph in section 3.1 to describe how monitoring
            architecture is applied to ASM/SSM.</t>

            <t>Other Editorial Changes.</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>

      <section title="draft-ietf-avtcore-monarch-09">
        <t>The following are the major changes compared to 07: <list
            style="symbols">
            <t>Rephrase application level metric definition.</t>

            <t>Add one new section to clarify where to measure QoE related
            parameters.</t>

            <t>Add text in section 5.3 to clarify the failure case when
            measurement interval is not sent.</t>

            <t>Add text in section 5.3 to clarify how to deal with multiple
            measurements information blocks carried in the same packet.</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>

      <section title="draft-ietf-avtcore-monarch-08">
        <t>The following are the major changes compared to 07: <list
            style="symbols">
            <t>Editorial change to the reference.</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>

      <section title="draft-ietf-avtcore-monarch-07">
        <t>The following are the major changes compared to 06: <list
            style="symbols">
            <t>Clarify the XR block code points consumption issue in the
            section 4 and new section 5.4.</t>

            <t>Other editorial changes.</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>

      <section title="draft-ietf-avtcore-monarch-06">
        <t>The following are the major changes compared to 05: <list
            style="symbols">
            <t>Some editorial changes.</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>

      <section title="draft-ietf-avtcore-monarch-05">
        <t>The following are the major changes compared to 04: <list
            style="symbols">
            <t>Replace "chunk" with "new SDES item".</t>

            <t>Add texts in security section to discussion potential security
            issues.</t>

            <t>Add new sub-section 5.3 to discuss Reducing Measurement
            information repetition.</t>

            <t>Other editorial changes.</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>

      <section title="draft-ietf-avtcore-monarch-04">
        <t>The following are the major changes compared to 03: <list
            style="symbols">
            <t>Update section 5.2 to clarify using SDES packet to carry
            correlation information.</t>

            <t>Remove section 5.3 since additional identity information goes
            to SDES packet and using SSRC to identify each block is standard
            RTP feature.</t>

            <t>Swap the last two paragraphs in the section 4 since identity
            information duplication can not been 100% avoided.</t>

            <t>Other editorial changes.</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>

      <section title="draft-ietf-avtcore-monarch-03">
        <t>The following are the major changes compared to 02: <list
            style="symbols">
            <t>Update bullet 2 in section 4 to explain the ill-effect of
            Identity Information duplication.</t>

            <t>Update bullet 3 in section 4 to explain why Correlating RTCP XR
            with the non-RTP data is needed.</t>

            <t>Update section 5.2 to focus on how to reduce the identity
            information repetition</t>

            <t>Update section 5.3 to explain how to correlate identity
            information with the non-RTP data</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>

      <section title="draft-ietf-avtcore-monarch-02">
        <t>The following are the major changes compared to 01: <list
            style="symbols">
            <t>Deleting first paragraph of Section 1.</t>

            <t>Deleting Section 3.1, since the interaction with the management
            application is out of scope of this draft.</t>

            <t>Separate identity information correlation from section 5.2 as
            new section 5.3.</t>

            <t>Remove figure 2 and related text from section 5.2.</t>

            <t>Editorial changes in the section 4 and the first paragraph of
            section 7.</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>

      <section title="draft-ietf-avtcore-monarch-01">
        <t>The following are the major changes compared to 00: <list
            style="symbols">
            <t>Restructure the document by merging section 4 into section
            3.</t>

            <t>Remove section 4.1,section 5 that is out of scope of this
            document.</t>

            <t>Remove the last bullet in section 6 and section 7.3 based on
            conclusion of last meeting.</t>

            <t>Update figure 1 and related text in section 3 according to the
            monitor definition in RFC3550.</t>

            <t>Revise section 9 to address monitor declaration issue.</t>

            <t>Merge the first two bullet in section 6.</t>

            <t>Add one new bullet to discuss metric block association in
            section 6.</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>

      <section title="draft-ietf-avtcore-monarch-00">
        <t>The following are the major changes compared to
        draft-hunt-avtcore-monarch-02: <list style="symbols">
            <t>Move Geoff Hunt and Philip Arden to acknowledgement
            section.</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>
    </section>
  </back>
</rfc>
