<?xml version="1.0" ?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">

<?rfc toc='yes'?>
<rfc docName="draft-ietf-idr-best-external-05" ipr="trust200902">
<front>
    <title abbrev='best-external path advertisement'>
    Advertisement of the best external route in BGP</title>

<author initials='P.' surname='Marques' fullname='Pedro Marques'>
    <address>
        <email>pedro.r.marques@gmail.com</email>
    </address>
</author>

<author initials='R.' surname='Fernando' fullname='Rex Fernando'>
    <organization>Cisco Systems</organization>
    <address>
    <postal>
	<street>170 W. Tasman Dr.</street>
	<city>San Jose</city><region>CA</region><code>95134</code>
	<country>US</country>
    </postal>
    <email>rex@cisco.com</email>
    </address>
</author>

<author initials='E.' surname='Chen' fullname='Enke Chen'>
    <organization>Cisco Systems</organization>
    <address>
    <postal>
	<street>170 W. Tasman Dr.</street>
	<city>San Jose</city><region>CA</region><code>95134</code>
	<country>US</country>
    </postal>
    <email>enkechen@cisco.com</email>
    </address>
</author>

<author initials='P.' surname='Mohapatra' fullname='Pradosh Mohapatra'>
    <organization>Cisco Systems</organization>
    <address>
    <postal>
	<street>170 W. Tasman Dr.</street>
	<city>San Jose</city><region>CA</region><code>95134</code>
	<country>US</country>
    </postal>
    <email>pmohapat@cisco.com</email>
    </address>
</author>

<author initials='H.' surname='Gredler' fullname='Hannes Gredler'>
    <organization>Juniper Networks</organization>
    <address>
        <postal>
          <street>1194 N. Mathilda Ave.</street>
          <city>Sunnyvale</city>
          <region>CA</region>
          <code>94089</code>
          <country>US</country>
        </postal>
        <email>hannes@juniper.net</email>
    </address>
</author>

    <date month="January" year="2012"/>
    <area>Routing</area>

    <abstract>
    <t>The current <xref target="RFC4271">BGP-4 protocol specification</xref>
    states that
the selection process chooses the best path for a given route which is added to the Loc-Rib and advertised to all peers.
    </t>
    <t>Previous <xref target="RFC1771">versions</xref> of the specification
defined a different rule for Internal BGP Updates. Given that Internal paths
are not re-advertised to Internal peers, it was specified that the best of
the external paths, as determined by the path selection tie breaking algorithm,
would be advertised to Internal peers.</t>

    <t>This document extends that procedure to operate in environments where
<xref target="RFC4456">Route Reflection</xref> or
<xref target="RFC5065">Confederations</xref> are used and
explains why advertising the additional routing information can improve convergence time without causing routing loops.</t>
    <t>Additional benefits include reduction of inter-domain churn and avoidance of permanent route oscillation.</t>
    </abstract>

</front>

<middle>

<section title="Introduction">
    <t>Earlier versions of the <xref target="RFC1771">BGP-4 protocol
specification</xref> prescribed different route advertisement rules for
Internal and External peers. While the overall best path would be advertised to External peers, Internal peers are advertised the best of the externally received paths.</t>

    <t>This Internal advertisement rule was never implemented as
specified and was latter dropped from the protocol. There is a
trade-off in advertising the "best-external" route versus the behavior
that became common standard of not advertising the route when the
selected best path is received from an Internal peer. By not
advertising information in this case it is possible to reduce state
both in the local BGP speaker as well as in the network overall. Early BGP
implementations where very concerned with reducing state as they where
limited to relatively low memory footprints (e.g. 16 MB). There is also
the possible concern regarding advertising a path different than the path
that has been selected for forwarding.
    </t>

    <t>However, advertising the best external route, when different from the best route, presents additional information into an IBGP mesh which may be of value for several purposes including:
    </t>
    <t><list style='symbols'>
        <t>Faster restoration of connectivity. By providing additional paths, that may be used to fail over in case the primary path becomes invalid or is withdrawn.</t>
	<t>Reducing inter-domain churn and traffic black-holing due to the
           readily available alternate path.</t>
        <t>Reducing the potential for situations of permanent <xref target="RFC3345">IBGP route oscillation</xref>.</t>
        <t>Improving selection of lower MED routes from the same neighboring
            AS.</t>
     </list></t>

    <t>This document defines procedures to select the best external route for each peer.  It also describes how above benefits are realized with best external route announcement with the help of certain scenarios.</t>

</section>

<section title="Requirements Language">
    <t> The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in <xref target="RFC2119">RFC 2119</xref>.
    </t>
</section>

<section title="Generalization">
    <t>The <xref target="RFC1771">BGP-4 protocol</xref> has extended with
two alternative mechanisms that provide ways to reduce the operational
complexity of route distribution within an AS:
<xref target="RFC4456">Route Reflection</xref> and
<xref target="RFC5065">Confederations</xref>. It is important to be able
to express route advertisement rules in the context of both of these mechanisms.
    </t>
    <t>When Route Reflection is used, Internal peers are further classified
depending of the reflection cluster they belong to. Non-client internal peers
form one BGP peering mesh. Each set of RR clients with the same "cluster-id"
configuration forms a separate mesh.</t>
    <t>When selecting the path to add to the
Adj-RIB-OUT, this document specifies that the path that originate from the same mesh MAY be excluded from consideration. This results in an Adj-RIB-OUT selection per mesh (the set of non-client peers or a specific cluster).</t>
    <t>Similarly, when BGP Confederations are used, each confederated AS is a
    BGP mesh. As with the Route Reflection scenario, when selecting the path
    to add to the Adj-RIB-OUT, routes from the same mesh MAY be excluded.</t>
</section>

<section title="Algorithm for selection of the Adj-RIB-OUT path">
    <t>The objective of this protocol extension is to improve the quality of
the routing information known to a particular BGP mesh with minimum
additional cost in terms of processing and state.</t>
    <t>Towards that goal, it is useful to define a total order between the
    Adj-RIB-In routes which provides both the same overall best path as the
    algorithm defined in the
    <xref target="RFC4271">current BGP-4 specification</xref> as well as an
    ordering of alternate routes. Using this total order it is then
    computationally efficient to select the path for a specific Adj-RIB-OUT
    by excluding the routes that have been received from the BGP mesh
    corresponding to the peer (or set of peers).
    </t>

    <t>In order to achieve this, it is helpful to introduce the concept of path group. A group is the set of paths that compare as equal through all the steps prior to the MED comparison step (as defined in section 9.1.2.2 of <xref target="RFC4271">RFC 4271</xref> and have been received from the same neighbor AS.
    </t> 
    <t>Paths are ordered within a group via MED or subsequent route selection rules.</t>
<figure>
<preamble>In pseudo-code:</preamble>
<artwork align='center'><![CDATA[
function compare(path_1, path_2) {
    cmp_result cmp = selection_steps_before_med(path_1, path_2);
    if (cmp != cmp_result.equal) {
        return cmp;
    }
    if (neighbor_as(path_1) == neighbor_as(path_2)) {
        return selection_steps_after_med(path_1, path_2);
    }

    if (is_group_best(path_1)) {
        if (!is_group_best(path_2)) {
            return cmp_result.greater_than;
        }
        return selection_steps_after_med(path_1, path_2);
    } else {
        if (is_group_best(path_2)) {
	    return cmp_result.less_than;
        }
        /* Compare the best paths of respective groups */
        return compare(group_best(path_1), group_best(path_2));
    }
}
]]></artwork>
</figure>

    <t>As an example, the following set of received routes:</t>

<texttable title='Path Attribute Table'>
<ttcol>Path</ttcol> <ttcol>AS</ttcol> <ttcol>MED</ttcol> <ttcol>rtr_id</ttcol>
<c>a</c> <c>1</c><c>10</c><c>10</c>
<c>b</c> <c>2</c> <c>5</c> <c>1</c>
<c>c</c> <c>1</c> <c>5</c> <c>5</c>
<c>d</c> <c>2</c><c>20</c><c>20</c>
<c>e</c> <c>2</c><c>30</c><c>30</c>
<c>f</c> <c>3</c><c>10</c><c>20</c>
</texttable>
    <t>Would yield the following order (from the most to the least preferred):
    </t>
    <t><list>
        <t>b &lt; d &lt; e &lt; c &lt; a &lt; f</t>
    </list></t>

    <t>In this example, comparison of the best path within each group provides the sequence (b &lt; c &lt; f). The remaining paths are ordered in relation to their respective group best.</t>

    <t>The first path in the ordering above is the best overall path for a given NLRI. When selecting a path for a particular Adj-RIB-Out (or set of RIB-Outs)
an implementation MAY choose to select the first path in the global order
which was not received from the same BGP mesh (as defined above) as the target peer (or peers).</t>
</section>

<section title="Advertisement Rules">
    <t><list style='numbers'>
    
    <t>When advertising a route to a non-client Internal peer, a BGP speaker
MAY choose to select the first path in order that did not originate from
the same BGP mesh (i.e. the set of non-client Internal peers) whenever
the best overall path has been received from this mesh and would be suppressed
by the Internal BGP non-readvertisement rule.</t>

    <t>When advertising a route to a Route Reflection client peer, in case the
overall best path has been received from the same cluster, a BGP speaker
MUST be able to advertise the best overall path to all the members of the
cluster other than the originator, unless "client-to-client" reflection is
disabled. The implementation MAY choose to advertise an alternate path to
the specific peer that originates the best overall path by excluding from
consideration all paths with the same originator-id.</t>

    <t>When "client-to-client" reflection is disabled and the cluster is
operating as a mesh, a Route Reflector MAY opt to advertise to the cluster
the preferred path from the set of paths not received from the cluster. While
this deployment mode is currently uncommon, it can be a practical way to
guarantee path diversity inside the cluster.</t>

    <t>A confederation border route MAY choose to advertise an alternate
path towards its Internal BGP mesh or towards a con-fed member AS following
the same procedure as defined above.</t>
    </list></t>

</section>

<section title="Consistency between routing and forwarding">
    <t>The internal update advertisement rules contained in the original
<xref target="RFC1771">BGP-4 specification</xref> can lead to situations
where traffic is forwarded through a route other than the route advertised by
BGP.</t>
    <t>Inconsistencies between forwarding and routing are highly undesirable.  Service providers use BGP with the dual objective of learning reach-ability information and expressing policy over network resources.  The latter assumes that forwarding follows routing information.</t>
    <t>Consider the Autonomous system presented in figure 1, where r1 ... r4 are members of a single IBGP mesh and routes a, b, and c are received from external peers.</t>

<figure title='Inconsistency in Routing'>
<artwork align='center'><![CDATA[                
     AS 1 (c)
       |
     +----+           +----+
     | r1 |...........| r2 |
     +----+           +----+
       .
       .
       .
       .
       .
       .
     +----+           +----+
     | r3 |...........| r4 | --- ebgp --- AS X
     +----+           +----+
    /      \
   /        \
AS 1 (a)  AS 2 (b)
]]></artwork>
</figure>

<texttable title='Path Attribute Table'>
<ttcol>Path</ttcol> <ttcol>AS</ttcol> <ttcol>MED</ttcol> <ttcol>rte_id</ttcol>
<c>a</c> <c>1</c> <c>10</c>   <c>1</c>
<c>b</c> <c>2</c>  <c>5</c>  <c>10</c>
<c>c</c> <c>1</c>  <c>5</c>   <c>5</c>
</texttable>
            <t>
                 Following the rules as specified in <xref target="RFC1771">RFC 1771</xref>, router r3 will select path (b) received from AS 2 as its overall best to install in the Loc-Rib, since path (b) is preferable to path (c), the lowest MED route from AS 1.  However for the purposes of Internal Update route selection, it will ignore the presence of path (c), and elect (a) as its advertisement, via the router-id tie-breaking rule.
            </t>
            <t>
                 In this scenario, router r4 will receive (c) from r1 and (a) from r3. It will pick the lowest MED route (c) and advertise it out via IBGP to AS X. However at this point routing is inconsistent with forwarding as traffic received from AS X will be forwarded towards AS 2, while the IBGP advertisement is being made for an AS 1 path.
            </t>
            <t>
                 Routing policies are typically specified in terms of neighboring AS-es.  In the situation above, assuming that AS 1 is network for which this AS provides transit services while AS 2 and AS X are peer networks, one can easily see how the inconsistency between routing and forwarding would lead to transit being inadvertently provided between AS X and AS 2.  This could lead to persistent forwarding loops.
            </t>
            <t>
                 Inconsistency between routing and forwarding may happen, whenever a GP speaker chooses to advertise an external route into IBGP that is different from the overall best route and its overall best is external.
            </t>
        </section>
        <section title="Applications"/>
        <section title="Fast Connectivity Restoration">
            <t>
                 When two exits are available to reach a particular destination and one is preferred over the other, the availability of an alternate path provides fast connectivity restoration when the primary path fails.
            </t>
            <t>
                 Restoration can be quick since the alternate path is already at hand. The border router could recompute the backup route and perinatal it in FIB ready to be switched when the primary goes away.  Note that this requires the border router that's the backup to also perinatal the secondary path and switch to it on failure.
            </t>
        </section>
        <section title="Inter-Domain Churn Reduction">
            <t>
                 Within an AS, the non availability of backup best leads to a border router sending a withdraw upstream when the primary fails.  This leads to inter-domain churn and packet loss for the time the network takes to converge to the alternate path.  Having the alternate path will reduces the churn and eliminates packet loss.
            </t>
        </section>
        <section title="Reducing Persistent IBGP oscillation">
            <t>
                 Advertising the best external route, according to the algorithm described in this document will reduce the possibility of route oscillation by introducing additional information into the IBGP system.
            </t>
            <t>
                 For a permanent oscillation condition to occur, it is necessary that a circular dependency between paths occurs such that the selection of a new best path by a router, in response to a received IBGP advertisement, causes the withdrawal of information that another router depends on in order to generate the original event.
            </t>
            <t>
                 In vanilla BGP, when only the best overall route is advertised, as in most implementations, oscillation can occur whenever there are 2 or clusters/sub-AS-es such that at least one cluster has more than one path that can potentially contribute to the dependency.
            </t>
        </section>
        <section title="Deployment Considerations">
            <t>
                 The mechanism specified in the draft allows a BGP speaker to advertise a route that is not the best route used for forwarding. This is a departure from the current behavior.  However, consistency in the path selection process across the AS is still guaranteed since the ingress routers will not choose the best-external route as the best route for a destination in steady state (for the same reason that the BGP speaker announcing the best-external route chose an IBGP route as best instead of the externally learnt route).  Though it is possible to alter this assurance by defining route policies on IBGP sessions, use of such policies in IBGP is not recommended, especially with best-external announcement turned on in the network.  It is also worth noting that such inconsistency in routing and forwarding is mitigated in a tunneled network.
            </t>
        </section>
        <section title="Acknowledgments">
            <t>
                 This document greatly benefits from the comments of Yakov Rekhter, John Scudder, Eric Rosen, Jenny Yuan, Jay Borkenhagen, Salkat Ray and
Jakob Heitz.
            </t>
        </section>
        <section title="IANA Considerations">
            <t>
                 This document has no actions for IANA.
            </t>
        </section>
        <section title="Security Considerations">
            <t>
                 There are no additional security risks introduced by this design.
            </t>
        </section>
    </middle>
<back>
    <references>
        <?rfc include="reference.RFC.1771.xml"?>
        <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119.xml"?>
        <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3345.xml"?>
        <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4271.xml"?>
        <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4456.xml"?>
        <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5065.xml"?>
    </references>	  
</back>
</rfc>
