<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!-- edited with XMLSPY v5 rel. 4 U (http://www.xmlspy.com) by Fred Baker (private) -->
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/authoring/rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc toc="no"?>
<?rfc tocompact="no"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="6"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<rfc category="std" docName="draft-bhatia-karp-ospf-ip-layer-protection-00"
     ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="OSPF IP Layer Protection">Mechanism to protect OSPFv2 authentication 
    from IP Layer Issues</title>

    <author fullname="Manav Bhatia" initials="M.B." surname="Bhatia">
      <organization>Alcatel-Lucent</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>
          <city>Bangalore</city>
          <code></code>
          <region></region>
          <country>India</country>
        </postal>
        <phone></phone>
        <email>manav.bhatia@alcatel-lucent.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date day="7" month="October" year="2010" />

    <area>Routing Area</area>
    <workgroup>KARP Working Group</workgroup>

    <abstract>
      <t>The IP header is not covered by the MAC in the cryptographic authentication scheme  
      as described in RFC 2328 and RFC 5709, and an attack can be made to exploit  
      this omission. This draft proposes a simple change in how the authentication
      is computed to eliminate most of such attacks.
      </t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>

        <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
        "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
        document are to be interpreted as described in RFC2119 <xref
        target="RFC2119"></xref>.</t>

        <t>When used in lower case, these words convey their typical use in
        common language, and are not to be interpreted as described in RFC2119
        <xref target="RFC2119"></xref>.</t>
  

    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>The OSPFv2 <xref target="RFC2328"></xref> cryptographic 
    authentication as described in <xref target="RFC2328"></xref> and 
   later updated in <xref target="RFC5709"></xref> does not include the IP
   header.  This can be exploited to launch several attacks as the source address 
  in the IP header is no longer protected. The OSPF specification,  in certain cases, requires the implementations to 
  look at the source address carried in the IP header to determine the neighbor the 
packet was recieved from. Changing the source address of a packet
   can thus, confuse the reciever which can be exploited to produce a number of denial of service attacks. 
<xref target="I-D.ietf-opsec-routing-protocols-crypto-issues"></xref>.  If the packet is
   interpreted as coming from a different neighbor, the sequence number
   received from the neighbor may be updated.  This may disrupt
   communication with the legitimate neighbor.  Hello packets may be
   reflected to cause a neighbor to appear to have one-way
   communication.  Old Database descriptions may be reflected in cases
   where the per-packet sequence numbers are sufficiently divergent in
   order to disrupt an adjacency <xref target="I-D.hartman-ospf-analysis"></xref>.
   </t> 
<t>
	<xref target="RFC2328"></xref> states that implementations MUST offer keyed MD5 
   authentication. It is likely that this will be deprecated in favor of  the stronger algorithms
   described in <xref target="RFC5709"></xref> in future deployments.
</t>
  <t>
	This draft proposes a simple change in the cryptographic authentication 
	mechanism, as currently described in <xref target="RFC5709"></xref>,
    to prevent such IP layer attacks.
  </t>
</section>

      <section title="Cryptographic Authentication Mechanism in OSPFv2">
	<t>
	The overall cryptographic authentication process defined in 
 <xref target="RFC5709"></xref> remains unchanged.
To reduce the potential for confusion, this section
   minimises the repetition of text from RFC 5709 and is
   incorporated here by reference  <xref target="RFC5709"></xref>. </t>

	<t>RFC 5709, Section 3.3, describes how the cryptographic authentication
   must be computed. It requires OSPFv2 packet's Authentication Trailer 
	 (which is the appendage described in RFC 2328, Section D.4.3, Page 233, items
       (6)(a) and (6)(d)) to be filled with the value Apad where Apad is a 
	hexadecimal constant value 0x878FE1F3 repeated (L/4) times, where L is the length
	of the hash being used and is measured in octets rather than bits.
   </t>
</section>
<section title="Proposed Enhancement">
	<t>
	
	This document updates the definition of  Apad which is currently a constant defined in <xref target="RFC5709"></xref>  to
    the source address thats carried in the IP header of the OSPFv2 protocol packet. Routers at the sending side 
    must initialize Apad to a value of the source address that would be used when sending out the OSPFv2 packet, repeated 
   L/4 times, where L is the length of the hash, measured in octets.

The basic idea is to incorporate the source address
   from the IP header in the cryptographic authentication computation so that
  any change there can be detected.</t>

<t>

   At the recieving end implementations MUST initialize Apad as the source
  address that exists in the IP Header of the incoming OSPFv2 protocol packet, repeated L/4 times, instead 
  of the constant that's currently defined in <xref target="RFC5709"></xref>.

 Besides changing the value of Apad this document does not introduce any other
 changes to the authentication mechanism described in <xref target="RFC5709"></xref>.



 <t> This would prevent all attacks where a rogue OSPF router changes
 the source address of  the protocol packet  and reflects it on some other
 interface as the authentication check would fail and all such packets would get
rejected.
</t>
</t>
</section>

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>This document enhances the security of OSPFv2 and provides a solution
           to prevent certain denial of service attacks that can be launched by changing
         the source address of the OSPFv2 protocol packet. The proposal defined  
       does not introduce any new  security concerns.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>This document has no actions for IANA.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>
     </t>      
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc ?>
<?rfc include='reference.RFC.2119'?>

       <?rfc include='reference.RFC.2328'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.5709'?>
 
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <?rfc ?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.hartman-ospf-analysis'?>
      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-opsec-routing-protocols-crypto-issues'?>	

    </references>

  </back>
</rfc>
