<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc toc="no"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<rfc category="info" docName="draft-bhatia-moving-ah-to-historic-00 "
     ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="Moving AH to Historic">Moving Authentication Header (AH) to Historic </title>

<author fullname="Manav Bhatia" initials="M." surname="Bhatia">
      <organization>Alcatel-Lucent</organization>

      <address>
        <email>manav.bhatia@alcatel-lucent.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
  
    <date day="30" month="December" year="2011" />

    <abstract>
      <t> This document recommends retiring Authentication Header (AH) and 
            discusses the reasons for doing so. It recommends moving RFC 4302 
           to Historic status.</t>
    </abstract>

    <note title="Requirements Language">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
      document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
      target="RFC2119">RFC 2119</xref>.</t>
    </note>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
	<t> IPsec uses two protocols to provide traffic security services --
   Authentication Header (AH) and Encapsulating Security Payload (ESP).
   Both protocols are described in detail in their respective RFCs
   <xref target="RFC4302"></xref> <xref target="RFC4303"></xref>
    </t>

	<t> <xref target="RFC4301"></xref>  recommends IPsec implementations 
           to MUST support ESP and MAY support AH. Support for AH was downgraded to MAY because
   experience has shown that there are very few contexts in which ESP
   cannot provide the requisite security services.  Note that ESP can be
   used to provide only integrity, without confidentiality, making it
   comparable to AH in most contexts.
	</t>

	<t> AH offers integrity and
      data origin authentication, with optional (at the discretion of
      the receiver) anti-replay features. ESP, on the other hand,
      offers the same set of services, and also additionally offers confidentiality.  
	</t>

	<t> These protocols may be applied individually or in combination with
   each other to provide IPv4 and IPv6 security services.  However, most
   security requirements can be met through the use of ESP by itself.
   Each protocol supports two modes of use: transport mode and tunnel
   mode.  In transport mode, AH and ESP provide protection primarily for
   next layer protocols; in tunnel mode, AH and ESP are applied to
   tunneled IP packets.  <xref target="RFC4301"></xref>   describes
   detailed differences between these two modes.
	</t>

	<t> There is no particular security problem with using AH. It lives up to its security claims. 
      Its just that its completely redundant with ESP, since ESP will NULL encryption (ESP-NULL) <xref target="RFC2410"></xref> can provide
       the same functionality and the world can do with one less protocol. </t>

     <t> Moving AH to historic doesn't mean that people have to stop using AH right now.
            It only means that in the opinion of the community there are now better alternatives.
           Moving AH to historic will discourage new protocols to mandate the use of AH.
           It however, does not preclude the possibility of new work to IETF that will require or enhance AH.
           It just means that the authors will have to explain why that solution is really needed
           and why ESP-NULL cant be used instead.
	</t>
          </section>

    <section title="AH and ESP">
	<t> It is alleged that AH provides more security than ESP in the transport mode 
           as AH also authenticates the IP header fields. This argument
          is however moot as ESP in the tunnel mode can provide the 
           same level of security since the payload now includes the
           original IP header. It is also believed by many that securing the
           IP header isnt really very important <xref target="Schneier"></xref>.
	</t>

	<t> It is commonly believed that AH is quite useful in securing the
          IPv6 extension headers. AH protects most of the basic IPv6 header,
         the non-mutable extension headers after the AH, and the IP payload. 
         Protection for the IPv6 header excludes the mutable fields: DSCP, ECN, 
         Flow Label, and Hop Limit. ESP, on the other hand, doesn't protect the 
         immutable parts of the IPv6 header nor those of any extension header.
         This can however be fixed by putting the IPv6 extension headers that
         are required to be protected after the ESP header. Hop-by-Hop options 
         are not an issue, as the intermediate hops do not have keys to verify the message
         authentication code so they cannot really be protected anyways.
	</t>

	<t> AH breaks Network Address Translators (NATs). This is because AH relies on the sanctity of the IP header
       so that any tamperings, even by a NAT, get detected and packets get discarded.
       Solving this issue requires another device that fixes the NAT translation back to the original 
       one (a specific case of Double NAT).  ESP, on the other hand, fixes this problem
       by encapsulating ESP packets inside UDP packets for traversing NATs <xref target="RFC3948"></xref>.
	</t>

	<t> Firewalls in the enterprise environments often require visibility into packets, ranging from simple packet header
   inspection to deeper payload examination. Routers also often need to deep inspect control traffic
       to prioritize certain protocol packets over the others. This was initially difficult with ESP since was impossible
      to know whether an ESP packet was integrity protected or encrypted by merely inspecting the packet. This was
      easy with AH since the payload was transmitted in clear. This problem however has been solved by introducing WESP
      <xref target="RFC5840"></xref> which defines a mechanism to provide additional information
   in relevant IPsec packets so intermediate devices can efficiently differentiate between encrypted and integrity-only ESP packets.   
	</t>
	
	<t> ESP-NULL seems to do everything useful that can be done with AH. Given this, it makes sense to move AH to 
       Historic status so that newer protocols dont mandate or propose extensions that rely on AH to be supported.
	</t>

    </section>


    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>Its argued that ESP in the tunnel mode is equivalent to the AH in the transport mode.
          It should however be noted that ESP tunnel mode SA applied to an IPv6 flow results in at least 50
   bytes of additional overhead per packet.  This additional overhead
   may be undesirable for many bandwidth-constrained wireless and/or
   satellite communications networks, as these types of infrastructure
   are not overprovisioned.
</t>

	<t> Packet overhead is particularly significant for traffic profiles
   characterized by small packet payloads (e.g., various voice codecs).
   If these small packets are afforded the security services of an IPsec
   tunnel mode SA, the amount of per-packet overhead is increased.
	</t>

	<t> This issue will perhaps be alleviated by header compression
         schemes defined in <xref target="RFC5856"></xref> <xref target="RFC5857"></xref>
         and <xref target="RFC5858"></xref>.
         
	</t>
	      
    </section>

<section anchor="iana" title="IANA Considerations">
<t> None </t>
      
    </section>
  
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119"?>

<?rfc include='reference.RFC.2410'?>
<?rfc include='reference.RFC.4302'?>
<?rfc include='reference.RFC.4303'?>
<?rfc include='reference.RFC.4301'?>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      
<?rfc include='reference.RFC.3948'?>
<?rfc include='reference.RFC.5840'?>
<?rfc include='reference.RFC.5856'?>
<?rfc include='reference.RFC.5857'?>
<?rfc include='reference.RFC.5858'?>

  <reference anchor="Schneier"
         target="http://www.schneier.com/paper-ipsec.pdf">
        <front> 
          <title>A Cryptographic Evaluation of IPsec</title>

          <author fullname="Niels Ferguson" initials="N" surname="Ferguson">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="Bruce Schneier" initials="B" surname="Schneier">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date month="December " year="2003" />
        </front>
      </reference>
	
   </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
