<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc toc="no"?>
<?rfc tocompact="no"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="6"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<rfc category="std" docName="draft-bhatia-zhang-karp-bfd-analysis-02"
     ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="BFD Gap Analysis">Analysis of Bidirectional Forwarding
    Detection (BFD) Security According to KARP Design Guide</title>

    <author fullname="Manav Bhatia" initials="M.B." surname="Bhatia">
      <organization>Alcatel-Lucent</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>

          <city>Bangalore</city>

          <code></code>

          <region></region>

          <country>India</country>
        </postal>

        <phone></phone>

        <email>manav.bhatia@alcatel-lucent.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Dacheng Zhang" initials="D." surname="Zhang">
      <organization>Huawei Technologies co., LTD.</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>

          <city>Beijing</city>

          <region></region>

          <code></code>

          <country>China</country>
        </postal>

        <phone></phone>

        <facsimile></facsimile>

        <email>zhangdacheng@huawei.com</email>

        <uri></uri>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date day="25" month="January" year="2012" />

    <abstract>
      <t>This document analyzes the Bidirectional Forwarding Detection
      protocol (BFD) according to the guidelines set forth in section 4.2 of
      draft-ietf-karp-design-guide.</t>
    </abstract>

    <note title="Requirements Language">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
      document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
      target="RFC2119">RFC 2119</xref>.</t>
    </note>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>This document performs a gap analysis of the current state of BFD
      <xref target="RFC5880"></xref> according to the requirements of <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-karp-design-guide"></xref>. Previously, the OPSEC
      working group has provided an analysis of cryptographic issues with BFD
      in <xref target="RFC6039"></xref>.</t>

      <t>The existing BFD specifications provide a very initial security
      solution. Key ID is provided so that the key used in securing a packet
      can be changed on demand. Two cryptographic algorithms (MD5 and SHA-1)
      are supported for Integrity protection of the control packets; the
      algorithms are both demonstrated to be subject to collision attacks.
      While these attacks will not necessarily affect BFD, other routing
      protocols like RIPv2 <xref target="RFC4822"></xref>, IS-IS <xref
      target="RFC5310"></xref> and OSPFv2 <xref target="RFC5709"></xref> have
      moved to stronger algorithms and it is imperative that BFD also does
      that as it does not make much sense to secure these routing protocols
      with a stronger authentication algorithm if BFD continues using a weaker
      security algorithm.</t>

      <t>While BFD uses a non-decreasing per-packet sequence number to protect
      itself from intra-connection replay attacks, it still leaves the
      protocol vulnerable to the inter-session replay attacks.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Requirements to Meet ">
      <t>There are several requirements described in section 3 of <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-karp-threats-reqs"></xref> that BFD does not currently
      meet:</t>

      <t><list style="empty">
          <t>Replay Protection: BFD provides an incomplete intra-session and
          no inter-session replay attack protection; this creates significant
          denial-of-service opportunities.</t>

          <t>Strong Algorithms: the cryptographic algorithms adopted for
          message authentication in BFD are MD5 or SHA-1 based. However, both
          algorithms are known to be vulnerable to collision attacks. <xref
          target="I-D.ietf-bfd-generic-crypto-auth"></xref> and 
          <xref target="I-D.ietf-bfd-hmac-sha"></xref>  together propose a solution to
          support HMAC with the SHA-2 family of hash functions for
          BFD.</t>

          <t>DoS Attacks: BFD packets can be sent at millisecond intervals
          (the protocol uses timers at microsecond intervals). When malicious
          packets are sent at short intervals, with the authentication bit
          set, it can cause a DoS attack.</t>
        </list>The remainder of this document explains the details of how
      these requirements fail to be met and proposes mechanisms for addressing
      them.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Current State ">
      <t><xref target="RFC5880"></xref> describes five authentication
      mechanisms for the integrity protection of BFD control packets: Simple
      Password, Keyed MD5 <xref target="RFC1321"></xref>, Meticulous Keyed
      MD5, Keyed SHA-1 and Meticulous SHA-1. In the simple password mechanism,
      every control packet is associated with a password transported in plain
      text; attacks eavesdropping the network traffic can easily learn the
      password and compromise the security of the corresponding BFD session.
      In the Keyed MD5 and the Meticulous Keyed MD5 mechanisms, BFD nodes use
      share secret keys to generate keyed MD5 digests for control packets.
      Similarly, in the Keyed SHA-1 and the Meticulous Keyed SHA-1 mechanisms,
      BFD nodes use shared secret keys to generate keyed SHA-1 digests for
      control packets. Note that in the keyed authentication mechanisms, every
      BFD control packet is associated with a non-decreasing 32-bit sequence
      number to resist replay attacks. In the Keyed MD5 and the Keyed SHA-1
      mechanisms, the sequence member is only required to increase
      occasionally. However, in the Meticulous Keyed MD5 and the Meticulous
      Keyed SHA-1 mechanisms, the sequence member is required to monotonically
      increase with each succesive packet.</t>

      <t>Additionally, limited key updating functionality is provided. There
      is a Key ID in every authenticated BFD control packet, indicating the
      key used to hash the packet. However, there is no mechanism described to
      provide a smooth key rollover that the BFD routers can use when moving
      from one key to the other.</t>

      <t>The BFD session timers are defined with the granularity of
      microseconds, and it is common in practice to send BFD packets at
      millisecond intervals. Since the cryptographic sequence number space is
      only 32 bits, a sequence number used in a BFD session may reach its
      maximum value and roll over within limited period. For instance, if a
      sequence number is increased by one every millisecond, then it will
      reach its maximum value in less than 8 weeks. This can result in potential
      inter-session replay attacks especially when BFD uses the non-meticulous
      authentication modes.</t>

      <t>Note that when using authentication mechanisms, BFD requests the
      sequence of a received BFD packets drops with a limited range (3*
      Detection time multiplier). Therefore, when meticulous authentication
      modes are used, a replayed BFD packet will be rejected if it cannot
      fit into a relatively short window (3 times of the detect interval of
      the session). This introduces some difficulties for replaying packets.
      However, in a non-meticulous authentication mode, such windows
      can be large as sequence numbers are only increased occassionally, 
      thus making it easier to perform replay attacks .</t>

      <t>In a BFD session, each node needs to select a 32-bit discriminator
      to identify itself. Therefore, a BFD session is identified by two
      discriminators. If a node will randomly select a new discriminator for a
      new session and use authentication mechanism to secure the control
      packets, inter-session replay attacks can be mitigated to some extent.
      However, in existing BFD demultiplexing mechanisms, the discriminators
      used in a new BFD session may be predictable. In some deployment
      scenarios, the discriminators of BFD routers may be decided by the
      destination and source addresses. So, if the sequence number of a BFD
      router rolls over for some reasons (e.g., reboot), the
      discriminators used to identify the new session will be identical to the
      ones used in the previous session. This makes performing a reply attack
      relatively simple. </t>

      <t>BFD allows a mode called the echo mode. Echo packets are not defined
      in the BFD specification, though they can keep the BFD session up. The
      format of the echo packet is local to the sending side and there are no
      guidelines on the properties of these packets beyond the choice of the
      source and destination addresses. While the BFD specification recommends
      applying security mechanisms to prevent spoofing of these packets, there
      are no guidelines on what type of mechanisms are appropriate.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Impacts of BFD Replays ">
      <t>As discussed, BFD cannot meet the requirements of inter-session or
      intra-session replay protection. This section discusses the impacts of
      BFD replays.</t>

      <t>When cryptographic authentication mechanisms are adopted for BFD, a
      non-decreasing 32-bit long sequence number is used. In the Keyed MD5 and
      the Keyed SHA-1 mechanisms, the sequence member is not required to
      increase for every packet. Therefore an attacker can keep replaying the
      packets with the latest sequence number until the sequence number is
      updated. This issue is eliminated in the Meticulous Keyed MD5 and the
      Meticulous Keyed SHA-1 mechanisms. However, note that a sequence number
      may reach its maximum and be rolled over in a session. In this case,
      without the support from a automatic key management mechanism, the BFD
      session will be vulnerable to replay attacks performed by sending the
      packets before the roll over of the sequence number. For instance, an
      attacker can replay a packet with a sequence number which is larger than
      the current one. If the replayed packet is accepted, the victim will
      reject the legal packets whose sequence members are less than the one in
      the replayed packet. Therefore, the attacker can get a good chance to
      bring down the BFD session.</t>

      <t>Additionally, the BFD specification allows for the change of
      authentication state based on the state of a received packet. For
      instance, according to <xref target="RFC5880"></xref>, if the state of a
      accepted packet is down, the receiver of the packet needs to transfer
      its state to down as well. Therefore, an elaborately selected replayed
      packet can cause a serious denial-of-service attack.</t>

      <t>BFD does not provide any solution to deal with inter-session replay
      attacks. If two subsequent BFD sessions adopt an identical discriminator
      pair and use the same cryptographic key to secure the control packets,
      it is intuitive to use a malicious authenticated packet (stored from the
      past session) to perform inter-connection replay attacks.</t>

      <t>Any security issues in the BFD echo mode will directly affect the BFD
      protocol and session states, and hence the network stability. For
      instance, any replay attacks would be indistinguishable from normal
      forwarding of the tested router. An attack would still cause a faulty
      link to be believed to be up, but there is little that can be done about
      it. However, if the echo packets are guessable, it may be possible to
      spoof from an external source and cause BFD to believe that a one-way
      link is really bidirectional. As a result, it is important that the echo
      packets contain random material that is also checked upon reception.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>This document makes no request of IANA.</t>

      <t>Note to RFC Editor: this section may be removed on publication as an
      RFC.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t></t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>We would like to thank Alexander Vainshtein for his comments on this document.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119"?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.1321'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6039'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.5880'?>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-karp-threats-reqs'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-karp-design-guide'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-bfd-generic-crypto-auth'?>
      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-bfd-hmac-sha'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.4822'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.5310'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.5709'?>
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
