<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!-- This template is for creating an Internet Draft using xml2rfc,
     which is available here: http://xml.resource.org. -->
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!-- One method to get references from the online citation libraries.
     There has to be one entity for each item to be referenced. 
     An alternate method (rfc include) is described in the references. -->
<!ENTITY RFC2119 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3588 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3588.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC2434 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2434.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4005 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4005.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4675 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4675.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5226 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5226.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5777 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5777.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5624 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5624.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5866 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5866.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6144 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6144.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6145 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6145.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6146 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6146.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6147 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6147.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC1661 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1661.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3022 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3022.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4097 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4097.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC2663 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2663.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC2776 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2776.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3550 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3550.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3303 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3303.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3304 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3304.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5189 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5189.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3411 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3411.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6241 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6241.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.draft-ietf-behave-lsn-requirements SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.draft-ietf-behave-lsn-requirements-03.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.narten-iana-considerations-rfc2434bis SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.narten-iana-considerations-rfc2434bis.xml">
]>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<!-- used by XSLT processors -->
<!-- For a complete list and description of processing instructions (PIs), 
     please see http://xml.resource.org/authoring/README.html. -->
<!-- Below are generally applicable Processing Instructions (PIs) that most I-Ds might want to use.
     (Here they are set differently than their defaults in xml2rfc v1.32) -->
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<!-- give errors regarding ID-nits and DTD validation -->
<!-- control the table of contents (ToC) -->
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<!-- generate a ToC -->
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<!-- the number of levels of subsections in ToC. default: 3 -->
<!-- control references -->
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<!-- use symbolic references tags, i.e, [RFC2119] instead of [1] -->
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<!-- sort the reference entries alphabetically -->
<!-- control vertical white space 
     (using these PIs as follows is recommended by the RFC Editor) -->
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<!-- do not start each main section on a new page -->
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<!-- keep one blank line between list items -->
<!-- end of list of popular I-D processing instructions -->
<rfc category="std" docName="draft-ietf-dime-nat-control-11" ipr="trust200902">
  <!-- ipr="full3978"-->

  <!-- category values: std, bcp, info, exp, and historic
     ipr values: full3667, noModification3667, noDerivatives3667
     you can add the attributes updates="NNNN" and obsoletes="NNNN" 
     they will automatically be output with "(if approved)" -->

  <!-- ***** FRONT MATTER ***** -->

  <front>
    <!-- The abbreviated title is used in the page header - it is only necessary if the 
         full title is longer than 39 characters -->

    <title abbrev="Diameter NAT Control Application">Diameter Network Address
    and Port Translation Control Application</title>

    <!-- add 'role="editor"' below for the editors if appropriate -->

    <!-- Another author who claims to be an editor -->

    <author fullname="Frank Brockners" initials="F." surname="Brockners">
      <organization>Cisco</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Hansaallee 249, 3rd Floor</street>

          <!-- Reorder these if your country does things differently -->

          <city>DUESSELDORF</city>

          <region>NORDRHEIN-WESTFALEN</region>

          <code>40549</code>

          <country>Germany</country>
        </postal>

        <email>fbrockne@cisco.com</email>

        <!-- uri and facsimile elements may also be added -->
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Shwetha Bhandari" initials="S." surname="Bhandari">
      <organization>Cisco</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Cessna Business Park, Sarjapura Marathalli Outer Ring
          Road</street>

          <city>Bangalore, KARNATAKA 560 087</city>

          <country>India</country>
        </postal>

        <email>shwethab@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Vaneeta Singh" initials="V." surname="Singh">
      <organization></organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>18, Cambridge Road</street>

          <city>Bangalore 560008</city>

          <country>India</country>
        </postal>

        <email>vaneeta.singh@gmail.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Victor Fajardo" initials="V." surname="Fajardo">
      <organization>Telcordia Technologies</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>1 Telcordia Drive #1S-222</street>

          <city>Piscataway, NJ 08854</city>

          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>

        <email>vf0213@gmail.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date day="2" month="September" year="2011" />

    <!-- If the month and year are both specified and are the current ones, xml2rfc will fill 
         in the current day for you. If only the current year is specified, xml2rfc will fill 
	 in the current day and month for you. If the year is not the current one, it is 
	 necessary to specify at least a month (xml2rfc assumes day="1" if not specified for the 
	 purpose of calculating the expiry date).  With drafts it is normally sufficient to 
	 specify just the year. -->

    <!-- Meta-data Declarations -->

    <area>General</area>

    <workgroup>Internet Engineering Task Force</workgroup>

    <!-- WG name at the upperleft corner of the doc,
         IETF is fine for individual submissions.  
	 If this element is not present, the default is "Network Working Group",
         which is used by the RFC Editor as a nod to the history of the IETF. -->

    <keyword>diameter</keyword>

    <!-- Keywords will be incorporated into HTML output
         files in a meta tag but they have no effect on text or nroff
         output. If you submit your draft to the RFC Editor, the
         keywords will be used for the search engine. -->

    <abstract>
      <t>This document describes the framework, messages, and procedures for
      the Diameter Network address and port translation Control Application.
      This Diameter application allows per endpoint control of Network Address
      Translators and Network Address and Port Translators, which are added to
      networks to cope with IPv4-address space depletion. This Diameter
      application allows external devices to configure and manage a Network
      Address Translator device - expanding the existing Diameter-based AAA
      and policy control capabilities with a Network Address Translators and
      Network Address and Port Translators control component. These external
      devices can be network elements in the data plane such as a Network
      Access Server, or can be more centralized control plane devices such as
      AAA-servers. This Diameter application establishes a context to commonly
      identify and manage endpoints on a gateway or server, and a Network
      Address Translator and Network Address and Port Translator device. This
      includes, for example, the control of the total number of Network
      Address Translator bindings allowed or the allocation of a specific
      Network Address Translator binding for a particular endpoint. In
      addition, it allows Network Address Translator devices to provide
      information relevant to accounting purposes.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction" toc="default">
      <t>Internet service providers deploy Network Address Translators (NATs)
      and Network Address and Port Translators (NAPTs) <xref
      target="RFC3022"></xref> in their networks. A key motivation for doing
      so is the depletion of available public IPv4 addresses. This document
      defines a Diameter application allowing providers to control the
      behavior of NAT and NAPT devices that implement IPv4-to-IPv4 network
      address and port translation <xref target="RFC2663"></xref> as well as
      stateful IPv6-to-IPv4 address family translation translation as defined
      in <xref target="RFC2663"></xref>, <xref target="RFC6145"></xref>, and
      <xref target="RFC6146"></xref>. The use of a Diameter application allows
      for simple integration into the existing Authentication, Authorization
      and Accounting (AAA) environment of a provider.</t>

      <t>The Diameter Network address and port translation Control Application
      (DNCA) offers the following capabilities:</t>

      <t><list style="numbers">
          <t>Limits or defines the number of NAPT/NAT bindings made available
          to an individual end point or user. The main motivation for
          restricting the number of bindings on a per end point basis is to
          protect the service of the service provider against denial of
          service attacks. If multiple end points share a single public IP
          address, these end points can share fate. If one end point would
          (either intentionally, or due to mis-behavior, mis-configuration,
          mal-ware, etc.) be able to consume all available bindings for a
          given single public IP address, service would be hampered (or might
          even become unavailable) for those other end points sharing the same
          public IP address. The efficiency of a NAPT deployment depends on
          the maximum number of bindings an end point could use. Given that
          the typical number of bindings an end point uses depends on the type
          of end point (e.g. a personal computer of a broadband user is
          expected to use a higher number of bindings than a simple mobile
          phone) and a NAPT device is often shared by different types of end
          points, it is desirable to actively manage the maximum number of
          bindings. This requirement is specified in REQ-3 of <xref
          target="I-D.ietf-behave-lsn-requirements"></xref></t>

          <t>Supports the allocation of specific NAPT/NAT bindings. Two types
          of specific bindings can be distinguished:<list style="symbols">
              <t>Allocation of a pre-defined NAT binding: Both the internal
              and external IP address and port pair are specified within the
              request. Some deployment cases, such as access to a web-server
              within a user&rsquo;s home network with IP address and port,
              benefit from statically configured bindings.</t>

              <t>Allocation of an external IP address for a given internal IP
              address: The allocated external IP address is reported back to
              the requestor. In some deployment scenarios, the application
              requires immediate knowledge of the allocated binding for a
              given internal IP address but does not control the allocation of
              the external IP address; for example, SIP-proxy server
              deployments.</t>
            </list></t>

          <t>Defines the external address pool(s) to be used for allocating an
          external IP address: External address pools can either be
          pre-assigned at the NAPT/NAT device, or specified within a request.
          If pre-assigned address pools are used, a request needs to include a
          reference to identify the pool. Otherwise, the request contains a
          description of the IP address pool(s) to be used; for example, a
          list of IP-subnets. Such external address pools can be used to
          select the external IP address in NAPT/NAT bindings for multiple
          subscribers.</t>

          <t>Generates reports and accounting records: Reports established
          bindings for a particular user. The collected information is used by
          accounting systems for statistical purposes.</t>

          <t>Queries and retrieves details about bindings on demand: This
          feature complements the previously mentioned accounting
          functionality (see item 4). This feature can be used by an entity to
          find NAT-bindings belonging to one or multiple end points on the
          NAT-device. The entity is not required to create a DNCA control
          session to perform the query, but would obviously still need to
          create a Diameter session complying to the security
          requirements.</t>

          <t>Identifies a subscriber or endpoint on multiple network devices
          (NAT/NAPT device, the AAA-server, or the Network Access Server
          (NAS)): Endpoint identification is facilitated through a Global
          Endpoint ID. Endpoints are identified through a single or a set of
          classifiers, such as IP address, Virtual Local Area Network (VLAN)
          identifier, or interface identifier which uniquely identify the
          traffic associated with a particular global endpoint.</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>With the above capabilities, DNCA qualifies as a MIDCOM protocol
      <xref target="RFC3303"></xref>, <xref target="RFC3304"></xref>, <xref
      target="RFC5189"></xref> for middle boxes which perform NAT. The MIDCOM
      protocol evaluation <xref target="RFC4097"></xref> evaluated Diameter as
      a candidate protocol for MIDCOM. DNCA provides the extensions to the
      Diameter base protocol <xref target="RFC3588"></xref> following the
      MIDCOM protocol requirements, such as the support of NAT-specific rule
      transport, support for oddity of mapped ports, as well as support for
      consecutive range port numbers. DNCA adds to the MIDCOM protocol
      capabilities in that it allows to maintain the reference to an end point
      representing a user or subscriber in the control operation, enabling the
      control of the behavior of a NAT-device on a per end point basis.
      Following the requirements of different operators and deployments,
      different management protocols are employed. Examples include e.g. SNMP
      <xref target="RFC3411"></xref> and NETCONF <xref
      target="RFC6241"></xref> which can both be used for device
      configuration. Similarly, DNCA is complementing existing MIDCOM
      implementations, offering a MIDCOM protocol option for operators with an
      operational environment that is Diameter-focused which desire to use
      Diameter to perform per end point NAT control. </t>

      <t>This document is structured as follows: Section 2 lists terminology,
      while Section 3 provides an introduction to DNCA and its overall
      deployment framework. Sections 4 to 8 cover DNCA specifics, with Section
      4 describing session management, Section 5 the use of the Diameter base
      protocol, Section 6 new commands, Section 7 Attribute Value Pairs(AVPs)
      used, and Section 8 accounting aspects. Section 9 presents AVP
      occurrence tables. IANA and security considerations are addressed in
      Sections 10 and 11.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Conventions" title="Conventions">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
      document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
      target="RFC2119"></xref>.</t>

      <t>Abbreviations used in this document:</t>

      <t><list style="empty">
          <t>AAA: Authentication, Authorization, Accounting</t>

          <t>DNCA: Diameter Network address and port translation Control
          Application</t>

          <t>NAPT: Network Address and Port Translation, see also <xref
          target="RFC3022"></xref></t>

          <t>NAT: Network Address Translation (NAT and NAPT are used in this
          document interchangeably)</t>

          <t>NAT-binding or binding: Association of two IP address/port pairs
          (with one IP address typically being private and the other one
          public) to facilitate NAT</t>

          <t>NAT Binding Predefined template: Is a policy template or
          configuration that is predefined at the NAT-device. It may contain
          NAT-bindings, IP-address pools for allocating the external
          IP-address of a NAT-binding, the maximum number of allowed
          NAT-bindings for end-points, etc.</t>

          <t>NAT-device: Network Address Translator or Network Address and
          Port Translator: An entity performing NAT or NAPT.</t>

          <t>NAT-controller: Entity controlling the behavior of a
          NAT-device.</t>

          <t>NAS: Network Access Server</t>

          <t>NCR: NAT Control Request</t>

          <t>NCA: NAT Control Answer</t>

          <t>NAT44: IPv4 to IPv4 network address and port translation, see
          <xref target="RFC2663"></xref></t>

          <t>NAT64: IPv6 to IPv4 address family translation, see <xref
          target="RFC6145"></xref> and <xref target="RFC6146"></xref></t>

          <t>PPP: Point-to-Point Protocol <xref target="RFC1661"></xref></t>
        </list></t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="framework" title="Deployment Framework">
      <section title="Deployment Scenario">
        <t><xref target="fig-network-deployment"></xref> shows a typical
        network deployment for IPv4-Internet access. A user&rsquo;s IPv4 host
        gains access to the Internet though a NAS, which facilitates the
        authentication of the endpoint and configures the user&rsquo;s
        connection according to the authorization and configuration data
        received from the AAA-server upon successful authentication. Public
        IPv4 addresses are used throughout the network.</t>

        <figure anchor="fig-network-deployment"
                title="Typical network deployment for internet access">
          <artwork><![CDATA[
                      +---------+
                      |         |
                      |   AAA   |
                      |         |
                      +---------+
                           |
                           |
                           |
                           |
 +---------+          +---------+             +----------+
 |  IPv4   |          |         |             |  IPv4    |
 |  Host   |----------|   NAS   |-------------| Internet |
 |         |          |         |             |          |
 +---------+          +---------+             +----------+

 <-------------------- Public IPv4 ---------------------->
]]></artwork>
        </figure>

        <t><xref target="fig-NAT-deployment"></xref> depicts the deployment
        scenario where a service provider places a NAT between the host and
        the public Internet. The objective is to provide the customer with
        connectivity to the public IPv4 Internet. The NAT-device performs
        network address and port (and optionally address family) translation,
        depending on whether the access network uses private IPv4 addresses or
        public IPv6 addresses, to public IPv4 addresses. Note that there may
        be more than one NAS, NAT-device, or AAA-entity in a deployment,
        although the figures only depict one entity each for clarity.</t>

        <t>If the NAT-device would be put in place without any endpoint
        awareness, the service offerings of the service provider could be
        impacted as detailed in <xref
        target="I-D.ietf-behave-lsn-requirements"></xref>. This includes cases
        like:</t>

        <t><list style="symbols">
            <t>Provisioning static NAT bindings for particular endpoints</t>

            <t>Using different public IP address pools for different set of
            endpoints (for example, residential or business customers)</t>

            <t>Reporting allocated bindings on a per endpoint basis</t>

            <t>Integrate control of the NAT-device into the already existing
            per endpoint management infrastructure of the service provider</t>
          </list></t>

        <figure anchor="fig-NAT-deployment"
                title="Access network deployment with NAT">
          <artwork><![CDATA[
                +---------+
                |         |
                |   AAA   |
                |         |
                +---------+
                     |
                     |
                     |
                     |
  +--------+    +---------+    +--------+    +----------+
  |        |    |         |    |        |    |          |
  |  Host  |----|   NAS   |----|  NAT-  |----| IPv4-    |
  |        |    |         |    | device |    | Internet |
  +--------+    +---------+    +--------+    +----------+

For NAT44 deployments (IPv4 host):
     <----- Private IPv4 ----------><--- Public IPv4 --->

For NAT64 deployments (IPv6 host):
     <----- Public  IPv6 ----------><--- Public IPv4 --->
]]></artwork>
        </figure>

        <t><xref target="fig-NAT-deployment"></xref> shows a typical
        deployment for IPv4-Internet access involving a NAT-device within the
        service provider network. The figure describes two scenarios: One
        where an IPv4-host (with a private IPv4 address) accesses the
        IPv4-Internet, as well as one where an IPv6-host accesses the
        IPv4-Internet.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Diameter NAPT Control Application Overview">
        <t>DNCA runs between two DNCA Diameter peers. One DNCA Diameter peer
        resides within the NAT-device, the other DNCA Diameter peer resides
        within a NAT-controller (discussed in Section 3.3). DNCA allows per
        endpoint control and management of NAT within the NAT-device. Based on
        Diameter, DNCA integrates well with the suite of Diameter applications
        deployed for per endpoint authentication, authorization, accounting,
        and policy control in service provider networks.</t>

        <t>DNCA offers:<list style="symbols">
            <t>Request and answer commands to control the allowed number of
            NAT bindings per endpoint to request the allocation of specific
            bindings for an endpoint, to define the address pool to be used
            for an endpoint.</t>

            <t>Provides per endpoint reporting of the allocated NAT
            bindings.</t>

            <t>Provides unique identification of an endpoint on NAT-device,
            AAA-server and NAS, to simplify correlation of accounting data
            streams.</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>DNCA allows controlling the behavior of a NAT-device on a per
        endpoint basis during initial session establishment and at later
        stages by providing an update procedure for already established
        sessions. Using DNCA, per endpoint NAT binding information can be
        retrieved either using accounting mechanisms or through an explicit
        session query to the NAT.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Deployment Scenarios For DNCA">
        <t>DNCA can be deployed in different ways. DNCA supports deployments
        with "n" NAT-controllers and "m" NAT-devices, with n and m equal to or
        greater than 1. For DNCA, the session representing a particular
        endpoint is atomic. Any deployment MUST ensure that for every given
        endpoint only a single NAT-controller and only a single NAT-device are
        active at any point in time. This is to ensure that NAT-devices
        controlled by multiple NAT-controllers do not receive conflicting
        control requests for a particular endpoint, or would be unclear which
        NAT-controller to send accounting information to.</t>

        <t>Two common deployment scenarios are outlined in <xref
        target="fig-NAT-integrated-deployment"></xref> (&ldquo;integrated
        deployment&rdquo;) and <xref
        target="fig-NAT-autonomous-deployment"></xref> (&ldquo;autonomous
        deployment&rdquo;). Per the note above, multiple instances of
        NAT-controllers and NAT-devices could be deployed. The figures only
        show single instances for reasons of clarity. The two shown scenarios
        differ in which entity fulfills the role of the NAT-controller. Within
        the figures (C) denotes the network element performing the role of the
        NAT-controller.</t>

        <t>The integrated deployment approach hides the existence of the
        NAT-device from external servers, such as the AAA-server. It is suited
        for environments where minimal changes to the existing AAA deployment
        are desired. The NAS and the NAT-device are Diameter peers supporting
        the DNCA. The Diameter peer within the NAS, performing the role of the
        NAT-controller, initiates and manages sessions with the NAT-device,
        exchanges NAT specific configuration information and handles reporting
        and accounting information. The NAS receives reporting and accounting
        information from the NAT-device. With this information, the NAS can
        provide a single accounting record for the endpoint. A system
        correlating the accounting information received from the NAS and
        NAT-device would not be needed.</t>

        <t>An example network attachment for an integrated NAT deployment can
        be described as follows: An endpoint connects to the network, with the
        NAS being the point of attachment. After successful authentication,
        the NAS receives endpoint related authorization data from the
        AAA-server. A portion of the authorization data applies to per
        endpoint configuration on the NAS itself, another portion describes
        authorization and configuration information for NAT control aimed at
        the NAT-device. The NAS initiates a DNCA session to the NAT-device and
        sends relevant authorization and configuration information for the
        particular endpoint to the NAT-device. This can comprise NAT-bindings,
        which have to be pre-established for the endpoint, or management
        related configuration, such as the maximum number of NAT-bindings
        allowed for the endpoint. The NAT-device sends its per endpoint
        accounting information to the NAS, which aggregates the accounting
        information received from the NAT-device with its local accounting
        information for the endpoint into a single accounting stream towards
        the AAA-server.</t>

        <figure anchor="fig-NAT-integrated-deployment"
                title="NAT control deployment: Integrated deployment">
          <artwork><![CDATA[
                +---------+
                |         |
                |   AAA   |
                |         |
                +---------+
                     |
                     |
                     |
  +--------+    +---------+    +--------+    +----------+
  |        |    |   (C)   |    |        |    |          |
  |  Host  |----|   NAS   |----|  NAT-  |----| IPv4-    |
  |        |    |         |    | device |    | Internet |
  +--------+    +---------+    +--------+    +----------+

For NAT44 deployments (IPv4 host):
     <----- Private IPv4 ----------><--- Public IPv4 --->

For NAT64 deployments (IPv6 host):
     <----- Public  IPv6 ----------><--- Public IPv4 --->
]]></artwork>
        </figure>

        <t><xref target="fig-NAT-integrated-deployment"></xref> shows examples
        of integrated deployments. The figure describes two scenarios: One
        where an IPv4-host (with a private IPv4 address) accesses the
        IPv4-Internet, as well as one where an IPv6-host accesses the
        IPv4-Internet.</t>

        <t>The autonomous deployment approach decouples user management on the
        NAS and NAT-device. In the autonomous deployment approach, the
        AAA-system and the NAT-device are the Diameter peers running the DNCA.
        The AAA-system also serves as NAT-controller. It manages the
        connection to the NAT-device, controls the per endpoint configuration,
        and also receives accounting and reporting information from the
        NAT-device. Different from the integrated deployment scenario, the
        autonomous deployment scenario does not &ldquo;hide&rdquo; the
        existence of the NAT-device from the AAA infrastructure. Here two
        accounting streams are received by the AAA-server for one particular
        endpoint, one from the NAS, and one from the NAT-device.</t>

        <figure anchor="fig-NAT-autonomous-deployment"
                title="NAT control deployment: Autonomous deployment">
          <artwork><![CDATA[
                +---------+
                |   (C)   |
                |   AAA   |---------
                |         |         |
                +---------+         |
                     |              |
                     |              |
                     |              |
  +--------+    +---------+    +---------+    +----------+
  |  IPv4/ |    |         |    |         |    |  IPv4    |
  |  IPv6  |----|   NAS   |----|  NAT-   |----| Internet |
  |  Host  |    |         |    | device  |    |          |
  +--------+    +---------+    +---------+    +----------+

For NAT44 deployments (IPv4 host):
     <----- Private IPv4 ----------><--- Public IPv4 --->

For NAT64 deployments (IPv6 host):
     <----- Public  IPv6 ----------><--- Public IPv4 --->]]></artwork>
        </figure>

        <t><xref target="fig-NAT-autonomous-deployment"></xref> shows examples
        of autonomous deployments. The figure describes two scenarios: One
        where an IPv4-host (with a private IPv4 address) accesses the
        IPv4-Internet, as well as one where an IPv6-host accesses the
        IPv4-Internet.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="sec-dnca"
             title="DNCA Session Establishment and Management">
      <t>Note that this section forward references some of the commands and
      AVPs defined for DNCA. Please refer to <xref
      target="sec-dnca-commands"></xref> and <xref
      target="sec-dnca-avps"></xref> for details. DNCA runs between a Diameter
      peer residing in a NAT-controller and a Diameter peer residing in a
      NAT-device. The Diameter peer within the NAT-controller is always the
      control requesting entity: It initiates, updates, or terminates the
      sessions. Sessions are initiated when the NAT-controller learns about a
      new endpoint (i.e., host) that requires a NAT service. This could for
      example be due to the entity hosting the NAT-controller receiving
      authentication, authorization, or accounting requests for or from the
      endpoint. Alternate methods that could trigger session setup include
      local configuration, receipt of a packet from a formerly unknown
      IP-address, etc.</t>

      <section title="Session Establishment">
        <t>The DNCA Diameter peer within the NAT-controller establishes a
        session with the DNCA Diameter peer within the NAT-device to control
        the behavior of the NAT function within the NAT-device. During session
        establishment, the DNCA Diameter peer within the NAT-controller passes
        along configuration information to DNCA Diameter peer within the
        NAT-device. The session configuration information comprises the
        maximum number of bindings allowed for the endpoint associated with
        this session, a set of pre-defined NAT bindings to be established for
        this endpoint, or a description of the address pool, that external
        addresses are to be allocated from.</t>

        <t>The DNCA Diameter peer within the NAT-controller generates a
        NAT-Control Request (NCR) message to the DNCA Diameter peer within the
        NAT-device with NC-Request-Type AVP set to INITIAL_REQUEST to initiate
        a Diameter NAT control session. On receipt of a NCR the DNCA Diameter
        peer within the NAT-device sets up a new session for the endpoint
        associated with the endpoint classifier(s) contained in the NCR. The
        DNCA Diameter peer within the NAT-device notifies its DNCA Diameter
        peer within the NAT-controller about successful session setup using a
        NAT-Control Answer (NCA) message with Result-Code set to
        DIAMETER_SUCCESS. <xref target="fig-session-establishment"></xref>
        shows the initial protocol interaction between the two DNCA Diameter
        peers.</t>

        <t>The initial NAT-Control-Request MAY contain configuration
        information for the session, which specifies the behavior of the
        NAT-device for the session. The configuration information that MAY be
        included, comprises: <list style="symbols">
            <t>A list of NAT bindings, which should be pre-allocated for the
            session; for example, in case a user requires a fixed external
            IP-address/port pair for one of his applications.</t>

            <t>The maximum number of NAT-bindings allowed for an endpoint.</t>

            <t>A description of the external IP-address pool(s) to be used for
            the session.</t>

            <t>A reference to a NAT Binding Predefined template on the
            NAT-device, which is applied to the session. Such a NAT Binding
            Predefined template on the NAT-device may contain, for example,
            the name of the IP-address pool that external IP-addresses should
            be allocated from, the maximum number of bindings permitted for
            the endpoint, etc.</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>In certain cases, the NAT-device may not be able to perform the
        tasks requested within the NCR. These include the following: <list
            style="symbols">
            <t>If a DNCA Diameter peer within the NAT-device receives a NCR
            from a DNCA Diameter peer within a NAT-controller with
            NC-Request-Type AVP set to INITIAL_REQUEST that identifies an
            already existing session; that is, DNCA Diameter peer and endpoint
            identifier match an already existing session, the DNCA Diameter
            peer within the NAT-device MUST return an NCA with Result-Code set
            to SESSION_EXISTS, and provide the Session-Id of the existing
            session in the Duplicate-Session-Id AVP.</t>

            <t>If a DNCA Diameter peer within the NAT-device receives a NCR
            from a DNCA Diameter peer within a NAT-controller with
            NC-Request-Type AVP set to INITIAL_REQUEST that matches more than
            one of the already existing sessions; that is, DNCA Diameter peer
            and endpoint identifier match already existing sessions, the DNCA
            Diameter peer within the NAT-device MUST return an NCA with
            Result-Code set to INSUFFICIENT-CLASSIFIERS. In case a DNCA
            Diameter peer receives a NCA that reports
            Insufficient-Classifiers, it MAY choose to retry establishing a
            new session using additional or more specific classifiers.</t>

            <t>If the NCR contains a NAT Binding Predefined template not
            defined on the NAT-device, the DNCA Diameter peer within the
            NAT-device MUST return an NCA with Result-Code AVP set to
            UNKNOWN_BINDING_TEMPLATE_NAME.</t>

            <t>In case the NAT-device is unable to establish all of the
            bindings requested in the NCR, the DNCA Diameter peer MUST return
            an NCA with Result-Code set to BINDING_FAILURE. A DNCA Diameter
            peer within a NAT-device MUST treat a NCR as an atomic operation;
            hence none of the requested bindings will be established by the
            NAT-device. Either all requested actions within a NCR MUST be
            completed successfully, or the entire request fails.</t>

            <t>If a NAT-device does not have sufficient resources to process a
            request, the DNCA Diameter peer MUST return an NCA with
            Result-Code set to RESOURCE_FAILURE.</t>

            <t>In case Max-NAT-Binding, NAT-Control-Definition as well as
            NAT-Control-Binding-Template are included in the NCR, and the
            values in Max-NAT-Binding and NAT-Control-Definition contradict
            those specified in the pre-provisioned template on the NAT-device
            which NAT-Control-Binding-Template references, Max-NAT-Binding and
            NAT-Control-Definition MUST override the values specified in the
            template that NAT-Control-Binding-Template refers to.</t>
          </list></t>

        <figure anchor="fig-session-establishment"
                title="Initial NAT control request and session establishment  ">
          <artwork><![CDATA[
NAT-controller (DNCA Diameter peer)   NAT-device (DNCA Diameter peer)
            |                                           |
            |                                           |
            |                                           |
         Trigger                                        |
            |                                           |
            |                   NCR                     |
            |------------------------------------------>|
            |                                           |
            |                                           |
            |                                           |
            |                                           |
            |                                 If Able to comply
            |                                 with Request then
            |                                 Create session state
            |                                           |
            |                                           |
            |                     NCA                   |
            |<------------------------------------------|
            |                                           |
            |                                           |]]></artwork>
        </figure>

        <t>Note: The DNCA Diameter peer within the NAT-device creates session
        state only if it is able to comply with the NCR. On success it will
        reply with an NCA with Result-Code set to DIAMETER_SUCCESS.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Session Re-Authorization">
        <t>Session re-authorization is performed if the NAT-controller desires
        to change the behavior of the NAT-device for an existing session.
        Session re-authorization could be used, for example, to change the
        number of allowed bindings for a particular session, or establish or
        remove a pre-defined binding.</t>

        <t>The DNCA Diameter peer within the NAT-controller generates a NCR
        message to the DNCA Diameter peer within the NAT-device with
        NC-Request-Type AVP set to UPDATE_REQUEST upon receiving a trigger
        signal. If the session is updated successfully, the DNCA Diameter peer
        within the NAT-device notifies the DNCA Diameter peer within the
        NAT-controller about the successful session update using a NAT-Control
        Answer (NCA) message with Result-Code set to DIAMETER_SUCCESS. <xref
        target="fig-session-re-auth"></xref> shows the protocol interaction
        between the two DNCA Diameter peers.</t>

        <t>In certain cases, the NAT-device may not be able to perform the
        tasks requested within the NCR. These include the following: <list
            style="symbols">
            <t>If DNCA Diameter peer within a NAT-device receives an NCR
            update or query request for a non-existent session, it MUST set
            Result-Code in the answer to DIAMETER_UNKNOWN_SESSION_ID.</t>

            <t>If the NCR contains a NAT Binding Predefined template not
            defined on the NAT-device, an NCA with Result-Code AVP set to
            UNKNOWN_BINDING_TEMPLATE_NAME MUST be returned.</t>

            <t>If the NAT-device cannot establish the requested binding
            because the maximum number of allowed bindings has been reached
            for the endpoint classifier, an NCA with Result-Code AVP set to
            MAXIMUM_BINDINGS_REACHED_FOR_ENDPOINT MUST be returned to the DNCA
            Diameter peer.</t>

            <t>If the NAT-device cannot establish some or all of the bindings
            requested in an NCR, but has not yet reached the maximum number of
            allowed bindings for the endpoint, an NCA with Result-Code set to
            BINDING_FAILURE MUST be returned. As already noted, the DNCA
            Diameter peer in a NAT-device MUST treat an NCR as an atomic
            operation. Hence none of the requested bindings will be
            established by the NAT-device in case of failure. Actions
            requested within a NCR are either all successful or all fail.</t>

            <t>If the NAT-device does not have sufficient resources to process
            a request, an NCA with Result-Code set to RESOURCE_FAILURE MUST be
            returned.</t>

            <t>If an NCR redefines the maximum number of NAT-bindings allowed
            for the endpoint, the new value MUST override any previously
            defined limit on NAT bindings. It depends on the implementation of
            the NAT-device on how the NAT-device copes with a case where the
            new value is lower than the actual number of allocated bindings.
            The NAT-device SHOULD refrain from enforcing the new limit
            immediately (that is, actively remove bindings), but rather
            disallows the establishment of new bindings until the current
            number of bindings is lower than the newly established maximum
            number of allowed bindings.</t>

            <t>If an NCR specifies a new NAT Binding Predefined template on
            the NAT-device, the NAT Binding Predefined template overrides any
            previously defined rule for the session. Existing NAT-bindings
            SHOULD NOT be impacted by the change of templates.</t>

            <t>In case Max-NAT-Binding, NAT-Control-Definition as well as
            NAT-Control-Binding-Template are included in the NCR, and the
            values in Max-NAT-Binding and NAT-Control-Definition contradict
            those specified in the pre-provisioned template on the NAT-device
            which NAT-Control-Binding-Template references, Max-NAT-Binding and
            NAT-Control-Definition MUST override the values specified in the
            template that the NAT-Control-Binding-Template refers to.</t>
          </list>Note: Already established bindings for the session SHOULD NOT
        be affected in case the tasks requested within the NCR cannot be
        completed.</t>

        <figure anchor="fig-session-re-auth"
                title="NAT control request for session update ">
          <artwork><![CDATA[
NAT-controller (DNCA Diameter peer)   NAT-device (DNCA Diameter peer)
            |                                           |
            |                                           |
            |                                           |
     Change of session                                  |
        attributes                                      |
            |                                           |
            |                   NCR                     |
            |------------------------------------------>|
            |                                           |
            |                                           |
            |                                   If able to comply 
            |                                   with the request:
            |                                  Update session state
            |                                           |
            |                                           |
            |                     NCA                   |
            |<------------------------------------------|
            |                                           |]]></artwork>
        </figure>
      </section>

      <section title="Session and Binding Query">
        <t>A Session and NAT-binding query MAY be used by the DNCA Diameter
        peer within the NAT-controller to either retrieve information on the
        current bindings for a particular session at the NAT-device or
        discover the session identifier for a particular external IP
        address/port pair.</t>

        <t>A DNCA Diameter peer within the NAT-controller starts a session
        query by sending an NCR message with NC-Request-Type AVP set to
        QUERY_REQUEST. <xref target="fig-session-query"></xref> shows the
        protocol interaction between the DNCA Diameter peers.</t>

        <t>Two types of query requests exist. The first type of query request
        uses the session ID as input parameter to the query. It is to allow
        the DNCA Diameter peer within the NAT-controller to retrieve the
        current set of bindings for a specific session. The second type of
        query request is used to retrieve the session identifiers, along with
        the associated bindings, matching a criteria. This enables the DNCA
        Diameter peer within the NAT-controller to find those sessions, which
        utilize a specific external IP-address.</t>

        <t><list style="numbers">
            <t>Request a list of currently allocated NAT bindings for a
            particular session: On receiving a NCR, the NAT-device SHOULD look
            up the session information for the session ID contained in the
            NCR, and report all currently active NAT-bindings for the session
            using an NCA message with Result-Code set to DIAMETER_SUCCESS. In
            this case the NCR MUST NOT contain a NAT-Control-Definition AVP.
            Each NAT-binding is reported in a NAT-Control-Definition AVP. In
            case the session ID is unknown, the DNCA Diameter peer within the
            NAT-device MUST return an NCA message with Result-Code set to
            DIAMETER_UNKNOWN_SESSION_ID.</t>

            <t>Retrieve session IDs and internal IP address/port pairs for one
            or multiple external IP-address/port pairs: If the DNCA Diameter
            peer within the NAT-controller wishes to retrieve the session
            ID(s) for one or multiple external IP-address/port pairs, it MUST
            include the external IP-address/port pair(s) as part of the
            NAT-Control-Definition AVP of the NCR. The external
            IP-address/port pair(s) are pre-known to the controller via
            configuration, AAA interactions, or other means. The session ID is
            not included in the NCR or the NCA for this type of a query. The
            DNCA Diameter peer within the NAT-device SHOULD report the
            NAT-bindings and associated session IDs corresponding to the
            external IP-address/port pairs in an NCA message using one or
            multiple instances of the NAT-Control-Definition AVP. The
            Result-Code is set to DIAMETER_SUCCESS. In case an external
            IP-address/port pair has no associated existing NAT-binding, the
            NAT-Control-Definition AVP contained in the reply just contains
            the NAT-External-Address AVP.</t>
          </list></t>

        <figure anchor="fig-session-query" title="Session query">
          <artwork><![CDATA[
NAT-controller (DNCA Diameter peer)   NAT-device (DNCA Diameter peer)
            |                                           |
            |                                           |
            |                                           |
  DNCA Session Established                              |
            |                                           |
            |                   NCR                     |
            |------------------------------------------>|
            |                                           |
            |                                           |
            |                                           |
            |                                           |
            |                          Look up corresponding session
            |                            and associated NAT-bindings
            |                                           |
            |                   NCA                     |
            |<------------------------------------------|
            |                                           |
            |                                           |
            |                                           |]]></artwork>
        </figure>
      </section>

      <section anchor="sec-dnca-sess-term" title="Session Termination">
        <t>Similar to session initiation, session tear down MUST be initiated
        by the DNCA Diameter peer within the NAT-controller. The DNCA Diameter
        peer sends a Session Terminate Request (STR) message to its peer
        within the NAT-device upon receiving a trigger signal. The source of
        the trigger signal is outside the scope of this document. As part of
        STR message processing the DNCA Diameter peer within the NAT-device
        MAY send an accounting stop record reporting all bindings. All the
        NAT-bindings belonging to the session MUST be removed and the session
        state MUST be cleaned up. The DNCA Diameter peer within the NAT-device
        MUST notify its DNCA Diameter peer in the NAT-controller about
        successful session termination using a Session Terminate Answer (STA)
        message with Result-Code set to DIAMETER_SUCCESS. <xref
        target="fig-session-terminate"></xref> shows the protocol interaction
        between the two DNCA Diameter peers.</t>

        <t>If a DNCA Diameter peer within a NAT-device receives a STR and
        fails to find a matching session, the DNCA Diameter peer MUST return a
        STA with Result-Code set to DIAMETER_UNKNOWN_SESSION_ID.</t>

        <figure anchor="fig-session-terminate"
                title="Terminate NAT control session">
          <artwork><![CDATA[
NAT-controller (DNCA Diameter peer)   NAT-device (DNCA Diameter peer)
            |                                            |
            |                                            |
         Trigger                                         |
            |                                            |
            |                   STR                      |
            |------------------------------------------->|
            |                                            |
            |                                            |
            |                                            |
            |                                            |
            |                                            |
            |           Send accounting stop             |
            |<-------------------------------------------|
            |       reporting all session bindings       |
            |                                            |
            |                                            |
            |                                  Remove NAT-bindings
            |                                       of session   
            |                                            |
            |                                  Terminate session /
            |                                 Remove session state
            |                                            |
            |                                            |
            |                                            |
            |                  STA                       |
            |<-------------------------------------------|
            |                                            |
            |                                            |]]></artwork>
        </figure>
      </section>

      <section title="Session Abort">
        <t>An Abort-Session-Request (ASR) message is sent from the DNCA
        Diameter peer within the NAT-device to the DNCA Diameter peer within
        the NAT-controller when it is unable to maintain a session due to
        resource limitations. The DNCA Diameter peer within the NAT-controller
        MUST acknowledge successful session abort using a Abort Session Answer
        (ASA) message with Result-Code set to DIAMETER_SUCCESS. <xref
        target="fig-session-abort"></xref> shows the protocol interaction
        between the DNCA Diameter peers. The DNCA Diameter peers will start a
        session termination procedure as described in <xref
        target="sec-dnca-sess-term"></xref> following an ASA with Result-Code
        set to DIAMETER_SUCCESS.</t>

        <t>If the DNCA Diameter peer within a NAT-controller receives an ASR
        but fails to find a matching session, it MUST return an ASA with
        Result-Code set to DIAMETER_UNKNOWN_SESSION_ID. If the DNCA Diameter
        peer within the NAT-controller is unable to comply with the ASR for
        any other reason, an ASA with Result-Code set to
        DIAMETER_UNABLE_TO_COMPLY MUST be returned.</t>

        <figure anchor="fig-session-abort" title="Abort NAT control session">
          <artwork><![CDATA[
NAT-controller (DNCA Diameter peer)   NAT-device (DNCA Diameter peer)
            |                                            |
            |                                            |
            |                                         Trigger
            |                                            |
            |                   ASR                      |
            |<-------------------------------------------|
            |                                            |
            |                                            |
            |                                            |
            |                  ASA                       |
            |------------------------------------------->|
            |                                            |
            |                                            |
            |                                            |
            |           On successful ASA                |
            |<------Session Termination Procedure------->|]]></artwork>
        </figure>
      </section>

      <section title="Failure cases of the DNCA Diameter peers">
        <t>This document does not specify the behavior in case the NAT-device
        and NAT-controller, or their respective DNCA Diameter peers are out of
        sync or lose state. This could happen for example if one of the
        entities restarts, in case of a (temporary) loss of network
        connectivity etc. Example failure cases include the following:</t>

        <t><list style="symbols">
            <t>NAT-controller and the DNCA Diameter peer within the
            NAT-controller lose state (e.g., due to a restart). In this case,
            <list style="symbols">
                <t>the DNCA Diameter peer within the NAT-device MAY receive an
                NCR with NC-Request-Type AVP set to INITIAL_REQUEST that
                matches an existing session of the DNCA Diameter peer within
                the NAT-device. The DNCA Diameter peer within the NAT-device
                MUST return Result-Code that contains Duplicate-Session-Id AVP
                to report the Session-ID of the existing session. The DNCA
                Diameter peer within the NAT-controller MAY send an explicit
                Session Terminate Request (STR) for the older session, which
                was lost.</t>

                <t>a DNCA Diameter peer MAY receive accounting records for a
                session that does not exist. The DNCA Diameter peer sends an
                accounting answer with Result-Code set to
                DIAMETER_UNKNOWN_SESSION_ID in response. On receiving the
                response, the DNCA Diameter peer SHOULD clear the session and
                remove associated session state.</t>
              </list></t>

            <t>NAT-device and the DNCA Diameter peer within NAT-device lose
            state. In such a case, the DNCA Diameter peer MAY receive a NCR
            with NC-Request-Type AVP set to UPDATE_REQUEST for a non-existent
            session. The DNCA Diameter peer MUST return an NCA with
            Result-Code set to DIAMETER_UNKNOWN_SESSION_ID.</t>

            <t>The DNCA Diameter peer within the NAT-controller is
            unreachable, for example detected by Diameter device watchdog
            messages (as defined in Section 5.5 of <xref
            target="RFC3588"></xref>), or down and accounting requests from
            the DNCA Diameter peer fail to get a response. The mechanism to
            ensure that a DNCA Diameter peer within the NAT-controller no
            longer has associated state for a session which was cleared or
            removed by the DNCA Diameter peer within the NAT-device is beyond
            the scope of this document.</t>

            <t>The DNCA Diameter peer within the NAT-device is unreachable or
            down and NCR fails to get a response. Handling of this case
            depends on the actual service offering of the service provider.
            The service provider could for example choose to stop offering
            connectivity service.</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="sec-diameter-base-use"
             title="Use of the Diameter Base Protocol">
      <t>The Diameter Base Protocol defined by <xref target="RFC3588"></xref>
      applies with the clarifications listed in the present specification.</t>

      <section anchor="sec-diameter-messages"
               title="Securing Diameter Messages ">
        <t>For secure transport of Diameter messages, the recommendations in
        <xref target="RFC3588"></xref> apply.</t>

        <t>DNCA Diameter peers SHOULD verify their identity during the
        Capabilities Exchange Request procedure.</t>

        <t>A DNCA Diameter peer within the NAT-device SHOULD verify that a
        DNCA Diameter peer that issues a NCR command is allowed to do so based
        on: <list style="symbols">
            <t>The identity of the DNCA Diameter peer</t>

            <t>The type of NCR Command</t>

            <t>The content of the NCR Command</t>

            <t>Any combination of the above</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>

      <section title="Accounting Functionality">
        <t>Accounting functionality (accounting session state machine, related
        command codes and AVPs) is defined in <xref
        target="sec-accounting"></xref> below.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Use of Sessions">
        <t>Each DNCA session MUST have a globally unique Session-ID as defined
        in <xref target="RFC3588"></xref>, which MUST NOT be changed during
        the lifetime of a DNCA session. The Diameter Session-ID serves as the
        global endpoint identifier. The DNCA Diameter peers maintain state
        associated with the Session-ID. This globally unique Session-ID is
        used for updating, accounting, and terminating the session. A DNCA
        session MUST NOT have more than one outstanding request at any given
        instant. A DNCA Diameter peer sends an Abort-Session-Request as
        defined in <xref target="RFC3588"></xref> if it is unable to maintain
        sessions due to resource limitation.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Routing Considerations">
        <t>It is assumed that the DNCA Diameter peer within a NAT-controller
        knows the DiameterIdentity of the Diameter peer within a NAT-device
        for a given endpoint. Both the Destination-Realm and Destination-Host
        AVPs are present in the request from a DNCA Diameter peer within a
        NAT-controller to a DNCA Diameter peer within a NAT-device.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Advertising Application Support">
        <t>Diameter nodes conforming to this specification MUST advertise
        support for DNCA by including the value of TBD in the
        Auth-Application-Id of the Capabilities-Exchange-Request and
        Capabilities-Exchange-Answer command<xref target="RFC3588">
        </xref>.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="sec-dnca-commands" title="DNCA Commands">
      <t>The following commands are used to establish, maintain and query
      NAT-bindings.</t>

      <section anchor="sec-dnca-ncr" title="NAT-Control Request (NCR) Command">
        <t>The NAT-Control Request (NCR) command, indicated by the command
        field set to TBD and the "R" bit set in the Command Flags field, is
        sent from the DNCA Diameter peer within the NAT-controller to the DNCA
        Diameter peer within the NAT-device in order to install
        NAT-bindings.</t>

        <t>User-Name, Logical-Access-Id, Physical-Access-ID,
        Framed-IP-Address, Framed-IPv6-Prefix, Framed-Interface-Id,
        EGRESS-VLANID, NAS-Port-ID, Address-Realm, Calling-Station-ID AVPs
        serve as identifiers for the endpoint.</t>

        <t>Message format:</t>

        <figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[   < NC-Request > ::= < Diameter Header: TBD, REQ, PXY>
                    [ Session-Id ]
                    { Auth-Application-Id }
                    { Origin-Host }
                    { Origin-Realm }
                    { Destination-Realm }
                    { Destination-Host }
                    { NC-Request-Type }
                    [ Origin-State-Id ]
                 *1 [ NAT-Control-Remove ]
                 *1 [ NAT-Control-Install ]
                    [ User-Name ]
                    [ Logical-Access-Id ]
                    [ Physical-Access-ID ]
                    [ Framed-IP-Address ]
                    [ Framed-IPv6-Prefix ]
                    [ Framed-Interface-Id ]
                    [ EGRESS-VLANID]
                    [ NAS-Port-ID]
                    [ Address-Realm ]
                    [ Calling-Station-ID ]
                  * [ Proxy-Info ]
                  * [ Route-Record ]
                  * [ AVP ]
]]></artwork>
        </figure>
      </section>

      <section anchor="sec-dnca-nca" title="NAT-Control Answer (NCA) Command">
        <t>The NAT-Control-Answer (NCA) command, indicated by the Command-Code
        field set to TBD and the "R" bit cleared in the Command Flags field,
        is sent by the DNCA Diameter peer within the NAT-device in response to
        NAT-Control-Request command.</t>

        <t>Message format:</t>

        <figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[   <NC-Answer> ::= < Diameter Header: TBD, PXY >
                   [ Session-Id ]
                   { Origin-Host }
                   { Origin-Realm }
                   { Result-Code }
                   [ NC-Request-Type ]
                 * [ NAT-Control-Definition ]
                   [ Current-NAT-Bindings   ]
                   [ Origin-State-Id ]
                   [ Error-Message ]
                   [ Error-Reporting-Host ]
                 * [ Failed-AVP ]
                 * [ Proxy-Info ]
                   [ Duplicate-Session-ID ]
                 * [ Redirect-Host]
                   [ Redirect-Host-Usage ]
                   [ Redirect-Max-Cache-Time ]
                 * [ Proxy-Info ]
                 * [ Route-Record ]
                 * [ Failed-AVP ]
                 * [ AVP ]

]]></artwork>
        </figure>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="NAT Control Application Session State Machine">
      <t>This section contains a set of finite state machines, representing
      the life cycle of a DNCA session, which MUST be observed by all
      implementations of the DNCA Diameter application. The DNCA Diameter
      peers are stateful and the state machine maintained is similar to the
      stateful Client and Server authorization state machine described in
      <xref target="RFC3588"></xref>. When a session is moved to the Idle
      state, any resources that were allocated for the particular session must
      be released. Any event not listed in the state machines MUST be
      considered as an error condition, and an answer, if applicable, MUST be
      returned to the originator of the message.</t>

      <t>In the state table, the event 'Failure to send NCR' means that the
      DNCA Diameter peer within the NAT-controller is unable to send the NCR
      command to the desired destination. This could be due to the peer being
      down, or due to the peer sending back the transient failure or temporary
      protocol error notification DIAMETER_TOO_BUSY or DIAMETER_LOOP_DETECTED
      in the Result-Code AVP of an NCA.</t>

      <t>In the state table "FAILED NCA" means that the DNCA Diameter peer
      within the NAT-device was not able to honor the corresponding NCR. This
      can happen due to any transient and permanent error at the NAT-device or
      its associated DNCA Diameter peer within indicated by the following
      error Result-Code values: RESOURCE_FAILURE,
      UNKNOWN_BINDING_TEMPLATE_NAME, BINDING_FAILURE,
      MAXIMUM_BINDINGS_REACHED_FOR_ENDPOINT, SESSION_EXISTS,
      INSUFFICIENT_CLASSIFIERS.</t>

      <t>The following state machine is observed by a DNCA Diameter peer
      within a NAT-controller. The state machine description uses the term
      "access session" to describe the connectivity service offered to the
      endpoint or host. "Access session" should not be confused with the
      Diameter session ID.</t>

      <t><figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[          DNCA Diameter peer within a NAT-controller
   State     Event                          Action     New State
   -------------------------------------------------------------
   Idle      New endpoint detected that     Send       Pending
             requires NAT Control           NCR
                                            Initial 
                                            Request

   Idle      ASR Received                   Send ASA   Idle
             for unknown session            with
                                            Result-Code
                                            = UNKNOWN_
                                            SESSION_ID

   Pending   Successful NCA                 Setup      Open
             received                       complete

   Pending   Successful NCA                 Send STR   Discon
             received
             but peer unable to provide
             service

   Pending   Error processing successful    Send STR   Discon
             NCA

   Pending   Failed                         Clean up   Idle
             NCA received

   Open      NAT control                    Send       Open
             update required                NCR Update
                                            Request

   Open      Successful                                Open
             NCA received  

   Open      Failed                         Clean up   Idle
             NCA received                  
             

   Open      Access session end detected    Send STR   Discon
             

   Open      ASR Received,                  Send ASA   Discon
             access session will be         with
             terminated                     Result-Code
                                            = SUCCESS,
                                            Send STR

   Open      ASR Received,                  Send ASA   Open
             access session will not        with
             be terminated                  Result-Code
                                            != SUCCESS
   
   Discon    ASR Received                   Send ASA   Idle

   Discon    STA Received                   Discon.    Idle
                                            user/device]]></artwork>
        </figure></t>

      <t>The following state machine is observed by a DNCA Diameter peer
      within a NAT-device.</t>

      <figure>
        <artwork><![CDATA[
          DNCA Diameter peer within a NAT-device
   State     Event                          Action     New State
   -------------------------------------------------------------
   Idle      NCR Query request              Send       Idle
             received, and                  successful
             able to provide requested      NCA 
             NAT Binding report             

   Idle      NCR received                   Send       Open
             and able to                    successful
             provide requested              NCA
             NAT control service

   Idle      NCR request                    Send       Idle
             received, and                  failed 
             unable to provide requested    NCA
             NAT control service
     
   Open      NCR  request                   Send       Open
             received, and                  successful
             able to provide requested      NCA
             NAT control service       

   Open      NCR request                    Send       Idle
             received, and                  failed 
             unable to provide requested    NCA,
             NAT control service            Clean up

   Open      Unable to continue             Send ASR   Discon
             providing requested
             NAT control service

   Discon    Failure to send ASR            Wait,      Discon
                                            resend ASR

   Discon    ASR successfully sent and      Clean up   Idle
             ASA Received with Result-Code

   Not       ASA Received                   None       No change
   Discon

   Any       STR Received                   Send STA,  Idle
                                            Clean up]]></artwork>
      </figure>
    </section>

    <section anchor="sec-dnca-avps" title="DNCA AVPs">
      <t></t>

      <section title="Reused Base Protocol AVPs">
        <t>The following table describes the AVPs reused from Diameter Base
        Protocol <xref target="RFC3588"></xref>; their AVP Code values, types,
        and possible flag values; and whether the AVP MAY be encrypted.The
        <xref target="RFC3588"></xref> specifies the AVP Flag rules for AVPs
        in section 4.5. The Diameter AVP rules are defined in the <xref
        target="RFC3588"></xref>, section 4.</t>

        <figure anchor="tab-avps-from-diameter-base" suppress-title="true">
          <artwork><![CDATA[                                                +---------+
                                                |  AVP    |
                                                |  Flag   | 
                                                |  rules  |
+-----------------------------------------------|-----+---+---------+
|                           AVP                 |     |   |         |
| Attribute Name            Code     Data Type  |MUST |MAY|   Encr  |
+-----------------------------------------------+-----+---+---------+
|Acct-Interim-Interval      85       Unsigned32 | M   | P |    Y    |
|Auth-Application-Id        258      Unsigned32 | M   | P |    N    |
|Destination-Host           293      DiamIdent  | M   | P |    N    |
|Destination-Realm          283      DiamIdent  | M   | P |    N    |
|Error-Message              281      UTF8String | M   | P |    N    |
|Error-Reporting-Host       294      DiamIdent  | M   | P |    N    |
|Failed-AVP                 279      Grouped    | M   | P |    N    |
|Origin-Host                264      DiamIdent  | M   | P |    N    |
|Origin-Realm               296      DiamIdent  | M   | P |    N    |
|Origin-State-Id            278      Unsigned32 | M   | P |    N    |
|Proxy-Info                 284      Grouped    | M   | P |    N    |
|Result-Code                268      Unsigned32 | M   | P |    N    |
|Route-Record               282      DiamIdent  | M   |   |    N    |
|Session-Id                 263      UTF8String | M   | P |    Y    |
|User-Name                  1        UTF8String | M   | P |    Y    |
+-----------------------------------------------+-----+---+---------+]]></artwork>

          <postamble>Table 1: DIAMETER AVPs used from Diameter
          base</postamble>
        </figure>

        <t>The Auth-Application-Id AVP (AVP Code 258) is assigned by IANA to
        Diameter applications. The value of the Auth-Application-Id for the
        Diameter NAT Control Application is TBD.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="sec_result-codes"
               title="Additional Result-Code AVP Values">
        <t>This section defines new values for the Result-Code AVP which SHALL
        be supported by all Diameter implementations that conform to the
        present document.</t>

        <section title="Success">
          <t>No new Result-Code AVP value is defined within this category.</t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="sec_result-code-transient" title="Transient Failures">
          <t>Result-Code AVP values that fall within the transient failures
          category are those used to inform a peer that the request could not
          be satisfied at the time that it was received. The request may be
          able to be satisfied in the future.</t>

          <t>The following new values of the Result-Code AVP are defined:</t>

          <t><list style="empty">
              <t>RESOURCE_FAILURE (TBD)<list style="empty">
                  <t>The DNCA Diameter peer within the NAT-device indicates
                  that the binding could not be installed or a new session
                  could not be created due to resource shortage.</t>
                </list></t>
            </list></t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="sec_result-code-permanent"
                 title="Permanent Failures ">
          <t>The Result-Code AVP values, which fall within the permanent
          failures category are used to inform the peer that the request
          failed, and should not be attempted again. The request may be able
          to be satisfied in the future.</t>

          <t>The following new values of the Result-Code AVP are defined:</t>

          <t><list style="empty">
              <t>UNKNOWN_BINDING_TEMPLATE_NAME (TBD)<list style="empty">
                  <t>The DNCA Diameter peer within the NAT-device indicates
                  that the binding could not be installed or a new session
                  could not be created because the specified
                  NAT-Control-Binding-Template AVP, that refers to a
                  predefined policy template in the NAT-device, is
                  unknown.</t>
                </list>BINDING_FAILURE (TBD)<list style="empty">
                  <t>DNCA indicates that the requested binding(s) could not be
                  installed. For example: Requested ports are already in
                  use.</t>
                </list></t>

              <t>MAXIMUM_BINDINGS_REACHED_FOR_ENDPOINT (TBD)<list
                  style="empty">
                  <t>The DNCA Diameter peer within the NAT-device denies the
                  request because the maximum number of allowed bindings has
                  been reached for the specified endpoint classifier.</t>
                </list></t>

              <t>SESSION_EXISTS (TBD)<list style="empty">
                  <t>The DNCA Diameter peer within the NAT-device denies
                  request to initialize a new session, if it already has a
                  DNCA session that uses the same set of classifiers as
                  indicated by the DNCA Diameter peer within the
                  NAT-controller in the new session initialization
                  request.</t>
                </list></t>

              <t>INSUFFICIENT_CLASSIFIERS (TBD)<list style="empty">
                  <t>The DNCA Diameter peer within the NAT-device requests to
                  initialize a new session, if the classifiers in the request
                  match more than one of the existing sessions on the DNCA
                  Diameter peer within the NAT-device.</t>
                </list></t>
            </list></t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section title="Reused NASREQ Diameter Application AVPs">
        <t>The following table describes the AVPs reused from the Diameter
        Network Access Server Application <xref target="RFC4005"></xref>;
        their AVP Code values, types, and possible flag values; and whether
        the AVP MAY be encrypted.The <xref target="RFC3588"></xref> specifies
        the AVP Flag rules for AVPs in section 4.5. The Diameter AVP rules are
        defined in the <xref target="RFC3588"></xref>, section 4.</t>

        <figure anchor="tab-avps-from-nasreq" suppress-title="true">
          <artwork><![CDATA[                                       +---------------------+
                                       |    AVP Flag rules   |
+------------------+------+------------|----+-----+----+-----|----+
|                  | AVP  |            |    |     |SHLD| MUST|    |
| Attribute Name   | Code |  Value Type|MUST| MAY | NOT|  NOT|Encr|
|------------------|------|------------|----+-----+----+-----|----|
| NAS-Port         |   5  | Unsigned32 | M  |  P  |    |  V  | Y  |
| NAS-Port-Id      |  87  | UTF8String | M  |  P  |    |  V  | Y  |
| Calling-Station- |  31  | UTF8String | M  |  P  |    |  V  | Y  |
|   Id             |      |            |    |     |    |     |    |
| Framed-IP-Address|   8  | OctetString| M  |  P  |    |  V  | Y  |
| Framed-Interface-|  96  | Unsigned64 | M  |  P  |    |  V  | Y  |
|   Id             |      |            |    |     |    |     |    |
| Framed-IPv6-     |  97  | OctetString| M  |  P  |    |  V  | Y  |
|  Prefix          |      |            |    |     |    |     |    |
+------------------+------+------------|----+-----+----+-----|----+]]></artwork>

          <postamble>Table 2: Reused NASREQ Diameter application
          AVPs</postamble>
        </figure>
      </section>

      <section title="Reused AVPs from RFC 4675 ">
        <t>The following table describes the AVPs reused from "RADIUS
        Attributes for Virtual LAN and Priority Support" specification <xref
        target="RFC4675"></xref>; their AVP Code values, types, and possible
        flag values; and whether the AVP MAY be encrypted.The <xref
        target="RFC3588"></xref> specifies the AVP Flag rules for AVPs in
        section 4.5. The Diameter AVP rules are defined in the <xref
        target="RFC3588"></xref>, section 4.</t>

        <figure anchor="tab-avps-from-rfc4675" suppress-title="true">
          <artwork><![CDATA[                                       +---------------------+
                                       |    AVP Flag rules   |
+------------------+------+------------|----+-----+----+-----|----+
|                  | AVP  |            |    |     |SHLD| MUST|    |
| Attribute Name   | Code |  Value Type|MUST| MAY | NOT|  NOT|Encr|
|------------------|------|------------|----+-----+----+-----|----|
| Egress-VLANID    |  56  | OctetString| M  |  P  |    |  V  | Y  |
+------------------+------+------------|----+-----+----+-----|----+]]></artwork>

          <postamble>Table 3: Reused attributes from RFC 4675</postamble>
        </figure>
      </section>

      <section title="Reused AVPs from Diameter QoS Application">
        <t>The following table describes the AVPs reused from the Traffic
        Classification and Quality of Service (QoS) Attributes for Diameter
        <xref target="RFC5777"></xref>; their AVP Code values, types, and
        possible flag values; and whether the AVP MAY be encrypted.The <xref
        target="RFC3588"></xref> specifies the AVP Flag rules for AVPs in
        section 4.5. The Diameter AVP rules are defined in the <xref
        target="RFC3588"></xref>, section 4.</t>

        <figure anchor="tab-avps-from-diameter-qos" suppress-title="true">
          <artwork><![CDATA[                                                +---------+
                                                |  AVP    |
                                                |  Flag   | 
                                                |  rules  |
+-----------------------------------------------|-----+---+---------+
|                           AVP                 |     |   |         |
| Attribute Name            Code     Data Type  |MUST |MAY|   Encr  |
+-----------------------------------------------+-----+---+---------+
|Port                       530     Integer32   |  M  | P |    Y    |
|Protocol                   513     Enumerated  |  M  | P |    Y    |
|Direction                  514     Enumerated  |  M  | P |    Y    |
+-----------------------------------------------+-----+---+---------+
]]></artwork>

          <postamble>Table 4: Reused QoS-attributes</postamble>
        </figure>
      </section>

      <section title="Reused AVPs from ETSI ES 283 034, e4 Diameter Application">
        <t>The following table describes the AVPs reused from the Diameter e4
        Application <xref target="ETSIES283034"></xref>; their AVP Code
        values, types, and possible flag values; and whether the AVP MAY be
        encrypted.The <xref target="RFC3588"></xref> specifies the AVP Flag
        rules for AVPs in section 4.5. The Diameter AVP rules are defined in
        the <xref target="RFC3588"></xref>, section 4. The Vendor-ID field in
        these AVP header will be set to ETSI (13019).</t>

        <figure anchor="tab-avps-from-diameter-e4" suppress-title="true">
          <artwork><![CDATA[                                                +---------+
                                                |  AVP    |
                                                |  Flag   | 
                                                |  rules  |
+-----------------------------------------------|-----+---+---------+
|                           AVP                 |     |   |         |
| Attribute Name            Code     Data Type  |MUST |MAY|   Encr  |
+-----------------------------------------------+-----+---+---------+
|Address-Realm              301     OctetString | M,V |   |    Y    |
|Logical-Access-Id          302     OctetString |   V | M |    Y    |
|Physical-Access-ID         313     UTF8String  |   V | M |    Y    |
+-----------------------------------------------+-----+---+---------+
]]></artwork>

          <postamble>Table 5: Reused AVPs from Diameter e4
          application</postamble>
        </figure>
      </section>

      <section anchor="tab-new-avps" title="DNCA Defined AVPs">
        <t>The following table describes the new Diameter AVPs defined in this
        document; their AVP Code values, types, and possible flag values; and
        whether the AVP MAY be encrypted.The <xref target="RFC3588"></xref>
        specifies the AVP Flag rules for AVPs in section 4.5. The Diameter AVP
        rules are defined in the <xref target="RFC3588"></xref>, section 4.
        The AVPs defined here MUST NOT have the V bit in the AVP Flag set.</t>

        <figure suppress-title="true">
          <artwork><![CDATA[                                                +---------+
                                                |  AVP    |
                                                |  Flag   | 
                                                |  rules  |
+-----------------------------------------------|-----+---+---------+
|                           AVP                 |     |   |         |
| Attribute Name            Code     Data Type  |MUST |MAY|   Encr  |
+-----------------------------------------------+-----+---+---------+
|NC-Request-Type        TBD  8.7.1   Enumerated | M   | P |    Y    |
|NAT-Control-Install    TBD  8.7.2   Grouped    | M   | P |    Y    |
|NAT-Control-Remove     TBD  8.7.3   Grouped    | M   | P |    Y    |
|NAT-Control-Definition TBD  8.7.4   Grouped    | M   | P |    Y    |
|NAT-Internal-Address   TBD  8.7.5   Grouped    | M   | P |    Y    |
|NAT-External-Address   TBD  8.7.6   Grouped    | M   | P |    Y    |
|Max-NAT-Bindings       TBD  8.7.7   Unsigned32 | M   | P |    Y    |
|NAT-Control-           TBD  8.7.8   OctetString| M   | P |    Y    |
| Binding-Template                              |     |   |         |
|Duplicate-             TBD  8.7.9   UTF8String | M   | P |    Y    |
| Session-ID                                    |     |   |         |
|NAT-External-Port-     TBD  8.7.10  Enumerated | M   | P |    Y    |
| Style                                         |     |   |         |
|NAT-Control-Record     TBD  9.2.1   Grouped    | M   | P |    Y    |
|NAT-Control-           TBD  9.2.2   Enumerated | M   | P |    Y    |
| Binding-Status                                |     |   |         |
|Current-NAT-Bindings   TBD  9.2.3   Unsigned32 | M   | P |    Y    |
+-----------------------------------------------+-----+---+---------+
]]></artwork>

          <postamble>Table 6: New Diameter AVPs</postamble>
        </figure>

        <section anchor="avp_NC-Request-Type" title="NC-Request-Type AVP">
          <t>The NC-Request-Type AVP (AVP Code TBD) is of type Enumerated and
          contains the reason for sending the NAT-Control-Request command. It
          shall be present in all NAT-Control-Request messages.</t>

          <t>The following values are defined: <list style="empty">
              <t>INITIAL_REQUEST (1)<list style="empty">
                  <t>An Initial Request is to initiate a Diameter NAT control
                  session between the DNCA Diameter peers.</t>
                </list>UPDATE_REQUEST (2)<list style="empty">
                  <t>An Update Request is used to update bindings previously
                  installed on a given access session, to add new binding on a
                  given access session, or to remove one or several binding(s)
                  activated on a given access session.</t>
                </list></t>

              <t>QUERY_REQUEST (3)<list style="empty">
                  <t>Query Request is used to query a NAT-device about the
                  currently installed bindings for an endpoint classifier.</t>
                </list></t>
            </list></t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="avp_NAT-Control-Install"
                 title="NAT-Control-Install AVP">
          <t>The NAT-Control AVP (AVP code TBD) is of type Grouped, and it is
          used to activate or install NAT bindings. It also contains
          Max-NAT-Bindings that defines the maximum number of NAT bindings
          allowed for an end point and the NAT-Control-Binding-Template that
          references a predefined template on the NAT-device that may contain
          static binding, a maximum number of bindings allowed, an IP-address
          pool from which external binding addresses should be allocated, etc.
          If the NAT-External-Port-Style AVP is present, then the NAT-device
          MUST select the external ports for the NAT-Bindings as per the style
          specified. The NAT-External-Port-Style is applicable for
          NAT-Bindings defined by the NAT-Control-Definition AVPs whose
          NAT-External-Address or Port AVPs within the NAT-External-Address
          are unspecified.</t>

          <t>AVP format:</t>

          <figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[  NAT-Control-Install ::= < AVP Header: TBD >
                           * [ NAT-Control-Definition ]
                             [ NAT-Control-Binding-Template ]
                             [ Max-NAT-Bindings ]
                             [ NAT-External-Port-Style ]
                           * [ AVP ]]]></artwork>
          </figure>
        </section>

        <section anchor="avp_NAT-Control-Remove"
                 title="NAT-Control-Remove AVP">
          <t>The NAT-Control-Remove AVP (AVP code TBD) is of type Grouped, and
          it is used to deactivate or remove NAT-bindings. At least one of the
          two AVPs (NAT-Control-Definition AVP, NAT-Control-Binding-Template
          AVP) SHOULD be present in the NAT-Control-Remove AVP.</t>

          <t>AVP format:</t>

          <figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[  NAT-Control-Remove ::= < AVP Header: TBD >
                          * [ NAT-Control-Definition ]
                            [ NAT-Control-Binding-Template ]
                          * [ AVP ]]]></artwork>
          </figure>
        </section>

        <section anchor="avp_NAT-Control-Definition"
                 title="NAT-Control-Definition AVP">
          <t>The NAT-Control-Definition AVP (AVP code TBD) is of type Grouped,
          and it describes a binding.</t>

          <t>The NAT-Control-Definition AVP uniquely identifies the binding
          between the DNCA Diameter peers.</t>

          <t>If both the NAT-Internal-Address and NAT-External-Address AVP(s)
          are supplied, it is a pre-defined binding.</t>

          <t>If the NAT-External-Address AVP is not specified then the
          NAT-device MUST select the external port as per the
          NAT-External-Port-Style AVP, if present in the
          NAT-Control-Definition AVP.</t>

          <t>The Protocol AVP describes the transport protocol for the
          binding. The NAT-Control-Definition AVP can contain either zero or
          one Protocol AVP. If the Protocol AVP is omitted and if both
          internal and external IP-address are specified then the binding
          reserves the IP-addresses for all transport protocols.</t>

          <t>The Direction AVP is of type Enumerated. It specifies the
          direction for the binding. The values of the enumeration applicable
          in this context are: "IN","OUT". If Direction AVP is OUT or absent,
          the NAT-Internal-Address refers to the IP-address of the endpoint
          that needs to be translated. If Direction AVP is "IN",
          NAT-Internal-Address is the destination IP-address that has to be
          translated.</t>

          <t>AVP format:</t>

          <figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[  NAT-Control-Definition ::= < AVP Header: TBD >
                              { NAT-Internal-Address }
                              [ Protocol ]
                              [ Direction ]
                              [ NAT-External-Address ]
                              [ Session-Id ]
                            * [ AVP ]]]></artwork>
          </figure>
        </section>

        <section anchor="avp_NAT-Internal-Address"
                 title="NAT-Internal-Address AVP">
          <t>The NAT-Internal-Address AVP (AVP code TBD) is of type Grouped.
          It describes the internal IP-address and port for a binding.
          Framed-IPV6-Prefix and Framed-IP-Address AVPs are mutually
          exclusive.</t>

          <t>AVP format:</t>

          <figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[  NAT-Internal-Address ::= < AVP Header: TBD >
                            [ Framed-IP-Address ]
                            [ Framed-IPv6-Prefix ]
                            [ Port]
                          * [ AVP ]]]></artwork>
          </figure>
        </section>

        <section anchor="avp_NAT-External-Address"
                 title="NAT-External-Address AVP">
          <t>The NAT-External-Address AVP (AVP code TBD) is of type Grouped,
          and it describes the external IP-address and port for a binding. The
          external IP-address specified in this attribute can be reused for
          multiple endpoints by specifying the same address in the respective
          NAT-External-Address AVPs. If the external IP-address is not
          specified and the NAT-External-Port-Style AVP is specified in the
          NAT-Control-Definition AVP then the NAT-device MUST select external
          port as per the NAT-External-Port-Style AVP.</t>

          <t>AVP format:</t>

          <figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[  NAT-External-Address ::= < AVP Header: TBD >
                            [ Framed-IP-Address ]
                            [ Port ]
                          * [ AVP ]]]></artwork>
          </figure>
        </section>

        <section anchor="avp_Max-NAT-Bindings" title="Max-NAT-Bindings">
          <t>The Max-NAT-Bindings AVP (AVP code TBD) is of type Unsigned32. It
          indicates the maximum number of NAT-bindings allowed for a
          particular endpoint.</t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="avp_NAT-Control-Binding-Rule"
                 title="NAT-Control-Binding-Template AVP">
          <t>The NAT-Control-Binding-Template AVP (AVP code TBD) is of type
          OctetString. It defines a name for a policy template that is
          predefined at the NAT-device. Details on the contents and structure
          of the template and configuration are outside the scope of this
          document. The policy to which this AVP refers to may contain
          NAT-bindings, IP-address pool for allocating the external IP-address
          of a NAT-binding, and maximum number of allowed NAT-bindings. Such
          policy template can be reused by specifying the same
          NAT-Control-Binding-Template AVP in the corresponding
          NAT-Control-Install AVPs of multiple endpoints.</t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="avp_Duplicate-Session-Id"
                 title="Duplicate-Session-Id AVP">
          <t>The Duplicate-Session-Id AVP (AVP Code TBD) is of type
          UTF8String. It is used to report errors and contains the Session-Id
          of an existing session.</t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="avp_NAT-External-Port-Style"
                 title="NAT-External-Port-Style AVP">
          <t>The NAT-External-Port-Style AVP (AVP Code TBD) is of type
          Enumerated and contains the style to be followed while selecting the
          external port for a NAT-Binding relative to the internal port.</t>

          <t>The following values are defined: <list style="empty">
              <t>FOLLOW_INTERNAL_PORT_STYLE (1)<list style="empty">
                  <t>External port numbers selected MUST follow the same
                  sequence and oddity as the internal ports of the
                  NAT-bindings. The port odditity is required to support
                  protocols like RTP and RTCP as defined in <xref
                  target="RFC3550"></xref>. If for example the internal port
                  in a requested NAT-binding is odd numbered then the external
                  port allocated MUST also be odd numbered, and vice versa for
                  an even numbered port. In addition, the sequence of port
                  numbering is maintained: If internal ports are consecutive,
                  then the NAT-device MUST choose consecutive external ports
                  for the NAT-bindings.</t>
                </list></t>
            </list></t>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="sec-accounting" title="Accounting Commands">
      <t>The DNCA reuses session based accounting as defined in the Diameter
      Base Protocol<xref target="RFC3588"></xref> to report the bindings per
      endpoint. This reporting is achieved by sending Diameter Accounting
      Requests (ACR) [Start, Interim and Stop] from the DNCA Diameter peer
      within the NAT-device to its associated DNCA Diameter peer within the
      NAT-controller.</t>

      <t>The DNCA Diameter peer within the NAT-device sends an ACR Start on
      receiving a NCR with NC-Request-Type AVP set to INITIAL_REQUEST for a
      session or on creation of the first binding for a session requested in
      an earlier NCR. DNCA may send ACR Interim updates, if required, either
      due to a change in bindings resulting from a NCR with NC-Request-Type
      AVP set to UPDATE_REQUEST, or periodically as specified in
      Acct-Interim-Interval by the DNCA Diameter peer within the
      NAT-controller, or when it creates or tears down bindings. An ACR Stop
      is sent by the DNCA Diameter peer within the NAT-device on receiving
      STR.</t>

      <t>The function of correlating the multiple bindings used by an endpoint
      at any given time is relegated to the post processor.</t>

      <t>The DNCA Diameter peer within the NAT-device may trigger an interim
      accounting record when the maximum number of bindings, if received in an
      NCR, is reached.</t>

      <section title="NAT Control Accounting Messages">
        <t>The ACR and ACA messages are reused as defined in the Diameter Base
        Protocol <xref target="RFC3588"></xref> for exchanging endpoint NAT
        binding details between the DNCA Diameter peers. The DNCA Application
        IDs is used in the accounting commands. ACR contains one or more
        optional NAT-Control-Record AVPs to report the bindings. The
        NAT-device indicates the number of allocated NAT bindings to the
        NAT-controller using the Current-NAT-Bindings AVP. This number needs
        to match the number of bindings identified as active within the
        NAT-Control-Record AVP.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="NAT Control Accounting AVPs">
        <t>In addition to AVPs for ACR specified in <xref
        target="RFC3588"></xref>, the DNCA Diameter peer within the NAT-device
        must add the NAT-Control-Record AVP.</t>

        <section anchor="avp_NAT-Control-Record" title="NAT-Control-Record">
          <t>The NAT-Control-Record AVP (AVP code TBD) is of type Grouped. It
          describes a binding and its status. If NAT-Control-Binding-Status is
          set to Created, Event-Timestamp indicates the binding creation time.
          If NAT-Control-Binding-Status is set to Removed, Event-Timestamp
          indicates the binding removal time. If NAT-Control-Binding-Status is
          active, Event-Timestamp need not be present; if a value is present,
          it indicates that binding is active at the given time.</t>

          <figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[  NAT-Control-Record ::= < AVP Header: TBD >
                         { NAT-Control-Definition }
                         { NAT-Control-Binding-Status } 
                         [ Event-Timestamp ]]]></artwork>
          </figure>
        </section>

        <section anchor="avp_NAT-Control-Binding-Status"
                 title="NAT-Control-Binding-Status">
          <t>The NAT-Control-Binding-Status AVP (AVP code TBD) is of type
          enumerated. It indicates the status of the binding - created,
          removed, or active.</t>

          <t>The following values are defined: <list style="empty">
              <t>Created (1)<list style="empty">
                  <t>NAT binding is created.</t>
                </list></t>

              <t>Active (2)<list style="empty">
                  <t>NAT binding is active.</t>
                </list></t>

              <t>Removed (3)<list style="empty">
                  <t>NAT binding was removed.</t>
                </list></t>
            </list></t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="avp_Current-NAT-Bindings"
                 title="Current-NAT-Bindings">
          <t>The Current-NAT-Bindings AVP (AVP code TBD) is of type
          Unsigned32. It indicates the number of NAT bindings active on the
          NAT-device.</t>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="sec-avp-occurence-table" title="AVP Occurrence Table">
      <t>The following sections present the AVPs defined in this document and
      specify the Diameter messages in which they can be present. Note: AVPs
      that can only be present within a Grouped AVP are not represented in
      this table.</t>

      <t>The table uses the following symbols:</t>

      <t><list style="empty">
          <t><list hangIndent="10" style="hanging">
              <t hangText="0">The AVP MUST NOT be present in the message.</t>

              <t hangText="0+">Zero or more instances of the AVP can be
              present in the message.</t>

              <t hangText="0-1">Zero or one instance of the AVP can be present
              in the message. It is considered an error if there is more than
              one instance of the AVP.</t>

              <t hangText="1">One instance of the AVP MUST be present in the
              message.</t>

              <t hangText="1+">At least one instance of the AVP MUST be
              present in the message.</t>
            </list></t>
        </list></t>

      <section title="DNCA AVP Table for NAT Control Initial and Update Requests">
        <t>The following table lists DNCA specific AVPs that have to be
        present in NCRs and NCAs with NC-Request-Type set to INITIAL_REQUEST
        or UPDATE_REQUEST.</t>

        <figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[                                    +-------------------+
                                    |  Command Code     |
+-----------------------------------+-------------------+
| Attribute Name                        NCR    NCA      |
+-------------------------------------------------------+
|NC-Request-Type                         1      1       |
|NAT-Control-Install                     0-1    0       |
|NAT-Control-Remove                      0-1    0       |
|NAT-Control-Definition                  0      0       |
|Current-NAT-Bindings                    0      0       |
|Duplicate-Session-Id                    0      0-1     |
+-------------------------------------------------------+]]></artwork>
        </figure>

        <t>Note that any combination of "NAT-Control-Install" and
        "NAT-Control-Remove" AVPs could be present in an update or initial
        requests. Consider the following examples:</t>

        <t><list style="empty">
            <t>Neither "NAT-Control-Install AVP" nor "NAT-Control-Remove AVP"
            are present: This could for example be the case if the
            NAT-controller would only want to receive accounting information,
            but not control NAT-bindings.</t>

            <t>Only "NAT-Control-Install AVP" is present: This could for
            example be the case if a new NAT-binding is installed for an
            existing session.</t>

            <t>Only "NAT-Control-Remove AVP" is present: This could for
            example be the case if a new NAT-binding is removed from an
            existing session.</t>

            <t>Both, "NAT-Control-Install AVP" and "NAT-Control-Remove AVP"
            are present: This could for example be the case if a formerly
            created NAT-binding is removed and a new NAT-binding is
            established within the same request.</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>

      <section title="DNCA AVP Table for Session Query request">
        <t>The following table lists DNCA specific AVPs that have to be
        present in NCRs and NCAs with NC-Request-Type set to
        QUERY_REQUEST.</t>

        <figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[                                    +-------------------+
                                    |  Command Code     |
+-----------------------------------+-------------------+
| Attribute Name                        NCR    NCA      |
+-------------------------------------------------------+
|NC-Request-Type                         1      1       |
|NAT-Control-Install                     0      0       |
|NAT-Control-Remove                      0      0       |
|NAT-Control-Definition                  0      0+      |
|Current-NAT-Bindings                    0      1       |
|Duplicate-Session-Id                    0      0       |
+-------------------------------------------------------+]]></artwork>
        </figure>
      </section>

      <section title="DNCA AVP Table for Accounting Message">
        <t>The following table lists DNCA specific AVPs, which may or may not
        be present in ACR and ACA messages.</t>

        <figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[                                    +-------------------+
                                    |  Command Code     |
+-----------------------------------+-------------------+
| Attribute Name                        ACR    ACA      |
+-------------------------------------------------------+
|NAT-Control-Record                      0+     0       |
|Current-NAT-Bindings                    1      0       |
+-------------------------------------------------------+
]]></artwork>
        </figure>
      </section>
    </section>

    <!-- -->

    <!-- Possibly a 'Contributors' section ... 
-->

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>This section contains the namespaces that have either been created in
      this specification, or the values assigned to existing namespaces
      managed by IANA.</t>

      <t>In the subsections below, when we speak about review by a Designated
      Expert, please note that the designated expert will be assigned by the
      IESG. Initially, such Expert discussions take place on the AAA WG
      mailing list.</t>

      <section title="Application Identifier">
        <t>This specification assigns the value &lt;TBD&gt;, 'Diameter NAT
        Control Application', to the Application Identifier namespace defined
        in <xref target="RFC3588"></xref>. See <xref target="sec-dnca"></xref>
        for more information.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Command Codes">
        <t>This specification uses the value &lt;TBD&gt; from the Command code
        namespace defined in <xref target="RFC3588"></xref> for the
        NAT-Control-Request (NCR), NAT-Control-Answer (NCA) commands. See
        <xref target="sec-dnca-ncr"></xref> and <xref
        target="sec-dnca-nca"></xref> for more information on these
        commands.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="AVP Codes">
        <t>This specification assigns the values &lt;TBD&gt; from the AVP code
        namespace defined in <xref target="RFC3588"></xref>. See <xref
        target="tab-new-avps"></xref> for the assignment of the namespace in
        this specification.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Result-Code AVP Values ">
        <t>This specification assigns the values &lt;TBD&gt; (4xxx, 5xxx,
        5xxx, 5xxx, 5xxx,5xxx) from the Result-Code AVP value namespace
        defined in <xref target="RFC3588"></xref>. See <xref
        target="sec_result-codes"></xref> for the assignment of the namespace
        in this specification.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="NC-Request-Type AVP">
        <t>As defined in <xref target="avp_NC-Request-Type"></xref>, the
        NC-Request-Type AVP includes Enumerated type values 1 - 3. IANA has
        created and is maintaining a namespace for this AVP. All remaining
        values are available for assignment by a Designated Expert <xref
        target="RFC5226"></xref>.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="NAT-External-Port-Style AVP">
        <t>As defined in <xref target="avp_NAT-External-Port-Style"></xref>,
        the NAT-External-Port-Style AVP includes Enumerated type value 1. IANA
        has created and is maintaining a namespace for this AVP. All remaining
        values are available for assignment by a Designated Expert <xref
        target="RFC5226"></xref>.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="NAT-Control-Binding-Status AVP">
        <t>As defined in <xref target="avp_NC-Request-Type"></xref>, the
        NAT-Control-Binding-Status AVP includes Enumerated type values 1 - 3.
        IANA has created and is maintaining a namespace for this AVP. All
        remaining values are available for assignment by a Designated Expert
        <xref target="RFC5226"></xref>.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>This document describes procedures for controlling NAT related
      attributes and parameters by an entity, which is non-local to the device
      performing NAT. This section discusses security considerations for DNCA.
      This includes the interactions between the Diameter peers within a
      NAT-controller and a NAT-device as well as general considerations for
      NAT-control in a service provider network.</t>

      <t>Security between a NAT-controller and a NAT-device has a number of
      components: authentication, authorization, integrity, and
      confidentiality.</t>

      <t>Authentication refers to confirming the identity of an originator for
      all datagrams received from the originator. Lack of authentication of
      Diameter messages between the Diameter peers can jeopardize the
      fundamental service of the peering network elements. A consequence of
      not authenticating the message sender by the recipient would be that an
      attacker could spoof the identity of a "legitimate" authorizing entity
      in order to change the behavior of the receiver. An attacker could for
      example launch a denial of service attack by setting the maximum number
      of bindings for a session on the NAT-device to zero; provision bindings
      on a NAT-device which include IP-addresses already in use in other parts
      of the network; or request session termination of the Diameter session
      and hamper a user's connectivity. Lack of authentication of a NAT-device
      to a NAT-controller could lead to situations where the NAT-device could
      provide a wrong view of the resources (i.e. NAT-bindings). In addition,
      NAT Binding Predefined template on the NAT-device could be configured
      differently than expected by the NAT-controller. Failing of any of the
      two DNCA Diameter peers to provide the required credentials should be
      subject to logging. The corresponding logging infrastructure of the
      operator SHOULD be built in a way that it can mitigate potential denial
      of service attacks resulting from large amounts of logging events. This
      could include proper dimensioning of the logging infrastructure combined
      with policing the maximum amount of logging events accepted by the
      logging system to a threshold which the system is known to be able to
      handle.</t>

      <t>Authorization refers to whether a particular authorizing entity is
      authorized to signal a network element requests for one or more
      applications, adhering to a certain policy profile. Failing the
      authorization process might indicate a resource theft attempt or failure
      due to administrative and/or credential deficiencies. In either case,
      the network element should take the proper measures to log such
      attempts.</t>

      <t>Integrity is required to ensure that a Diameter message exchanged
      between the Diameter peers has not been maliciously altered by
      intermediate devices. The result of a lack of data integrity enforcement
      in an untrusted environment could be that an impostor will alter the
      messages exchanged between the peers. This could cause a change of
      behavior of the peers, including the potential of a denial of
      service.</t>

      <t>Confidentiality protection of Diameter messages ensures that the
      signaling data is accessible only to the authorized entities. When
      signaling messages between the DNCA Diameter peers traverse untrusted
      networks, lack of confidentiality will allow eavesdropping and traffic
      analysis.</t>

      <t>Diameter offers security mechanisms to deal with the functionality
      demanded above. DNCA makes use of the capabilities offered by Diameter
      and the underlying transport protocols to deliver these requirements
      (see <xref target="sec-diameter-messages"></xref>). If the DNCA
      communication traverses untrusted networks, messages between DNCA
      Diameter peers SHOULD be secured using either IPsec or TLS. Please refer
      to <xref target="RFC3588"></xref>, section 13 for details. DNCA Diameter
      peers SHOULD perform bilateral authentication, authorization as well as
      procedures to ensure integrity and confidentiality of the information
      exchange. In addition the Session-Id chosen for a particular Diameter
      session SHOULD be chosen in a way that it is hard to guess in order to
      mitigate issues through potential message replay.</t>

      <t>DNCA Diameter peers SHOULD have a mutual trust setup. This document
      does not specify a mechanisms for authorization between the DNCA
      Diameter peers. The DNCA Diameter peers SHOULD be provided with
      sufficient information to make an authorization decision. The
      information can come from various sources, for example the peering
      devices could store local authentication policy, listing the identities
      of authorized peers.</t>

      <t>Any mechanism or protocol providing control of a NAT-device, and DNCA
      is an example of such a control mechanism, could allow for misuse of the
      NAT-device given that it enables the definition of per-destination or
      per-source rules. Misuse could include anti-competitive practices among
      providers, censorship, crime, etc. NAT-control could be used as a tool
      for preventing or redirecting access to particular sites. For instance,
      by controlling the NAT bindings, one could ensure that end points aren't
      able to receive particular flows, or that those flows are redirected to
      a relay that snoops or tampers with traffic instead of directly
      forwarding the traffic to the intended end point. In addition one could
      set up a binding in a way that the source IP address used is one of a
      relay so that traffic coming back can be snooped on or interfered with.
      The protections on DNCA and its Diameter protocol exchanges don't
      prevent such abuses of NAT-control. A service provider deploying DNCA
      needs to make sure that higher layer processes and procedures are put in
      place which allow them to detect and mitigate misuses.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Examples">
      <t>This section shows example DNCA message content and exchange.</t>

      <section title="DNCA Session Establishment Example">
        <t><xref target="fig-session-establishment-example"></xref> depicts a
        typical call flow for DNCA session establishment.</t>

        <t>In this example, the NAT-controller:</t>

        <t><list style="letters">
            <t>requests a maximum of 100 NAT-bindings for the end point.</t>

            <t>defines a static binding for a TCP connection which associates
            the internal IP-Address:Port 192.0.2.1:80 with the external
            IP-Address:Port 198.51.100.1:80 for the end point.</t>

            <t>requests the use of a preconfigured template called
            "local-policy" while creating NAT-bindings for the end point.</t>
          </list></t>

        <figure anchor="fig-session-establishment-example"
                title="Initial NAT control request and session establishment  example">
          <artwork><![CDATA[end point             NAT-Controller (within NAS)           NAT-device 
   |                            |                               |
   |                            |                               |
   |      1. Trigger            |                               |
   |--------------------------->|                               |
   |       +-------------------------------------+              |
   |       |  2. Determine that NAT control      |              |
   |       |     is required for the end point   |              |  
   |       +-------------------------------------+              |
   |                            |                               |
   |                            |                               |
   |                           ...................................
   |                           .|   3. Diameter Base CER/CEA    |.
   |                           .|<----------------------------->|.
   |                           ...................................
   |                            |                               |
   |                            |                               |
   |                            |         4.  NCR               |
   |                            |------------------------------>|
   |                            |                               |
   |                            |                     5. DNCA session  
   |                            |                        established      
   |                            |                               | 
   |                            |         6.  NCA               |
   |                            |<------------------------------|  
   |                            |                               |
   |                            |                               |
   |                  7. Data traffic                           |
   |----------------------------------------------------------->| 
   |                            |                               |
   |                            |                               |
   |                            |                    8. NAT Bindings
   |                            |                     created as per
   |                            |                   directives in the
   |                            |                       DNCA session   
   |                            |                               |

]]></artwork>
        </figure>

        <t>Detailed description of the steps shown in <xref
        target="fig-session-establishment-example"></xref>:</t>

        <t><list style="numbers">
            <t>The NAT-controller (co-located with the NAS here) creates state
            for an end point based on a trigger. This could for example be the
            successful establishment of a Point-to-Point Protocol (PPP) <xref
            target="RFC1661"></xref> access session.</t>

            <t>Based on the configuration of the DNCA Diameter peer within the
            NAT-controller, the NAT-controller determines that NAT-control is
            required and is to be enforced at a NAT-device.</t>

            <t>If there is no Diameter session already established with the
            DNCA Diameter peer within NAT-device, a Diameter connection is
            established and Diameter Base CER/CEA are exchanged.</t>

            <t>The NAT-Controller creates an NCR message (see below) and sends
            it to the NAT-device. This example shows IPv4 to IPv4 address and
            port translation. For IPv6 to IPv4 translation, the
            Framed-IP-Address AVP would be replaced by the Framed-IPv6-Address
            AVP with the value set to the IPv6 address of the end point.
            <figure anchor="fig-NAT-session-establish-example"
                suppress-title="true">
                <artwork><![CDATA[   < NC-Request > ::= < Diameter Header: TBD, REQ, PXY>
                    Session-Id =  "natC.example.com:33041;23432;"
                    Auth-Application-Id = <DNCA Application ID>
                    Origin-Host = "natC.example.com"  
                    Origin-Realm = "example.com"
                    Destination-Realm = "example.com"
                    Destination-Host = "nat-device.example.com"
                    NC-Request-Type = INITIAL_REQUEST
                    User-Name = "subscriber_example1"
                    Framed-IP-Address = "192.0.2.1"
                    NAT-Control-Install = {
                         NAT-Control-Definition = {
                            Protocol = TCP
                            Direction = OUT
                            NAT-Internal-Address = {
                                 Framed-IP-Address = "192.0.2.1"
                                 Port = 80
                            }
                            NAT-External-Address = {
                                 Framed-IP-Address = "198.51.100.1"
                                 Port = 80
                            }
                         }
                         Max-NAT-Bindings = 100
                         NAT-Control-Binding-Template = "local-policy"
                   }]]></artwork>
              </figure></t>

            <t>The NAT-device establishes a DNCA session as it is able to
            comply with the request.</t>

            <t>The NAT-device sends an NCA to indicate the successful
            completion of the request. <figure suppress-title="true">
                <artwork><![CDATA[   <NC-Answer> ::= < Diameter Header: TBD, PXY >
                    Session-Id =  "natC.example.com:33041;23432;"
                    Origin-Host = "nat-device.example.com"  
                    Origin-Realm = "example.com"
                    NC-Request-Type = INITIAL_REQUEST
                    Result-Code = DIAMETER_SUCCESS

]]></artwork>
              </figure></t>

            <t>The end point sends packets that reach the NAT-device.</t>

            <t>The NAT-device performs NAT for traffic received from the end
            point with source address 192.0.2.1. Traffic with source
            IP-address 192.0.2.1 and port 80 are translated to the external
            IP-address 198.51.100.1 and port 80. Traffic with source
            IP-address 192.0.2.1 and a source port different from 80 will be
            translated to IP-address 198.51.100.1 and a port chosen by the
            NAT-device. Note that this example assumes that the NAT-device
            follows typical binding allocation rules for end points, in that
            only a single external IP-address is used for all traffic received
            from a single IP-address of an end point. The NAT-device will
            allow a maximum of 100 NAT-bindings be created for the end
            point.</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>

      <section title="DNCA Session Update with Port Style Example">
        <t>This section gives an example for a DNCA session update: A new set
        of NAT-bindings is requested for an existing session. The request
        contains a directive ( the "NAT-External-Port-Style" AVP set to
        FOLLOW_INTERNAL_PORT_STYLE) that directs the NAT-device to maintain
        port-sequence and port-oddity for the newly created NAT-bindings. In
        the example shown, the internal ports are UDP port 1036 and 1037. The
        NAT-device follows the directive selects the external ports
        accordingly. The NAT-device would for example create a mapping of
        192.0.2.1:1036 to 198.51.100.1:5056 and 192.0.2.1:1037 to
        198.51.100.1:5057, thereby maintaining port oddity (1036-&gt;5056,
        1037-&gt;5057) and sequence ( the consecutive internal ports 1036 and
        1037 map to the consecutive external ports 5056 and 5057).</t>

        <figure anchor="fig-NAT-session-update-example" suppress-title="true">
          <artwork><![CDATA[   < NC-Request > ::= < Diameter Header: TBD, REQ, PXY>
                    Session-Id =  "natC.example.com:33041;23432;"
                    Auth-Application-Id = <DNCA Application ID>
                    Origin-Host = "natC.example.com"  
                    Origin-Realm = "example.com"
                    Destination-Realm = "example.com"
                    Destination-Host = "nat-device.example.com"
                    NC-Request-Type = UPDATE_REQUEST
                    NAT-Control-Install = {
                        NAT-Control-Definition = {
                            Protocol = UDP
                            Direction = OUT
                            NAT-Internal-Address = {
                                 Framed-IP-Address = "192.0.2.1"
                                 Port = 1035
                            }
                        }
                        NAT-Control-Definition = {
                            Protocol = UDP
                            Direction = OUT
                            NAT-Internal-Address = {
                                 Framed-IP-Address = "192.0.2.1"
                                 Port = 1036
                            }
                        }
                        NAT-External-Port-
                               Style = FOLLOW_INTERNAL_PORT_STYLE
                    }]]></artwork>
        </figure>
      </section>

      <section title="DNCA Session Query Example">
        <t>This section shows an example for DNCA session query for a
        subscriber whose internal IP-Address is 192.0.2.1.</t>

        <figure anchor="fig-NAT-session-query-example" suppress-title="true">
          <artwork><![CDATA[   < NC-Request > ::= < Diameter Header: TBD, REQ, PXY>
                    Auth-Application-Id = <DNCA Application ID>
                    Origin-Host = "natC.example.com"  
                    Origin-Realm = "example.com"
                    Destination-Realm = "example.com"
                    Destination-Host = "nat-device.example.com"
                    NC-Request-Type = QUERY_REQUEST
                    Framed-IP-Address = "192.0.2.1"]]></artwork>
        </figure>

        <t>The NAT-device constructs an NCA to report all currently active
        NAT-bindings whose internal address is 192.0.2.1.</t>

        <figure anchor="fig-NAT-session-query-answer-example"
                suppress-title="true">
          <artwork><![CDATA[      <NC-Answer> ::= < Diameter Header: TBD, PXY >
                    Origin-Host = "nat-device.example.com"  
                    Origin-Realm = "example.com"
                    NC-Request-Type = QUERY_REQUEST
                    NAT-Control-Definition = {
                            Protocol = TCP
                            Direction = OUT
                            NAT-Internal-Address = {
                                Framed-IP-Address = "192.0.2.1"
                                Port = 80
                               }
                            NAT-External-Address = {
                                 Framed-IP-Address = "198.51.100.1"
                                 Port = 80
                               }
                            Session-Id = "natC.example.com:33041;23432;"
                    }
                    NAT-Control-Definition = {
                            Protocol = TCP
                            Direction = OUT
                            NAT-Internal-Address = {
                                Framed-IP-Address = "192.0.2.1"
                                Port = 1036
                               }
                            NAT-External-Address = {
                                 Framed-IP-Address = "198.51.100.1"
                                 Port = 5056
                               }
                            Session-Id = "natC.example.com:33041;23432;"
                    }
                    NAT-Control-Definition = {
                            Protocol = TCP
                            Direction = OUT
                            NAT-Internal-Address = {
                                Framed-IP-Address = "192.0.2.1"
                                Port = 1037
                               }
                            NAT-External-Address = {
                                 Framed-IP-Address = "198.51.100.1"
                                 Port = 5057
                               }
                            Session-Id = "natC.example.com:33041;23432;"
                    }   ]]></artwork>
        </figure>
      </section>

      <section title="DNCA Session Termination Example">
        <t>In this example the NAT-controller decides to terminate the
        previously established DNCA session. This could for example be the
        case as a result of an access session (e.g. a PPP session) associated
        with an end point been torn down.</t>

        <figure anchor="fig-session-teardown-example"
                title=" NAT control session termination example  ">
          <artwork><![CDATA[
    NAT-Controller                            NAT-device 
          |                                       |
          |                                       |
 +--------------+                                 |
 |  1. Trigger  |                                 |
 +--------------+                                 |
          |                                       |
          |                                       | 
          |             2.  STR                   |
          |-------------------------------------->|
          |                                       |
          |                             3. DNCA session 
          |                                   lookup 
          |             4.  ACR                   |
          |<--------------------------------------|
          |                                       |
          |             5.  ACA                   |
          |-------------------------------------->|  
          |                                       |
          |                                       |  
          |                             6. DNCA bindings
          |                            and session cleanup 
          |                                       |
          |             7.  STA                   |
          |<--------------------------------------|  
          |                                       |]]></artwork>
        </figure>

        <t>The following steps describe the sequence of events for tearing
        down the DNCA session in the example above:</t>

        <t><list style="numbers">
            <t>The NAT-controller receives a trigger that a DNCA session
            associated with a specific end point should be terminated. An
            example event could be the termination of the PPP <xref
            target="RFC1661"></xref> access session to an end point in a NAS.
            The NAS correspondingly triggers the NAT-controller request
            tear-down of the associated DNCA session.</t>

            <t>The NAT-controller creates the required NCR message and sends
            it to the NAT-device: <figure
                anchor="fig-NAT-session-termination-example"
                suppress-title="true">
                <artwork><![CDATA[   < STR >     ::= < Diameter Header: 275, REQ, PXY>
                    Session-Id =  "natC.example.com:33041;23432;"
                    Auth-Application-Id = <DNCA Application ID>
                    Origin-Host = "natC.example.com"  
                    Origin-Realm = "example.com"
                    Destination-Realm = "example.com"
                    Destination-Host = "nat-device.example.com"
                    Termination-Cause = DIAMETER_LOGOUT
]]></artwork>
              </figure></t>

            <t>The NAT-device looks up the DNCA session based on the
            Session-Id AVP and finds a previously established active
            session.</t>

            <t>The NAT-device reports all NAT-bindings established for that
            subscriber using an ACR: <figure
                anchor="fig-NAT-session-accounting-request-example"
                suppress-title="true">
                <artwork><![CDATA[   < ACR >     ::= < Diameter Header: 271, REQ, PXY>
                    Session-Id =  "natC.example.com:33041;23432;"
                    Auth-Application-Id = <DNCA Application ID>
                    Origin-Host = "nat-device.example.com"  
                    Origin-Realm = "example.com"
                    Destination-Realm = "example.com"
                    Destination-Host = "natC.example.com"
                    Accounting-Record-Type = STOP_RECORD
                    Accounting-Record-Number = 1
                    NAT-Control-Record = {
                        NAT-Control-Definition = {
                            Protocol = TCP
                            Direction = OUT
                            NAT-Internal-Address = {
                                Framed-IP-Address = "192.0.2.1"
                                Port = 5001
                               }
                            NAT-External-Address = {
                                 Framed-IP-Address = "198.51.100.1"
                                 Port = 7777
                               }
                           }
                          NAT-Control-Binding-Status = Removed
                       }

]]></artwork>
              </figure></t>

            <t>The NAT-controller receives and processes the ACR as per its
            configuration. It responds with an ACA to the NAT-device. <figure
                suppress-title="true">
                <artwork><![CDATA[   <ACA>      ::= < Diameter Header: 271, PXY >
                    Session-Id =  "natC.example.com:33041;23432;"
                    Origin-Host = "natC.example.com"  
                    Origin-Realm = "example.com"
                    Result-Code = DIAMETER_SUCCESS
                    Accounting-Record-Type = STOP_RECORD
                    Accounting-Record-Number = 1

]]></artwork>
              </figure></t>

            <t>On receipt of the ACA the NAT-device cleans up all NAT-bindings
            and associated session state for the end point.</t>

            <t>NAT-device sends an STA. On receipt of the STA the
            NAT-controller will clean up the corresponding session state.
            <figure suppress-title="true">
                <artwork><![CDATA[   <STA>      ::= < Diameter Header: TBD, PXY >
                    Session-Id =  "natC.example.com:33041;23432;"
                    Origin-Host = "nat-device.example.com"  
                    Origin-Realm = "example.com"
                    Result-Code = DIAMETER_SUCCESS
]]></artwork>
              </figure></t>
          </list></t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>The authors would like to thank Jari Arkko, Wesley Eddy, Stephen
      Farrell, Miguel A. Garcia, David Harrington, Jouni Korhonen, Matt
      Lepinski, Avi Lior, Chris Metz, Pallavi Mishra, Lionel Morand, Robert
      Sparks, Martin Stiemerling, Dave Thaler, Hannes Tschofenig, Sean Turner,
      Shashank Vikram, Greg Weber, and Glen Zorn for their input on this
      document.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Change History (to be removed prior to publication as an RFC) ">
      <t>Changes from -00 to -01</t>

      <t><list style="letters">
          <t>new values for Result-Code AVP used - instead of
          Experimental-Result AVP</t>

          <t>added support for transport specific binding (UDP/TCP)</t>

          <t>added support for twice-NAT</t>

          <t>clarified the use of the two different types of
          query-requests</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>Changes from -01 to -02</t>

      <t><list style="letters">
          <t>Reference to pull mode removed, session initiation event
          clarified in section 4.1</t>

          <t>added Redirect-* AVPs in NCA command</t>

          <t>Removed reference to Called-Station-Id AVP in NCR command</t>

          <t>Editorial changes</t>

          <t>added support for bindings providing AFT (NAT64)</t>
        </list>Changes from -02 to -03<list style="letters">
          <t>Editorial changes</t>
        </list>Changes from -03 to -04<list style="letters">
          <t>Editorial changes suggested in WG last call review</t>

          <t>Removed NCR Request type terminate and replaced with STR</t>

          <t>All references to Auth-Session-State are removed and a new
          section to describe FSM for Manager and Agent has been added</t>

          <t>Clarified reuse of External address and address pools among
          multiple subscribers</t>
        </list>Changes from -04 to -05<list style="letters">
          <t>Removed references to Large Scale NAT as per review comments</t>
        </list>Changes from -05 to -06<list style="letters">
          <t>Editorial changes</t>
        </list>Changes from -06 to -07<list style="letters">
          <t>Added a note in section 4.3 stating the state of pre-existing
          bindings on update failure</t>

          <t>Security considerations are made consistent between sections 5.1
          and 12</t>

          <t>Editorial changes</t>
        </list>Changes from -07 to -08<list style="letters">
          <t>Added section 4.6 to describe session abort</t>

          <t>Editorial changes</t>

          <t>Nomenclature change: From DNCA Agent/Manager to DNCA Diameter
          peers identifying the location where they reside (NAT-controller or
          NAT-device)</t>

          <t>IANA consideration Section format changes</t>

          <t>Updated security section (included considerations directly,
          rather than referring to Diameter QoS similarities).</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>Changes from -08 to -09</t>

      <t><list style="letters">
          <t>expanded on the need for an SP controlling the maximum number of
          bindings of an end point (see introduction section)</t>

          <t>added a paragraph in the security section outlining general
          mis-uses of NAT-control (non specific to DNCA), with DNCA being an
          example of such a NAT-control protocol</t>

          <t>editorial changes</t>
        </list>Changes from -09 to -10<list style="letters">
          <t>Section 4 and security considerations updated with RFC 2119
          language</t>

          <t>NAT-External-Port-Style AVP added to aid external port oddity
          requirement as per MIDCOM framework</t>

          <t>NAT related RFCs added in normative reference</t>

          <t>Section 13 added to provide example DNCA message exchange
          flows</t>

          <t>Added a description to provide DNCA comparison with MIDCOM</t>

          <t>n:1 deployment model for NAT-controllers and NAT-devices
          explicitly specified</t>

          <t>editorial changes as per IESG DISCUSS comments</t>
        </list></t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <!--  *****BACK MATTER ***** -->

  <back>
    <!-- References split into informative and normative -->

    <!-- There are 2 ways to insert reference entries from the citation libraries:
     1. define an ENTITY at the top, and use "ampersand character"RFC2629; here (as shown)
     2. simply use a PI "less than character"?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119.xml"?> here
        (for I-Ds: include="reference.I-D.narten-iana-considerations-rfc2434bis.xml")

     Both are cited textually in the same manner: by using xref elements.
     If you use the PI option, xml2rfc will, by default, try to find included files in the same
     directory as the including file. You can also define the XML_LIBRARY environment variable
     with a value containing a set of directories to search.  These can be either in the local
     filing system or remote ones accessed by http (http://domain/dir/... ).-->

    <references title="Normative References">
      <!--?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"?-->

      &RFC2119;

      &RFC3588;

      &RFC4675;

      &RFC5777;

      &RFC5226;

      <reference anchor="ETSIES283034">
        <front>
          <title>Telecommunications and Internet Converged Services and
          Protocols for Advanced Networks (TISPAN),Network Attachment
          Sub-System (NASS),e4 interface based on the Diameter
          protocol.</title>

          <author fullname="ETSI" surname="ETSI">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date month="September" year="2008" />
        </front>
      </reference>

      &RFC4005;
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      &RFC6241;

      &RFC6146;

      &RFC6145;

      &RFC3411;

      &RFC3022;

      &I-D.draft-ietf-behave-lsn-requirements;

      &RFC5189;

      &RFC3550;

      &RFC2663;

      &RFC3303;

      &RFC3304;

      &RFC4097;

      &RFC1661;
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
