<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY HUIHAI PUBLIC ''
'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml'> 
<!ENTITY RFC2234 PUBLIC ''
'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2234.xml'>     
<!ENTITY RFC3588 PUBLIC ''
'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3588.xml'>     
<!ENTITY RFC5226 PUBLIC ''
'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5226.xml'> 
<!ENTITY RFC4005 PUBLIC ''
'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4005.xml'> 
<!ENTITY RFC4004 PUBLIC ''
'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4004.xml'> 
<!ENTITY RFC4072 PUBLIC ''
'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4072.xml'> 
<!ENTITY RFC4301 PUBLIC ''
'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4301.xml'> 
<!ENTITY RFC4303 PUBLIC ''
'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4303.xml'> 
<!ENTITY RFC5447 PUBLIC ''
'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5447.xml'>
<!ENTITY I-D.ietf-dime-mip6-split PUBLIC ''
'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-dime-mip6-split.xml'>
<!ENTITY RFC3748 PUBLIC ''
'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3748.xml'> 
<!ENTITY RFC2136 PUBLIC ''
'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2136.xml'> 
<!ENTITY RFC1035 PUBLIC ''
'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1035.xml'> 
<!ENTITY I-D.ietf-netlmm-pmip6-ipv4-support PUBLIC ''
'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-netlmm-pmip6-ipv4-support.xml'>
<!ENTITY RFC4186 PUBLIC ''
'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4186.xml'> 
<!ENTITY RFC4282 PUBLIC ''
'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4282.xml'> 
<!ENTITY RFC4283 PUBLIC ''
'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4283.xml'> 
<!ENTITY RFC2132 PUBLIC ''
'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2132.xml'> 
<!ENTITY RFC3775 PUBLIC ''
'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3775.xml'> 
<!ENTITY I-D.ietf-mip6-nemo-v4traversal PUBLIC ''
'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-mip6-nemo-v4traversal.xml'>
<!ENTITY RFC5213 PUBLIC ''
'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5213.xml'>
<!ENTITY RFC2131 PUBLIC ''
'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2131.xml'>
<!ENTITY RFC3315 PUBLIC ''
'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3315.xml'>
<!ENTITY I-D.ietf-mext-binding-revocation PUBLIC ''
'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-mext-binding-revocation.xml'>
<!ENTITY I-D.ietf-netlmm-lma-discovery PUBLIC ''
'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-netlmm-lma-discovery.xml'>
<!ENTITY RFC5149 PUBLIC ''
'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5149.xml'>
<!ENTITY RFC3580 PUBLIC ''
'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3580.xml'>
]>


<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc iprnotified="no" ?>
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<?rfc autobreaks="yes" ?>

<rfc category="std" ipr="trust200902" docName="draft-ietf-dime-pmip6-04.txt">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="Diameter Support for Proxy Mobile IPv6">Diameter Proxy Mobile IPv6:
      Mobile Access Gateway and Local Mobility Anchor Interaction with Diameter Server
    </title>

    <author role="editor" initials="J" surname="Korhonen" fullname="Jouni Korhonen">
      <organization>Nokia Siemens Network</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Linnoitustie 6</street>
          <city>Espoo</city>
          <code>FI-02600</code>
          <country>Finland</country>
        </postal>
        <email>jouni.nospam@gmail.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Julien Bournelle" surname="Bournelle" initials="J.">
      <organization>Orange Labs</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>38-4O rue du general Leclerc</street>
          <city>Issy-Les-Moulineaux</city>
          <code>92794</code>
          <country>France</country>
        </postal>
        <email>julien.bournelle@orange-ftgroup.com</email>
      </address>
    </author> 

    <author initials="K." surname="Chowdhury" fullname="Kuntal Chowdhury">
      <organization>Starent Networks</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>30 International Place</street>
          <city>Tewksbury</city>
          <code>MA  01876</code>
          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>
        <email>kchowdhury@starentnetworks.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author initials="A" surname="Muhanna" fullname="Ahmad Muhanna">
      <organization abbrev="">Nortel</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>2221 Lakeside Blvd.</street>
          <city>Richardson</city>
          <region>TX</region> 
          <code>75082</code>
          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>
        <email>amuhanna@nortel.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>    
      <author initials="U." surname="Meyer" fullname="Ulrike Meyer">
         <organization>RWTH Aachen</organization>
         <address>
                <email>meyer@umic.rwth-aachen.de</email>
            </address>
      </author>


    <date year="2009"/>
    <area>Operations and Management</area>
    <workgroup>Diameter Maintenance and Extensions (DIME)</workgroup>
    <keyword>Internet-Draft</keyword>
    <keyword>Diameter</keyword>
    <keyword>Proxy Mobile IPv6</keyword>
    <abstract>

      <t>This specification defines Authentication, Authorization, and
         Accounting interactions between Proxy Mobile IPv6 entities (both
         Mobile Access Gateway and Local Mobility Anchor) and
         an Authentication, Authorization, and
         Accounting server within a Proxy Mobile IPv6 Domain.
         These Authentication, Authorization, and
         Accounting interactions are primarily used to download and update mobile
         node specific policy profile information between Proxy Mobile IPv6
         entities and a remote policy store.
      </t>


    </abstract>
    </front>

    <middle>
    <!-- ====================================================================== -->

    <section anchor="introduction" title="Introduction">
      <t>This specification defines Authentication, Authorization, and
         Accounting (AAA) interactions between a Mobile Access  Gateway (MAG)
         and an AAA server, and between a Local  Mobility Anchor  (LMA) and an
         AAA server within a Proxy Mobile IPv6 (PMIPv6) Domain <xref target="RFC5213"/>.
         These AAA interactions are primarily used to download and update mobile
         node (MN) specific policy profile information between PMIPv6 entities
         (a MAG and a LMA) and a remote policy store.
      </t>
      <t>Dynamic assignment and downloading of MN's
         policy profile information to a MAG from a remote policy store is a
         desirable feature to ease the deployment and network  maintenance of
         larger PMIPv6 domains.  For this purpose, the same AAA infrastructure
         that is used for authenticating and authorizing the MN for a network
         access, can be leveraged to download some or all of the necessary
         policy profile information to the MAG.
      </t> 
      <t>Once the network has authenticated the MN, the MAG sends a
         Proxy Binding Update (PBU) to the LMA in order to setup a mobility
         session on behalf of the MN. When the LMA receives the
         PBU, the LMA may need to authorize the received PBU against the
         AAA infrastructure. The same AAA infrastructure that can be used for the 
         authorization of the PBU, is also used to update the remote policy
         store with the LMA provided MN specific mobility session related
         information.
      </t>
      <t>In the context of this specification the 
         home AAA server (HAAA) functionality is co-located with the remote
         policy store. The NAS functionality may be co-located with the MAG
         function in the network access router. Diameter <xref target="RFC3588"/>
         is the used AAA protocol.
      </t>

    </section>   <!-- introduction -->

    <!-- ========================================================= -->

    <section anchor="terms" title="Terminology and Abbreviations">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL
         NOT",  "SHOULD",  "SHOULD  NOT",  "RECOMMENDED",  "MAY",  and
         "OPTIONAL"  in  this  document   are  to  be  interpreted  as
         described in RFC2119 <xref target="RFC2119"/>.
      </t>

      <t>The general terminology used in this document can be found in
         <xref target="RFC5213"/> and <xref target="I-D.ietf-netlmm-pmip6-ipv4-support"/>.
         The following  additional  or clarified
         terms are also used in this document:
      </t>

      <t><list style="hanging">

        <t hangText="Network Access Server (NAS):">
           <vspace blankLines="1"/>A device that provides an access service for a
           user to a network. In the context of this document the NAS may be
	   integrated into or co-located to a MAG. The NAS contains a Diameter
	   client function.
           <vspace blankLines="1"/>
        </t>

        <t hangText="Home AAA (HAAA):">
           <vspace blankLines="1"/> An Authentication, Authorization, and 
           Accounting (AAA) server located in user's home network. A HAAA is
	       essentially a Diameter server.
           <vspace blankLines="1"/>
        </t>
      </list></t> 
    </section>
 
    <section title="Solution Overview">
      <t>This document addresses the AAA interactions and AAA-based session
         management functionality needed in the
         PMIPv6 Domain. This document defines Diameter based AAA interactions 
         between the MAG and the HAAA, and between the LMA and the HAAA. 
      </t>

      <t>The policy profile is downloaded from the HAAA to the MAG
         during the MN attachment to the PMIPv6 Domain.
         <xref   target="pmip6-scenario"/>  shows  the
         participating network entities. This document, however, 
         concentrates on the MAG, LMA, and
         the HAAA (the home Diameter server).
      </t>

            
      <t><figure anchor="pmip6-scenario" title="Proxy Mobile IPv6 Domain
         Interaction with Diameter HAAA Server">
<artwork><![CDATA[
 +--------+
 | HAAA & | Diameter +-----+
 | Policy |<---(2)-->| LMA |
 | Store  |          +-----+
 +--------+             | <--- LMA-Address
      ^                 |
      |               // \\
  +---|------------- //---\\----------------+
 (    |  IPv4/IPv6  //     \\                )
 (    |   Network  //       \\               )
  +---|-----------//---------\\-------------+
      |          //           \\
  Diameter      // <- Tunnel1  \\ <- Tunnel2
     (1)       //               \\
      |        |- MAG1-Address   |- MAG2-Address
      |     +----+             +----+
      +---->|MAG1|             |MAG2|
            +----+             +----+ 
               |                 |
               |                 |
             [MN1]             [MN2]

  Legend:

    (1): MAG-to-HAAA interaction is described
         in Section 7.1
    (2): LMA-to-HAAA interaction is described
         in Section 7.2
]]></artwork>
      </figure></t>
      <t>When  a MN attaches to a PMIPv6 Domain, a
         network access  authentication  procedure is usually started. The
         choice  of the  authentication mechanism  is specific  to the
         access network deployment, but  could be based on the
         Extensible     Authentication     Protocol    (EAP)     <xref
         target="RFC3748"/>. During  the network access authentication
         procedure, the MAG  acting as a NAS queries  the HAAA through
         the AAA  infrastructure using  the Diameter protocol.  If the
         HAAA detects  that the subscriber is also  authorized for the
         PMIPv6 service,  PMIPv6 specific information is returned
         along with the successful
         network access authentication answer to the MAG.
      </t>

      <t>After the MN  has been successfully authenticated, the MAG
         sends a PBU to the LMA based on the MN's policy profile information.
         Upon receiving the PBU the LMA interacts
         with the HAAA and fetches the relevant parts of the subscriber policy
         profile and authorization
         information related to the mobility service session.
         In this specification, the HAAA has the role of the PMIPv6
         remote policy store.
      </t>
    </section> <!-- overview -->
  
    <!-- ====================================================================== -->
  
    <section anchor="cmds" title="Generic Application Support and Command Codes">

        <t>This specification does not define new Application-IDs or Command
           Codes for
           the MAG-to-HAAA or for the LMA-to-HAAA Diameter connections. Rather,
           this specification is generic to any Diameter application (and their
           commands) that is suitable for a network access authentication and
           authorization.
           Example applications include NASREQ <xref target="RFC4005"/> 
           and EAP <xref target="RFC4072"/>.
        </t>

      <section title="MAG-to-HAAA Interface">
        <t>The MAG-to-HAAA interactions are primarily used for 
           bootstrapping PMIPv6 mobility service session when
           a MN attaches and authenticates to a PMIPv6 Domain.
           This includes the bootstrapping of PMIPv6 session
           related information. The same interface
           may also be used for accounting. The MAG acts as a Diameter client.

        </t>

        <t>Whenever the MAG sends a Diameter request message to the HAAA, the
           User-Name AVP SHOULD contain the MN's identity unless the identity
           is being suppressed for policy reasons - for example, when identity
           hiding is in effect. The MN identity, if
           available, MUST be in Network Access Identifier (NAI) <xref
           target="RFC4282"/> format. At minimum
           the home realm of the MN MUST be available at the MAG when
           the network access authentication takes place. Otherwise
           the MAG is not able to route the Diameter request messages
           towards the correct HAAA. The MN identity used on the MAG-to-HAAA
           interface and in the User-Name AVP MAY entirely be related to the
           network access authentication, and therefore not suitable to be
           used as the MN-ID mobility option value in the subsequent PBU/PBA
           messages. See the related discussion on MN's identities in
           <xref target="mnid"/> and in <xref target="l2hmnid"/>.
        </t>
        <t>For the session management and service authorization purposes,
           session state SHOULD be maintained on the MAG-to-HAAA interface.
           See the discussion in <xref target="sersel"/>.
        </t>

      </section> <!-- command codes -->

      <section title="LMA-to-HAAA Interface" anchor="l2hmnid">
        <t>The-LMA-to HAAA interface may be used for multiple
           purposes. These include the authorization of the incoming
           PBU, updating the LMA address to the HAAA, delegating the assignment
           of the MN-HNP or the IPv4-HoA to the HAAA, and for
           accounting and PMIPv6 session management. The primary purpose of
           this interface is to update the HAAA with the LMA address information
           in case of dynamically assigned LMA, and exchange the MN address
           assignment information between the LMA and the HAAA.
        </t>
        <t>The LMA-to-HAAA interface description is intended for different
           types of deployments and architectures. Therefore, this specification
           only outlines AVPs and considerations that the deployment specific
           Diameter applications need to take into account from the PMIPv6 and
           LMAs point of view.
        </t>
        <section title="General Operation and Authorization of PBU">
          <t>Whenever the LMA sends a Diameter request message to the HAAA, the
             User-Name AVP SHOULD contain the MN's identity. The LMA provided
             identity in the User-Name AVP is strongly RECOMMENDED to be the
             same as the MN's
             identity information in the PBU MN-ID <xref target="RFC4283"/>
             <xref target="RFC5213"/> mobility option. The identity SHOULD also
             be the same as used on the MAG-to-HAAA interface, but in the case
             those identities differ the HAAA MUST have a mechanism of mapping
             the MN identity used on the MAG-to-HAAA interface to the identity
             used on the LMA-to-HAAA interface.
          </t>
          <t>If the PBU contains the MN Link-Layer Identifier option,
             the Calling-Station-Id AVP SHOULD be included in the request
             message containing the received Link-Layer Identifier. Furthermore,
             if the PBU contains the Service Selection mobility option
             <xref target="RFC5149"/>, the  Service-Selection AVP SHOULD be
             included in the request message containing the received service
             identifier. Both MN Link-Layer Identifier and the Service selection
             can be used to provide more information for the PBU authorization
             step in the HAAA.
          </t>
          <t>The Auth-Request-Type AVP MUST be set to the value AUTHORIZE_ONLY.
             The Diameter session related aspects discussed in
             <xref target="session"/> need to be taken into consideration when
             designing the Diameter application for the LMA-to-HAAA interface.
             If the HAAA is not able to authorize the subscriber's mobility
             service session, then the reply
             message to the LMA MUST have the Result-Code AVP set to
             value DIAMETER_AUTHORIZATION_REJECTED (5003) indicating
             a permanent failure. A failed authorization obviously results to a
             rejection of the PBU and a PBA with an appropriate error Status
             Value MUST be sent back to the MAG.
          </t>
          <t>The authorization step MUST be performed at
             least for the initial PBU session up a mobility session, when the
             LMA-to-HAAA interface is deployed. For the subsequent re-registration
             and handover PBUs, the authorization step MAY be repeated (in this
             case, the LMA-to-HAAA interface should also maintain an authorization
             session state).
          </t>
        </section>
        <section title="Updating LMA Address to HAAA">
          <t>In case of a dynamic LMA  discovery and assignment
             <xref target="I-D.ietf-netlmm-lma-discovery"/> the HAAA and the
             remote policy store may need to be updated with the selected LMA
             address information. The update can be done during the PBU
             authorization step using the LMA-to-HAAA interface. This specification
             uses the MIP6-Agent-Info AVP and its MIP-Home-Agent-Address and
             MIP-Home-Agent-Host sub-AVPs for carrying the LMA's address information
             from the LMA to the HAAA. The LMA address information in the request
             message MUST contain the IP address of the LMA or the FQDN identifying
             uniquely the LMA, or both. The LMA address information
             refers to PMIPv6 part of the LMA, not necessarily the LMA part
             interfacing with the AAA infrastructure.
          </t>
          <t>This specification does not define any HAAA initiated LMA relocation
             functionality. Therefore, when the MIP6-Agent-Info AVP is included
             in Diameter answer messages sent from the HAAA to the LMA,
             the HAAA indicates this by setting the MIP-Home-Agent-Address AVP
             to all zeroes address (e.g., 0::0) and not including the
             MIP-Home-Agent-Host AVP.
          </t>
        </section>
        <section title="Mobile Node Address Update and Assignment">
          <t>The LMA and the HAAA use the MIP6-Home-Link-Prefix AVP to
             exchange the MN-HNP when appropriate. Similarly, the LMA and the HAAA
             use the PMIP6-IPv4-Home-Address AVP to exchange the IPv4-MN-HoA
             when appropriate. These AVPs are encapsulated inside
             the MIP6-Agent-Info AVP. The MN address information exchange is
             again done during the PBU authorization step. The HAAA MAY also
             use the LMA provided MN address information as a part of the
             information used to authorize the PBU.
          </t>
          <t>Which entity is actually responsible for the address management
             is deployment specific within the PMIPv6 Domain and MUST be
             pre-agreed on per deployment basis. When the LMA is responsible
             for the address management, the MIP6-Agent-Info AVP is used to
             inform the HAAA and the remote policy store of the MN-HNP/IPv4-MN-HoA
             assigned to the MN. 
          </t>
          <t>It is also possible that the LMA delegates the
             address management to the HAAA. In this case, the MN-HNP/IPv4-MN-HoA
             are set to undefined addresses (as described in <xref target="info"/>)
             in the Diameter request message sent from the LMA to the HAAA. The LMA
             expects to receive the HAAA assigned HNP/IPv4-MN-HoA in the
             corresponding Diameter answer message.
          </t>
         </section>
        <!--/section-->
      </section>
    </section>
  
    <!-- ====================================================================== -->

    <section title="Attribute Value Pair Definitions">
      <t>This section describes Attribute Value Pairs (AVPs) defined by this
         specification or re-used from existing specifications in a PMIPv6
         specific way. Derived Diameter AVP Data Formats such as Address and
         UTF8String are defined in Section 4.3 of RFC 3588. Grouped AVP values
         are defined in Section 4.4 of RFC 3588.
      </t>

      <section title="MIP6-Agent-Info AVP" anchor="info">
        <t>The MIP6-Agent-Info grouped AVP (AVP Code 486) is defined in <xref
           target="RFC5447"/>. The AVP is used to carry 
           LMA addressing related information and a MN-HNP. This
           specification extends the MIP6-Agent-Info with the
           PMIP6-IPv4-Home-Address AVP using the Diameter
           extensibility rules defined in <xref target="RFC3588"/>.
           The PMIP6-IPv4-Home-Address AVP contains the IPv4-MN-HoA. 
        </t>
        <t>The extended MIP6-Agent-Info AVP results to the following grouped AVP:
        </t>
        <figure><artwork><![CDATA[
    MIP6-Agent-Info ::= < AVP-Header: 486 >
                      *2[ MIP-Home-Agent-Address ]
                        [ MIP-Home-Agent-Host ]
                        [ MIP6-Home-Link-Prefix ]
                        [ PMIP6-IPv4-Home-Address ]
                      * [ AVP ]
]]></artwork>
        </figure>  
        <t>If the MIP-Home-Agent-Address is set to all zeroes address (e.g., 0::0),
           the receiver of the MIP6-Agent-Info AVP MUST ignore the
           MIP-Home-Agent-Address AVP.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section title="PMIP6-IPv4-Home-Address AVP">
        <t>The PMIP6-IPv4-Home-Address AVP (AVP Code TBD2) is of type Address
           and contains an IPv4 address. This AVP is used to carry
           the IPv4-MN-HoA, if available, from the HAAA to the MAG.
           This AVP SHOULD only be present when the MN is statically provisioned
           with the IPv4-MN-HoA. Note that proactive dynamic assignment of the
           IPv4-MN-HoA by the HAAA may result in unnecessary reservation of
           IPv4 address resources, because the MN may considerably delay or completely
           bypass its IPv4 address configuration.
        </t>
        <t>The PMIP6-IPv4-Home-Address  AVP is also  used on the LMA-to-HAAA
           interface. The AVP contains the IPv4-MN-HoA
           assigned to the MN. If the LMA
           delegates the assignment of the IPv4-MN-HoA to the HAAA,
           the AVP MUST contain all zeroes IPv4 address (i.e., 0.0.0.0) in the
           request message. If the LMA delegated the IPv4-MN-HoA           assignment to the HAAA, then the AVP contains the           HAAA assigned IPv4-MN-HoA in the response message.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section title="MIP6-Home-Link-Prefix AVP" anchor="MIP6-Home-Link-Prefix">
        <t>The MIP6-Home-Link-Prefix  AVP  (AVP  Code  125)  is  defined
           in <xref target="RFC5447"/>. This AVP is
           used to carry the MN-HNP, if available, from the HAAA to the MAG.
           The low 64 bits of the prefix  MUST be all zeroes.
        </t>
        <t>The  MIP6-Home-Link-Prefix  AVP  is also  used on the LMA-to-HAAA
           interface. The AVP contains the
           prefix assigned to the MN. If the LMA
           delegates the assignment of the MN-HNP to the HAAA,
           the AVP MUST contain all zeroes address (i.e., 0::0) in the
           request message. If the LMA delegated the MN-HNP           assignment to the HAAA, then the AVP contains the           HAAA assigned MNM-HNP in the response message.
        </t>

      </section>

      <section title="PMIP6-DHCP-Server-Address AVP">
        <t>The PMIP6-DHCP-Server-Address AVP (AVP Code TBD1) is of type Address
           and contains the IP address of the Dynamic Host Configuration Protocol
           (DHCP) server assigned to the MAG serving the newly attached MN. If
           the AVP contains a DHCPv4 <xref target="RFC2131"/> server
           address, then the Address type MUST be IPv4. If the AVP contains a
           DHCPv6 <xref target="RFC3315"/> server address, then the Address type
           MUST be IPv6. The HAAA MAY assign a DHCP server to the MAG in
           deployments where the MAG acts as a DHCP Relay
           <xref target="I-D.ietf-netlmm-pmip6-ipv4-support"/>. 
        </t>
      </section>
      
      <section title="MIP6-Feature-Vector AVP" anchor="capability">
        <t>The MIP6-Feature-Vector AVP  is originally defined in <xref
           target="RFC5447"/>.   This  document
           defines new capability flag bits according to the IANA rules in
           RFC 5447.
        </t>
        <t><list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="PMIP6_SUPPORTED (0x0000010000000000)">
             <vspace blankLines="1"/> When the MAG/NAS sets this
             bit in the MIP6-Feature-Vector AVP, it is an indication
             to the HAAA that the NAS supports PMIPv6. When the
             HAAA sets this bit in the response MIP6-Feature-Vector AVP, it
             indicates that the HAAA also has PMIPv6 support. This
             capability bit can also be used to allow PMIPv6 mobility
             support in a subscription granularity. 
             <vspace blankLines="1"/>
          </t>

          <t hangText="IP4_HOA_SUPPORTED (0x0000020000000000)">
             <vspace blankLines="1"/> Assignment of the
             IPv4-MN-HoA is supported. When the MAG sets this
             bit in the MIP6-Feature-Vector AVP, it indicates that the MAG
             implements a minimal functionality of a DHCP server (and a
             relay) and is able to deliver IPv4-MN-HoA to the MN. When the
             HAAA sets this bit in the response MIP6-Feature-Vector AVP, it
             indicates that the HAAA has authorized the use of IPv4-MN-HoA
             for the MN. If this bit is unset in the returned
             MIP6-Feature-Vector AVP, the HAAA does not authorize the
             configuration of IPv4 address.
             <vspace blankLines="1"/>
          </t>

          <t hangText="LOCAL_MAG_ROUTING_SUPPORTED (0x0000040000000000)">
             <vspace blankLines="1"/>Direct routing of IP packets
             between MNs anchored to the same MAG is supported. When a
             MAG sets this bit in the MIP6-Feature-Vector, it indicates
             that  routing IP  packets between  MNs anchored  to the
             same  MAG  is   supported,  without  reverse  tunneling
             packets via the LMA or requiring any Route Optimization 
             related signaling (e.g. the Return Routability Procedure in
             <xref target="RFC3775"/>) prior direct routing.  If this
             bit is cleared in the returned MIP6-Feature-Vector AVP, the
             HAAA does not authorize direct routing of packets between
             MNs anchored to the same MAG. The MAG SHOULD support this policy
             feature per-MN and per-subscription basis.
             <vspace blankLines="1"/>
          </t>

        </list></t>
        <t>The MIP6-Feature-Vector AVP is also used on 
           the LMA to HAAA interface.
           Using the capability announcement AVP it is possible
           to perform a simple capability negotiation between the LMA and
           the HAAA. Those capabilities that are announced by both parties
           are also known to be mutually supported. The capabilities
           listed in earlier are also supported
           in the LMA to HAAA interface. The LMA to HAAA interface
           does not define any new capability values.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section title="Mobile-Node-Identifier AVP" anchor="mnid">
        <t>The Mobile-Node-Identifier AVP (AVP Code TBD3) is of type
           UTF8String and contains the
           mobile node identifier (MN-Identifier, see <xref
           target="RFC5213"/>) in the NAI <xref target="RFC4282"/>
           format. This AVP is used on the MAG-to-HAAA interface. The
           Mobile-Node-Identifier AV is designed for
           deployments where the MAG does not have a way to
           find out such MN identity that could be used in subsequent
           PBU/PBA exchanges (e.g., due to identity hiding during the
           network access authentication) or the HAAA wants to assign
           periodically changing identities to the MN.
        </t>
        <t>The Mobile-Node-Identifier AVP is returned in the answer message
           that ends a successful authentication (and possibly an
           authorization) exchange between the MAG and the HAAA,
           assuming the HAAA is also able to provide the MAG with the
           MN-Identifier in the first place. The
           MAG MUST use the received MN-Identifier, if it has not been
           able to get the mobile node identifier through other means.
           If the MAG already has a valid mobile node identifier, then
           the MAG MUST silently discard the received 
           MN-identifier. 
        </t>
      </section>

      <section title="Calling-Station-Id AVP">
        <t>The Calling-Station-Id AVP (AVP Code 31) is of type UTF8String and
           contains a Link-Layer Identifier of the MN.  This  
           identifier corresponds to the Link-Layer Identifier as defined in
           RFC 5213 Section 2.2 and 8.6. The Link-Layer Identifier is encoded
           in ASCII format (upper case only), with octet values separated by a
           "-". Example: "00-23-32-C9-79-38". The encoding is actually the
           same as the MAC address encoding in Section 3.21 of RFC 3580.
           
        </t>
      </section>
      <section title="Service-Selection AVP" anchor="sersel">
        <t>The Service-Selection AVP (AVP Code 493) is of type UTF8String and
           contains a LMA provided service identifier on the LMA-to-HAAA
           interface. This AVP is re-used from <xref
           target="I-D.ietf-dime-mip6-split"/>. The service identifier may be used to assist the
           PBU authorization and the assignment of the MN-HNP and the IPv4-MN-HoA
           as described in RFC 5149 <xref target="RFC5149"/>.  The identifier MUST
           be unique within the PMIPv6 Domain. In the absence of the
           Service-Selection AVP in the request message, the HAAA may want 
           to inform the LMA
           of the default service provisioned to the MN and
           include the Service-Selection AVP in the response message.
        </t>
        <t>It is also possible that the MAG receives the service selection
           information from the MN, for example, via some lower layer mechanism.
           In this case the MAG MUST include the Service-Selection AVP also
           in the MAG-to-HAAA request messages. In absence of the Service-Selection AVP
           in the MAG-to-HAAA request messages, the HAAA may want to inform the MAG
           of the default service provisioned to the MN and
           include the Service-Selection AVP in the response message. 
        </t>
        <t>Whenever the Service-Selection AVP is included either in a request
           message or in a response message, and the AAA interaction with 
           HAAA completes successfully, it is an indication that
           the HAAA also authorized the MN to some service. This should be
           taken into account when considering what to include in the
           Auth-Request-Type AVP.
        </t>
        <t>The service selection concept supports signaling one service at
           time. However, the MN policy profile MAY support multiple services
           being used simultaneously. For this purpose, the HAAA MAY return
           multiple LMA and service pairs (see <xref target="conf"/>) to the
           MAG in a response message that ends a successful authentication
           (and possibly an authorization) exchange between the MAG and the
           HAAA. Whenever the MN initiates additional mobility session to
           another service (using a link layer or deployment specific method),
           the provisioned service information is already contained in the MAG.
           Therefore, there is no need for additional AAA signaling between
           the MAG and the HAAA.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section title="Service-Configuration AVP" anchor="conf">
        <t>The Service-Configuration AVP (AVP Code TBD4) is of type Grouped and
           contains a service and a LMA pair. The HAAA can use this AVP 
           to inform the MAG of MN's subscribed services and LMAs where those
           services are hosted in.  
        </t>
        <figure><artwork><![CDATA[
    Service-Configuration ::= < AVP-Header: TBD4 >
                              [ MIP6-Agent-Info ]
                              [ Service-Selection ]
                            * [ AVP ]
]]></artwork>
        </figure>  
      </section>
    </section>


    <!-- ========================================================= -->

    <section title="Proxy Mobile IPv6 Session Management" anchor="session">
      <t>Concerning  a  PMIPv6  mobility session,   the  HAAA,
         the MAG and the LMA Diameter entities SHOULD be stateful and
         maintain the corresponding Authorization Session State Machine
         defined in <xref target="RFC3588"/>. If a state is maintained,
         then a PMIPv6 mobility session that can be identified by any
         of the Binding Cache (BCE) Lookup Keys described in RFC 5213
         (see Sections 5.4.1.1., 5.4.1.2. and 5.4.1.3.) MUST
         map to a single Diameter Session-Id. If the PMIPv6 Domain allows
         further separation of sessions, for example, identified
         by the RFC 5213 BCE Lookup Keys and the service selection
         combination (see <xref target="sersel"/> and <xref target="RFC5149"/>),
         then a single Diameter Session-Id MUST map to a PMIPv6 mobility
         session identified by the RFC 5213 BCE Lookup Keys and the
         selected service.
      </t>
      <t>If both the MAG-to-HAAA and the LMA-to-HAAA interfaces are
         deployed in a PMIPv6 Domain, and a state is maintained on
         both interfaces, then one PMIPv6 mobility session would have
         two distinct Diameter sessions on the HAAA. The HAAA needs
         to be aware of this deployment possibility and SHOULD allow
         multiple
         Diameter sessions for the same PMIPv6 mobility session.
      </t>
      <t>
         Diameter session termination related commands described in
         the following sections may be exchanged between the LMA and
         the HAAA, or between the MAG and the HAAA. 
         The actual PMIPv6 session termination procedures take place
         at PMIPv6 protocol level and are described in more detail in
         RFC 5213 and <xref target="I-D.ietf-mext-binding-revocation"/>. 
      </t>

      <section title="Session-Termination-Request">
        <t>The LMA or the MAG MAY send the Session-Termination-Request
           (STR) command <xref target="RFC3588"/> to inform the HAAA that the
           termination of an ongoing PMIPv6 session is in progress. 
        </t>
      </section>

      <section title="Session-Termination-Answer">
        <t>The Session-Termination-Answer (STA) <xref
           target="RFC3588"/> is sent by the HAAA to
           acknowledge the termination of a PMIPv6 session.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section title="Abort-Session-Request">
        <t>The HAAA MAY send the Abort-Session-Request (ASR) command
           <xref target="RFC3588"/> to the LMA or to the MAG and
           request termination of a PMIPv6 session.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section title="Abort-Session-Answer">
        <t>The Abort-Session-Answer (ASA) command <xref
           target="RFC3588"/>is sent by the LMA or the MAG to
           acknowledge that the termination of a PMIPv6 session.
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>



    <!-- ====================================================================== -->
      
    <section title="Attribute Value Pair Occurrence Tables">
      <t>The following tables list the PMIPv6 MAG-to-HAAA interface and
         LMA-to-HAAA interface AVPs including those that are defined in
         <xref target="RFC5447"/>.
      </t>

      <t>The <xref target="magavptable"/> contains the AVPs and
         their occurrences on the MAG-to-HAAA interface. The AVPs that
         are part of grouped AVP are not listed in the table, rather
         only the grouped AVP is listed.
      </t>

      <section title="MAG-to-HAAA Interface" anchor="magavpsection">

      <t><figure anchor="magavptable" title="MAG-to-HAAA Interface
      Generic Diameter Request and Answer Commands AVPs">
<artwork><![CDATA[
                                  +---------------+
                                  |  Command-Code |
                                  |-------+-------+
   Attribute Name                 |  REQ  |  ANS  |
   -------------------------------+-------+-------+
   PMIP6-DHCP-Server-Address      |   0   |  0+   |
   MIP6-Agent-Info                |  0+   |  0+   |
   MIP6-Feature-Vector            |  0-1  |  0-1  |
   Mobile-Node-Identifier         |  0-1  |  0-1  |
   Calling-Station-Id             |  0-1  |   0   |
   Service-Selection              |  0-1  |   0   |
   Service-Configuration          |   0   |  0+   |
                                  +-------+-------+
]]></artwork>
      </figure>
      </t>
      </section>

      <section title="LMA-to-HAAA Interface" anchor="lmaavpsection">

      <t><figure anchor="lmaavptable" title="LMA-to-HAAA Interface
      Generic Diameter Request and Answer Commands AVPs">
<artwork><![CDATA[
                                  +---------------+
                                  |  Command-Code |
                                  |-------+-------+
   Attribute Name                 |  REQ  |  ANS  |
   -------------------------------+-------+-------+
   MIP6-Agent-Info                |  0-1  |  0-1  |
   MIP6-Feature-Vector            |  0-1  |  0-1  |
   Calling-Station-Id             |  0-1  |   0   |
   Service-Selection              |  0-1  |  0-1  |
   User-Name                      |  0-1  |  0-1  |
                                  +-------+-------+
]]></artwork>
      </figure>
      </t>

      </section>
    </section>

    <!-- ====================================================================== -->

    <section title="Example Signaling Flows">
      <t><xref target="example1"/> shows a signaling flow example during PMIPv6         bootstrapping using the AAA interactions defined in this         specification.  In step (1) of this example, the MN is authenticated to
         PMIPv6 Domain using EAP-based authentication. The MAG to the HAAA signaling
         uses the Diameter EAP Application. During step (2), the LMA uses Diameter         NASREQ application to authorize the MN with the HAAA server.
      </t>
      <t>The MAG-to-HAAA AVPs, as listed in <xref target="magavpsection"/> 
         are used during step (1). These AVPs are included only in the Diameter
         EAP Request (DER) message which starts the EAP exchange and in the
         corresponding Diameter EAP Answer (DEA)
         message which successfully completes this EAP exchange. The LMA-to-HAAA
         AVPs, as listed in <xref target="lmaavpsection"/>, are used         during step (2). Step (2) is used to authorize the MN request for the         mobility service and update the HAAA server with the assigned LMA
         information. In addition, this step may be used to dynamically assist
         in the assignment of the MN-HNP.
      </t>
      <t><figure title="MAG and LMA Signaling Interaction with AAA server duringPMIPv6 bootstrapping" anchor="example1">
<artwork><![CDATA[
MN                 MAG/NAS                LMA                  HAAA  
|                     |                    |                    |
| L2 attach           |                    |                    |
|-------------------->|                    |                    |
| EAP/req-identity    |                    |                    |
|<--------------------|                    |                    |
| EAP/res-identity    | DER + MAG-to-HAAA AVPs                  | s
|-------------------->|---------------------------------------->| t
| EAP/req #1          | DEA (EAP request #1)                    | e
|<--------------------|<----------------------------------------| p
| EAP/res #2          | DER (EAP response #2)                   |
|-------------------->|---------------------------------------->| 1
:                     :                    :                    :
:                     :                    :                    :
| EAP/res #N          | DER (EAP response #N)                   |
|-------------------->|---------------------------------------->|
| EAP/success         | DEA (EAP success) + MAG-to-HAAA AVPs    |
|<--------------------|<----------------------------------------|
:                     :                    :                    :
:                     :                    :                    :
|                     | PMIPv6 PBU         | AAR +              | s
|                     |------------------->| LMA-to-HAAA AVPs   | t
|                     |                    |------------------->| e
|                     |                    | AAA +              | p
|                     |                    | LMA-to-HAAA AVPs   |
|                     | PMIPv6 PBA         |<-------------------| 2
| RA                  |<-------------------|                    |
|<--------------------|                    |                    |
:                     :                    :                    :
:                     :                    :                    :
| IP connectivity     | PMIPv6 tunnel up   |                    |
|---------------------|====================|                    |
|                     |                    |                    |
]]></artwork>
      </figure>
      </t>
    </section>



    <!-- ====================================================================== -->

    <section title="IANA Considerations">
      <section title="Attribute Value Pair Codes">
        <t>This specification defines the following new AVPs:

<figure><artwork><![CDATA[
  PMIP6-DHCP-Server-Address   is set to TBD1
  PMIP6-IPv4-Home-Address     is set to TBD2
  Mobile-Node-Identifier      is set to TBD3
  Service-Configuration       is set to TBD4
]]></artwork></figure></t>
      </section>

      <section title="Namespaces">
        <t>This specification defines new values to the Mobility 
           Capability registry (see <xref
           target="RFC5447"/>)
           for use with the MIP6-Feature-Vector
           AVP: 

<figure><artwork><![CDATA[
Token                            | Value                | Description
---------------------------------+----------------------+------------
PMIP6_SUPPORTED                  | 0x0000010000000000   | [RFC TBD]
IP4_HOA_SUPPORTED                | 0x0000020000000000   | [RFC TBD]
LOCAL_MAG_ROUTING_SUPPORTED      | 0x0000040000000000   | [RFC TBD]
]]></artwork></figure>
        </t>
      </section>
      <!--section title="Result-Code AVP Values">
        <t>This specification requests IANA to allocate a new value to
           the Result-Code AVP (AVP Code 268) address space within the Permanent
           Failures category (5xxx) defined in <xref target="RFC3588"/>:
<figure><artwork><![CDATA[
  DIAMETER_PMIP6_AUTHORIZATION_FAILED  is set to TBD5
]]></artwork></figure>
        </t>
      </section-->
    </section>

    <!-- ====================================================================== -->

    <section title="Security Considerations">
      <t>The security considerations of the Diameter Base protocol <xref
         target="RFC3588"/>, Diameter EAP application <xref target="RFC4072"/>,
         Diameter NASREQ application <xref target="RFC4005"/>
         and Diameter Mobile IPv6 integrated scenario bootstrapping <xref
         target="RFC5447"/> are applicable to this document.
      </t>
      <t>In general, the Diameter messages may be transported between the LMA and the
         Diameter server via one or more AAA brokers or Diameter agents.  In
         this case the LMA to the Diameter server AAA communication rely on the
         security properties of the intermediate AAA brokers and Diameter
         agents (such as proxies).
      </t>
    </section>

    <!-- ====================================================================== -->

    <section title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>Jouni Korhonen would like to thank the TEKES GIGA program MERCoNe-project for
         providing funding to work on this document while he was with
         TeliaSonera. The authors also thank Pasi Eronen, Peter McCann,
         Spencer Dawkins and Marco Liebsch for their detailed reviews on this
         document.
      </t>
    </section>


    <!-- ====================================================================== -->

    </middle>

    <!-- ====================================================================== -->

    <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      &HUIHAI;
      &RFC3588;
      &RFC4072;
      &RFC4005;
      &RFC4282;
      &RFC5213;
      &I-D.ietf-dime-mip6-split;
      &RFC5447;
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      &I-D.ietf-netlmm-pmip6-ipv4-support;
      &I-D.ietf-mext-binding-revocation;
      &RFC3775;
      &RFC3748;
      &RFC4283;
      &RFC5149;
      &RFC2131;
      &RFC3315;
      &I-D.ietf-netlmm-lma-discovery;
    </references>
    </back>
</rfc>
