<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='http://xml.resource.org/authoring/rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY rfc5213 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5213.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc3588 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3588.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc5779 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5779.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc4005 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4005.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc5447 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5447.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.ietf-netext-pmip6-lr-ps PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-netext-pmip6-lr-ps.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.wu-netext-local-ro PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.wu-netext-local-ro.xml">
]>
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<rfc category="std" docName="draft-ietf-dime-pmip6-lr-06" ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="PMIP6 Localized Routing Support">Diameter Support for Proxy
    Mobile IPv6 Localized Routing</title>

    <author fullname="Glen Zorn" initials="G" surname="Zorn">
      <organization>Network Zen</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>227/358 Thanon Sanphawut</street>

          <city>Bang Na</city>

          <region>Bangkok</region>

          <code>10260</code>

          <country>Thailand</country>
        </postal>

        <phone>+66 (0) 87-040-4617</phone>

        <email>gwz@net-zen.net</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Qin Wu" initials="Q." surname="Wu">
      <organization abbrev="Huawei">Huawei Technologies Co.,
      Ltd.</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>101 Software Avenue, Yuhua District</street>

          <city>Nanjing</city>

          <region>Jiangsu</region>

          <code>21001</code>

          <country>China</country>
        </postal>

        <phone>+86-25-84565892</phone>

        <email>sunseawq@huawei.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Marco Liebsch" initials="M." surname="Liebsch">
      <organization abbrev="NEC">NEC Europe Ltd.</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Kurfuersten-Anlage 36</street>

          <city>Heidelberg</city>

          <region></region>

          <code>69115</code>

          <country>Germany</country>
        </postal>

        <email>liebsch@nw.neclab.eu</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Jouni Korhonen" initials="J." surname="Korhonen">
      <organization abbrev="NSN">Nokia Siemens Networks</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Linnoitustie 6</street>

          <city>Espoo FI-02600</city>

          <region></region>

          <code></code>

          <country>Finland</country>
        </postal>

        <email>jouni.nospam@gmail.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date year="2011" />

    <abstract>
      <t>In Proxy Mobile IPv6, packets received from a Mobile Node (MN) by the
      Mobile Access Gateway (MAG) to which it is attached are typically
      tunneled to a Local Mobility Anchor (LMA) for routing. The term
      "localized routing" refers to a method by which packets are routed
      directly between an MN's MAG and the MAG of its Correspondent Node (CN)
      without involving any LMA. In order to establish a localized routing
      session between two Mobile Access Gateways in a Proxy Mobile IPv6
      domain, two tasks must be accomplished: <list style="numbers">
          <t>The usage of localized routing must be authorized for both MAGs
          and</t>

          <t>The address of the MAG to which the Correspondent Node (CN) is
          attached must be ascertained</t>
        </list> This document specifies how to accomplish these tasks using
      the Diameter protocol.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t><xref target="RFC5213">Proxy Mobile IPv6 (PMIPv6)</xref> allows the
      Mobility Access Gateway to optimize media delivery by locally routing
      packets within itself, avoiding tunneling them to the Mobile Node's
      Local Mobility Anchor. This is referred to as "local routing" in RFC
      5213. However, this mechanism is not applicable to the typical scenarios
      in which the MN and CN are connected to different MAGs and are
      registered to the same LMA or different LMAs. In these scenarios (<xref
      target="RFC6279">as described in</xref>), the relevant information
      needed to set up a localized routing path (e.g., the addresses of the
      Mobile Access Gateways to which the MN and CN are respectively attached)
      is distributed between their respective Local Mobility Anchors. This may
      complicate the setup and maintenance of localized routing. <vspace
      blankLines="1" />Therefore, in order to establish a localized routing
      path between the two Mobile Access Gateways, the Mobile Node's MAG must
      identify the LMA that is managing the Correspondent Node's traffic and
      then obtain the address of the Correspondent Node's MAG from that LMA.
      In Proxy Mobile IPv6, the LMA to be assigned to the CN may be maintained
      as a configured entry in the Correspondent Node's policy profile located
      on an Authentication, Authorization and Accounting (AAA) server.
      However, there is no relevant work discussing how AAA-based mechanisms
      can be used by the Mobile Node's LMA to discover the address of the
      Correspondent Node's LMA during the setup of localized routing. The
      method by which the Mobile Node's MAG or LMA interacts with the
      Correspondent Node's LMA to identify the Correspondent Node's MAG is
      also unspecified. <vspace blankLines="1" /> This document describes AAA
      support for the authorization and discovery of PMIPv6 mobility entities
      during localized routing. In LMA discovery, Diameter <xref
      target="RFC3588"></xref> is used to authorize the localized routing
      service and provide the Mobile Node's MAG/LMA with information regarding
      the Correspondent Node's LMA. In MAG discovery, AAA is used to determine
      whether Mobile Node's MAG is allowed to fetch the address of the
      Correspondent Node's MAG from the Correspondent Node's LMA. If MAG
      discovery is successful, the Correspondent Node's LMA will respond to
      the Mobile Node's MAG with the address of the Correspondent Node's
      MAG.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Solution Overview">
      <t>MAG/LMA discovery is a prerequisite to the establishment of a direct
      routing path between MAG1 and MAG2 (associated with MN1 and MN2
      respectively). This document addresses how to resolve the destination
      MN’s MAG by means of interaction between the LMA and the AAA server.
      <xref target="ref_arch"></xref> shows the reference architecture for
      Localized Routing Service Authorization. This reference architecture
      assumes <list style="symbols">
          <t>MN1 and MN2 belong to different LMAs or the same LMA. If MN1 and
          MN2 belong to the same LMA, the LMA1 and LMA2 to which MN1 and MN2
          are anchored in the figure1 should be the same LMA. If MN1 and MN2
          belong to different LMAs, the LMA1 and LMA2 in the figure 1 are in
          the same provider domain as described in <xref
          target="RFC6279"></xref>.</t>

          <t>The MAG and LMA support Diameter client functionality.</t>
        </list> <figure align="center" anchor="ref_arch"
          title="Localized Routing Service Authorization Reference Architecture">
          <artwork>
                      +---------+
           LMA2?      |  AAA &amp;  |
              +------&gt;| Policy  |&lt;----------+
              |       | Profile |           |
          Diameter    +---------+        Diameter
          (Step a)                       (Step b)
              |                             |
              |                             |
              |                             |
     LMA2? +--V-+             +----+        |
  +-------&gt;|LMA1|             |LMA2|&lt;-------+
  |        +----+             +----+
  |          |                  |
  |         //                  \\
 PMIP      //                    \\
  |       //                      \\
  |       |                        |
  |     +----+  MAG2?            +----+
  +----&gt;|MAG1|&lt;--------          |MAG2|
        +----+                   +----+
           :                        :
        +---+                     +---+
        |MN1|                     |MN2|
        +---+                     +---+
</artwork>
        </figure> The interaction of the MAG and LMA with the AAA server
      according to the extension specified in this document considers the
      follows features: <list style="letters">
          <t>The interaction of LMA1 with the AAA server is used to authorize
          the localized routing service and, if necessary, fetch the IP
          address of LMA2 (Step a in Figure 1)</t>

          <t>LMA2 interaction with the AAA server is used to determine whether
          MAG1 or LMA1 is allowed to obtain the IP address of MAG2 (Step b in
          Figure 1)</t>
        </list>Note that if MN1 and MN2 are connected to different MAGs but
      share the same LMA, the interaction between LMA1 and the AAA server
      should be exactly the same as the case where MNs belong to MAGs under
      different LMAs.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Attribute Value Pair Definitions">
      <t>This section describes Attribute Value Pairs (AVPs) defined by this
      specification or re-used from existing specifications in a PMIPv6
      specific way.</t>

      <section title="MIP6-Agent-Info AVP">
        <t>The MIP6-Agent-Info grouped AVP (AVP Code 486) is defined in <xref
        target="RFC5779"></xref>. This AVP is used to carry LMA addressing in
        AAA response.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="PMIP6-IPv4-Home-Address AVP">
        <t>The PMIP6-IPv4-Home-Address AVP (AVP Code 505) is defined in <xref
        target="RFC5779"></xref>. This AVP is used to carry the IPv4-MN-HoA
        [RFC5844] in AAR/Request, from the LMA to the HAAA.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="MIP6-Home-Link-Prefix AVP">
        <t>The MIP6-Home-Link-Prefix AVP (AVP Code 125) is defined in <xref
        target="RFC5779"></xref>. This AVP is used to carry the MN-HNP in
        AAR/request, if available, from the LMA to the HAAA.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="MIP6-Feature-Vector AVP">
        <t>The MIP6-Feature-Vector AVP is originally defined in <xref
        target="RFC5447"></xref>. This document defines new capability flag
        bits according to the IANA rules in RFC 5447.</t>

        <t>INTER_MAG_ROUTING_SUPPORTED (TBD)<list>
            <t>Direct routing of IP packets between MNs anchored to the
            different MAG without involving any LMA is supported. This bit is
            used with MN-HNP or IPv4-MN-HoA. When a LMA sets this bit in the
            MIP6-Feature-Vector and MN-HNP or IPv4-MN-HoA corresponding to
            Correspondent Node is carried with this bit, it indicates to HAAA
            that Mobile Node associated with this LMA is allowed to use
            localized routing but the LMA needs to know from HAAA if
            Correspondent Node is allowed to use localized routing. If the
            MN-HNPs or IPv4-MN-HoAs corresponding to both Mobile node and
            Correspondent node are carried with this bit, it indicate that
            both MN and CN are allowed to use localized routing. Note that
            localized routing related signaling is required prior localized
            routing. If this bit is cleared in the returned
            MIP6-Feature-Vector AVP, the HAAA does not authorize direct
            routing of packets between MNs anchored to the different MAG. The
            LMA SHOULD support this policy feature on a per-MN and
            per-subscription basis.</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Example Signaling flows">
      <section title="Localized Routing Service Authorization">
        <t>Localized Routing Service Authorization also can happen during the
        network access authentication procedure <xref
        target="RFC5779"></xref>,i.e., before Localized routing is
        initialized. In this case, the preauthorized pairs of LMA/prefix sets
        can be downloaded to Proxy Mobile IPv6 entities during RFC5779
        procedure. Localized routing can be initiated once a destination of
        received packet matches to some of the prefixes received during
        RFC5779 procedure.</t>

        <t><xref target="fig2"></xref> shows an example scenario where MAG1
        acts as a Diameter client, processing the data packet from MN1 to MN2
        and requesting authorization of localized routing. In this example
        scenario, MN1 and MN2 are anchored to LMA1 and LMA2 respectively if
        MN1 and MN2 belong to the different LMA, otherwise, the LMA to which
        MN1 and MN2 are anchored should be the same LMA,i.e., LMA1 or LMA2. In
        the case where MNs belong to the different LMAs, in order to setup a
        localized routing path with MAG2, MAG1 must first locate the entity
        that maintains the data required to setup the path (i.e., LMA2) by
        sending a Request message to LMA1. Note that the discovery of LMA2 is
        only done once and the request message is Localized routing
        initialization (LRI) message in the <xref target="fig2"></xref> and
        belong to the Initial phase of the localized routing; once LMA1 has
        obtained the address of LMA2 from the AAA serer, LMA1 may associate
        address of LMA2 with the Mobile Node's cached data for future use
        (e.g., in the case of a handover). The Diameter client in LMA1 sends
        an AA-Request (AAR) message to the Diameter server. The message
        contains an instance of the MIP6-Feature-Vector (MFV) AVP (<xref
        target="RFC5447"></xref>, Section 4.2.5) with the
        INTER_MAG_ROUTING_SUPPORTED bit (<xref target="IANA"></xref>) set and
        an instance of the MIP6-Home-Link-Prefix AVP (<xref
        target="RFC5779"></xref>, Section 5.3) or an instance of the
        PMIP6-IPv4-Home-Address AVP (<xref target="RFC5779"></xref>, Section
        5.2) containing the IP address/HNP of MN2. <vspace
        blankLines="1" />The Diameter server authorizes localized routing
        service by checking if MN2 is allowed to use localized routing and if
        LMA2 and LMA1 are in the same provider domain. if so, the Diameter
        Server responds with an AA-Answer (AAA) message encapsulating an
        instance of the MIP6-Agent-Info AVP <xref target="RFC5779"></xref>
        containing the IP address and/or Fully Qualified Domain Name (FQDN) of
        LMA2 and an instance of the MIP6- Feature-Vector (MFV) AVP (<xref
        target="RFC5447"></xref>, Section 4.2.5) with the
        INTER_MAG_ROUTING_SUPPORTED bit (Section 7) set indicating Direct
        routing of IP packets between MNs anchored to the different MAG is
        supported. . LMA1 then determines the IP address of LMA2 using the
        data returned in the MIP6-Agent-Info and responds to MAG1 with the
        address of LMA2 in the localized routing acknowledge message (LRA in
        the <xref target="fig2"></xref>). MAG1 can verify whether both MAGs
        are under the same LMA by comparing LMA1 address with LMA2 address.
        MAG1 then requests the address of MAG2 from LMA2 and uses that address
        to setup the localized routing path between itself and MAG2 via a
        Proxy Binding Update (PBU)/Proxy Binding Acknowledgement (PBA) message
        exchange <xref target="RFC5213"></xref>.</t>

        <t>In the case where MNs share the same LMA, the MAG1 should send a
        request message (LRI in the <xref target="fig2"></xref>) to LMA for
        localized routing which includes IP address of MN2. The subsequent
        interaction between LMA1 and the AAA should be exact the same as the
        case where MNs belong to different LMAs. If authorization in the
        Diameter server is successful, the LMA may look up MAG2 address
        directly based on IP address of MN2 and respond a message to the MAG1
        with IP address of MAG2 included.</t>

        <t><figure anchor="fig2"
            title="MAG-initiated Localized Routing Authorization">
            <artwork>
+---+    +----+    +----+     +---+    +----+  +----+   +---+
|MN1|    |MAG1|    |LMA1|     |AAA|    |LMA2|  |MAG2|   |MN2|
+-+-+    +-+--+    +-+--+     +-+-+    +-+--+  +-+--+   +-+-+
  |        |         |          |        |       |        |
  |     Anchored     |          |        |    Anchored    |
  o------------------o          |        o-------+--------o
Data[MN1-&gt;MN2]       |          |        |       |        |
  |-------&gt;| LRI(MN2)|          |        |       |        |
  |        |--------&gt;|          |        |       |        |
  |        |         |AAR(MFV, MN2)      |       |        |
  |        |         |---------&gt;|        |       |        |
  |        |         |AAA(MFV, LMA2)     |       |        |
  |      LRA([LMA2]) |&lt;---------|        |       |        |
  |        |&lt;--------|          |        |       |        |
  |                  |          |        |       |        |
</artwork>
          </figure></t>

        <t><xref target="fig3"></xref> shows another example scenario, in
        which the LMA1 acts as a Diameter client, processing the data packet
        from MN2 to MN1 and requesting the authorization of localized routing.
        In this example scenario, MN1 and MN2 are anchored to LMA1 and LMA2
        respectively. In contrast with the signaling flow of <xref
        target="fig2"></xref>, the difference is that it is LMA1 instead of
        MAG1 which initiates the setup of the localized routing path. <vspace
        blankLines="1" />The Diameter client in LMA1 sends an AA-Request (AAR)
        message to the Diameter server. The message contains an instance of
        the MIP6- Feature-Vector AVP (<xref target="RFC5447"></xref>, Section
        4.2.5) with the INTER_MAG_ROUTING_SUPPORTED bit set and an instance of
        the MIP6-Home- Link-Prefix AVP (<xref target="RFC5779"></xref>,
        Section 5.3) or an instance of the PMIP6-IPv4-Home-Address AVP (<xref
        target="RFC5779"></xref>, Section 5.2) containing the IP address/HNP
        of MN2. The Diameter server authorizes localized routing service by
        checking if MN2 is allowed to use localized routing and if LMA2 and
        LMA1 are in the same domain. If so, the Diameter server responds with
        an AA-Answer (AAA) message encapsulating an instance of the
        MIP6-Agent-Info AVP <xref target="RFC5779"></xref> containing the IP
        address and/or Fully Qualified Domain Name (FQDN) of LMA2 and an
        instance of the MIP6- Feature-Vector (MFV) AVP (<xref
        target="RFC5447"></xref>, Section 4.2.5) with the
        INTER_MAG_ROUTING_SUPPORTED bit (Section 7) set indicating Direct
        routing of IP packets between MNs anchored to the different MAG is
        supported. . LMA1 then determines the IP address of LMA2 using the
        data returned in the MIP6-Agent-Info AVP and responds to MAG1 with the
        address of LMA2.</t>

        <t>In the case where MNs share the same LMA, the Diameter client in
        LMA1 sends an AA-Request (AAR) message to the Diameter server. The
        interaction between LMA1 and the AAA should be exact the same as the
        case where MNs belong to different LMAs. If authorization in the
        Diameter server is successful, the LMA may look up MAG2 address
        directly based on IP address of MN2 and send a request message (LRI in
        the <xref target="fig3"></xref>) to the MAG1 for localized routing
        with IP address of MAG2 included. The MAG1 confirms the success of
        localized routing if localized routing path can be setup.</t>

        <t><figure align="center" anchor="fig3"
            title="LMA-initiated Localized Routing Authorization ">
            <artwork>
      +---+    +----+  +----+     +---+      +----+  +----+   +---+
      |MN1|    |MAG1|  |LMA1|     |AAA|      |LMA2|  |MAG2|   |MN2|
      +-+-+    +-+--+  +-+--+     +-+-+      +-+--+  +-+--+   +-+-+
        |        |       |          |          |       |        |
        |     Anchored   |          |          |    Anchored    |
        o--------+-------o Data[MN2-&gt;MN1]      o-------+--------o
        |        |       |&lt;-----    |          |       |        |
        |        |       |AAR(MFV,MN2)         |       |        |
        |        |       |---------&gt;|          |       |        |
        |          LRI   |AAA(MFV,LMA2)        |       |        |
        |    (MN2,[LMA2])|&lt;---------|          |       |        |
        |        |&lt;------|          |          |       |        |
        |     LRA(Succ)  |          |          |       |        |
        |        |------&gt;|          |          |       |        |
</artwork>
          </figure></t>

        <t><xref target="fig4"></xref> shows another example scenario, similar
        to the example scenario illustrated in <xref target="fig3"></xref>,
        LMA1 does not respond to MAG1 with the address of LMA2, instead
        setting up a localized routing path directly between itself and LMA2
        via localized routing signaling.<figure align="center" anchor="fig4"
            title="LMA-initiated Localized Routing Authorization">
            <artwork>
     +---+    +----+  +----+     +---+      +----+  +----+   +---+
     |MN1|    |MAG1|  |LMA1|     |AAA|      |LMA2|  |MAG2|   |MN2|
     +-+-+    +-+--+  +-+--+     +-+-+      +-+--+  +-+--+   +-+-+
       |        |       |          |          |       |        |
       |     Anchored   |          |          |    Anchored    |
       o--------+-------o Data[MN2-&gt;MN1]      o-------+--------o
       |        |       |&lt;-----    |          |       |        |
       |        |       |AAR(MFV,MN2)         |       |        |
       |        |       |---------&gt;|          |       |        |
       |        |       |AAA(MFV,LMA2)        |       |        |
       |        |       |&lt;---------|          |       |        |
       |        |       Localized routing setup       |        |
       |        |       |&lt;-------------------&gt;|       |        |
</artwork>
          </figure></t>
      </section>

      <section title="Diameter Server Authorizes MAG Location Query">
        <t><xref target="fig5"></xref> shows an example scenario in which LMA2
        acts as a Diameter client, receiving MAG location request and
        requesting authorization for MAG location Query to the AAA server. In
        this example scenario, MN1 and MN2 may be anchored to LMA1 and LMA2
        respectively or belong to the same LMA. In the case where MNs belong
        to the different LMAs, MAG1 or LMA1 should has already known the
        recipient of localized routing is LMA2. If MAG1 initiates LR, MAG1 may
        take option 1 in the <xref target="fig5"></xref> and solicit LMA2 to
        look up the IP address of the MAG to which MN2 is currently attached
        (in this case, MAG2) according to the IP addresses/HNPs of MN2. If
        LMA1 initiate LR, LMA1 may take option 2 in the <xref
        target="fig5"></xref> and solicit LMA2 to look up IP address of the
        MAG to which MN2 is currently attached. LMA2 validates the request
        (LRI in the <xref target="fig5"></xref>) from MAG1 by sending an AAR
        to the Diameter server containing the IP address/HNP of MN1
        (encapsulated in an instance of the MIP6-Home- Link-Prefix AVP or an
        instance of PMIP6-IPv4-Home-Address AVP) and an instance of the
        MIP6-Feature- Vector AVP (<xref target="RFC5779"></xref>, Section 5.5)
        with the INTER_MAG_ROUTING_SUPPORTED bit set. If the authorization is
        successful, the Diameter server responds with an AA-Answer (AAA)
        message encapsulating an instance of the MIP6- Feature-Vector (MFV)
        AVP (<xref target="RFC5447"></xref>, Section 4.2.5) with the
        INTER_MAG_ROUTING_SUPPORTED bit (Section 7) set indicating Direct
        routing of IP packets between MNs anchored to the different MAG is
        supported. LMA2 then looks up the IP address of MAG2 based on the IP
        address/HNP of MN2 and responds to MAG1 or LMA1 with the IP address of
        MAG2. <figure align="center" anchor="fig5"
            title="Diameter Server Authorizes MAG Location Query">
            <artwork>
 +---+    +----+  +----+     +---+      +----+  +----+   +---+
 |MN1|    |MAG1|  |LMA1|     |AAA|      |LMA2|  |MAG2|   |MN2|
 +-+-+    +-+--+  +-+--+     +-+-+      +-+--+  +-+--+   +-+-+
   |        |       |          |          |       |        |
   |     Anchored   |          |          |    Anchored    |
   o----------------o          |          o-------+--------o
 Data[MN1-&gt;MN2]     |          |          |       |        |
   |-------&gt;|       |          |          |       |        |
   |        |       LRI(MN1,MN2 )         |       |        |
   |        |-------+----------+---------&gt;|\      |        |
   |        |       |          |          | |     |        |
   |        |       |         AAR(MFV,MN1)|Option 1        |
   |        |       |          |&lt;-------- | |     |        |
   |        |       |        AAA(MFV,LMA1)| |     |        |
   |        |       |          |---------&gt;| |     |        |
   |        |       LRA(MAG2 )            | |     |        |
   |        |&lt;--------------------------- |/      |        |
   |        |                             |       |        |
   |        |       |LRI(MN1,MN2)         |\      |        |
   |        |       +----------+---------&gt;| |     |        |
   |        |       |         AAR(MFV,MN1)|Option 2        |
   |        |       |          |&lt;-------- | |     |        |
   |        |       |        AAA(MFV,LMA1)| |     |        |
   |        |       |          |---------&gt;| |     |        |
   |        |       |    LRA(MAG2)        | |     |        |
   |        |       |&lt;------------------- |/      |        |
   |        |       |                             |        |
   |        |       |Localized routing setup      |        |
   |        |&lt;------+----------------------------&gt;|        |
   |        |===================================-&gt;|        |
   |        |       |          |          |       |-------&gt;|
   |        |       |          |          |    Data[MN2-&gt;MN1]
   |&lt;------ |&lt;-===================================|&lt;-------|
   |        |       |          |          |       |        |
</artwork>
          </figure></t>

        <t>In the case where MNs share the same LMA, LR should be initiated by
        LMA1(i.e.,LMA2) since only LMA1 knows both MN1 and MN2 belong to
        itself by lookup its binding cache corresponding to MN1 and MN2.
        Unlike the case where MNs belong to different LMAs, the interaction
        between LMAs in option 2 is omitted since LMA1 and LMA2 are the same
        entity. The interaction between LMA1 and the AAA should be exact the
        same as the case where MNs belong to different LMAs.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Localized Routing Service Authorization in Networks with Multiple AAA Servers">
      <figure align="left" anchor="fig6"
              title="Use of a Diameter Redirect Agent to Support Localized Routing Service Authorization in Networks with Multiple AAA servers">
        <artwork>
                   +------------------------------------+
                   (                      AAA           )
                   (     +--------+     Backend         )
                   (     |Redirect|                     )
                   (     | Agent  |                     )
                   (     +--------+                     )
                   (         ^                          )
                   (         |                          )
                   (         |                          )
                   (         v                          )
                   (  +---------+          +---------+  )
                +----&gt;| AAA1 &amp;  |          | AAA2 &amp;  |&lt;---+
                |  (  | Policy  |&lt;--------&gt;| Policy  |  ) |
                |  (  | Profile |          | Profile |  ) |
                |  (  +---------+          +---------+  ) |
                |  (      ^                     ^       ) |
                |  +----- | ------------------- |-------+ |
                |         A1                    A2        |
                |         |                     |         |
                |         |                     |         |
             Diameter     v                     v      Diameter
                B1       +----+  LMA2 ?     +----+        B2
                |        |LMA1| ------&gt;     |LMA2|        |
                |        +----+             +----+        |
                |          |                  |           |
                |         //                  \\          |
                |        //                    \\         |
                |       //                      \\        |
                |       |                        |        |
                |     +----+                   +----+     |
                +----&gt;|MAG1|                   |MAG2|&lt;----+
                      +----+                   +----+
                         :                        :
                      +---+                     +---+
                      |MN1|                     |MN2|
                      +---+                     +---+
</artwork>
      </figure>

      <t>Referring to an architecture with multiple AAA servers (as
      illustrated in <xref target="fig6"></xref>), AAA1 may not maintain the
      LMA to be assigned to MN2 as a configured entry in the Correspondent
      Node's Policy profile, as AAA2 holds this information in its policy
      store. In such a case, AAA1 contacts a Diameter redirect agent [RFC3588]
      to request the AAA server being responsible for maintaining MN2's policy
      profile. AAA2 checks if MN2 is allowed to use localized routing and if
      so, responds with the IP address of LMA2 corresponding to MN2 and sends
      the results back to LMA1 via AAA1. Details about the use of redirect
      agents in this context are beyond scope of this document.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>The security considerations for the <xref target="RFC4005">Diameter
      NASREQ</xref> and <xref target="RFC5779">Diameter Proxy Mobile
      IPv6</xref> applications are also applicable to this document. <vspace
      blankLines="1" /> The service authorization solicited by the MAG or the
      LMA relies upon the existing trust relationship between the MAG/LMA and
      the AAA server.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>This specification specifies a new value in the Mobility Capability
      registry <xref target="RFC5447"></xref> for use with the
      MIP6-Feature-Vector AVP: INTER_MAG_ROUTING_SUPPORTED (TBD).</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Contributors">
      <t>Paulo Loureiro, Jinwei Xia and Yungui Wang all contributed to early
      versions of this document.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Acknowledgement">
      <t>The authors would like to thank Carlos Jesús Bernardos Cano for his
      valuable comments and suggestions on this document.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Change Log">
      <section title="draft-ietf-dime-pmip6-lr-03">
        <t>The following are the major changes compared to previous version
        02: <list style="symbols">
            <t>Allow return the LMA address in all cases.</t>

            <t>Using localized routing for terminology consistency.</t>

            <t>Allow localized routing service authorization before localized
            routing is initialized.</t>

            <t>Treat MAGs under the different LMA in the same way as the MAGs
            under the same LMA.</t>

            <t>Get rid of references to individual drafts and only get
            alignment with Localized routing PS document.</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>

      <section title="draft-ietf-dime-pmip6-lr-04">
        <t>The following are the major changes compared to previous version
        03: <list style="symbols">
            <t>Move the last paragraph in section 3 to the first
            paragraph.</t>

            <t>Using “request” rather than “localized routing optimization
            request”.</t>

            <t>Using “respond” rather than “localized routing optimization
            response”.</t>

            <t>Remove the informative reference to
            [I-D.wu-netext-local-ro].</t>

            <t>Using “discovery” rather than “resolution”.</t>

            <t>Section 5 Fix Typo: “LMA”-&gt;”LMA2”.</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>

      <section title="draft-ietf-dime-pmip6-lr-05">
        <t>The following are the major changes compared to previous version
        04: <list style="symbols">
            <t>Redraw the figure 1 to get alignment with the described
            text.</t>

            <t>Section 2 Fix Typo: “the interaction between LMA1 interaction
            and the AAA server-&gt; the interaction between LMA1 and the AAA
            server”</t>

            <t>Section 3 Fix Typo “the data packet from MN1 to MN2 and
            requesting -&gt; the data packet from MN2 to MN1 and
            requesting”</t>

            <t>Section 4 Fix Typo: “MAG1 or LMA may solicit-&gt; MAG1 or LMA1
            may solicit"”</t>

            <t>Differentiate MAG initiated case from LMA initiated case in
            Figure5</t>

            <t>Add text in section 3 and 4 to explicitly explain how LR
            authorization works in A21.</t>

            <t>Change “localized routing is allowed between MAG1 and MAG2” in
            section 3,4,5 to “MN2 is allowed to use localized routing”.</t>

            <t>Update the abstract to make the description consistent</t>

            <t>Highlight the figure 2,3,4,5 and related texts are examples of
            how LR authorization works using Diameter AAA protocol.</t>

            <t>Reference Update.</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>

      <section title="draft-ietf-dime-pmip6-lr-06">
        <t>The following are the major changes compared to previous version
        05: <list style="symbols">
            <t>Mandate to use MFV in AAA/Answer message.</t>

            <t>Add text regarding the use of PMIP6-IPv4-Home-Address
            [RFC5779].</t>

            <t>Add reference to RFC5844 to support for MN's IPv4-HoA.</t>

            <t>Use MIP6-Agent-Info in an AAA/response to carry LMA
            address.</t>

            <t>Use MIP6-Home-Link-Prefix &amp; PMIP6-IPv4-Home-Address in an
            AAR/request to carry MN's address.</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      &rfc5779;

      &rfc3588;

      &rfc5213;

      &rfc4005;

      &rfc5447;

      <reference anchor="RFC5844">
        <front>
          <title>IPv4 Support for Proxy Mobile IPv6</title>

          <author fullname="Ryuji Wakikawa" initials="R." surname="Wakikawa">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="Sri Gundavelli" initials="S." surname="Gundavelli">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date month="May" year="2010" />

          <abstract>
            <t>This document specifies extensions to the Proxy Mobile IPv6
            protocol for adding IPv4 protocol support. The scope of IPv4
            protocol support is two-fold: 1) enable IPv4 home address mobility
            support to the mobile node, and 2) allow the mobility entities in
            the Proxy Mobile IPv6 domain to exchange signaling messages over
            an IPv4 transport network.</t>
          </abstract>
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="5844" />

        <format target="http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc5844.txt" type="TXT" />
      </reference>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <reference anchor="RFC6279">
        <front>
          <title>PMIPv6 Localized Routing Problem Statement</title>

          <author fullname="Marco Liebsch" initials="M." surname="Liebsch">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="Sangjin Jeong" initials="S." surname="Jeong">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="Qin Wu" initials="Q." surname="Wu">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date month="June" year="2011" />

          <abstract>
            <t>Proxy Mobile IPv6 is the IETF standard for network-based
            mobility management. In Proxy Mobile IPv6, mobile nodes are
            topologically anchored at a Local Mobility Anchor, which forwards
            all data for registered mobile nodes. The setup and maintenance of
            localized routing, which allows forwarding of data packets between
            mobile nodes and correspondent nodes directly without involvement
            of the Local Mobility Anchor in forwarding, is not considered.
            This document describes the problem space of localized routing in
            Proxy Mobile IPv6.</t>
          </abstract>
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="6279" />

        <format target="http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc6279.txt" type="TXT" />
      </reference>
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
