<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!-- This template is for creating an Internet Draft using xml2rfc,
     which is available here: http://xml.resource.org. -->
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!-- One method to get references from the online citation libraries.
     There has to be one entity for each item to be referenced. 
     An alternate method (rfc include) is described in the references. -->

<!ENTITY RFC3963 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3963.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5201 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5201.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5944 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5944.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6275 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6275.xml">
<!ENTITY LISP SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.draft-ietf-lisp-15.xml">
]>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<!-- used by XSLT processors -->
<!-- For a complete list and description of processing instructions (PIs), 
     please see http://xml.resource.org/authoring/README.html. -->
<!-- Below are generally applicable Processing Instructions (PIs) that most I-Ds might want to use.
     (Here they are set differently than their defaults in xml2rfc v1.32) -->
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<!-- give errors regarding ID-nits and DTD validation -->
<!-- control the table of contents (ToC) -->
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<!-- generate a ToC -->
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<!-- the number of levels of subsections in ToC. default: 3 -->
<!-- control references -->
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<!-- use symbolic references tags, i.e, [RFC2119] instead of [1] -->
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<!-- sort the reference entries alphabetically -->
<!-- control vertical white space 
     (using these PIs as follows is recommended by the RFC Editor) -->
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<!-- do not start each main section on a new page -->
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<!-- keep one blank line between list items -->
<!-- end of list of popular I-D processing instructions -->
<rfc category="info" docName="draft-shima-clouds-net-portability-reqs-and-models-01" ipr="trust200902">
  <!-- category values: std, bcp, info, exp, and historic
     ipr values: full3667, noModification3667, noDerivatives3667
     you can add the attributes updates="NNNN" and obsoletes="NNNN" 
     they will automatically be output with "(if approved)" -->

  <!-- ***** FRONT MATTER ***** -->

  <front>
    <!-- The abbreviated title is used in the page header - it is only necessary if the 
         full title is longer than 39 characters -->

    <title abbrev="Network Portability">Network Portability Requirements and Models for Cloud Environment</title>

    <!-- add 'role="editor"' below for the editors if appropriate -->

    <!-- Another author who claims to be an editor -->

    <author fullname="Keiichi Shima" initials="K." surname="Shima">
      <organization>IIJ Innovation Institute Inc.</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>1-105 Kanda-Jinbocho</street>

          <!-- Reorder these if your country does things differently -->

          <city>Chiyoda-ku</city>

          <region>Tokyo</region>

          <code>101-0051</code>

          <country>Japan</country>
        </postal>

        <!-- <phone>+81 352056464</phone> -->

        <email>keiichi@iijlab.net</email>

        <!-- uri and facsimile elements may also be added -->
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Yuji Sekiya" initials="Y." surname="Sekiya">
      <organization>The University of Tokyo</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>2-11-16 Yayoi</street>

          <!-- Reorder these if your country does things differently -->

          <city>Bunkyo-ku</city>

          <region>Tokyo</region>

          <code>113-8658</code>

          <country>Japan</country>
        </postal>

        <!-- <phone>+81 358412788</phone> -->

        <email>sekiya@wide.ad.jp</email>

        <!-- uri and facsimile elements may also be added -->
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Katsuhiro Horiba" initials="K." surname="Horiba">
      <organization>Keio University</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>5322 Endo</street>

          <!-- Reorder these if your country does things differently -->

          <city>Fujisawa</city>

          <region>Kanagawa</region>

          <code>252-0882</code>

          <country>Japan</country>
        </postal>

        <!-- <phone>+81 358412788</phone> -->

        <email>qoo@sfc.wide.ad.jp</email>

        <!-- uri and facsimile elements may also be added -->
      </address>
    </author>

    <date day="17" month="October" year="2011" />

    <!-- If the month and year are both specified and are the current ones, xml2rfc will fill 
         in the current day for you. If only the current year is specified, xml2rfc will fill 
	 in the current day and month for you. If the year is not the current one, it is 
	 necessary to specify at least a month (xml2rfc assumes day="1" if not specified for the 
	 purpose of calculating the expiry date).  With drafts it is normally sufficient to 
	 specify just the year. -->

    <!-- Meta-data Declarations -->

    <area>Application</area>

    <workgroup>Network Working Group</workgroup>

    <!-- WG name at the upperleft corner of the doc,
         IETF is fine for individual submissions.  
	 If this element is not present, the default is "Network Working Group",
         which is used by the RFC Editor as a nod to the history of the IETF. -->

    <keyword></keyword>

    <!-- Keywords will be incorporated into HTML output
         files in a meta tag but they have no effect on text or nroff
         output. If you submit your draft to the RFC Editor, the
         keywords will be used for the search engine. -->

    <abstract>
      <t>
	Recent progress of virtual machine technology made it possible
	to host various Internet service nodes in a so called cloud
	environment.  The virtual machine hosting technology provides
	a method to migrate a virtual machine from one hypervisor to
	another.  However, such a technology is mainly focusing on a
	migration between hypervisors attached to the same link, and
	tend not to consider migration over the Internet.  This
	document mentions the purpose of that type of operation and
	describe several possible operation methods to provide network
	portability in cloud systems.
      </t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>
	This document describes requirements and methodology of
	network migration for inter-datacenter and inter-clouds. The
	progress of virtualization technology changed the way to build
	Internet services completely.  For example, the PaaS (Platform
	as a Services) is one of the innovative concept of computing
	service utilizing virtualization technology.  It provides
	network-oriented service APIs to software layer which scales
	out by increasing the number of virtual nodes and scales in by
	decreasing the number of virtual nodes based on the load of
	the software requests.
      </t>
      <t>
	A PaaS is built and provided in single datacenter by single
	organization nowadays, however, the needs of building
	distributed, inter-datacenter PaaS, and inter-connecting
	existing PaaS(es) are growing.  Recently people expect
	sustainable service much more seriously than ever before. If a
	datacenter is encountered network circuit or power troubles,
	administrators or users of PaaS want to move the virtual nodes
	in a datacenter to other datacenters or other PaaS(es) without
	service interruption.
      </t>
      <t>
	In order to migrate virtual nodes between inter-datacenter
	and inter-clouds without service interruptions and changes,
	network portability technologies are required between the
	datacenters and clouds.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section title="Network Portability Requirements">
      <t> 
	The requirements of network portability for migrating vitrual
	nodes between datacenters and between clouds are below.
      </t>
      <t>
	<list style="symbols">
	  <t>
	    Providing the same user service networks between each
	    datacenter and cloud <vspace blankLines="1" />
	  
	    Each user has different service networks and it should be
	    possible for users to use their networks on any
	    datacenters or clouds. If the service infrastructure is
	    operated by a single administrative organization, it is
	    possible to use VLAN and VPN technologies to achieve this
	    property, however, building user networks using such
	    technologies is difficult in inter-datacenters or
	    inter-clouds cases where administrative organizations
	    differ.  Since VLAN is a layer-2 technology and it
	    requires direct circuit between datacenters, it is
	    difficult considering the cost to keep the direct line.
	    VPN is a cost-effective technology and it is possible to
	    provide user networks on each datacenters and clouds,
	    however, if the clouds are administrated by different
	    organizations, it is difficult and costly for
	    administrators to build a lot of VPN connection for all
	    user networks.
	  </t>
	  <t>
	    Movement policy management mechanism <vspace blankLines="1"
	    />

	    When a network is moved from one datacenter or cloud
	    system to another, it must be permitted and authorized by
	    the destination system in some way.
	  </t>
	  <t>
	    High-Availability of user networks <vspace blankLines="1"
	    />

	    Even if using VLAN and VPN technologies, each user network
	    has a single connecting point to the Internet. It may be a
	    single point of failure of inter-datacenter and
	    inter-clouds PaaS service. Network potability in
	    inter-datacenters and inter-clouds should provide
	    High-Availability capability.
	  </t>
	</list>
      </t>
    </section>

    <section title="Network Portability Models">
      <t>
	We consider two kinds of network portability models in this
	draft.  One is the host-oriented portability model, and the
	other is the network-oriented portability model.
      </t>

      <section title="Host-oriented Portability Model">
	<t>
	  In this model, each host (virtual machine) manages the
	  network portability.  To adpot this model, each host must be
	  equipped with some kinds of host mobility support.  Every
	  time a host migrates from one hypervisor to another
	  hypervisor and the attached network environment of the
	  migrated host changes, the host must be trigger mobility
	  function to adapt the current attached network environment.
	  Examples implementation of this model are using host
	  mobility protocols such as <xref target="RFC5944">Mobile
	  IP</xref>, <xref target="RFC6275">Mobile IPv6</xref>, <xref
	  target="RFC5201">HIP</xref>, or <xref
	  target="I-D.ietf-lisp">LISP</xref> and advertising host route
	  entry from the moving node.
	</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Network-oriented Portability Model">
	<t>
	  In this model, the network resource to which the host is
	  attached before migration and after migration does not
	  change.  Since the migrated host doesn't notice the network
	  environment change, it can continue to work after the
	  migration.  To provide the same network environment, the
	  cloud system must support network resource migration between
	  the previous location and current location of the host.
	  Examples of this model is using VLAN, and using VPN
	  connection.
	</t>
      </section>

    </section>

    <section title="Implementation Examples">
      <t>
	In this section, we show some of the implementation example of
	network portability in cloud system.  <xref
	target="VLAN-based" /> describes an example of the
	network-based network portability implementation using wide
	area VLAN configuration.  <xref target="NEMO-based" />
	describes another example of the network-based network
	portability implementation using <xref target="RFC3963">NEMO
	BS.</xref> <xref target="MIPv6-based" /> describes an example
	of the host-based network portability implementation using
	Mobile IPv6.  <xref target="Routing-based" /> describes
	another example of the host-based network portability
	implementation using host route technology.  <xref
	target="LISP-based" /> shows yet another example of host-based
	approach.
      </t>

      <section anchor="VLAN-based" title="Wide area VLAN-based Network Porability">
	<t>
	  One possible solution to provide network portability in a
	  cloud system is that to provide a seamless layer 2 network
	  to the entire cloud system.  Recently, since the wide area
	  connectivity is getting faster and faster, so it becomes
	  realistic to extend a layer 2 network from one site to other
	  site where is geographically far.
	</t>
	<t>
	  In this case, the hypervisor and host configuration become
	  simple.  All the hypervisors are attached to the same layer
	  2 link which is widely extended to every sites which consist
	  the entire cloud system.  A host is configured with the
	  network which is bridged to the wide area layer 2 network.
	</t>
	<t>
	  The migration procedure does not require any additional
	  configuration or operation.  Since all the hypervisors share
	  the same layer 2 network, hosts can migrate to any one of
	  the hypervisors attached to the layer 2 network.
	</t>
	<t>
	  The policy management of the network resource mobility is
	  performed as a part of the VLAN management.  Whether the
	  destination service provider accept network resource
	  migration or not is same as whether they accept to offer
	  their VLAN resource to the source service provider.
	</t>
	<t>
	  For the redundancy, the same technologies for VLAN can be
	  used.
	</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="NEMO-based" title="NEMO-based Network Porability">
	<t>Another way to provide network portability is to use
	  network mobility technology such
	  as <xref target="RFC3963">NEMO BS</xref>.  In this model,
	  the cloud operator puts several mobile routers (MRs) in the
	  cloud and assigns mobile network prefixes (MNPs) to each of
	  the MR.  The MRs are basically hidden to the users of the
	  cloud system.  Users do not need to know what is happning
	  when the network migration occurs.
	</t>
	<t>The MRs are prepared as virtual machines in the cloud
	  system as same as other normal host machines.  Since the MNP
	  bound to each MR moves with the MR, all the hosts attached
	  to the MNP must also move with the MR.  Below is an example
	  operation of the migration procedure performed in this
	  case.
	</t>
	<t>The cloud system first prepares a home network prefix used
	  as a base network of all the MRs in the cloud system, and
	  prepares a home agent (HA) to serve the network mobility
	  function.  Each MR has two network interfaces; one is for
	  the local attachment point to get a care-of address, the
	  other is for the presistent network to host other virtual
	  machines which move with the MR.
	</t>
	<t>As many virtual machies as possible can be put on the
	  persistent network of the MR, however, when network
	  migration is performed, all the machines inside the
	  persistent network must be moved altogether.  So, if we want
	  to move a virtual machine one by one, we must put only one
	  virtual machine in the persistent segment.  It depends on
	  the configuration of the service system.  For example, if we
	  design a kind of web service system that consists of a web
	  server and a backend database server, then we may put these
	  two into the one persistent network.  Because those two
	  servers must be on the same segment anyway, simultaneous
	  migration will not be a limitation in this scenario.
	</t>
	<t>The persistent networks that are bound to MNPs are virtual
	  networks defined in hypervisors.  The requirement to the
	  virtual network is that the network must be identified by a
	  virtual machine with a static identifier (e.g. the name of
	  the virtual network) independent of the hypervisors on which
	  the virtual machine runs.  For example, if a virtual machine
	  attaches to a virtual network whose name is 'mobile-net-1'
	  on hypervisor A and migrates to hypervisor B, then the
	  hypervisor B must be able to provide a virtual network which
	  is identified by the name 'mobile-net-1'.
	</t>
	<t>Whem a network is migrated, all the related virtual
	  machines must be moved to the same destination hypervisor.
	  That includes a MR, all the hosts attached to the MNP of the
	  MR.  Once a MR migrates to other hypervisor, it will detect
	  the external interface status and find that the network is
	  changed.  The MR then initiates the procedure of NEMO BS,
	  acquires a new care-of address, and registers its new
	  location to the HA.  For the hosts inside the MNP, no
	  additional action is required, since the network environment
	  of the MNP is maintained by the MR and no change happens to
	  that network.
	</t>
	<t>
	  The policy management of the network resource mobility is
	  performed as a part of mobility management policy of NEMO
	  BS.  For example, some kind of roaming mechanism between the
	  source and destination service providers and service level
	  agreement are used to implement the policy management.
	</t>
	<t>Similar to Mobile IPv6, the system may need to deploy some
	  mechanisms to add high availability function to the home
	  agent, since it is a single point of failure of Mobile
	  IPv6-based mechanism.  The mechanism for high availability
	  of home agents is out of scope of this document.
	</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="MIPv6-based" title="Mobile IPv6-based Network Porability">
	<t>
	  In this case, all the hosts (which are virtual machines in a
	  cloud system) are assumed to have Mobile IP function.  A
	  home agent must also exist as a part of the cloud system to
	  serve home network of the mobile hosts.
	</t>
	<t>
	  Each host attaches to any one of the virtual or bridged
	  networks that hypervisors provide.  Based on the procedure
	  of the Mobile IPv6, the host configures its care-of address
	  using some kinds of address configuration mechanisms
	  provided at the attached network, and register it with its
	  home address to the home agent.  The detailed Mobile IPv6
	  operation procedure and configuration procedures is not
	  described here.
	</t>
	<t>When a host is migrated from one hypervisor to another
	  hypervisor, the network to which the migrated host attached
	  changes, if the hypervisors are not attached to the same
	  network segment.  The migrated host detects the new network
	  environment using the Mobile IPv6 function, and acquire a
	  new care-of address of the network under the new
	  hypervisor.
	</t>
	<t>
	  As same as the NEMO BS case, the policy management of the
	  network resource mobility is performed as a part of mobility
	  management policy of Mobile IPv6.  For example, some kind of
	  roaming mechanism between the source and destination service
	  providers and service level agreement are used to implement
	  the policy management.
	</t>
	<t>Similar to Mobile IPv6, the system may need to deploy some
	  mechanisms to add high availability function to the home
	  agent, since it is a single point of failure of Mobile
	  IPv6-based mechanism.  The mechanism for high availability
	  of home agents is out of scope of this document.
	</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="Routing-based" title="Routing-based Network Portability">
	<t>
	  Using host route entry is another way to implement
	  host-based network portability.  In order to use this
	  mothod, every host which is moving between different
	  networks must run routing daemon program on it.  The node
	  advertises its host route entry to the upstream router of
	  the attached segment periodically.
	</t>
	<t>
	  As you can see, this method needs access right to the
	  routing repository of the attached cloud system.  Also,
	  distributing host route entry is impossible from different
	  AS domain.  So this method is usually limited to one
	  administrative domain.
	</t>
	<t>
	  The policy management of the network resource mobility is
	  performed as a part of route filtering mechanism.  The
	  destination service provider has to configure their routers
	  to accept routing information sent from legitimate moving
	  virtual machines.
	</t>
	<t>
	  To achieve redundancy, any kind of redundancy mechanisms of
	  routing layer can be used.
	</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="LISP-based" title="LISP-based Network Portability">
	<t>
	  LISP is a two layer communication protocol that aims to
	  separate locator layer and identifier layer.  Applying this
	  technology to a host enables the host to move everywhere in
	  the Internet.
	</t>
	<t>
	  In this scenario, every network segments where virtual
	  machines are supposed to be migrated must have LISP
	  capability, that is, every network must have at least one
	  XTR node to intercept traffic from the LISP-based virtual
	  machines and tunnel it to the other end of XTR or ITR which
	  is the tunnel end node of the destination identifier of the
	  traffic.  Also, because this mechanism is using LISP, the
	  entire system must have some kind of locator-identifier
	  mapping system which is being discussed in the LISP Working
	  Group.
	</t>
	<t>
	  The policy management of the network resource mobility is
	  performed as a part of the LISP operation.  The XTR node of
	  the destination service provider must be configured to
	  accept the legitimate LISP-based virtual machines.
	</t>
	<t>
	  The redundancy will be provided as a part of the LISP
	  operation too.
	</t>
      </section>

    </section>

    <section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>We thank the members of the WIDE project for discussion on
	this network migration technologies, and their bravery to use
	the experimental cloud system we constructed.</t>
    </section>

    <!-- Possibly a 'Contributors' section ... -->

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>This memo includes no request to IANA.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>The management NEMO HA shuld be secure and the tunnels
	between NEMO nodes should use secure transportation, such as
	SSL or IPsec.
      </t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <!--  *****BACK MATTER ***** -->

  <back>
    <!-- References split into informative and normative -->

    <!-- There are 2 ways to insert reference entries from the citation libraries:
     1. define an ENTITY at the top, and use "ampersand character"RFC2629; here (as shown)
     2. simply use a PI "less than character"?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119.xml"?> here
        (for I-Ds: include="reference.I-D.narten-iana-considerations-rfc2434bis.xml")

     Both are cited textually in the same manner: by using xref elements.
     If you use the PI option, xml2rfc will, by default, try to find included files in the same
     directory as the including file. You can also define the XML_LIBRARY environment variable
     with a value containing a set of directories to search.  These can be either in the local
     filing system or remote ones accessed by http (http://domain/dir/... ).-->

    <references title="Normative References">
      <!--?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"?-->
      &RFC3963;
      &RFC5201;
      &RFC5944;
      &RFC6275;
      &LISP;
    </references>

  </back>
</rfc>
