<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<rfc category="std" docName="draft-bcd-6man-ntp-server-ra-opt-00 "
     ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="IPv6 Router Advertisement Support for NTP">IPv6 Router Advertisement Option for NTP Server Configuration </title>

<author fullname="Manav Bhatia" initials="M." surname="Bhatia">
      <organization>Alcatel-Lucent</organization>

      <address>
        <email>manav.bhatia@alcatel-lucent.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

<author fullname="Xu Chen" initials="X." surname="Chen">
      <organization>Huawei</organization>

      <address>
        <email>zhangdacheng@huawei.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>


   <author fullname="Dacheng Zhang" initials="D." surname="Zhang">
      <organization>Huawei</organization>

      <address>
        <email>zhangdacheng@huawei.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>


  
    <date day="20" month="December" year="2011" />

    <abstract>
      <t> This document specifies a new IPv6 Router Advertisement option to
   allow IPv6 routers to advertise Network Time Protocol version 4 or greater server
   location information to IPv6 hosts.</t>
    </abstract>

    <note title="Requirements Language">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
      document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
      target="RFC2119">RFC 2119</xref>.</t>
    </note>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
	<t>NTP <xref target="RFC5905"></xref> servers form a core component of the Internet infrastructure.  They are
         used to provide time and synchronization services for hosts and routers in a network, 
          which is critical for many applications (event logging, security mechanisms and other
          services). In order to synchronize the time, all routers and hosts need to be configured
          to point to a NTP server that will provide clocking to all the devices. This ensures accurate
         and synchronized time among all devices. Its usually recommended to choose
         among several NTP servers in case one of the servers becomes unreachable or
         its clock becomes unreliable.</t>

      <t>Neighbor Discovery (ND) for IP Version 6 and IPv6 Stateless Address
   Autoconfiguration provide ways to configure either fixed or mobile
   nodes with one or more IPv6 addresses, default routers and some other
   parameters like the link-layer address of the interface from which
   the Router Advertisement is sent, link MTU <xref target="RFC4861"></xref>, 
   IP address of the DNS servers <xref target="RFC5006"></xref>, etc. 
   </t>

      <t> This document proposes a new mechanism which uses a new IPv6
   Router Advertisement (RA) option to allow IPv6 routers to advertise
   NTP server addresses to IPv6 hosts.
</t>

	<t> RA-based NTP configuration is a useful, optional alternative in
   networks where an IPv6 host's address is autoconfigured through IPv6
   stateless address autoconfiguration, and where the delays in
   acquiring server addresses and communicating with the servers are
   critical.  RA-based NTP configuration allows the host to acquire the
   nearest server addresses on every link.  Furthermore, it learns these
   addresses from the same RA message that provides configuration
   information for the link, thereby avoiding an additional protocol
   run.  This can be beneficial in some mobile environments, such as
   with Mobile IPv6.
	</t>

	<t> The NTP Server Option that this document proposes is an extension of 
          Router Advertisment. It does not change the basic function of the existing ND/SLAAC mechanisms.
	</t>

	<t> Information that an IPv6 host or a router needs to run the basic Internet  
           applications (such as the Clock Synchronization, Timestamp Verification, Certificate Expiration check, etc.) 
           can be obtained with the addition of this option to Neighbor Discovery and address autoconfiguration. 
	</t>

	<t> This mechanism works over a broad range of scenarios and leverages IPv6 Neighbor Discovery.  
           This works well on links that are high performance (e.g., Ethernet LANs) and low performance
            (e.g., cellular networks). In the latter case, by combining the NTP server information (that this draft proposes) 
           with the other information in the Router Advertisement, the IPv6 devices can learn all the information needed to use 
         most Internet applications in a single transaction. This not only saves bandwidth, but also minimizes the delay 
         needed to learn the NTP server information.
	</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Overview">
	<t> This document defines a new ND option called NTP Server option that
   contains the addresses of the NTP servers.  Existing ND
   transport mechanisms (i.e., Advertisements and Solicitations) are
   used.  This works in the same way that hosts learn about routers and
   prefixes.  An IPv6 host can configure the IPv6 addresses of one or
   more NTP servers via RA messages periodically sent by a router or
   solicited by Router Solicitation (RS) messages.
	</t>

	<t> This approach requires NTP Server information to be configured in the
   routers sending the advertisements.  The configuration of NTP server
   addresses in the routers can be done by manual configuration. The
   automatic configuration of NTP server addresses in routers is out of scope
   for this document.
	</t>

    <t>The location of the NTP service, like any other Internet service, can
   be specified by an IP address or a Fully Qualified Domain Name
   (FQDN). 
	</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="NDE" title="Neighbor Discovery Extension">
	<t> The IPv6 NTP configuration mechanism in this document defines a new ND
   option in Neighbor Discovery - the NTP Server (NTPS) option.

   This option serves as a container for server location information
   related to one NTP server or Simple Network Time Protocol (SNTP) 
   <xref target="RFC4330"></xref>
   server.  This option can appear multiple times in a RA
   message.  Each instance of this option is to be considered by the NTP
   client or SNTP client as a server to include in its configuration.
	</t>
	<t> The option itself does not contain any value.  Instead, it contains
   one or several suboptions that carry NTP server or SNTP server
   location.  This option MUST include one, and only one, time source
   suboption.  It carries the NTP server or SNTP server location as a Unicast or
   Multicast IPv6 address or as an NTP server or SNTP server FQDN.  More
   time source suboptions may be defined in the future.  While the FQDN
   option offers the most deployment flexibility, resiliency as well as
   security, the IP address options are defined to cover cases where a
   DNS dependency is not desirable.

   If the NTP server or SNTP server location is an IPv6 multicast
   address, the client SHOULD use this address as an NTP multicast group
   address and listen to messages sent to this group in order to
   synchronize its clock. </t>

<t>     The format of the NTP Server (NTPS) Option is:
	</t>

<figure title='Figure 1: NTP Server Option in the RA'>
	 <artwork align='center'>
        0                   1                   2                   3
         0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
        +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
        |     Type      |     Length    |
        +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
        |                                                               |
        |                                                               |
        ~               NTP Server Address Sub Options                  ~
        |                                                               |
        |                                                               |
        +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+                                                               |
        |                                                               |
        ~                         Padding                               ~
        |                                                               |
        |                                                               |
        +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+

	</artwork>
         </figure>

	<t> Fields:
	</t>

	<t> Type:  8 bit identifier of the NTP Server option type in the RA message - To be assigned by IANA.
	</t>

	<t> Length: 8 bit unsigned integer. Total length of the included 
           sub options (including the Type and Length fields) is in units of
                   8 octets.  
	</t>
	<t>NTP Server Address Sub Options : List of NTP server addresses sub options
	</t>

	<t> Padding: It is optional and is used, if required, to preserve IPv6 8-octet alignment.
	</t>

    <section anchor="Unicast" title="NTP Server Unicast Address Suboption">
	<t> This suboption is intended to appear inside the NTP Server Option within the RA message.
    It specifies the IPv6 unicast address of an NTP server or
   SNTP server available to the client.
	</t>

<figure title='Figure 2: NTP Server Unicast Address Suboption'>
	 <artwork align='center'>
        0                   1                   2                   3
         0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
        +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
        |     Type      |     Length    |
        +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
        |                                                               |
        |                                                               |
        |               Unicast IPv6 address of NTP server              |
        |                                                               |
        +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+           
	</artwork>
         </figure>

	<t> Fields:
	</t>

	<t> Type:  8 bit identifier of the NTP Server Unicast Address Suboption - To be assigned by IANA.
	</t>

	<t> Length:8 bit unsigned integer. Total length of the sub options (including the Type and Length fields) 
           in octets. Its set to 18
	</t>

	<t> Unicast IPv6 address of NTP server:  An IPv6 Address
	</t>
	</section>

<section anchor="mcast" title="NTP Server Multicast Address Suboption">
	<t> This suboption is intended to appear inside the NTP Server Option within the RA message.
    It specifies the IPv6 Multicast Group address of an NTP server or
   SNTP server available to the client.
	</t>

<figure title='Figure 2: NTP Server Multicast Address Suboption'>
	 <artwork align='center'>
        0                   1                   2                   3
         0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
        +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
        |     Type      |     Length    |
        +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
        |                                                               |
        |                                                               |
        |             Multicast IPv6 address of NTP server              |
        |                                                               |
        +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+                                                               |

	</artwork>
         </figure>

	<t> Fields:
	</t>

	<t> Type:  8 bit identifier of the NTP Server Multicast Address Suboption - To be assigned by IANA.
	</t>

	<t> Length:8 bit unsigned integer. Total length of the sub options (including the Type and Length fields) 
           in octets. Its set to 18
	</t>

	<t> Multicast IPv6 address of NTP server:  An IPv6 Address
	</t>
	</section>

<section anchor="fqdn" title="NTP Server FQDN Suboption">
	<t> This suboption is intended to appear inside the NTP Server Option within the RA message.
    It specifies the FQDN of an NTP server or
   SNTP server available to the client.
	</t>

<figure title='Figure 2: NTP Server FQDN Suboption'>
	 <artwork align='center'>
         0                   1                   2                   3
         0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
        +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
        |     Type      |     Length    |
        +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
        |                                                               |
        |                                                               |
        |                   FQDN of NTP server                          |
        |                                                               |
        +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+                                                               |
                             

	</artwork>
         </figure>

	<t> Fields:
	</t>

	<t> Type:  8 bit identifier of the NTP Server FQDN Suboption - To be assigned by IANA.
	</t>

	<t> Length:8 bit unsigned integer. Total length of the FQDN field and including the Type and Length fields 
           in octets. 
	</t>

	<t> FQDN of NTP server:   Fully-Qualified Domain Name of the NTP server or SNTP server.
           This field MUST be encoded as described in <xref target="RFC3315"></xref>. Internationalized domain names are not allowed
           in this field.
	</t>
	</section>
	</section>

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>Because NTPS option does not change the base functions of existing
   ND/SLAAC mechanism, it can be claimed that the NTP Server option for RA has
   vulnerabilities similar to those existing in current mechanisms. If
   the Secure Neighbor Discovery (SEND) protocol is used as a security
   mechanism for ND, all the ND options including the NTP Server option are
   automatically included in the signatures <xref target="RFC3971"></xref>, and the NTPS
   transport is integrity-protected.</t>
      
    </section>

<section anchor="iana" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>IANA needs to assign an option code for the NTP Server Option that will 
            be used in the Router Advertisments. </t>
       <t> IANA is required to maintain a new number space of NTP Server 
   suboptions as defined in this document. IANA
   should assign future NTP time source suboptions with an "IETF Consensus"
   policy as described in <xref target="RFC5226"></xref>.

</t>
      
    </section>

    <section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>This document is built upon draft-chen-ntps-ra-opt-00 which 
           expired eons ago.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119"?>
<?rfc include='reference.RFC.4861'?>
<?rfc include='reference.RFC.5905'?>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      
<?rfc include='reference.RFC.3971'?>
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.5006'?> 
     <?rfc include='reference.RFC.4330'?>
   <?rfc include='reference.RFC.3315'?>
<?rfc include='reference.RFC.5226'?>
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
