<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="no"?>
<?rfc comments="no"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>


<rfc category="info" docName="draft-sprecher-mpls-tp-migration-03.txt"
     ipr="pre5378Trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="MPLS-TP migration">
					Migration Considerations and Techniques for Multiprotocol Label Switching Transport 
					Profile based Networks and Services</title>

    <author fullname="Nurit Sprecher" initials="N." surname="Sprecher">
      <organization>Nokia Siemens Networks</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>3 Hanagar St. Neve Ne'eman B</street>

          <city>Hod Hasharon</city>

          <region />

          <code>45241</code>

          <country>Israel</country>
        </postal>

        <email>nurit.sprecher@nsn.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Yaacov Weingarten" initials="Y." surname="Weingarten">
      <organization>Nokia Siemens Networks</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>3 Hanagar St. Neve Ne'eman B</street>

          <city>Hod Hasharon</city>

          <region />

          <code>45241</code>

          <country>Israel</country>
        </postal>
		
        <email>yaacov.weingarten@nsn.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
      
     <author fullname="Kyung-Yeop Hong" initials="K.Y." surname="Hong">
      <organization>Cisco Systems, Inc.</organization> 
	  <address>
        <postal>
          <street>300 Beaver Brook Road</street>

          <city>Boxborough</city>

          <region>Massachusetts</region>

          <code>01719</code>

          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>
		
        <email>hongk@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

     <author fullname="Luyuan Fang" initials="L." surname="Fang">
      <organization>Cisco Systems, Inc. </organization> 	  
	   <address>
        <postal>
          <street>300 Beaver Brook Road</street>

          <city>Boxborough</city>

          <region>MA</region>

          <code>01719</code>

          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>
		
        <email>lufang@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
	  
	  </author>


   
    <date year="2011" />

    <abstract>
	  
	  <t>MPLS-TP defines a packet-based network architecture and a comprehensive set 
	  of tools that allow service providers to reliably deliver next generation services 
	  and applications, in a simple, scalable, and cost-effective way. Such services 
	  are BW-hungry based and require strict guaranteed SLA. Delivering next generation 
	  services over an MPLS-TP based network in an economic way, enables service providers 
	  to remain competitive while increasing their revenues.</t> 
	  <t>This document presents the motivations for migrating from different legacy transport 
	  networks and services to MPLS-TP, and discusses the considerations and strategies  
	  for the migration.</t>
	  <t>The document also proposes specific activities and techniques needed to ensure 
	  a smooth migration path from the different transport networks and services to MPLS-TP.
	  </t>
    </abstract>

  </front>

  <middle>
  <note title='Editors&apos; Note:'>
	<t>This Informational Internet-Draft is aimed at achieving IETF Consensus before 
	publication as an RFC and will be subject to an IETF Last Call.</t>
	<t>[RFC Editor, please remove this note before publication as an RFC and insert the 
	correct Streams Boilerplate to indicate that the published RFC has IETF Consensus.]</t>
    </note>

    <section title="Introduction">
		
		<section title="Overview of MPLS-TP">
		  <t>The Transport Profile for MPLS (MPLS-TP) is being specified in the IETF 
		  as part of a joint effort with the ITU-T to develop a definition of the MPLS 
		  network that will fulfill the strict requirements for transport networks that 
		  are accepted by the ITU-T.  This profile will be based on the definitions of 
		  the MPLS, MPLS Traffic Engineering, and Multi-Segment Pseudo-Wire architectures 
		  defined in <xref target="RFC3031" />, <xref target="RFC3985" />, and 
		  <xref target="RFC5659" />.</t>
		  
		  <t>The requirements for MPLS-TP are detailed in <xref target="RFC5654" />.  These
		  requirements were developed in full cooperation between the IETF and ITU-T, and 
		  reflect the needs to adhere to the architecture of MPLS while including the 
		  enhanced level of service transparency, and  Operations, Administration, and 
		  Maintenance (OAM) functionality required for stable transport networks.  The
		  requirements for the OAM functionality are further developed and defined in 
		  <xref target="MPLS-TP-OAM" />, providing the list of OAM procedures to be 
		  supported by MPLS-TP.</t>
		  
		  <t>The architecture for MPLS-TP is defined in <xref target="RFC5921" /> 
		  and builds upon the experience of the MPLS architecture.  The architecture is
		  designed to allow MPLS-TP networks to operate whether the configuration was
		  implemented by use of control-plane signaling or a management application.  
		  In addition, the MPLS-TP architecture is designed to support networks that may 
		  not be using IP forwarding and addressing.  The framework defines the different 
		  service structures supported by MPLS-TP and the interworking between these 
		  service structures and existing MPLS services.  Also defined are the characteristics 
		  of the profile that defines MPLS-TP.  This synergy of architectures guarantees the 
		  service provider the ability to provide services with guaranteed and strict Service 
		  Level Agreements in a highly scalable robust network while reducing operational costs.</t>
		  
		  <t>A main focus of MPLS-TP is the definition of OAM functionality for MPLS 
		  data paths that support the transport services.  MPLS-TP provides a comprehensive 
		  set of OAM tools for fault management and performance monitoring, supporting the 
		  network and the services at different nested levels (i.e. at the end-to-end level, 
		  a segment of a path, and link level). The OAM tools may be used to monitor the 
		  network infrastructure, to enhance the general behavior, and performance level of 
		  the network. The tools may also be used to monitor the service level offered to 
		  the end customer, allowing verification of the SLA parameters, and enabling rapid 
		  response in the event of a failure or service degradation. The OAM tools help
		  reduce OPEX, minimizing the overhead of trouble shooting, and enhancing customer 
		  satisfaction which, in turn, helps to enable the delivery of high-margin premium 
		  services. </t>
		  
		  <t> The architectural constructs and the methodology of the OAM functionality is 
		  defined by <xref target="MPLS-TP-OAM-Fwk" />.  This includes the definition of 
		  the transport entities that are monitored by the OAM procedures and detailed 
		  description of how the OAM procedures are applied to these transport entities.  
		  A central issue in MPLS-TP OAM is the independence of the OAM from the existence of an 
		  operational control plane in the network.  This feature is supported by the 
		  creation of an in-band control channel that is used to transmit the OAM 
		  procedures across the transport paths.  A cornerstone of the definition of the 
		  OAM procedures is to use existing IETF OAM tools as the basis of the MPLS-TP 
		  OAM procedures wherever possible, this principle is used as the underlying 
		  foundation for the definition of the OAM tools defined for MPLS-TP.</t>
		  
		  <t>Protection mechanisms for the MPLS-TP transport paths are described in 
		  <xref target="MPLS-TP-Surviv" /> and are conformed with different topological
		  configurations of the network.</t>
		</section>
		
		<section title="Motivations for Upgrading Networks">
		  <t>The growth of packet traffic has significantly increased, driven by the high demand 
		  and penetration of new packet-based services and multimedia applications, across the 
		  access, aggregation and core networks and is expected to continue to increase. 
		  With the movement toward packet-based services, the transport network has to evolve 
		  to encompass the provision of packet-aware capabilities while enabling carriers to 
		  leverage their installed, as well as planned, transport infrastructure investments.</t>
		   
		  <t>Carriers are in need of technologies capable of efficiently supporting packet-based 
		  services and applications on their transport networks with guaranteed Service Level 
		  Agreements (SLAs).  The need to increase their revenue while remaining competitive 
		  forces operators to look for the lowest network Total Cost of Ownership (TCO), and 
		  as such requires investment in equipment and facilities (Capital Expenditure (CAPEX)) 
		  and Operational Expenditure (OPEX) be minimized.</t>
			  
		  <t>There are a number of technology options for carriers to meet the challenge of increased 
 		   service sophistication and transport efficiency, with increasing usage of hybrid packet-transport 
		   and circuit-transport technology solutions.  To address this challenge, it is essential that 
		   packet-transport technology be available that can provide reliability, operational simplicity -
		   preserving the look and feel to which service providers have accustomed, multi-layer operations, 
		   resiliency, control, and multi-technology management.</t>

		  <t>Transport carriers require control and deterministic usage of network resources.  They need 
		  end-to-end control to engineer network paths and to efficiently utilize network resources.  
		  They require capabilities to support static (management-plane-based) or dynamic (control-plane-based) 
		  provisioning of deterministic, protected, and secured services and their associated resources. For 
		  transport carriers, it is also important to ensure smooth interworking of the packet transport network 
		  with other existing/legacy packet networks, and provide mappings to enable packet transport carriage 
		  over a variety of transport network infrastructures.</t>

		  <t>MPLS is a maturing packet technology and it is already playing an important role in transport 
		  networks and services. The development of MPLS-TP has proposed a set of compatible technology 
		  enhancements to existing MPLS standards to extent the definition of MPLS toward supporting traditional 
		  transport operational models. These enhancements inherit all the supporting QoS, recovery, control and 
		  data plane mechanisms already defined within standards. MPLS-TP will enable the deployment of packet-based 
		  transport networks that will efficiently scale to support packet services in a simple and cost-effective 
		  way.</t>  
		</section>
		
    </section>
	  
    <section title="Terminology and References">
	  <section title="Acronyms">
	    <texttable align="left" style="none">
          <preamble>This draft uses the following acronyms:</preamble>

          <ttcol align="left"></ttcol>

          <ttcol align="left"></ttcol>

          <c>MPLS-TP</c>

          <c>Multiprotocol Label Switching - Transport Protocol</c>

          <c>OAM</c>

          <c>Operations, Administration, and Maintenance</c>
		</texttable>
	  </section>
    </section>
	  
    <section title="General Migration Strategies">
	  <t>A migration strategy is necessary for service providers to maintain their installed 
	  base and minimize the investment in new equipment.  The migration should be a smooth and
	  seamless transfer of technology while continuing to support the services that generate
	  the revenues.  This means that the migration strategy should address the following 
	  considerations:</t>
	  
	  <list style="symbols">
		<t>Cost-effective &ndash; Minimize the number of migration steps, stay within budget for
		both operating (OPEX) and capital (CAPEX) expenses.</t>
		<t>Service continuity &ndash; perform the switchover without a service break to existing
		customers and their services.</t>
		<t>Provide a reliable fall-back &ndash; don't burn your bridges until the new connections
		are secure and robust enough to maintain the service-level agreements.</t>
		<t>Minimum switchover time &ndash; when everything is in place need to minimize the 
		side-effects by minimizing the time needed to have the new service platform performing.</t>
		<t>Aspects of data-plane, OAM and recovery mechanisms, control plane and management-plane</t>
		</list>
	  
	  <t>Different migration models have been discussed in the literature.  The most basic 
	  model, forklifting the new technology, in our case MPLS-TP, onto the network involves
	  simultaneously upgrading the entire network to work with the new technology.  This 
	  type of migration is very risky if the new technology does not work as expected in 
	  the live network after disabling the legacy technology.  In order to minimize the risk,
	  it could be possible to install an entire parallel network based on MPLS-TP and then
	  switch over from the legacy network to the MPLS-TP network.  However, this would be very 
	  costly, i.e. purchasing equipment for two parallel networks, and again could not 
	  guarantee that the new technology network would work as planned.  This, in turn, would 
	  cause a major disruption of services.  Therefore, in the following descriptions we 
	  concentrate on the following models:</t>
	  
	  <list style="symbols">
	    <t>Island model &ndash; introducing the MPLS-TP in separate sub-domains of the 
		network.  The transport paths may cross the different technology domains that are 
		connected by gateways.  See section 3.1 for more details.</t>
		<t>Phased model &ndash; where the existing equipment is slowly upgraded with new
		MPLS-TP capabilities as needed.  For more details see section 3.2.</t>
		<t>Integrated model &ndash; network nodes are either legacy nodes or dual-mode 
		nodes supporting both legacy and MPLS-TP capabilities.  See section 3.3 for more
		details.</t>
		</list>
	  
	   <t>It should be noted that not all of these models are relevant to migration from
	   specific legacy technologies.  The relevance for each technology of the particular 
	   migration model will be discussed in the sections below that discuss the specific
	   technologies.</t> 
	   
	 <section title="Island model">
	   <t>In this migration model presented previously in <xref target="RFC5145" /> the 
	   service provider introduces clusters of MPLS-TP nodes that are interconnected with 
	   the legacy clusters through border nodes.  The border nodes act as gateways, that
	   are responsible for the mapping or adaptation of protocol elements that may be 
	   transmitted between legacy and MPLS-TP nodes.</t>
	   
	   <t>End-to-end services may traverse between the islands.  The configuration of the 
	   transport paths may be &quot;balanced&quot; or &quot;unbalanced&quot;.  In a 
	   balanced path configuration both endpoints of the path are nodes of the same 
	   technology, but the path may have crossed islands of the other technology in the
	   middle of the path, see <xref target="figure1" />.  An unbalanced path 
	   configuration would be if the path starts at a node of one technology and ends 
	   at a node supporting the second technology, see <xref target="figure1" />.</t>
	   
        <figure anchor="figure1" title="Balanced island path">
          <artwork><![CDATA[

     +----+   +--+   +----+   +--+   +----+  +--+   +----+
     |Lgcy|   |LN|   |Brdr|   |TP|   |Brdr|  |LN|   |Lgcy|
     |    |==========|    |==========|    |=========|    |
   ..|........Service...Transport...Path.................|...
     |    |==========|    |==========|    |=========|    |
     |Conn|   |  |   |Gtwy|   |  |   |Gtwy|  |  |   |Conn|
     +----+   +--+   +----+   +--+   +----+  +--+   +----+
     .                . .              . .              .
     |     Legacy     | |    MPLS-TP   | |    Legacy    |
     |<----Island---->| |<---Island--->| |<---Island--->|
	 
               LN - one or more Legacy Nodes
               TP - one or more MPLS-TP LSR
        Brdr Gtwy - Border node that acts as gateway
        Lgcy Conn - Legacy node that where service connects
   ]]></artwork>
        </figure>

        <figure anchor="figure2" title="Unbalanced island path">
          <artwork><![CDATA[

         +----+   +--+   +----+   +--+   +----+
         |Lgcy|   |LN|   |Brdr|   |TP|   | TP |
         |    |==========|    |==========|    |
     ....|...Service...Transport...Path.......|...
         |    |==========|    |==========|    |
         |Conn|   |  |   |Gtwy|   |  |   |Conn|
         +----+   +--+   +----+   +--+   +----+
         .                . .              . 
         |     Legacy     | |    MPLS-TP   |
         |<----Island---->| |<---Island--->| 
		 
                 LN - one or more Legacy Nodes
                 TP - one or more MPLS-TP LSR
          Brdr Gtwy - Border node that acts as gateway
          Lgcy Conn - Legacy node that where service connects
		   TP  Conn - MPLS-TP LER
   ]]></artwork>
        </figure>

 	   <t>The tools that may be used at the border, gateway, nodes may be based
	   on either layered networks &ndash; only when using balanced islands, or
	   on an interworking or mapping function between protocols.  An MPLS-TP 
	   island would provide the layered network solution through the use of 
	   an LSP between TE-links to carry legacy traffic, when possible.</t>
	   
	   <t>This model is very useful when upgrading the network in stages, where
	   new MPLS-TP equipment is upgraded in clusters that form an island.  These
	   islands can be slowly expanded and merged until they create a single 
	   MPLS-TP network.  Whenever the islands are expanded or merged make-before-break
	   procedures should be employed in order to keep services running.</t>
	   </section>
	   
	 <section title="Phased model">
	   <t>In this model the existing equipment is upgraded with the features and 
	   functionality of the new technology.  The new functionality is introduced as
	   needed, while ensuring interoperability with the legacy technology.  This is
	   highly dependent upon the equipment to support the new functionality and the
	   support of all the vendors to implement the same functionality.</t>
	   
	   <t>The advantage of this model is that it allows the service provider to 
	   quickly support enhanced capabilities on his existing equipment.  However, 
	   this model is not applicable to all legacy technologies.  For this to work
	   the new capabilities need to be backward compatible with the legacy 
	   technology, and all of the vendors, involved in the migration, need to 
	   implement the new capabilities specified by the service provider.</t>
	   </section>
	   
	 <section title="Integrated model">
	   <t>This model allows the operator to run services over two clouds of the
	   network simultaneously.  One cloud would continue to support the legacy
	   technology, while the second cloud would support the new MPLS-TP services.  
	   The services would be routed to the proper cloud by new &quot;dual-mode&quot;
	   nodes that would support an integrated MPLS-TP and legacy functionality, see
	   <xref target="figure3" />.  These dual-mode nodes would route the different 
	   services to the paths in the different technology clouds.  This avoids the
	   need for interworking that is required in the island model described in 
	   section 3.1.</t>

        <figure anchor="figure3" title="Integrated model network">
          <artwork><![CDATA[
                  ______________________________________
                _/    Service Provider's Network        \
               /             ____     ___       ____     \___     
             _/            _/    \___/   \    _/    \__      \ 
            /             /               \__/ ...     \_     \___
           /             /              .......   ...    \        \
          |    +--------|   ...Legacy Logical Network ..  |---+    |
          |    |.........\..   ..    ..                ../....|    |
          |    |.         \   ___....  ___     __      _/    .|    |
          |  +----+        \_/   \____/   \___/  \____/     +----+ |
         ....|Dual|                                         |Dual|...
          |  |    |                                         |    | |
         ****|Mode|          ____     ___       ____        |Mode|***
          |  +----+        _/    \___/   \    _/    \__     +----+ |
           \   | *        /               \__/         \_    *|    | 
            \  | ******* /***                          **\****|   /
             \ +--------|    ***MPLS-TP Logical Ntwrk***  |---+  /
              \____      \      ***    *****   *****     /      |
                   \      \   ___  ****___  ***__      _/      /
                    \      \_/   \____/   \___/  \____/    ___/
                     \____________________________________/	

                  .... - Legacy service path
                  **** - MPLS-TP service path
   ]]></artwork>
        </figure>

	  <t>Gradual migration is supported by this model.  The dual-mode nodes are 
	  either legacy nodes that are upgraded to support MPLS-TP functionality. 
	  Services can be switched gradually from the legacy transport paths to the 
	  MPLS-TP paths as they become available, using make-before-break procedures.
	  Eventually, as all the service paths are transferred to MPLS-TP the legacy
	  technology cloud can be taken off-line.</t>

	   </section>
	</section>
	
	<section title="Migrating from TDM">
		
		<section title="Main motivation">
		</section>
		
		<section title="Migration Activities and Techniques">
		</section>
	</section> 
	
	<section title="Migrating from ATM">
		
		<section title="Main motivation">
		</section>
		
		<section title="Migration activities and Techniques">
		</section>
	</section> 
		
	<section title="Migrating from Ethernet">
		
		<section title="Main motivation">
		</section>
		
		<section title="Migration activities and Techniques">
		</section>
	</section> 
	
	<section title="Migrating from MPLS">
		
		<section title="MPLS-TE">
			<section title="Main motivation">
			</section>
		
			<section title="Migration activities and Techniques">
			</section>
		</section>			
	
		<section title="IP/MPLS">
			<section title="Main motivation">
			</section>
	
			<section title="Migration activities and Techniques">
			</section>
		</section>	
	</section>

	
	<section title="Migrating from pre-standard MPLS-TP (T-MPLS)">
		
		<section title="Main motivation">
		</section>
		
		<section title="Migration activities and Techniques">
		</section>
	</section> 
	

	<section title="Manageability Considerations">	
	</section>		  
	  
	<section title="Security Considerations">	
	</section>		  
	  
	<section title="IANA Considerations">	
		<t>This informational document makes no requests for IANA action.</t>				 
	</section>	

	<section title="Acknowledgments">	
	</section>		  
	  	  
	</middle>

  <back>
   

   <references title="Normative References"> 
  
	<!--Begin inclusion reference.RFC.5654-->
    <reference anchor="RFC5654">
        <front>
          <title abbrev="RFC5317">Requirements of an MPLS Transport Profile</title> 
           <author fullname="B.Niven-Jenkins" initials="B." role="editor" surname="Niven-Jenkins">
		   </author>
           <author fullname="D.Brungard" initials="D." role="editor" surname="Brungard">
		   </author>
		   <author fullname="M.Betts" initials="M." role="editor" surname="Betts">
		   </author>
		   <author fullname="N.Sprecher" initials="N." surname="Sprecher">
		   </author>
		   <author fullname="S.Ueno" initials="S." surname="Ueno">
		   </author>
          <date year="2009" month="February" /> 
         </front>
         <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="5317" />
     </reference>
      <!-- End inclusion reference.RFC.5317 -->	

	<!--Begin inclusion reference.MPLS-TP-OAM-->
    <reference anchor="MPLS-TP-OAM">
        <front>
          <title abbrev="MPLS-TP-OAM">Requirements for OAM in MPLS Transport Networks</title> 
            <author fullname="Italo Busi" initials="I." role="editor" surname="Busi">
			</author>
            <author fullname="B.Niven-Jenkins" initials="B." role="editor" surname="Niven-Jenkins">
			</author>
         </front>
         <seriesInfo name="draft-ietf-mpls-tp-oam-requirements," value="Work in Progress" />
     </reference>
      <!-- End inclusion reference.MPLS-TP-OAM-->		

	<!--Begin inclusion reference.MPLS-TP-OAM-Framework-->
    <reference anchor="MPLS-TP-OAM-Fwk">
        <front>
          <title abbrev="MPLS-TP-OAM-Framework">A Framework for MPLS in Transport Networks</title> 
            <author fullname="I.Busi" initials="I." role="editor" surname="Busi">
			</author>
            <author fullname="B.Niven-Jenkins" initials="B." role="editor" surname="Niven-Jenkins">
			</author>
         </front>
         <seriesInfo name="draft-ietf-mpls-tp-oam-framework," value="Work in Progress" />
     </reference>
      <!-- End inclusion reference.MPLS-TP-OAM-Framework-->		

	<!--Begin inclusion reference.MPLS-TP-Survivability-Framework-->
    <reference anchor="MPLS-TP-Surviv">
        <front>
          <title abbrev="MPLS-TP-Survivability">Multiprotocol Label Switching Transport
		  Profile Survivability Framework</title> 
            <author fullname="Nurit Sprecher" initials="N." role="" surname="Sprecher">
			</author>
            <author fullname="Adrian Farrel" initials="A." role="" surname="Farrel">
			</author>
         </front>
         <seriesInfo name="draft-ietf-mpls-tp-survive-fwk," value="Work in Progress" />
     </reference>
      <!-- End inclusion reference.MPLS-TP-Survivability-Framework-->		
	  
    </references>

   <references title="Informative References">

	<!--Begin inclusion reference.RFC.3985-->
    <reference anchor="RFC3985">
        <front>
          <title abbrev="RFC3985">Pseudo Wire Emulation Edge-to-Edge (PWE3) Architecture</title> 
		   <author fullname="Stewart Bryant" initials="S." surname="Bryant">
		   </author>
		   <author fullname="P. Pate" initials="P." surname="Pate">
          </author>
          <date year="2005" month="March" /> 
         </front>
         <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="3985" />
     </reference>
      <!-- End inclusion reference.RFC.3985 -->	

	<!--Begin inclusion reference.RFC.3031-->
    <reference anchor="RFC3031">
        <front>
          <title abbrev="RFC3031">Multiprotocol Label Switching Architecture</title> 
		   <author fullname="E.Rosen" initials="E." surname="Rosen">
		   </author>
		   <author fullname="A.Viswanathan" initials="A." surname="Viswanathan">
          </author>
		  <author fullname="R.Callon" initials="R." surname="Callon">
          </author>
          <date year="2001" month="January" /> 
         </front>
         <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="3031" />
     </reference>
      <!-- End inclusion reference.RFC.3031 -->	

	<!--Begin inclusion reference.RFC.5659-->
    <reference anchor="RFC5659">
        <front>
          <title abbrev="RFC5659">An Architecture for Multi-Segment Pseudo Wire Emulation
		  Edge-to-Edge</title> 
		   <author fullname="Matthew Bocci" initials="M." surname="Bocci">
		   </author>
		   <author fullname="Stewart Bryant" initials="S." surname="Bryant">
          </author>
          <date year="2009" month="October" /> 
         </front>
         <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="5659" />
     </reference>
      <!-- End inclusion reference.RFC.5659 -->	

	<!--Begin inclusion reference.RFC.5145-->
	<!--  Needs to be updated with proper content!! -->
    <reference anchor="RFC5145">
        <front>
          <title abbrev="RFC5145">Framework for MPLS-TE to GMPLS Migration</title> 
		   <author fullname="Kohei Shiomoto" initials="K." surname="Shiomoto">
		   </author>
          <date year="2008" month="March" /> 
         </front>
         <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="5145" />
     </reference>
      <!-- End inclusion reference.RFC.5145 -->	

      	<!--Begin inclusion reference.RFC.5921-->
    <reference anchor="RFC5921">
        <front>
          <title abbrev="RFC5921">A Framework for MPLS in Transport Networks</title> 
           <author fullname="M.Bocci" initials="M." role="editor" surname="Bocci">
		   </author>
           <author fullname="S.Bryant" initials="S." role="editor" surname="Bryant">
		   </author>
           <author fullname="D.Frost" initials="D." role="editor" surname="Frost">
		   </author>
		   <author fullname="L.Levrau" initials="L." role="editor" surname="Levrau">
		   </author>
		   <author fullname="L.Berger" initials="L." role="editor" surname="Berger">
		   </author>
         </front>
         <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="5921"/>
     </reference>
      <!-- End inclusion reference.RFC.5921 -->	

     	<!--Begin inclusion reference.RFC.5920-->
    <reference anchor="RFC5920">
        <front>
          <title abbrev="RFC5920">A Framework for MPLS in Transport Networks</title> 

		   <author fullname="L.Levrau" initials="L." role="editor" surname="Levrau">
		   </author>
         </front>
         <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="5920"/>
     </reference>
      <!-- End inclusion reference.RFC.5920-->	
	  [RFC5920]  Fang, L. Ed., "Security Framework for MPLS and GMPLS Networks", July 2010.

 
	</references>
	 
  </back>
</rfc>