<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY RFC2119 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5286 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5286.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3906 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3906.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4090 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4090.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5714 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5714.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5305 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5305.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5715 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5715.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3630 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3630.xml">
<!ENTITY REMOTE-LFA SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-rtgwg-remote-lfa.xml">
<!ENTITY LFA-TE SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.litkowski-rtgwg-lfa-rsvpte-cooperation.xml">
<!ENTITY LFA-APPLICABILITY SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6571.xml">
]>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="rfc2629.xslt" ?>
<!-- used by XSLT processors -->
<!-- OPTIONS, known as processing instructions (PIs) go here. -->
<!-- For a complete list and description of PIs,
     please see http://xml.resource.org/authoring/README.html. -->
<!-- Below are generally applicable PIs that most I-Ds might want to use. -->
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<!-- give errors regarding ID-nits and DTD validation -->
<!-- control the table of contents (ToC): -->
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<!-- generate a ToC -->
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<!-- the number of levels of subsections in ToC. default: 3 -->
<!-- control references: -->
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<!-- use symbolic references tags, i.e, [RFC2119] instead of [1] -->
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<!-- sort the reference entries alphabetically -->
<!-- control vertical white space: 
     (using these PIs as follows is recommended by the RFC Editor) -->
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<!-- do not start each main section on a new page -->
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<!-- keep one blank line between list items -->
<!-- end of popular PIs -->
<rfc category="std" docName="draft-ietf-rtgwg-lfa-manageability-00"
     ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="LFA manageability">Operational management of Loop Free
    Alternates</title>

    <author fullname="Stephane Litkowski" initials="S" surname="Litkowski">
      <organization>Orange</organization>

      <address>
        <!-- postal><street/><city/><region/><code/><country/></postal -->

        <!-- <phone/> -->

        <!-- <facsimile/> -->

        <email>stephane.litkowski@orange.com</email>

        <!-- <uri/> -->
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Bruno Decraene" initials="B" surname="Decraene">
      <organization>Orange</organization>

      <address>
        <!-- postal><street/><city/><region/><code/><country/></postal -->

        <!-- <phone/> -->

        <!-- <facsimile/> -->

        <email>bruno.decraene@orange.com</email>

        <!-- <uri/> -->
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Clarence Filsfils" initials="C" surname="Filsfils">
      <organization>Cisco Systems</organization>

      <address>
        <!-- postal><street/><city/><region/><code/><country/></postal -->

        <!-- <phone/> -->

        <!-- <facsimile/> -->

        <email>cfilsfil@cisco.com</email>

        <!-- <uri/> -->
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Kamran Raza" initials="K" surname="Raza">
      <organization>Cisco Systems</organization>

      <address>
        <!-- postal><street/><city/><region/><code/><country/></postal -->

        <!-- <phone/> -->

        <!-- <facsimile/> -->

        <email>skraza@cisco.com</email>

        <!-- <uri/> -->
      </address>
    </author>

    <date year="2013"/>

    <area/>

    <workgroup>Routing Area Working Group</workgroup>

    <!-- <keyword/> -->

    <!-- <keyword/> -->

    <!-- <keyword/> -->

    <!-- <keyword/> -->

    <abstract>
      <t>Loop Free Alternates (LFA), as defined in RFC 5286 is an IP Fast
      ReRoute (IP FRR) mechanism enabling traffic protection for IP traffic (and MPLS LDP traffic by extension).
      Following first deployment experiences, this document provides operational feedback on LFA, highlights some limitations, and proposes a set of refinements to address those limitations. 
	  It also proposes required management specifications.</t>
	  <t>This proposal is also applicable to remote LFA solution.</t>
    </abstract>
	
	<note title="Requirements Language">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
      document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
      target="RFC2119"/>.</t>
  </note>
  
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section anchor="intro" title="Introduction">


      <t>Following the first deployments of Loop Free Alternates (LFA), this document provides feedback to the community about the management of LFA.

	  <list>
<t>Section 2 provides real uses cases illustrating some limitations and suboptimal behavior.</t>

<t>Section 3 proposes requirements for activation granularity and policy based selection of the alternate.</t>

<t>Section 4 express requirements for the operational management of LFA.
</t>
</list>
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="outcomes-alternate"
             title="Operational issues with default LFA tie breakers">
      <t><xref target="RFC5286"/> introduces the notion of tie breakers when selecting the LFA among multiple candidate 
      alternate next-hops. When multiple LFA exist, RFC 5286 has favored the selection of the LFA providing the best coverage of the failure cases. While this is indeed a goal, this is one among multiple and in some deployment this lead to the selection of a suboptimal LFA. 
	  The following sections details real use cases of such limitations.</t>

      <t> Note that the use case of per-prefix LFA is assumed throughout this analysis.</t>

      <section anchor="outcomes-alternate-case1"
               title="Case 1: Edge router protecting core failures">
        <figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[
	R1 --------- R2 ---------- R3 --------- R4
	|      1           100           1       |
	|                                        |
	| 100                                    | 100
	|                                        |
	|      1           100           1       |
	R5 --------- R6 ---------- R7 --------- R8 -- R9 - PE1
	|             |            |             |
	| 5k          | 5k         | 5k          | 5k
	|             |            |             |
	+--- n*PEx ---+            +---- PE2 ----+
	                                  |
	                                  |
	                                 PEy
				 
						Figure 1
				]]></artwork>

          <postamble>Rx routers are core routers using n*10G
          links. PEs are connected using links with lower bandwidth.</postamble>
        </figure>

        <t>In figure 1, let us consider the traffic flowing from PE1 to PEx. The nominal path is R9-R8-R7-R6-PEx. Let us consider the
        failure of link R7-R8. For R8, R4 is not an LFA and the only available LFA is
        PE2.</t>

        <t>When the core link R8-R7 fails, R8 switches all traffic destined to all the
        PEx towards the edge node PE2. Hence an edge node and edge links are used to protect the failure of a core link.
		Typically, edge links have less capacity than core links and congestion may occur on PE2 links. Note that although PE2 was not directly affected by
        the failure, its links become congested and its traffic will suffer from the congestion.</t>

        <t>In summary, in case of failure, the impact on customer traffic is: <list style="symbols">
            <t>From PE2 point of view : <list style="symbols">
                <t>without LFA: no impact</t>

                <t>with LFA:  traffic is partially dropped (but
                possibly prioritized by a QoS mechanism). It must be highlighted that in such situation, traffic not affected by the failure may be affected by the congestion.</t>
              </list></t>

            <t>From R8 point of view: <list style="symbols">
                <t>without LFA: traffic is totally dropped until
                convergence occurs.</t>

                <t>with LFA:  traffic is partially dropped (but
                possibly prioritized by a QoS mechanism). </t>
              </list></t>
          </list></t>
		  <t>Besides the congestion aspects of using an Edge router as an alternate to protect a core failure, a service provider may consider this as a bad routing design and would like to prevent it.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="outcomes-alternate-case2"
               title="Case 2: Edge router choosen to protect core failures while core LFA exists">
        <figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[
	R1 --------- R2 ------------ R3 --------- R4
	|      1           100       |     1     |
	|                            |           |
	| 100                        | 30        | 30
	|                            |           |
	|     1        50        50  |    10     |
	R5 -------- R6 ---- R10 ---- R7 -------- R8 --- R9 - PE1
	|            |         \                 |
	| 5000       | 5000     \ 5000           | 5000
	|            |           \               |
	+--- n*PEx --+            +----- PE2 ----+
 	                                  |
 	                                  |
 	                                 PEy

	                  Figure 2
				]]></artwork>

          <postamble>Rx routers are core routers meshed with n*10G
          links. PEs are meshed using links with lower bandwidth.</postamble>
        </figure>

        <t>In the figure 2, let us consider the traffic coming from PE1 to PEx.
        Nominal path is R9-R8-R7-R6-PEx. Let us consider the
        failure of the link R7-R8. For R8, R4 is a link-protecting LFA and PE2 is a node-protecting LFA. PE2 is chosen as best
        LFA due to its better protection type. Just like in case 1, this may lead to congestion on PE2 links upon LFA activation.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="outcomes-alternate-case3"
               title="Case 3: suboptimal core alternate choice">
        <figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[
            +--- PE3 --+
           /            \
     1000 /              \ 1000
         /                \
 +----- R1 ---------------- R2 ----+
 |      |       500         |      |
 | 10   |                   |      | 10
 |      |                   |      |
 R5     | 10                | 10   R7
 |      |                   |      |
 | 10   |                   |      | 10
 |      |       500         |      |
 +---- R3 ---------------- R4 -----+
         \                 /
          \               /
           \             /
            +--- PE1 ---+
	  
            Figure 3
			]]></artwork>

          <postamble>Rx routers are core routers. R1-R2 and R3-R4 links are 1G
          links. All others inter Rx links are 10G links.</postamble>
        </figure>

        <t>In the figure above, let us consider the failure of link R1-R3. For
        destination PE3, R3 has two possible alternates: <list
            style="symbols">
            <t>R4, which is node-protecting</t>

            <t>R5, which is link-protecting</t>
          </list> R4 is chosen as best LFA due to its better protection type. However, it
        may not be desirable to use R4 for bandwidth
        capacity reason. A service provider may prefer to use high bandwidth
        links as prefered LFA. In this example, prefering shortest path over
        protection type may achieve the expected behavior, but in cases where
        metric are not reflecting bandwidth, it would not work and some other
        criteria would need to be involved when selecting the best LFA.</t>
      </section>

		<section anchor="outcomes-alternate-case4"
               title="Case 4: ISIS overload bit on LFA computing node">
        <figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[


    P1       P2
    |   \  /   |
 50 | 50 \/ 50 | 50
    |    /\    |
    PE1-+  +-- PE2
     \        /
   45 \      / 45	 
       -PE3-+
       (OL set)
	  
            Figure 4
			]]></artwork>

        </figure>

        <t>In the figure above, PE3 has its overload bit set (permanently, for design reason) and wants to protect traffic using LFA for destination PE2.</t>
		<t>On PE3, the loopfree condition is not satisified : 100 !&lt; 45 + 45. PE1 is thus not considered as an LFA. 
		However thanks to the overload bit set on PE3, we know that PE1 is loopfree so PE1 is an LFA to reach PE2.</t>
		<t>In case of overload condition set on a node, LFA behavior must be clarified.</t>
		
      </section>
    </section>

	
    <section anchor="configuration" title="Configuration requirements">
      <t>Controlling best alternate and LFA activation granularity is a
      requirement for Service Providers. This section defines 
      configuration requirements for LFA.</t>

      <section anchor="config-activation" title="LFA enabling/disabling scope">
        <t>The granularity of LFA activation should be controlled
       (as alternate nexthop consume memory in forwarding
        plane).</t>

        <t>An implementation of LFA SHOULD allow its activation with the following criteria: <list style="symbols">
            <t>Per address-family : ipv4 unicast, ipv6
            unicast, LDP IPv4 unicast, LDP IPv6 unicast ...</t>

            <t>Per routing context : VRF, virtual/logical
            router, global routing table, ...</t>

            <t>Per interface</t>

            <t>Per protocol instance, topology, area</t>

            <t>Per prefixes: prefix protection SHOULD have a better
            priority compared to interface protection. This means that if a
            specific prefix must be protected due to a configuration request,
            LFA must be computed and installed for this prefix even if the
            primary outgoing interface is not configured for protection.</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="config-policy" title="Policy based LFA selection">
        <t>When multiple alternates exist, LFA selection algorithm is based on tie breakers. Current tie breakers do not provide sufficient control on how
        the best alternate is chosen. This document proposes an enhanced tie breaker
        allowing service providers to manage all specific cases:</t>

        <t><list style="numbers">
            <t>An implementation of LFA SHOULD support policy-based decision
            for determining the best LFA.</t>

            <t>Policy based decision SHOULD be based on multiple criterions,
            with each criteria having a level of preference.</t>

            <t>If the defined policy does not permit to determine a unique best
            LFA, an implementation SHOULD pick only one based on its own decision, as a default behavior.
			An implementation SHOULD also support election of multiple LFAs, for loadbalancing purposes.</t>

            <t>Policy SHOULD be applicable to a protected interface or to a
            specific set of destinations. In case of application on the
            protected interface, all destinations primarily routed on this
            interface SHOULD use the interface policy.</t>
	
			<t>It is an implementation choice to reevaluate policy dynamically or not (in case of policy change). 
			If a dynamic approach is chosen, the implementation SHOULD recompute the best LFAs and reinstall them in FIB, without service disruption.
			If a non-dynamic approach is chosen, the policy would be taken into account upon the next IGP event. In this case, the implementation SHOULD support a command to manually force the recomputation/reinstallation of LFAs.</t>
          </list></t>

        <section anchor="config-policy-mandatory" title="Mandatory criteria">
          <t>An implementation of LFA MUST support the following 
          criteria: <list style="symbols">
              <t>Non candidate link: A link marked as "non
              candidate" will never be used as LFA.</t>

              <t>A primary nexthop being protected by another primary nexthop
              of the same prefix (ECMP case).</t>

              <t>Type of protection provided by the alternate: link
              protection, node protection. In case of node protection preference, an implementation SHOULD support fallback to link protection if node protection is not available.</t>
		  
              <t>Shortest path: lowest IGP metric used to reach the
              destination.</t>

              <t>SRLG (as defined in <xref target="RFC5286"/> Section 3).</t>
            </list></t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="config-policy-enhanced" title="Enhanced criteria">
          <t>An implementation of LFA SHOULD support the following enhanced
          criteria: <list style="symbols">
		  	  <t>Downstreamness of a neighbor : preference of a downstream path over a non downstream path SHOULD be configurable.</t>
	
              <t>Link coloring with : include, exclude and preference based system.</t>

              <t>Link Bandwidth.</t>

              <t>Neighbor preference.</t>

              <t>Neighbor type: link or tunnel alternate. This means that
              user may change preference between link alternate or tunnel
              alternate (link prefered over tunnel,
              or considered as equal).</t>
            </list></t>



          <section anchor="config-policy-enhanced-detail-linkcolor"
                   title="Link coloring">
            <t>Link coloring is a powerful system to control the choice of alternates. 
			Protecting interfaces are tagged with colors.
            Protected interfaces are configured to include some colors with a
            preference level, and exclude others.</t>
			<t>Link color information SHOULD be signalled in the IGP. 
			How signalling is done is out of scope of the document but it may be useful to reuse existing admin-groups from traffic-engineering extensions.</t>

            <t> <figure>
                <artwork><![CDATA[
               PE2 
               |   +---- P4
               |  /
      PE1 ---- P1 --------- P2
               |      10Gb
           1Gb | 
               |
               P3
				
		     Figure 5
				]]></artwork>
              </figure> 
			  Example : P1 router is connected to three P routers and two
            PEs.</t>
			  <t>P1 is configured to protect the P1-P4 link. We
            assume that given the topology, all neighbors are candidate LFA. We would like to enforce a policy in the network where only a core
            router may protect against the failure of a core link, and where high capacity
            links are prefered.</t>

            <t>In this example, we can use the proposed link coloring by:</t>

            <t><list style="symbols">
                <t>Marking PEs links with color RED</t>

                <t>Marking 10Gb CORE link with color BLUE</t>

                <t>Marking 1Gb CORE link with color YELLOW</t>

                <t>Configured the protected interface P1-&gt;P4 with : <list
                    style="symbols">
                    <t>Include BLUE, preference 200</t>

                    <t>Include YELLOW, preference 100</t>

                    <t>Exclude RED</t>
                  </list></t>
              </list></t>

            <t>Using this, PE links will never be used to protect against
            P1-P4 link failure and 10Gb link will be be preferred.</t>

            <t>The main advantage of this solution is that it can easily be duplicated on other interfaces and other nodes without
            change. A Service Provider has only to define the color system
            (associate color with a significance), as it is done already for TE
            affinities or BGP communities.</t>

            <t>An implementation of link coloring: <list style="symbols">
                <t>SHOULD support multiple include and exclude colors on a
                single protected interface.</t>

                <t>SHOULD provide a level of preference between included
                colors.</t>

                <t>SHOULD support multiple colors configuration on a single
                protecting interface.</t>
              </list></t>
          </section>

		  <section anchor="config-policy-enhanced-detail-bw" title="Bandwidth">
		  <t>
			As mentionned in previous sections, not taking into account bandwidth of an alternate could lead to congestion during FRR activation.
			We propose to base the bandwidth criteria on the link speed information for the following reason : 
			<list style="symbols">
			<t>if a router S has a set of X destinations primarly forwarded to N, using per prefix LFA may lead to have a subset of X protected by a neighbor N1, another subset by N2, another subset by Nx ...</t>
			<t>S is not aware about traffic flows to each destination and is not able to evaluate how much traffic will be sent to N1,N2, ... Nx in case of FRR activation.</t>
			
			</list>
			
			Based on this, it is not useful to gather available bandwidth on alternate paths, as the router does not know how much bandwidth it requires for protection.
			The proposed link speed approach provides a good approximation with a small cost as information is easily available.
			</t>
			<t>
			The bandwidth criteria of the policy framework SHOULD work in two ways :
			<list style="symbols">
			<t>PRUNE : exclude a LFA if link speed to reach it is lower than the link speed of the primary nexthop interface.</t>
			<t>PREFER : prefer a LFA based on his bandwidth to reach it compared to the link speed of the primary nexthop interface.</t>
			</list>
		   </t>
		   </section>
          

          <section anchor="config-policy-enhanced-detail-neighbor-preference"  title="Neighbor preference">
            <t>Rather than tagging interface on each node (using link color)
            to identify neighbor node type (as example), it would be helpful if routers could be identified in the IGP. This would permit a grouped processing on multiple nodes.
			Some existing IGP extension like SUB-TLV 1 of TLV 135 may be useful for this purpose.
			As an implementation must be able to exclude some specific neighbors (see mandatory criterions), an implementation :
			
			<list style="symbols">
			<t>SHOULD be able to give a preference to specific neighbor.</t>
			<t>SHOULD be able to give a preference to a group of neighbor.</t>
			<t>SHOULD be able to exclude a group of neighbor.</t>
			</list>
			</t>
			<t>A specific neighbor may be identified by its interface or IP address and group of neighbors may be identified by a marker like SUB-TLV1 in TLV135.
			As multiple prefixes may be present in TLVs 135, an heuristic is required to choose the appropriate one that will identify the neighbor and will transport the tag associated with the neighbor preference. 
			</t>
			<t>
			We propose the following algorithm to select the prefix :
			<list style="numbers">
			<t>Select the prefix in TLV#135 that is equal to TLV#134 value (Router ID) and prefix length is 32.</t>
			<t>Select the prefix in TLV#135 that is equal to TLV#132 value (IP Addresses) and prefix length is 32, it must be noted that TLV#132 may transport multiple addresses and so multiple matches may happen.</t>
			<t>If multiple prefixes are matching TLV#132 values, choose the highest one.</t>
			</list>
			</t>

            <t>Consider the following network: <figure>
                <artwork><![CDATA[
               PE3
               |
               |
               PE2 
               |   +---- P4
               |  /
      PE1 ---- P1 -------- P2
               |      10Gb
           1Gb |
               |
               P3

          Figure 6			   
	]]>
	
				</artwork>
              </figure> In the example above, each node is configured with a specific tag flooded through the IGP. 
			  <list
                style="symbols">
                <t>PE1,PE3: 200 (non candidate).</t>

                <t>PE2: 100 (edge/core).</t>

                <t>P1,P2,P3: 50 (core).</t>
              </list> 
			  A simple policy could be configured on P1 to choose the
            best alternate for P1-&gt;P4 based on router function/role as
            follows : <list style="symbols">
                <t>criteria 1 -&gt; neighbor preference: exclude tag 100 and 200.</t>
                <t>criteria 2 -&gt; bandwidth.</t>
              </list></t>
          </section>

          <section anchor="config-policy-enhanced-detail-linktunnel"
                   title="Link vs remote alternate">
            <t>In addition to LFA, tunnels (IP, LDP or RSVP-TE) to distant routers
            may be used to complement LFA coverage (tunnel tail used as
            virtual neighbor). When a router has multiple alternate candidates
            for a specific destination, it may have connected alternates (link alternates) and remote alternates reachable via a tunnel. 
			Link alternates may not always provide an
            optimal routing path and it may be preferable to select a remote
            alternate over a link alternate. The usage of tunnels to extend LFA coverage
			is described in <xref target="I-D.ietf-rtgwg-remote-lfa"/> and <xref target="I-D.litkowski-rtgwg-lfa-rsvpte-cooperation"/>.</t>

            <t>In figure 1, there is no core alternate for R8 to reach PEs
            located behind R6, so R8 is using PE2 as alternate, which may
            generate congestion when FRR is activated. Instead, we could
            have a remote core alternate for R8 to protect PEs destinations.
            For example, a tunnel from R8 to R3 would ensure a LFA protection without any impact.</t>
			
			<t>
			There is a requirement to be able to compare remote alternates (reachable through a tunnel) to link alternates (a remote alternate may provide a better protection than a link alternate based on service provider's criteria).
			Policy will associate a preference to each alternate whatever their type (link or remote) and will elect the best one.
			</t>
          </section>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="operational" title="Operational aspects">
      <section anchor="oper-lfa-ISIS-overload"
               title="ISIS overload bit on LFA computing node">
	   <t>In <xref target="RFC5286"/>, Section 3.5, the setting of the overload bit condition in LFA computation is only taken into account for the case where a neighbor has the overload bit set.
	   </t>
	   <t>In addition to RFC 5286 inequality 1 Loop-Free Criterion (Distance_opt(N, D) &lt; Distance_opt(N, S) + Distance_opt(S, D)), the IS-IS overload bit of the LFA calculating neighbor (S) SHOULD be taken into account. Indeed, if it has the overload bit set, no neighbor will loop back to traffic to itself.</t>
	 </section>
	  

      <section anchor="oper-lfa-manualtrigger"
               title="Manual triggering of FRR">
        <t>Service providers often use using manual link shutdown (using
        router CLI) to perform some network changes/tests. Especially testing or troubleshooting FRR
		requires to perform the manual shutdown on the remote end of the link as generally a local shutdown would not trigger FRR.
		To enhance such situation, an implementation SHOULD 
        support triggering/activating LFA Fast Reroute for a given link when a
        manual shutdown is done.</t>
		
      </section>

      <section anchor="oper-lfa-information"
               title="Required local information">
        <t>LFA introduction requires some enhancement in standard routing
        information provided by implementations. Moreover, due to the non 100%
        coverage, coverage informations is also required.</t>

        <t>Hence an implementation : <list style="symbols">
            <t>MUST be able to display, for every prefixes, the primary
            nexthop as well as the alternate nexthop information.</t>

            <t>MUST provide coverage information per activation domain of LFA
            (area, level, topology, instance, virtual router, address family ...).</t>

            <t>MUST provide number of protected prefixes as well as non protected prefixes globally.</t>

            <t>SHOULD provide number of protected prefixes as well as non protected prefixes per link.</t>

            <t>MAY provide number of protected prefixes as well as non protected prefixes per priority if
            implementation supports prefix-priority insertion in RIB/FIB.</t>

            <t>SHOULD provide a reason for chosing an alternate (policy and
            criteria) and for excluding an alternate.</t>

            <t>SHOULD provide the list of non protected prefixes and the
            reason why they are not protected (no protection required or no
            alternate available).</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="oper-lfa-alert" title="Coverage monitoring">
        <t>It is pretty easy to evaluate the coverage of a network in a nominal
        situation, but topology changes may change the coverage. In some
        situations, the network may no longer be able to provide the required level of
        protection. Hence, it becomes very important for service providers to
        get alerted about changes of coverage.</t>

        <t>An implementation SHOULD : <list style="symbols">
            <t>provide an alert system if total coverage (for a node) is below a defined
            threshold or comes back to a normal situation.</t>

            <t>provide an alert system if coverage of a specific link is below
            a defined threshold or comes back to a normal situation.</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>An implementation MAY : <list style="symbols">
            <t>provide an alert system if a specific destination is not
            protected anymore or when protection comes back up for this
            destination</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>Although the procedures for providing alerts are beyond the scope
        of this document, we recommend that implementations consider
        standard and well used mechanisms like syslog or SNMP traps.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>This document does not introduce any change in security consideration
      compared to <xref target="RFC5286"/>.</t>
    </section>

	<section anchor="Contributors" title="Contributors">
	<t>
   Significant contributions were made by Pierre Francois, Hannes Gredler and Mustapha Aissaoui which the authors would like to acknowledge.
</t>
	</section>
	
    <section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements"/>

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>This document has no action for IANA.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      &RFC2119;
      &RFC5286;  
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      &RFC3630;
	  &RFC3906;
	  &RFC4090;
	  &RFC5714;
      &RFC5715;
      &RFC5305;
	  &REMOTE-LFA;
      &LFA-APPLICABILITY;
	  &LFA-TE;
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
