<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!-- This template is for creating an Internet Draft using xml2rfc,
     which is available here: http://xml.resource.org. -->
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!-- One method to get references from the online citation libraries.
     There has to be one entity for each item to be referenced. 
     An alternate method (rfc include) is described in the references. -->
<!ENTITY RFC2119 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5548 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5548.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5673 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5673.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5826 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5826.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5867 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5867.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6206 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6206.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.ietf-6man-rpl-option SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-6man-rpl-option.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.ietf-roll-rpl SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-roll-rpl.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.ietf-roll-routing-metrics SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-roll-routing-metrics.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.ietf-roll-p2p-rpl SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-roll-p2p-rpl.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.ietf-roll-terminology SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-roll-terminology.xml">
]>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<!-- used by XSLT processors -->
<!-- For a complete list and description of processing instructions (PIs), 
     please see http://xml.resource.org/authoring/README.html. -->
<!-- Below are generally applicable Processing Instructions (PIs) that most I-Ds might want to use.
     (Here they are set differently than their defaults in xml2rfc v1.32) -->
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<!-- give errors regarding ID-nits and DTD validation -->
<!-- control the table of contents (ToC) -->
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<!-- generate a ToC -->
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<!-- the number of levels of subsections in ToC. default: 3 -->
<!-- control references -->
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<!-- use symbolic references tags, i.e, [RFC2119] instead of [1] -->
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<!-- sort the reference entries alphabetically -->
<!-- control vertical white space 
     (using these PIs as follows is recommended by the RFC Editor) -->
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<!-- do not start each main section on a new page -->
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<!-- keep one blank line between list items -->
<!-- end of list of popular I-D processing instructions -->
<rfc category="std" docName="draft-ietf-roll-applicability-ami-02"
     ipr="trust200902">
  <!-- category values: std, bcp, info, exp, and historic
     ipr values: full3667, noModification3667, noDerivatives3667
     you can add the attributes updates="NNNN" and obsoletes="NNNN" 
     they will automatically be output with "(if approved)" -->

  <!-- ***** FRONT MATTER ***** -->

  <front>
    <!-- The abbreviated title is used in the page header - it is only necessary if the 
         full title is longer than 39 characters -->

    <title abbrev="RPL Applicability for AMI">Applicability Statement for the
    Routing Protocol for Low Power and Lossy Networks (RPL) in AMI
    Networks</title>

    <!-- add 'role="editor"' below for the editors if appropriate -->

    <!-- Another author who claims to be an editor -->

    <author fullname="Daniel Popa" initials="D.P." surname="Popa">
      <organization>Itron</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>52 Rue Camille Desmoulins</street>

          <city>92448 Issy les Moulineaux</city>

          <country>France</country>
        </postal>

        <email>daniel.popa@itron.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Jorjeta Jetcheva" initials="J.J." surname="Jetcheva">
      <organization>Itron</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>2111 N Molter Rd.</street>

          <city>Liberty Lake</city>

          <region>WA 99019</region>

          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>

        <email>jorjeta.jetcheva@itron.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Nicolas Dejean" initials="N.D." surname="Dejean">
      <organization>Elster SAS</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Espace Concorde, 120 impasse JB Say</street>

          <region>Perols, 34470</region>

          <country>France</country>
        </postal>

        <email>nicolas.dejean@coronis.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Ruben Salazar" initials="R.S." surname="Salazar">
      <organization>Landis+Gyr</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>30000 Mill Creek Ave # 100</street>

          <city>Alpharetta</city>

          <region>GA</region>

          <code>30022</code>
        </postal>

        <email>ruben.salazar@landisgyr.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Jonathan W. Hui" initials="J.H." surname="Hui">
      <organization>Cisco</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>170 West Tasman Drive</street>

          <city>San Jose</city>

          <region>California</region>

          <code>95134</code>

          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>

        <phone>+408 424 1547</phone>

        <email>jonhui@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date year="2011" />

    <!-- If the month and year are both specified and are the current ones, xml2rfc will fill 
         in the current day for you. If only the current year is specified, xml2rfc will fill 
	 in the current day and month for you. If the year is not the current one, it is 
	 necessary to specify at least a month (xml2rfc assumes day="1" if not specified for the 
	 purpose of calculating the expiry date).  With drafts it is normally sufficient to 
	 specify just the year. -->

    <!-- Meta-data Declarations -->

    <area>Routing Area</area>

    <workgroup>ROLL</workgroup>

    <!-- WG name at the upperleft corner of the doc,
         IETF is fine for individual submissions.  
	 If this element is not present, the default is "Network Working Group",
         which is used by the RFC Editor as a nod to the history of the IETF. -->

    <keyword>template</keyword>

    <!-- Keywords will be incorporated into HTML output
         files in a meta tag but they have no effect on text or nroff
         output. If you submit your draft to the RFC Editor, the
         keywords will be used for the search engine. -->

    <abstract>
      <t>This document discusses the applicability of RPL in Advanced Metering
      Infrastructure (AMI) networks.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>Advanced Metering Infrastructure (AMI) systems enable the
      measurement, configuration, and control of energy, gas and water
      consumption and distribution, through two-way scheduled, on exception,
      and on-demand communication.</t>

      <t>AMI networks are composed of millions of endpoints, including meters,
      distribution automation elements, and home area network devices. They
      are typically inter-connected using some combination of wireless
      technologies and power-line communications, along with a backhaul
      network providing connectivity to "command-and-control" management
      software applications at the utility company back office.</t>

      <section title="Electric Metering">
        <t>In many deployments, in addition to measuring energy consumption,
        the electric meter network plays a central role in the Smart Grid
        since it enables the utility company to control and query the electric
        meters themselves and also since it can serve as a backhaul for all
        other devices in the Smart Grid, e.g., water and gas meters,
        distribution automation and home area network devices. Electric meters
        may also be used as sensors to monitor electric grid quality and to
        support applications such as Electric Vehicle charging.</t>

        <t>Electric meter networks are composed of millions of smart meters
        (or nodes), each of which is resource-constrained in terms of
        processing power, storage capabilities, and communication bandwidth,
        due to a combination of factors including Federal Communications
        Commission (FCC) or other continents' regulations on spectrum use,
        American National Standards Institute (ANSI) standards or other
        continents' regulation on meter behavior and performance, on heat
        emissions within the meter, form factor and cost considerations. These
        constraints result in a compromise between range and throughput, with
        effective link throughput of tens to a few hundred kilobits per second
        per link, a potentially significant portion of which is taken up by
        protocol and encryption overhead when strong security measures are in
        place.</t>

        <t>Electric meters are often interconnected into multi-hop mesh
        networks, each of which is connected to a backhaul network leading to
        the utility company network through a network aggregation point, e.g.,
        an LBR (LLN Border Router). </t>
      </section>

      <section title="Gas and Water Metering">
        <t>While electric meters typically consume electricity from the same
        electric feed that they are monitoring, gas and water meters typically
        run on a modest source of stored energy (e.g., batteries).</t>

        <t>In some scenarios, gas and water meters are integrated into the
        same AMI network as the electric meters and may operate as network
        endpoints (rather than routers) in order to prolong their own
        lifetime. In other scenarios, however, such meters may not have the
        luxury of relying on a fully powered AMI routing infrastructure but
        must communicate through a dedicated infrastructure to reach a LBR.
        This infrastructure can be either powered by the electricity grid, by
        battery-based devices, or ones relying on alternative sources of
        energy (e.g., solar power).</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Routing Protocol for LLNs (RPL)">
        <t>RPL provides routing functionality for mesh networks that can scale
        up to thousands of resource-constrained devices, interconnected by low
        power and lossy links, and communicating with the external network
        infrastructure through a common aggregation point(s) (e.g., a
        LBR).</t>

        <t>RPL builds a Directed Acyclic Graph (DAG) routing structure rooted
        at the LBR, ensures loop-free routing, and provides support for
        alternate routes, as well as, for a wide range of routing metrics and
        policies.</t>

        <t>RPL was desgined to operate in energy-constrained environments and
        includes energy-saving mechanisms (e.g., Trickle timers) and
        energy-aware metrics. Its ability to support multiple different
        metrics and constraints at the same time enables it to run efficiently
        in heterogeneous networks composed of nodes and links with vastly
        different characteristics<xref
        target="I-D.ietf-roll-routing-metrics"></xref>.</t>

        <t>This note describes the applicability of RPL (as defined in <xref
        target="I-D.ietf-roll-rpl"></xref>) to AMI deployments. RPL was
        designed to meet the following application requirements: <list
            style="symbols">
            <t>Routing Requirements for Urban Low-Power and Lossy Networks
            <xref target="RFC5548"></xref>.</t>

            <t>Industrial Routing Requirements in Low-Power and Lossy Networks
            <xref target="RFC5673"></xref>.</t>

            <t>Home Automation Routing Requirements in Low-Power and Lossy
            Networks <xref target="RFC5826"></xref>.</t>

            <t>Building Automation Routing Requirements in Low-Power and Lossy
            Networks <xref target="RFC5867"></xref>.</t>
          </list> The Routing Requirements for Urban Low-Power and Lossy
        Networks are applicable to AMI networks as well.</t>

        <t>The terminology used in this document is defined in <xref
        target="I-D.ietf-roll-terminology"></xref>.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Requirements Language">
        <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
        "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
        document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
        target="RFC2119">RFC 2119</xref>.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Deployment Scenarios">
      <section title="Network Topology">
        <t>AMI networks are composed of millions of endpoints distributed
        across both urban and rural environments. Such endpoints include
        electric, gas, and water meters, distribution automation elements, and
        home area network devices. Devices in the network communicate directly
        with other devices in close proximity using a variety of low-power
        and/or lossy link technologies that are both wired and wireless (e.g.,
        IEEE 802.15.4, IEEE P1901.2, and 802.11). In addition to serving as
        sources and destinations of packets, many network elements typically
        also forward packets and thus form a mesh topology.</t>

        <section title="Electric Meter Network">
          <t>In a typical AMI deployment, groups of meters within physical
          proximity form routing domains, each in the order of a 1,000 to
          10,000 meters. Thus, each electric meter mesh typically has several
          thousand wireless endpoints, with densities varying based on the
          area and the terrain. For example, apartment buildings in urban
          centers may have hundreds of meters in close proximity, whereas
          rural areas may have sparse node distributions and include nodes
          that only have a small number of network neighbors.</t>

          <t>Each routing domain is connected to the larger IP infrastructure
          through one or more LBRs, which provide Wide Area Network (WAN)
          connectivity through various traditional network technologies, e.g.,
          Ethernet, cellular, private WAN. Paths in the mesh between a network
          node and the nearest LBR may be composed of several hops or even
          several tens of hops.</t>

          <t>Powered from the main line, electric meters have less energy
          constraints than battery powered devices, such as gas and water
          meters, and can afford the additional resources required to route
          packets. In mixed environments, electric meters can provide the
          routing topology while gas and water meters can operate as leaf
          nodes.</t>

          <t>Electric meter networks may also serve as transit networks for
          other types of devices, including distribution automation elements
          (e.g., sensors and actuators), and in-home devices. These other
          devices may utilize a different link-layer technology than the one
          used in the meter network.</t>

          <t>The routing protocol operating in networks with the topology
          characteristics described above needs to be able to scale with
          network size and number of forwarding hops, and have the ability to
          handle a wide range of network densities.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Energy-Constrained Network Infrastructure">
          <t>In the absence of a co-located electric meter network, gas and
          water meters must either connect directly to the larger IP network
          infrastructure or rely on a dedicated routing infrastructure.
          Deploying such infrastructures is a challenging task as the routing
          devices can sometimes only be placed in specific locations and thus
          do not always have access to a continous energy source.
          Battery-operated or energy-harvesting (e.g., equipped with solar
          panels) routers are thus often used in these kinds of scenarios.</t>

          <t>Due to the expected lifetime (10 to 20 years) of such networks
          and their reliance on alternative sources of energy, energy
          consumption needs to be taken into account when designing and
          deploying them. There are a number of challenging trade-offs and
          considerations that exist in that respect. One such consideration is
          that managing a higher number of meters per router leads to
          increased energy consumption. However, increasing the number of
          routers in the network and thus reducing the number of meters
          managed by each router increases deployment and maintenance costs.
          At the same time, the use of a sparser routing infrastructure
          necessitates the use of higher transmit power levels at nodes in the
          network, which causes increased energy consumption.</t>

          <t>The deployment and operational needs of energy-constrained
          network infrastructure require the use of routing mechanisms that
          take into account energy consumption, minimize energy use and
          prolong network lifetime.</t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section title="Traffic Characteristics">
        <section title="Smart Metering Data">
          <t>In current AMI deployments, metering applications typically
          require all smart meters to communicate with a few head-end servers,
          deployed in the utility company data center.</t>

          <t>Head-end servers generate data traffic to configure smart
          metering devices or initiate queries, and use unicast and multicast
          to efficiently communicate with a single device or groups of devices
          respectively (i.e., Point-to-Multipoint (P2MP) communication). The
          head-end server may send a single small packet at a time to the
          meters (e.g., a meter read request, a small configuration change) or
          a series of large packets (e.g., a firmware upgrade across one or
          even thousands of devices). The frequency of large file transfers,
          e.g., firmware upgrade of all metering devices, is typically much
          lower than the frequency of sending configuration messages or
          queries.</t>

          <t>Each smart meter generates Smart Metering Data (SMD) traffic
          according to a schedule (e.g., periodic meter reads), in response to
          on-demand queries (e.g., on-demand meter reads), or in response to
          some local event (e.g., power outage, leak detection). Such traffic
          is typically destined to a single head-end server.</t>

          <t>The SMD traffic is thus highly asymmetric, where the majority of
          the traffic generated by the smart meters typically goes through the
          LBRs, and is directed from the smart meter devices to the head-end
          servers, in a Multipoint-to-Point (MP2P) fashion.</t>

          <t>Current SMD traffic patterns are fairly uniform and
          well-understood. The traffic generated by the head-end server and
          destined to metering devices is dominated by periodic meter reads,
          while traffic generated by the metering devices is typically
          uniformly spread over some periodic read time-window.</t>

          <t>Smart metering applications typically do not have hard real-time
          constraints, but they are often subject to bounded latency and
          stringent reliability service level agreements. </t>

          <t>From a routing perspective, SMD applications require efficient
          P2MP communication between the devices in the network and one or
          more LBRs. In addition, timely loop resolution and broken link
          repair are needed to meet latency requirements. Finally, the
          availability of redundant paths is important for increasing network
          reliability.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Distribution Automation Communication">
          <t>Distribution Automation (DA) applications typically involve a
          small number of devices that communicate with each other in a
          Point-to-Point (P2P) fashion, and may or may not be in close
          physical proximity.</t>

          <t>DA applications typically have more stringent latency
          requirements than SMD applications.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Emerging Applications">
          <t>There are a number of emerging applications such as electric
          vehicle charging. These applications may require P2P communication
          and may eventually have more stringent latency requirements than SMD
          applications.</t>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Using RPL to Meet Functional Requirements">
      <t>The functional requirements for most AMI deployments are similar to
      those listed in <xref target="RFC5548"></xref>:<list style="symbols">
          <t>The routing protocol MUST be capable of supporting the
          organization of a large number of nodes into regions containing on
          the order of 10^2 to 10^4 nodes each.</t>

          <t>The routing protocol MUST provide mechanisms to support
          configuration of the routing protocol itself.</t>

          <t>The routing protocol SHOULD support and utilize the large number
          of highly directed flows to a few head-end servers to handle
          scalability.</t>

          <t>The routing protocol MUST dynamically compute and select
          effective routes composed of low-power and lossy links. Local
          network dynamics SHOULD NOT impact the entire network. The routing
          protocol MUST compute multiple paths when possible.</t>

          <t>The routing protocol MUST support multicast and anycast
          addressing. The routing protocol SHOULD support formation and
          identification of groups of field devices in the network.</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>RPL supports: <list style="symbols">
          <t>Large-scale networks characterized by highly directed traffic
          flows between each smart meter and the head-end servers in the
          utility network. To this end, RPL builds a Directed Acyclic Graph
          (DAG) rooted at each LBR.</t>

          <t>Zero-touch configuration. This is done through in-band methods
          for configuring RPL variables using DIO messages.</t>

          <t>The use of links with time-varying quality characteristics. This
          is accomplished by allowing the use of metrics that effectively
          capture the quality of a path (e.g., Expected Transmission Count
          (ETX)) and by limiting the impact of changing local conditions by
          discovering and maintaining multiple DAG parents, and by using local
          repair mechanisms when DAG links break.</t>
        </list></t>
    </section>

    <section title="RPL Profile">
      <t>This section outlines a RPL profile for a representative AMI
      deployment.</t>

      <section title="RPL Features">
        <section title="RPL Instances">
          <t>RPL operation is defined for a single RPL instance. However,
          multiple RPL instances can be supported in multi-service networks
          where different applications may require the use of different
          routing metrics and constraints, e.g., a network carrying both SDM
          and DA traffic.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Storing vs. Non-Storing Mode">
          <t>In most scenarios, electric meters are powered by the electric
          grid they are monitoring and are not energy-constrained. Instead,
          the capabilities of an electric meter are primarily determined by
          cost. As a result, different AMI deployments can vary significantly
          in terms of the memory, computation, and communication trade-offs
          they embody. For this reason, the use of RPL storing or non-storing
          mode SHOULD be deployment specific.</t>

          <t>For example, when meters are memory constrained and cannot
          adequately store the route tables necessary to support downward
          routing in a typical deployment, non-storing mode is preferred. When
          nodes are capable of storing such routing tables, storing mode may
          lead to reduced overhead and route repair latency.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="DAO Policy">
          <t>Two-way communication is a requirement in AMI systems. As a
          result, nodes SHOULD send DAO messages to establish downward paths
          from the root to themselves.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Path Metrics">
          <t>Smart metering deployments utilize link technologies that may
          exhibit significant packet loss and thus require routing metrics
          that take packet loss into account. To characterize a path over such
          link technologies, AMI deployments can use the Expected Transmission
          Count (ETX) metric as defined in<xref
          target="I-D.ietf-roll-routing-metrics"></xref>.</t>

          <t>For water- and gas-only networks that do not rely on powered
          infrastructure, simpler metrics that require less energy to compute
          would be more appropriate. In particular, hop count and link quality
          level may be more suitable. Additional metrics specifically designed
          for such networks may be defined in companion RFCs.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Objective Function">
          <t>RPL relies on an Objective Function for selecting parents and
          computing path costs and rank. This objective function is decoupled
          from the core RPL mechanisms and also from the metrics in use in the
          network. Two objective functions for RPL have been defined at the
          time of this writing, OF0 and MRHOF, both of which define the
          selection of a preferred parent and backup parents, and are suitable
          for AMI deployments. </t>

          <t>Neither of the currently defined objective functions supports
          multiple metrics that might be required in heterogeneous networks
          (e.g., networks composed of devices with different energy
          constraints). Additional objective functions specifically designed
          for such networks may be defined in companion RFCs.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="DODAG Repair">
          <t>To effectively handle time-varying link characteristics and
          availability, AMI deployments SHOULD utilize the local repair
          mechanisms in RPL.</t>

          <t>Local repair is triggered by broken link detection and in storing
          mode by loop detection as well. </t>

          <t>The first local repair mechanism consists of a node detaching
          from a DODAG and then re-attaching to the same or to a different
          DODAG at a later time. While detached, a node advertises an infinite
          rank value so that its children can select a different parent. This
          process is known as poisoning and is described in Section 8.2.2.5 of
          <xref target="I-D.ietf-roll-rpl"></xref>. While RPL provides an
          option to form a local DODAG, doing so in AMI deployments is of
          little benefit since AMI applications typically communicate through
          a LBR. After the detached node has made sufficient effort to send
          notification to its children that it is detached, the node can
          rejoin the same DODAG with a higher rank value. The configured
          duration of the poisoning mechanism needs to take into account the
          disconnection time applications running over the network can
          tolerate. Note that when joining a different DODAG, the node need
          not perform poisoning. </t>

          <t>The second local repair mechanism controls how much a node can
          increase its rank within a given DODAG Version (e.g., after
          detaching from the DODAG as a result of broken link or loop
          detection). Setting the DAGMaxRankIncrease to a non-zero value
          enables this mechanism, and setting it to a value of less than
          infinity limits the cost of count-to-infinity scenarios when they
          occur, thus controlling the duration of disconnection applications
          may experience.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Multicast">
          <t>RPL defines multicast support for its storing mode of operation,
          where the DODAG structure built for unicast packet dissemination is
          used for multicast distribution as well. In particular, multicast
          forwarding state creation is done through DAO messages with
          multicast target options sent along the DODAG towards the root.
          Thereafter nodes with forwarding state for a particular group
          forward multicast packets along the DODAG by copying them to all
          children from which they have received a DAO with a multicast target
          option for the group.</t>

          <t>Multicast support for RPL in non-storing mode will be defined in
          companion RFCs.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Security">
          <t>AMI deployments operate in areas that do not provide any physical
          security. For this reason, the link layer, transport layer and
          application layer technologies utilized within AMI networks
          typically provide security mechanisms to ensure authentication,
          confidentiality, integrity, and freshness. As a result, AMI
          deployments may not need to implement RPL's security mechanisms and
          could rely on link layer and higher layer security features.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="P2P communications">
          <t>Distribution Automation and other emerging applications may
          require efficient P2P communications. Basic P2P capabilities are
          already defined in the RPL RFC <xref
          target="I-D.ietf-roll-rpl"></xref>. Additional mechanisms for
          efficient P2P communication are being developed in companion
          RFCs.</t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section title="Recommended Configuration Defaults and Ranges">
        <section title="Trickle Parameters">
          <t>Trickle was designed to be density-aware and perform well in
          networks characterized by a wide range of node densities. The
          combination of DIO packet suppression and adaptive timers for
          sending updates allows Trickle to perform well in both sparse and
          dense environments.</t>

          <t>Node densities in AMI deployments can vary greatly, from nodes
          having only one or a handful of neighbors to nodes having several
          hundred neighbors. In high density environments, relatively low
          values for Imin may cause a short period of congestion when an
          inconsistency is detected and DIO updates are sent by a large number
          of neighboring nodes nearly simultaneously. While the Trickle timer
          will exponentially backoff, some time may elapse before the
          congestion subsides. While some link layers employ contention
          mechanisms that attempt to avoid congestion, relying solely on the
          link layer to avoid congestion caused by a large number of DIO
          updates can result in increased communication latency for other
          control and data traffic in the network.</t>

          <t>To mitigate this kind of short-term congestion, this document
          recommends a more conservative set of values for the Trickle
          parameters than those specified in <xref target="RFC6206"></xref>.
          In particular, DIOIntervalMin is set to a larger value to avoid
          periods of congestion in dense environments, and
          DIORefundancyConstant is parameterized accordingly as described
          below. These values are appropriate for the timely distribution of
          DIO updates in both sparse and dense scenarios while avoiding the
          short-term congestion that might arise in dense scenarios.</t>

          <t>Because the actual link capacity depends on the particular link
          technology used within an AMI deployment, the Trickle parameters are
          specified in terms of the link's maximum capacity for transmitting
          link-local multicast messages. If the link can transmit m link-local
          multicast packets per second on average, the expected time it takes
          to transmit a link-local multicast packet is 1/m seconds. <list
              style="hanging">
              <t hangText="DIOIntervalMin:">AMI deployments SHOULD set
              DIOIntervalMin such that the Trickle Imin is at least 50 times
              as long as it takes to transmit a link-local multicast packet.
              This value is larger than that recommended in <xref
              target="RFC6206"></xref> to avoid congestion in dense urban
              deployments as described above. In energy-constrained
              deployments (e.g., in water and gas battery-based routing
              infrastructure), DIOIntervalMin MAY be set to a value resulting
              in a Trickle Imin of several (e.g. 2) hours.</t>

              <t hangText="DIOIntervalDoublings:">AMI deployments SHOULD set
              DIOIntervalDoublings such that the Trickle Imax is at least 2
              hours or more. For very energy constrained deployments (e.g.,
              water and gas battery-based routing infrastructure),
              DIOIntervalDoublings MAY be set to a value resulting in a
              Trickle Imax of several (e.g., 2) days.</t>

              <t hangText="DIORedundancyConstant:">AMI deployments SHOULD set
              DIORedundancyConstant to a value of at least 10. This is due to
              the larger chosen value for DIOIntervalMin and the proportional
              relationship between Imin and k suggested in <xref
              target="RFC6206"></xref>. This increase is intended to
              compensate for the increased communication latency of DIO
              updates caused by the increase in the DIOIntervalMin value,
              though the proportional relationship between Imin and k
              suggested in <xref target="RFC6206"></xref> is not preserved.
              Instead, DIORedundancyConstant is set to a lower value in order
              to reduce the number of packet transmissions in dense
              environments. </t>
            </list></t>
        </section>

        <section title="Other Parameters">
          <t><list style="symbols">
              <t>AMI deployments SHOULD set MinHopRankIncrease to 256,
              resulting in 8 bits of resolution (e.g., for the ETX
              metric).</t>

              <t>To enable local repair, AMI deployments SHOULD set
              MaxRankIncrease to a value that allows a device to move a small
              number of hops away from the root. With a MinHopRankIncrease of
              256, a MaxRankIncrease of 1024 would allow a device to move up
              to 4 hops away.</t>
            </list></t>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Manageability Considerations">
      <t>Network manageability is a critical aspect of smart grid network
      deployment and operation. With millions of devices participating in the
      smart grid network, many requiring real-time reachability, automatic
      configuration, and lightweight network health monitoring and management
      are crucial for achieving network availability and efficient
      operation.</t>

      <t>RPL enables automatic and consistent configuration of RPL routers
      through parameters specified by the DODAG root and disseminated through
      DIO packets. The use of Trickle for scheduling DIO transmissions ensures
      lightweight yet timely propagation of important network and parameter
      updates and allows network operators to choose the trade-off point they
      are comfortable with respect to overhead vs. reliability and timeliness
      of network updates. </t>

      <t>The metrics in use in the network along with the Trickle Timer
      parameters used to control the frequency and redundancy of network
      updates can be dynamically varied by the root during the lifetime of the
      network. To that end, all DIO messages SHOULD contain a Metric Container
      option for disseminating the metrics and metric values used for DODAG
      setup. In addition, DIO messages SHOULD contain a DODAG Configuration
      option for disseminating the Trickle Timer parameters throughout the
      network.</t>

      <t>The possibility of dynamically updating the metrics in use in the
      network as well as the frequency of network updates allows deployment
      characteristics (e.g., network density) to be discovered during network
      bring-up and to be used to tailor network parameters once the network is
      operational rather than having to rely on precise pre-configuration.
      This also allows the network parameters and the overall routing protocol
      behavior to evolve during the lifetime of the network.</t>

      <t>RPL specifies a number of variables and events that can be tracked
      for purposes of network fault and performance monitoring of RPL routers.
      Depending on the memory and processing capabilities of each smart grid
      device, various subsets of these can be employed in the field.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Security Considerations">
      <t>Smart grid networks are subject to stringent security requirements as
      they are considered a critical infrastructure component. At the same
      time, since they are composed of large numbers of resource-constrained
      devices inter-connected with limited-throughput links, many available
      security mechanisms are not practical for use in such networks. As a
      result, the choice of security mechanisms is highly dependent on the
      device and network capabilities characterizing a particular
      deployment.</t>

      <t>In contrast to other types of LLNs, in smart grid networks
      centralized administrative control and access to a permanent secure
      infrastructure is available. As a result link-layer, transport-layer
      and/or application-layer security mechanisms are typically in place and
      using RPL&rsquo;s secure mode is not necessary. </t>
    </section>

    <section title="Other Related Protocols">
      <t>This document contains no other related protocols.</t>
    </section>

    <!-- Possibly a 'Contributors' section ... -->

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>This memo includes no request to IANA.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>The authors would like to acknowledge the review, feedback, and
      comments of Dominique Barthel, Philip Levis, and Jari Arkko.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <!--  *****BACK MATTER ***** -->

  <back>
    <!-- References split into informative and normative -->

    <!-- There are 2 ways to insert reference entries from the citation libraries:
     1. define an ENTITY at the top, and use "ampersand character"RFC2629; here (as shown)
     2. simply use a PI "less than character"?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119.xml"?> here
        (for I-Ds: include="reference.I-D.narten-iana-considerations-rfc2434bis.xml")

     Both are cited textually in the same manner: by using xref elements.
     If you use the PI option, xml2rfc will, by default, try to find included files in the same
     directory as the including file. You can also define the XML_LIBRARY environment variable
     with a value containing a set of directories to search.  These can be either in the local
     filing system or remote ones accessed by http (http://domain/dir/... ).-->

    <references title="Informative References">
      &RFC5548;

      &RFC5673;

      &RFC5826;

      &RFC5867;

      &RFC6206;

      &I-D.ietf-6man-rpl-option;

      &I-D.ietf-roll-rpl;

      &I-D.ietf-roll-routing-metrics;

      &I-D.ietf-roll-p2p-rpl;

      &I-D.ietf-roll-terminology;
    </references>

    <references title="Normative References">
      &RFC2119;
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
<!--  LocalWords:  unicast anycast
 -->
