<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='http://xml.resource.org/authoring/rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="no" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<?rfc linkmailto="yes" ?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY RFC2119 PUBLIC ''
'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml'>
<!ENTITY RFC5594 PUBLIC ''
'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5594.xml'>
<!ENTITY RFC2975 PUBLIC ''
'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2975.xml'>
<!ENTITY RFC3588 PUBLIC ''
'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3588.xml'>
<!ENTITY RFC3576 PUBLIC ''
'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3576.xml'>
<!ENTITY RFC4006 PUBLIC ''
'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4006.xml'>
<!ENTITY RFC2866 PUBLIC ''
'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2866.xml'>
<!ENTITY RFC2865 PUBLIC ''
'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2865.xml'>
<!ENTITY I-D.livingood-woundy-congestion-mgmt PUBLIC ''
'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.livingood-woundy-congestion-mgmt.xml'>
<!ENTITY I-D.irtf-p2prg-mythbustering PUBLIC ''
'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.irtf-p2prg-mythbustering.xml'>
]>

<rfc category="info" ipr="trust200902" docName="draft-tschofenig-conex-ps-01.txt">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="Congestion Exposure PS">Congestion Exposure Problem Statement</title>
    <author initials="H." surname="Tschofenig" fullname="Hannes Tschofenig">
      <organization>Nokia Siemens Networks</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Linnoitustie 6</street>
          <city>Espoo</city>
          <code>FIN-02600</code>
          <country>Finland</country>
        </postal>
        <phone>+358 (50) 4871445</phone>
        <email>Hannes.Tschofenig@gmx.net</email>
        <uri>http://www.tschofenig.priv.at</uri>
      </address>
    </author>
    <!-- 
    <author initials="B." surname="Aboba" fullname="Bernard Aboba">
      <organization>Microsoft Corporation</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>One Microsoft Way</street>
          <city>Redmond</city>
          <region>WA</region>
          <code>98052</code>
          <country>US</country>
        </postal>
        <email>bernarda@microsoft.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    -->

    <author fullname="Alissa Cooper" initials="A." surname="Cooper">
      <organization>Center for Democracy &amp; Technology</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>1634 I Street NW, Suite 1100</street>
          <city>Washington</city>
          <region>DC</region>
          <code/>
          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>
        <email>acooper@cdt.org</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date year="2009"/>
    <area>Transport Area</area>
    <workgroup>CONEX</workgroup>
    <keyword>Internet-Draft</keyword>
    <abstract>
      <t> The increasingly ubiquitous availability of broadband, together with flat-rate pricing,
        have made the use of new kinds of peer-to-peer applications increasingly common. From the
        perspective of the Internet's evolution and its contributions to end user value, this is
        very exciting. However, the uptick in peer-to-peer application usage has also contributed to
        the rise of "high-consuming users" who take their flat-rate contracts to the limit by
        continuously file-sharing to the maximum extent possible. Network operators have responded
        to this phenomenon in a number of different fashions.</t>
      <t> This document discusses the problems created for operators by high-consuming users and
        illustrates a number of techniques operators are currently using to cope with high bandwidth
        usage. </t>
    </abstract>
  </front>
  <middle>

    <!-- ====================================================================== -->

    <section anchor="introduction" title="Introduction">
      <t> In recent years, network operators around the world have begun to feel the affects of
        "high-consuming users" -- those who use the maximum amount of bandwidth possible, usually
        for the purpose of peer-to-peer file sharing. In 2006 K. Cho et al. <xref target="traffic"/>
        reported that for residential Japanese broadband connections, "a small number of users
        dictate the overall behavior; 4% of high-consuming users account for 75% of the inbound
        volume, and the fiber users account for 86% of the inbound volume." A more recent paper
        published December 2008, see <xref target="traffic2"/>, confirms that the distribution has
        not changed much. User-to-user traffic comprised 63% of overall residential traffic volume.
        The authors noted not only a changing traffic distribution, but also a substantial increase
        in overall traffic growth (37% per year). Operators in other countries have experienced
        similar shifts. </t>
      <t> This trend does not necessarily present a problem on its face, as increased traffic
        volumes do not automatically lead to congestion. However, in some cases where operators were
        not expecting these changes in growth rates and traffic consumption, their pricing models
        and congestion management architectures have proved inadequate. In some countries, fierce
        competition among Internet access providers has yielded low profit margins. This has
        increased the pressure on operators to find effective ways to deal with high- consuming
        users who cost them more money than the bulk of their subscribers. Furthermore, some
        broadband networks (such as cable networks) may not have the ideal characteristics (routing
        topology, for example) to support high volumes of user-to-user traffic. </t>
      <t>Congestion and cost are closely related. As stated in RFC 5594 <xref target="RFC5594"/>,
        "... congestion can be viewed merely as a manifestation of cost. An ISP that invests in
        capacity could be considered to be paying to relieve congestion. Or, if subscribers are
        charged for congesting the network, then cost and congestion could be viewed as one and the
        same. The distinction between them may thus be artificial.". The upshot for network
        operators is: those who produce a lot of traffic cost a lot. </t>
      <t> Operators are now facing a range of options for addressing this problem. There are many
        factors to consider for each kind of solution, including how the solution performs, its
        cost, what the public relations impact of using a particular solution might be, and what
        legal framework exists to support the use of a particular solution. The performance
        considerations must take into account the balance between device performance and forwarding
        performance (since many of the solution mechanisms slow down forwarding performance), and
        this determination is intimiately related to measuring a solution's overall cost. </t>
      <t> In some cases, the popularity of flat-rate pricing plans exacerbate the congestion problem
        because an individual's bandwidth usage is not tied to his or her monthly bill, creating an
        incentive to use as much bandwidth as possible and leaving operators to cover the costs of
        all their users with essentially equal payments from each. Operators know that users
        appreciate the certainty of having the bill amount remain the same for each billing period,
        allowing users to plan their costs accordingly. But while flat-rate pricing avoids billing
        uncertainty, it creates performance uncertainty: users cannot be sure that the performance
        of their connections is not being altered or degrated based on how the network operator
        manages congestion. Unfortunately, most of the solutions described below create some
        performance uncertainty, and thus users are unlikely to view them as ideal solutions,
        despite users' well known preference for flat-rate pricing. </t>
    </section>

    <!-- ====================================================================== -->

    <section title="State-of-the-Art Building Blocks">

      <t>Two means of learning about the resource consumption and the traffic traveling through the
        network that are in use today are accounting and deep packet inspection. </t>

      <section title="Accounting">
        <t> RFC 2975 <xref target="RFC2975"/> describes accounting as "The collection of resource
          consumption data for the purposes of capacity and trend analysis, cost allocation,
          auditing, and billing.".</t>
        <t> Over the years the number of information elements that can be sent from an accounting
          client to an accounting server using standardized protocols, such as RADIUS (see <xref
            target="RFC2866"/> and <xref target="RFC2865"/>) and Diameter <xref target="RFC3588"/>,
          has increased. The existence of standardized protocols has allowed different AAA networks
          to interconnect. These protocols are now used in almost every enterprise and operator
          network. The initial accounting mechanisms envisioned a rather non-real time nature in
          reporting resource consumption but with mechanisms like like Diameter Credit Control <xref
            target="RFC4006"/> allowed real-time credit control checks. </t>
        <t>Although they are popular, RADIUS and Diameter are not the only protocols that can be
          used to collect usage information and to trigger responses. Other approaches, as
          documented in <xref target="I-D.livingood-woundy-congestion-mgmt"/>, lead to similar
          results.</t>
      </section>
      <section title="Deep Packet Inspection">
        <t>Deep packet inspection (DPI) refers to the observation and analysis of traffic that
          passes through operator networks up to the application layer. This allows operators to
          determine the applications and/or application-layer protocols that subscribers are using
          and respond on a per-application or per-protocol basis.</t>
        <t> The process of inspecting traffic, particularly in real time, can be highly
          performance-intensive. DPI equipment may also require continous software updates to ensure
          that the detection engine recognizes the latest protocol variants. </t>
        <t> There may be a number of other factors that contribute to a network operator's decision
          to use DPI, including potential user backlash, privacy impact, and legal concerns. </t>
        <t> Depending on the configuration of the device doing the inspection, packet
          dropping/blocking and other usages might be applied. For example, content sharing p2p
          applications maintain many simultaneous TCP connections with other nodes for the purpose
          of simultaneous downloads. An operator may, for example, limit . Certain end user
          contracts may also allow operators to ban servers from residential access. </t>
      </section>

    </section>

    <section title="Network Operator Responses to Congestion">
      <t> Once they have collected congestion information using either of the techniques described
        above or others, network operators have a number of options for how to respond. For all of
        these options, it is up to the operator to decide the breadth and depth of its response:
        which users will be affected, the time frame in which congestion will be managed, whether
        specific applications or protocols will be targeted, and so forth. Operators can chose from
        both technical and pricing/contract-based options. Technical options include:</t>
      <t>
        <list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="Wholistic traffic shaping:"><vspace blankLines="1"/> End user contracts often
            provide users with a certain threshold for baseline usage volume (which is typically
            quite high). Subsequently, if consumption goes beyond the threshold, all of the user's
            traffic is given reduced priority vis a vis other users on the network. Some operators
            may only shape traffic during times of congestion or peak usage periods (even if a user
            has exceeded his or her baseline threshold). </t>
          <t hangText="Per-application or per-protocol shaping:">
            <vspace blankLines="1"/>Network operators that can identify particular applications or
            protocols creating congestion may decide to throttle only those applications or
            protocols. They may also take indirect steps that result in the shaping of only certain
            applications, such as limiting the number of simultaneous TCP connection setups from a
            single subscriber (to handle peer-to-peer traffic), or preventing users from hosting
            servers on residential connections. An example of an ISP's fair usage policy describing
            how it manages specific protocols is included in Appendix A.</t>

          <t hangText="Class-Based Assignment:"><vspace blankLines="1"/>In this technique users are
            classified into a set of classes depending on their past behavior. Subsequently, their
            traffic is treated according to their associated classes. This may prevent lightweight
            users from feeling the effects of sharing network capacity with heavy users. This
            mechanism requires some form of packet marking to be able to differentiate light users
            from heavy users. </t>

          <t hangText="Pricing/contract-based options include:">
            <vspace blankLines="1"/>
            <list style="hanging">
              <t hangText="Charging for Excessive Traffic:">Network operators may charge users
                differently for traffic that exeeds a certain threshold compared to the traffic that
                falls below the threshold. </t>
              <t hangText="Suspending or Discontinuing Contracts:"> In some rare cases ISPs may
                decide to suspend or terminate the contracts of heavy users. In some cases this
                response may be associated with a security issue; when an operator recognizes a
                botnet-infected machine generating excessive traffic, it may hotline all the traffic
                of that particular machine to a separate network, and ultimately suspend or
                terminate the machine's connection. In some cases the same technique has been
                applied to users engaged in heavy P2P usage, either intentionally or due to a false
                alarm caused by a statistical traffic analysis. </t>
            </list>
          </t>
        </list>
      </t>
    </section>

    <!-- ====================================================================== -->

    <section title="New Activities">
      <t> Following the IETF Workshop on Peer-to-Peer (P2P) Infrastructure in 2008 (see <xref
          target="RFC5594"/>), two working groups and one research group were created that relate to
        the congestion issues created by peer-to-peer application usage: :<list style="empty">
          <t> LEDBAT (Low Extra Delay Background Transport) <xref target="ledbat"/> is designed to
            keep the latency across a congested bottleneck low even as it is saturated. This allows
            applications that send large amounts of data, particularly upstream on home connections
            (such as peer-to-peer applications) to operate without destroying the user experience in
            interactive applications. <vspace blankLines="1"/> LEDBAT holds substantial promise
            should P2P clients adopt it widely. This solution has been focused on P2P applications,
            and its applicability to other applications, such as video using H.264, is unclear.</t>

          <t>ALTO (Application-Layer Traffic Optimization) <xref target="alto"/> aims to design and
            specify mechanisms that will provide applications, typically P2P applications, with
            information to perform better- than-random initial peer selection to increase their
            performance and at the same time to avoid excessive cross-domain traffic that tends to
            be more expensive for the operator. ALTO services may take different approaches at
            balancing factors such as maximum bandwidth, minimum cross-domain traffic, or lowest
            cost to the user, but in all cases the goal is to expose information that can ameliorate
            the interactions between peer-to-peer usage and other usages of shared networks. </t>

          <t>Peer to Peer Research Group <xref target="p2prg"/> aims to provide a discussion forum
            for resarchers related to all sorts of challenges presented by P2P systems in general,
            such as P2P streaming, interconnecting distinct P2P application overlays, security and
            privacy. Current work on exposing myths about peer-to-peer filesharing <xref
              target="I-D.irtf-p2prg-mythbustering"/> provides a number of references to support
            some of the claimed benefits of ALTO solutions mechanisms, such as the expected decrease
            in cross- domain traffic. </t>
        </list>
      </t>
    </section>

    <!-- ====================================================================== -->

    <section title="Summary">
      <t> High-consuming users are a reality. Operators that would like to counteract the impact of
        heavy users on their networks have a fair number of tools at their disposal. These tools may
        allow operators to identify heavy users, collect performance and usage indications, and
        choose from a variety of mitigating steps depending on the operator's preferred business
        practices. Subscriber-specific information, including policies, resource consumption
        information, and details about the current network attachment point, may be available in
        accounting servers. Information about the network topology and the state of particular
        topology elements may be available in the network management infrastructure. Solution
        approaches similar to <xref target="I-D.livingood-woundy-congestion-mgmt"/> have
        demonstrated one way of taking congestion information into consideration.</t>
      <t> The currently available mechanisms for identifying and mitigating congestion largely run
        wholly within an operator's network and without a lot of information exchange about
        congestion information to or from end hosts or other network operators. Exposing this
        information may allow end devices to make more informed decisions (although policy
        enforcement would still be required by the operator). </t>
      <t> The collection of congestion information poses the challenge of deciding where in the
        network to put the metering agents to ensure that enough information is collected at the
        right point in time. Distributed collection and the correlation of the information across
        different nodes is a complex task. An approach that collects this congestion information
        along the path of the data packet (via inband signaling) would simplify this task.
        Regardless of the technical solution utilized for collecting information, certain users will
        undoubtedly observe the effects of decisions that operators make about how to handle
        congestion. Allowing users to understand these decisions will be crucial and having a
        channel to send feedback to the end device and/or subscriber would be a helpful step towards
        increased transparency. </t>

    </section>

    <!-- ====================================================================== -->

    <section title="Security Considerations">
      <t> This document highlights approaches for dealing with high-consuming network users and all
        of them raise security and privacy concerns. It does not introduce new mechanisms. The
        security considerations for the existing mechanisms mentioned apply. </t>
    </section>

    <!-- ====================================================================== -->

    <section title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>This document does not require actions by IANA.</t>
    </section>

    <!-- ====================================================================== -->

    <section title="Acknowledgments">
      <t> The authors would like to thank Alan DeKok, Jens-Peter Haack, Alexander Bachmutsky, Jonne
        Soininen, Joachim Charzinski, Hannu Flinck, Joachim Kroß, Jouni Korhonen, Mayutan Arumaithurai, Richard Woundy,
        Daniel Correa Lobato, Luca Caviglione, Tommy Lindgren, Lars Eggert, for their time to
        discuss the topic. Additionally, we would like to thank Marcin Matuszewski for his help with
        the P2P infrastructure workshop paper (since it was used as a starting point for the work on
        this memo). </t>
    </section>
  </middle>
  <!-- ====================================================================== -->
  <back>
    <references title="Normative References"> &RFC2119; </references>
    <references title="Informative References"> &RFC5594; &RFC2975; &RFC3588;
      &RFC3576; &RFC4006; &RFC2866; &RFC2865;
      &I-D.livingood-woundy-congestion-mgmt; &I-D.irtf-p2prg-mythbustering; <reference
        anchor="traffic">
        <front>
          <title>The impact and implications of the growth in residential user-to-user traffic</title>
          <author initials="K" surname="Cho" fullname="Kenjiro Cho">
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <author initials="K" surname="Fukuda" fullname="Kensuke Fukuda">
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <author initials="H" surname="Kato" fullname="Hiroshi Kato">
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <author initials="A" surname="Kato" fullname="Akira Kato">
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <date year="2006"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="SIGCOMM Comput. Commun. Rev." value="36"/>
        <format type="HTML" target="http://doi.acm.org/10.1145/1151659.1159938"/>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="traffic2">
        <front>
          <title>Observing slow crustal movement in residential user traffic, in International
            Conference On Emerging Networking Experiments And Technologies, Proceedings of the 2008
            ACM CoNEXT Conference, Madrid, Spain, Article No. 12</title>
          <author initials="K" surname="Cho" fullname="Kenjiro Cho">
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <author initials="K" surname="Fukuda" fullname="Kensuke Fukuda">
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <author initials="H" surname="Esaki" fullname="Hiroshi Esaki">
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <author initials="A" surname="Kato" fullname="Akira Kato">
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <date year="2008"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="" value=""/>
        <format type="HTML" target="http://portal.acm.org/citation.cfm?doid=1544012.1544024"/>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="alto" target="http://www.ietf.org/dyn/wg/charter/alto-charter.html">
        <front>
          <title/>
          <!-- The title's extraneous quote marks in the text ouput will be removed before 
            publication, unless you want to add a title to this reference. -->
          <author>
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <date/>
        </front>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="ledbat" target="http://www.ietf.org/dyn/wg/charter/ledbat-charter.html">
        <front>
          <title/>
          <!-- The title's extraneous quote marks in the text ouput will be removed before 
            publication, unless you want to add a title to this reference. -->
          <author>
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <date/>
        </front>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="p2prg" target="http://www.irtf.org/charter?gtype=rg&group=p2prg">
        <front>
          <title/>
          <!-- The title's extraneous quote marks in the text ouput will be removed before 
            publication, unless you want to add a title to this reference. -->
          <author>
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <date/>
        </front>
      </reference>
    </references>

    <section anchor="policy" title="Example Policy Statement">

      <section title="Fair Usage Policy">

        <section title="What is the Fair Usage Policy?">


          <t>The Fair Usage Policy is designed to ensure that the service received by the vast
            majority of our customers is not negatively impacted because of extremely heavy usage by
            a very small minority of customers. This is why ISP X continuously monitors network
            performance and may restrict the speed available to very heavy users during peak time.
            This applies to customers on all Options. Note if you are a heavy user we will only
            restrict your speed, service will not be stopped so ability to upload and download
            remains. No restrictions will be imposed outside of the peak times. Only a very small
            minority of customers will ever be affected by this (less than 1 %). </t>

        </section>
        <section title="How do I know I'm a very heavy user?">

          <t> There is no hard and fast usage limit that determines if you are a heavy user as the
            parameters that determine heavy use vary with the demands placed on the network at that
            given time. If you have a query about fair usage related restrictions on your line
            please call us. </t>
        </section>


        <section title="I have Contract Option 3, does the Fair Usage Policy
    apply to me?">

          <t> Yes, the Fair Usage Policy applies to all customers on all Options, including Option
            3. Option 3 allows unlimited downloads and uploads inclusive of the monthly rental
            price, so you will not be charged for over-use, however this does not preclude ISP X
            from restricting your speed at peak times if you are a heavy user. If you are an Option
            3 heavy user this does not prevent you from continuing to use your service, nor does it
            cost you any more but it ensures that you do not negatively impact the majority of our
            customers who share the available bandwidth with you. </t>
        </section>

        <section title="Peer to Peer (P2P)">

          <section
            title="I'm noticing slower P2P speeds at peak times even though I'm not a
    very heavy user, why is this?">
            <t> P2P is the sharing and delivery of files amongst groups of people who are logged on
              to a file sharing network. P2P consumes a significant and highly disproportionate
              amount of bandwidth when in use even by small numbers of users. </t>
            <t>This is why we have a peak time policy where we limit P2P speeds to manage the amount
              of bandwidth that is used by this application in particular. </t>
            <t>Without these limits all our customers using their broadband service at peak times
              would suffer, regardless of whether they are using P2P or not. It's important to
              remember that P2P isn't a time-critical application so if you do need to download
              large files we advise you to do this at off-peak times when no restrictions are
              placed, not only will you be able to download faster but your usage will not
              negatively impact other users. </t>
          </section>

          <section title="Does this mean I can't use Peer-to-Peer (P2P) applications?">

            <t> No, we are not stopping you from using any P2P service, P2P will just be slowed down
              at peak times. Again, P2P is not generally a time-sensitive application. </t>
          </section>

        </section>
      </section>

    </section>
  </back>

</rfc>
