<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='http://xml.resource.org/authoring/rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="no" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<?rfc linkmailto="yes" ?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY RFC2119 PUBLIC ''
'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml'>
<!ENTITY RFC5594 PUBLIC ''
'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5594.xml'>
<!ENTITY RFC2975 PUBLIC ''
'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2975.xml'>
<!ENTITY RFC3588 PUBLIC ''
'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3588.xml'>
<!ENTITY RFC3576 PUBLIC ''
'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3576.xml'>
<!ENTITY RFC4006 PUBLIC ''
'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4006.xml'>
<!ENTITY RFC2866 PUBLIC ''
'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2866.xml'>
<!ENTITY RFC2865 PUBLIC ''
'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2865.xml'>
<!ENTITY I-D.livingood-woundy-congestion-mgmt PUBLIC ''
'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.livingood-woundy-congestion-mgmt.xml'>
<!ENTITY I-D.irtf-p2prg-mythbustering PUBLIC ''
'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.irtf-p2prg-mythbustering.xml'>
]>

<rfc category="info" ipr="trust200902" docName="draft-tschofenig-conex-ps-00.txt">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="Congestion Exposure PS">Congestion Exposure Problem Statement</title>
    <author initials="H." surname="Tschofenig" fullname="Hannes Tschofenig">
      <organization>Nokia Siemens Networks</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Linnoitustie 6</street>
          <city>Espoo</city>
          <code>FIN-02600</code>
          <country>Finland</country>
        </postal>
        <phone>+358 (50) 4871445</phone>
        <email>Hannes.Tschofenig@gmx.net</email>
        <uri>http://www.tschofenig.priv.at</uri>
      </address>
    </author>
    <!-- 
    <author initials="B." surname="Aboba" fullname="Bernard Aboba">
      <organization>Microsoft Corporation</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>One Microsoft Way</street>
          <city>Redmond</city>
          <region>WA</region>
          <code>98052</code>
          <country>US</country>
        </postal>
        <email>bernarda@microsoft.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    --> 
    
    <author fullname="Alissa Cooper" initials="A." surname="Cooper">
      <organization>Center for Democracy &amp; Technology</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>1634 I Street NW, Suite 1100</street>
          <city>Washington</city>
          <region>DC</region>
          <code/>
          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>
        <email>acooper@cdt.org</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date year="2009"/>
    <area>Transport Area</area>
    <workgroup>CONEX</workgroup>
    <keyword>Internet-Draft</keyword>
    <abstract>
      <t> The availability of broadband connections together with flat-rate pricing has made new
        types of peer-to-peer applications possible. From an Internet evolution and end user value
        point of view this is very exciting. As a consequence, an increase of user-to-user traffic
        was observable all around the world over the last few years. With the usage of p2p systems
        the observation can be made that a certain group of users, called high-consuming users,
        decided to use their flat-rate contract excessively. This in turn seems to have caused
        network operators to take actions.</t>
      <t>This document illustrates a couple of techniques used by operators today to deal with
        excessive bandwidth usage. More information can improve the decision making process.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>
  <middle>

    <!-- ====================================================================== -->

    <section anchor="introduction" title="Introduction">

      <t>In 2006 K. Cho et al. <xref target="traffic"/> published a paper about the growth of
        residential user-to-user traffic in Japan that indicates '... a small number of users
        dictate the overall behavior; 4 % of high-consuming users account for 75 % of the inbound
        volume, and the fiber users account for 86 % of the inbound volume.'. The same paper also
        indicates a substantial increase in traffic growth, namely 37 % per year according, and not
        just a different distribution of traffic among the users. At that time 63 % of the
        residential traffic volume is contributed by user-to-user traffic. </t>
      <!--      <t>
        <list style="empty">
          <t>There is fewer detailed research data for other countries, such as in Europe or in the
            US, available. [Editor's Note: Are there any reference to more recent data? How did the
            traffic growth evolve in the last few years and how the traffic distribution with
            respect to user-to-user traffic?] </t>
        </list>
      </t>
-->
      <t> These numbers itself do not represent a problem as by themself and do not necessarily lead
        to congestion. However, some operators very likely had different expectations about the
        growth rates and traffic consumption of individual users and statistics (used for their
        pricing models) did not work out too well for them. The profit margins for Internet access
        are quite slim due to fierce competition. This puts a lot of pressure on operators to deal
        with these high-consuming users who cost them a lot of money. Finally, some broadband
        networks may not have the ideal characteristics (such as the topology for routing traffic)
        for user-to-user traffic (e.g., Cable Networks). </t>
      <t>
        <list style="empty">
          <t> Congestion is often mentioned in this context and as stated in RFC 5594 <xref
              target="RFC5594"/> "... congestion can be viewed merely as a manifestation of cost. An
            ISP that invests in capacity could be considered to be paying to relieve congestion. Or,
            if subscribers are charged for congesting the network, then cost and congestion could be
            viewed as one and the same. The distinction between them may thus be artificial.". </t>
          <!-- <t>Furthermore, one has to consider how ISPs data traffic pricing works. [Editor's Note:
            Add text here.]</t> -->
        </list>
      </t>
      <t>To summarize in a simplistic way, those who produce a lot of traffic cost a lot.</t>
      <t> Operators are now facing a range of options, see sections below, that can be taken and
        there is a tradeoff between what is allowed (legally and from a public relation point of
        view) and what is useful from a performance point of view. The latter aspect can be seen
        from the point of view of a device performance (as many of the mechanisms actually slow down
        the forwarding performance quite a bit) and consequently a cost challenge.</t>

      <t> The existence of flat rate pricing contributes to some of the problems since the bandwidth
        usage in total needs to be covered by the money obtained from broadband customers but the
        usage of individual users is not reflected in the amount. As such, users that rarely utilize
        the network pay the same amount as someone who uses P2p filesharing excessively. </t>

      <t>However, from a psychological point of view humans tend to strive to avoid uncertainty and
        hence offerings that reduced uncertainty. For a user there are essentially two aspects to
        worry about <list style="symbols">
          <t>Uncertainty in the bill: unpredicable costs that make planning difficult.</t>
          <t>Uncertainty in the performance: performance degradation as part of the actions being
            taken</t>
        </list> True flat rate pricing avoids uncertainty in the bill. Unfortunately, most of the
        solutions described below lead to some uncertainty and thereby increase unhappyness of
        customers. </t>
    </section>

    <!-- ====================================================================== -->

    <section title="State-of-the-Art Building Blocks">

      <section title="Means of Identifying the Causes of Congestion">

        <t> RFC 2975 <xref target="RFC2975"/> describes accounting as "The collection of resource
          consumption data for the purposes of capacity and trend analysis, cost allocation,
          auditing, and billing.".</t>

        <t> Over the years the number of information elements that can be sent from an accounting
          client to an accounting server using standardized protocols, such as RADIUS (see <xref
            target="RFC2866"/> and <xref target="RFC2865"/>) and Diameter <xref target="RFC3588"/>,
          has increased. The fact that standardized protocols have been available allowed different
          AAA networks to be interconnected and their usage can be found in almost every enterprise
          and operator network. The initial accounting mechanisms envisioned a rather non-real time
          nature in reporting resource consumption but with mechanisms like like Diameter Credit
          Control <xref target="RFC4006"/> allowed real-time credit control checks. </t>
        <t> It has to be noted that RADIUS and Diameter are not the only protocols that can be used
          to collect usage information and to trigger certain actions, even they are fairly popular.
          Other approaches, as documented in <xref target="I-D.livingood-woundy-congestion-mgmt"/>,
          lead to similar results.</t>

        <t>Deep packet inspection refers to inspecting traffic that passes through the operators
          networks up to the application layer. Depending on the configuration of the device traffic
          shaping, packet dropping/blocking and other usages might be applied. For example, content
          sharing p2p applications maintain many simultaneous TCP connections with other nodes for
          the purpose of simultaneous downloads. An operator may, for example, limit the number of
          connection setups from a single subscriber. Certain end user contracts may also allow
          operators to ban servers from residential access. </t>
        <t>Determining the type of application that a subscriber is running was seen as necessary to
          throttle only certain applications, instead of impacting the full range of traffic a
          subscriber is using. A side-effect is the additional investment for the device and
          operational costs. The process of inspecting traffic is performance intensive and
          continous software updates are necessary to ensure that the detection engine recognizes
          the latest protocol variants. Additionally, the attempt to selectively deal with
          applications (even though these applications might be the reason for the high traffic
          volume) has not been received well by the users. </t>
      </section>
      <section title="Potential Actions Operators might take in Response">
        <t>What actions are taken based on the collected information and in what time frame is
          largely left to the choice of those who run the infrastructure. In the context of this
          discussion the collected information may be used to charge the user per volume, per time
          and in various different combinations. Additionally, the RADIUS and Diameter allow the
          server side with a server-initiated message (see Change of Authorization in <xref
            target="RFC3576"/>, and the functionality provided in the Diameter Base specification
            <xref target="RFC3588"/>) to push decisions to the AAA clients, typically edge nodes,
          acting as enforcement nodes. These decisions include actions like shaping or packet
          marking. </t>
        <t>
          <list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="Shaping:"> End user contracts often offer a combination of 'flat-rate'
              scheme whereby a fixed price tariff is used up to a certain usage volume (typically
              quite high for regular usage). Subsequently, if the consumption goes beyond a certain
              threshold then the entire traffic is given lower priority and potentially shaped.
                <list style="empty">
                <t>In many countries operators have to offer a clear description of the service they
                  offer and since the term 'flat-rate' is already associated with a certain meaning
                  the term 'Unlimited Data Rate' is often used for this type of service. Contracts
                  typically contain statements that allow certain actions to be taken. An example of
                  such a fair use statement can be found in <xref target="policy"/>. </t>
              </list> Note that traffic shaping is often only applied to high-consuming users (since
              they are known based on the accounting procedures) or the effect becomes only visible
              during peak hours when the network fills up. </t>

            <t hangText="Class-Based Assignment:"> In this technique users are classified into a set
              of classes depending on their past behavior. Subsequently, the traffic is treated
              according to the associated class. It is ensured that the traffic of lightweight
              users, users that really rarely use their Internet connection, cannot be pushed away
              by heavy users. This mechanism again requires some form of DiffServ marking to be in
              place. </t>

            <t hangText="Charging for Excessive Traffic:"> As a possible action a user might get
              charged differently for traffic that exeeds a certain threshold compared to the
              traffic that falls within the agreed limits. </t>

            <t hangText="Discontinuing Contracts:">In some rare cases ISP also decided to cut
              connectivity under certain condition. In fact this might be justified in certain
              cases. For example, in case of new botnets malware distribution when the operator
              recognizes an infected machine and hotlines the entire traffic of that particular
              machine to a separate network and, like in WLAN hotspots, HTTP traffic is intercepted
              to display further information. In some cases the same technique has been applied with
              excessive usage of P2P traffic, either intentionally or due to a false alarm caused by
              a statistical traffic analysis technique.<vspace blankLines="1"/> In France the HADOPI
              law adopted in parliament that allowed an 'independent authority' to punish copyright
              violators with a temporary suspension of their Internet access has raised discussions
              within Europe about the fundamental right to 'communicate and express' and its
              applicability to the Internet access. Although this discussion is still ongoing the
              French Supreme Court had striked down portions of the law arguing that any restriction
              of such a right can only be decided by a judge. </t>
          </list>
        </t>
      </section>

    </section>

    <!-- ====================================================================== -->

    <section title="New Activities">
      <t> In response to the P2P infrastructure workshop in 2008 (with a summary documented <xref
          target="RFC5594"/>) two working groups and one research group has been created that focus
        on a certain area of the application space:<list style="empty">
          <t> LEDBAT (Low Extra Delay Background Transport) <xref target="ledbat"/> is designed to
            allow to keep the latency across the congested bottleneck low even as it is saturated.
            This allows applications that send large amounts of data, particularly upstream on home
            connections, such as peer-to-peer application, to operate without destroying the user
            experience in interactive applications. <vspace blankLines="1"/> LEDBAT is a promising
            approach when applied widely in P2P clients. This solution has been focused P2P applications, and its applicability to other applications, such as video using H.264, is unclear.</t>
          <t>ALTO (Application-Layer Traffic Optimization) <xref target="alto"/> aims to design and
            specify mechanisms that will provide applications, typically P2P applications, with
            information to perform better-than-random initial peer selection to increase their
            performance and at the same time to avoid excessive cross-domain traffic that tends to
            be more expensive for the operator. For legal content ALTO mechanisms with the ability
            for ISPs to deploy proxies appear to be a viable solution. However, a lot of the content
            being distributed in P2P filesharing networks today is not legal and caching such
            content by operators could turn out problematic for them. </t>
          <t>Peer to Peer Research Group <xref target="p2prg"/> aims to provide a discussion forum
            for resarchers related to all sorts of challenges of P2P systems in general, such as P2P
            streaming, interconnecting distinct P2P application overlays, security and privacy, etc.
              <xref target="I-D.irtf-p2prg-mythbustering"/> provides a number of literature
            references to support some of the claimed benefits of ALTO solutions mechanisms, such as
            the expected decrease in cross-domain traffic. </t>
        </list>
      </t>
    </section>

    <!-- ====================================================================== -->

    <section title="Summary">
      <t> Heavy users are a reality. Operators that would like to counteract the impact of heavy
        users on their networks have a fair number of tools at their disposal. These tools may allow
        operators to identify heavy users, collect performance and usage indications, and choose
        from a variety of mitigating steps depending on the operator's preferred business practices.
        Subscriber-specific information, including policies, resource consumption information, and
        details about the current network attachment point, may be available in accounting servers.
        Information about the network topology and the state of particular topology elements may be
        available in the network management infrastructure. Solution approaches similar to <xref
          target="I-D.livingood-woundy-congestion-mgmt"/> have demonstrated one way of taking
        congestion information into consideration. </t>
      <t> The currently available mechanisms for identifying and mitigating congestion largely run
        wholly within an operator's network and without a lot of information exchange about
        congestion information to or from end hosts or other network operators. Exposing this
        information may allow end devices to make more informed decisions (although policy
        enforcement would still be required by the operator).</t>
      <t> The collection of congestion information poses the challenge of deciding where in the
        network to put the metering agents to ensure that enough information is collected at the
        right point in time. Distributed collection and the correlation of the information across
        different nodes is a complex task. An approach that collects this congestion information
        along the path of the data packet (via inband signaling) would simplify this task.
        Regardless of the technical solution utilized for collecting information, certain users will
        undoubtedly observe the effects of decisions that operators make about how to handle
        congestion. Allowing users to understand these decisions will be crucial and having a
        channel to send feedback to the end device and/or subscriber would be a helpful step towards
        increased transparency. </t>

    </section>

    <!-- ====================================================================== -->

    <section title="Security Considerations">
      <t>This document highlights approaches for dealing with heavy network usage and all of them
        raise security and privacy concerns. This document does, however, not introduce new
        mechanism and hence the reader is referred to the description of the respective
      mechanism.</t>
    </section>

    <!-- ====================================================================== -->

    <section title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>This document does not require actions by IANA.</t>
    </section>

    <!-- ====================================================================== -->

    <section title="Acknowledgments">
      <t> The authors would like to thank Alan DeKok, Jens-Peter Haack, Jouni Korhonen, Tommy Lindgren, Lars Eggert, for their time to discuss the topic. Additionally, we
        would like to thank Marcin Matuszewski for his help with the P2P infrastructure workshop
        paper (as it was used as a starting point). </t>
    </section>
  </middle>
  <!-- ====================================================================== -->
  <back>
    <references title="Normative References"> &RFC2119; </references>
    <references title="Informative References"> &RFC5594; &RFC2975; &RFC3588;
      &RFC3576; &RFC4006; &RFC2866; &RFC2865;
      &I-D.livingood-woundy-congestion-mgmt; &I-D.irtf-p2prg-mythbustering; <reference
        anchor="traffic">
        <front>
          <title>The impact and implications of the growth in residential user-to-user traffic</title>
          <author initials="K" surname="Cho" fullname="Kenjiro Cho">
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <author initials="K" surname="Fukuda" fullname="Kensuke Fukuda">
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <author initials="H" surname="Kato" fullname="Hiroshi Kato">
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <author initials="A" surname="Kato" fullname="Akira Kato">
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <date year="2006"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="SIGCOMM Comput. Commun. Rev." value="36"/>
        <format type="HTML" target="http://doi.acm.org/10.1145/1151659.1159938"/>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="alto" target="http://www.ietf.org/dyn/wg/charter/alto-charter.html">
        <front>
          <title/>
          <!-- The title's extraneous quote marks in the text ouput will be removed before 
            publication, unless you want to add a title to this reference. -->
          <author>
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <date/>
        </front>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="ledbat" target="http://www.ietf.org/dyn/wg/charter/ledbat-charter.html">
        <front>
          <title/>
          <!-- The title's extraneous quote marks in the text ouput will be removed before 
            publication, unless you want to add a title to this reference. -->
          <author>
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <date/>
        </front>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="p2prg" target="http://www.irtf.org/charter?gtype=rg&group=p2prg">
        <front>
          <title/>
          <!-- The title's extraneous quote marks in the text ouput will be removed before 
            publication, unless you want to add a title to this reference. -->
          <author>
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <date/>
        </front>
      </reference>
    </references>

    <section anchor="policy" title="Example Policy Statement">

      <section title="Fair Usage Policy">

        <section title="What is the Fair Usage Policy?">


          <t>The Fair Usage Policy is designed to ensure that the service received by the vast
            majority of our customers is not negatively impacted because of extremely heavy usage by
            a very small minority of customers. This is why ISP X continuously monitors network
            performance and may restrict the speed available to very heavy users during peak time.
            This applies to customers on all Options. Note if you are a heavy user we will only
            restrict your speed, service will not be stopped so ability to upload and download
            remains. No restrictions will be imposed outside of the peak times. Only a very small
            minority of customers will ever be affected by this (less than 1 %). </t>

        </section>
        <section title="How do I know I'm a very heavy user?">

          <t> There is no hard and fast usage limit that determines if you are a heavy user as the
            parameters that determine heavy use vary with the demands placed on the network at that
            given time. If you have a query about fair usage related restrictions on your line
            please call us. </t>
        </section>


        <section title="I have Contract Option 3, does the Fair Usage Policy
    apply to me?">

          <t> Yes, the Fair Usage Policy applies to all customers on all Options, including Option
            3. Option 3 allows unlimited downloads and uploads inclusive of the monthly rental
            price, so you will not be charged for over-use, however this does not preclude ISP X
            from restricting your speed at peak times if you are a heavy user. If you are an Option
            3 heavy user this does not prevent you from continuing to use your service, nor does it
            cost you any more but it ensures that you do not negatively impact the majority of our
            customers who share the available bandwidth with you. </t>
        </section>

        <section title="Peer to Peer (P2P)">

          <section
            title="I'm noticing slower P2P speeds at peak times even though I'm not a
    very heavy user, why is this?">
            <t> P2P is the sharing and delivery of files amongst groups of people who are logged on
              to a file sharing network. P2P consumes a significant and highly disproportionate
              amount of bandwidth when in use even by small numbers of users. </t>
            <t>This is why we have a peak time policy where we limit P2P speeds to manage the amount
              of bandwidth that is used by this application in particular. </t>
            <t>Without these limits all our customers using their broadband service at peak times
              would suffer, regardless of whether they are using P2P or not. It's important to
              remember that P2P isn't a time-critical application so if you do need to download
              large files we advise you to do this at off-peak times when no restrictions are
              placed, not only will you be able to download faster but your usage will not
              negatively impact other users. </t>
          </section>

          <section title="Does this mean I can't use Peer-to-Peer (P2P) applications?">

            <t> No, we are not stopping you from using any P2P service, P2P will just be slowed down
              at peak times. Again, P2P is not generally a time-sensitive application. </t>
          </section>

        </section>
      </section>

    </section>
  </back>

</rfc>
