<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
	<!ENTITY RFC5031 PUBLIC '' 
	'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5031.xml'>
	<!ENTITY RFC3967 PUBLIC '' 
	'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3967.xml'>
	<!ENTITY RFC2026 PUBLIC '' 
	'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2026.xml'>
	<!ENTITY RFC2865 PUBLIC '' 
	'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2865.xml'>
	<!ENTITY RFC3427 PUBLIC '' 
	'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3427.xml'>
    <!ENTITY I-D.ietf-ecrit-local-emergency-rph-namespace PUBLIC '' 
    'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-ecrit-local-emergency-rph-namespace.xml'>
    <!ENTITY I-D.peterson-rai-rfc3427bis PUBLIC '' 
    'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.peterson-rai-rfc3427bis.xml'>
    <!ENTITY I-D.ietf-behave-turn PUBLIC '' 
    'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-behave-turn.xml'>
    <!ENTITY I-D.ietf-radext-design PUBLIC '' 
    'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-radext-design.xml'>
    <!ENTITY I-D.ietf-geopriv-radius-lo PUBLIC '' 
    'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-geopriv-radius-lo.xml'>
    <!ENTITY I-D.ietf-geopriv-http-location-delivery PUBLIC '' 
    'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-geopriv-http-location-delivery.xml'>
    <!ENTITY I-D.ietf-sip-location-conveyance PUBLIC '' 
    'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-sip-location-conveyance.xml'>
]>
<rfc category="info" ipr="trust200902" docName="draft-tschofenig-rai-reducing-delays-01.txt">
	<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
	<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
	<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
	<?rfc iprnotified="no" ?>
	<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
	<front>
		<title abbrev="Reducing Delays">A Pragmatic Approach for Reducing Delays in Publishing
			Documents within the Real-time Applications and Infrastructure (RAI) Area</title>
		<author initials="H." surname="Tschofenig" fullname="Hannes Tschofenig">
			<organization>Nokia Siemens Networks</organization>
			<address>
				<postal>
					<street>Linnoitustie 6</street>
					<city>Espoo</city>
					<code>02600</code>
					<country>Finland</country>
				</postal>
				<phone>+358 (50) 4871445</phone>
				<email>Hannes.Tschofenig@gmx.net</email>
				<uri>http://www.tschofenig.priv.at</uri>
			</address>
		</author>
		<author initials="H." surname="Schulzrinne" fullname="Henning Schulzrinne">
			<organization>Columbia University</organization>
			<address>
				<postal>
					<street>Department of Computer Science</street>
					<street>450 Computer Science Building</street>
					<city>New York</city>
					<region>NY</region>
					<code>10027</code>
					<country>US</country>
				</postal>
				<phone>+1 212 939 7004</phone>
				<email>hgs+ecrit@cs.columbia.edu</email>
				<uri>http://www.cs.columbia.edu</uri>
			</address>
		</author>
		<author initials="M." surname="Isomaki" fullname="Markus Isomaki">
			<organization>Nokia</organization>
			<address>
				<postal>
					<street>P.O.BOX 100</street>
					<street>00045 NOKIA GROUP</street>
					<city>Helsinki</city>
					<country>Finland</country>
				</postal>
				<phone/>
				<email>markus.isomaki@nokia.com</email>
			</address>
		</author>
		<date year="2009"/>
		<workgroup>rai</workgroup>
		<abstract>
			<t>During the last year, participants in the Real-time Applications and Infrastructure
				(RAI) area have been quite active in discussing proposals that could improve their
				way of working. This document is a contribution to that discussion and focuses on
				the reduction of delays experienced in producing specifications. We believe that
				this is one of the main problems in the RAI area (and quite likely in other areas of
				the IETF as well) and it requires attention. A number of side effects, caused by the
				long specification work, are illustrated in this document. </t>
		</abstract>
	</front>
	<middle>
		<section title="Introduction">
			<t> Many participants in the Real-time Applications and Infrastructure (RAI) area have
				noticed that it takes several years for a specification from the initial working
				group item to the published RFC. A brief look at
				http://www.arkko.com/tools/lifecycle/ (for documents like ICE, SIP Location
				Conveyance, SIP configuration framework) very quickly confirms this observation.
				Several years are quickly spent. In various cases these delays have had negative
				effects on the deployment situation and on interoperability. In some other cases the
				relationship between a long delay and lack of deployment cannot be directly observed
				and there are more complex reasons that can only be analysed on a per-specification
				basis. For example, some of the interoperability problems that got discussed during
				the SIP Interoperability Workshop at IETF#70 (see
				http://www.sipforum.org/component/option,com_docman/task,cat_view/gid,42/Itemid,75)
				may have been caused by specifications with too many options.</t>
			<t>The authors are not aware of a detailed and structured analysis of the documents
				within the RAI area with respect to their delays. With some documents there is the
				question whether additional delay is actually problematic, particularly when they
				have a research character. One could argue that optimizations to the process should
				not be started without a detailed analysis of the main causes for these delays.
				Unfortunately, the delays are the effects of actions taken by individuals and
				blaming them for the problems is not helpful, particularly since the accused persons
				are very likely to disagree.</t>
			<t>Protocol specifications that are not deployed are useless regardless how fast they
				found their way through the IETF. This document, however, does not attempt to
				discuss problems of publishing specifications that do not meet market demands
				(especially since different IETF participants target different market segments, some
				of which might not even closely reflect the properties of the Internet). </t>
			<t>Instead, this document only focuss on delays assuming that the only problem to be
				solved is that specifications are not published in a timely fashion.</t>
		</section>

		<!-- ****************************************************************************************** -->

		<section title="Reasons for Delays">
			<t>The authors believe that the following list provides a fairly complete list of
				reasons for delays in the process of publishing a specification: <list
					style="hanging">
					<t hangText="Interworking between different working groups:"><vspace
							blankLines="1"/>While it may sound fairly unproblematic to work on a
						single specification in different working groups experience has shown the
						opposite. Typically, the problems are related to the lack of understanding
						of the usage scenarios, different schedules and priorities, unclear
						responsibilities, different workstyles in different groups, etc. A similar
						problem can also be observed when special expert groups need to get
						involved, e.g., in the form of XML directorates, reviews of URI schemes,
						application layer design aspects. <vspace blankLines="1"/> Examples that
						support the above statement can be found with RADIUS GEOPRIV <xref
							target="I-D.ietf-geopriv-radius-lo"/> (interaction between GEOPRIV and
						RADEXT), HELD <xref target="I-D.ietf-geopriv-http-location-delivery"/>
						(interaction between GEOPRIV and the APPS area), and SIP Location Conveyance
							<xref target="I-D.ietf-sip-location-conveyance"/> (interaction between
						GEOPRIV and SIP). </t>

					<t hangText="Interworking with other SDOs:"><vspace blankLines="1"/>Similarly to
						the interworking between different IETF working groups one might already
						expect problems in the interworking with other SDOs as the differences might
						quickly increase due to the different set of participants, fairly different
						standardization procedures and deadlines ('yes, in some SDOs deadlines are
						taken serious even though they are completely artificial'), different
						architectural approaches, different business models, different target
						markets (e.g., enterprise networks, cellular networks, military networks)
						different security assumptions. <vspace blankLines="1"/> Examples can be
						found throughout the IETF. In the RAI area the SIP change process (see <xref
							target="RFC3427"/> and the currently discussed revision of it <xref
							target="I-D.peterson-rai-rfc3427bis"/>) build the basis of the
						interworking. Unfortunately, it turned out that in practice problems show up
						with the lack of participation of persons in both organizations. A high
						priority item from, for example, the TISPAN leads to a lot of confusion and
						lack of interest in the IETF RAI area due to the lack of context. There are,
						however, different models in the IETF as well where a lot of the actual
						protocol work is outsourced to the respective organization. An example would
						be the RADEXT working group with their work on RADIUS <xref target="RFC2865"
						/>; a protocol that is being used by a number of SDOs. Although the
						specifications that are sometimes produced outside the IETF do not meet the
						quality expectations in the IETF they do at least not cause resources from
						IETF participants to be wasted when there is little to no interest in that
						specific work. To provide a minimum degree of guidance rules have been
						outlined that should be followed when defining new extensions for RADIUS,
						see <xref target="I-D.ietf-radext-design"/>. </t>

					<t hangText="Disagreement about architectural approaches:"><vspace
							blankLines="1"/> Sometimes document authors have a different
						architectural approach in mind that is incompatible with a large part of the
						working group members. Often, these aspects are discovered fairly late in
						the process particularly when the document lacks a description of the
						assumptions and the security architecture. Often, the problems are related
						to the interworking with other SDOs as the solution approach developed with
						the IETF specification as seen by the authors as a building block that has
						then to be fit into an architecture developed elsewhere (often without
						explicitly stating who else would be doing that work). <vspace
							blankLines="1"/> Examples include the stream of work regarding GETS/MLPP
						(partially done in the IEPREP working group). </t>

					<t hangText="Review marathon:"><vspace blankLines="1"/> Getting a document
						through the IETF process does not happen without reviews. There are reviews
						before the document becomes a WG item, reviews while the document is within
						the group, some chairs demand reviews before they issue a WGLC to probe
						'readiness', someone in between reviews by special expert groups are done
						(also by other SDOs and external groups, if necessary), then comes the WGLC,
						review by the responsible AD, review by the IESG, review by directorates
						(and there are many of those) and (depending on the type of document and
						history) an IETF Last Call. Everybody has an opinion, often not necessarily
						a technical opinion, on how documents should be written and why other
						solution approaches have not been explored. Reviewers need time and then the
						review comments often cannot be ignored but need to be discussed and
						resolved. When reviews happen later in the process then text changes are
						often expected to keep the reviewer happy. IESG members frequently put
						DISCUSSes on reviews and this increases their priority allowing a single
						person to, for example, delay the publication of a document for an extended
						period of time. From a psychological point of view reviewers are in the
						unfortunate position that they have the feeling that something must be
						improved as an outcome of the review activity. As soon as documents leave
						the working group the transparency is largely lost, despite IESG comments
						being sent to the authors, WG chairs and responsible ADs and despite
						information being available in the I-D tracker. Mentally, many working group
						members consider documents to be 'done' when they leave the working group.
							<vspace blankLines="1"/> The authors are not arguing that reviews are
						unnecessary but there has to be balance with respect to the goal that is
						about to be accomplished. </t>

					<t hangText="Degeneration of the 3-level Standards Track process:"><vspace
							blankLines="1"/>RFC 2026 <xref target="RFC2026"/> describes the
						'Internet Standards Process' and describes the level of Standards Track
						documents, namely 'Proposed Standard' to 'Draft Standard' to 'Internet
						Standard'. It appears that IETF participants are less likely to spend their
						time on advancing documents from 'Proposed Standard' to 'Draft Standard',
						particularly since the industry to a large extent does not understand the
						standards process anyway. More and more it can be observed how a fairly
						small group of people get together and produce de-facto standards by
						finishing specifications in an astonishing time frame together with a large
						number of implementations that the Internet community is willing to deploy.
						The standards process utilized in the IETF is, unfortunately, not tailored
						to these type of developments. Experimental documents on the other hand,
						although easier to publish through the IETF, have the stigma of being very
						unbaked. In certain environments the label of 'experimental' is considered
						as a problem. Putting normative references to informational or experimental
						RFCs in Standards Track documents later makes the publication process more
						complex due to the need for Down-Refs <xref target="RFC3967"/>. </t>

					<t hangText="Feature creep and overall complexity:">
						<vspace blankLines="1"/>Setting up a working group takes some time, getting
						working group members to agree that a certain document has to become WG item
						also takes a lot of time, the time it takes to publish it as an RFC takes
						even longer and producing more extensions involves also a certain overhead
						(e.g., re-chartering, new working group/BOF, new milestones, support from
						the working group). It is therefore not surprising that document
						authors/edtiors or the working group are sometimes tempted to add a tiny
						feature here and another small feature there. <vspace blankLines="1"/> A
						further favorite 'passion' is to generalize the solution. In theory this is
						a good idea since the same protocol can then be used in a variety of
						different usage scenarios. In most case, this has lead to more complexity,
						much longer time to finish the specification and sometimes none of the use
						cases are consequently covered appropriately. For some, the SIP
						configuration framework might be an example. </t>

					<t hangText="Lack of time:"><vspace blankLines="1"/> The IETF to a large extend
						consists of volunteers (rather than standardization specialists and
						consultants), who have a fairly limited time budget. Those who are involved
						in the development of standards tend to have time constraints (e.g.,
						authors, WG participants, WG chairs, ADs, Expert Reviewers, etc.). This is
						quite normal. <vspace blankLines="1"/> Problems arise when the lack of time
						causes considerable delays in completing work other people rely on. Consider
						the following hypothetical case. Bob is an expert in writing specifications
						and he has a lot of energy and enthusiasm. He is assigned as the main editor
						of a specification. The work on the specification takes some time (typically
						years) but Bob does his job well and the community respects him. Over time
						Bob develops new interests, might even change his job and does not show the
						same availability anymore. Still, Bob remains in charge of the document and
						Bob does not recognize that he is unable to commit the necessary time to get
						the job done. A similar situation can happen in any other role previously
						mentioned. </t>

					<t hangText="Missing running code:"><vspace blankLines="1"/> Although most
						people would agree that running code is very useful many specifications are
						not backed up with it. Since specifications change a lot over the lifetime
						before being published as an RFC (even at a very late stage) it can be
						pretty frustrating to have running code in an early stage. The standards
						process considers interoperable code but due to the long time it takes to
						publish specifications it is rarely utilized. <vspace blankLines="1"/> As an
						example, the TURN specification <xref target="I-D.ietf-behave-turn"/> has
						changed quite considerably over time. Those who implemented earlier versions
						essentially had to re-write their code.</t>

					<t hangText="Onerous extensibility rules:"><vspace blankLines="1"/> Many
						document authors feel insecure when writing IANA consideration sections and
						for some reasons these consideration sections often demand Standards Track
						documents to introduce new extensions. <vspace blankLines="1"/> A recent
						example can be found with the Service URN document <xref target="RFC5031"/>,
						which requires a Standards Track document for allocating a new top-level
						top-level service labels. With the new extensions that the working group had
						seen it became cumbersome to progress these documents in a timely fashion
						through the working group. </t>

					<t hangText="AD and IESG overload:"><vspace blankLines="1"/> Some documents need
						significant time after leaving the working group until they are published.
						It is unclear that these delays yield significantly better documents in the
						end. Part of the problem is that the current IETF area director model seems
						to assume that ADs spend the equivalent of a full-time job on their
						"volunteer" job, which appears to be unrealistic, particularly when ADs have
						been in office for several years. Compared to other organizations, the AD
						"span of control" is very large, supervising twenty or more working group
						chairs.</t>

					<t hangText="Exhaustion:"><vspace blankLines="1"/>As the publication process
						wears on, the amount of change per time unit continuously decreases. Because
						of the long delays, authors are often working on many documents in parallel,
						making it difficult for them to switch context and remember all the issues
						when they update documents. As the initial excitement about a problem fades
						after a few years, editing such documents becomes a chore, further delaying
						the publication. This leads to author exhaustion. <vspace blankLines="1"
						/>Thus, to the extent possible, most documents should be finished in no more
						than three IETF meetings: gauge interest and agreement on basic approach
						during the first IETF meeting and assign reviewers, reach consensus on the
						technical issues during the second IETF meeting and get a final WG approval
						during the third one, if needed. </t>
				</list>
			</t>
		</section>

		<section title="Suggestions">
			<t> Below, we present a set of suggestions to reduce publication delays. We believe that
				many of the suggestions can be used together, and some can be used experimentally to
				see if they produce significant improvements. <list style="hanging">

					<t hangText="Improving the chartering process:"><vspace blankLines="1"/> It
						takes far too long to add an item to a charter. If there's interest in the
						working group and the document is below a certain size and complexity (based
						on the judgement by the WG chair) and three reviewer volunteers, the
						document should just get into the next cycle. </t>

					<t hangText="State assumptions clearly:"><vspace blankLines="1"/> Sometimes a
						specific protocol specification is target for usage in a certain environment
						(or envisioned context). The working group may be fine with such an approach
						but often the document does not state the usage environment. This often
						leads to confusion in the review process. For example, some documents are
						being progressed through the IETF where the main use case can be found in
						the 3GPP IMS architecture. Maybe the document assumes that other
						organizations utilize the specification in a specific context. There are
						often additional operational aspects that need to be considered in order to
						come to a complete solution. <vspace blankLines="1"/> A recent example can
						be found in the work on <xref
							target="I-D.ietf-ecrit-local-emergency-rph-namespace"/> where the
						document essentially only specifies the syntax but the semantic is supposed
						to be provided by organizations outside the IETF. </t>

					<t hangText="Delegate down:"><vspace blankLines="1"/> In most organizations,
						middle management is given significant decision authority, usually described
						by the financial impact of a decision. A CEO of company does not approve
						every contract, user manual or feature list. The current IETF review model
						is predicated on the notion that the IESG reviews protocols to ensure that
						they do not damage the Internet. However, most of the current RAI documents
						are extensions and bug fixes that are likely to have only local effects.
							<vspace blankLines="1"/> To reduce AD and IESG load, working group
						chairs should be able to handle most documents until they reach the RFC
						editor, unless there is an objection during IETF last call. IESG members are
						expected to voice their objection during that last call period, triggering
						formal IESG review. Only efforts that introduce new protocols or are likely
						to have significant Internet-wide impact require more extensive review.
							<vspace blankLines="1"/> When a document is added to the WG work list,
						it should be flagged to indicate that it will require a full review. All
						other documents receive a lighter late-stage review. </t>

					<t hangText="Clearly label IETF discussion slots:"><vspace blankLines="1"/>Given
						the three-meeting model mentioned earlier, the IETF meeting presentations
						should be structured accordingly, with a clear set of questions to be
						answered. For example, the first presentation needs to answer questions
						about architectural assumptions, relation to other work, dependencies,
						importance of the problem and alternative approaches. Working group chairs
						should work with document authors to structure presentations, possibly
						providing templates. In this model, the second discussion is crucial and
						should be given ample time, if necessary enhancing the plenary working group
						meeting with break-out meetings before and after the WG meeting slot. (It is
						a waste of time to have 200 people listen to a discussion where only a
						handful can really make significant contributions.) </t>

					<t hangText="Journal-like review model:">
						<vspace blankLines="1"/> When a new document is submitted to the working
						group, the working group chair determines at latest at the next IETF meeting
						whether there is sufficient interest to pursue this work. If so, he or she
						seeks at least three reviewers from the working group. If such reviewers
						cannot be found, the document lacks sufficient interest. Authors may suggest
						qualified reviewers. Reviewers are given a two-month review deadline, so
						that reviews would typically arrive mid-cycle between IETF meetings. The
						basic process could follow the GenArt review model, which could proceed in
						parallel. As needed, a specialized reviewer might be assigned to only look
						at specific issues, such as XML usage, security aspects or congestion
						control. <vspace blankLines="1"/> The reviews should be tracked in an issue
						tracker, in addition to being disseminated via the working group mailing
						list. As a short-term measure until the IETF tools are enhanced, existing
						conference review tools might be used, as they offer definable review forms
						(e.g., to separate editorial and technical issues) and automated review
						reminder mechanisms. <vspace blankLines="1"/> This approach closely models
						the review process used by scientific journals and technical conferences. </t>

					<t hangText="Increasing implementation feedback:"><vspace blankLines="1"/> When
						documents are able to progress faster through the IETF participants should
						feel encouraged to provide an update that includes bug fixes and other
						corrections based on implementation efforts. A possible approach to
						accomplish this today is to publish documents as informational and
						experimental RFCs (faster) and to advance them to Standars Track once
						implementation (or even deployment) experience is available. </t>

					<t hangText="Delegate work to other SDOs:">
						<vspace blankLines="1"/>We believe that the updated version of the SIP
						Change Process <xref target="I-D.peterson-rai-rfc3427bis"/> goes into the
						right direction already. </t>

					<t hangText="Additional WG chair training:"><vspace blankLines="1"/> We suggest
						to use some of the WG chair training lunches to offer room for discussions
						on how to avoid delays in progressing documents and to collect the best
						current practises. </t>

					<t hangText="Virtual interim meetings:"><vspace blankLines="1"/>Many document
						authors do their IETF work in the two-week period around the submission
						deadlines before an IETF meeting. This leads to fairly low document update
						cycles. A tool to increase the time that is spent on documents per IETF
						cycle working style is to hold virtual interim meetings (i.e., phone
						conferences). This is common practice also in other organizations and helps
						to stay focused on open issues. Sometimes chairs regularly contact the main
						document authors to discuss the editing progress and the status of open
						issues. It is useful to allow working group members to participate and
						distribute notes about this informal communication. </t>

					<t hangText="Keep track of the WG status:"><vspace blankLines="1"/> Sometimes no
						progress is made because there is uncertainty about who is responsible for
						taking the next step. Periodic reminders (even with tool support) would help
						to make the workflow more visible. Examples of these periodic status updates
						can be found here
						http://www.ietf.org/mail-archive/web/ecrit/current/msg05785.html,
						http://www.ietf.org/mail-archive/web/ops-area/current/msg00467.html and
						http://www.ietf.org/mail-archive/web/saag/current/msg02242.html. </t>

					<t hangText="Document status updates:"><vspace blankLines="1"/> Each document
						must have an dedicated editor. This person is responsible for making sure
						that the status of the document is known. Ensuring a regular interval for
						reporting is helpful, such as once a month. The fact that such a short
						report (a few lines in most cases) is written already reminds the editor to
						look at open issues, which often helps to make progress. <vspace
							blankLines="1"/> Too often, document editors erroneously believe that it
						is the responsibility of the working group to drive the process and the lack
						of feedback is an indication that the document is ready. </t>
					<t hangText="Keep your ADs informed:"><vspace blankLines="1"/> As previously
						argued it is important to keep the working group informed about the current
						status. In the same style it is important to let the ADs know what the
						current status of the work is. Regular phone conference calls, e.g. once a
						month, are a possible approach. </t>

					<t hangText="Assign new editors:"><vspace blankLines="1"/> If the original
						author clearly cannot complete the work in a timely fashion, the working
						group chair should routinely re-assign an editor to the document, after,
						say, a one-year delay since the -00 draft. If no other person is capable to
						take that role, this indicates that the document is either too long, too
						complicated or of insufficient interest to merit further consideration as-is
						and needs to be split up, simplified or abandoned.</t>

					<t hangText="Enhance I-D tracker:"><vspace blankLines="1"/> The I-D tracker
						should indicate who is supposed to be reviewing the document and by what
						deadline. It should also clearly indicate who has the "token" on the
						document, i.e, whether the next action is expected to come from the working
						group chair, a reviewer or set of reviewers, a directorate, or the authors. </t>

					<t hangText="Posting minutes:"><vspace blankLines="1"/>The working group
						chair(s) must publish the meeting minutes (of a face-to-face or virtual
						interim meeting) within a few days after the meeting. This helps to ensure
						that action items can be captured by the participants. Too often details are
						lost with longer delays and the benefit of the meeting may get lost. </t>

					<t hangText="Prepare meeting slides appropriately:"><vspace blankLines="1"
						/>Slides are a common way to present open issues and to provide a status
						update during (virtual) interm and face-to-face meetings. Often the slides
						are available to working group chairs a few minutes before the meeting
						starts. Furthermore, the style of slides often does not serve as a suitable
						form to discuss the content. Since small time slots are allocated there is
						no time to get many of the participants up-to-speed with the discussed issue
						leaving a large number of the participants clueless. Although it is the seen
						as the responsibility of the participant to read into the subject it is also
						questionable whether a presentation with only a handfull of persons
						understanding the issue is really helpful. Instead, the document editor and
						the document authors should consider using alternative means of preparing
						the content in a suitable format to ensure that a large number of persons
						are actually able to provide a feedback. An example, for such an approach
						can be found with blog posts
						http://www.hueniverse.com/hueniverse/2009/04/explaining-the-oauth-session-fixation-attack.html
						or http://www.hueniverse.com/hueniverse/2008/10/beginners-gui-1.html.
							<vspace blankLines="1"/> The IETF meetings are about discussion and
						discussions need to be prepared. Not everybody is able to have get a
						definitive opinion while listening to a 5-10 minute (particularly when the
						topic is complex). Consider that not everyone is given with the gift to give
						presentations that are easy to understand (considering also the language
						barrier). Consequently, if the audience is not prepared then there is no
						discussion. Trying to close open issues will be difficult.</t>

					<t hangText="Stay connected:">
						<vspace blankLines="1"/> Exchanging information about ongoing activies and
						challenges in a timely fashion it is vital to have other persons contact
						information (e.g. IM nicknames, various phone numbers, etc.). An email
						conversation is often not timely enough. A working group chair, for example,
						should at least have the contact details of the ADs responsible for the
						working group, the document authors and the key working group members.</t>
				</list>
			</t>
		</section>

		<section title="Security Considerations">
			<t>This document discusses process related aspects that are not directly related to
				security. However, the outcome of an improved process might have a positive impact
				on security provided by the deployed specifications.</t>
		</section>
		<section title="Acknowledgements">
			<t>We would like to thank all of those you care about the process related aspects in the
				IETF as they contribute to the impact of the work produced by the IETF in the
				future. We would also like to thank everyone participating on the RAI area mailing
				list for their input during the RAI reorganization discussions.</t>
			<t>We would particularly like to thank Benoit Claise for his feedback to the
			document.</t>
		</section>

		<!-- ****************************************************************************************** -->

	</middle>
	<back>
		<!-- 		<references title="Normative References"> </references> -->
		<references title="Informative References">
			&I-D.ietf-ecrit-local-emergency-rph-namespace; &I-D.peterson-rai-rfc3427bis;
			&RFC5031; &I-D.ietf-behave-turn; &RFC3967; &RFC2026; &RFC2865;
			&I-D.ietf-radext-design; &I-D.ietf-geopriv-radius-lo;
			&I-D.ietf-geopriv-http-location-delivery; &I-D.ietf-sip-location-conveyance;
			&RFC3427; </references>

	</back>

</rfc>
