<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!-- This is built from a template for a generic Internet Draft. Suggestions for
     improvement welcome - write to Brian Carpenter, brian.e.carpenter @ gmail.com -->

<!-- This can be converted using the Web service at http://xml.resource.org/experimental.html
     (which supports the latest, sometimes undocumented and under-tested, features.) -->

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [

<!-- You need one entry like the following for each RFC referenced -->

<!ENTITY RFC2119 PUBLIC ''
  'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml'>
<!ENTITY RFC2629 PUBLIC ''
  'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2629.xml'>
<!ENTITY RFC2460 PUBLIC ''
  'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2460.xml'>
<!ENTITY RFC6437 PUBLIC ''
  'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6437.xml'>
<!ENTITY RFC6438 PUBLIC ''
  'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6438.xml'>
<!ENTITY RFC6434 PUBLIC ''
  'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6434.xml'>
<!ENTITY RFC6296 PUBLIC ''
  'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6296.xml'>
<!ENTITY RFC4864 PUBLIC ''
  'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4864.xml'>
<!ENTITY RFC2991 PUBLIC ''
  'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2991.xml'>
<!ENTITY RFC6436 PUBLIC ''
  'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6436.xml'>
<!ENTITY RFC6294 PUBLIC ''
  'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6294.xml'>


<!-- You need one entry like the following for each I-D referenced -->


<!ENTITY DRAFT-ecmp SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-6man-flow-ecmp.xml"> 

]>


<?rfc toc="yes"?>            <!-- You want a table of contents -->
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>        <!-- Use symbolic labels for references -->
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>       <!-- This sorts the references -->
<?rfc iprnotified="no" ?>    <!-- Change to "yes" if someone has disclosed IPR for the draft -->
<?rfc compact="yes"?>


<!-- This defines the specific filename and version number of your draft (and inserts the appropriate IETF boilerplate -->
<rfc ipr="trust200902" docName="draft-ietf-intarea-flow-label-balancing-00" category="info" >


<front>
<title abbrev="Flow Label Load Balancers">Using the IPv6 Flow Label for Server Load Balancing</title>


<author initials="B. E." surname="Carpenter" fullname="Brian Carpenter">
    <organization abbrev="Univ. of Auckland"></organization>
    <address>
      <postal>
        <street>Department of Computer Science</street>
        <street>University of Auckland</street>
        <street>PB 92019</street>
        <city>Auckland</city>
        <region></region>
        <code>1142</code>
        <country>New Zealand</country>
      </postal>
      
      <email>brian.e.carpenter@gmail.com</email>
    </address>
</author>




   <author fullname="Sheng Jiang" initials="S." surname="Jiang">
      <organization>Huawei Technologies Co., Ltd</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Q14, Huawei Campus</street>
          <street>No.156 Beiqing Road</street>
          <city>Hai-Dian District, Beijing</city>
          <code>100095</code>
          <country>P.R. China</country>
        </postal>
        <email>jiangsheng@huawei.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

   <author fullname="Willy Tarreau" initials="W." surname="Tarreau">
      <organization>Exceliance</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>R&amp;D Produits reseau</street>
          <street>3 rue du petit Robinson</street>
          <city>78350 Jouy-en-Josas</city>
          <country>France</country>
        </postal>
        <email>w@1wt.eu</email>
      </address>
    </author>

 


 <date day="15" month="January" year="2013" />

<area>Internet</area>
<workgroup>IntArea</workgroup>

 


<abstract>

<t>This document describes how the IPv6 flow label as currently specified can be used to enhance layer 3/4 load distribution and balancing for large server farms. 
</t>
    
</abstract>
</front>

<middle>
<section anchor="intro" title="Introduction">

<t>The IPv6 flow label has been redefined <xref target="RFC6437"/> and is
now a recommended IPv6 node requirement <xref target="RFC6434"/>.
Its use for load sharing in multipath routing has been specified <xref target="RFC6438"/>. 
Another scenario in which the flow label could be used is in load distribution for large
server farms. Load distribution is a slightly more general term than load balancing,
but the latter is more commonly used. This document starts with brief introductions
to the flow label and to load balancing techniques, and then describes how the flow label
can be used to enhance layer 3/4 load balancers in particular. </t>

<t>The motivation for this approach is to improve the performance of most types of
layer 3/4 load balancers, especially for traffic including multiple IPv6 extension
headers and in particular for fragmented packets. Fragmented packets, often the
result of customers reaching the load balancer via a VPN with a limited MTU,
are a common performance problem. </t>

</section> <!-- intro -->

<section anchor="flowl" title="Summary of Flow Label Specification">

<t>The IPv6 flow label is a 20 bit field included in every IPv6 header <xref target="RFC2460"/>.
It is recommended to be supported in all IPv6 nodes by <xref target="RFC6434"/> and it is
defined in <xref target="RFC6437"/>. 
There is additional background material in <xref target="RFC6436"/> and <xref target="RFC6294"/>.
According to its definition, the flow label should be
set to a constant value for a given traffic flow (such as an HTTP connection), and that
value will belong to a uniform statistical distribution, making it potentially valuable
for load balancing purposes. </t>

<t>Any device that has access
to the IPv6 header has access to the flow label, and it is at a fixed position
in every IPv6 packet. In contrast, transport layer information, such as
the port numbers, is not always in a fixed position, since it follows
any IPv6 extension headers that may be present. In fact, the logic of finding
the transport header is always more complex for IPv6 than for IPv4,
due to the absence of an Internet Header Length field in IPv6. Additionally, if packets
are fragmented, the flow label will be present in all fragments, but the transport header
will only be in one packet. Therefore, within the
lifetime of a given transport layer connection, the flow label can be
a more convenient "handle" than the port number for identifying that
particular connection. </t>

<t>According to RFC 6437, source hosts
should set the flow label, but, if they do not (i.e. its value is zero),
forwarding nodes (such as the first-hop router) may set it instead. In both cases,
the flow label value must be constant for a given transport session, normally identified
by the IPv6 and Transport header 5-tuple. By default, the flow label value should be calculated
by a stateless algorithm. The resulting value should form part of a statistically
uniform distribution, regardless of which node sets it.  </t>

<t>It is recognised that at the time of writing, very few traffic flows include
a non-zero flow label value. The mechanism described below is one that can be added to
existing load balancing mechanisms, so that it will become effective as more
and more flows contain a non-zero label. If the flow label is in fact set to zero,
it will not affect the information entropy of the IPv6 header. Even if the flow label
is chosen from an imperfectly uniform distribution, it will nevertheless increase the header entropy.
These facts allow for progressive introduction of load balancing based on the flow label. </t>

<t>A careful reading of RFC 6437 shows that for a given source accessing
a well-known TCP port at a given destination, the flow label is, in effect, a substitute for
the source port number, found at a fixed position in the layer 3 header. </t>

<t>The flow label is defined as an end-to-end component of the IPv6 header, but
there are three qualifications to this:</t>

<t><list style="numbers">
<t>Until the RFC 6437 standard is widely implemented as recommended by RFC 6434, the flow label will often be
set to the default value of zero. </t>

<t>Because of the recommendation to use a stateless algorithm to calculate
the label, there is a low (but non-zero) probability that two
simultaneous flows from the same source to the same destination have the
same flow label value despite having different transport protocol port numbers. </t>

<t>The flow label field is in an unprotected part of the IPv6 header, which means
that intentional or unintentional changes to its value cannot be easily detected by
a receiver. </t>
</list></t>

<t>The first two points are addressed below in <xref target="role"/> and the third in
<xref target="security"/>. </t> 




</section> <!-- flowl -->

<section anchor="lbsumm" title="Summary of Load Balancing Techniques">

<t>Load balancing for server farms is achieved by a variety of methods, often used in combination
<xref target="Tarreau"/>. The flow
label is not relevant to all of them, and the actual load balancing algorithm (the choice of which
server to use for a new client session) is irrelevant to this discussion. </t>
<t><list style="symbols">
 <t>The simplest method is simply using the DNS to return different server
 addresses for a single name such as www.example.com to different users. This is typically done by rotating
 the order in which different addresses are listed by the relevant authoritative DNS server,
 on the assumption that
 the client will pick the first one. Routing may be configured such that the different
 addresses are handled by different ingress routers. The flow label can have no impact
 on this method and it is not discussed further. </t>

 <t>Another method, for HTTP servers, is to operate a layer 7 reverse proxy in front of the server farm. The reverse
 proxy will present a single IP address to the world, communicated to clients by a single AAAA record. For each
 new client session (an incoming TCP connection and HTTP request), it will pick a particular server and proxy
 the session to it. The act of proxying should be more efficient and less resource-intensive
 than the act of serving the required content.
 The proxy must retain TCP state and proxy state for the duration of the session. This TCP state
 could, potentially, include the incoming flow label value. </t>

 <t>A component of some load balancing systems is an SSL reverse proxy farm. The individual SSL proxies 
 handle all cryptographic aspects and exchange raw HTTP with the actual servers. Thus, from the load
 balancing point of view, this really looks just like a server farm, except that it's specialised for HTTPS.
 Each proxy will retain SSL and TCP and maybe HTTP state for the duration of the session, and the TCP
 state could potentially include the flow label. </t>

 <t>Finally the "front end" of many load balancing systems is a layer 3/4 load balancer. While it can
 be a dedicated device, it is also a standard function of some network switches
 or routers (e.g. using ECMP, <xref target="RFC2991"/>). In this case, it is the layer 3/4 load balancer
 whose IP address is published
 as the primary AAAA record for the service. All client sessions will pass through this device.
 According to the specific scenario, it will spread new sessions across the actual application
 servers, across an SSL proxy farm, or across a set of layer 7 proxies. In all cases, the
 layer 3/4 load balancer has to recognize incoming packets as belonging to new or existing
 client sessions, and choose the target server or proxy so as to ensure persistence.
 'Persistence' is defined as guaranteeing that a given session will run to completion on
 a single server. The layer 3/4 load balancer therefore needs to inspect each incoming packet
 to identify the session. There are two common types of layer 3/4 load balancers, the totally
 stateless ones which only act on packets, generally involving a per-packet hashing of
 easy-to-find information such as the source address and/or port into a server number, and
 the stateful ones which take the routing decision on the very first packets of a session
 and maintain the same direction for all packets belonging to the same session. Clearly,
 both types of layer 3/4 balancers could inspect and make use of the flow label value. 
 <vspace blankLines="1"/>
 Our focus is on how the balancer identifies a particular flow. For clarity, note that two aspects
 of layer 3/4 load balancers could not be affected by use of the flow label to identify sessions:
 <vspace blankLines="1"/>
 <list style="numbers">
   <t>Balancers use various techniques to redirect traffic to a specific target server. 
   <vspace blankLines="1"/>
   - All servers are configured with the same IP address, they are all on the same LAN, and the load balancer
   sends directly to their individual MAC addresses.
   <vspace/>
   - Each server has its own IP address, and the balancer uses an IP-in-IP tunnel to reach it.
   <vspace/>
   - Each server has its own IP address, and the balancer performs NAPT (network address and port translation)
     to deliver the client's packets to that address.
   <vspace blankLines="1"/>
   The choice between these methods is not affected by use of the flow label. <vspace blankLines="1"/></t>
   
   <t>A layer 3/4 balancer must correctly handle Path MTU Discovery by forwarding
   relevant ICMPv6 packets in both directions. This too is not affected by use of the flow label. </t>
 </list> 
 </t>
</list></t>



<t>The following diagram, inspired by <xref target="Tarreau"/>, shows a maximum layout. </t>

<figure><artwork>
     ___________________________________________
    (                                           )
    (          Clients in the Internet          )
    (___________________________________________)
           |                            |
      ------------                ------------
      | Ingress  |                | Ingress  |
      | router   |                | router   |
      ------------                ------------
        ___|_______DNS-based____________|___
             |     load splitting     |
             |                        |
             |                        |
        ------------             ------------
        | L3/4 ASIC|             | L3/4 ASIC|
        | balancer |             | balancer |
        ------------             ------------
             |          load          |     
             |        spreading       |     
   __________|________________________|___________
       |              |            |          |
 ------------   ------------   --------   --------
 |HTTP proxy|...|HTTP proxy|   | SSL  |...| SSL  |
 | balancer |   | balancer |   | proxy|   | proxy|
 ------------   ------------   --------   --------
   ____|_____________|_____________|_________|_____ 
     |          |          |          |          |
 --------   --------   --------   --------   --------
 |HTTP  |   |HTTP  |   |HTTP  |   |HTTP  |   |HTTP  |
 |server|   |server|   |server|   |server|   |server|
 --------   --------   --------   --------   --------
 </artwork> </figure>               

<t>From the previous paragraphs, we can identify several points
in this diagram where the flow label might be relevant:</t>
<t><list style="numbers">
 <t>Layer 3/4 load balancers.</t>
 <t>SSL proxies.</t>
 <t>HTTP proxies.</t>
</list></t>
<t>However, usage by the proxies seems unlikely to be cost-effective, so in this
document we focus only on layer 3/4 balancers. </t>
</section> <!-- lbsumm -->

<section anchor="role" title="Applying the Flow Label to L3/L4 Load Balancing">


<t>
The suggested model for using the flow label in a load balancing mechanism
is as follows: </t>
<t><list style="symbols">
 <t>We are only concerned with IPv6 traffic in which the flow label value has been set
    at or near the source according to <xref target="RFC6437"/>.
    If the flow label of an incoming packet is zero, load balancers will continue to 
    use the transport header in the traditional way. As the use of the flow label becomes
    more prevalent according to RFC 6434,
    load balancers, and therefore users, will reap a growing performance benefit. </t>

 <t>If the flow label of an incoming packet is non-zero, layer 3/4 load balancers can
    use the 2-tuple {source address, flow label}
    as the session key for whatever load distribution algorithm they support.
    If any IPv6 extension headers, including fragment headers, are present, this
    will be significantly quicker than
    searching for the transport port numbers later in the packet.
    Moreover, the transport layer information such as the source port
    is not repeated in fragments, which generally prevents stateless
    load balancers from supporting fragmented traffic since they
    generally cannot reassemble fragments.
    <vspace blankLines="1"/>
    A stateless layer 3/4 load balancer would simply apply a hash algorithm to the
    2-tuple {source address, flow label} on all packets, in order to select the same
    target server consistently for a given flow.
    <vspace blankLines="1"/>
    A stateful layer 3/4 load balancer
    would apply its usual load distribution algorithm to the first packet of a session,
    and store the {2-tuple, server} association in a table so that subsequent packets belonging
    to the same session are forwarded to the same server. Thus, for all subsequent
    packets of the session, it can ignore all IPv6 extension headers, which should
    lead to a performance benefit. Whether this benefit is valuable will depend on
    engineering details of the specific load balancer. 
    <vspace blankLines="1"/>
    Layer 3/4 balancers that redirect
    the incoming packets by NAPT are not expected to obtain any saving of time by using the flow label,
    because they have no choice but to follow the extension header chain, in order to locate
    and modify the port number and transport checksum. The same would apply to
    balancers that perform TCP state tracking for any reason.
    </t>
 <t>Note that correct handling of ICMPv6 for Path MTU Discovery requires the layer 3/4 balancer
    to keep state for the client source address, independently of either the port
    numbers or the flow label. </t>
 <t>SSL and HTTP proxies, if present, should forward the flow
    label value towards the server. This has no performance benefit, but
    is consistent with the general RFC 6437 model for the flow label. </t>
</list></t>

<t>It should be noted that the performance benefit, if any, depends entirely on
engineering trade-offs in the design of the L3/L4 balancer. An extra test is needed
(is the label non-zero?), but all logic for handling extension headers can be omitted
except for the first packet of a new flow. Since the
only state to be stored is the 2-tuple and the server identifier, storage
requirements will be reduced. Additionally, the method will work for
fragmented traffic and for flows where the transport information
is missing (unknown transport protocol) or obfuscated (e.g., IPsec). 
Traffic reaching the load balancer via a VPN is particularly prone
to the fragmentation issue, due to MTU size issues.
For some load balancer designs, these are very significant advantages. </t>

<t>In the unlikely event of two simultaneous flows from the same
source address having the same flow label value, the two flows would end up assigned
to the same server, where they would be distinguished as normal by their
port numbers. Since this would be a statistically rare event, it would
not damage the overall load balancing effect. Moreover, it is very likely
that there will be many more flow label values than servers at
most sites (1 million possible label values), so it is already expected that
multiple flow label values will end up on the same server for a given
IP address. </t>

<t>In the case that many thousands of clients are hidden behind the same large-scale
NAPT (network address and port translator) with a single shared IP address, the assumption
of low probability of conflicts might become incorrect, unless flow label values are random
enough to avoid following similar sequences for all clients. This is not expected to
be a factor for IPv6 anyway, since there is no need to implement large-scale
NAPT with address sharing <xref target="RFC4864"/>. The statistical assumption is valid
for sites that implement network prefix translation <xref target="RFC6296"/>, since this
technique provides a different address for each client. </t>

</section> <!-- role -->



<section anchor="security" title="Security Considerations">

<t>Security aspects of the flow label are discussed in <xref target="RFC6437"/>.
As noted there, a malicious source or man-in-the-middle could disturb load balancing
by manipulating flow labels. This risk already exists today where the source address
and port are used as hashing key in layer 3/4 load balancers, as well as where a
persistence cookie is used in HTTP to designate a server. It even exists on layer
3 components which only rely on the source address to select a destination, making
them more DDoS-prone. Nevertheless, all these methods are currently used because the benefits
for load balancing and persistence hugely outweigh the risks. The flow label does
not significantly alter this situation. </t>

<t>Specifically, the specification <xref target="RFC6437"/> states that "stateless classifiers
should not use the flow label alone to control load distribution, and stateful classifiers should include
explicit methods to detect and ignore suspect flow label values." The former point is answered
by also using the source address. The latter point is more complex. If the risk is considered
serious, the site ingress router or the layer 3/4 balancer should use a suitable heuristic to verify incoming
flows with non-zero flow label values. If a flow from a given source address and port number does not have a constant
flow label value, it is suspect and should be dropped. This would deal with both intentional and
accidental changes to the flow label. </t>

<t>RFC 6437 notes in its Security Considerations that if the covert channel risk is considered
   significant, a firewall might rewrite non-zero flow labels. As long as this is done as
   described in RFC 6437, it will not invalidate the mechanisms described above. </t>

<t>The flow label may be of use in protecting against distributed denial of service (DDOS) attacks
against servers. As noted in RFC 6437, a source should generate flow label values that are
hard to predict, most likely by including a secret nonce in the hash used to generate
each label. The attacker does not know the nonce and therefore has no way to invent
flow labels which will all target the same server, even with knowledge of both the hash
algorithm and the load balancing algorithm. Still, it is important to understand that it
is always trivial to force a load balancer to stick to the same server during an attack,
so the security of the whole solution must not rely on the unpredicatability of the flow
label values alone, but should include defensive measures like most load balancers already
have against abnormal use of source address or session cookies.</t>

<t>New flows are assigned to a server according to any of the usual algorithms available on
the load balancer (e.g., least connections, round robin, etc.). The association between the
flow label value and the server is stored in a table (often called stick table) so that future
connections using the same flow label can be sent to the same server. This method is more robust
against a loss of server and also makes it harder for an attacker to target a specific server,
because the association between a flow label value and a server is not known externally.</t>

 
</section> <!-- security -->


<section anchor="iana" title="IANA Considerations">
   <t>This document requests no action by IANA. </t>
</section> <!-- iana -->




<section anchor="ack" title="Acknowledgements">

<t>
Valuable comments and contributions were made by
Fred Baker,
Lorenzo Colitti,
Joel Jaeggli,
Gurudeep Kamat,
Warren Kumari,
Julia Renouard,
Julius Volz,
and others.
 </t>

<t>This document was produced using the xml2rfc tool
<xref target="RFC2629"/>.</t>

</section> <!-- ack -->


<section anchor ="changes" title="Change log [RFC Editor: Please remove]">

<t>draft-ietf-intarea-flow-label-balancing-00: WG adoption, minor WG comments, 2013-01-15.</t>
<t>draft-carpenter-flow-label-balancing-02: updates based on external review, 2012-12-05.</t>
<t>draft-carpenter-flow-label-balancing-01: update following comments, 2012-06-12.</t>
<t>draft-carpenter-flow-label-balancing-00: restructured after IETF83, 2012-05-08.</t>
<t>draft-carpenter-v6ops-label-balance-02: clarified after WG discussions, 2012-03-06.</t>
<t>draft-carpenter-v6ops-label-balance-01: updated with community comments, additional author, 2012-01-17.</t>
<t>draft-carpenter-v6ops-label-balance-00: original version, 2011-10-13.</t>


</section> <!-- changes -->

</middle>

<back>

<references title="Normative References">

&RFC2460;
&RFC6434;
&RFC6437;


</references>

<references title="Informative References">

&RFC2629;
&RFC6438;
&RFC6296;
&RFC4864;
&RFC2991;
&RFC6436;
&RFC6294;

<reference anchor="Tarreau" target="http://1wt.eu/articles/2006_lb/">
<front>
<title>Making applications scalable with load balancing</title>
<author initials="W. " surname="Tarreau" fullname="Willy Tarreau"/> 
<date year="2006"/>
</front>
</reference>
  
</references>




</back>
</rfc>

