<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!-- This template is for creating an Internet Draft using xml2rfc,
     which is available here: http://xml.resource.org. -->
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!-- One method to get references from the online citation libraries.
     There has to be one entity for each item to be referenced. 
     An alternate method (rfc include) is described in the references. -->

<!ENTITY RFC2974 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2974.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3376 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3376.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3810 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3810.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4601 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4601.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6052 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6052.xml">
]>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<!-- used by XSLT processors -->
<!-- For a complete list and description of processing instructions (PIs), 
     please see http://xml.resource.org/authoring/README.html. -->
<!-- Below are generally applicable Processing Instructions (PIs) that most I-Ds might want to use.
     (Here they are set differently than their defaults in xml2rfc v1.32) -->
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<!-- give errors regarding ID-nits and DTD validation -->
<!-- control the table of contents (ToC) -->
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<!-- generate a ToC -->
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<!-- the number of levels of subsections in ToC. default: 3 -->
<!-- control references -->
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<!-- use symbolic references tags, i.e, [RFC2119] instead of [1] -->
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<!-- sort the reference entries alphabetically -->
<!-- control vertical white space 
     (using these PIs as follows is recommended by the RFC Editor) -->
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<!-- do not start each main section on a new page -->
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<!-- keep one blank line between list items -->
<!-- end of list of popular I-D processing instructions -->

<rfc category="info" docName="draft-eubanks-mboned-transition-overview-03" ipr="trust200902">
  <!-- category values: std, bcp, info, exp, and historic
     ipr values: trust200902, noModificationTrust200902, noDerivativesTrust200902
     pre5378Trust200902
     you can add the attributes updates="NNNN" and obsoletes="NNNN" 
     they will automatically be output with "(if approved)" -->

  <!-- ***** FRONT MATTER ***** -->

  <front>
    <!-- The abbreviated title is used in the page header - it is only necessary if the 
         full title is longer than 39 characters -->

    <title>Multicast Transition Overview</title>

    <!-- add 'role="editor"' below for the editors if appropriate -->

    <!-- Another author who claims to be an editor -->

  <author initials="H" surname="Asaeda" fullname="Hitoshi Asaeda">
    <organization>Keio University</organization>
    <address>
      <postal>
        <street>Graduate School of Media and Governance</street>
        <street>5322 Endo</street>
        <city>Fujisawa</city> <region>Kanagawa</region>
        <code>252-0882</code>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </postal>
      <email>asaeda@wide.ad.jp</email>
      <uri>http://www.sfc.wide.ad.jp/~asaeda/</uri>
    </address>
  </author>

  <author initials="M." surname="Eubanks" fullname="Marshall Eubanks">
    <organization>AmericaFree.TV</organization>
    <address>
      <postal>
        <street>P.O. Box 141</street>
        <city>Clifton</city>
        <region>VA</region>
        <code>20124</code>
        <country>USA</country>
      </postal>
      <phone></phone>
      <email>marshall.eubanks@gmail.com</email>
    </address>
  </author>

    <author fullname="Tina Tsou" initials="T." surname="Tsou">
      <organization>Huawei Technologies (USA)</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>2330 Central Expressway</street>
          <city>Santa Clara</city>
          <region>CA</region>
          <code>95050</code>
          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>
        <phone>+1 408 330 4424</phone>
        <email>Tina.Tsou.Zouting@huawei.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

  <author initials="S." surname="Venaas" fullname="Stig Venaas">
    <organization>Cisco Systems</organization>
    <address>
      <postal>
        <street>Tasman Drive</street>
        <city>San Jose</city>
        <region>CA</region>
        <code>95134</code>
        <country>USA</country>
      </postal>
      <phone></phone>
      <email>stig@cisco.com</email>
    </address>
  </author>

    <date year="2012" />

    <!-- If the month and year are both specified and are the current ones,
    xml2rfc will fill in the current day for you. If only the current year is
    specified, xml2rfc will fill in the current day and month for you. If the
    year is not the current one, it is necessary to specify at least a month
    (xml2rfc assumes day="1" if not specified for the purpose of calculating
    the expiry date).  With drafts it is normally sufficient to specify just
    the year. -->

    <!-- Meta-data Declarations -->

    <area>Operations and Administration</area>

    <workgroup>Internet Engineering Task Force</workgroup>

    <!-- WG name at the upperleft corner of the doc,
         IETF is fine for individual submissions.  
   If this element is not present, the default is "Network Working Group",
         which is used by the RFC Editor as a nod to the history of the IETF. -->

    <abstract>
      <t> IPTV providers must serve content to their customers during the period
      of transition from IPv4 to IPv6. During this period, the content provider
      may support only one version of IP while the customer supports only the
      other. Likewise, the network between the provider and its customer may
      include segments supporting only one version of IP or another. </t>
      
      <t>This document provides an overview of the multicast transition problem.
      It also provides an overview of the solution space. The solution space is
      characterized by an adaptation function (AF) that provides an interface 
      between IPv4 and IPv6 multicast domains.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>IPTV providers must serve content to their customers during the period
      of transition from IPv4 to IPv6. During this period, the content provider
      may support only one version of IP while the customer supports only the
      other. Likewise, the network between the provider and its customer may 
      include segments supporting only one version of IP or another. </t>
      
      <t>This document provides an overview of the multicast transition problem.
      It also provides an overview of the solution space. The solution space is
      characterized by an adaptation function (AF) that provides an interface 
      between IPv4 and IPv6 multicast domains.</t> 

      <t>Section 2 describes the problem space in detail. This section describes
      an environment that includes a content provider, a customer, and an
      intervening network. Any component of that environment may support only
      one version of IP or the other. At points where IPv4-only devices lie on
      one side and IPv6-only devices on the other, an adaptation function is
      required.</t>
      
      <t>Section 3 proposes a framework for the solution.
      Section 4 defines formal requirements for any proposed solution.</t>

    </section>

    <section anchor="probs" title="A Look At the Multicast Transition Problem Space">
   
       <t>Historically, IPTV providers have served IPv4 content to consumers 
       over IPv4 multicast networks. CPE has supported IPv4 only. As the Internet
       transitions to IPv6, IPv6-capable equipment will be deployed by content
       providers and consumers, as well as the networks that connect them to one
       another. So long as all of the newly deployed gear supports both IPv4 and
       IPv6, the transition to IPv6 may not require new IETF protocol 
       specifications. However, if some of the newly deployed gear supports IPv6
       only, incompatibilities will be introduced. </t>
       
       <t>An incompatibility occurs at a device lying along the path between the
       source and the receiver when the next device on the path on one side of 
       it supports a different version of IP from the next device on the path on
       the other side of it (i.e., one device supports IPv4 only and the other 
       supports IPv6 only). For the purposes of this document, we will call these
       points of incompatibility "IP version transition points". The communication
       path between provider and consumer (which includes both endpoints) can
       include zero or more IP version transition points. </t>
       
       <t>IP version transition points may be introduced at any point along the path.
       These IP version transition points may reside in the subscriber premises, at the
       CPE, in the intervening network etc. In addition, the Set Top Box (STB)
       and Electronic Program Guides (EPG) may have different IP versions. </t>
       
       <t>In order to maintain multicast connectivity, one or more adaptation
       functions (AF) are required. These adaption funtions may be deployed at
       each IP version transition point. However, if for instance there are
       IPv4-only and IPv6-only routers on the path, separated by dual-stack
       routers (routers supporting both IPv4 and IPv6), the adaption function
       may be placed anywhere along that dual-stack path.
       The AF operates in both
       the forwarding and control planes. Because it provides an interface
       between the IPv4 and IPv6 domain, it must be both IPv4-capable and 
       IPv6-capable. </t>
       
       <t>In most cases, the adaptation function will mediate between IPv4
       and IPv6 on both the control and forwarding planes. However, in scenarios
       where the path between provider and consumer contains multiple IP version
       transition points, adaptation function instances may tunnel traffic between one
       another. </t>

    </section><!-- probs -->
    
    
    <section anchor="solns" title="A Look At the Solution Space For Multicast Transition">
   
 			<t>The AF operates on both the forwarding and control planes. On the 
 			forwarding plane, the AF inserts itself into the forwarding path translating
 			multicast packets from one IP version to the other. On the control plane, 
 			the AF receives routing and signaling messages of one protocol and sends 
 			out routing and signaling messages of another protocol. If the device acts
			as a router this may be part of the usual message processing and generation,
			but it may also be done as translation of messages, without taking part in
			the protocol operations. [draft to come] provides a discussion of AF operation
 			and deployment.</t>
 			
 		  <section anchor="fwdPlane" title="AF Forwarding Plane Operation">
 		
 			  <t>The AF accepts packets from one IP version, removes the IP header,
 			  and replaces it with an IP Header of the other version. A significant 
 			  portion of that task is address translation. Ideally the address translation 
 		  	  strategy used by an AF should be algorithmic, stateless and reversible. This
			  should be simple when addresses from one IP version can simply be embedded
			  into another (IPv4 into IPv6), but this may not be possible in the opposite
			  direction. That the translation is reversible means that there is a stateless
			  algorithm for translating back into the original address.</t>
 			
 			  <t><xref target="RFC6052"/> provides an algorithm for translating unicast
 			  addresses between IPv4 and IPv6. Likewise 
 			  <xref target="I-D.mboned-64-mcast-addr-fmt"/> provides an algorithm for 
 			  multicast address conversion between IPv4 and IPv6. Note that using this
			  algorithm, different translators could choose different IPv6 prefixes for
			  embedding the IPv4 addresses. But the format allows for stateless
			  translation back to the original IPv4 addresses.</t> 			

 			  <t>Other issues associated with IP version translation may arise (e.g.,
 			  fragmentation and checksums). The scope of these issues is wider than that
			  of multicast transition. As such issues are identified, they will be
			  resolved in conjunction with appropriate IETF working groups.</t>
 		
 		  </section>
 		  
 		  
 		  <section anchor="ctlPlane" title="AF Control Plane Operation">
 		 
 		 	  <t>On the control plane, the AF mediates between:
 		 	  <list style="symbols">
 		 	    <t>IGMPv3 <xref target="RFC3376"/> and MLDv2 <xref target="RFC3810"/>;</t>
 		 	    <t>PIM(v4) <xref target="RFC4601"/> and PIM(v6);</t>
 		 	    <t>IGMPv3 and PIM(v6);</t>
 		 	    <t>MLD and PIM(v4);</t>
 		 	  </list>
 		 	  </t>
 		 	  
 		 	  <t>The IGMP-to-MLD translation may be configured to use only IGMPv2 
 		 	  features. It is defined in [draft to come].</t>
 		 	  
 		 	  <t>The PIM-to-PIM mediation operates between PIM protocol operations of
			  one IP version with operations of the other version. This mediation
			  is defined in [draft to come].</t>
 		 
 		  </section>
 		 
 		  
 		  <section anchor="discover" title="Source Discovery">
 		 
 		 	  <t>Multicast requires a mechanism through which a receiver can associate 
 		 	  a multicast stream with a multicast group address. The Session Announcement
 		 	  Protocol (SAP, <xref target="RFC2974"/>) is such a mechanism which is 
 		 	  still in use in academic environments and by some content providers.  
 		 	  AF translation rules for this 
 		 	  protocol are also described in [draft to come]. For commercial purposes,
 		 	  different standards development organizations have specified protocols 
 		 	  for transmission of electronic program guides. 
 		 	  <xref target="ID.tsou-multrans-addr-acquisition"/> specifies the operation
 		 	  of the AF in such an environment [... in a future version of the draft
 		 	  which comes to a conclusion on the best way forward].</t>
 		 
 		  </section>
 		  
 		  
 		  <section anchor="pathOpt" title="Transitional Multicast Path Optimization">
 		 
 		 	  <t>A mechanism to optimize the path to the multicast source for a 
 		 	  combination of IPv4 and IPv6 networks is not immediately required, but
 		 	  is a topic for future work.</t>
 		 
 		  </section>
 		 
    </section><!-- solns -->    
    
    <section anchor="reqs" title="Requirements">
   
       <t>From the description above, we can distill the following requirements:
       <list style="empty">
         <t>REQ 1: It must be possible for the receiver to acquire the multicast
         group address and, where applicable, the unicast source address of the
         target stream in the IP version that the receiver supports.</t>
         
         <t>REQ 2: It must be possible for the receiver to join the multicast
         distribution tree for the target stream even if the IP version used 
         in the interior of the network to which the receiver is attached is
         different from the version supported by the receiver.</t>
         
         <t>REQ 3: Where local policy permits, it must be possible to extend 
         the multicast distribution tree for a given stream across a network
         boundary where different IP versions are supported in the two networks
         separated by that boundary.</t>
         
         <t>REQ 4: When the multicast distribution tree for a given stream is
         extended across multiple network boundaries across one or more of 
         which the IP version changes, it must be possible to avoid multicast 
         routing loops.</t>
         
         <t>REQ 5: It must be possible to pass packets belonging to a given
         multicast stream to all joined receivers, regardless of changes in 
         IP version encountered along the way.</t>
         
         <t>REQ 6: Both ASM and SSM technology must be supported.</t>
         
         <t>REQ 7: The solution(s) should allow operators to minimize the 
         total incremental cost (investment plus operations during the 
         transitional period)) due to multicast transition.</t>
         
         <t>REQ 8: The solution(s) should provide a clear evolutionary path to
         all-IPv6 operation.</t>
        
       </list>
       </t>
   
    </section>

   
   
    <section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">
    
      <t>Ron Bonica inspired the writing of this memo and shaped its content.
      Michael McBride provided useful comments on an intermediate version of
      this document.</t>

    </section>

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
    
      <t>This memo includes no request to IANA.</t>

    </section>

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
    
      <t>To come.</t>
      
    </section>
  </middle>

  <!--  *****BACK MATTER ***** -->

  <back>
    <references title="Informative References">
    
      &RFC2974;
      &RFC3376;
      &RFC3810;
      &RFC4601;
      &RFC6052;
      
			<reference anchor="I-D.mboned-64-mcast-addr-fmt">
				<front>
          <title>IPv4-Embedded IPv6 Multicast Address Format (Work in Progress)</title>
          <author initials="M." surname="Boucadair" fullname="M. Boucadair">
            <organization>France Telecom</organization>
          </author>
          <author initials="J." surname="Qin" fullname="J. Qin">
            <organization>ZTE</organization>
          </author>
          <author initials="Y." surname="Lee" fullname="Y. Lee">
            <organization>Comcast</organization>
          </author>
          <author initials="S." surname="Venaas" fullname="S. Venaas">
            <organization>Cisco Systems</organization>
          </author>
          <author initials="X." surname="Li" fullname="X. Li">
            <organization>CERNET Center/Tsinghua University</organization>
          </author>
          <author initials="M." surname="Xu" fullname="M. Xu">
            <organization>Tsinghua University</organization>
          </author>
          <date month="February" year="2012"/>
        </front>
			</reference>

      
      <reference anchor="ID.tsou-multrans-addr-acquisition">
         <front>
          <title>Address Acquisition For Multicast Content When Source and Receiver Support Differing IP Versions (Work in Progress)</title>
          <author initials="T." surname="Tsou" fullname="T. Tsou">
            <organization>Huawei Technologies (USA)</organization>
          </author>
          <date month="December" year="2011"/>
        </front>
      </reference>
   
    </references>

  </back>
</rfc>
