<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!-- This template is for creating an Internet Draft using xml2rfc,
     which is available here: http://xml.resource.org. -->
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!-- One method to get references from the online citation libraries.
     There has to be one entity for each item to be referenced. 
     An alternate method (rfc include) is described in the references. -->

<!ENTITY RFC2236 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2236.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC2710 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2710.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3376 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3376.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3810 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3810.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6052 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6052.xml">
]>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<!-- used by XSLT processors -->
<!-- For a complete list and description of processing instructions (PIs), 
     please see http://xml.resource.org/authoring/README.html. -->
<!-- Below are generally applicable Processing Instructions (PIs) that most I-Ds might want to use.
     (Here they are set differently than their defaults in xml2rfc v1.32) -->
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<!-- give errors regarding ID-nits and DTD validation -->
<!-- control the table of contents (ToC) -->
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<!-- generate a ToC -->
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<!-- the number of levels of subsections in ToC. default: 3 -->
<!-- control references -->
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<!-- use symbolic references tags, i.e, [RFC2119] instead of [1] -->
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<!-- sort the reference entries alphabetically -->
<!-- control vertical white space 
     (using these PIs as follows is recommended by the RFC Editor) -->
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<!-- do not start each main section on a new page -->
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<!-- keep one blank line between list items -->
<!-- end of list of popular I-D processing instructions -->

<rfc category="info" docName="draft-eubanks-mboned-transition-overview-00" ipr="trust200902">
  <!-- category values: std, bcp, info, exp, and historic
     ipr values: trust200902, noModificationTrust200902, noDerivativesTrust200902
     pre5378Trust200902
     you can add the attributes updates="NNNN" and obsoletes="NNNN" 
     they will automatically be output with "(if approved)" -->

  <!-- ***** FRONT MATTER ***** -->

  <front>
    <!-- The abbreviated title is used in the page header - it is only necessary if the 
         full title is longer than 39 characters -->

    <title>Multicast Transition Overview</title>

    <!-- add 'role="editor"' below for the editors if appropriate -->

    <!-- Another author who claims to be an editor -->

  <author initials="H." surname="Asaeda" fullname="Hitoshi Asaeda">
    <organization></organization>
    <address>
      <postal>
        <street></street>
        <city></city>
        <region></region>
        <code></code>
        <country></country>
      </postal>
      <phone></phone>
      <email>asaeda@sfc.wide.ad.jp</email>
    </address>
  </author>

  <author initials="M." surname="Eubanks" fullname="Marshall Eubanks">
    <organization>AmericaFree.TV</organization>
    <address>
      <postal>
        <street>P.O. Box 141</street>
        <city>Clifton</city>
        <region>VA</region>
        <code>20124</code>
        <country>USA</country>
      </postal>
      <phone></phone>
      <email>marshall.eubanks@gmail.com</email>
    </address>
  </author>

    <author fullname="Tina Tsou" initials="T." surname="Tsou">
      <organization>Huawei Technologies (USA)</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>2330 Central Expressway</street>
          <city>Santa Clara</city>
          <region>CA</region>
          <code>95050</code>
          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>
        <phone>+1 408 330 4424</phone>
        <email>Tina.Tsou.Zouting@huawei.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

  <author initials="S." surname="Venaas" fullname="Stig Venaas">
    <organization>Cisco Systems</organization>
    <address>
      <postal>
        <street>Tasman Drive</street>
        <city>San Jose</city>
        <region>CA</region>
        <code>95134</code>
        <country>USA</country>
      </postal>
      <phone></phone>
      <email>stig@cisco.com</email>
    </address>
  </author>

    <date month="January" year="2012" />

    <!-- If the month and year are both specified and are the current ones,
    xml2rfc will fill in the current day for you. If only the current year is
    specified, xml2rfc will fill in the current day and month for you. If the
    year is not the current one, it is necessary to specify at least a month
    (xml2rfc assumes day="1" if not specified for the purpose of calculating
    the expiry date).  With drafts it is normally sufficient to specify just
    the year. -->

    <!-- Meta-data Declarations -->

    <area>Operations and ASdministration</area>

    <workgroup>Internet Engineering Task Force</workgroup>

    <!-- WG name at the upperleft corner of the doc,
         IETF is fine for individual submissions.  
   If this element is not present, the default is "Network Working Group",
         which is used by the RFC Editor as a nod to the history of the IETF. -->

    <abstract>
      <t>The transition from IPv4 to IPv6 raises issues for multicast signaling
      and multicast content distribution. This memo describes the problem and
      briefly surveys the solution space.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>The transition from IPv4 to IPv6 presents challenges for multicast
      operation. It is common in practice to encounter 
      differences between IP versions
      supported along the path between the source and the
      receiver, with some nodes only supporting IPv4, some IPv6, for both multicast
      and unicast. <xref target="ID.jaclee-behave-v4v6-mcast-ps"/> illustrates
      the different end-to-end configurations that can occur during transition
      (and identifies the most likely ones) while exploring the problem of
      multicast transition for IPTV applications in particular. The reason 
      that the draft concentrates on IPTV is that this  
      application is encountering multicast transition issues in the present and 
      these are likely to intensify in 
      the near future. In this document, "multicast transition" will specifically refer
      to transitions between IPv4 and IPv6 or vice versa, including networks with multiple transitions,
      say from IPv4 to IPv6 and back to IPv4, and a "multicast domain" will refer to a network or sub-network
      supporting one or both variants of Internet multicast. Note that networks may support both 
      versions of the Internet protocol without supporting multicast in both versions, and so multicast 
      transitions may be required even in
      cases where end-to-end unicast transport is supported.</t> 

      <t>The present memo provides a quick survey of the problem space and
      the possible solutions, as an aid to further discussion of the topic 
      of multicast transition.</t>

      <section title="Requirements Language">
        <t>This document contains no requirements language.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="probs" title="A Look At the Multicast Transition Problem Space">
   
       <t>As <xref target="ID.jaclee-behave-v4v6-mcast-ps"/> points out, in common 
       practice multicast video 
       transport actually happens in three stages. First, the receiver has to 
       acquire the address(es) that it needs to request a particular multicast 
       stream. It always needs to learn the multicast group address or addresses.
       If source-specific multicast (SSM) is deployed, it also needs to learn the
       associated unicast source address for each multicast group address. 
       Existing arrangements to support this
       acquisition process will in some cases need modification to ensure that
       the receiver acquires the address(es) in the IP version that it 
       understands. </t>
       
       <t>Following address acquisition, the receiver uses multicast signaling
       to request delivery of the user-selected multicast stream or streams. The key issue 
       at this stage is that each time the multicast signaling crosses a 
       boundary between a network supporting one IP version and a network 
       supporting the other, the address(es) designating the requested multicast 
       stream need to be remapped to the new version. This is required in all cases
       for the group addresses, and also for unicast source addresses for SSM. In addition, in the 
       particular case where there is a transition at the receiver itself, 
       protocol interworking between IGMP 
       (<xref target="RFC2236"/>, <xref target="RFC3376"/>) and MLD 
       (<xref target="RFC2710"/>, <xref target="RFC3810"/>) may be necessary. 
       Even in the case where the receiver shares a link with a (dual stack) 
       multicast router, such interworking may be considered to occur internally 
       in the multicast router as an intermediate step. </t>
       
       <t>The creation of multicast trees in response to multicast signaling 
       relies on the use of reverse path forwarding (RPF) to avoid the creation
       of routing loops; this is also required in networks performing transitions between 
       multicast domains. In the face of address remapping, it has been suggested
       that each network along the path from source to receiver needs to know
       the ultimate source address for RPF to work. Thus, part of the multicast
       transition problem is to make sure that this information is available at
       the appropriate point in the routing process, or to devise an alternative means for doing this
       that would avoid routing loops without end to end source discovery. </t>
       
       <t>The final stage of multicast acquisition is the actual delivery of
       packets of multicast content, i.e., the flooding of data down the multicast trees. 
       Again, address mapping is required across
       each IP version boundary. The source and group addresses appearing in the one network 
       must be replaced by corresponding source and group addresses in the other
       IP version before the packet can be forwarded for its next stage of
       travel.</t>
       
       <t>Address remapping across IP version boundaries is required in all 
       three stages of acquisition of a multicast stream. 
       <xref target="ID.venaas-behave-v4v6mc-framework"/> examines the issue 
       of translation between IPv4 and IPv6 multicast addresses in various 
       scenarios. In many cases of practical interest, stateless mapping is 
       possible.</t>

      <t>A key point is that address 
       mapping requires coordination both in space and in time. To ensure that
       the multicast stream requested is the one delivered, the same address(es), or
       a unique mapping of those addresses,
       must be used to designate the stream at any given point, whether at the
       stage of address acquisition, multicast signaling, or multicast content
       delivery. Moreover, coordination between successive multicast domains in the path 
       is required to ensure that the address(es) requested by the 
       receiver are mapped in the source network to the stream that the user 
       wishes to acquire. In stateless mapping, the network must ensure that two streams that might
       be requested by a given user are not
       given the same address(es) at the same time; this is more difficult when transitioning into an IPv4 domain given the 
       smaller range of address space available in IPv4.</t>
   
    </section><!-- probs -->
    
    
    <section anchor="solns" title="A Look At the Solution Space For Multicast Transition">
   
       <t>Consistently with the problem space overview, the multicast transition 
       problem divides naturally into three parts:
       <list style="numbers">
          <t>providing a multicast group and possibly unicast source address 
          to the receiver in the IP version supported by the receiver;</t>
          
          <t>mediating the exchange of multicast signaling and content between 
          the receiver and its network when the two 
          support different IP versions;</t>
          
          <t>mediating the exchange of multicast signaling and content between 
          two networks supporting different IP versions along the path between the
          source and the receiver.</t>
       </list>
       </t>

      <t>Problem 1 is addressed in <xref target="ID.tsou-multrans-addr-acquisition"/>.
      In the IPTV case, the key element in the solution  for address 
      acquisition (discovery) is the processing of the electronic program guide (EPG) that 
      provides the receiver with the multicast group and possibly the unicast 
      source addresses it needs to request specific program instances. Three
      possible strategies are considered:
      <list style="symbols">
         <t>recognition and conversion of unsupported-IP-version addresses at the 
         receiver after it receives the EPG, through a protocol exchange with
         a mapping function in the network;</t>
         
         <t>interception and remapping of addresses in the EPG as necessary by 
         the network to which the receiver is attached, before the receiver 
         receives information from the EPG;</t>
         
         <t>administrative modification of the EPG in advance of acquisition,
         either to provide the specific version required by each receiver or
         to carry addresses in both versions in a form that allows the receiver
         to select the version it supports.</t>
      </list>
      </t>

      <t>Problem 2 is addressed in <xref target="ID.zhou-multrans-af1-specification"/>.
      That draft uses the term "Type 1 Adaptation Function" (AF1) for a mediating
      function between the receiver and the network. This function has two parts:
      translating the multicast access signaling (IGMP or MLD) to the signaling
      appropriate to the other IP version (MLD or IGMP respectively), and modifying
      incoming packets of content to the version supported by the receiver. These
      packets may need either header translation or decapsulation, depending on
      the deployment. Difficulties in evolution of the decapsulation option with
      the transition to all-IPv6 operation are noted.</t>

      <t>Problem 3 is addressed in 
      <xref target="ID.taylor-multrans-af2-specification"/>. Here the term "Type 2
      Adaptation Function" (AF2) is used for the function required. Again, this
      function operates both on multicast signaling and multicast content. On
      the signaling side, the function maps the addresses contained in PIM
      messages from one IP version to the other. With respect to content, depending
      on deployment, the AF2 either encapsulates or translates the headers of 
      incoming packets of multicast content before forwarding them toward the
      receiver.</t>

      <t>A basic tool required for all of these problems is a method to map
      consistently between IPv4 and IPv6 versions of the source and group 
      addresses. <xref target="RFC6052"/> provides the necessary mapping for the
      unicast source addresses, if present. 
      <xref target="ID.boucadair-behave-64-multicast-address-format"/> provides 
      a stateless solution for the mapping between IPv4 and IPv6 multicast 
      addresses.</t>

      <t><xref target="ID.softwire-dslite-multicast"/> is essentially an applicability
      statement, showing the application of the AF1, AF2, and address mapping to
      the particular case where DS-Lite is deployed. AF1 is located in the
      "multicast B4" (mB4), along with the unicast DS-Lite B4 function, at the 
      customer edge. AF2 is located in the "multicast AFTR" at the border between
      the IPv6 network to which the customer is attached and the IPv4 network
      containing the source. The draft specifies the use of encapsulation of 
      multicast content across the IPv6 network.</t>

      <t><xref target="ID.xu-softwire-mesh-multicast"/> deals with the particular 
      case where a multicast-capable network provides a transit service between 
      other multicast-capable networks of differing IP versions. Its interaction
      with the proposed AF2 functionality requires further study.</t> 
   
    </section><!-- solns -->
   
   
    <section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">
    
      <t>Ron Bonica inspired the writing of this memo and shaped its content.</t>

    </section>

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>This memo includes no request to IANA.</t>

    </section>

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
    
      <t>To come.</t>
      
    </section>
  </middle>

  <!--  *****BACK MATTER ***** -->

  <back>
    <references title="Informative References">
    
      &RFC2236;
      &RFC2710;
      &RFC3376;
      &RFC3810;
      &RFC6052;
      
      <reference anchor="ID.jaclee-behave-v4v6-mcast-ps">
         <front>
          <title>IPv4-IPv6 Multicast: Problem Statement and Use Cases (Work in progress)</title>
          <author initials="C." surname="Jacquenet" fullname="C. Jacquenet">
            <organization>France Telecom</organization>
          </author>
          <author initials="M." surname="Boucadair" fullname="M. Boucadair">
            <organization>France Telecom</organization>
          </author>
          <author initials="Y." surname="Lee" fullname="Y. Lee">
            <organization>Comcast</organization>
          </author>
          <author initials="J." surname="Qin" fullname="J. Qin">
            <organization>ZTE</organization>
          </author>
          <author initials="T." surname="Tsou" fullname="T. Tsou">
            <organization>Huawei Technologies (USA)</organization>
          </author>
          <date month="November" year="2011"/>
        </front>
      </reference>
     
      <reference anchor="ID.venaas-behave-v4v6mc-framework">
        <front>
           <title>Framework for IPv4/IPv6 Multicast Translation (Work in progress)</title>
          <author initials="S." surname="Venaas" fullname="S. Venaas">
            <organization>Cisco Systems</organization>
          </author>
          <author initials="X." surname="Li" fullname="X. Li">
            <organization>CERNET Center/Tsinghua University</organization>
          </author>
          <author initials="C." surname="Bao" fullname="C. Bao">
            <organization>CERNET Center/Tsinghua University</organization>
          </author>
          <date month="June" year="2011"/>
        </front>
      </reference>
    
      <reference anchor="ID.tsou-multrans-addr-acquisition">
         <front>
          <title>Address Acquisition For Multicast Content When Source and Receiver Support Differing IP Versions (Work in progress)</title>
          <author initials="T." surname="Tsou" fullname="T. Tsou">
            <organization>Huawei Technologies (USA)</organization>
          </author>
          <date month="December" year="2011"/>
        </front>
      </reference>
   
      <reference anchor="ID.zhou-multrans-af1-specification">
        <front>
           <title>Specification of a Provider-Managed Adaptive Function Between a Multicast Receiver and a Provider Network Supporting a Different IP Version (Work in progress)</title>
          <author initials="C." surname="Zhou" fullname="C. Zhou">
            <organization>Huawei Technologies</organization>
          </author>
          <author initials="T." surname="Taylor" fullname="T. Taylor">
            <organization>Huawei Technologies</organization>
          </author>
          <date month="December" year="2011"/>
        </front>
      </reference>
  
      <reference anchor="ID.taylor-multrans-af2-specification">
         <front>
          <title>Specification of an Adaptation Function Between Two Multicast Networks Supporting Different IP Versions (Work in progress)</title>
          <author initials="T." surname="Taylor" fullname="T. Taylor">
            <organization>Huawei Technologies</organization>
          </author>
          <author initials="C." surname="Zhou" fullname="C. Zhou">
            <organization>Huawei Technologies</organization>
          </author>
          <date month="December" year="2011"/>
        </front>
      </reference>
 
      <reference anchor="ID.boucadair-behave-64-multicast-address-format">
         <front>
          <title>IPv4-Embedded IPv6 Multicast Address Format (Work in progress)</title>
          <author initials="M." surname="Boucadair" fullname="M. Boucadair">
            <organization>France Telecom</organization>
          </author>
          <author initials="J." surname="Qin" fullname="J. Qin">
            <organization>ZTE</organization>
          </author>
          <author initials="Y." surname="Lee" fullname="Y. Lee">
            <organization>Comcast</organization>
          </author>
          <author initials="S." surname="Venaas" fullname="S. Venaas">
            <organization>Cisco Systems</organization>
          </author>
          <author initials="X." surname="Li" fullname="X. Li">
            <organization>CERNET Center/Tsinghua University</organization>
          </author>
          <author initials="M." surname="Xu" fullname="M. Xu">
            <organization>CERNET Center/Tsinghua University</organization>
          </author>
          <date month="October" year="2011"/>
        </front>
      </reference>
  
      <reference anchor="ID.softwire-dslite-multicast">
         <front>
          <title>Multicast Extensions to DS-Lite Technique in Broadband Deployments (Work in progress)</title>
          <author initials="Q." surname="Wang" fullname="Q. Wang">
            <organization>China Telecom</organization>
          </author>
          <author initials="J." surname="Qin" fullname="J. Qin">
            <organization>ZTE</organization>
          </author>
          <author initials="M." surname="Boucadair" fullname="M. Boucadair">
            <organization>France Telecom</organization>
          </author>
          <author initials="C." surname="Jacquenet" fullname="C. Jacquenet">
            <organization>France Telecom</organization>
          </author>
          <author initials="Y." surname="Lee" fullname="Y. Lee">
            <organization>Comcast</organization>
          </author>
          <date month="October" year="2011"/>
        </front>
      </reference>
 
      <reference anchor="ID.xu-softwire-mesh-multicast">
         <front>
          <title>Softwire Mesh Multicast (Work in progress)</title>
          <author initials="M." surname="Xu" fullname="M. Xu">
            <organization>Tsinghua University</organization>
          </author>
          <author initials="Y." surname="Cui" fullname="Y. Cui">
            <organization>Tsinghua University</organization>
          </author>
          <author initials="S." surname="Yang" fullname="S. Yang">
            <organization>Tsinghua University</organization>
          </author>
          <author initials="C." surname="Metz" fullname="C. Metz">
            <organization>Cisco Systems</organization>
          </author>
          <author initials="G." surname="Shepherd" fullname="G. Shepherd">
            <organization>Cisco Systems</organization>
          </author>
          <date month="July" year="2011"/>
        </front>
      </reference>
     
    </references>

  </back>
</rfc>
