<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!-- References are listed here so that they can be called via Entity attributes later -->
<!ENTITY RFC2119 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
]>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<!-- PROCESSING INSTRUCTIONS - GENERAL -->
<!-- EACH ONE STARTS WITH '?' BELOW -->
<!-- give errors on I-D nits and perform DTD validation -->
<!-- control the table of contents (ToC) -->
<?rfc strict='yes' ?>
<?rfc toc='yes'?>
<!-- generate a ToC -->
<!-- the number of levels of subsections in ToC. default: 3 -->
<?rfc tocdepth='4'?>
<!-- END GENERAL PROCESSING -->
<!-- PROCESSING INSTRUCTIONS - CONTROL OF REFERENCES -->
<!-- use symbolic references tags, i.e, [RFC2119] instead of [1] -->
<?rfc symrefs='yes'?>
<!-- sort the reference entries alphabetically -->
<!-- control vertical white space -->
<?rfc sortrefs='yes' ?>
<!-- do not start each main section on a new page -->
<?rfc compact='yes' ?>
<!-- keep one blank line between list items -->
<?rfc subcompact='no' ?>
<!-- END REFERENCE PROCESSING -->
<rfc category="info" docName="draft-jjmb-v6ops-comcast-ipv6-experiences-02"
     ipr="trust200902">
  <!-- FRONT SECTION -->

  <front>
    <title abbrev="Comcast IPv6 Trial/Deployment Experiences">Comcast IPv6
    Trial/Deployment Experiences</title>

    <author fullname="John Jason Brzozowski" initials="J.B."
            surname="Brzozowski">
      <organization abbrev="Comcast">Comcast Cable
      Communications</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>One Comcast Center</street>

          <street>1701 John F. Kennedy Boulevard</street>

          <city>Philadelphia</city>

          <region>PA</region>

          <code>19103</code>

          <country>US</country>
        </postal>

        <email>john_brzozowski@cable.comcast.com</email>

        <uri>http://www.comcast.com</uri>
      </address>

      <!-- author role='editor' is an optional value here -->
    </author>

    <author fullname="Chris Griffiths" initials="C.G." surname="Griffiths">
      <organization abbrev="Comcast">Comcast Cable
      Communications</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>One Comcast Center</street>

          <street>1701 John F. Kennedy Boulevard</street>

          <city>Philadelphia</city>

          <region>PA</region>

          <code>19103</code>

          <country>US</country>
        </postal>

        <email>chris_griffiths@cable.comcast.com</email>

        <uri>http://www.comcast.com</uri>
      </address>

      <!-- author role='editor' is an optional value here -->
    </author>

    <date day="2" month="October" year="2011" />

    <!-- META-DATA DECLARATIONS -->

    <area>Operations and Management Area</area>

    <!-- WG name at the upperleft corner of the doc; 'Internet Engineering Task Force' is fine for individual submissions.  -->

    <workgroup>IPv6 Operations</workgroup>

    <!-- Keywords will be incorporated into HTML output files in a meta tag but they have no effect on text or nroff output. If you submit your draft to the RFC Editor, the keywords will be used for the search engine. -->

    <keyword>RFC</keyword>

    <keyword>Request for Comments</keyword>

    <keyword>I-D</keyword>

    <keyword>Internet-Draft</keyword>

    <keyword>XML</keyword>

    <keyword>Extensible Markup Language</keyword>

    <keyword>Comcast</keyword>

    <keyword>ISP</keyword>

    <keyword>Internet Service Provider</keyword>

    <keyword>IPv6</keyword>

    <keyword>Trial</keyword>

    <keyword>Deployment</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>This document outlines the various technologies Comcast has trialed
      as part of the company's ongoing IPv6 initiatives. The focus here are
      the technologies and experiences specific to enabling IPv6 for
      subscriber services like high speed data or Internet. Comcast has
      learned a great deal about various technologies that we feel are
      important to share with the community.</t>
    </abstract>

    <!-- END META-DATA DECLARATIONS -->
  </front>

  <!-- END FRONT SECTION -->

  <!-- MIDDLE SECTION -->

  <middle>
    <section anchor="ReqLang" title="Requirements Language" toc="include">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
      document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
      target="RFC2119"></xref>.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>Beginning in early 2010 Comcast announced plans to leverage the work
      the company has been doing related to IPv6 to conduct a number of IPv6
      technology trials. These trials were specifically aimed at enabling IPv6
      for subscriber services. The purpose of this document is to outline the
      technologies that have been trialed thus far along with experiences and
      observations that adopters of the same may find valuable in their own
      planning and deployment processes.</t>

      <t>Further, there may be some additional feedback that the various
      groups within the IETF may wish to take into account as part of ongoing
      standards efforts.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="_6to4" title="6to4">
      <t>During production deployment planning the widespread use of 6to4
      [RFC3068] to access content and services over IPv6 was assessed. In some
      scenarios 6to4 usage increased several hundred times. At the time
      Comcast had not deployed its own 6to4 relay infrastructure as such open
      relays being operated by independent third parties were by default used
      to facilitate 6to4-based communications. The deployment and default use
      of open 6to4 relays appears to be a key variable behind the sub-optimal
      performance associated with the use of 6to4. An important thing to note
      is that some home gateway vendors have turned on 6to4 by default, and in
      some of these implementations, they have not presented a user interface
      a user interface to disable it. For operators that have not deployed
      IPv6 or have IPv6 incapable infrastructures should note that the use of
      6to4 is likely occurring today across their infrastructure. Many
      operating systems and home networking devices continue to support 6to4
      and in some cases have 6to4 and other transition technologies enabled by
      default.</t>

      <t>As a community there appears to be some consensus that long term the
      use of 6to4 is not desirable, however, in the near term it is clear that
      6to4 will be used in specific scenarios. The expectation and goal is to
      see 6to4 usage diminish over time until use of the same is displaced by
      an alternate technique to access content and services over IPv6. While
      the debate continues over how and when to deprecate 6to4, it is clear
      that 6to4 should not be recommended as a primary mechanism to access
      content and services over IPv6.</t>

      <t>The following documents outline the recommendations surrounding the
      use and status of 6to4 from a standards point of view:</t>

      <t><list style="numbers">
          <t>[draft-ietf-v6ops-6to4-advisory]</t>

          <t>[draft-ietf-v6ops-6to4-to-historic]</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>Comcast deployed a series of five (5) 6to4 relays in a geographically
      dispersed configuration across our network. The purpose of these relays
      was to reduce the latency typically associated with 6to4 usage. During
      our analysis, the use of off network, open 6to4 relays was determined to
      yield nearly unusable conditions depending on the geographic location of
      the end user relative to the open 6to4 relay. By deploying on-network
      6to4 relays, latency in most cases was reduced by over 50%, which
      instantly yielded considerable improvements from an end user point of
      view. The simplistic design and deployment of these relays enabled us to
      rapidly put them in network, and in some cases create a better
      experience for some of our users who had 6to4 enabled.</t>

      <t>Through the use of commodity x86 based servers that run a standard
      Linux Operating System, we reduced deployment and operating costs, while
      still maintaining a fault tolerant design. Each 6to4 relay was dual
      stacked, and with a simple kernel module, we enabled the 6to4
      configuration. Some 6to4 specific configurations were required to ensure
      compatibility across a wide range of end points. The logic to anycast
      the 6to4 records was handled by the network infrastructure providing
      connectivity to the 6to4 relays, and health checking enabled us to
      automatically remove the route for any relay from the routing table in
      case of failure.</t>

      <figure anchor="_comcast_6to4_relay"
              title="Comcast 6to4 Data Center View">
        <artwork><![CDATA[  
	   

                           Router Announces			 
      <---------.            IPv4 Anycast            .--------->
      Redundant |            192.88.99.1             | Redundant 
      Network   |           +------------+           | Network      
      Path      |           |  Network   |           | Path
                +-----------+   Router   +-----------+
                            +------------+
                            IPv4 |  | IPv6
                       Interface |  | Interface
                              +--+--+--+
                              | Linux  |
                              |  6to4  |
                              | Relay  |
                              +--------+

                           
                           
                     ]]></artwork>
      </figure>
    </section>

    <section anchor="_6rd" title="6RD">
      <t>6RD [draft-townsley-ipv6-6rd] is another transition technology
      similar to 6to4 that Comcast has deployed as part of technology trials.
      While 6RD yields some improvements over 6to4, 6RD is ultimately a
      tunneling technology. As such, it is subject to the challenges faced by
      other tunneling technologies.</t>

      <t>As advertised, 6RD frees adopters from some restrictions typically
      associated with 6to4. The use of anycast addressing (IPv4 and IPv6) is
      no longer required and the infrastructure, like 6to4, is straightforward
      to deploy. However, at the time of deployment it was observed that a
      limited number of border relay (BR) implementations were available. This
      appears to be an evolving area with more implementations becoming
      available. Similarly it was observed that there we few if any customer
      edge (CE) implementations available to support a trial of the
      technology. As such engineering implementations were leveraged to
      evaluate 6RD. Further, there were no implementations available that
      supported the 6RD DHCPv4 options [draft-ietf-softwire-ipv6-6rd]. Because
      of this, every 6RD CE used for trial was manually configured with the
      necessary information required to enable 6RD. In order to support a wide
      scale production deployment leveraging 6RD an operator would have to
      ensure their DHCP infrastructure supports the required 6RD DHCPv4
      options along with targeted 6RD CE devices.</t>

      <t>Trial configurations included two (2) 6RD BRs, which were
      intentionally deployed in geographically dispersed configuration. An
      anycast design was used to enable 6RD with a well known IPv4 anycast
      address and FQDN for the 6RD BR. The use of anycast eased manual
      configuration and deployment. Additionally, an IPv6 /32 was used to
      support the 6RD trials permitting subscriber devices were able to yield
      a usable IPv6 /64 on the LAN side of the 6RD CE.</t>

      <t>The quantity and location of the 6RD BRs is a key variable when
      planning the deployment of 6RD. Comcast specifically deployed a limited
      quantity of BRs resulting in some end users being "closer" to the BRs
      than others. Proximity to the 6RD BRs is an important factor that
      impacts the end user experience. While 6RD yields some improvements over
      6to4, 6RD is ultimately a tunneling technology as such use of the same
      is subject to the challenges faced by other tunneling technologies.</t>

      <t>Placement and quantity of 6RD BRs is also a significant variable to
      consider when assessing impacts to performance and IPv6 geo-location. A
      centralized approach to deploying 6RD BRs will yield undesirable impacts
      to IPv6 geo-location in that end users leveraging a particular 6RD BR
      that is geographically distant from their true location will not
      accurately represent the origin of the end user request. Conversely,
      deploying 6RD BRs that are near to end users may require a substantial
      quantity of 6RD BRs depending on the operator network.</t>

      <t>The following provides an overview of the Comcast 6RD trial network
      design:</t>

      <figure anchor="_comcast_6rd" title="Comcast 6RD Overview">
        <artwork><![CDATA[ 
      +-------------------------------------------------------------+
      |                           Internet                          |
      +-------+-------------------------------------------+---------+
       IPv6   |                                           |    IPv6
      +-------+--------+                          +-------+--------+
      |                |                          |                |
      |    Router      |                          |    Router      |
      |                |                          |                |
      +---+--------+---+                          +---+---------+--+
          |        |                                  |         |
      IPv4|        | IPv6                       IPv4  |         | IPv6
          |        |                                  |         |
      +---+--------+---+                          +---+---------+--+
      |                |                          |                |
      |   6rd-br-01    |                          |   6rd-br-02    |
      |                |     6rd.comcast.net      |                |
      +----------------+     _..-'      -.._      +----------------+
                         _.-'               `--._
                    _.--'                        ``-.__
                _.-'  IPv6                   IPv6      `-.._
         ,-..--'   encapsulated           encapsulated      ``-..
        (   )        in IPv4                in IPv4          (   )
         `-'                                                  `-'
       6rd CE                                                6rd CE
          |                                                    |
          |  IPv6                                              | IPv6
          |                                                    |]]></artwork>
      </figure>
    </section>

    <section anchor="_nds" title="Native Dual Stack">
      <t>Native dual stack is central to Comcast's IPv6 program for trial and
      production deployment. Native dual stack is the model where IPv4
      services remain as-is with native IPv6 support introduced in parallel or
      simultaneously. Many of the details surrounding how this is achieved are
      documented as part of the CableLabs Data Over Cable Service Interface
      Specification (DOCSIS) 3.0 [DOCSIS3.0]. However, relevant trial and
      deployment specific information that is of interest to the IETF
      community will be documented.</t>

      <t>Native dual stack trials depend on the upgrade and enablement of
      Cable Modem Termination Systems [CMTS] to support IPv6. A CMTS is a
      device that end users in a cable network connect directly to using their
      cable modem [CM]. As with IPv4, native support for IPv6 is critical for
      the delivery of services to end users in a DOCSIS network. Anything less
      could yield an undesirable end user experience or instability in the
      operator network that could adversely impact larger populations of
      users.</t>

      <t>Given the CMTS requirements, native dual stack trials have initially
      been limited to specific areas of the network. Further, where CMTS
      platforms have been upgraded and enabled to support IPv6 end users have
      been incrementally enabled with support for IPv6. Again this is to
      ensure a controlled introduction with a specific focus on maintaining
      stability. Initially, a limited combination of cable modem and IGD
      devices are being used to support trial activities. Over time diversity
      for both cable modem and IGDs are expected to grow. To date a number of
      cable modems support the ability to enable native dual stack
      connectivity to CPEs devices behind them. A subset of pre-DOCSIS 3.0 and
      all DOCSIS 3.0 devices support this capability. The population of DOCSIS
      devices that support these capabilities varies from operator to
      operator.</t>

      <t>Trial enablement requires the stateful provisioning of an IGD using
      stateful DHCPv6 [RFC3315] for the IGD WAN interface and delegated
      prefixes [RFC3633] for LAN side connectivity. Similarly, trial supported
      direct attachment of IPv6 capable CPE devices to the CM. In this
      configuration the CPE is provisioned with one or more IPv6 addresses via
      stateful DHCPv6 [RFC3315] in similar fashion to the IGD WAN interface.
      The quantity of devices supporting a native dual stack mode of operation
      is growing. While some devices are upgradable to support native dual
      stack many devices deployed today are not upgradable to support this
      functionality. Early implementations of devices or devices that are
      upgradable to support native IPv6 were found to only require and/or
      support the use of an IPv6 /64 for LAN side connectivity. This has been
      an acceptable mode of operation, however, over time IGDs will be
      required to support more advanced functionality including the ability to
      support multiple, routed IPv6 LANs. While support for a single IPv6 /64
      is in place today support for shorter IPv6 prefixes is also supported.
      It is important for operators to ensure they design and plan support
      across their infrastructures for delegated prefixes that are shorter
      than /64.</t>

      <figure anchor="_comcat_native_dual_stack"
              title="Comcast Native Dual Stack">
        <artwork><![CDATA[



    +-------------------------------------------------------------+
    |                           Internet                          |
    +-------+---------------------+---------------------+---------+
                                  | Native Dual Stack
                                  |
                          +-------+--------+
                          |                |
                          |    Router      |
                          |                |
                          +---+---+----+---+
                                  |
                                  | Native Dual Stack
                                  |
                      +-----------+------------+
                      |   Cable Modem          |
                      |   Termination System   |
        '''''''''''''''   (CMTS)               '''''''''''''
        |             +------------------------+           |
        |                                                  |
        |                                                  |
     +--+---+                                           +--+---+
     |      | Cable                                     |      | Cable
     +--+---+ Modem                                     +--+---+ Modem
     +--+---+                                              |
     |      | IGD     <----Native IPv4 and IPv6---->       |
     +--+---+                                              |
       ,+.                                                ,+.
      (   )   Computer                                   (   ) Computer 
       `-'    (CPE)                                       `-'  (CPE)]]></artwork>
      </figure>
    </section>

    <section title="Dual Stack Lite">
      <t>Part of Comcast's trial plans includes the trialing of Dual Stack
      Lite. At this time trial planning for the same is underway. While
      Comcast plans on trialing Dual Stack Lite there are no plans at this
      time to deploy Dual Stack Lite beyond a limited technology trial.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="_content" title="Content and Services">
      <t>During early phases of our trials Comcast leveraged reverse proxies
      to expedite the availability of content natively over IPv6. Open source
      technology running on Linux based servers was used to enable the reverse
      proxies. To ensure that the origin content, which is IPv4 only, is
      available natively over IPv6 the proxy servers required native dual
      stack connectivity. This model allowed us to ensure that Internet facing
      access to Comcast content occurred natively over IPv6.</t>

      <t>As third party CDNs introduce production quality support for IPv6 we
      plan to move away from the use of proxy servers and fully towards native
      dual stack for Comcast content and services. Native dual stack content
      is but the first step to ensure the same can be IPv6 only at some point
      in the future. Observations from Comcast's participation in World IPv6
      day suggest it is premature to rely on IPv6-only content at this
      time</t>

      <t>Further as part of our trials Comcast has also recently enabled IPv6
      Message Transfer Agents (MTA), in a limited fashion, to allow a subset
      of Comcast trial users to send electronic mail using SMTP over IPv6..
      Due to the limited availability of spam mitigation for IPv6 Comcast
      trials does not include the receipt of electronic mail over IPv6. In
      order to enable the receipt of electronic mail over IPv6 spam mitigation
      must be in place.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="_backoffice" title="Backoffice">
      <t>We made the decision early on in our design discussions to move all
      systems to a dual-stack design since we felt that this was the best way
      to transition to IPv6. The re-architect of many core systems like DNS,
      DHCP, OSS/BSS, and Billing systems took many years to plan and complete
      and this approach has paid off and allowed us to rapidly move towards
      support for dual-stack at the edge of our network, including support for
      our customers devices.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="_worldipv6" title="World IPv6 Day">
      <t>During World IPv6 day, Comcast observed a significant increase in
      native IPv6 traffic once content providers enabled AAAA records for
      their websites. The resulting traffic has continued to increase even
      after World IPv6 when about 50% of the websites that participated in
      World IPv6 Day left their AAAA records enabled after the day. We view
      this as a positive sign for continuing to drive more IPv6 traffic.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="_conclusion" title="Conclusion">
      <t>To date Comcast trial activities have yielded important, useful
      information about the various technologies that are available to
      facilitate the transition to IPv6. Observations and experience to date
      confirms that native dual stack is the preferred approach to transition
      to IPv6, where possible. While the various tunneling technologies are
      indeed straightforward to deploy there are a number of variables that
      must be considered when planning to deploy the same.</t>

      <t>Support for native dual stack continues to evolve across various
      broadband technologies and within consumer electronics. As evidenced by
      World IPv6 Day many of the world's largest content providers are also
      making progress with their IPv6 capabilities.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>This document makes no request of IANA.</t>

      <t>Note to RFC Editor: this section may be removed on publication as an
      RFC.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>There are no security considerations at this time.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>Thanks to the Comcast team supporting the various trial and
      production deployment activities:</t>

      <t><list style="empty">
          <t>Jonathan Boyer</t>

          <t>Chris Griffiths</t>

          <t>Tom Klieber</t>

          <t>Yiu Lee</t>

          <t>Jason Livingood</t>

          <t>Anthony Veiga</t>

          <t>Joel Warburton</t>

          <t>Richard Woundy</t>
        </list></t>
    </section>

    <!-- appendix -->
  </middle>

  <!-- END MIDDLE SECTION -->

  <!-- BACK SECTION -->

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      &RFC2119;
    </references>

    <section title="Document Change Log">
      <t>[RFC Editor: This section is to be removed before publication]</t>

      <t>-02: Grammatical items and re-wording of some sections. We have also
      added a new World IPv6 Day section.</t>

      <t>-01: Added C. Griffiths as co-author. Currently working on ascii art
      and several new sections.</t>

      <t>-00: First version published.</t>
    </section>
  </back>

  <!-- END BACK SECTION -->
</rfc>
<!-- FOR REFERENCE -->
<!-- less than is &lt -->
<!-- ampersand is &amp -->
<!-- apostrophe is &apos -->
<!-- quotation is &quot -->
