<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<?rfc strict="yes"?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<rfc category="info" docName="draft-howard-isp-ip6rdns-05"
     ipr="pre5378Trust200902" obsoletes="" submissionType="IETF" updates="">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="Reverse DNS in IPv6 for ISPs">Reverse DNS in IPv6 for
    Internet Service Providers</title>

    <author fullname="Lee Howard" initials="L" role="" surname="Howard">
      <organization>Time Warner Cable</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>13820 Sunrise Valley Drive</street>

          <city>Herndon</city>

          <region>VA</region>

          <code>20171</code>

          <country>US</country>
        </postal>

        <email>lee.howard@twcable.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date day="20" month="November" year="2012" />

    <area>Operations and Management</area>

    <workgroup>Internet Engineering Task Force</workgroup>

    <keyword>ipv6 rdns</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>In IPv4, Internet Service Providers (ISPs) commonly provide
      IN-ADDR.ARPA. information for their customers by prepopulating the zone
      with one PTR record for every available address. This practice does not
      scale in IPv6. This document analyzes different approaches for ISPs to
      manage the ip6.arpa zone for IPv6 address space assigned to many
      customers.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section anchor="intro" title="Introduction" toc="default">
      <t>Best practice <xref format="default" pageno="false"
      target="RFC1033"></xref> is that "Every Internet-reachable host should
      have a name"<xref format="default" pageno="false"
      target="RFC1912"></xref>that is recorded with a PTR resource record in
      the .ARPA zone. Many network services perform a PTR lookup on the source
      address of incoming packets before performing services.</t>

      <t>Some of the most common uses for reverse DNS include:</t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>Building trust. An administrator who spends time and effort
          properly maintaining DNS records might be assumed to spend time and
          effort on other maintenance, so the network might be more
          trustworthy.</t>

          <t>Validating other data. Information from reverse DNS may be
          compared to information higher in the stack (for instance, mail
          originator), with a lower trustworthiness if they are
          dissimilar.</t>

          <t>Some degree of location information can often be inferred, since
          most administrators create reverse zones corresponding to
          aggregation points, which often correspond with geographical areas.
          This information is useful for geolocation services and for law
          enforcement.</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>Individual Internet users in the residential or consumer scale,
      including small and home businesses, are constantly joining or moving on
      the Internet. For large Internet service providers who serve residential
      users, maintenance of individual PTR records is often impractical.
      Administrators at ISPs should evaluate methods for responding to reverse
      DNS queries in IPv6.</t>

      <section title="Reverse DNS in IPv4" toc="default">
        <t>ISPs that provide access to many residential users typically assign
        one or a few IPv4 addresses to each of those users, and populate an
        IN-ADDR.ARPA zone with one PTR record for every IPv4 address. Some
        ISPs also configure forward zones with matching A records, so that
        lookups match. For instance, if an ISP Example.com aggregated
        192.0.2.0/24 at a network hub in Anytown in the province of AnyWhere,
        the reverse zone might look like:</t>

        <t><list hangIndent="6" style="hanging">
            <t>1.2.0.192.IN-ADDR-ARPA. IN PTR
            1.user.anytown.AW.example.com.</t>

            <t>2.2.0.192.IN-ADDR-ARPA. IN PTR
            2.user.anytown.AW.example.com.</t>

            <t>3.2.0.192.IN-ADDR-ARPA. IN PTR
            3.user.anytown.AW.example.com.</t>

            <t>.</t>

            <t>.</t>

            <t>.</t>

            <t>254.2.0.192.IN-ADDR-ARPA. IN PTR
            254.user.anytown.AW.example.com.</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>The conscientious Example.com might then also have a zone:<list
            hangIndent="6" style="hanging">
            <t>1.user.anytown.AW.example.com. IN A 192.0.2.1</t>

            <t>2.user.anytown.AW.example.com. IN A 192.0.2.2</t>

            <t>3.user.anytown.AW.example.com. IN A 192.0.2.3</t>

            <t>.</t>

            <t>.</t>

            <t>.</t>

            <t>254.user.anytown.AW.example.com. IN A 192.0.2.254</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>Many ISPs generate PTR records for all IP addresses used for
        customers, and many create the matching A record.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Reverse DNS Considerations in IPv6" toc="default">
        <t>The length of individual addresses makes manual zone entries
        cumbersome. A sample entry for 2001:0db8:0f00:0000:0012:34ff:fe56:789a
        might be:</t>

        <t><list hangIndent="6" style="hanging">
            <t>a.9.8.7.6.5.e.f.f.f.4.3.2.1.0.0.0.0.0.0.0.0.f.0.8.b.d.0.1.0.0.2.IP6.ARPA.
            IN PTR 1.user.anytown.AW.example.com.</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>Since 2^^80 possible addresses could be configured in the
        2001:db8:f00/48 zone alone, it is impractical to write a zone with
        every possible address entered. If 1000 entries could be written per
        second, the zone would still not be complete after 38 trillion
        years.</t>

        <t>Furthermore, since the 64 bits in the host portion of the address
        are frequently assigned using SLAAC <xref format="default"
        pageno="false" target="RFC4862"></xref> when the host comes online, it
        is not possible to know which addresses may be in use ahead of
        time.</t>

        <t><xref format="default" pageno="false" target="RFC1912"></xref>is an
        informational document that says "PTR records must point back to a
        valid A record" and further that the administrator should "Make sure
        your PTR and A records match."<xref format="default" pageno="false"
        target="RFC1912"></xref> DNS administrators of residential ISPs should
        consider how to follow this advice for AAAA and PTR RRs in the
        residential ISP.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Alternatives in IPv6" toc="default">
      <t>Several options exist for providing reverse DNS in IPv6. All of these
      options also exist for IPv4, but the scaling problem is much less severe
      in IPv4. Each option should be evaluated for its scaling ability, its
      compliance with existing standards and best practices, and its
      availability in common systems.</t>

      <section title="No Response" toc="default">
        <t>Some ISP DNS administrators may choose to provide only a NXDomain
        response to PTR queries for subscriber addresses. Providing a negative
        response in response to PTR queries does not satisfy the expectation
        in<xref format="default" pageno="false" target="RFC1912"> </xref> for
        entries to match. Users of services which are dependent on a
        successful lookup will have a poor experience. For instance, some web
        services and SSH connections wait for a DNS response, even NXDOMAIN,
        before responding. DNS administrators should consider the uses for
        reverse DNS records and the number of services affecting the number of
        users when evaluating this option.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Wildcard match" toc="default">
        <t>The use of wildcards in the DNS is described in <xref
        format="default" pageno="false" target="RFC4592"></xref>, and their
        use in IPv6 reverse DNS is described in <xref format="default"
        pageno="false" target="RFC4472"></xref>.</t>

        <t>While recording all possible addresses is not scalable, it may be
        possible to record a wildcard entry for each prefix assigned to a
        customer. Consider also that "inclusion of wildcard NS RRSets in a
        zone is discouraged, but not barred. "<xref format="default"
        pageno="false" target="RFC4035"></xref></t>

        <t>This solution generally scales well. However, since the response
        will match any address in the wildcard range (/48, /56, /64, etc.), a
        forward DNS lookup on that response given will not be able to return
        the same hostname. This method therefore fails the expectation in
        <xref format="default" pageno="false" target="RFC1912"></xref> for
        forward and reverse to match. DNSsec <xref format="default"
        pageno="false" target="RFC4035"></xref> scalability is limited to
        signing the wildcard zone, which may be satisfactory.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Dynamic DNS" toc="default">
        <t>One way to ensure forward and reverse records match is for hosts to
        update DNS servers dynamically, once interface configuration (whether
        SLAAC, DHCPv6, or other means) is complete, as described in<xref
        format="default" pageno="false" target="RFC4472"> </xref>. Hosts would
        need to provide both AAAA and PTR updates, and would need to know
        which servers would accept the information.</t>

        <t>This option should scale as well or as poorly as IPv4 dynamic DNS
        does. Dynamic DNS may not scale effectively in large ISP networks
        which have no single master name server. The ISP's DNS system may
        provide a point for Denial of Service attacks, including many
        attempted dDNS updates. Accepting updates only from authenticated
        sources may mitigate this risk, but only if authentication itself does
        not require excessive overhead. No authentication of dynamic DNS
        updates is inherently provided; implementers should consider use of
        TSIG<xref format="default" pageno="false" target="RFC2845"> </xref>,
        or at least ingress filtering so updates are only accepted from
        customer address space from internal network interfaces, and consider
        impacts on scalability. UDP is allowed per <xref format="default"
        pageno="false" target="RFC2136"> </xref> so transmission control is
        not assured, though the host should expect an ERROR or NOERROR message
        from the server <xref format="default" pageno="false"
        target="RFC2136"> </xref>; TCP provides transmission control, but the
        updating host would need to be configured to use TCP.</t>

        <t>Administrators should consider what domain will contain the
        records, and who will provide the names. If subscribers provide
        hostnames, they may provide inappropriate strings. Consider
        "ihate.example.com" or "badword.customer.example.com" or
        "celebrityname.committed.illegal.acts.example.com."</t>

        <section title="Dynamic DNS from Individual Hosts" toc="default">
          <t>In the simplest case, a residential user will have a single host
          connected to the ISP. Since the typical residential user cannot
          configure IPv6 addresses and resolving name servers on their hosts,
          the ISP should provide address information conventionally (i.e.,
          their normal combination of RAs, DHCP, etc.), and should provide a
          DNS Recursive Name Server and Domain Search List as described in
          <xref format="default" pageno="false" target="RFC3646"></xref> or
          <xref target="RFC6106"></xref>. In determining its Fully Qualified
          Domain Name, a host will typically use a domain from the Domain
          Search List. This is an overloading of the parameter; multiple
          domains could be listed, since hosts may need to search for
          unqualified names in multiple domains, without necessarily being a
          member of those domains. Administrators should consider whether the
          domain search list actually provides an appropriate DNS suffix(es)
          when considering use of this option. For purposes of dynamic DNS,
          the host would concatenate its local hostname (e.g., "hostname")
          plus the domain(s) in the Domain Search List (e.g.,
          "customer.example.com"), as in "hostname.customer.example.com."</t>

          <t>Once it learns its address, and has a resolving name server, the
          host must perform an SOA lookup on the ip6.arpa record to be added,
          to find the owner, which will lead to the SOA record. Several
          recursive lookups may be required to find the longest prefix which
          has been delegated. The DNS administrator must designate the Primary
          Master Server for the longest match required. Once found, the host
          sends dynamic AAAA and PTR updates using the concatenation defined
          above ("hostname.customer.example.com").</t>

          <t>In order to use this alternative, hosts must be configured to use
          dynamic DNS. This is not default behavior for many hosts, which is
          an inhibitor for the large ISP. This option may be scalable,
          although registration following an outage may cause signficant load,
          and hosts using privacy extensions <xref target="RFC4941"></xref>
          may update records daily. It is up to the host to provide matching
          forward and reverse records, and to update them when the address
          changes.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Dynamic DNS through Residential Gateways"
                 toc="default">
          <t>Residential customers may have a gateway, which may provide
          DHCPv6 service to hosts from a delegated prefix. ISPs should provide
          a DNS Recursive Name Server and Domain Search List to the gateway,
          as described above and in<xref format="default" pageno="false"
          target="RFC3646"> </xref> and <xref target="RFC6106"></xref>. There
          are two options for how the gateway uses this information. The first
          option is for the gateway to respond to DHCPv6 requests with the
          same DNS Recursive Name Server and Domain Search List provided by
          the ISP. The alternate option is for the gateway to relay dynamic
          DNS updates from hosts to the servers and domain provided by the
          ISP. Host behavior is unchanged; they should provide updates to the
          ISP's servers as described above.</t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="dDNSdelg" title="Dynamic DNS Delegations"
                 toc="default">
          <t>An ISP may delegate authority for a subdomain such as
          "customer12345.anytown.AW.customer.example.com" or
          "customer12345.example.com" to the customer's gateway. Each domain
          thus delegated must be unique within the DNS. The ISP may also then
          delegate the ip6.arpa zone for the prefix delegated to the customer,
          as in (for 2001:db8:f00::/48) "0.0.f.0.8.b.d.0.1.0.0.2.ip6.arpa."
          Then the customer could provide updates to their own gateway, with
          forward and reverse. However, individual hosts connected directly to
          the ISP rarely have the capability to run DNS for themselves;
          therefore, an ISP can only delegate to customers with gateways
          capable of being authoritative name servers. If a device requests a
          DHCPv6 Prefix Delegation, that may be considered a reasonably
          reliable indicator that it is a gateway, rather than an individual
          host. It is not necessarily an indicator that the gateway is capable
          of providing DNS services, and therefore cannot be relied upon as a
          way to test whether this option is feasible.</t>

          <t>If the customer's gateway is the name server, it provides its own
          information to hosts on the network, as normally done for enterprise
          networks, and as described in <xref format="default" pageno="false"
          target="RFC2136"></xref>.</t>

          <t>An ISP may elect to provide authoritative responses as a
          secondary server to the customer's primary server.</t>

          <t>To implement this alternative, users' residential gateways must
          be capable of acting as authoritative name servers capable of
          dynamic DNS updates. There is no mechanism for an ISP to dynamically
          communicate to a user's equipment that a zone has been delegated, so
          user action would be required. Most users have neither the equipment
          nor the expertise to run DNS servers, so this option is unavailable
          to the residential ISP.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Generate Dynamic Records " toc="default">
          <t>An ISP's name server that receives a dynamic forward or reverse
          DNS update may create a matching entry. Since a host capable of
          updating one is generally capable of updating the other, this should
          not be required, but redundant record creation will ensure a record
          exists. ISPs implementing this method should check whether a record
          already exists before accepting or creating updates.</t>

          <t>This method is also dependent on hosts being capable of providing
          dynamic DNS updates, which is not default behavior for many
          hosts.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Populate from DHCP Server" toc="default">
          <t>A ISP's DHCPv6 server may populate the forward and reverse zones
          when the DHCP request is received, if the request contains enough
          information. <xref format="default" pageno="false"
          target="RFC4704"></xref></t>

          <t>However, this method will only work for a single host address
          (IA_NA); the ISP's DHCP server would not have enough information to
          update all records for a prefix delegation. If the zone authority is
          delegated to a home gateway which used this method, the gateway
          could update records for residential hosts. To implement this
          alternative, users' residential gateways would have to support the
          FQDN DHCP option, and would have to either have the zones
          configured, or send dDNS messages to the ISP's name server.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Populate from RADIUS Server" toc="">
          <t>A user may receive an address or prefix from a RADIUS <xref
          target="RFC2865"></xref> server, the details of which may be
          recorded via RADIUS Accounting <xref target="RFC2866"></xref> data.
          The ISP may populate the forward and reverse zones from the
          accounting data if it contains enough information. This solution
          allows the ISP to populate data concerning allocated prefixes (as
          per 2.2 (wildcards)) and CPE endpoints, but as with 2.3.5 does not
          allow the ISP to populate information concerning individual
          hosts.</t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section title="Delegate DNS " toc="default">
        <t>For customers who are able to run their own DNS servers, such as
        commercial customers, often the best option is to delegate the reverse
        DNS zone to them, as described in <xref format="default"
        pageno="false" target="RFC2317"></xref> (for IPv4). However, since
        most residential users have neither the equipment nor the expertise to
        run DNS servers, this method is unavailable to residential ISPs.</t>

        <t>This is a general case of the specific case described in<xref
        format="default" pageno="false" target="dDNSdelg"> </xref>. All of the
        same considerations still apply.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Dynamically Generate PTR When Queried (&quot;On the Fly&quot;)"
               toc="default">
        <t>Common practice in IPv4 is to provide PTR records for all
        addresses, regardless of whether a host is actually using the address.
        In IPv6, ISPs may generate PTR records for all IPv6 addresses as the
        records are requested. Configuring records "on the fly" may consume
        more processor resource than other methods, but only on demand. A
        denial of service is therefore possible, which may be mitigated with
        rate-limiting and normal countermeasures.</t>

        <t>An ISP using this option should generate a PTR record on demand,
        and cache or prepopulate the forward (AAAA) entry for the duration of
        the time-to-live of the PTR. This option has the advantage of assuring
        matching forward and reverse entries, while being simpler than dynamic
        DNS. Administrators should consider whether the lack of user-specified
        hostnames is a drawback.</t>

        <t>This method may not scale well in conjunction with DNSsec <xref
        format="default" pageno="false" target="RFC4035"></xref>, because of
        the additional load, but since keys may be pregenerated for zones, and
        not for each record, the risk is moderate. Unsigned records can
        indicate that these records are less trusted, which might be
        acceptable.</t>

        <t>Another consideration is that the algorithm used for generating the
        record must be the same on all servers for a zone. In other words, any
        server for the zone must produce the same response for a given query.
        Administrators managing a variety of rules within a zone might find it
        difficult to keep those rules synchronized on all servers.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Recommendations">
      <t>The best accuracy would be achieved if ISPs delegate authority along
      with address delegation. Where users do not operate authoritative name
      servers, dynamic DNS updates can provide accurate data, if user hosts
      support it, and if it scales. Where dynamic DNS is impractical, an ISP
      has no knowledge of hostnames, and therefore can either provide a
      wildcard response or a dynamically generated response. It may be noted
      that some ISPs currently provide a negative response for PTR queries for
      IPv6 addresses.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Security Considerations" toc="default">
      <section title="Using Reverse DNS for Security" toc="default">
        <t>Some people think the existence of reverse DNS records, or matching
        forward and reverse DNS records, provides useful information about the
        hosts with those records. For example, one might infer that the
        administrator of a network with properly configured DNS records was
        better-informed, and by further inference more responsible, than the
        administrator of a less-thoroughly configured network. For instance,
        most email providers will not accept incoming connections on port 25
        unless forward and reverse DNS entries match. If they match, but
        information higher in the stack (for instance, mail source) is
        inconsistent, the packet is questionable. These records may be easily
        forged though, unless DNSsec or other measures are taken. The string
        of inferences is questionable, and may become unneeded if other means
        for evaluating trustworthiness (such as positive reputations) become
        predominant in IPv6.</t>

        <t>Providing location information in PTR records is useful for
        troubleshooting, law enforcement, and geolocation services, but for
        the same reasons can be considered sensitive information.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="DNS Security with Dynamic DNS" toc="default">
        <t>Security considerations of using dynamic DNS are described in <xref
        format="default" pageno="false" target="RFC3007"></xref>. DNS Security
        Extensions are documented in<xref format="default" pageno="false"
        target="RFC4033"> </xref>.</t>

        <t>Interactions with DNSsec are described throughout this
        document.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Considerations for Other Uses of the DNS" toc="default">
        <t>Several methods exist for providing encryption keys in the DNS. Any
        of the options presented here may interfere with these key
        techniques.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>The author would like to thank Alain Durand, JINMEI Tatuya, David
      Freedman, Andrew Sullivan, Chris Griffiths, Darryl Tanner, Ed Lewis,
      John Brzozowski, Chris Donley, Wes George, Jason Weil, John Spence, Ted
      Lemon, and Chris Roosenraad.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="IANA Considerations" toc="default">
      <t>There are no IANA considerations or implications that arise from this
      document.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <reference anchor="RFC1033">
        <front>
          <title>Domain Administrators Operators Guide</title>

          <author initials="M." surname="Lottor">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date month="November" year="1987" />
        </front>

        <format target="http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc1033" type="HTML" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RFC1912">
        <front>
          <title>Common DNS Operational and Configuration Errors</title>

          <author initials="D" surname="Barr">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date month="February" year="1996" />
        </front>

        <format target="http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc1912" type="HTML" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RFC2136">
        <front>
          <title>Dynamic Updates in the Domain Name System (DNS
          UPDATE)</title>

          <author initials="P" role="editor" surname="Vixie">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author initials="S" surname="Thomson">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author initials="Y" surname="Rekhter">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author initials="J" surname="Bound">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date month="April" year="1917" />
        </front>

        <format target="http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc2136" type="HTML" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RFC2845">
        <front>
          <title>Secret Key Transaction Authentication for DNS (TSIG)</title>

          <author>
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date />
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RFC2865" target="">
        <front>
          <title> Remote Authentication Dial In User Service (RADIUS)</title>

          <author>
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date />
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RFC2866">
        <front>
          <title>RADIUS Accounting</title>

          <author>
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date />
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RFC3007">
        <front>
          <title>Secure Domain Name System (DNS) Dynamic Update</title>

          <author initials="B" surname="Wellington">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date month="November" year="2000" />
        </front>

        <format target="http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc3007" type="HTML" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RFC3646">
        <front>
          <title>DNS Configuration options for Dynamic Host Configuration
          Protocol for IPv6 (DHCPv6)</title>

          <author initials="R" role="editor" surname="Droms">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date month="December" year="2003" />
        </front>

        <format target="http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc3646" type="HTML" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RFC4033">
        <front>
          <title>DNS Security Introduction and Requirements</title>

          <author>
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date />
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RFC4035">
        <front>
          <title>Protocol Modifications for the DNS Security
          Extensions</title>

          <author initials="R" surname="Arends">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author initials="R" surname="Austein">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author initials="M." surname="Larson">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author initials="D." surname="Massey">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author initials="S." surname="Rose">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date month="March" year="2005" />
        </front>

        <format target="http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc4035" type="HTML" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RFC4592">
        <front>
          <title>The Role of Wildcards in the Domain Name System</title>

          <author initials="E" surname="Lewis">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date month="July" year="2006" />
        </front>

        <format target="http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc4592" type="HTML" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RFC4704">
        <front>
          <title>The Dynamic Host Configuration Protocol for IPv6 (DHCPv6)
          Client Fully Qualified Domain Name (FQDN) Option</title>

          <author fullname="" initials="M" surname="Stapp">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="" initials="Y" surname="Volz">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="" initials="Y" surname="Rekhter">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date />
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RFC4862">
        <front>
          <title>IPv6 Stateless Address Autoconfiguration</title>

          <author initials="S" surname="Thomson">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author initials="T" surname="Narten">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author initials="T" surname="Jinmei">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date month="September" year="2007" />
        </front>

        <format target="http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc4826" type="HTML" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RFC6106">
        <front>
          <title>IPv6 Router Advertisement Options for DNS Configuration
          </title>

          <author>
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date />
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RFC4941">
        <front>
          <title>Privacy Extensions for Stateless Address Autoconfiguration in
          IPv6</title>

          <author>
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date />
        </front>
      </reference>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <reference anchor="RFC2317">
        <front>
          <title>Classless IN-ADDR.ARPA delegation</title>

          <author initials="H." surname="Eidnes">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author initials="G." surname="de Groot">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author initials="P." surname="Vixie">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date month="March" year="1998" />
        </front>

        <format target="http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc2317" type="HTML" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RFC2535">
        <front>
          <title>Domain Name System Security Extensions</title>

          <author initials="D." surname="Eastlake">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date month="March" year="1999" />
        </front>

        <format target="http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc2535" type="HTML" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RFC4472">
        <front>
          <title>Operational Considerations and Issues with IPv6 DNS</title>

          <author initials="A." surname="Durand">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author initials="J." surname="Ihren">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author initials="P." surname="Savola">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date month="April" year="2006" />
        </front>

        <format target="http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc4472" type="HTML" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="rmap-consider">
        <front>
          <title>draft-ietf-dnsop-reverse-mapping-considerations-06</title>

          <author initials="D." surname="Senie">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author initials="A." surname="Sullivan">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date month="March" year="2008" />
        </front>

        <format target="http://tools.ietf.org/html/draft-ietf-dnsop-reverse-mapping-considerations-06"
                type="HTML" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="inaddr-reqd">
        <front>
          <title>draft-ietf-dnsop-inaddr-required-07</title>

          <author initials="D." surname="Senie">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date month="August" year="2005" />
        </front>

        <format target="http://tools.ietf.org/html/draft-ietf-dnsop-inaddr-required-07"
                type="HTML" />
      </reference>
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
