<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [

<!ENTITY rfc1034 PUBLIC ''
       "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1034.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc1035 PUBLIC ''
       "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1035.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc1123 PUBLIC ''
       "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1123.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc2119 PUBLIC ''
       "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc2606 PUBLIC ''
       "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2606.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc3861 PUBLIC ''
       "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3861.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc4406 PUBLIC ''
       "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4406.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc4408 PUBLIC ''
       "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4408.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc4870 PUBLIC ''
       "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4870.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc4871 PUBLIC ''
       "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4871.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc5226 PUBLIC ''
       "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5226.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc5518 PUBLIC ''
       "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5518.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc5617 PUBLIC ''
       "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5617.xml">
]>

<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>

<!-- Try to enforce the ID-nits conventions and DTD validity -->
<?rfc strict="no" ?>

<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<!-- If "yes" eliminates blank lines before main section entries. -->
<?rfc tocdepth="2"?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>

<!-- Expand crefs and put them inline -->
<?rfc comments='yes' ?>
<?rfc inline='yes' ?>

<!-- RFC references as names, not numbers -->
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>

<!-- When yes, insert editing marks: editing marks consist of a
     string such as <29> printed in the blank line at the
     beginning of each paragraph of text. -->
<?rfc editing="no" ?>

<rfc ipr="trust200902" docName="draft-levine-dbr-00"
	 category="std" updates="5518">
  <front>
	<title>
	   Discard by Reference
        </title>

    <author fullname="John R. Levine" initials="J.L."
			 surname="Levine" >
         <organization>Taughannock Networks</organization>
         <address>
            <postal>
               <street>PO Box 727</street>
               <city>Trumansburg</city>
               <code>14886</code>
               <region>NY</region>
            </postal>
            <email>standards@taugh.com</email>
         </address>
      </author>
    <date month="June" year="2010" />

    <abstract>
      <t>Domains can authenticate their outgoing mail using DKIM or
	other techniques. In some cases where miscreants frequently
	use a domain without authorization in the Author address in
	e-mail messages, it may be prudent for recipient mail systems
	to discard unauthenticated mail as likely to be fraudulent.
	This specification defines an extension to Vouch by Reference
	(VBR) that allows a certifier to identify such domains, and
	that recipients can use either in conjunction with or
	independently of VBR.
      </t>
    </abstract>

  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t><xref target="RFC5518">Vouch by Reference</xref> allows a
	third party certifier to certify the owner of a domain name
	that is associated with received mail.  In typical usage, a
	recipient uses VBR to identify mail from known reliable
	senders so it can can bypass spam filters.</t>
      <t>A few domains, such as those of banks and online greeting cards,
	are frequently used without authorization
	in unwanted "phish" messages, intended
	to trick recipients into revealing personal information, to
	render messages that include malware installers, or other
	undesirable actions.
	If a domain can authenticate all of its outgoing mail using
	<xref target="RFC4871">DKIM</xref>
	or other means, any unsigned message is likely to be unauthorized,
	give or take the possibility that a legitimate message could fail
	authentication due to the known shortcomings of authentication
	systems.
	For a limited number of domains, if the domain is indeed frequently
	used without authorization,
	the domain does authenticate all its mail, its mail is
	likely to be received in ways that don't make authentication fail,
	and the cost of losing a legitimate message is relatively low, the
	overall harm to recipients could be minimized by discarding
	unauthenticated messages.
      </t>
      <t>Since they are already evaluating the domains' practices, third
	party certifiers are well positioned to evaluate the suitability
	of domains for a policy of discarding unauthenticated messages.
	This document specifies a method for publishing discard advice
	as an extension to VBR.
      </t>
      <t>
        <list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="Requirements Notation:  "> The key words "MUST", "MUST
            NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT",
            "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be
            interpreted as described in <xref target="RFC2119" />
          </t>
        </list>
      </t>
    </section>  <!-- end of intro -->

    <section anchor="ident" title="Author Domain Identity and Authentication">
      <t>
	Although an e-mail message potentially is associated with
	a variety of domains, this specification
	imports the term Author Domain from Section 2 of
	<xref target="RFC5617">ADSP</xref>.
	The identity on which the discard advice is based is the Author
	Domain.
      </t>
      <t>Section 7 of <xref target="RFC5518">VBR</xref> specifies the
	methods that a recipient can use to obtain an accountable domain
	for a message, for use with VBR.
	If a message has an accountable domain that is the same as the
	Author Domain, the message is Author Authenticated.
	If there is no such accountable domain, the message is 
	not Author Authenticated.
      </t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="pub" title="Publication of Discard Advice">
      <t>Section 5 of <xref target="RFC5518">VBR</xref> specifies
	the DNS query to look up the certification status of a domain.
	This specification extends the semantics of that query to include
	a check for discard advice.
	If, for example, a message had an Author Domain of somebank.example,
	and a certifier's domain were certifier-a.example, the recipient
	would make a DNS query for a TXT record at:	
      </t>
      <t>	
	somebank.example._vouch.certifier-a.example
      </t>
      <t>
      (Note that the Author Domain may or may not be the same domain
      as a VBR accountable domain for the message.)
      </t>
      <t>
	Section 6 of  <xref target="RFC5518">VBR</xref> specifies the
	types of message content that a certifier can vouch for, as
	a space-separated
	list of lower case text strings placed in the TXT record.
	The discard advice is also placed in the same text record as
	lower case strings.
	The strings for types of message content are disjoint from those
	for discard advice, and VBR clients MUST ignore unknown strings, so
	the contents of the TXT records remain unambiguous, and usable
	by pure VBR clients.
      </t>
  
      <section anchor="terms" title="Terms for discard advice">
      <t>
	This specification defines the following string for discard advice.
      </t>
      <t>
      <list style="hanging">
	<t hangText="discardable -">
	  Discard the message if it is not Author Authenticated.
	</t>
      </list>
      </t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="lookup" title="Checking for Discard Advice">
      <t>A receiver performs the following steps:
      </t>
      <t>
      <list style='numbers'>
	<t>Extract the Author Domain from the message.
	</t>
	<t>Check to see whether the message is Author Authenticated.
	  If it is, stop.  The advice for Author Authenticated
	  messages is always not to discard them.
	</t>
	<t>It the message is not Author Authenticated,
	  fetch the VBR record for the Author Domain for the desired
	  certifier, as described in <xref target="pub" />.  If the
	  DNS lookup fails (NXDOMAIN or NODATA status in the DNS
	  response), stop. The certifier offers no discard advice for
	  the domain.
	</t>

	<t>Check the TXT record for the terms in <xref target="terms"
	  />.  If the record includes "discardable", the advice is to
	  discard the message.
	</t>
      </list>
      </t>
    </section>

    <section title="Certifier Considerations">

      <section title="What Domains are Appropriate for Discard Advice">

	<t>A certifier should only publish advice to discard a
	  domain's mail after careful analysis, since doing so
	  increases the risk that a valid message will not be
	  delivered to a recipient that desired to receive it.</t>

	<t>Is all of the domain's mail sent directly from the domain's
	  own servers?  If mail can legitmately be sent any other way,
	  it is likely that there will be legitimate mail that is not
	  authenticated.  Common situations where mail is sent from
	  other servers include roaming users sending through hotel
	  networks, users who consolidate multiple mailboxes using a
	  Web mail system, and mail sent through mailing lists.</t>

	<t>Does the domain have individual users composing messages by
	  hand, or is all of the mail generated by software?  Experience
	  suggests that individual users are far more likely to send
	  legitmate mail that is not authenticated.</t>

	<t>Is all of the domain's mail transactional notifications?
	  For some domains, all mail reports the status of
	  an account or transaction, such as "we shipped your order"
	  or "your bank statement is available." These messages
	  typically direct the recipient to look at a Web
	  site with complete information about the transaction or
	  account. The risk from discarding mail from these domains
	  is relatively limited.  Since the intended recipient can
	  always recover the information in a lost message by visiting
	  the Web site, no information is lost, just delayed, if a message
	  is not received.
	</t>

	<t>Is the domain a significant phishing target?  Some domains
	  appear in e-mail without authorization far more often than
	  others. If a domain rarely appears in e-mail without
	  authorization in the first place, it is relatively unlikely
	  that an unsigned message is fraudulent rather than being a
	  legitimate message. In that case it would be unwise to
	  discard unsigned messages, since those messages are likely
	  to be legitimate. On the other hand, if a domain is used
	  without authorization in large numbers of messages, it is
	  much more likely that an unsigned message is fraudulent.
	</t>

	</section>

      <section title="Selection of Authentication Methods">
	<t>A certifier SHOULD document the authentication method or
	  methods that
	  it expects to be used by the domains for which it publishes
	  discard advice.  Recipients SHOULD interpret discard
	  advice relative to those methods.  If a certifer documents
	  more than one method, such as DK and DKIM, Author Authenticated
	  mail can be
	  authenticated by any of those methods.  (This could be the case
	  if a domain were migrating from DomainKeys to DKIM, and signs
	  some of its mail with one and some with the other.</t>
	
      </section>
      <section title="Certification and Discard Advice for the Same Domain ">
	<t>A certifier may wish to certify a domain's mail,
	  and also publish discard advice for that domain.
	  A likely example would be a financial organization that sends
	  authenticated transactional mail, and is also a major phishing
	  target.  In that case, the certifier vouches for the domain's
	  authenticated mail, and advises recipients to discard
	  unauthenticated mail.
	  The certifier's VBR record for that domain would contain:
	</t>
	<t>
	  transaction discardable
	</t>
	<t>
	  Note the recipients can use only the certification, only the discard
	  advice, or both.
	</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Receiver Considerations">
      <t>The steps for checking discard advice and for checking VBR
	certification are different, even though a receiver may do both
	for the same message, and fetch the same VBR record from the DNS
	for both. Most notably, while receivers only do VBR checks for
	messages that contain a VBR-Info header field, they need to make
	discard advice checks for any message that is not Author Authenticated,
	since it is unlikely that miscreants will add VBR-Info header fields.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>This document makes no requests to IANA.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>Discarding any incoming mail introduces a risk of losing
	legitimate messages.  A mail system that uses discard advice
	should carefully weigh the relative risk of lost messages
	against that of delivering mail containing phishes or malware.
      </t>
      <t>VBR and discard advice by their design delegate part of a
	mail system's management to a third party, with the risk
	of mishandling mail if the third party is incompetent or
	malicious.  Before making such a delegation, a system's
	management SHOULD satisify itself that the third party's
	advice is of acceptable quality.
      </t>
    </section>

  </middle>

  <!--  *****BACK MATTER ***** -->

  <back>

      <!-- &rfc1034;	Domain names - concepts -->
      <!-- &rfc1035;	Domain names - implementation and specification -->
    <references title="Normative References">
      &rfc2119; <!-- requirements notation -->
      &rfc4871;	<!-- DKIM -->
      &rfc5518;	<!-- VBR -->
      &rfc5617;	<!-- DKIM ADSP -->

    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
	   
      &rfc4406; <!-- Sender ID -->
      &rfc4408; <!-- SPF -->
      &rfc4870;	<!-- DK -->
      &rfc5226;   <!-- IANA Considerations rules -->

    </references>    <!-- end of all references -->


  </back>
</rfc>
