<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?> 
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc iprnotified="no"?>
<?rfc strict="yes"?>

<rfc ipr="trust200902"
     docName="draft-ietf-opsawg-syslog-msg-mib-06.txt"
     category="std">

  <!--
  $Id: syslog-msg-mib.xml 3198 2009-08-13 19:50:43Z schoenw $
  -->

  <front>

    <title abbrev="SYSLOG-MSG-MIB">
      Definitions of Managed Objects for Mapping SYSLOG Messages to
      Simple Network Management Protocol (SNMP) Notifications
    </title>

    <author initials="J." surname="Schoenwaelder"
            fullname="Juergen Schoenwaelder">
      <organization>Jacobs University Bremen</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Campus Ring 1</street>
          <city>28725 Bremen</city>
          <country>Germany</country>
        </postal>
        <email>j.schoenwaelder@jacobs-university.de</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author initials="A." surname="Clemm"
            fullname="Alexander Clemm">
      <organization>Cisco Systems</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>170 West Tasman Drive</street>
          <city>San Jose, CA 95134-1706</city>
          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>
        <email>alex@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    
    <author initials="A." surname="Karmakar"
            fullname="Anirban Karmakar">
      <organization>Cisco Systems</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>170 West Tasman Drive</street>
          <city>San Jose, CA 95134-1706</city>
          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>
        <email>akarmaka@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    
    <date month="August" year="2009"/>
    
    <area>Operations and Management</area>
    
    <keyword>Network Management</keyword>
    <keyword>Simple Network Management Protocol</keyword>
    <keyword>SNMP</keyword>
    <keyword>Notifications</keyword>
    <keyword>Syslog</keyword>
    
    <abstract>
      <t>
        This memo defines a portion of the Management Information Base
        (MIB) for use with network management protocols in the
        Internet community. In particular, it defines a mapping of
        SYSLOG messages to Simple Network Management Protocol (SNMP)
        notifications.
      </t>
    </abstract>
    
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>
        SNMP <xref target="RFC3410"/> <xref target="RFC3411"/> and
        SYSLOG <xref target="RFC5424"/> are two widely used protocols
        to communicate event notifications. Although co-existence of
        several management protocols in one operational environment is
        possible, certain environments require that all event
        notifications are collected by a single system daemon such as
        a SYSLOG collector or an SNMP notification receiver via a
        single management protocol. In such environments, it is
        necessary to translate event notifications between management
        protocols.
      </t>
      <t>
        This document defines an SNMP MIB module to represent SYSLOG
        messages and to send SYSLOG messages as SNMP notifications to
        SNMP notification receivers.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section title="The Internet-Standard Management Framework">
      <t>
        For a detailed overview of the documents that describe the
        current Internet-Standard Management Framework, please refer
        to section 7 of RFC 3410 <xref target="RFC3410"/>
      </t>
      <t>
        Managed objects are accessed via a virtual information store,
        termed the Management Information Base or MIB. MIB objects are
        generally accessed through the Simple Network Management
        Protocol (SNMP). Objects in the MIB are defined using the
        mechanisms defined in the Structure of Management Information
        (SMI). This memo specifies a MIB module that is compliant to
        the SMIv2, which is described in STD 58, RFC 2578
        <xref target="RFC2578"/>, STD 58, RFC 2579
        <xref target="RFC2579"/> and STD 58, RFC 2580
        <xref target="RFC2580"/> .
      </t>
    </section>

    <section title="Conventions">
      <t>
        The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL",
        "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY",
        and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as
        described in <xref target="RFC2119"/>.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="overview" title="Overview">
      <t>
        SYSLOG messages are translated to SNMP by a SYSLOG-to-SNMP
        translator.  Such a translator acts as a SYSLOG collector
        <xref target="RFC5424"/> and implements a MIB module according
        to the SNMP architecture <xref target="RFC3411"/>. The
        translator might be tightly coupled to an SNMP agent or it
        might interface with an SNMP agent via a subagent protocol.
      </t>
      <t>
        After initialization, the SYSLOG-to-SNMP translator will
        listen for SYSLOG messages. On receiving a message, the
        message will be parsed to extract information as described in
        the MIB module. A conceptual table is populated with
        information extracted from the SYSLOG message and finally a
        notification may be generated.
      </t>
      <t>
        The MIB module is organized into a group of scalars and two
        tables. The syslogMsgControl group contains two scalars
        controlling the maximum size of SYSLOG messages recorded
        in the tables and whether SNMP notifications are generated
        for SYSLOG messages.
      </t>
      <figure>
        <artwork>
--syslogMsgObjects(1)
  |
  +--syslogMsgControl(1)
     |
     +-- Unsigned32 syslogMsgTableMaxSize(1)
     +-- TruthValue syslogMsgEnableNotifications(2)
        </artwork>
      </figure>
      <t>
        The syslogMsgTable contains one entry for each recorded SYSLOG
        message. The basic fields of SYSLOG messages as well as
        message properties are represented in different columns of the
        conceptual table.
      </t>
      <figure>
        <artwork>
--syslogMsgObjects(1)
  |
  +--syslogMsgTable(2)
     |
     +--syslogMsgEntry(1) [syslogMsgIndex]
        |
        +-- Unsigned32      syslogMsgIndex(1)
        +-- SyslogFacility  syslogMsgFacility(2)
        +-- SyslogSeverity  syslogMsgSeverity(3)
        +-- Unsigned32      syslogMsgVersion(4)
        +-- SyslogTimeStamp syslogMsgTimeStamp(5)
        +-- DisplayString   syslogMsgHostName(6)
        +-- DisplayString   syslogMsgAppName(7)
        +-- DisplayString   syslogMsgProcID(8)
        +-- DisplayString   syslogMsgMsgID(9)
        +-- Unsigned32      syslogMsgSDParams(10)
        +-- OctetString     syslogMsgMsg(11)
        </artwork>
      </figure>
      <t>
        The syslogMsgSDTable contains one entry for each structured
        data element parameter contained in a SYSLOG message. Since
        structured data elements are optional, the relationship
        between the syslogMsgTable and the syslogMsgSDTable ranges
        from one-to-zero to one-to-many.
      </t>
      <figure>
        <artwork>
--syslogMsgObjects(1)
  |
  +--syslogMsgSDTable(3)
     |
     +--syslogMsgSDEntry(1)       [syslogMsgIndex,
        |                          syslogMsgSDParamIndex,
        |                          syslogMsgSDID,
        |                          syslogMsgSDParamName]
        |
        +-- Unsigned32             syslogMsgSDParamIndex(1)
        +-- DisplayString          syslogMsgSDID(2)
        +-- DisplayString          syslogMsgSDParamName(3)
        +-- SyslogParamValueString syslogMsgSDParamValue(4)
        </artwork>
      </figure>
    </section>

    <section anchor="relationship" title="Relationship to Other MIB Modules">
      <t>
        The NOTIFICATION-LOG-MIB <xref target="RFC3014"/> provides a
        generic mechanism for logging SNMP notifications in order to
        deal with lost SNMP notifications, e.g., due to transient
        communication problems.  Applications can poll the
        notification log to verify that they have not missed important
        SNMP notifications.
      </t>
      <t>
        The MIB module defined in this memo provides a mechanism for
        logging SYSLOG notifications. This additional SYSLOG
        notification log is provided because (a) SYSLOG messages might
        not lead to SNMP notification (this is configurable) and (b)
        SNMP notifications might not carry all information associated
        with a SYSLOG notification.
      </t>
      <t>
        The MIB module IMPORTS objects from SNMPv2-SMI
        <xref target="RFC2578"/>, SNMPv2-TC <xref target="RFC2579"/>,
        SNMPv2-CONF <xref target="RFC2580"/>, SNMP-FRAMEWORK-MIB
        <xref target="RFC3411"/>, and SYSLOG-TC-MIB
        <xref target="RFC5427"/>.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="syslog" title="Relationship to the SNMP Notification to SYSLOG Mapping">
      <t>
        A companion document defines a mapping of SNMP notifications
        to SYSLOG messages
        <xref target="I-D.ietf-opsawg-syslog-snmp"/>.  This section
        discusses the possibilities of using both specifications in
        combination.
      </t>
      <t>
        A SYSLOG collector implementing the SYSLOG-MSG-MIB module and
        the mapping of SNMP notifications to SYSLOG messages may be
        configured to translate received SYSLOG messages containing
        SNMP notifications back into the original SNMP notification.
        In this case, the relevant tables of the SYSLOG-MSG-MIB will
        not be populated for SYSLOG messages carrying SNMP
        notifications. This configuration allows operators to build a
        forwarding chain where SNMP notifications are "tunneled"
        through SYSLOG messages. Due to size restrictions of the
        SYSLOG transports and the more verbose textual encoding used
        by SYSLOG, there is a possibility that SNMP notification
        content gets truncated while tunneled through SYSLOG and thus
        the resulting SNMP notification may be incomplete.
      </t>
      <t>
        An SNMP management application supporting the SYSLOG-MSG-MIB
        and the mapping of SNMP notifications to SYSLOG messages may
        process information from the SYSLOG-MSG-MIB in order to emit a
        SYSLOG message representing the SYSLOG message recorded in the
        SYSLOG-MSG-MIB module. This configuration allows operators to
        build a forwarding chain where SYSLOG messages are "tunneled"
        through SNMP messages. A notification receiver can determine
        whether a syslogMsgNotification contained all structured data
        element parameters of a SYSLOG message. In case parameters are
        missing, a forwarding application MUST retrieve the missing
        parameters from the SYSLOG-MSG-MIB. Regular polling of the
        SYSLOG-MSG-MIB can be used to take care of any lost SNMP
        notifications.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="definitions" title="Definitions">
      <figure>
        <artwork>
SYSLOG-MSG-MIB DEFINITIONS ::= BEGIN

IMPORTS
    MODULE-IDENTITY, OBJECT-TYPE, NOTIFICATION-TYPE, Unsigned32, mib-2
        FROM SNMPv2-SMI
    TEXTUAL-CONVENTION, DisplayString, TruthValue
        FROM SNMPv2-TC
    OBJECT-GROUP, NOTIFICATION-GROUP, MODULE-COMPLIANCE
        FROM SNMPv2-CONF
    SyslogFacility, SyslogSeverity
        FROM SYSLOG-TC-MIB;

syslogMsgMib MODULE-IDENTITY
    LAST-UPDATED "200908130800Z"
    ORGANIZATION "IETF OPSAWG Working Group"
    CONTACT-INFO
        "Juergen Schoenwaelder
         &lt;j.schoenwaelder@jacobs-university.de&gt;
         Jacobs University Bremen
         Campus Ring 1
         28757 Bremen
         Germany

         Alexander Clemm
         &lt;alex@cisco.com&gt;
         Cisco Systems
         170 West Tasman Drive
         San Jose, CA 95134-1706
         USA

         Anirban Karmakar
         &lt;akarmaka@cisco.com&gt;
         Cisco Systems
         170 West Tasman Drive
         San Jose, CA 95134-1706
         USA"
    DESCRIPTION
        "This MIB module represent SYSLOG messages as SNMP objects.

         Copyright (c) 2009 IETF Trust and the persons identified as
         the document authors.  All rights reserved.

         Redistribution and use in source and binary forms, with or
         without modification, are permitted provided that the
         following conditions are met:

         - Redistributions of source code must retain the above
           copyright notice, this list of conditions and the
           following disclaimer.

         - Redistributions in binary form must reproduce the above
           copyright notice, this list of conditions and the
           following disclaimer in the documentation and/or other
           materials provided with the distribution.

         - Neither the name of Internet Society, IETF or IETF
           Trust, nor the names of specific contributors, may be
           used to endorse or promote products derived from this
           software without specific prior written permission.

         THIS SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED BY THE COPYRIGHT HOLDERS AND
         CONTRIBUTORS 'AS IS' AND ANY EXPRESS OR IMPLIED
         WARRANTIES, INCLUDING, BUT NOT LIMITED TO, THE IMPLIED
         WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY AND FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR
         PURPOSE ARE DISCLAIMED.  IN NO EVENT SHALL THE COPYRIGHT
         OWNER OR CONTRIBUTORS BE LIABLE FOR ANY DIRECT, INDIRECT,
         INCIDENTAL, SPECIAL, EXEMPLARY, OR CONSEQUENTIAL DAMAGES
         (INCLUDING, BUT NOT LIMITED TO, PROCUREMENT OF SUBSTITUTE
         GOODS OR SERVICES; LOSS OF USE, DATA, OR PROFITS; OR
         BUSINESS INTERRUPTION) HOWEVER CAUSED AND ON ANY THEORY OF
         LIABILITY, WHETHER IN CONTRACT, STRICT LIABILITY, OR TORT
         (INCLUDING NEGLIGENCE OR OTHERWISE) ARISING IN ANY WAY OUT
         OF THE USE OF THIS SOFTWARE, EVEN IF ADVISED OF THE
         POSSIBILITY OF SUCH DAMAGE.

         This version of this MIB module is part of RFC XXXX; see
         the RFC itself for full legal notices."
    REVISION "200908130800Z"
    DESCRIPTION
        "Initial version issued as part of RFC XXXX."
-- RFC Ed.: replace XXXX with actual RFC number & remove this note
    ::= { mib-2 XXX }
-- RFC Ed.: replace XXX with IANA-assigned number & remove this note

-- textual convention definitions

SyslogTimeStamp ::= TEXTUAL-CONVENTION
    DISPLAY-HINT "2d-1d-1d,1d:1d:1d.3d,1a1d:1d"
    STATUS       current
    DESCRIPTION
       "A date-time specification. This type is similar to the
        DateAndTime type defined in the SNMPv2-TC except that
        the subsecond granulation is microseconds instead of
        deciseconds and that a zero-length string can be used
        to indicate a missing value.

        field  octets  contents                  range
        -----  ------  --------                  -----
          1      1-2   year*                     0..65536
          2       3    month                     1..12
          3       4    day                       1..31
          4       5    hour                      0..23
          5       6    minutes                   0..59
          6       7    seconds                   0..60
                       (use 60 for leap-second)
          7     8-10   microseconds              0..999999
          8      11    direction from UTC        '+' / '-'
          9      12    hours from UTC*           0..13
         10      13    minutes from UTC          0..59

        * Notes:
        - the value of year is in network-byte order
        - the value of microseconds is in network-byte order
        - daylight saving time in New Zealand is +13

        For example, Tuesday May 26, 1992 at 1:30:15 PM EDT would be
        displayed as:

                        1992-5-26,13:30:15.0,-4:0

        Note that if only local time is known, then timezone
        information (fields 11-13) is not present."
    SYNTAX      OCTET STRING (SIZE (0 | 10 | 13))

SyslogParamValueString ::= TEXTUAL-CONVENTION
    DISPLAY-HINT "65535t"
    STATUS       current
    DESCRIPTION
       "The value of a SYSLOG SD-PARAM is represented using the
        ISO/IEC IS 10646-1 character set, encoded as an octet string
        using the UTF-8 transformation format described in RFC3629.

        Since additional code points are added by amendments to the
        10646 standard from time to time, implementations must be
        prepared to encounter any code point from 0x00000000 to
        0x7fffffff.  Byte sequences that do not correspond to the
        valid UTF-8 encoding of a code point or are outside this
        range are prohibited. Similarly, overlong UTF-8 sequences
        are prohibited.

        UTF-8 may require multiple bytes to represent a single
        character / code point; thus the length of this object in
        octets may be different from the number of characters
        encoded.  Similarly, size constraints refer to the number of
        encoded octets, not the number of characters represented by
        an encoding."
    REFERENCE
       "RFC3629: UTF-8, a transformation format of ISO 10646"
    SYNTAX     OCTET STRING

-- object definitions

syslogMsgNotifications OBJECT IDENTIFIER ::= { syslogMsgMib 0 }
syslogMsgObjects       OBJECT IDENTIFIER ::= { syslogMsgMib 1 }
syslogMsgConformance   OBJECT IDENTIFIER ::= { syslogMsgMib 2 }

syslogMsgControl       OBJECT IDENTIFIER ::= { syslogMsgObjects 1 }

syslogMsgTableMaxSize OBJECT-TYPE
    SYNTAX      Unsigned32
    MAX-ACCESS  read-write
    STATUS      current
    DESCRIPTION
       "The maximum number of syslog messages that may be held in
        syslogMsgTable.  A particular setting does not guarantee that
        there is sufficient memory available for the maximum number
        of table entries indicated by this object. A value of 0 means
        no fixed limit.

        If an application reduces the limit while there are syslog
        messages in the syslogMsgTable, the syslog messages that are
        in the syslogMsgTable for the longest time MUST be discarded
        to bring the table down to the new limit.

        The value of this object should be kept in nonvolatile
        memory."
    DEFVAL      { 0 }
    ::= { syslogMsgControl 1 }

syslogMsgEnableNotifications OBJECT-TYPE
    SYNTAX      TruthValue
    MAX-ACCESS  read-write
    STATUS      current
    DESCRIPTION
       "Indicates whether syslogMsgNotification notifications are
        generated.

        The value of this object should be kept in nonvolatile
        memory."
    DEFVAL      { false }
    ::= { syslogMsgControl 2 }

syslogMsgTable OBJECT-TYPE
    SYNTAX      SEQUENCE OF SyslogMsgEntry
    MAX-ACCESS  not-accessible
    STATUS      current
    DESCRIPTION
       "A table containing recent syslog messages. The size of the
        table is controlled by the syslogMsgTableMaxSize object."
    ::= { syslogMsgObjects 2 }

syslogMsgEntry OBJECT-TYPE
    SYNTAX      SyslogMsgEntry
    MAX-ACCESS  not-accessible
    STATUS      current
    DESCRIPTION
       "An entry of the syslogMsgTable."
    INDEX { syslogMsgIndex }
    ::= { syslogMsgTable 1 }

SyslogMsgEntry ::= SEQUENCE {
    syslogMsgIndex      Unsigned32,
    syslogMsgFacility   SyslogFacility,
    syslogMsgSeverity   SyslogSeverity,
    syslogMsgVersion    Unsigned32,
    syslogMsgTimeStamp  SyslogTimeStamp,
    syslogMsgHostName   DisplayString,
    syslogMsgAppName    DisplayString,
    syslogMsgProcID     DisplayString,
    syslogMsgMsgID      DisplayString,
    syslogMsgSDParams   Unsigned32,
    syslogMsgMsg        OCTET STRING
}

syslogMsgIndex OBJECT-TYPE
    SYNTAX      Unsigned32 (1..4294967295)
    MAX-ACCESS  not-accessible
    STATUS      current
    DESCRIPTION
       "A monotonically increasing number used to identify entries in
        the syslogMsgTable. When syslogMsgIndex reaches the maximum
        value (4294967295) the value wraps back to 1.

        Applications periodically polling the syslogMsgTable for new
        entries should take into account that a complete rollover of
        syslogMsgIndex will happen if more than 4294967294 messages
        are received during a poll interval."
    ::= { syslogMsgEntry 1 }

syslogMsgFacility OBJECT-TYPE
    SYNTAX      SyslogFacility
    MAX-ACCESS  read-only
    STATUS      current
    DESCRIPTION
       "The facility of the syslog message."
    REFERENCE
       "RFC5424: The Syslog Protocol (section 6.2.1)
        RFC5427: Textual Conventions for Syslog Management"
    ::= { syslogMsgEntry 2 }

syslogMsgSeverity OBJECT-TYPE
    SYNTAX      SyslogSeverity
    MAX-ACCESS  read-only
    STATUS      current
    DESCRIPTION
       "The severity of the syslog message"
    REFERENCE
       "RFC5424: The Syslog Protocol (section 6.2.1)
        RFC5427: Textual Conventions for Syslog Management"
    ::= { syslogMsgEntry 3 }

syslogMsgVersion OBJECT-TYPE
    SYNTAX      Unsigned32 (0..999)
    MAX-ACCESS  read-only
    STATUS      current
    DESCRIPTION
       "The version of the syslog message. A value of 0 indicates
        that the version is unknown."
    REFERENCE
       "RFC5424: The Syslog Protocol (section 6.2.2)"
    ::= { syslogMsgEntry 4 }

syslogMsgTimeStamp OBJECT-TYPE
    SYNTAX      SyslogTimeStamp
    MAX-ACCESS  read-only
    STATUS      current
    DESCRIPTION
       "The timestamp of the syslog message. A zero length
        string is returned if the timestamp is unknown."
    REFERENCE
       "RFC5424: The Syslog Protocol (section 6.2.3)"
    ::= { syslogMsgEntry 5 }

syslogMsgHostName OBJECT-TYPE
    SYNTAX      DisplayString (SIZE (0..255))
    MAX-ACCESS  read-only
    STATUS      current
    DESCRIPTION
       "The hostname and the (optional) domain name of the syslog
        message. A zero-length string indicates an unknown hostname.
        The SYSLOG protocol specification constrains this string to
        printable US-ASCII code points."
    REFERENCE
       "RFC5424: The Syslog Protocol (section 6.2.4)"
    ::= { syslogMsgEntry 6 }

syslogMsgAppName OBJECT-TYPE
    SYNTAX      DisplayString (SIZE (0..48))
    MAX-ACCESS  read-only
    STATUS      current
    DESCRIPTION
       "The app-name of the syslog message. A zero-length string
        indicates an unknown app-name. The SYSLOG protocol
        specification constrains this string to printable US-ASCII
        code points."
    REFERENCE
       "RFC5424: The Syslog Protocol (section 6.2.5)"
    ::= { syslogMsgEntry 7 }

syslogMsgProcID OBJECT-TYPE
    SYNTAX      DisplayString (SIZE (0..128))
    MAX-ACCESS  read-only
    STATUS      current
    DESCRIPTION
       "The procid of the syslog message. A zero-length string
        indicates an unknown procid. The SYSLOG protocol specification
        constrains this string to printable US-ASCII code points."
    REFERENCE
       "RFC5424: The Syslog Protocol (section 6.2.6)"
    ::= { syslogMsgEntry 8 }

syslogMsgMsgID OBJECT-TYPE
    SYNTAX      DisplayString (SIZE (0..32))
    MAX-ACCESS  read-only
    STATUS      current
    DESCRIPTION
       "The msgid of the syslog message. A zero-length string
        indicates an unknown msgid. The SYSLOG protocol specification
        constrains this string to printable US-ASCII code points."
    REFERENCE
       "RFC5424: The Syslog Protocol (section 6.2.7)"
    ::= { syslogMsgEntry 9 }

syslogMsgSDParams OBJECT-TYPE
    SYNTAX      Unsigned32
    MAX-ACCESS  read-only
    STATUS      current
    DESCRIPTION
       "The total number of structured data element parameters
        carried in the syslog message. This number effectively
        indicates the number of entries in the syslogMsgSDTable.
        It can be used, for example, by a notification receiver
        to determine whether a notification carried all 
        structured data element parameters of a syslog message."
    ::= { syslogMsgEntry 10 }

syslogMsgMsg OBJECT-TYPE
    SYNTAX      OCTET STRING
    MAX-ACCESS  read-only
    STATUS      current
    DESCRIPTION
       "The message part of the syslog message. The syntax does not
        impose a size restriction. Implementations of this MIB module
        may truncate the message part of the syslog message such that
        it fits into the size constraints imposed by the implementation
        environment. Such truncations can also happen elsewhere in the
        syslog forwarding chain.

        If the first octets contain the value 'EFBBBF'h, then the rest
        of the message is a UTF-8 string. Since syslog messages may be
        truncated at arbitrary octet boundaries during forwarding, the
        message may contain invalid UTF-8 encodings at the end."
    REFERENCE
       "RFC5424: The Syslog Protocol (sections 6.1 and 6.4)"
    ::= { syslogMsgEntry 11 }

syslogMsgSDTable OBJECT-TYPE
    SYNTAX      SEQUENCE OF SyslogMsgSDEntry
    MAX-ACCESS  not-accessible
    STATUS      current
    DESCRIPTION
       "A table containing structured data elements of syslog
        messages."
    ::= { syslogMsgObjects 3 }

syslogMsgSDEntry OBJECT-TYPE
    SYNTAX      SyslogMsgSDEntry
    MAX-ACCESS  not-accessible
    STATUS      current
    DESCRIPTION
       "An entry of the syslogMsgSDTable."
    INDEX { syslogMsgIndex, syslogMsgSDParamIndex,
            syslogMsgSDID, syslogMsgSDParamName }
    ::= { syslogMsgSDTable 1 }

SyslogMsgSDEntry ::= SEQUENCE {
    syslogMsgSDParamIndex  Unsigned32,
    syslogMsgSDID          DisplayString,
    syslogMsgSDParamName   DisplayString,
    syslogMsgSDParamValue  SyslogParamValueString
}

syslogMsgSDParamIndex OBJECT-TYPE
    SYNTAX      Unsigned32 (1..4294967295)
    MAX-ACCESS  not-accessible
    STATUS      current
    DESCRIPTION
       "This object indexes the structured data element parameters
        contained in a SYSLOG message. The first structured data
        element parameter has the index value 1 and subsequent
        parameters are indexed by incrementing the index of the
        previous parameter. The index increases across structured
        data element boundaries so that the value reflects the
        position of a structured data element parameter in a
        SYSLOG message."
    REFERENCE
       "RFC5424: The Syslog Protocol (section 6.3.3)"
    ::= { syslogMsgSDEntry 1 }

syslogMsgSDID OBJECT-TYPE
    SYNTAX      DisplayString (SIZE (1..32))
    MAX-ACCESS  not-accessible
    STATUS      current
    DESCRIPTION
       "The name (SD-ID) of a structured data element. The SYSLOG
        protocol specification constrains this string to printable
        US-ASCII code points."
    REFERENCE
       "RFC5424: The Syslog Protocol (section 6.3.2)"
    ::= { syslogMsgSDEntry 2 }

syslogMsgSDParamName OBJECT-TYPE
    SYNTAX      DisplayString (SIZE (1..32))
    MAX-ACCESS  not-accessible
    STATUS      current
    DESCRIPTION
       "The name of a parameter of the structured data element. The
        SYSLOG protocol specification constrains this string to
        printable US-ASCII code points."
    REFERENCE
       "RFC5424: The Syslog Protocol (section 6.3.3)"
    ::= { syslogMsgSDEntry 3 }

syslogMsgSDParamValue OBJECT-TYPE
    SYNTAX      SyslogParamValueString
    MAX-ACCESS  read-only
    STATUS      current
    DESCRIPTION
       "The value of the parameter of a syslog message identified by
        the index of this table. The value is stored in the unescaped
        format."
    REFERENCE
       "RFC5424: The Syslog Protocol (section 6.3.3)"
    ::= { syslogMsgSDEntry 4 }

-- notification definitions

syslogMsgNotification NOTIFICATION-TYPE
    OBJECTS     { syslogMsgFacility, syslogMsgSeverity, 
                  syslogMsgVersion, syslogMsgTimeStamp, 
                  syslogMsgHostName, syslogMsgAppName,
                  syslogMsgProcID, syslogMsgMsgID,
                  syslogMsgSDParams, syslogMsgMsg }
    STATUS      current
    DESCRIPTION
       "The syslogMsgNotification is generated when a new syslog
        message is received and the value of
        syslogMsgGenerateNotifications is true.

        Implementations may add syslogMsgSDParamValue objects as long
        as the resulting notification fits into the size constraints
        imposed by the implementation environment and the notification
        message size constraints imposed by maxMessageSize [RFC3412]
        and SNMP transport mappings."
    ::= { syslogMsgNotifications 1 }

-- conformance statements

syslogMsgGroups      OBJECT IDENTIFIER ::= { syslogMsgConformance 1 }
syslogMsgCompliances OBJECT IDENTIFIER ::= { syslogMsgConformance 2 }

syslogMsgFullCompliance MODULE-COMPLIANCE
    STATUS      current
    DESCRIPTION
       "The compliance statement for implementations of the
        SYSLOG-MSG-MIB."
    MODULE      -- this module
    MANDATORY-GROUPS {
        syslogMsgGroup,
        syslogMsgSDGroup,
        syslogMsgControlGroup,
        syslogMsgNotificationGroup
    }
    ::= { syslogMsgCompliances 1 }

syslogMsgReadOnlyCompliance MODULE-COMPLIANCE
    STATUS      current
    DESCRIPTION
       "The compliance statement for implementations of the
        SYSLOG-MSG-MIB that do not support read-write access."
    MODULE      -- this module
    MANDATORY-GROUPS {
        syslogMsgGroup,
        syslogMsgSDGroup,
        syslogMsgControlGroup,
        syslogMsgNotificationGroup
    }
    OBJECT syslogMsgTableMaxSize
       MIN-ACCESS  read-only
       DESCRIPTION
          "Write access is not required."
    OBJECT syslogMsgEnableNotifications
       MIN-ACCESS  read-only
       DESCRIPTION
          "Write access is not required."
    ::= { syslogMsgCompliances 2 }

syslogMsgNotificationCompliance MODULE-COMPLIANCE
    STATUS      current
    DESCRIPTION
       "The compliance statement for implementations of the
        SYSLOG-MSG-MIB that do only generate notifications and not
        provide a table to allow read access to syslog message
        details."
    MODULE      -- this module
    MANDATORY-GROUPS {
        syslogMsgGroup,
        syslogMsgSDGroup,
        syslogMsgNotificationGroup
    }
    OBJECT      syslogMsgFacility
    MIN-ACCESS  accessible-for-notify
    DESCRIPTION
        "Read access is not required."
    OBJECT      syslogMsgSeverity
    MIN-ACCESS  accessible-for-notify
    DESCRIPTION
       "Read access is not required."
    OBJECT      syslogMsgVersion
    MIN-ACCESS  accessible-for-notify
    DESCRIPTION
       "Read access is not required."
    OBJECT      syslogMsgTimeStamp
    MIN-ACCESS  accessible-for-notify
    DESCRIPTION
       "Read access is not required."
    OBJECT      syslogMsgHostName
    MIN-ACCESS  accessible-for-notify
    DESCRIPTION
       "Read access is not required."
    OBJECT      syslogMsgAppName
    MIN-ACCESS  accessible-for-notify
    DESCRIPTION
       "Read access is not required."
    OBJECT      syslogMsgProcID
    MIN-ACCESS  accessible-for-notify
    DESCRIPTION
       "Read access is not required."
    OBJECT      syslogMsgMsgID
    MIN-ACCESS  accessible-for-notify
    DESCRIPTION
       "Read access is not required."
    OBJECT      syslogMsgSDParams
    MIN-ACCESS  accessible-for-notify
    DESCRIPTION
       "Read access is not required."
    OBJECT      syslogMsgMsg
    MIN-ACCESS  accessible-for-notify
    DESCRIPTION
       "Read access is not required."
    OBJECT      syslogMsgSDParamValue
    MIN-ACCESS  accessible-for-notify
    DESCRIPTION
       "Read access is not required."
    ::= { syslogMsgCompliances 3 }

syslogMsgNotificationGroup NOTIFICATION-GROUP
    NOTIFICATIONS {
        syslogMsgNotification
    }
    STATUS      current
    DESCRIPTION
       "The notifications emitted by this MIB module."
    ::= { syslogMsgGroups 1 }

syslogMsgGroup OBJECT-GROUP
    OBJECTS {
        -- syslogMsgIndex,
        syslogMsgFacility,
        syslogMsgSeverity,
        syslogMsgVersion,
        syslogMsgTimeStamp,
        syslogMsgHostName,
        syslogMsgAppName,
        syslogMsgProcID,
        syslogMsgMsgID,
        syslogMsgSDParams,
        syslogMsgMsg
    }
    STATUS      current
    DESCRIPTION
       "A collection of objects representing a syslog message
        excluding structured data elements."
    ::= { syslogMsgGroups 2 }

syslogMsgSDGroup OBJECT-GROUP
    OBJECTS {
        -- syslogMsgSDParamIndex,
        -- syslogMsgSDID,
        -- syslogMsgSDParamName,
        syslogMsgSDParamValue 
    }
    STATUS      current
    DESCRIPTION
       "A collection of objects representing the structured data
        elements of a syslog message."
    ::= { syslogMsgGroups 3 }

syslogMsgControlGroup OBJECT-GROUP
    OBJECTS {
        syslogMsgTableMaxSize,
        syslogMsgEnableNotifications
    }
    STATUS      current
    DESCRIPTION
       "A collection of control objects to control the size of the
        syslogMsgTable and to enable / disable notifications."
    ::= { syslogMsgGroups 4 }

END
        </artwork>
      </figure>
    </section>    

    <section anchor="Usage Examples" title="Usage Example">
      <t>
        The following example shows a valid syslog message including
        structured data. The otherwise-unprintable Unicode BOM is
        represented as "BOM" in the example.
      </t>
      <figure>
        <artwork>
  &lt;165&gt;1 2003-10-11T22:14:15.003Z mymachine.example.com
  evntslog - ID47 [exampleSDID@32473 iut="3" eventSource="Application"
  eventID="1011"] BOMAn application event log entry...
        </artwork>
      </figure>
      <t>
        This syslog message leads to the following entries in the
        syslogMsgTable and the syslogMsgSDTable (note that string
        indexes are written as strings for readability reasons):
      </t>
      <figure>
        <artwork>
  syslogMsgIndex.1 = 1
  syslogMsgFacility.1 = 20
  syslogMsgSeverity.1 = 5
  syslogMsgVersion.1 = 1
  syslogMsgTimeStamp.1 = 2003-10-11,22:14:15.003,+0:0
  syslogMsgHostName.1 = "mymachine.example.com"
  syslogMsgAppName.1 = "evntslog"
  syslogMsgProcID.1 = "-"
  syslogMsgMsgID.1 = "ID47"
  syslogMsgMsg.1 = "BOMAn application event log entry..."
  syslogMsgSDParamValue.1.1."exampleSDID@32473"."iut"
      = "3"
  syslogMsgSDParamValue.1.2."exampleSDID@32473"."eventSource"
      = "Application"
  syslogMsgSDParamValue.1.3."exampleSDID@32473"."eventID" 
      = "1011"
        </artwork>
      </figure>

    </section>
    
    <section anchor="IANA Considerations" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>
        The IANA is requested to assign a value for "XXX" under the
        'mib-2' subtree and to record the assignment in the SMI
        Numbers registry.  When the assignment has been made, the RFC
        Editor is asked to replace "XXX" (here and in the MIB module)
        with the assigned value.
      </t>
    </section>
    
    <section title="Security Considerations">
      <t>
        There are a number of management objects defined in this MIB module
        with a MAX-ACCESS clause of read-write and/or read-create.  Such
        objects may be considered sensitive or vulnerable in some network
        environments.  The support for SET operations in a non-secure
        environment without proper protection can have a negative effect on
        network operations.  These are the tables and objects and their
        sensitivity/vulnerability:
      </t>
      <t>
        <list style="symbols">
          <t>
            syslogMsgTableMaxSize: This object controls how many
            entries are kept in the syslogMsgTable. Unauthorized
            modifications may either cause increased memory
            consumption (by setting this object to a large value) or
            turn off the capability to retrieve notifications using
            GET class operations (by setting this object to
            zero). This might be used to hide traces of an attack.
          </t>
          <t>
            syslogMsgEnableNotifications: This object enables
            notifications. Unauthorized modifications to disable
            notification generation can be used to hide an attack by
            preventing management applications that use SNMP from
            receiving real-time notifications about events carried in
            syslog messages. Unauthorized modifications to enable
            notification generation may be used as part of a denial of
            service attack against a network management system if for
            example the SYSLOG-to-SNMP translator accepts unauthorized
            syslog messages.
          </t>
        </list>
      </t>
      <t>
        Some of the readable objects in this MIB module (i.e., objects
        with a MAX-ACCESS other than not-accessible) may be considered
        sensitive or vulnerable in some network environments.  It is
        thus important to control even GET and/or NOTIFY access to
        these objects and possibly to even encrypt the values of these
        objects when sending them over the network via SNMP.  These
        are the tables and objects and their
        sensitivity/vulnerability:
      </t>
      <t>
        <list style="symbols">
          <t>
            syslogMsgTableMaxSize, syslogMsgEnableNotifications: These
            objects provide information whether SYSLOG messages are
            forwarded as SNMP notifications and how many messages will
            be maintained in the syslogMsgTable. This information
            might be exploited by an attacker in order to plan actions
            with the goal of hiding attack activities.
          </t>
          <t>
            syslogMsgFacility, syslogMsgSeverity, syslogMsgVersion,
            syslogMsgTimeStamp, syslogMsgHostName, syslogMsgAppName,
            syslogMsgProcID, syslogMsgMsgID, syslogMsgSDParams,
            syslogMsgMsg, syslogMsgSDParamValue: These objects carry
            the content of syslog messags and the syslog message
            oriented security considerations of
            <xref target="RFC5424"/> apply. In particular, an attacker
            who gains access to SYSLOG messages via SNMP may use the
            knowledge gained from SYSLOG messages to compromise a
            machine or do other damage. It is therefore desirable to
            configure SNMP access control rules enforcing a consistent
            security policy for SYSLOG messages.
          </t>
        </list>
      </t>
      <t>
        SNMP versions prior to SNMPv3 did not include adequate
        security.  Even if the network itself is secure (for example
        by using IPsec), even then, there is no control as to who on
        the secure network is allowed to access and GET/SET
        (read/change/create/delete) the objects in this MIB module.
      </t>
      <t>
        It is RECOMMENDED that implementers consider the security
        features as provided by the SNMPv3 framework (see [RFC3410],
        section 8), including full support for the SNMPv3
        cryptographic mechanisms (for authentication and privacy).
      </t>
      <t>
        Further, deployment of SNMP versions prior to SNMPv3 is NOT
        RECOMMENDED.  Instead, it is RECOMMENDED to deploy SNMPv3 and
        to enable cryptographic security.  It is then a
        customer/operator responsibility to ensure that the SNMP
        entity giving access to an instance of this MIB module is
        properly configured to give access to the objects only to
        those principals (users) that have legitimate rights to indeed
        GET or SET (change/create/delete) them.
      </t>
      <t>
        Using the security features of the SNMPv3 framework secures
        the transport of SYSLOG data via SNMP only. It is therefore
        RECOMMENDED that deployments use SYSLOG security mechanisms in
        order to prevent attackers from adding malicious SYSLOG data
        to the MIB tables.
      </t>
    </section>
    
    <section title="Acknowledgments">
      <t>
        The editors wish to thank the following individuals for
        providing helpful comments on various versions of this
        document: Martin Bjorklund, Washam Fan, Rainer Gerhards, Wes
        Hardacker, David Harrington, Tom Petch, Juergen Quittek, Dan
        Romascanu, and Bert Wijnen.
      </t>
    </section>
  </middle>
 
  <back>

    <references title="Normative References">
      
      <reference anchor="RFC2119">
        <front>
          <title>
            Key words for use in RFCs to Indicate Requirement Levels
          </title>
          <author initials="S." surname="Bradner" fullname="Scott Bradner">
            <organization>Harvard University</organization>
          </author>
          <date month="March" year="1997"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="BCP" value="14"/>
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="2119"/>
      </reference>
      
      <reference anchor="RFC3411">
        <front>
          <title>
            An Architecture for Describing Simple Network Management 
            Protocol (SNMP) Management Frameworks
          </title>
          <author initials="D." surname="Harrington" fullname="Dave Harrington">
            <organization>Enterasys Networks</organization>
          </author>
          <author initials="R." surname="Presuhn" fullname="Randy Presuhn">
            <organization>BMC Software, Inc.</organization>
          </author>
          <author initials="B." surname="Wijnen" fullname="Bert Wijnen">
            <organization>Lucent Technologies</organization>
          </author>
          <date month="December" year="2002"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="STD" value="62"/>
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="3411"/>
      </reference>
      
      <reference anchor="RFC3412">
        <front>
          <title>
            Message Processing and Dispatching for the Simple Network
            Management Protocol (SNMP)
          </title>
          <author initials="J." surname="Case" fullname="Jeff Case">
            <organization>SNMP Research, Inc.</organization>
          </author>
          <author initials="D." surname="Harrington" fullname="Dave Harrington">
            <organization>Enterasys Networks</organization>
          </author>
          <author initials="R." surname="Presuhn" fullname="Randy Presuhn">
            <organization>BMC Software, Inc.</organization>
          </author>
          <author initials="B." surname="Wijnen" fullname="Bert Wijnen">
            <organization>Lucent Technologies</organization>
          </author>
          <date month="December" year="2002"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="STD" value="62"/>
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="3412"/>
      </reference>
      
      <reference anchor="RFC5424">
        <front>
          <title>
            The Syslog Protocol
          </title>
          <author initials="R." surname="Gerhards" fullname="Rainer Gerhards">
            <organization>Adiscon GmbH</organization>
          </author>
          <date month="March" year="2009"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="5424"/>
      </reference>
      
      <reference anchor="RFC5427">
        <front>
          <title>
            Textual Conventions for Syslog Management
          </title>
          <author initials="G." surname="Keeni" fullname="Glenn Mansfield Keeni">
            <organization>Cyber Solutions Inc.</organization>
          </author>
          <date month="March" year="2009"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="5427"/>
      </reference>
      
      <reference anchor="RFC2578">
        <front>
          <title>
            Structure of Management Information Version 2 (SMIv2) 
          </title>
          <author initials="K." surname="McCloghrie" fullname="Keith McCloghrie">
            <organization>Cisco Systems, Inc</organization>
          </author>
          <author initials="D." surname="Perkins" fullname="David Perkins">
            <organization>SNMPinfo</organization>
          </author>
          <author initials="J." surname="Schoenwaelder" fullname="Juergen Schoenwaelder">
            <organization>TU Braunschweig</organization>
          </author>
          <date month="April" year="1999"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="2578"/>
        <seriesInfo name="STD" value="58"/>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RFC2579">
        <front>
          <title>
            Textual Conventions for SMIv2 
          </title>
          <author initials="K." surname="McCloghrie" fullname="Keith McCloghrie">
            <organization>Cisco Systems, Inc</organization>
          </author>
          <author initials="D." surname="Perkins" fullname="David Perkins">
            <organization>SNMPinfo</organization>
          </author>
          <author initials="J." surname="Schoenwaelder" fullname="Juergen Schoenwaelder">
            <organization>TU Braunschweig</organization>
          </author>
          <date month="April" year="1999"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="2579"/>
        <seriesInfo name="STD" value="58"/>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RFC2580">
        <front>
          <title>
            Conformance Statements for SMIv2
          </title>
          <author initials="K." surname="McCloghrie" fullname="Keith McCloghrie">
            <organization>Cisco Systems, Inc</organization>
          </author>
          <author initials="D." surname="Perkins" fullname="David Perkins">
            <organization>SNMPinfo</organization>
          </author>
          <author initials="J." surname="Schoenwaelder" fullname="Juergen Schoenwaelder">
            <organization>TU Braunschweig</organization>
          </author>
          <date month="April" year="1999"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="2580"/>
        <seriesInfo name="STD" value="58"/>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RFC3629">
        <front>
          <title>UTF-8, a transformation format of ISO 10646</title>
          <author initials="F." surname="Yergeau" fullname="F. Yergeau">
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <date month="November" year="2003"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="STD" value="63"/>
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="3629"/>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="I-D.ietf-opsawg-syslog-snmp">
        <front>
          <title>
            Mapping Simple Network Management Protocol (SNMP)
            Notifications to SYSLOG Messages
          </title>
          <author initials="V." surname="Marinov" fullname="Vladislav Marinov">
            <organization>Jacobs University Bremen</organization>
          </author>
          <author initials="J." surname="Schoenwaelder" fullname="Juergen Schoenwaelder">
            <organization>Jacobs University Bremen</organization>
          </author>
          <date month="March" year="2009"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="Internet Draft" value="(work in progress)"/>
      </reference>
      
    </references>
      
    <references title="Informative References">
      
      <reference anchor="RFC3410">
        <front>
          <title>
            Introduction and Applicability Statements for
            Internet-Standard Management Framework
          </title>
          <author initials="J." surname="Case" fullname="Jeff Case">
            <organization>SNMP Research, Inc.</organization>
          </author>
          <author initials="R." surname="Mundy" fullname="Russ Mundy">
            <organization>Network Associates Laboratories</organization>
          </author>
          <author initials="D." surname="Partain" fullname="David Partain">
            <organization>Ericsson</organization>
          </author>
          <author initials="B." surname="Stewart" fullname="Bob Stewart">
            <organization>Retired</organization>
          </author>
          <date month="December" year="2002"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="3410"/>
      </reference>
      
      <reference anchor="RFC3014">
        <front>
          <title>
            Notification Log MIB
          </title>
          <author role="editor" initials="R." surname="Kavasseri" fullname="Ramanathan Kavasseri">
            <organization>Cisco Systems, Inc.</organization>
          </author>
          <date month="November" year="2002"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="3014"/>
      </reference>
      
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>

<!-- Local Variables:                                           -->
<!-- compile-command: "xml2rfc syslog-msg-mib.xml"               -->
<!-- ispell-local-dictionary: "american"                        -->
<!-- sgml-declaration: "/usr/lib/sgml/declaration/xml.decl"     -->
<!-- sgml-omittag:nil                                           -->
<!-- sgml-shorttag:t                                            -->
<!-- sgml-namecase-general:t                                    -->
<!-- sgml-minimize-attributes:nil                               -->
<!-- sgml-always-quote-attributes:t                             -->
<!-- sgml-indent-step:2                                         -->
<!-- sgml-indent-data:t                                         -->
<!-- sgml-parent-document:nil                                   -->
<!-- sgml-exposed-tags:nil                                      -->
<!-- sgml-local-catalogs:nil                                    -->
<!-- sgml-local-ecat-files:nil                                  -->
<!-- End:                                                       -->
