<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!-- This template is for creating an Internet Draft using xml2rfc,
    which is available here: http://xml.resource.org. -->
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!-- One method to get references from the online citation libraries.
    There has to be one entity for each item to be referenced. 
    An alternate method (rfc include) is described in the references. -->

<!ENTITY RFC2119 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC2629 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2629.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3552 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3552.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5226 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5226.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6350 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6350.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6501 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6501.xml">
]>

<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<!-- used by XSLT processors -->
<!-- For a complete list and description of processing instructions (PIs), 
    please see http://xml.resource.org/authoring/README.html. -->
<!-- Below are generally applicable Processing Instructions (PIs) that most I-Ds might want to use.
    (Here they are set differently than their defaults in xml2rfc v1.32) -->
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<!-- give errors regarding ID-nits and DTD validation -->
<!-- control the table of contents (ToC) -->
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<!-- generate a ToC -->
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<!-- the number of levels of subsections in ToC. default: 3 -->
<!-- control references -->
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<!-- use symbolic references tags, i.e, [RFC2119] instead of [1] -->
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<!-- sort the reference entries alphabetically -->
<!-- control vertical white space 
    (using these PIs as follows is recommended by the RFC Editor) -->
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<!-- do not start each main section on a new page -->
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<!-- keep one blank line between list items -->
<!-- end of list of popular I-D processing instructions -->
<rfc category="info" docName="draft-groves-clue-role-clarifications-00" ipr="trust200902">
 <!-- category values: std, bcp, info, exp, and historic
    ipr values: trust200902, noModificationTrust200902, noDerivativesTrust200902,
       or pre5378Trust200902
    you can add the attributes updates="NNNN" and obsoletes="NNNN" 
    they will automatically be output with "(if approved)" -->

 <!-- ***** FRONT MATTER ***** -->

 <front>
   <!-- The abbreviated title is used in the page header - it is only necessary if the 
        full title is longer than 39 characters -->

   <title abbrev="Abbreviated Title">Use of "Roles" in CLUE</title>

   <!-- add 'role="editor"' below for the editors if appropriate -->

   <!-- Another author who claims to be an editor -->

   <author fullname="Christian Groves" initials="C" role="editor"
           surname="Groves">
     <organization>Huawei</organization>

     <address>
       <postal>
         <street></street>

         <!-- Reorder these if your country does things differently -->

         <city>Melbourne</city>

         <region></region>

         <code></code>

         <country>Australia</country>
       </postal>

       <email>Christian.Groves@nteczone.com</email>

       <!-- uri and facsimile elements may also be added -->
     </address>
   </author>
      <author fullname="Weiwei Yang" initials="W" 
           surname="Yang">
     <organization>Huawei</organization>

     <address>
       <postal>
         <street></street>

         <!-- Reorder these if your country does things differently -->

         <city></city>

         <region></region>

         <code></code>

         <country>P.R.China</country>
       </postal>

       <email>tommy@huawei.com</email>

       <!-- uri and facsimile elements may also be added -->
     </address>
   </author>

      <author fullname="Roni Even" initials="R"
           surname="Even">
     <organization>Huawei</organization>

     <address>
       <postal>
         <street></street>

         <!-- Reorder these if your country does things differently -->

         <city>Tel Aviv</city>

         <region></region>

         <code></code>

         <country>Isreal</country>
       </postal>

       <email>roni.even@mail01.huawei.com</email>

       <!-- uri and facsimile elements may also be added -->
     </address>
   </author>

   <date year="2013" />

   <!-- If the month and year are both specified and are the current ones, xml2rfc will fill 
        in the current day for you. If only the current year is specified, xml2rfc will fill 
	 in the current day and month for you. If the year is not the current one, it is 
	 necessary to specify at least a month (xml2rfc assumes day="1" if not specified for the 
	 purpose of calculating the expiry date).  With drafts it is normally sufficient to 
	 specify just the year. -->

   <!-- Meta-data Declarations -->

   <area>Real-time Applications and Infrastructure Area</area>

   <workgroup>CLUE</workgroup>

   <!-- WG name at the upperleft corner of the doc,
        IETF is fine for individual submissions.  
	 If this element is not present, the default is "Network Working Group",
        which is used by the RFC Editor as a nod to the history of the IETF. -->

   <keyword>template</keyword>

   <!-- Keywords will be incorporated into HTML output
        files in a meta tag but they have no effect on text or nroff
        output. If you submit your draft to the RFC Editor, the
        keywords will be used for the search engine. -->

   <abstract>
     <t>There have been recent discussions on the CLUE and DISPATCH mailing lists about "roles" associated with multimedia conferences. From the discussions it was apparent that there is some confusion as to what the current defined roles actually imply and that people had different understanding of the meaning and scope of the term "role". This draft seeks to identify the various "roles" that may be associated with a multimedia conference and to provide a grouping and nomenclature for further discussions on this topic.</t>
	 <t>Specific to CLUE this draft proposes a number of attributes to be able to clearly identify the various roles that may be associated with a media capture.</t>
   </abstract>
 </front>

 <middle>
   <section title="Introduction">
		<t>The purpose of this document is to collect together different types of "roles" or attributes of people participating within a multi-media conference. It is recognised that a person may have multiple roles in a conference that denote different information regarding their social and/or organisational status. For example: At a "Internal organisational level" a person may have the role of "Chief Executive Officer (CEO)" but from a conference control level may be a "Participant" who cannot control the conference despite having large amount of power in a company. The definition of a role may also give information regarding the type of organisation a person is from. For example: From "Professor" it could be assumed that the person is from an educational institution, however this assumption may be false as a Professor is a title of a person. One's status is an important aspect in social interactions. Telepresence is designed to increase the experience of normal social interactions so communication of status is an important aspect.</t>
		<t>From a media perspective a media stream that either depicts a person or carries their voice could be attributed with the person's role/s.</t>
	</section>
	 
	<section title="Role Categories"> 
		<t>As shown above the term "role" can be associated with a wide range of characteristics.  The sections below attempt to collect roles into different sub-categories of related roles. When a person talks about "role" it is important to identify the category of role that is being talked about as these are likely to have semantic differences.</t>
		
		<t>For example: When using the role "chairman" it could be considered as: <list hangIndent="8" style="hanging">
        	<t hangText="a)">a meeting role - the person who runs the meeting through the agenda</t>
			<t hangText="b)">a conference control role - the person who controls the conference system that allows people to speak</t>
			<t hangText="c)">the person is the chairman of a company and is participating in the conference</t>
		</list></t>
	 	<t>Each of the above is a different function with potentially the same label.</t>
	
		<section title="Meeting Roles">
			<t>These roles relate to typical traditional functions when a meeting is held. These roles are related to the running of the meeting itself, i.e. with respect to the agenda. These roles pre-date multimedia conferencing and are typically needed whenever a meeting is held. Knowing who has these roles is integral to running a successful meeting.</t>
			<t><list hangIndent="8" style="hanging">
				<t hangText="1.">Chairman (<xref target="RFC6501"/>. moderator?) (Leader - Person who convenes the meeting) (facilitator - keeps discussion going)</t>
				<t hangText="2.">Vice-Chairman</t>
				<t hangText="3.">Secretary/Scribe/Recorder/Minute Taker</t>
				<t hangText="4.">Member/Participant/Audience</t>
				<t hangText="5.">Presenter/Lecturer</t>
				<t hangText="6.">Translator</t>
				<t hangText="7.">Timekeeper</t>
			</list></t>
		</section>
		
		<section title="Conference System Control Roles">
			<t>These roles are related to the establishment and maintenance of the multimedia conference and are related to the scope of conference system only.  It can be beneficial for other people to know who has these roles. For example: If the controller is responsible for selecting which people/endpoints can speak it might be beneficial to observe them for visual CLUEs on how they determine the turn taking process.</t>
			<t><list hangIndent="18" style="hanging">
				<t hangText="Speaker/Presenter">Can share content/media with others.</t>
				<t hangText="Controller/Host">Indicates the person responsible for controlling admission to the conference. Sets up the meeting, adds and shares contents, control who presents and talks.</t>
				<t hangText="Participant">Indicates a participant in the conference who does not have any special control. Receives media and content from presenter.</t>
			</list></t>
		</section>
		
		<section title="Institution type">
			<t>This type indicates the type of organisation a person is from. This could be helpful to scope a person's title.</t>
			<t><list hangIndent="8" style="hanging">
				<t hangText="1.">Industry (this could be broken into segments, i.e. healthcare, telecommunications etc.)</t>
				<t hangText="2.">Government</t>
				<t hangText="3.">Non-governmental organisation (NGO)</t>
				<t hangText="4.">Educational</t>
				<t hangText="5.">Religious</t>
				<t hangText="6.">Not for profit</t>
				<t hangText="7.">Military</t>
				<t hangText="8.">Private</t>
				<t hangText="9.">Etc.</t>
			</list></t>
		</section>
		
		<section title="Person Name Title">
			<t>Common honorific titles relate to a person's gender (Social Title) i.e. Mr, Mrs, Miss etc. however there are other titles used to show aristocratic status (Hereditary title) (Honorary title) or one's role in government, a religious, military or educational institution. For example: Doctor (Professional Title), Professor (Academic Title) and Air Marshall (Military title). These are placed into context and relative authority given by the organisation type.</t>
			<t>Wikipedia provides a discussion of the different types of titles: http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Title</t>
			<t>It can be seen that there are hundreds of possible titles related to a person's status.</t>
			<t>A further complication is that a title may be repeated i.e. Honorary Doctor (Hon Dr).</t>
			<t>There are some standards that allow for the carriage of titles (these are discussed below) however there does not appear to be a standard definition containing all the titles.</t>
			<t>Appendix A of Standards Australia AS 4590-2006 "Interchange of client information" provides a list of some common titles.</t>
			<t><xref target="ITU.X520.2001"/> does contain syntax for Title (the designated position or function of the object within an organization) and allows it's usage in Commonname attribute (which vCard uses) however this does not provide any values.</t>
			<t>OASIS have developed standards for naming in the OASIS Identity Metasystem Interoperability (IMI) Technical Committee:
 (https://www.oasis-open.org/committees/tc_home.php?wg_abbrev=ciq). </t>
 			<t>However they do not define a set of allowed titles. See: Extensible Name Language (xML) Standard Description Document for W3C DTD/Schema</t>
			<t>Beyond the common set of English honorific titles it may be difficult to implement a policy based on a standard set.</t>
		</section>
		
		<section title="Person Occupation (Job Title)">
			<t>Persons can be further classified by their occupation. In some respects this is a combination of institution type and title. There is already a standard ISCO-8 "International Standard Classification of Occupations" that groups jobs into 10 major groups:</t>
			<t><list hangIndent="8" style="hanging">
				<t hangText="1-">Managers</t>
				<t hangText="2-">Professionals</t>
				<t hangText="3-">Technicians and associate professionals</t>
				<t hangText="4-">Clerical support workers</t>
				<t hangText="5-">Service and sales workers</t>
				<t hangText="6-">Skilled agricultural, forestry and fishery workers</t>
				<t hangText="7-">Craft and related trades workers</t>
				<t hangText="8-">Plant and machine operators, and assemblers</t>
				<t hangText="9-">Elementary occupations</t>
				<t hangText="0-">Armed forces occupations</t>
			</list></t>
			<t>These categories are further broken down into to provide more detailed information regarding the job. For example:</t>
			<t><list hangIndent="8" style="hanging">
				<t>Major Group 1</t>
				<t>Managers</t>
				<t><list hangIndent="8" style="hanging">
					<t hangText="11">Chief executives, senior officials and legislators</t>
						<t><list hangIndent="8" style="hanging">
						<t hangText="111">Legislators and senior officials</t>
						<t hangText="112">Managing directors and chief executives</t>
					</list></t>
				</list></t>
			</list></t>
			<t>It may be advantageous to utilise this specification to indicate the organisational position of someone. A free text field could provide extra information if the user determines it is necessary.</t>
		</section>
		
		<section title="Organisation Name">
			<t>Rather than providing person information an endpoint could provide information regarding an organisation name. For example: it may not matter that media is from a certain person you may want media from a certain company. </t>
			<t>OASIS as mentioned above provides guidelines on organisation name formats.</t>
			<t>vCard <xref target="RFC6350"/> also allows the indication of an organisation name.</t>
		</section>
		
		<section title="Meeting Specific Roles">
			<t>Rather than being international and regionally accepted roles, roles may also be internal to an organisation or group.  This group may define their own roles as integral to the meeting process and it may be advantageous for other people in the meeting to know these roles. For example:</t>
			<t>Toastmasters (http://www.toastmasters.org/meetingroles.aspx) define the roles of: Ah-counter, Evaluator, General Evaluater, Grammarian, Meeting Speaker, Pledge, etc.</t>
			<t>So in the scope of a Telepresence conference between toastmasters participants it should be possible to select captures based on their agreed set of roles. They could be scoped by organisation. However for the wider community these roles would largely be meaningless.</t>
			<t>Another example would be the Telemedical use case. A capture of "the patient" would be difficult to express using the normal conference roles.</t>
		</section>
		
		<section title="Other Considerations">
			<t>This draft has only considered this issue from an English language perspective. Further consideration would be needed on the use of non-English roles and any potential mapping.</t>
		</section>
	</section>
	 
	<section title="Relation to CLUE">
		<t><xref target="I-D.groves-clue-capture-attr"/> proposed a number of attributes to describe media captures. One of those was the "role" attribute. The intention of the "role" attribute was to allow the consumer to advertise that a media capture has a person and/or conference role associated with it. During discussions it was noted that more work was needed on the allowed values.</t>
		<t>As shown above the term "role" relates to a wide range of functions so the CLUE work on roles should be more specific on what function/s are supported. If more than one role type is supported it may be more appropriate to support several attributes, each specific to a particular function.</t>
		<t>An advertiser may populate "role" information either by manual or automatic provisioning. Manual configuration would be that the participant enter the information at the time of meeting establishment. Automatic provisioning is where the conference system uses previously supplied information to populate the role information. This could be provided when the system is provisioned or based on electronic exchange of information. For example the Popov room at the ITU-T allows the insertion of an identity card at a seating position which the conference system can use.</t>
		<t>The basic premise of CLUE is that the attributes are used by a consumer to select which of the advertised media captures it wants. Therefore it is assumed that the "role" type information is only used in scope of CLUE. For example: the CLUE role information would not be used by SIP XCON (<xref target="RFC6501"/>) to determine conference policies. Like the other CLUE attributes the "role" information may also be used to determine display/playout characteristics by a consumer.</t>
		<t>A secondary premise is that by knowing the "role" of the person/media capture it enhances the social interactions in the conference. What the relevance of the different "role" functions has to a consumer is largely a matter of local policy. A person associated with the consuming endpoint may be more interested in seeing the company CEO than the person chairing the meeting. This different relevance may also be based on cultural preferences / norms.</t>
		<t>The various "role" categories are discussed below in the context of relevance to CLUE.</t>
		
		<section title="Meeting Roles">
			<t>As described in section 2.1 these roles are key to most meetings. They describe the functions related to the running of the meeting. They are NOT related to running a conferencing system. These roles are assigned to people within a meeting. As a media capture may capture more than one person it means that an attribute describing meeting roles must allow more than one value per media capture. A person may also have more than one meeting role, i.e. a secretary and time keeper. Multiple people within a capture may also have the same role, i.e. three people in a capture may all be participants. In such a case a meeting role attribute would only need a single value "participant".</t>
			<t>A media capture may contain people with the following meeting roles:<list hangIndent="16" style="hanging">
        		<t hangText="Chairman">A person who convenes the meeting and presides over discussions. Also known as a moderator or rapporteur.</t>
				<t hangText="Vice-Chairman">A person who assist the chairman.</t>
				<t hangText="Secretary">A person who is responsible for documenting the meeting. Also known as a scribe, recorder or minute taker.</t>
				<t hangText="Participant">A person who is participating in a meeting that has no other role in a meeting. Also known as a member, participant or audience.</t>
				<t hangText="Presenter">A person who has been invited to present a message to the meeting. Also known as a lecturer.</t>
				<t hangText="Translator">A person who translates from one language to another in a meeting.</t>
				<t hangText="Timekeeper">A person who is responsible who records the time taken for the meeting.</t>
			</list></t>
			<t>It is proposed to add a capture attribute "Meeting Role" to CLUE with the above values.</t>
		</section>	
	
		<section title="Meeting Specific Roles">
			<t>As discussed in section 2.7 it is possible that certain group may define their own meeting roles. The ability to carry this information should be possible in CLUE. To facilitate the carriage of this information in CLUE it is proposed to add a free text field to the "Meeting Role" attribute proposed in section 3.1 above.</t>
		</section>
		
		<section title="Conference System Control Roles">
			<t>As mentioned in section 2.2 conference system control roles relate to the control of the electronic conference.  For CLUE an attribute with the Conference Control role would indicate that the person depicted in the media capture has certain conference control responsibilities. It does not provide any authorisation in a conference management system for these conference control roles. The information is provided as a means for the consumer to select media captures and for display/playout purposes.</t>
			<t>The following conference system control roles are proposed:<list hangIndent="16" style="hanging">
        		<t hangText="Presenter">Indicates a person that can share content/media with others. May also be known as speaker.</t>
	        	<t hangText="Controller">Indicates the person responsible for controlling admission to the conference. Sets up the meeting, adds and shares contents, control who presents and talks. Also known as "host".</t>
        		<t hangText="Participant">Indicates a participant in the conference who does not have any special control. Receives media and content from presenter.</t>
			</list></t>
		
			<t>Unlike meeting role a person can only have one conference system control role at a time. However as multiple people can be captured in a media capture the conference system control role may have multiple values.</t>
			<t>It is proposed to add an attribute "Conference System Control Role" to CLUE with the above attributes.</t>
		</section>
		
		<section title="Institution type">
			<t>CLUE media captures are more likely to be selected based on the person and their position and company rather than the type of organisation that they are from. This can be omitted from CLUE.</t>
		</section>
		
		<section title="Personal Information">
			<section title="Person Name Title">	
				<t>As described in section 2.4 above there may be many different variations of a person name title. There are also non-English speaking titles that would need to be conveyed. It is unlikely that all the variations could be enumerated. As discussed above a person's title gives important information regarding the social status of that person. It is noted that vCard <xref target="RFC6350"/> section 6.2.2 allows title as part of the "n" attribute.  As a means to provide information regarding the person in a capture it is proposed to allow vCard <xref target="RFC6350"/> descriptions to be linked with CLUE media captures. This is a standardised form of providing information regarding a person's title, name and contact details as well as additional attributes. This would allow a Consumer to choose captures based on a rich set of information as well as using this information for display.</t>
			</section>
			
			<section title="Person Occupation (Job Title)">	
				<t>As has been discussed Consumers may choose to receive a particular media capture based on the role of a person. For example a consumer may always want to see a managing director. vCard provides a "title" parameter in <xref target="RFC6350"/> section 6.6.1 and the "role" parameter in section 6.6.2. These parameters are based on <xref target="ITU.X520.2001"/> "title" and "business category" attributes. If CLUE utilises the vCard format then it could utilise these parameters to carry information regarding a person's occupation.</t>
				<t>The vCard "role" parameter is a single text value. In order to provide interoperability between advertiser and consumers CLUE could recommend that the ISO classifications as discussed in section 2.5 be used whilst allowing an advertiser to use a free text field.</t>
				<t>Therefore it is proposed that CLUE allow vCard/s be associated with media captures for this purpose.</t>
			</section>
			
			<section title="Organisation Name">	
				<t>vCard <xref target="RFC6350"/> defines a data format for representing and exchanging a variety of information about individuals and other entities. The information is grouped into the following set of properties:<list hangIndent="8" style="hanging">
					<t hangText="o">Identification Properties</t>
					<t hangText="o">Delivery addressing properties</t>
					<t hangText="o">Communications Properties</t>
					<t hangText="o">Organizational Properties</t>
					<t hangText="o">Explanatory Properties</t>
					<t hangText="o">Security Properties</t>
					<t hangText="o">Calendar Properties</t>
				</list></t>
				<t>These properties allow a wide range of information to be transmitted in a manner that interoperable between an advertiser and consumer. vCard allows the description of persons, groups, organisation and locations. This would allow an Advertiser to send information regarding the organisation and location where the endpoint is located as well as the people participating in the conference. Having this information available regarding the persons/groups/organisations allows for service innovation.</t>
				<t>As discussed previously metadata regarding captures needs to be sent before or with the CLUE messages as the data needs to be an input into capture selection. Leaving such information to be collected later in the conference establishment process e.g. via XCON or some other means would not be appropriate.</t>
				<t>An advertiser may choose to send a minimal set of information such as only a name or a more complete set with personal title, job title etc. The only mandatory vCard field (apart from syntax related ones) is the "FN" (Formatted name) property (section 6.2.1/<xref target="RFC6350"/>). This relates to the vCard "object" rather than a "person" which allows for names other than person names to be used. So an endpoint could transit the meeting roles even if the names of the people in the conference are not available.</t>
				<t>vCard also allows information to be transmitted in multiple languages as specified by a language property parameter.</t>
				<t>The vCard format is also a widely supported for electronic business cards and are often associated with e-mail messages. Rather than defining a new format for personal information in CLUE it would be beneficial to capitalise on a format that enjoys wide use.</t>
				<t>In terms of the CLUE data model it may not be necessary to carry a vCard format syntax for each capture due to the fact that a person/group/organisation may appear in multiple capture. For example: An Advertiser that has 3 cameras (VC1,VC2,VC3) each capturing one person, one camera (VC4) capturing the room and a microphone capturing the room would be advertised as:<list hangIndent="4" style="hanging">
					<t hangText="">CSE1(VC1[vCARD1{syntax}],VC2[vCARD2{syntax}],VC3[vCARD3{syntax}])</t>
					<t hangText="">CSE2(VC4[vCARD1{syntax},vCARD2{syntax},vCARD3{syntax}])</t>
					<t hangText="">CSE3(AC1[vCARD1{syntax},vCARD2{syntax},vCARD3{syntax}])</t>
				</list></t>
				<t>If the contents of each of the vCARDs was large this would result in a large CLUE message size. Therefore it would be more appropriate to transmit the vCARDs in a separate section of the CLUE message and provide a pointer to the card in a capture attribute. Additionally rather than transmitting the entire vCARD in the CLUE message a URI to location where the vCARD can be downloaded should be possible.</t>
			</section>
		</section>
	</section>
		
	<section title="Capture scene attributes">	
		<t>The current CLUE framework contains a Capture Scene attribute "Description" which is a human-readable description of the capture scene. As can be seen vCard allows a rich description regarding a person or an organisation. In the case that a scene represents an endpoint as a whole rather than associating a vCard with each media capture it may be desirable to associate a vCard with the Capture Scene. </t>
	</section>
	
	<section title="Summary of proposed updates">
		<t><list hangIndent="8" style="hanging">
		<t hangText="1.">The addition of a capture attribute "Meeting Role" attribute with values as per section 3.1 and 3.2.</t>
		<t hangText="2.">The addition of a capture attribute "Conference System Control Role" attribute with values as per section 3.3.</t>
		<t hangText="3.">The addition of a capture attribute "vCard" that allows one or more vCards according to <xref target="RFC6350"/> to be associated with a capture.</t>
		<t hangText="4.">The addition of a capture attribute "End point vCard" that allows a "group", "org" or "location" kind of vCard according to section 6.1.4/<xref target="RFC6350"/> to be associated with a capture.</t>
		</list></t>
	</section>

    <section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">
     <t>This template was derived from an initial version written by Pekka
     Savola and contributed by him to the xml2rfc project.</t>
	</section>
	
   <!-- Possibly a 'Contributors' section ... -->

   <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
     <t>The "Meeting Roles" and "Conference Control Roles" attribute may have an IANA registry associated with them to facilitate the addition of future new roles.</t>
	 <t>vCard already has IANA registration procedures for new properties, parameters and values.</t>
   </section>

   <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
     <t>Providing "meeting role", "conference control role" and "vCard" attributes raises the question of whether the endpoint (or the people at the endpoint) are authorized to provide the roles and are who they say they are?</t>
	 <t>The context of the use of these attributes is for the purposes of choosing media captures not to provide pre-authorization for the control of conference control function. It is expected that the original SIP exchange would provide an "authorisation" between the Advertiser and Consumer to utilize a CLUE signaling channel. Therefore there is some level of trust between these two entities.</t>
	 <t>An Advertiser could send false information regarding a media capture. For example it may assert in a vCard attribute that a person in a capture is "King Richard" when the person is not. However this is not problematic only for "role" related attributes it applies to any asserted information in CLUE i.e. every attribute.</t>
	</section>
	
 </middle>

 <!--  *****BACK MATTER ***** -->

 <back>
   <!-- References split into informative and normative -->

   <!-- There are 2 ways to insert reference entries from the citation libraries:
    1. define an ENTITY at the top, and use "ampersand character"RFC2629; here (as shown)
    2. simply use a PI "less than character"?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119.xml"?> here
       (for I-Ds: include="reference.I-D.narten-iana-considerations-rfc2434bis.xml")
    Both are cited textually in the same manner: by using xref elements.
    If you use the PI option, xml2rfc will, by default, try to find included files in the same
    directory as the including file. You can also define the XML_LIBRARY environment variable
    with a value containing a set of directories to search.  These can be either in the local
    filing system or remote ones accessed by http (http://domain/dir/... ).-->

   <references title="Normative References">
     <!--?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"?-->
     &RFC2119;

   </references>

   <references title="Informative References">
     <!-- Here we use entities that we defined at the beginning. -->

     &RFC2629;

     &RFC3552;

     &RFC5226;
	 
	 &RFC6350;
	 
	 &RFC6501;
	 
	 <?rfc include="reference.I-D.ietf-clue-framework.xml"?>
	 
	 <?rfc include="reference.I-D.groves-clue-capture-attr.xml"?>
	 
	 <?rfc include="reference.ITU.X520.2001.xml"?>
	 
<!--	  <reference anchor="I-D.ietf-clue-framework">
       <front>
         <title>Framework for Telepresence Multi-Streams</title>

         <author initials="A" surname="Romanow">
           <organization></organization>
         </author>
		 <author initials="M" surname="Duckworth">
           <organization></organization>
         </author>
		 <author initials="A" surname="Pepperell">
           <organization></organization>
         </author>
		  <author initials="B" surname="Baldino">
           <organization></organization>
         </author>
         <date year="draft-ietf-clue-framework-09 (work in progress)" />
       </front>
     </reference> -->
	</references>

   <!-- Change Log

v00 2006-03-15  EBD   Initial version

v01 2006-04-03  EBD   Moved PI location back to position 1 -
                     v3.1 of XMLmind is better with them at this location.
v02 2007-03-07  AH    removed extraneous nested_list attribute,
                     other minor corrections
v03 2007-03-09  EBD   Added comments on null IANA sections and fixed heading capitalization.
                     Modified comments around figure to reflect non-implementation of
                     figure indent control.  Put in reference using anchor="DOMINATION".
                     Fixed up the date specification comments to reflect current truth.
v04 2007-03-09 AH     Major changes: shortened discussion of PIs,
                     added discussion of rfc include.
v05 2007-03-10 EBD    Added preamble to C program example to tell about ABNF and alternative 
                     images. Removed meta-characters from comments (causes problems).

v06 2010-04-01 TT     Changed ipr attribute values to latest ones. Changed date to
                     year only, to be consistent with the comments. Updated the 
                     IANA guidelines reference from the I-D to the finished RFC.  -->
 </back>
</rfc>
