<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY rfc2119 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc3627 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3627.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc4291 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4291.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc4443 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4443.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc3756 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3756.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc5375 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5375.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc4861 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4861.xml">
]>
<rfc category="std" docName="draft-kohno-ipv6-prefixlen-p2p-02.txt"
     ipr="trust200902" obsoletes="" submissionType="IETF"
     updates="3627,4291,5375" xml:lang="en">
  <?rfc toc="yes" ?>

  <?rfc compact="yes"?>

  <?rfc subcompact="no"?>

  <?rfc symrefs="yes"?>

  <?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>

  <front>
    <title abbrev="IPv6 prefixlen p2p">Using 127-bit IPv6 Prefixes on
    Inter-Router Links</title>

    <author fullname="Miya Kohno" initials="M" surname="Kohno">
      <organization>Juniper Networks, Keio University</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Shinjuku Park Tower, 3-7-1 Nishishinjuku</street>

          <city>Shinjuku-ku</city>

          <region>Tokyo</region>

          <code>163-1035</code>

          <country>Japan</country>
        </postal>

        <email>mkohno@juniper.net</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Becca Nitzan" initials="B" surname="Nitzan">
      <organization>Juniper Networks</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>1194 North Marhilda Avenue</street>

          <city>Sunnyvale</city>

          <region>CA</region>

          <code>94089</code>

          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>

        <email>nitzan@juniper.net</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Randy Bush" initials="R" surname="Bush">
      <organization>Internet Initiative Japan</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>5147 Crystal Springs</street>

          <city>Bainbridge Island</city>

          <region>WA</region>

          <code>98110</code>

          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>

        <email>randy@psg.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Yoshinobu Matsuzaki" initials="Y" surname="Matsuzaki">
      <organization>Internet Initiative Japan</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Jinbocho Mitsui Building,</street>

          <city>1-105 Kanda Jinbo-cho</city>

          <region>Tokyo</region>

          <code>101-0051</code>

          <country>Japan</country>
        </postal>

        <email>maz@iij.ad.jp</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Lorenzo Colitti" initials="L" surname="Colitti">
      <organization>Google</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>1600 Amphitheatre Parkway,</street>

          <city>Mountain View</city>

          <region>CA</region>

          <code>94043</code>

          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>

        <email>lorenzo@google.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date month="July" year="2010" />

    <area>Internet Area</area>

    <workgroup>6man</workgroup>

    <keyword>I-D</keyword>

    <keyword>Internet-Draft</keyword>

    <keyword>IPv6</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>On inter-router point-to-point links, it is useful for security and
      other reasons, to use 127-bit IPv6 prefixes. Such a practice parallels
      the use of 31-bit prefixes in IPv4 <xref format="default" pageno="false"
      target="RFC3021"></xref>. This document outlines some of these reasons
      and specifies that 127-bit IPv6 prefix lengths must be supported on such
      links.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section anchor="Conventions" title=" Conventions Used In This Document"
             toc="default">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
      document are to be interpreted as described in <xref format="default"
      pageno="false" target="RFC2119">RFC 2119</xref>.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Introduction" title="Introduction" toc="default">
      <t><xref format="default" pageno="false" target="RFC4291">RFC
      4291</xref> specifies that interface IDs for all unicast address, except
      those that start with the binary value 000, are required to be 64 bits
      long and to be constructed in Modified EUI-64 format. In addition, it
      defines the Subnet-Router anycast address, which is intended to be used
      for applications where a node needs to communicate with any one of the
      set of routers on a link.</t>

      <t>Some operators have been using 127-bit prefixes, but this has been
      discouraged due to conflicts with Subnet-Router anycast <xref
      format="default" pageno="false" target="RFC3627"></xref>. However, using
      64-bit prefixes creates security issues which are particularly
      problematic on inter-router links, and there are other valid reasons to
      use prefixes longer than 64 bits, in particular /127 (see <xref
      format="default" pageno="false" target="Rationale"></xref>).</t>

      <t>This document provides rationale for using 127-bit prefix lengths,
      reevaluates the reasons why doing so was considered harmful, and
      specifies that /127 prefixes MUST be supported on inter-router links
      configured for use as point-to-point links.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Scope" title="Scope Of This Memo" toc="default">
      <t>This document is applicable to cases where operators assign specific
      addresses on inter-router point-to-point links and do not rely on
      link-local addresses. Many operators assign specific addresses for
      purposes of network monitoring, reverse DNS resolution for traceroute
      and other management tools, EBGP peering sessions, and so on.</t>

      <t>For the purposes of this document, an inter-router point-to-point
      link is a link to which only two routers and no hosts are attached. This
      may include Ethernet links which are configured to be point-to-point. In
      such cases, there is no need to support Neighbor Discovery for address
      resolution, and other general scenarios like the use of stateless
      addresss autoconfiguration are not relevant.</t>

      <t>Links between a router and a host, or links to which both routers and
      hosts are attached, are out of scope of this document.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Problems"
             title="Problems identified with 127-bit prefix lengths in the past"
             toc="default">
      <t><xref format="default" pageno="false" target="RFC3627"></xref>
      discourages the use of 127-bit prefix lengths due to conflicts with the
      Subnet-Router anycast addresses, while stating that the utility of
      Subnet-Router Anycast for point-to-point links is questionable.</t>

      <t><xref format="default" pageno="false" target="RFC5375"></xref> also
      says the usage of 127-bit prefix lengths is not valid and should be
      strongly discouraged, but the stated reason for doing this is to be in
      compliance with <xref format="default" pageno="false"
      target="RFC3627"></xref>.</t>

      <t>Though the analysis in the RFCs are correct, it contradicts the
      reality as to the /127 discussion. Given that Subnet-Router Anycast is
      not currently used, the RFCs could have been to recommend that
      Subnet-Router Anycast be disabled on prefixes that are 127 bits
      long.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Rationale" title="Reasons for using longer prefixes"
             toc="default">
      <t>There are various reasons for network operators to use IPv6 prefix
      length greater than 64, particularly 127, for inter-router links.</t>

      <section anchor="Pingpong" title="Ping-pong issue" toc="default">
        <t>As described in <xref format="default" pageno="false"
        target="PINGPONG"></xref>, a forwarding loop may occur on a
        point-to-point link with a prefix length shorter than 127. This does
        not affect interfaces that perform Neighbor Discovery, but some
        point-to-point links, which uses medium such as SONET, do not use
        Neighbor Discovery. As a consequence, configuring any prefix length
        shorter than 127 bits on these links can create an attack vector in
        the network.</t>

        <t>The pingpong issue happens in case of IPv4 as well. But due to the
        scarcity of IPv4 address space, the current practice is to assgin long
        prefix lengths such as /30 or /31 <xref format="default"
        pageno="false" target="RFC3021"></xref> on point-to-point links, thus
        the problem did not come to the fore.</t>

        <t>The latest ICMPv6 specification <xref format="default"
        pageno="false" target="RFC4443"></xref> provides a solution to this
        issue by specifying that a router receiving a packet on a
        point-to-point link sent to an address on the link itself must not
        forward the packet back onto the same link, instead generating an
        ICMPv6 Destination Unreachable (Code 3) message. However, checking
        every packets for this condition could have some drawbacks. </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="Neighbor Cache" title="Neighbor Cache Exhaustion issue"
               toc="default">
        <t>As described in Section 4.3.2 of <xref format="default"
        pageno="false" target="RFC3756"></xref>, the use of a 64-bit prefix
        length on an inter-router link that uses Neighbor Discovery (e.g.,
        Ethernet) potentially allows for denial-of-service attacks on the
        routers on the link.</t>

        <t>Consider an Ethernet link between two routers A and B to which a
        /64 subnet has been assigned. A packet sent to any address on the /64
        (except the addresses of A and B) will cause the router attempting to
        forward it to create an new cache entry in state INCOMPLETE, send a
        Neighbor Solicitation message to be sent on the link, start a
        retransmit timer, and so on <xref format="default" pageno="false"
        target="RFC4861"></xref>.</t>

        <t>By sending a continuous stream of packets to a large number of the
        2^64 - 3 addresses on the link that are not assigned to the routers
        (one for each router and one for Subnet-Router Anycast), an attacker
        can cause the routers to create a large number of neighbor cache
        entries and send a large number of Neighbor Solicitation packets which
        will never receive replies, possibly consuming a disproportionate
        amount of memory and processing resources. Sending the packets to one
        of the 2^24 addresses on the link that have the same Solicited-Node
        multicast address as of one of the routers also causes the other
        router to spend disproportionate amounts of processing time discarding
        useless Neighbor Solicitation messages.</t>

        <t>Careful implementation and rate-limiting can limit the impact of
        such an attack, but are unlikely to neutralize it completely.
        Rate-limiting neighbor solicitation messages will reduce CPU usage,
        and following the garbage-collection recommendations in <xref
        format="default" pageno="false" target="RFC4861"></xref> will maintain
        reachability, but if the link is down and neighbor cache entries have
        expired while the attack is ongoing, legitimate traffic (for example,
        BGP sessions) over the link might never be re-established because the
        routers cannot resolve each others' IPv6 addresses to MAC
        addresses.</t>

        <t>This attack is not specific to point-to-point links, but is
        particularly harmful in the case of point-to-point backbone links,
        which may carry large amounts of traffic to many destinations over
        long distances.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="Others" title="Other reasons" toc="default">
        <t>Though address space conservation considerations are less important
        for IPv6 than they are in IPv4, it may still be desirable to use the
        smallest possible prefix to number links (and thus use, for example,
        /127 for point-to-point links). For example, a large end-site that is
        assigned a /48 of IPv6 space may not want to reserve a full /64 for
        every point-to-point link to avoid renumbering in the future.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Recommendations" title="Recommendations" toc="default">
      <list>
        <t>In light of the above reasons, this document specifies that 127-bit
        prefix lengths MUST be supported on inter-router point-to-point links,
        and proposes that such links MAY be assigned 127-bit prefix lengths.
        If such a prefix is assigned to a link, Subnet-Router Anycast MUST be
        disabled for the prefix.</t>

        <t>The <xref format="default" pageno="false" target="RFC4291" />is to
        be revised to allow longer prefix than /64, and state that
        Subnet-router anycast address MUST be disabled if the prefix length of
        the link is /127. </t>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Security Considerations" title="Security Considerations"
             toc="default">
      <t>This draft addresses, among other things, various security
      issues.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="IANAConsiderations" title="IANA Considerations"
             toc="default">
      <t>None.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Contributors" title="Contributors" toc="default">
      <t>Chris Morrow, morrowc@google.com</t>

      <t>Pekka Savola, pekkas@netcore.fi</t>

      <t>Remi Despres, remi.despres@free.fr</t>

      <t>Thomas Narten, narten@us.ibm.com</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Acknowledgments" title="Acknowledgments" toc="default">
      <t>We'd like to thank Ron Bonica, Pramod Srinivasan, Olivier Vautrin,
      Tomoya Yoshida, Warren Kumari and Tatsuya Jinmei for their helpful
      inputs.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <reference anchor="RFC2119">
        <front>
          <title abbrev="RFC Key Words">Key words for use in RFCs to Indicate
          Requirement Levels</title>

          <author fullname="Scott Bradner" initials="S." surname="Bradner">
            <organization>Harvard University</organization>

            <address>
              <postal>
                <street>1350 Mass. Ave.</street>

                <street>Cambridge</street>

                <street>MA 02138</street>
              </postal>

              <phone>- +1 617 495 3864</phone>

              <email>sob@harvard.edu</email>
            </address>
          </author>

          <date month="March" year="1997" />

          <area>General</area>

          <keyword>keyword</keyword>

          <abstract>
            <t>In many standards track documents several words are used to
            signify the requirements in the specification. These words are
            often capitalized. This document defines these words as they
            should be interpreted in IETF documents. Authors who follow these
            guidelines should incorporate this phrase near the beginning of
            their document: <list>
                <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL",
                "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and
                "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described
                in RFC 2119.</t>
              </list></t>

            <t>Note that the force of these words is modified by the
            requirement level of the document in which they are used.</t>
          </abstract>
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="BCP" value="14" />

        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="2119" />

        <format octets="4723"
                target="http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc2119.txt" type="TXT" />

        <format octets="17491"
                target="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/html/rfc2119.html"
                type="HTML" />

        <format octets="5777"
                target="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/xml/rfc2119.xml"
                type="XML" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RFC4291">
        <front>
          <title>IP Version 6 Addressing Architecture</title>

          <author fullname="R. Hinden" initials="R." surname="Hinden">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="S. Deering" initials="S." surname="Deering">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date month="February" year="2006" />

          <abstract>
            <t>This specification defines the addressing architecture of the
            IP Version 6 (IPv6) protocol. The document includes the IPv6
            addressing model, text representations of IPv6 addresses,
            definition of IPv6 unicast addresses, anycast addresses, and
            multicast addresses, and an IPv6 node's required
            addresses.&lt;/t&gt;&lt;t&gt; This document obsoletes RFC 3513,
            "IP Version 6 Addressing Architecture". [STANDARDS TRACK]</t>
          </abstract>
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="4291" />

        <format octets="52897"
                target="http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc4291.txt" type="TXT" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RFC4443">
        <front>
          <title>Internet Control Message Protocol (ICMPv6) for the Internet
          Protocol Version 6 (IPv6) Specification</title>

          <author fullname="A. Conta" initials="A." surname="Conta">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="S. Deering" initials="S." surname="Deering">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="M. Gupta" initials="M." surname="Gupta">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date month="March" year="2006" />

          <abstract>
            <t>This document describes the format of a set of control messages
            used in ICMPv6 (Internet Control Message Protocol). ICMPv6 is the
            Internet Control Message Protocol for Internet Protocol version 6
            (IPv6). [STANDARDS TRACK]</t>
          </abstract>
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="4443" />

        <format octets="48969"
                target="http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc4443.txt" type="TXT" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RFC4861">
        <front>
          <title>Neighbor Discovery for IP version 6 (IPv6)</title>

          <author fullname="T. Narten" initials="T." surname="Narten">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="E. Nordmark" initials="E." surname="Nordmark">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="W. Simpson" initials="W." surname="Simpson">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="H. Soliman" initials="H." surname="Soliman">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date month="September" year="2007" />

          <abstract>
            <t>This document specifies the Neighbor Discovery protocol for IP
            Version 6. IPv6 nodes on the same link use Neighbor Discovery to
            discover each other's presence, to determine each other's
            link-layer addresses, to find routers, and to maintain
            reachability information about the paths to active neighbors.
            [STANDARDS TRACK]</t>
          </abstract>
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="4861" />

        <format octets="235106"
                target="http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc4861.txt" type="TXT" />
      </reference>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <reference anchor="RFC3021">
        <front>
          <title>Using 31-Bit Prefixes on IPv4 Point-to-Point Links</title>

          <author fullname="A. Retana et al. " initials="A. " surname="Retana">
            <organization>Cisco Systems</organization>
          </author>

          <date month="December" year="2000" />

          <abstract>
            <t>With ever-increasing pressure to conserve IP address space on
            the Internet, it makes sense to consider where relatively minor
            changes can be made to fielded practice to improve numbering
            efficiency. One such change, proposed by this document, is to
            halve the amount of address space assigned to point-to-point links
            (common throughout the Internet infrastructure) by allowing the
            use of 31-bit subnet masks in a very limited way.</t>
          </abstract>
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="3021" />

        <format octets="" target="http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc3021.txt"
                type="TXT" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RFC3627">
        <front>
          <title>Use of /127 Prefix Length Between Routers Considered
          Harmful</title>

          <author fullname="P. Savola" initials="P." surname="Savola">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date month="September" year="2003" />

          <abstract>
            <t>In some cases, the operational decision may be to use IPv6 /127
            prefix lengths, especially on point-to-point links between
            routers. Under certain situations, this may lead to one router
            claiming both addresses due to subnet-router anycast being
            implemented. This document discusses the issue and offers a couple
            of solutions to the problem; nevertheless, /127 should be avoided
            between two routers.</t>
          </abstract>
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="3627" />

        <format octets="12436"
                target="http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc3627.txt" type="TXT" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RFC3756">
        <front>
          <title>IPv6 Neighbor Discovery (ND) Trust Models and Threats</title>

          <author fullname="P. Nikander" initials="P." surname="Nikander">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="J. Kempf" initials="J." surname="Kempf">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="E. Nordmark" initials="E." surname="Nordmark">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date month="May" year="2004" />

          <abstract>
            <t>The existing IETF standards specify that IPv6 Neighbor
            Discovery (ND) and Address Autoconfiguration mechanisms may be
            protected with IPsec Authentication Header (AH). However, the
            current specifications limit the security solutions to manual
            keying due to practical problems faced with automatic key
            management. This document specifies three different trust models
            and discusses the threats pertinent to IPv6 Neighbor Discovery.
            The purpose of this discussion is to define the requirements for
            Securing IPv6 Neighbor Discovery. This memo provides information
            for the Internet community.</t>
          </abstract>
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="3756" />

        <format octets="56674"
                target="http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc3756.txt" type="TXT" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RFC5375">
        <front>
          <title>IPv6 Unicast Address Assignment Considerations</title>

          <author fullname="G. Van de Velde" initials="G."
                  surname="Van de Velde">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="C. Popoviciu" initials="C." surname="Popoviciu">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="T. Chown" initials="T." surname="Chown">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="O. Bonness" initials="O." surname="Bonness">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="C. Hahn" initials="C." surname="Hahn">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date month="December" year="2008" />

          <abstract>
            <t>One fundamental aspect of any IP communications infrastructure
            is its addressing plan. With its new address architecture and
            allocation policies, the introduction of IPv6 into a network means
            that network designers and operators need to reconsider their
            existing approaches to network addressing. Lack of guidelines on
            handling this aspect of network design could slow down the
            deployment and integration of IPv6. This document aims to provide
            the information and recommendations relevant to planning the
            addressing aspects of IPv6 deployments. The document also provides
            IPv6 addressing case studies for both an enterprise and an ISP
            network. This memo provides information for the Internet
            community.</t>
          </abstract>
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="5375" />

        <format octets="83809"
                target="http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc5375.txt" type="TXT" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="PINGPONG"
                 target="http://tools.ietf.org/html/draft-ietf-ipngwg-p2p-pingpong-00">
        <front>
          <title>Avoiding ping-pong packets on point-to-point links</title>

          <author fullname="Junichiro Itojun Hagino" initials="H"
                  surname="Hagino">
            <organization />
          </author>

          <author fullname="Tatsuya Jimmei" initials="T" surname="Jimmei">
            <organization />
          </author>
        </front>
      </reference>
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
