<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<rfc category="std" docName="draft-ietf-netext-bulk-re-registration-00"
     ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="PMIPv6 Bulk Re-registration">Bulk Re-registration for Proxy
    Mobile IPv6</title>
    <author role="editor" fullname="Fuad Abinader" initials="F." surname="Abinader">
	  <organization>Instituto Nokia de Tecnologia</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Av. Torquato Tapajos, 7200 - Km. 12 - Col Terra Nova</street>
          <city>Manaus</city>
          <region>AM</region>
          <code>69048-660</code>
          <country>BRAZIL</country>
        </postal>
        <email>fuad.junior@indt.org.br</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Sri Gundavelli" initials="S." surname="Gundavelli">
      <organization>Cisco</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>170 West Tasman Drive</street>

          <city>San Jose</city>

          <region>CA</region>

          <code>95134</code>

          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>

        <phone></phone>

        <facsimile></facsimile>

        <email>sgundave@cisco.com</email>

        <uri></uri>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Kent Leung" initials="K." surname="Leung">
      <organization>Cisco</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>170 West Tasman Drive</street>

          <city>San Jose</city>

          <region>CA</region>

          <code>95134</code>

          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>

        <phone></phone>

        <facsimile></facsimile>

        <email>kleung@cisco.com</email>

        <uri></uri>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Suresh Krishnan" initials="S." surname="Krishnan">
      <organization>Ericsson</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>8400 Decarie Blvd.</street>

          <city>Town of Mount Royal</city>

          <region>QC</region>

          <code></code>

          <country>Canada</country>
        </postal>

        <phone>+1 514 345 7900 x42871</phone>

        <facsimile></facsimile>

        <email>suresh.krishnan@ericsson.com</email>

        <uri></uri>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Domagoj Premec" initials="D." surname="Premec">
      <organization>Unaffiliated</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>

          <city></city>

          <code></code>

          <region></region>

          <country></country>
        </postal>

        <email>domagoj.premec@gmail.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date year="2010" />

    <area>Internet Area</area>

    <workgroup>Netext Working Group</workgroup>

    <keyword>Proxy Mobile IPv6</keyword>

    <keyword>PMIPv6</keyword>

    <keyword>bulk registrations</keyword>

    <keyword>MN group ID</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>Proxy Mobile IPv6 specification requires the Mobile Access Gateway
      (MAG) to send a separate Proxy Binding Update (PBU) message to the Local
      Mobility Agent (LMA) for each mobile node (MN) to renew the MN&rsquo;s
      mobility binding. This document defines a mechanism by which a MAG can
      update the mobility bindings of multiple MNs attached to it with a
      single PBU message to the serving LMA. This document also specifies a
      new mobility option that can be used by the mobility entities in a Proxy
      Mobile IPv6 domain for carrying the group affiliation of a mobile node
      in any of the mobility signaling messages.</t>
    </abstract>

    <note title="Requirements Language">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
      document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
      target="RFC2119">RFC 2119</xref>.</t>
    </note>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>The Proxy Mobile IPv6 base specification <xref
      target="RFC5213"></xref> uses the mobile node identifier in the mobility
      signaling messages for identifying the mobile node. However, the
      signaling messages lack the capability to identify a set of mobile nodes
      which have a common characteristic. A group identifier associated with a
      mobile node enables the ability to perform protocol operation on a set
      of mobile nodes via a single transaction. The group identifier provides
      a more optimal mechanism for protocol operation which would otherwise
      require multiple atomic transactions on a per mobile node basis.
      Following are some of the use-cases where such identifier can be
      used.</t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>In a blade architecture system running the local mobility anchor
          service, all the mobile node sessions anchored on a given card can
          be part of one single group. When there is a failure on a specific
          card, the local mobility anchor can initiate the revocation
          signaling to the mobile access gateway by sending a single
          revocation request carrying the group identifier.</t>

          <t>For periodic re-registrations, the mobile access gateway may send
          a single re-registration message for each of the mobile nodes'
          groups and perform re-registrations for all the mobile node's that
          are part of that group.</t>

          <t>The mobile access gateway or the local mobility anchor in a proxy
          mobile IPv6 domain may choose to revoke the registration of mobile
          node associated with a specific realm. In such cases the mobile
          access gateway or the local mobility anchor can perform the binding
          revocation signaling using the group ID associated with a specific
          set of mobile nodes.</t>
        </list>The remainder of this document defines a new mobility option,
      named Mobile Node Group Identifier option, that can be used by a local
      mobility anchor and a mobile access gateway for exchanging the mobile
      node's group identifier as well as its application for bulk periodic
      re-registrations.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Terminology">
      <t>General mobility related terminology is defined in <xref
      target="RFC3775"></xref>. Additional PMIPv6 specific terminology can be
      found in <xref target="RFC5213"></xref>.</t>

      <t><list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="PMIPv6 domain"><vspace blankLines="0" />Network
          providing the network based IP mobility service as defined in <xref
          target="RFC5213"></xref>.</t>

          <t hangText="PMIPv6"><vspace blankLines="0" />Proxy Mobile IPv6
          protocol specified in <xref target="RFC5213"></xref>.</t>

          <t hangText="Bulk re-registration"><vspace
          blankLines="0" />PBU/PBAck message exchange where the bulk
          re-registration flag (B) is set to 1</t>

          <t hangText="Bulk re-registration set"><vspace blankLines="0" />a
          set of MNs identified by the Mobile Node Group ID option to which the
          bulk re-registration operation applies.</t>
        </list></t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="overview" title="Bulk Re-registration Overview">
      <section title="Motivation for bulk re-registration">
        <t>In a PMIPv6 domain a single LMA serves multiple MAGs and the
        capacity of the LMA in terms of the number of attached MNs can be
        quite large. It can be expected that LMA capacity in managed networks
        may easily exceed hundreds of thousands or more attached MNs.</t>

        <t>The following simple formula gives an estimate of the average
        number of re-registration transactions per second as a function of the
        number of registered MNs and the binding lifetime period:</t>

        <t>transactions/sec = (number of registered MNs) / (binding
        lifetime*4)</t>

        <t>For 50.000 MNs and the binding lifetime of half an hour this gives:
        50000 MNs / 1800 sec = 27,7 transactions/sec</t>

        <t>Based on the above formula it is apparent that the default
        re-registration process where the MAG sends a separate message for
        each MN is inefficient or suboptimal. These re-registration messages
        consume significant network resources both in terms of processing
        power at the LMA and MAG and network bandwidth.</t>

        <t>This document proposes an optimization of the re-registration
        process by which the signaling load for re-registration can be reduced
        to a single transaction per MAG, irrespective of the number of
        attached MNs.</t>

        <t>According to this proposal a MAG adds a MN to a set of MNs
        re-registered in a bulk mode by setting the bulk re-registration bit
        (B) in the PBU message. The PBU message sent in response contains the
        Mobile Node Group Identifier mobility option which is defined later in
        this document. In the context of bulk re-registrations the Mobile Node
        Group Identifier is an opaque identifier that is allocated by the LMA
        and which uniquely identifies the bulk set to which the MN was
        added.</t>

        <t>A MAG requests a bulk re-registration for a set of MNs by sending a
        single PBU message which includes a Mobile Node Group Identifier
        mobility option and the LMA extends the binding lifetime of MNs that
        are members of that group. By using this method, the MAG and LMA
        accomplish the re-registration of MNs attached to a MAG in a single
        transaction. The number of re-registration transactions at the LMA
        becomes independent of the number of attached MNs; instead it is
        dependent only on the number of MAGs (i.e. bulk re-registration 
		sets).</t>

        <t>In addition to minimizing the signaling overhead associated with
        the lifetime extension of the mobility bindings, the MAG and LMA may
        use a single timer per bulk re-registration set to monitor the binding
        lifetime of all the member MNs instead of an individual timer per
        MN.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Bulk re-registration operation">
        <t>The bulk re-registration mechanism allows the MAG and the LMA to
        extend the binding lifetime for a number of MNs with a single
        transaction. The MAG and LMA maintain a set of MNs that can be
        re-registered in bulk mode. Such set is called a bulk re-registration
        set and is a subset of the MNs attached to a MAG. There can be
        multiple bulk re-registration sets for a given MAG-LMA pair; however, 
		there can be only one MAG and one LMA associated with a given bulk
		re-registration set.</t>
		
		<t> Initially 
        the bulk re-registration set is empty. MAG requests to add individual
        MNs to the bulk set by sending a regular PBU message that identifies
        an individual MN and additionally the bulk registration flag in the
        message is set to 1. Based on the received bulk re-registration bit
        the LMA adds the MN to the bulk re-registration set and responds with
        the PBAck message with the bulk registration flag (B) set to 1. The
        LMA identifies the bulk re-registration set to which the MN was added
        by including the Mobile Node Group ID option in the PBAck message.</t>

        <t>Once there is a non-empty bulk re-registration set, MAG can request
        to extend the binding lifetime for all MNs that are part of the bulk
        re-registration set by sending a PBU message with the bulk (B) bit set
        and by including the Mobile Node Group ID identify the bulk
        re-registration set. Such PBU message lacks any options that identify
        an individual MN. In particular, the MAG omits both the MN ID (Mobile
        Node Identifier) and the HNP (Home Network Prefix) options. From that,
		dual operations that try to operate (either adding or removing MNs) 
		over the current bulk re-registration set while at the same time 
		performing the bulk re-registration operation itself are not possible,
		and must be done with the use of two separate PBU messages.</t>

        <t>There may be different triggers that cause the MAG to request a
        bulk re-registration. Typically the trigger is the binding lifetime
        expiry of a MN that is a member of a bulk re-registration set. There
        could be other triggers as well, but they may be implementation or
        domain specific and outside the scope of this specification.</t>

        <t>When the MAG requests the MN to be added to the bulk
        re-registration set, the LMA includes the Mobile Node Group Identifier
        mobility option in the PBAck message. The Mobile Node Group Identifier
        is an opaque identifier allocated by the LMA that uniquely identifies
        the bulk set at the LMA to which the MN was added. The MAG associates
        the MN with the Mobile Node Group Identifier received in the
        PBAck.</t>

        <t>The MAG includes the Mobile Node Group Identifier mobility option
        set to the value previously received from the LMA to request the bulk
        re-registration for the MNs that are part of this particular bulk
        re-registration set. The MAG may include multiple instances of the
        Mobile Node Group Identifier option in the PBU message to request
        lifetime refreshment for several bulk sets in a single message.</t>

        <t>The LMA extends the mobility binding of all MNs that are members of
        indicated bulk re-registration sets and responds with PBAck message
        echoing the received Mobile Node Group Identifier mobility
        options.</t>

        <t>A MAG may remove a MN from a bulk re-registration set by sending a
        regular PBU message identifying the MN to be removed and with the bulk
        re-registration flag set to 0.</t>

        <t>When requested to add a MN to the bulk re-registration set, the LMA
        may reject the request. In this case the LMA processes the PBU message
        as if the bulk re-registration flag was not set and responds with
        PBAck message where the bulk re-registration flag is set to 0.</t>
		
		<t>Dual operations that try to extend binding time to some bulk 
		re-registration sets while at the same time terminating bindings with 
		other bulk re-registration sets (e.g. by setting zero lifetime) in the 
		same PBU message are not possible; as a consequence, these must be 
		performed with two separate PBU messages.</t>

        <t></t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Message formats">
      <t>This section introduces extensions to PBU and PBAck messages used in
      this specification.</t>

      <section title="Proxy Binding Update message" anchor="pbu_message">
        <figure anchor="PBU-format">
            <artwork><![CDATA[ 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
                                +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
                                |            Sequence #         |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|A|H|L|K|M|R|P|B|   Reserved    |            Lifetime           |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                                                               |
.                                                               .
.                        Mobility options                       .
.                                                               .
|                                                               |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
]]></artwork>
          </figure>

        <t>A Proxy Binding Update message is defined in the <xref
        target="RFC5213"></xref>. A new flag (B) is defined for the Binding
        Update message, as seen on <xref target="PBU-format"/>.</t>

        <t>Bulk Registration Flag (B)</t>

        <t>If the bulk registration flag (B) is set to 1, then the PBU message
        is a request to add the MN to the bulk re-registration set. If the
        bulk registration flag (B) is set to 0 and if the MN is found to be a
        member of the bulk re-registration set, then the MN is removed from
        the bulk re-registration set.</t>

        <t>Mobility Options</t>

        <t>For descriptions of the mobility options, refer to <xref
        target="RFC5213"></xref>. When the PBU message is sent to refresh
        bindings in a bulk mode, the message MUST contain at least one Mobile
        Node Group Identifier mobility option and does not contain the MN-ID
        and the HNP mobility options.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Proxy Binding Acknowledgment message" anchor="pback_message">
        <figure anchor="PBAck-message"
            title="Proxy Binding Acknowledgment message">
            <artwork><![CDATA[ 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
                                +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
                                |   Status      |K|R|P|B|  Res. |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|         Sequence #            |           Lifetime            |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                                                               |
.                                                               .
.                        Mobility options                       .
.                                                               .
|                                                               |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
]]></artwork>
          </figure>

        <t>A Proxy Binding Acknowledgment message is defined in the <xref
        target="RFC5213"></xref>. A new flag (B) is defined for the Binding
        Acknowledgment message, as seen on <xref target="PBAck-message"/>.</t>

        <t>Bulk Registration Flag (B)</t>

        <t>A new flag (B) is included in the Binding Acknowledgment message to
        indicate to the MAG that the MN was successfully added to the bulk
        re-registration set. The flag MUST NOT be set to the value of 1 if it
        was not set to 1 in the corresponding PBU message.</t>

        <t>Mobility Options</t>

        <t>For descriptions of these options, refer to <xref
        target="RFC5213"></xref>. When the bulk registration flag is set to 1
        in the PBU message, then the PBAck message MUST also contain the
        Mobile Node Group Identifier mobility option. When the Mobile Node
        Group Identifier mobility option(s) were included in the PBU message,
        the PBAck message echoes back the Mobile Node Group Identifier options
        from the PBU message.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Mobile Node Group Identifier Option " anchor="mnid_option">
        <t>A new option, Mobile Node Group Identifier option is defined for
        using it in Proxy Binding Update and Proxy Binding Acknowledgement
        messages exchanged between a local mobility anchor and mobile access
        gateway. This option is used for carrying the mobile node's group
        identifier.</t>

        <t>The alignment requirement for this option is 4n.</t>

        <figure anchor="GID_option"
                title="Mobile Node Group Identifier Option">
          <artwork><![CDATA[
      0                   1                   2                   3
      0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
     +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
     |      Type     |   Length      |           Sub-type            |
     +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
     |                 Mobile Node Group Identifier                  |
     +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+

]]></artwork>
        </figure>

        <t><list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="Type"><vspace blankLines="0" />&lt;IANA&gt;</t>

            <t hangText="Length"><vspace blankLines="0" />8-bit unsigned
            integer indicating the length in octets of the option, excluding
            the type and length fields. The value for this field MUST be set
            to 6.</t>

            <t hangText="Sub-type"><vspace blankLines="0" />Identifies the
            specific group type. This number space will be managed by the
            IANA.</t>

            <t hangText="Mobile Node Group Identifier ">A 32-bit field
            containing the mobile node's group identifier.</t>
          </list>The Mobile Node's Group Identifier option reflects the group
        affiliation that is local to the specific LMA-MAG pair. The specific
		value for the Mobile Node group Identifier is always determined by the
		LMA on the PBAck message, and must be used by the MAG on all future
		bulk re-registration procedures for that bulk re-registration set.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="MAG Operation">
      <t>The conceptual Binding Update List entry data structure maintained by
      the MAG, described in Section 6.1 of <xref target="RFC5213"></xref>,
      MUST be extended to store the mobile node's group identifier.</t>

      <t>Bulk re-registration operations are optional to PMIPv6 <xref 
	  target="RFC5213"/>, so the Mobile Node Group Identifier option MAY be used 
	  in the PBU message sent by the MAG to the LMA only when a bulk re-registration 
	  operation (refresh/termination) is intended. When this option is included, the
      identifier value in the option MUST be set to the mobile node's group
      identifier that was assigned previously by the LMA.</t>

      <t>When a new MN attaches to a MAG, the MAG registers the MN with the
      LMA by sending the PBU message formatted as described in <xref
      target="RFC5213"></xref>. Additionally, the MAG MAY set the bulk
      registration flag (B) in the PBU message to 1 to request the LMA to add
      the MN to the bulk registration set. The decision to request the bulk
      re-registration mode for a MN is a matter of local policy at the MAG and
      is outside the scope of this specification.</t>

      <t>The MAG SHALL maintain a separate bulk re-registration sets for each
      LMA.</t>

      <t>The MAG SHALL add the MN to its bulk re-registration set when it
      receives a PBAck message with the bulk registration bit set to 1 and if
      the corresponding PBU message was requesting the LMA to add the MN to
      the bulk re-registration set. The MAG SHALL associate the MN being
      registered with the Mobile Node Group Identifier received in the PBAck
      message.</t>

      <t>When the binding lifetime of any MN contained in the bulk
      re-registration set is about to expire, the MAG SHALL request the bulk
      re-registration by sending the PBU message containing the Mobile Node
      Group Identifier mobility option. The length of the Mobile Node Group
      Identifier option may be 0 in which case the MAG is requesting a
      refreshment of the binding lifetime for all MN attached to that MAG that
      were registered with the B flag set. Alternatively, the MAG MAY include
      one or more Mobile Node Group Identifier options containing the values
      that were indicated by the LMA in the PBAck messages when the MN was
      added to the bulk set. In this case the MAG asks for refreshment of
      specific bulk sets indicated by the Mobile Node Group Identifier
      options. The MAG SHALL NOT include the MN ID and the HNP options in the
      PBU message requesting bulk refreshment.</t>

      <t>The MAG MAY trigger a bulk re-registration at any time. The policy
      and exact conditions for these additional triggers are outside of scope
      of this specification.</t>

      <t>When the MAG receives a PBAck message indicating success and which
      echoes the Mobile Node Group Identifier options that were included in
      the corresponding PBU message, the MAG SHALL update the binding lifetime
      of all MNs belonging to the indicated groups to the lifetime value
      contained in the PBAck message. If in the case of bulk re-registration
      the PBAck message repeatedly indicates an error, the MAG SHALL fall back
      to individual re-registration mode.</t>

      <t>Instead of maintaining one timer per MN, the MAG MAY start a single
      timer per bulk registration set to oversee the binding lifetime of all
      MNs that are members of that bulk registration set.</t>

      <t>If the MAG sets the bulk re-registration bit to 1 in a PBU message
      but the bulk registration bit (B) is set to 0 in a PBAck message, the
      MAG SHALL process the PBAck message as per <xref
      target="RFC5213"></xref>. In addition, the MAG SHALL infer that the LMA
      does not support bulk re-registration procedure. The MAG SHALL switch to
      regular, per-MN re-registration mode as described in <xref
      target="RFC5213"></xref>. The MAG MAY retry the bulk re-registration
      procedure after sufficient time has elapsed from the previous
      unsuccessful bulk re-registration. This amount of time SHOULD be
      configurable at the MAG.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="LMA operation">
      <t>The conceptual Binding Cache entry data structure maintained by the
      LMA, described in Section 5.1 of <xref target="RFC5213"></xref>, MUST be
      extended to store the mobile node's group identifier.</t>

      <t>The Mobile Node Group Identifier option MAY be used in the PBAck
      message sent by the LMA to the MAG. When this option is included, the
      identifier value in the option MUST be set to the mobile node's group
      identifier, local to the local mobility anchor.</t>

      <t>When the LMA receives a PBU message with a bulk registration bit (B)
      set to 1, the LMA SHALL first process the PBU message as per <xref
      target="RFC5213"></xref>. Upon successful processing of the message, the
      LMA SHALL perform additional processing of the PBU message as described
      further below for bulk mode re-registrations.</t>

      <t>If the bulk re-registration flag in the PBU message is set to 1, the
      LMA MAY add the MN(s) indicated in the PBU to the set of MNs
      re-registered in a bulk mode, subject to the local policy. The decision
      whether to enable bulk re-registration mode is a matter of local policy
      at the LMA and is outside the scope of this specification.</t>

      <t>If the LMA decides to accept the bulk re-registration mode for the
      MN, it SHALL add the MN to a bulk re-registration set. The LMA SHALL
      maintain distinct bulk re-registrations set for each MAG and there could
      be several such sets per single MAG.</t>

      <t>Upon adding the MN to the bulk re-registration set, the LMA SHALL
      respond with the PBAck message containing the bulk registration bit set
      to 1. The LMA SHALL include the Mobile Node Group Identifier option in
      the PBAck message. The Mobile Node Group Identifier is allocated by the
      LMA and identifies the particular bulk set to which the MN is
      assigned.</t>

      <t>The PBU message without the MN ID and HNP options but including the
      Mobile Node Group Identifier mobility option is a valid message and
      indicates a request for bulk mode re-registration of all MNs that are
      members of the indicated bulk re-registration set. There MAY be several
      Mobile Node Group Identifier options in the PBU message, in which case
      the MAG requests the bulk refreshment of all MNs that are members of the
      indicated bulk sets. If the length of the Mobile Node Group Identifier
      option is zero, the MAG is requesting a lifetime refreshment of all the
      MN attached to the MAG that are members of any bulk set. The LMA SHALL
      extend the binding lifetime of all affected MNs attached to the MAG that
      sent the bulk PBU.</t>

      <t>The LMA SHALL set the binding lifetime of all MNs re-registered in a
      bulk mode to expire at the same point in time.</t>

      <t>Upon successful processing of bulk mode re-registration request, the
      LMA MUST respond with a PBAck message indicating success and echoing the
      mobility options received from the PBU. The lifetime in the PBAck
      message indicates the time when binding cache entries of affected MNs
      will expire.</t>

      <t>The LMA MAY reject the request for bulk re-registration. In this case
      the LMA MUST NOT update binding cache entries of any MNs and SHALL
      respond with PBAck indicating the reason for the rejection in the status
      code.</t>

      <t>After successfully processing the bulk PBU message, the LMA SHOULD
      start a single timer to oversee the binding lifetime of all MNs affected
      by this bulk re-registration transaction.</t>

      <t>The LMA not supporting this specification ignores the bulk
      re-registration bit (B) and the Mobile Node Group Identifier option in a
      PBU message and processes the message as per the baseline specification
      <xref target="RFC5213"></xref>. In this case the PBAck message sent in
      response contains the bulk re-registration bit (B) set to 0.</t>

      <t>If the LMA that does not support this specification receives a bulk
      PBU message that does not contain any options identifying a particular
      MN then the LMA responds with the PBAck message where the status field
      contains one of the following error codes:<list>
          <t>MISSING_HOME_NETWORK_PREFIX_OPTION</t>

          <t>MISSING_MN_IDENTIFIER_OPTION</t>
        </list>These error codes are defined in the baseline specification
      <xref target="RFC5213"></xref>.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
	  <t>This specification specifies a new flag (B) in the Proxy Binding 
	     Update (PBU) and Proxy Binding Acknowledgement (PBAck) messages of 
		 PMIPv6 <xref target="RFC5213"/>. This flag is defined in sections 
		 <xref target="pbu_message" /> and <xref target="pback_message" />.
	     IANA is requested to allocate the new flag (B) in the Proxy Binding
         Update and Proxy Binging Acknowledgement messages from the <xref 
		 target="RFC5213"/> Proxy Binding Update Flags and the <xref 
		 target="RFC5213"/> proxy Binding Acknowledgment Flags registries.</t>
	
      <t>This specification defines a new Mobility Header option, the Mobile
      Node Group Identifier option. This option is described in section <xref
      target="GID_option"></xref>. The Type value for this option needs to be
      assigned from the same numbering space as allocated for the other
      mobility options (as defined in <xref target="RFC3775"></xref>). Also, the
	  Sub-type field of the Mobile Node Group Identifier option (as defined in
	  <xref target="mnid_option"/>) must have its own brand-new, unique number 
	  pace allocated and managed by IANA.</t>

      <t>Note to RFC Editor: this section may be removed on publication as an
      RFC.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>The mobile node's identifier is always present in the Proxy Mobile
      IPv6 signaling messages and additionally carrying the group identity of
      the mobile node introduces similar vulnerabilities. Specifically, it
      exposes the group affiliation of the user and may result in compromising
      the privacy of the user or the location information.</t>

      <t>The Mobile Node Group Identifier option defined in this specification
      is for use in Proxy Binding Update and Proxy Binding Acknowledgement
      messages. This option is carried like any other mobility header option
      as specified in <xref target="RFC3775"></xref> and does not require any
      special security considerations.</t>

      <t>The bulk re-registration mechanism does not introduce any new
      security threat or vulnerability to the PMIPv6 specification.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>Thanks to Jouni Korhonen and Basavaraj Patil for their review and input.</t>

      <t>The authors would like to acknowledge the prior discussions on this
      topic in netlmm mailing list.</t>

    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <reference anchor="RFC2119">
        <front>
          <title abbrev="RFC Key Words">Key words for use in RFCs to Indicate
          Requirement Levels</title>

          <author fullname="Scott Bradner" initials="S." surname="Bradner">
            <organization>Harvard University</organization>

            <address>
              <postal>
                <street>1350 Mass. Ave.</street>

                <street>Cambridge</street>

                <street>MA 02138</street>
              </postal>

              <phone>- +1 617 495 3864</phone>

              <email>sob@harvard.edu</email>
            </address>
          </author>

          <date month="March" year="1997" />

          <area>General</area>

          <keyword>keyword</keyword>
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="BCP" value="14" />

        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="2119" />

        <format octets="4723" target="ftp://ftp.isi.edu/in-notes/rfc2119.txt"
                type="TXT" />

        <format octets="17491"
                target="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/html/rfc2119.html"
                type="HTML" />

        <format octets="5777"
                target="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/xml/rfc2119.xml"
                type="XML" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RFC3775">
        <front>
          <title>Mobility Support in IPv6</title>

          <author fullname="D. Johnson" initials="D." surname="Johnson">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="C. Perkins" initials="C." surname="Perkins">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="J. Arkko" initials="J." surname="Arkko">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date month="June" year="2004" />
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="3775" />

        <format octets="393514"
                target="ftp://ftp.isi.edu/in-notes/rfc3775.txt" type="TXT" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RFC5213">
        <front>
          <title>Proxy Mobile IPv6</title>

          <author fullname="S. Gundavelli" initials="S." surname="Gundavelli">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="K. Leung" initials="K." surname="Leung">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="V. Devarapalli" initials="V."
                  surname="Devarapalli">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="K. Chowdhury" initials="K." surname="Chowdhury">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="B. Patil" initials="B." surname="Patil">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date month="August" year="2008" />
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="5213" />

        <format octets="226902"
                target="ftp://ftp.isi.edu/in-notes/rfc5213.txt" type="TXT" />
      </reference>
    </references>

  </back>
</rfc>
