<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
    <!ENTITY RFC2119 PUBLIC '' 
      'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml'>
    <!ENTITY RFC3269 PUBLIC '' 
      'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3269.xml'>
    <!ENTITY RFC4282 PUBLIC '' 
      'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4282.xml'>
    <!ENTITY RFC4283 PUBLIC '' 
      'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4283.xml'>
    <!ENTITY RFC4285 PUBLIC '' 
      'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4285.xml'>
    <!ENTITY RFC5213 PUBLIC '' 
      'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5213.xml'>
    <!ENTITY RFC5844 PUBLIC '' 
      'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5844.xml'>
    <!ENTITY RFC4303 PUBLIC '' 
      'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4303.xml'>
    <!ENTITY RFC6275 PUBLIC '' 
      'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6275.xml'>
    <!ENTITY RFC4877 PUBLIC '' 
      'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4877.xml'>
    <!ENTITY RFC5555 PUBLIC '' 
      'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5555.xml'>
    <!ENTITY RFC6459 PUBLIC '' 
      'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6459.xml'>
    <!ENTITY RFC1035 PUBLIC '' 
      'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1035.xml'>
    <!ENTITY WIFI PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.gundavelli-v6ops-community-wifi-svcs.xml'> 



]>

<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>


<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>

<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc iprnotified="no" ?>
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<?rfc autobreaks="yes" ?>

<rfc category="std"
     ipr="trust200902"
     docName="draft-ietf-netext-rfc5149bis-02.txt"
     updates="5213"
     obsoletes="5149">
 <front>
  <title abbrev="Service Selection">Service Selection for Mobile IPv6 and Proxy Mobile IPv6</title>
  <author initials='J.' surname="Korhonen" fullname='Jouni Korhonen'>
   <organization abbrev="Nokia Siemens Networks">Nokia Siemens Networks</organization>
   <address>
    <postal>
     <street>Linnoitustie 6</street>
     <code>FIN-02600 Espoo</code>
     <country>Finland</country>
    </postal>
    <email>jouni.nospam@gmail.com</email>
   </address>
  </author>

  <author initials='U.' surname="Nilsson" fullname='Ulf Nilsson'>

   <organization abbrev="TeliaSonera">TeliaSonera Corporation</organization>

   <address>
    <postal>
     <street>Marbackagatan 11</street>
     <code>S-123 86 Farsta</code>
     <country>SWEDEN</country>
    </postal>
    <email>ulf.s.nilsson@teliasonera.com</email>
   </address>
  </author>

  <author initials='V' surname="Devarapalli" fullname='Vijay Devarapalli'>
    <address>
    <email>dvijay@gmail.com</email>
    </address>
  </author>
  
  <date year="2012"/>
  <area>Internet</area>
  <workgroup>Network-Based Mobility Extensions (Netext)</workgroup>
  
  <abstract>
   <t>In some Mobile IPv6 deployments, identifying the mobile node or the
   mobility service subscriber is not enough to distinguish between
   multiple services possibly provisioned to the mobile node and
   its mobility service subscription.  A capability to specify different
   services in addition to the mobile node identity can be leveraged to
   provide flexibility for mobility service providers on provisioning
   multiple services to one mobility service subscription.  This
   document describes a Service Selection Mobility Option for both
   conventional Mobile IPv6 and Proxy Mobile IPv6 that is intended to
   assist home agents and local mobility agents to make a specific service selection for the mobility service subscription during the binding registration procedure. This specification updates RFC5213 and obsoletes RFC5149.
   </t>
  </abstract>

  <note title="Requirements">
   <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
   "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
   document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
   target="RFC2119">RFC 2119</xref>.</t>
  </note>
 </front>

 <middle>
  <section title="Introduction">
   <t>Mobile IPv6 <xref target="RFC6275"/> can identify mobile nodes in various ways, including
   home addresses, Network Access Identifiers (NAIs) <xref target="RFC4282"/><xref target="RFC4283"/>, and
   credentials suitable for the Internet Key Exchange Protocol version 2
   (IKEv2) <xref target="RFC4877"/>. Proxy Mobile IPv6 <xref target="RFC5213"/> uses Home Network Prefix (HNP) and/or Mobile Node Identifier <xref target="RFC4283"/>. In some Mobile IPv6 deployments, identifying the
   mobile node or the mobility service subscriber via a Proxy Mobile
   IPv6 client <xref target="RFC5213"/> (hereafter, the mobile node and the Proxy Mobile IPv6 client are used interchangeably) is not enough to distinguish between multiple services possibly provisioned to the mobile node
   <!-- and its mobility service subscription-->.
   </t>
   <t>The capability to specify different services in addition to the
   mobile node identity can be leveraged to provide flexibility for
   mobility service providers to provide multiple services within the
   same mobility service subscription.  For example:
   </t>
   <t><list style="symbols">
   <t>Provide an enterprise data access for which the mobility service
      provider hosts connectivity and mobility services on behalf of the
      enterprise.</t>
   <t>Provide access to service domains that are otherwise not
      accessible from public networks because of some mobility service
      provider's business reasons.</t>
   <t>Provide simultaneous access to different service domains that are
      separated based on policies of the mobility service provider.</t>
   <t>Enable easier policy and quality of service assignment for
      mobility service providers based on the subscribed services.</t>
   <t>In the absence of a specifically indicated service, the home agent
      MUST act as if the default service, plain Internet access, had
      been requested.  There is no absolute requirement that this
      default service be allowed to all subscribers, but it is highly
      RECOMMENDED in order to avoid having normal subscribers employ
      operator-specific configuration values in order to get basic
      service.</t>   
   </list></t>
   <t>This document describes a Service Selection Mobility Option for
   (Proxy) Mobile IPv6 that is intended to assist home agents or local mobility agents to make specific service selections for the mobility service subscription during the binding registration procedure.  The service selection may affect home agent or local mobility agent routing decisions, Home Address or Home Network Prefix assignment policies, firewall settings, charging and security policies among others.  The Service Selection option should be used in every  (Proxy) Binding Update or Acknowledgement message.
   </t>
   <t>Some of the potential use-cases were listed earlier in this section.
   The general aim is better manageability of services and service
   provisioning from the point of view of both operators and service
   providers.  However, it should be understood that there are potential
   deployment possibilities where selecting a certain service may
   restrict simultaneous access to other services from a user's point of
   view.  For example, services may be located in different
   administrative domains or external customer networks that practice
   excessive filtering of inbound and outbound traffic.
   </t>
   <t>There are existing deployments using the Service Selection option. 3GPP PMIPv6-based Evolved Packet Core (EPC) <xref target="RFC6459"/> deployments use the Service Selection option to carry the Access Point Name (APN) <xref target="TS.23003"/>. Recently, service provider Wi-Fi services over residential architectures <xref target="I-D.gundavelli-v6ops-community-wifi-svcs"/> that intend to integrate into e.g., 3GPP EPC using PMIPv6, need Service Selection option again to carry the APN information for identifying a particular routing domain.
   </t>
  </section>


  <section title="Service Selection Mobility Option" anchor="opt">
   <t>At most one Service Selection Mobility option SHOULD be included in any
   (Proxy) Binding Update message. If and only if the (Proxy) Binding Update message included the Service Selection Option, then the corresponding (Proxy) Binding Acknowledgement message SHOULD also contain the Service Selection option with the service name in the Identifier.
   </t>
   <t>If the (Proxy) Binding Update message includes any authorization-related options (such as the Binding Authorization Data option <xref target="RFC6275"/>) or authentication related options (such as the Mobility Message Authentication option <xref target="RFC4285"/>), then the Service Selection option MUST appear before any mobility message authorization- or authentication-related options.
   </t>
   <t>The Service Selection option SHOULD NOT be sent to a correspondent
   node.  The mobile node cannot assume that the correspondent node has
   any knowledge about a specific service selection made between the
   mobile node and the home agent.
   </t>
   <t>The Service Selection option has no alignment requirement as such.

   <figure title="Service Selection Mobility Option" anchor="figopt">
<artwork><![CDATA[
 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
                                +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
                                |  Type = 20    |   Length      |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
| Identifier...                                                 ~
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
]]></artwork>
   </figure>
   </t>

   <t><list style="symbols">
    <t>Type: 8-bit identifier set to 20 of the type of the skipable
      mobility option.
    </t>
    <t>Length: 8-bit unsigned integer, representing the length of the
      Service Selection Mobility Option in octets, excluding the Option
      Type and Option Length fields.  A value of zero (0) is not
      allowed.
    </t>
    <t>Identifier: A variable-length encoded service identifier string
      used to identify the requested service.  The identifier string
      length is between 1 and 255 octets.  This specification allows
      international identifier strings that are based on the use of
      Unicode characters, encoded as UTF-8 <xref target="RFC3269"/>, and
      formatted using Normalization Form KC (NFKC) as specified in <xref 
      target="NFKC"/>.
      <vspace blankLines="1"/>
      Alternatively, based on the local configuration, the
      identifier string can be encoded using the  domain name style encoding 
      described in Section 3.1 of <xref target="RFC1035"/>. However, the
      terminating length of zero octet (i.e. the '\0' octet) is not
      included into the encoded identifier since the option length implicitly
      tells when the identifier string ends <xref target="TS.23003"/>.
      The selection of the  encoding is controlled by the  
      ServiceSelectionMobilityOptionFormat configuration object, see
      <xref target="objects"/>.
      <vspace blankLines="1"/>
      'ims', 'voip', and 'voip.companyxyz.example.com' are valid
      examples of Service Selection option Identifiers.  At minimum, the
      Identifier MUST be unique among the home agents to which the
      mobile node is authorized to register.
      <vspace blankLines="1"/>
    </t>
   </list>
   </t>
  </section>

  <section title="Processing Considerations">
   <section title="Binding Cache Entry Lookup Considerations">
    <t>Section 5.4.1 of <xref target="RFC5213"/> describes various Binding Cache Entry (BCE) lookup variations in the local mobility agent. Some existing Proxy Mobile IPv6 deployments have added the Service Selection option as one of the used BCE lookup keys. This implies that the Service Selection option SHOULD be included in all Proxy Binding Update messages, especially when the Home Network Prefix is not readily available.
    </t>
   </section>
   <section title="Mobile Node Considerations">
    <t>A mobile node or a Proxy Mobile IPv6 client MAY include, at most, one
   Service Selection Mobility Option into a (Proxy) Binding Update message.  The
   option is used to identify the service to be associated with the
   binding registration and SHOULD only be included into the initial
   Binding Update message sent to a home agent.  If the mobile node
   wishes to change the selected service, it is RECOMMENDED that the
   mobile node de-register the existing binding with the home agent
   before proceeding with a binding registration for a different
   service.  The provisioning of the service identifiers to the mobile
   node or to the Proxy Mobile IPv6 client is out of the scope of this
   specification.
   </t>
   <t>
   The placement of the Service Selection option is as follows: when
   present, this option MUST appear after the Mobile Node-Network Access
   Identifier (MN-NAI) option, if the MN-NAI option is present, and before any authorization- and authentication-related options.  The Service Selection option can be used with any mobile node identification method such as a home address, an MN-NAI, and credentials suitable for IKEv2.
   </t>
   <t>If the mobile node receives a (Proxy) Binding Acknowledgement with a Status Code set to SERVICE_AUTHORIZATION_FAILED and the mobile node has an existing binding with the Home Address or the Home Network Prefix used in the failed (Proxy) Binding Update message, the mobile node MUST delete the existing binding.  If there is no existing binding, the mobile node proceeds as with any failed initial binding registration.
    </t>
   <t>If the mobile node receives a (Proxy) Binding Acknowledgement with a Status Code set to MISSING_OR_UNKNOWN_SERVICE the mobile node proceeds as with any failed initial binding registration. The mobile node SHOULD log the event as it is usually an indication of a configuration error.
    </t>
   </section>

   <section title="Home Agent and Local Mobility Agent Considerations">
    <t>Upon receiving a (Proxy) Binding Update message with a Service Selection
   option, the home agent or the local mobility agent authenticates and authorizes the mobile node. If the home agent or the local mobility anchor supports the Service Selection and the Service Selection is required by the local policy, the home agent or the local mobility anchor MUST also verify that the mobile node is authorized for the service it included in the Service Selection option.  The services the mobile node is authorized for SHOULD be part of the general mobile node subscription profile. If the mobile node is not authorized for the service, the home agent or the local mobility agent MUST deny the registration and send a (Proxy) Binding Acknowledgement with a Status Code set to SERVICE_AUTHORIZATION_FAILED (151). If the (Proxy) Binding Update does not contain the Service Selection option or the indicated service is unknown,  the home agent or the local mobility agent SHOULD deny the registration and send a (Proxy) Binding Acknowledgement with a Status Code set to MISSING_OR_UNKNOWN_SERVICE (TBD).  
   </t>
   <t>If binding registration was successful in the home agent or the local mobility agent, then the (Proxy) Binding Acknowledgement SHOULD contain the Service Selection option with the service name in the Identifier.
   </t>
   <!-- t>Note that the home agent or the local mobility agent MAY change the client proposed service to something else based on the local policy.
   </t-->
   <t>
   The Service Selection option is used to assist the authorization and
   identifies a specific service that is to be authorized.  The Service
   Selection option MAY also affect the Home Address or the Home Network
   Prefix allocation when, for example, used with the MN-NAI option.
   For example, for the same NAI there MAY be different Home Addresses
   or Home Network Prefixes depending on the identified service.
   Furthermore, the Service Selection option MAY also affect the routing
   of the outbound IP packets in the home agent or the local mobility agent depending on the selected service.  The home agent MAY also apply different policy or quality of service treatment to traffic flows based on the selected
   service.
   </t>
   <t>
   If the newly arrived (Proxy) Binding Update message with a Service Selection
   option indicates a change in the selected service, then the home
   agent MUST re-authorize the mobile node.  Depending on the home agent or the local mobility agent policies, the services policies, Home Address or Home Network Prefix  allocation policies, and the subscription policies, the home agent may or may not be able to authorize the mobile node to the new
   service.  For example, the existing service and the new service could
   require different Home Network Prefixes.  If the authorization fails,
   then the home agent or the local mobility agent MUST deny the registration, delete any binding with the existing Home Address or Home Network Prefix, and send a (Proxy) Binding Acknowledgement with a Status Code set to
   SERVICE_AUTHORIZATION_FAILED (151).
   </t>
   </section>
   <section title="Correspondent Node Considerations">
    <t>Unless the correspondent node and the home agent share the same
   knowledge about mobility services, the Service Selection option is
   more or less useless information to the correspondent node.  The
   correspondent node SHOULD silently ignore the Service Selection
   option in this case.
    </t>
    <t>There are deployment cases where the home agent and a correspondent
   node, for example, belong to the same administrative domain.  In this
   case, it is possible that the correspondent node shares the same
   knowledge of the services as the home agent.  Therefore, the
   correspondent node is, for example, able to provide service-based
   traffic handling to mobile nodes.
   </t>
   </section>
  </section>
  
  <section title="Configuration Objects" anchor="objects">
   <t>This specification defines one configuration object that controls
  
   the encoding of the service identifier string.
  
   </t>
   <t><list style='hanging'>
    <t hangText="ServiceSelectionMobilityOptionFormat">
     <vspace blankLines="1"/>
     This configuration object is available in both a MAG and in a
LMA. When set
     to 'label', the PMIPv6 node encodes the service identifier 
     string
using <xref target="RFC1035"/> domain name encoding. When set
     to 'dotted', the PMIPv6 node encodes the service identifier 
     string
as any UTF-8 string.
    </t>
   </list></t>
  </section>

  <section title="Security Considerations">
   <t>The protection for the Service Selection Mobility Option depends on
   the service that is being identified and eventually selected.  If the
   service selection information should not be revealed on the wire,
   (Proxy) Binding Updates and (Proxy) Binding Acknowledgements should use Encapsulating Security Payload (ESP) <xref target="RFC4303"/> in transport mode with a non-null encryption transform to provide message confidentiality.
   </t>
  </section>
        
  <section title="IANA Considerations">
   <t>A Mobile IPv6 Mobility Option type has been assigned for the
   following new mobility option from <xref target="RFC6275"/> "Mobility Options" registry. The mobility option is defined in <xref target="opt"/>:
   <figure><artwork><![CDATA[
   Service Selection Mobility Option       is set to 20
]]></artwork></figure>

   A Mobile IPv6 registration denied by home agent Status Code has
   been assigned.  The Status Code was allocated from the range 128-255:

   <figure><artwork><![CDATA[
   SERVICE_AUTHORIZATION_FAILED            is set to 151
   MISSING_OR_UNKNOWN_SERVICE              is set to TBD
]]></artwork></figure>
   </t>

  </section>
 </middle>
 <back>
  <references title="Normative references">
   &RFC2119;
   &RFC6275;
   &RFC5213;

   <reference anchor='NFKC'>
    <front> 
     <title>Unicode Standard Annex #15; Unicode Normalization Forms</title>
      <author initials='M.' surname='Davis' fullname='Mark Davis'>
      <organization/>
     </author>
     <author initials='M.' surname='Durst' fullname='Martin Durst'>
      <organization />
     </author>
     <date year='2006' month='October' />
    </front>
    <seriesInfo name='Unicode' value='5.0.0' />
   </reference>

  </references>
  <references title="Informative references">
   &RFC1035;
   &RFC3269;
   &RFC4282;
   &RFC4283;
   &RFC4285;
   &RFC4303;
   &RFC4877;
   &RFC6459;
   &WIFI;

	<reference anchor='TS.23003'>
	<front>
	<title>Numbering, addressing and identification</title>
	<author><organization>3GPP</organization></author>
	<date day="15" month='June' year='2011' />
	</front>
	<seriesInfo name='3GPP TS' value='23.003 10.2.0' />
	<format type='HTML' target='http://www.3gpp.org/ftp/Specs/html-info/23003.htm' />
	</reference>


  </references>
  
  <section title="Changes from RFC5149">
   <section title="Service Selection option in a PBA" anchor="note1">
    <t>3GPP EPC PMIPv6-based interfaces echo the Service Selection option always back in Proxy Binding Acknowledgements. This is clarified from the RFC5149, which did not say anything about the Service Selection option in Proxy Binding Acknowledgement messages.
    </t>
   </section>

   <section title="Service Selection Identifier encoding" anchor="note2">
    <t>3GPP EPC decided to encode their Service Selection Identifiers using the <xref target="RFC1035"/> domain name style encoding <xref target="TS.23003"/>. Implementations has to take this into account when they intend to interoperate with 3GPP EPC.
    </t>
   </section>
   
   <section title="Using Service Selection as a BCE lookup key" anchor="note3">
    <t>3GPP EPC use the Service Selection option as one of the BCE lookup keys. This is additional to RFC5213 defined set of BCE lookup keys.
    </t>
   </section>
   
   <section title="Addition of a new Status Code" anchor="note4">
    <t>RFC5149 did not make a difference between a service authorization failure (SERVICE_AUTHORIZATION_FAILED) and a service not being provisioned in a home agent/local mobility agent or otherwise unknown (MISSING_OR_UNKNOWN_SERVICE).
    </t>
   </section>

   <section title="Change of the document category from Informational to Standards Track" anchor="note5">
    <t>RFC5149 has implementations by multiple vendors and there are several
    deployments. Furthermore, RFC5149 is not specific to 3GPP networks anymore.
    </t>
   </section>


   
  </section>
  
 </back>

</rfc>

