<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<rfc category="std" docName="draft-ietf-rtcweb-overview-04" ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="RTCWEB Overview">Overview: Real Time Protocols for
    Brower-based Applications</title>

    <author fullname="Harald T. Alvestrand" initials="H. T. "
            surname="Alvestrand">
      <organization>Google</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Kungsbron 2</street>

          <city>Stockholm</city>

          <region></region>

          <code>11122</code>

          <country>Sweden</country>
        </postal>

        <email>harald@alvestrand.no</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date day="20" month="June" year="2012" />

    <abstract>
      <t>This document gives an overview and context of a protocol suite
      intended for use with real-time applications that can be deployed in
      browsers - "real time communication on the Web".</t>

      <t>It intends to serve as a starting and coordination point to make sure
      all the parts that are needed to achieve this goal are findable, and
      that the parts that belong in the Internet protocol suite are fully
      specified and on the right publication track.</t>

      <t>This document is a work item of the RTCWEB working group.</t>
    </abstract>

    <note title="Requirements Language">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
      document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
      target="RFC2119">RFC 2119</xref>.</t>
    </note>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>The Internet was, from very early in its lifetime, considered a
      possible vehicle for the deployment of real-time, interactive
      applications - with the most easily imaginable being audio conversations
      (aka "Internet telephony") and videoconferencing.</t>

      <t>The first attempts to build this were dependent on special networks,
      special hardware and custom-built software, often at very high prices or
      at low quality, placing great demands on the infrastructure.</t>

      <t>As the available bandwidth has increased, and as processors and other
      hardware has become ever faster, the barriers to participation have
      decreased, and it has become possible to deliver a satisfactory
      experience on commonly available computing hardware.</t>

      <t>Still, there are a number of barriers to the ability to communicate
      universally - one of these is that there is, as of yet, no single set of
      communication protocols that all agree should be made available for
      communication; another is the sheer lack of universal identification
      systems (such as is served by telephone numbers or email addresses in
      other communications systems).</t>

      <t>Development of The Universal Solution has proved hard, however, for
      all the usual reasons.</t>

      <t>The last few years have also seen a new platform rise for deployment
      of services: The browser-embedded application, or "Web application". It
      turns out that as long as the browser platform has the necessary
      interfaces, it is possible to deliver almost any kind of service on
      it.</t>

      <t>Traditionally, these interfaces have been delivered by plugins, which
      had to be downloaded and installed separately from the browser; in the
      development of HTML5, application developers see much promise in the
      possibility of making those interfaces available in a standardized way
      within the browser.</t>

      <t>This memo describes a set of building blocks that can be made
      accessible and controllable through a Javascript API in a browser, and
      which together form a sufficient set of functions to allow the use of
      interactive audio and video in applications that communicate directly
      between browsers across the Internet. The resulting protocol suite is
      intended to enable all the applications that are described as required
      scenarios in the RTCWEB use cases document <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-rtcweb-use-cases-and-requirements"></xref>.</t>

      <t>Other efforts, for instance the W3C WebRTC, Web Applications and
      Device API working groups, focus on making standardized APIs and
      interfaces available, within or alongside the HTML5 effort, for those
      functions; this memo concentrates on specifying the protocols and
      subprotocols that are needed to specify the interactions that happen
      across the network.</t>

      <t></t>
    </section>

    <section title="Principles and Terminology">
      <t></t>

      <section title="Goals of this document">
        <t>The goal of the RTCWEB protocol specification is to specify a set
        of protocols that, if all are implemented, will allow an
        implementation to communicate with another implementation using audio,
        video and data sent along the most direct possible path between the
        participants.</t>

        <t>This document is intended to serve as the roadmap to the RTCWEB
        specifications. It defines terms used by other pieces of
        specification, lists references to other specifications that don't
        need further elaboration in the RTCWEB context, and gives pointers to
        other documents that form part of the RTCWEB suite.</t>

        <t>By reading this document and the documents it refers to, it should
        be possible to have all information needed to implement an RTCWEB
        compatible implementation.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Relationship between API and protocol">
        <t>The total RTCWEB/WEBRTC effort consists of two pieces:</t>

        <t><list style="symbols">
            <t>A protocol specification, done in the IETF</t>

            <t>A Javascript API specification, done in the W3C <xref
            target="W3C.WD-webrtc-20120209"></xref></t>
          </list>Together, these two specifications aim to provide an
        environment where Javascript embedded in any page, viewed in any
        compatible browser, when suitably authorized by its user, is able to
        set up communication using audio, video and auxiliary data, where the
        browser environment does not constrain the types of application in
        which this functionality can be used.</t>

        <t>The protocol specification does not assume that all implementations
        implement this API; it is not intended to be necessary for
        interoperation to know whether the entity one is communicating with is
        a browser or another device implementing this specification.</t>

        <t>The goal of cooperation between the protocol specification and the
        API specification is that for all options and features of the protocol
        specification, it should be clear which API calls to make to exercise
        that option or feature; similarly, for any sequence of API calls, it
        should be clear which protocol options and features will be invoked.
        Both subject to constraints of the implementation, of course.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="On interoperability and innovation">
        <t>The "Mission statement of the IETF" <xref target="RFC3935"></xref>
        states that "The benefit of a standard to the Internet is in
        interoperability - that multiple products implementing a standard are
        able to work together in order to deliver valuable functions to the
        Internet's users."</t>

        <t>Communication on the Internet frequently occurs in two phases:</t>

        <t><list style="symbols">
            <t>Two parties communicate, through some mechanism, what
            functionality they both are able to support</t>

            <t>They use that shared communicative functionality to
            communicate, or, failing to find anything in common, give up on
            communication.</t>
          </list>There are often many choices that can be made for
        communicative functionality; the history of the Internet is rife with
        the proposal, standardization, implementation, and success or failure
        of many types of options, in all sorts of protocols.</t>

        <t>The goal of having a mandatory to implement function set is to
        prevent negotiation failure, not to preempt or prevent
        negotiation.</t>

        <t>The presence of a mandatory to implement function set serves as a
        strong changer of the marketplace of deployment - in that it gives a
        guarantee that, as long as you conform to a specification, and the
        other party is willing to accept communication at the base level of
        that specification, you can communicate successfully.</t>

        <t>The alternative - that of having no mandatory to implement - does
        not mean that you cannot communicate, it merely means that in order to
        be part of the communications partnership, you have to implement the
        standard "and then some" - that "and then some" usually being called a
        profile of some sort; in the version most antithetical to the Internet
        ethos, that "and then some" consists of having to use a specific
        vendor's product only.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Terminology">
        <t>The following terms are used in this document, and as far as
        possible across the documents specifying the RTCWEB suite, in the
        specific meanings given here. Not all terms are used in this document.
        Other terms are used in their commonly used meaning.</t>

        <t>The list is in alphabetical order.</t>

        <t><list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="Agent:">Undefined term. See "SDP Agent" and "ICE
            Agent".</t>

            <t hangText="API:">Application Programming Interface - a
            specification of a set of calls and events, usually tied to a
            programming language or an abstract formal specification such as
            WebIDL, with its defined semantics.</t>

            <t hangText="Browser:">Used synonymously with "Interactive User
            Agent" as defined in the HTML specification <xref
            target="W3C.WD-html5-20110525"></xref>.</t>

            <t hangText="ICE Agent:">An implementation of the ICE <xref
            target="RFC5245"></xref> protocol. An ICE Agent may also be an SDP
            Agent, but there exist ICE Agents that do not use SDP (for
            instance those that use Jingle).</t>

            <t hangText="Interactive:">Communication between multiple parties,
            where the expectation is that an action from one party can cause a
            reaction by another party, and the reaction can be observed by the
            first party, with the total time required for the
            action/reaction/observation is on the order of no more than
            hundreds of milliseconds.</t>

            <t hangText="Media:">Audio and video content. Not to be confused
            with "transmission media" such as wires.</t>

            <t hangText="Media path:">The path that media data follows from
            one browser to another.</t>

            <t hangText="Protocol:">A specification of a set of data units,
            their representation, and rules for their transmission, with their
            defined semantics. A protocol is usually thought of as going
            between systems.</t>

            <t hangText="Real-time media:">Media where generation of content
            and display of content are intended to occur closely together in
            time (on the order of no more than hundreds of milliseconds).
            Real-time media can be used to support interactive
            communication.</t>

            <t hangText="SDP Agent:">The protocol implementation involved in
            the SDP offer/answer exchange, as defined in <xref
            target="RFC3264"></xref> section 3.</t>

            <t hangText="Signaling:">Communication that happens in order to
            establish, manage and control media paths.</t>

            <t hangText="Signaling Path:">The communication channels used
            between entities participating in signalling to transfer
            signaling. There may be more entities in the signaling path than
            in the media path.</t>
          </list>NOTE: Where common definitions exist for these terms, those
        definitions should be used to the greatest extent possible.</t>

        <t>TODO: Extend this list with other terms that might prove
        slippery.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Architecture and Functionality groups">
      <t>The model of real-time support for browser-based applications does
      not envisage that the browser will contain all the functions that need
      to be performed in order to have a function such as a telephone or a
      videoconferencing unit; the vision is that the browser will have the
      functions that are needed for a Web application, working in conjunction
      with its backend servers, to implement these functions.</t>

      <t>This means that two vital interfaces need specification: The
      protocols that browsers talk to each other, without any intervening
      servers, and the APIs that are offered for a Javascript application to
      take advantage of the browser's functionality.</t>

      <figure anchor="fig-browser-model" title="Browser Model">
        <artwork><![CDATA[

                                                                          
                     +------------------------+  On-the-wire              
                     |                        |  Protocols                
                     |      Servers           |--------->                 
                     |                        |                           
                     |                        |                           
                     +------------------------+                           
                                 ^                                        
                                 |                                        
                                 |                                        
                                 | HTTP/                                  
                                 | Websockets                             
                                 |                                              
                                 |                                        
                   +----------------------------+                         
                   |    Javascript/HTML/CSS     |                         
                   +----------------------------+                         
                Other  ^                 ^RTC                             
                APIs   |                 |APIs                            
                   +---|-----------------|------+                         
                   |   |                 |      |                         
                   |                 +---------+|                         
                   |                 | Browser ||  On-the-wire            
                   | Browser         | RTC     ||  Protocols              
                   |                 | Function|----------->              
                   |                 |         ||                         
                   |                 |         ||                         
                   |                 +---------+|                         
                   +---------------------|------+                         
                                         |                                
                                         V                                
                                    Native OS Services                    
                                                                          
                                                                          
                                                                          
                                                                          
                                                                          
                                                                          

]]></artwork>
      </figure>

      <t>Note that HTTP and Websockets are also offered to the Javascript
      application through browser APIs.</t>

      <t>As for all protocol and API specifications, there is no restriction
      that the protocols can only be used to talk to another browser; since
      they are fully specified, any device that implements the protocols
      faithfully should be able to interoperate with the application running
      in the browser.</t>

      <t>A commonly imagined model of deployment is the one depicted
      below.</t>

      <figure anchor="fig-webtrapezoid" title="Browser RTC Trapezoid">
        <artwork><![CDATA[                                                                  
                                                                          
             +-----------+             +-----------+                      
             |   Web     |             |   Web     |                      
             |           |  Signalling |           |                      
             |           |-------------|           |                      
             |  Server   |   path      |  Server   |                      
             |           |             |           |                      
             +-----------+             +-----------+                      
                  /                           \                           
                 /                             \ Application-defined      
                /                               \ over       
               /                                 \ HTTP/Websockets                    
              /  Application-defined over         \                       
             /   HTTP/Websockets                   \                      
            /                                       \                     
      +-----------+                           +-----------+               
      |JS/HTML/CSS|                           |JS/HTML/CSS|               
      +-----------+                           +-----------+               
      +-----------+                           +-----------+               
      |           |                           |           |               
      |           |                           |           |               
      |  Browser  | ------------------------- |  Browser  |               
      |           |          Media path       |           |               
      |           |                           |           |               
      +-----------+                           +-----------+               
]]></artwork>
      </figure>

      <t>On this drawing, the critical part to note is that the media path
      ("low path") goes directly between the browsers, so it has to be
      conformant to the specifications of the RTCWEB protocol suite; the
      signalling path ("high path") goes via servers that can modify,
      translate or massage the signals as needed.</t>

      <t>If the two Web servers are operated by different entities, the
      inter-server signalling mechanism needs to be agreed upon, either by
      standardization or by other means of agreement. Existing protocols (for
      example SIP or XMPP) could be used between servers, while either a
      standards-based or proprietary protocol could be used between the
      browser and the web server.</t>

      <t>For example, if both operators' servers implement SIP, SIP could be
      used for communication between servers, along with either a standardized
      signaling mechanism (e.g. SIP over Websockets) or a proprietary
      signaling mechanism used between the application running in the browser
      and the web server. Similarly, if both operators' servers implement
      XMPP, XMPP couild be used for communication between XMPP servers, with
      either a standardized signaling mechanism (e.g. XMPP over Websockets or
      BOSH) or a proprietary signaling mechanism used between the application
      running in the browser and the web server.</t>

      <t>The choice of protocols, and definition of the translation between
      them, is outside the scope of the RTCWEB standards suite described in
      the document.</t>

      <t>The functionality groups that are needed in the browser can be
      specified, more or less from the bottom up, as:</t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>Data transport: TCP, UDP and the means to securely set up
          connections between entities, as well as the functions for deciding
          when to send data: Congestion management, bandwidth estimation and
          so on.</t>

          <t>Data framing: RTP and other data formats that serve as
          containers, and their functions for data confidentiality and
          integrity.</t>

          <t>Data formats: Codec specifications, format specifications and
          functionality specifications for the data passed between systems.
          Audio and video codecs, as well as formats for data and document
          sharing, belong in this category. In order to make use of data
          formats, a way to describe them, a session description, is
          needed.</t>

          <t>Connection management: Setting up connections, agreeing on data
          formats, changing data formats during the duration of a call; SIP
          and Jingle/XMPP belong in this category.</t>

          <t>Presentation and control: What needs to happen in order to ensure
          that interactions behave in a non-surprising manner. This can
          include floor control, screen layout, voice activated image
          switching and other such functions - where part of the system
          require the cooperation between parties. XCON and Cisco/Tandberg's
          TIP were some attempts at specifying this kind of functionality;
          many applications have been built without standardized interfaces to
          these functions.</t>

          <t>Local system support functions: These are things that need not be
          specified uniformly, because each participant may choose to do these
          in a way of the participant's choosing, without affecting the bits
          on the wire in a way that others have to be cognizant of. Examples
          in this category include echo cancellation (some forms of it), local
          authentication and authorization mechanisms, OS access control and
          the ability to do local recording of conversations.</t>
        </list>Within each functionality group, it is important to preserve
      both freedom to innovate and the ability for global communication.
      Freedom to innovate is helped by doing the specification in terms of
      interfaces, not implementation; any implementation able to communicate
      according to the interfaces is a valid implementation. Ability to
      communicate globally is helped both by having core specifications be
      unencumbered by IPR issues and by having the formats and protocols be
      fully enough specified to allow for independent implementation.</t>

      <t>One can think of the three first groups as forming a "media transport
      infrastructure", and of the three last groups as forming a "media
      service". In many contexts, it makes sense to use a common specification
      for the media transport infrastructure, which can be embedded in
      browsers and accessed using standard interfaces, and "let a thousand
      flowers bloom" in the "media service" layer; to achieve interoperable
      services, however, at least the first five of the six groups need to be
      specified.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="ch-transport" title="Data transport">
      <t>Data transport refers to the sending and receiving of data over the
      network interfaces, the choice of network-layer addresses at each end of
      the communication, and the interaction with any intermediate entities
      that handle the data, but do not modify it (such as TURN relays).</t>

      <t>It includes necessary functions for congestion control: When not to
      send data.</t>

      <t>T are described in &lt;WORKING GROUP DRAFT "TRANSPORTS"&gt;.</t>

      <t>ICE is required for all media paths that use UDP; in addition to the
      ability to pass NAT boxes, ICE fulfils the need for guaranteeing that
      the media path is going to an UDP port that is willing to receive the
      data.</t>

      <t>The data transport protocols used by RTCWEB, as well as the details
      of interactions with intermediate boxes, such as firewalls, relays and
      NAT boxes, are intended to be described in a separate document; for now,
      notes are gathered in <xref target="app-transport"></xref>.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Data framing and securing">
      <t>The format for media transport is RTP <xref target="RFC3550"></xref>.
      Implementation of SRTP <xref target="RFC3711"></xref> is required for
      all implementations.</t>

      <t>The detailed considerations for usage of functions from RTP and SRTP
      are given in <xref target="I-D.ietf-rtcweb-rtp-usage"></xref>. The
      security considerations for the RTCWEB use case are in <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-rtcweb-security"></xref>, and the resulting security
      functions are described in <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-rtcweb-security-arch"></xref>.</t>

      <t>Considerations for the transfer of data that is not in RTP format is
      described in <xref target="I-D.ietf-rtcweb-data-channel"></xref>, and
      the resulting protocol is described in <xref
      target="I-D.jesup-rtcweb-data-protocol"></xref> (not yet a WG
      document)</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Data formats">
      <t>The intent of this specification is to allow each communications
      event to use the data formats that are best suited for that particular
      instance, where a format is supported by both sides of the connection.
      However, a minimum standard is greatly helpful in order to ensure that
      communication can be achieved. This document specifies a minimum
      baseline that will be supported by all implementations of this
      specification, and leaves further codecs to be included at the will of
      the implementor.</t>

      <t>The mandatory to implement codecs, as well as any profiling
      requirements for both mandatory and optional codecs, is described in
      &lt;WORKING GROUP DRAFT "MEDIA PROCESSING"&gt; (candidate draft: <xref
      target="I-D.cbran-rtcweb-codec"></xref>.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Connection management">
      <t>The methods, mechanisms and requirements for setting up, negotiating
      and tearing down connections is a large subject, and one where it is
      desirable to have both interoperability and freedom to innovate.</t>

      <t>The following principles apply:</t>

      <t><list style="numbers">
          <t>The RTCWEB media negotiations will be capable of representing the
          same SDP offer/answer semantics that are used in SIP <xref
          target="RFC3264"></xref>, in such a way that it is possible to build
          a signalling gateway between SIP and the RTCWEB media
          negotiation.</t>

          <t>It will be possible to gateway between legacy SIP devices that
          support ICE and appropriate RTP / SDP mechanisms, codecs and
          security mechanisms without using a media gateway. A signaling
          gateway to convert between the signaling on the web side to the SIP
          signaling may be needed.</t>

          <t>When a new codec is specified, and the SDP for the new codec is
          specified in the MMUSIC WG, no other standardization would should be
          required for it to be possible to use that in the web browsers.
          Adding new codecs which might have new SDP parameters should not
          change the APIs between the browser and javascript application. As
          soon as the browsers support the new codecs, old applications
          written before the codecs were specified should automatically be
          able to use the new codecs where appropriate with no changes to the
          JS applications.</t>
        </list>The particular choices made for RTCWEB, and their implications
      for the API offered by a browser implementing RTCWEB, are described in
      <xref target="I-D.ietf-rtcweb-jsep"></xref></t>
    </section>

    <section title="Presentation and control">
      <t>The most important part of control is the user's control over the
      browser's interaction with input/output devices and communications
      channels. It is important that the user have some way of figuring out
      where his audio, video or texting is being sent, for what purported
      reason, and what guarantees are made by the parties that form part of
      this control channel. This is largely a local function between the
      browser, the underlying operating system and the user interface; this is
      being worked on as part of the W3C API effort, and will be part of the
      peer connection API <xref target="W3C.WD-webrtc-20120209"></xref>, and
      the device control API <xref target="getusermedia"></xref>.
      Considerations for the implications of wanting to identify
      correspondents are described in <xref
      target="I-D.rescorla-rtcweb-generic-idp"></xref> (not a WG item).</t>

      <t></t>
    </section>

    <section title="Local system support functions">
      <t>These are characterized by the fact that the quality of these
      functions strongly influences the user experience, but the exact
      algorithm does not need coordination. In some cases (for instance echo
      cancellation, as described below), the overall system definition may
      need to specify that the overall system needs to have some
      characteristics for which these facilities are useful, without requiring
      them to be implemented a certain way.</t>

      <t>Local functions include echo cancellation, volume control, camera
      management including focus, zoom, pan/tilt controls (if available), and
      more.</t>

      <t>Certain parts of the system SHOULD conform to certain properties, for
      instance:</t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>Echo cancellation should be good enough to achieve the
          suppression of acoustical feedback loops below a perceptually
          noticeable level.</t>

          <t>Privacy concerns must be satisfied; for instance, if remote
          control of camera is offered, the APIs should be available to let
          the local participant to figure out who's controlling the camera,
          and possibly decide to revoke the permission for camera usage.</t>

          <t>Automatic gain control, if present, should normalize a speaking
          voice into &lt;whatever dB metrics makes sense here - most important
          that we have one only&gt;</t>
        </list>The requirements on RTCWEB systems in this category are found
      in &lt;WORKING GROUP DRAFT "MEDIA PROCESSING"&gt;; the proposed API for
      control of local devices are found in <xref
      target="getusermedia"></xref>.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>This document makes no request of IANA.</t>

      <t>Note to RFC Editor: this section may be removed on publication as an
      RFC.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>Security of the web-enabled real time communications comes in several
      pieces:</t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>Security of the components: The browsers, and other servers
          involved. The most target-rich environment here is probably the
          browser; the aim here should be that the introduction of these
          components introduces no additional vulnerability.</t>

          <t>Security of the communication channels: It should be easy for a
          participant to reassure himself of the security of his communication
          - by verifying the crypto parameters of the links he himself
          participates in, and to get reassurances from the other parties to
          the communication that they promise that appropriate measures are
          taken.</t>

          <t>Security of the partners' identity: verifying that the
          participants are who they say they are (when positive identification
          is appropriate), or that their identity cannot be uncovered (when
          anonymity is a goal of the application).</t>
        </list>The security analysis, and the requirements derived from that
      analysis, is contained in <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-rtcweb-security"></xref>.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>The number of people who have taken part in the discussions
      surrounding this draft are too numerous to list, or even to identify.
      The ones below have made special, identifiable contributions; this does
      not mean that others' contributions are less important.</t>

      <t>Thanks to Cary Bran, Cullen Jennings, Colin Perkins, Magnus
      Westerlund and Joerg Ott, who offered technical contributions on various
      versions of the draft.</t>

      <t>Thanks to Jonathan Rosenberg, Matthew Kaufman and others at Skype for
      the ASCII drawings in section 1.</t>

      <t>Thanks to Eric Rescorla, Justin Uberti, Henry Sinnreich, Colin
      Perkins and Simon Leinen for document review.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119"?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.3550'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.3264'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.3711'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.5245'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.5766'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-rtcweb-security'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-rtcweb-rtp-usage'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-rtcweb-data-channel'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-rtcweb-security-arch'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-rtcweb-jsep'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.tuexen-tsvwg-sctp-dtls-encaps'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-mmusic-sctp-sdp'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.nandakumar-rtcweb-stun-uri'?>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.3935'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-rtcweb-use-cases-and-requirements'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.jesup-rtcweb-data-protocol'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.rescorla-rtcweb-generic-idp'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.cbran-rtcweb-codec'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.W3C.WD-webrtc-20120209'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.W3C.WD-html5-20110525'?>

      <reference anchor="getusermedia"
                 target="http://dev.w3.org/2011/webrtc/editor/getusermedia.html">
        <front>
          <title>getusermedia: Getting access to local devices that can
          generate multimedia streams</title>

          <author fullname="Dan Burnett" initials="D" surname="Burnett">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="Anant Narayanan" initials="A" surname="Narayanan">
            <organization></organization>

            <address>
              <postal>
                <street></street>

                <city></city>

                <region></region>

                <code></code>

                <country></country>
              </postal>

              <phone></phone>

              <facsimile></facsimile>

              <email></email>

              <uri></uri>
            </address>
          </author>

          <date day="22" month="December" year="2011" />
        </front>
      </reference>
    </references>

    <section anchor="app-transport"
             title="Transport and Middlebox specification">
      <t>The draft referred to as "transport and middle boxes" in <xref
      target="ch-transport"></xref> has not been written yet. This appendix
      contains some keywords to what it should say; this also serves the
      purpose of linking to the drafts-in-progress that are relevant to this
      specification.</t>

      <t></t>

      <section title="System-provided interfaces">
        <t>The protocol specifications used here assume that the following
        protocols are available as system-level interfaces:</t>

        <t><list style="symbols">
            <t>UDP. This is the protocol assumed by most protocol elements
            described.</t>

            <t>TCP. This is used for HTTP/WebSockets, as well as for TURN/SSL
            and ICE-TCP.</t>
          </list>For both protocols, we assume the ability to set the DSCP
        code point of the sockets opened. We do not assume that the DSCP
        codepoints will be honored, and we do assume that they may be zeroed
        or changed, since this is a local configuration issue.</t>

        <t>We do not assume that the implementation will have access to ICMP
        or raw IP.</t>

        <t></t>
      </section>

      <section title="Middle box related functions">
        <t>The primary mechanism to deal with middle boxes is ICE, which is an
        appropriate way to deal with NAT boxes and firewalls that accept
        traffic from the inside, but only from the outside if it's in response
        to inside traffic (simple stateful firewalls).</t>

        <t>In order to deal with symmetric NATs, TURN MUST be supported.</t>

        <t>In order to deal with firewalls that block all UDP traffic, TURN
        over TCP MUST be supported. (QUESTION: What about ICE-TCP?)</t>

        <t>The following specifications MUST be supported:</t>

        <t><list style="symbols">
            <t>ICE <xref target="RFC5245"></xref></t>

            <t>TURN, including TURN over TCP [[QUESTION: and TURN over TLS]],
            <xref target="RFC5766"></xref>.</t>
          </list>For referring to ICE servers, we use the STUN URI, <xref
        target="I-D.nandakumar-rtcweb-stun-uri"></xref>.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Transport protocols implemented">
        <t>For data transport, we implement SCTP over DTLS over ICE. This is
        specified in <xref target="I-D.tuexen-tsvwg-sctp-dtls-encaps"></xref>.
        Negotiation of this transport in SCTP is defined in <xref
        target="I-D.ietf-mmusic-sctp-sdp"></xref>.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Change log">
      <t>This section may be deleted by the RFC Editor when preparing for
      publication.</t>

      <section title="Changes from draft-alvestrand-dispatch-rtcweb-datagram-00 to -01">
        <t>Added section "On interoperability and innovation"</t>

        <t>Added data confidentiality and integrity to the "data framing"
        layer</t>

        <t>Added congestion management requirements in the "data transport"
        layer section</t>

        <t>Changed need for non-media data from "question: do we need this?"
        to "Open issue: How do we do this?"</t>

        <t>Strengthened disclaimer that listed codecs are placeholders, not
        decisions.</t>

        <t>More details on why the "local system support functions" section is
        there.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Changes from draft-alvestrand-dispatch-01 to draft-alvestrand-rtcweb-overview-00">
        <t>Added section on "Relationship between API and protocol"</t>

        <t>Added terminology section</t>

        <t>Mentioned congestion management as part of the "data transport"
        layer in the layer list</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Changes from draft-alvestrand-rtcweb-00 to -01">
        <t>Removed most technical content, and replaced with pointers to
        drafts as requested and identified by the RTCWEB WG chairs.</t>

        <t>Added content to acknowledgements section.</t>

        <t>Added change log.</t>

        <t>Spell-checked document.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Changes from draft-alvestrand-rtcweb-overview-01 to draft-ietf-rtcweb-overview-00">
        <t>Changed draft name and document date.</t>

        <t>Removed unused references</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Changes from -00 to -01 of draft-ietf-rtcweb-overview">
        <t>Added architecture figures to section 2.</t>

        <t>Changed the description of "echo cancellation" under "local system
        support functions".</t>

        <t>Added a few more definitions.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Changes from -01 to -02 of draft-ietf-rtcweb-overview">
        <t>Added pointers to use cases, security and rtp-usage drafts (now WG
        drafts).</t>

        <t>Changed description of SRTP from mandatory-to-use to
        mandatory-to-implement.</t>

        <t>Added the "3 principles of negotiation" to the connection
        management section.</t>

        <t>Added an explicit statement that ICE is required for both NAT and
        consent-to-receive.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Changes from -02 to -03 of draft-ietf-rtcweb-overview">
        <t>Added references to a number of new drafts.</t>

        <t>Expanded the description text under the "trapezoid" drawing with
        some more text discussed on the list.</t>

        <t>Changed the "Connection management" sentence from "will be done
        using SDP offer/answer" to "will be capable of representing SDP
        offer/answer" - this seems more consistent with JSEP.</t>

        <t>Added "security mechanisms" to the things a non-gatewayed SIP
        devices must support in order to not need a media gateway.</t>

        <t>Added a definition for "browser".</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Changes from -03 to -04 of draft-ietf-rtcweb-overview">
        <t>Made introduction more normative.</t>

        <t>Several wording changes in response to review comments from EKR</t>

        <t>Added <xref target="app-transport"></xref> to hold references and
        notes that are not yet in a separate document.</t>

        <t></t>
      </section>
    </section>
  </back>
</rfc>
