<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<rfc category="exp" docName="draft-hartman-nvo3-security-requirements-01"
     ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="NVO3 security">Security Requirements of NVO3</title>

    <author fullname="Sam Hartman" initials="S." surname="Hartman">
      <organization>Painless Security</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>356 Abbott Street</street>

          <city>North Andover</city>

          <region>MA</region>

          <code>01845</code>

          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>

        <email>hartmans@painless-security.com</email>

        <uri>http://www.painless-security.com</uri>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Dacheng Zhang" initials="D." surname="Zhang">
      <organization>Huawei</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street/>

          <city>Beijing</city>

          <region/>

          <code/>

          <country>China</country>
        </postal>

        <phone/>

        <facsimile/>

        <email>zhangdacheng@huawei.com</email>

        <uri/>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Margaret Wasserman" initials="M." surname="Wasserman">
      <organization>Painless Security</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>356 Abbott Street</street>

          <city>North Andover</city>

          <region>MA</region>

          <code>01845</code>

          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>

        <phone>+1 781 405 7464</phone>

        <email>mrw@painless-security.com</email>

        <uri>http://www.painless-security.com</uri>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date day="15" month="July" year="2013"/>

    <abstract>
      <t>This draft discusses the security requirements and several issues
      which need to be considered in securing a virtualized data center
      network for multiple tenants (a NVO3 network for short). In addition,
      the draft also attempts to discuss how such issues could be addressed or
      mitigated.</t>
    </abstract>

    <note title="Requirements Language">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
      document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
      target="RFC2119">RFC 2119</xref>.</t>
    </note>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>Security is the key issue which needs to be considered in the design
      of a data center network. This document first lists the security risks
      that a NVO3 network may encounter and the security requirements that a
      NVO3 network need to fulfill. Then, this draft discusses the essential
      security approaches which could be applied to fulfill such
      requirements.</t>

      <t><xref target="ThreatModel">The remainder of this document is
      organized as follows. </xref> introduces the attack model of this work
      and the properties that a NOV3 security mechanism needs to enforce.
      <xref target="Requirements"/> describes the essential security
      mechanisms which should be provide in the generation of a NVO3 network.
      Then, in <xref target="Issues"/>, we analyze the challenges brought by
      the new features mentioned in<xref
      target="I-D.ietf-nvo3-overlay-problem-statement"/>.</t>

      <t/>
    </section>

    <section title="Terminology">
      <t>This document uses the same terminology as found in the NVO3
      Framework document <xref target="I-D.ietf-nvo3-framework"/> and <xref
      target="I-D.kreeger-nvo3-hypervisor-nve-cp"/>. Some of the terms defined
      in the framework document have been repeated in this section for the
      convenience of the reader, along with additional terminology that is
      used by this document.</t>

      <t>Tenant System (TS): A physical or virtual system that can play the
      role of a host, or a forwarding element such as a router, switch,
      firewall, etc. It belongs to a single tenant and connects to one or more
      VNs of that tenant.</t>

      <t>End System (ES): An end system of a tenant, which can be, e.g., a
      virtual machine(VM), a non-virtualized server, or a physical appliance.
      A TS is attached to a Network Virtualization Edge(NVE) node.</t>

      <t>Network Virtualization Edge (NVE): An NVE implements network
      virtualization functions that allow for L2/L3 tenant separation and
      tenant-related control plane activity. An NVE contains one or more
      tenant service instances whereby a TS interfaces with its associated
      instance. The NVE also provides tunneling overlay functions.</t>

      <t>Virtual Network (VN): This is a virtual L2 or L3 domain that belongs
      to a tenant.</t>

      <t>Information Mapping Authority (IMA). A back-end system that is
      responsible for distributing and maintaining the mapping information for
      the entire overlay system. Note that the WG never reached consensus on
      what to call this architectural entity within the overlay system, so
      this term is subject to change. In
      [I-D.ietf-nvo3-overlay-problem-statement], such a back-end system is
      referred to as a "oracle".</t>
    </section>

    <section title="NVO3 Overlay Architecture">
      <t/>

      <t><figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[      
       Please view in a fixed-width font such as Courier.

       Please view in a fixed-width font such as Courier.

                   ..................................
                   .                                .
                   .                                .
                   .                                .
                 +-+--+                          +--+-++--------+
 +--------+      | NV |                          | NV || Tenant |
 | Tenant +------+Edge|       L3 Overlay         |Edge|| System |
 | System |      +-+--+        Network           +--+-++--------+
 +--------+        .                                .
                   .                                .
                   .                                .
                   ..................................

]]></artwork>
        </figure>This figure illustrates a simple nov3 overlay example where
      NVEs provide a logical L2/L3 interconnect for the TSes that belong to a
      specific tenant network over L3 networks. A packet from a tenant system
      is encapsulated when they reach the egress NVE. Then encapsulated packet
      is then sent to the remote NVE through a proper tunnel. When reaching
      the ingress NVE, the packet is decapsulated and forwarded to the target
      tenant system. The address advertisements and tunnel mappings are
      distributed amonge the NVEs through either distributed control protocols
      or by certain centralized servers (called Information Mapping
      Authorities).</t>

      <t/>
    </section>

    <section anchor="ThreatModel" title="Threat Model">
      <t>To benefit the discussion, in this analysis work, attacks are
      classified into two categories: inside attacks and outside attacks. An
      attack is considered as an inside attack if the adversary performing the
      attack (inside attacker or insider) has got certain privileges in
      changing the configuration or software of a NVO3 device (or a network
      devices of the underlying network where the overlay is located upon) and
      initiates the attack within the overlay security perimeter. In contrast,
      an attack is referred to as an outside attack if the adversary
      performing the attack (outside attacker or outsider) has no such
      privilege and can only initiate the attacks from compromised TSes. Note
      that in a complex attack inside and outside attacking operations may be
      performed in a well organized way to expand the damages caused by the
      attack.</t>

      <t>This analysis assumes that security protocols, algorithms, and
      implementations provide the security properties for which they are
      designed; attacks depending on a failure of this assumption are out of
      scope. As an example, an attack caused by a weakness in a cryptographic
      algorithm is out of scope, while an attack caused by failure to use
      confidentiality when confidentiality is a security requirement is in
      scope.</t>

      <section title="Outsider Capabilities">
        <t>The following capabilities of outside attackers MUST be considered
        in the design of a NOV3 security mechanism:</t>

        <t><list style="numbers">
            <t>Eavesdropping on the packets,</t>

            <t>Replaying the intercepted packets, and</t>

            <t>Generating illegal packets and injecting them into the
            network.</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>With a successful outside attack, an attacker may be able to:<list
            style="numbers">
            <t>Analyze the traffic pattern of a tenant or an end device,</t>

            <t>Disrupt the network connectivity or degrade the network service
            quality, or</t>

            <t>Access the contents of the data/control packets if they are not
            encrypted.</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>

      <section title="Insider Capabilities">
        <t>It is assumed that an inside attacker can perform any types of
        outside attacks from the inside or outside of the overlay perimeter.
        In addition, in an inside attack, an attacker may use already obtained
        privilege to, for instance,</t>

        <t><list style="numbers">
            <t>Interfere with the normal operations of the overlay as a legal
            entity, by sending packets containing invalid information or with
            improper frequencies,</t>

            <t>Perform spoofing attacks and impersonate another legal device
            to communicate with victims using the cryptographic information it
            obtained, and</t>

            <t>Access the contents of the data/control packets if they are
            encrypted with the keys held by the attacker.</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>Note that in practice an insider controlling an underlying network
        device may break the communication of the overlays by discarding or
        delaying the delivery of the packets passing through it. However, this
        type of attack is out of scope.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Security Properties">
        <t>When encountering an attack, a virtual data center network MUST
        guarantee the following security properties:<list style="numbers">
            <t>Isolation of the VNs: <xref
            target="I-D.ietf-nvo3-overlay-problem-statement"> In</xref>, the
            data plane isolation requirement amongst different VNs has been
            discussed. The traffic within a virtual network can only be
            transited into another one in a controlled fashion (e.g., via a
            configured router and/or a security gateway). In addition, it MUST
            be ensured that an entity cannot make use of its privilege
            obtained within a VN to manipulate the overlay control plane to
            affect on the operations of other VNs.</t>

            <t>Spoofing detection: Under the attacks performed by a privileged
            inside attacker, the attacker cannot use the obtained
            cryptographic materials to impersonate another one.</t>

            <t>Integrity protection and message origin authentication for the
            control packets: The implementation of an overlay control plane
            MUST support the integrity protection on the signaling packets. No
            entity can modify a overlay signaling packet during its
            transportation without being detected. Also, an attacker cannot
            impersonate a legal victim (e.g., a NVE or another servers within
            the overlay) to send signaling packets without detection.</t>

            <t>Availability of the control plane: The design of the control
            plan must consider the DoS/DDoS attacks. Especially when there are
            centralized servers in the control plan of the overlay, the
            servers need to be well protected and make sure that they will not
            become the bottle neck of the control plane especially under DDOS
            attacks.</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>The following properties SHOULD be optionally provided:</t>

        <t><list style="numbers">
            <t>Confidentiality and integrity of the data traffic of TSes. In
            some conditions, the cryptographic protection on the TS traffic is
            not necessary. For example, if most of the ES data is headed
            towards the Internet and nothing is confidential, encryption or
            integrity protection on such data may be unnecessary. In addition,
            in the cases where the underlay network is secure enough, no
            additional cryptographic protection needs to be provided.</t>

            <t>Confidentiality of the control plane. On many occasions, the
            signaling messages can be transported in plaintext. However, when
            the information contained within the signaling messages are
            sensitive or valuable to attackers (e.g., the location of a ES,
            when a VM migration happens), the signaling messages related with
            that tenant SHOULD be encrypted.</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Requirements" title="Basic Security Approaches">
      <t>This section introduces the security mechanisms which could be used
      to provided in order to guarantee the security properties mentioned in
      section 4 when encountering attacks.</t>

      <section title="Securing the Communications between NVEs and TSes">
        <t>Assume there is a VNE providing a logical L2/L3 interconnect for a
        set of TSes. Apart from data traffics, the NVE and the TSes also need
        to exchange signaling messages in order to facilitate, e.g., VM online
        detection, VM migration detection, or auto-provisioning/service
        discovery <xref target="I-D.ietf-nvo3-framework"/>.</t>

        <t>The NVE and its associated TSes can be deployed in a distributed
        way (e.g., a NVE is implemented in an individual device, and VMs are
        located on servers) or in a co-located way (e.g., a NVE and the TSes
        it serves are located on the same server).</t>

        <t>In the former case, the data and control traffic between the NVE
        and the TSes are exchanged over network. If the NVE supports multiple
        VNs concurrently, the data/control traffics in different VNs MUST be
        isolated physically or by using VPN technologies. If the network
        connecting the NVE and the TSes is potentially accessible to
        attackers, the security properties of data traffic (e.g., integrity,
        confidentiality, and message origin authenticity) SHOULD be provided.
        The security mechanisms such as IPsec, SSL, and TCP-AO, can be used
        according to different security requirements.</t>

        <t>In order to guarantee the integrity and the origin authentication
        of signaling messages, integrated security mechanisms or additional
        security protocols need to be provided. In order to secure the
        data/control traffic, cryptographic keys need to be distributed to
        generate digests or signatures for the control packets. Such
        cryptographic keys can be manually deployed in advance or dynamically
        generated with certain automatic key management protocols (e.g., TLS
        <xref target="RFC5246"/>). The TSes belonging to different VNs MUST
        use different keys to secure the control packets exchanges with their
        NVE. Therefore, an attacker cannot use the keys it obtained from a
        compromised TS to generate bogus signaling messages and inject them
        into other VNs without being detected. For a better damage confinement
        capability, different TSes SHOULD use different keys to secure their
        control packet exchanges with NVEs, even if they belong to the same
        VN.</t>

        <t>In the co-located case, all the information exchanges between the
        NVE and the TSes are within the same device, and no standardized
        protocol need to be provided for transporting control/data packets. It
        is also important to keep the isolation of the TS traffic in different
        VNs. In addition, in the co-location fashion, because the NVE, the
        hypervisor, and the VMs are deployed on the same device, the computing
        and memory resources used by the NVE , the hypervisor, and the TSes
        need to be isolated to prevents a malicious or compromised TS from,
        e.g., accessing the memory of the NVE or affecting the performance of
        the NVE by occupying large amounts of computing resources.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Securing the Communications within Overlays">
        <t>This section analyzes the security issues in the control and data
        plans of a NVO3 overlay.</t>

        <section title="Control Plane Security">
          <t>It is the responsibility of the NVO3 network to protect the
          control plane packets transported over the underlay network against
          the attacks from the underlying network. The integrity and origin
          authentication of the messages MUST be guaranteed. The signaling
          packets SHOULD be encrypted when the signaling messages are
          confidential. To achieve such objectives, when the network devices
          exchange control plane packets, integrated security mechanisms or
          security protocols need to provided. In addition, cryptographic keys
          need to be deployed manually in advance or dynamically generated by
          using certain automatic key management protocols (e.g., TLS <xref
          target="RFC5246"/>).</t>

          <t>In order to enforce the security boundary of different VNs in the
          existence of inside adversaries, the signaling messages belonging to
          different VNs need to be secured by different keys. Otherwise, an
          inside attacker may try to use the keys obtained within a VN to
          impersonate the NVEs in other VNs and generate illegal signaling
          messages without being detected. If we expect to provide a better
          attack confinement capability and prevent a compromised NVE to
          impersonate other NVEs in the same VN, different NVEs working inside
          a VN need to secure their signaling messages with different keys.
          When there are centralized servers providing mapping information
          (IMAs) within the overlay, it will be important to prevent a
          compromised NVE from impersonating the centralized servers to
          communicate with other NVEs. A straightforward solution is to
          associate different NVEs with different keys when they exchange
          information with the centralized servers.</t>

          <t>In the cases where there are a large amount of NVEs working
          within a NVO3 overlay, manual key management may become infeasible.
          First, it could be burdensome to deploy pre-shared keys for
          thousands of NVEs, not to mention that multiple keys may need to be
          deployed on a single device for different purposes. Key derivation
          can be used to mitigate this problem. Using key derivation
          functions, multiple keys for different usages can be derived from a
          pre-shared master key. However, key derivation cannot protect
          against the situation where a system was incorrectly trusted to have
          the key used to perform the derivation. If the master key were
          somehow compromised, all the resulting keys would need to be
          changed. In addition, VM migration will introduce challenges to
          manual key management. The migration of a VM in a VN may cause the
          change of the NVEs which are involved within the NV. When a NVE is
          newly involved within a VN, it needs to get the key to join the
          operations within the VN. If a NVE stops supporting a VN, it should
          not keep the keys associated with that VN. All those key updates
          need to be performed at run time, and difficult to be handled by
          human beings. As a result, it is reasonable to introduce automated
          key management solutions such as EAP <xref target="RFC4137"/> for
          NVO3 overlays.</t>

          <t>When an automated key management solution for NVO3 overlays is
          deployed, as a part of the key management protocol, mutual
          authentication needs to be performed before two network devices in
          the overlay (NVEs or IMAs) start exchanging the control packets.
          After an authentication, an device can find out whether its peer
          holds valid security credentials is is the one who it has claimed.
          The authentication results is also necessary for authorization; it
          is important for a device to clarify the roles (e.g., a NVE or a
          IMA) that its authentication peer acts as in the overlay. Therefore,
          a compromised NVE cannot use it credential to impersonate an IMA to
          communicate with other NVEs. Only the control messages from the
          authenticated entity will be adopted. In addition, authorization MAY
          need to be performed. For instance, before accepting a control
          message, the receiver NVE needs to verify whether the message comes
          from one which is authorized to send that message. If the
          authorization fail, the control message will be discarded. For
          instance, if a control packet about a VN is sent from a NVE which is
          not authorized to support the VN, the packet will be discarded.</t>

          <t>The issues of DDOS attacks also need to be considered in
          designing the overlay control plane. For instance, in the VXLAN
          solution<xref target="I-D.mahalingam-dutt-dcops-vxlan"/>, an
          attacker attached to a NVE can try to manipulate the NVE to keep
          multicasting control messages by sending a large amount of ARP
          packets to query the inexistent VMs. In order to mitigate this type
          of attack, the NVEs SHOULD be only allowed to send signaling message
          in the overlay with a limited frequency. When there are centralized
          servers (e.g., the backend oracles providing mapping information for
          NVEs<xref target="I-D.ietf-nvo3-overlay-problem-statement"/>, or the
          SDN controllers) are located within the overlay, the potential
          security risks caused by DDOS attack on such servers can be more
          serious.</t>

          <t>In addition, during the design of the control plane, it is
          important to consider the amplification effects which may potential
          be used by attackers to carry out reflection attacks.</t>

          <t/>
        </section>

        <section title="Data Plan Security">
          <t><xref target="I-D.ietf-nvo3-framework"/> specifies a NVO3 overlay
          needs to generate tunnels between NVEs for data transportation. When
          a data packet reaches the boundary of a overlay, it will be
          encapsulated and forwarded to the destination NVE through a proper
          tunnel. It is normally assume that the underlying network connecting
          NVEs are secure to outside attacks since it is under the management
          of DC vendor and cannot be directly accessed by tenants. However,
          when facing inside attacks, conditions could be complex. For
          instance, an inside attacker compromising a underlying network
          device may intercept an encapsulated data packet transported a
          tunnel, modify the contents in the encapsulating tunnel packet and,
          transfer it into another tunnel without being detected. When the
          modified packet reaches a NVE, the NVE may decapsulated the data
          packet and forward it into a VN according to the information within
          the encapsulating header generated by the attacker. Similarly, a
          compromised NVE may try to redirect the data packets within a VN
          into another VN by adding improper encapsulating tunnel headers to
          the data packets. Under such circumstances, in order to enforce the
          VN isolation property, signatures or digests need to be generated
          for both data packets and the encapsulating tunnel headers in order
          to provide data origin authentication and integrity protection. In
          addition, NVEs SHOULD use different keys to secure the packets
          transported in different tunnels.</t>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Issues"
             title="Security Issues Imposed by the New Overlay Design Characteristics ">
      <t/>

      <section title="Scalability Issues">
        <t>NOV3 WG requires an overlay be able to work in an environment where
        there are many thousands of NVEs (e.g. residing within the
        hypervisors) and large amounts of trust domains (VNs). Therefore, the
        scalability issues should be considered. In the cases where a NVE only
        has a limited number of NVEs to communicate with, the scalability
        problem brought by the overhead of generating and maintaining the
        security channels with the remote NVEs is not serious. However, if a
        NVE needs to communicate with a large number of peers, the scalability
        issue could be serious. For instance, in<xref
        target="I-D.ietf-ipsecme-ad-vpn-problem"/>, it has been demonstrated
        it is not trivial to enabling a large number of systems to communicate
        directly using IPsec to protect the traffic between them.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Influence on Security Devices">
        <t>If the data packets transported through out an overlay are
        encrypted (e.g., by NVEs), it is difficult for a security device,
        e,g., a firewall deployed on the path connecting two NVEs to inspect
        the contents of the packets. The firewall can only know which VN the
        packets belong to through the VN ID transported in the outer header.
        If a firewall would like to identify which end device sends a packets
        or which end device a packet is sent to, the firewall can be deployed
        in some place where it can access the packet before it is encapsulated
        or un-encapsulated by NVEs. However, in this case, the firewall cannot
        get VN ID from the packet. If the firewall is used to process two VNs
        concurrently and there are IP or MAC addresses of the end devices in
        the two VNs overlapped, confusion will be caused. If a firewall can
        generate multiple firewalls instances for different tenants
        respectively, this issue can be largely addressed.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Security Issues with VM Migration">
        <t>The support of VM migration is an important issue considered in
        NVO3 WG. The migration may also cause security risks. Because the VMs
        within a VN may move from one server to another which connects to a
        different NVE, the packets exchanging between two VMs may be
        transferred in a new path. If the security policies deployed on the
        firewalls of the two paths are conflict or the firewalls on the new
        path lack essential state to process the packets. The communication
        between the VMs may be broken. To address this problem, one option is
        to enable the state migration and policy confliction detection between
        firewalls. The other one is to force all the traffic within a VN be
        processed by a single firewall. However this solution may cause
        traffic optimization issues.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>This document makes no request of IANA.</t>

      <t>Note to RFC Editor: this section may be removed on publication as an
      RFC.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>TBD</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">
      <t/>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.2119'?>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-nvo3-overlay-problem-statement'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-ipsecme-ad-vpn-problem'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.mahalingam-dutt-dcops-vxlan'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-nvo3-framework'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.kreeger-nvo3-hypervisor-nve-cp'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.4137'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.5246'?>
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
