<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<rfc category="exp" docName="draft-nvo3-security-document-00"
     ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="Abbreviated-Title">Security Requirement of NVO3</title>

    <author fullname="Author Name" initials="A." surname="Name">
      <organization/>
    </author>

    <date/>

    <abstract>
      <t>This draft discusses the security issues which need to be considered
      in achieving Data Center Network Virtualization over L3 tunnels and how
      such issues could be addressed or mitigated.</t>
    </abstract>

    <note title="Requirements Language">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
      document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
      target="RFC2119">RFC 2119</xref>.</t>
    </note>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t><xref target="I-D.ietf-nvo3-overlay-problem-statement"/> has
      indicated that there multiple properties that a virtualized data center
      networks for multiple tenants may need to provide ( e.g., large amounts
      of tenant end devices (e.g., VM), the support of VM migration, and
      dynamic network provisioning). This drafts introdcue the basic security
      requirement for such a data center network and analyzes the security
      issues brought by the new features.</t>

      <t>Section 2 describes the essential security requirements which should
      be fulfilled in the generation large scale virtual data center networks
      supporting multiple tenants. Then, in section 3 we analyze the
      challenges brought by the new features mentioned in <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-nvo3-overlay-problem-statement"/>.</t>

      <t/>
    </section>

    <section title="Terminologies">
      <t>end system: An end system of a tenant, which can be for instance a
      virtual machine(VM), a non-virtualized server, or a physical appliance.
      A TES attaches to Network Virtualization Edge(NVE) node.</t>

      <t>Network Virtualization Edge(NVE): An NVE implements network
      virtualization functions that allow for L2/L3 tenant separation,
      tenant-related control plane activity. An NVE contains one or more
      tenant service instances whereby a TES interfaces with its associated
      instance. The NVE also provides tunneling overlay functions.</t>

      <t>Top of Rack (TOR):</t>

      <t>Tentant End System (TES):</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Threat Model">
      <t>In the analysis, it is assumed that an attacker has the capability of
      <list style="numbers">
          <t>intercepting the packets transported through a virtual data
          center network,</t>

          <t>replaying the intercepted packets, and </t>

          <t>generating fake packets and injecting them into the network.</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>When using the above capability to perform a successful attack on a
      virtual data center network, an attacker may be able to</t>

      <t><list style="numbers">
          <t>obtain the data it is un-authorized to access,</t>

          <t>analyze the traffic pattern of a tenant or a end device, or</t>

          <t>disrupt and degrade the service quality of the network</t>
        </list></t>

      <t/>

      <t>Under the attacks mentioned above, a virtual data center network
      should guarantee the following security properties:<list style="numbers">
          <t> Isolation of the TES traffic. A TES in a VNI MUST not access the
          traffic or communicate with the TESes in other VNIs in an
          un-controlled way. In most conditions, two TESes in different VNIs
          are not allowed to access each other. In case the TESes need to
          communicate, their traffic SHOULD be processed by and monitored by
          certain security devices. </t>

          <t>Integrity and original authenticationof the control plane: All
          the control panel implementations of the overlay MUST support the
          integrity protection on the signaling packets. </t>

          <t>Avilability of the control plane: The design of teh control plan
          must consider the DDOS attacks. Especially, when there are
          centralized components in the control plan of the overlay, it is
          important to make sure that the centralized components will not
          become the bottle neck of the how system. </t>
        </list> </t>

      <t>And the following properties are optionally provided:</t>

      <t><list style="numbers">
          <t>Confidentiality and integrity of the TES traffic. In some
          conditions, the cryptographic protection on the TES traffic is not
          necessary. For example, if most of the TES data is headed towards
          the Internet and nothing is confidential, ecryption is redundant. In
          addition, in the cases where the underlay network is secure enough,
          no additional cryptograhpic protection needs to be provided. </t>

          <t>Confidentialiy of the control plan</t>
        </list></t>

      <t/>

      <t/>

      <t/>

      <t/>

      <t>Note that the following two types of attacks is out of the scope of
      this draft: the attacks taking advantage of social engineering, and the
      attacks taking advantage of the weak security algorithms, the drawbacks
      of security protocols, or the loopholes of security implementations.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Basic Security Requirements">
      <t/>

      <section title="Security Requirements Between NVEs and TS">
        <t>A NVE and the TESes it supports can be deployed in a distributed
        way (e.g., a NVE is implemented in a TOR switch, and VMs are located
        on servers) or on the same device (e.g., a NVE and the VMs it serves
        are located on the same server). </t>

        <t>In the former case, the information exchanged between the NVE and
        the end devices (e.g., the VMs ) MUST not be accessed by any
        unauthorized principal. If the network connecting the NVE and the end
        devices is assumed to be accessible to attackers and the data
        transported in the network is confidential, the security properties
        including the integrity, the confidentiality, and the message origin
        authenticity of the TES traffic need be protected, e.g., by IPsec,
        SSL, and etc. In addition, it is important to guarantee the isolation
        of different VNIs. If a NVE supports multiple NVIs concurrently, the
        traffic of different VNIs must be physically seperated or seperated by
        e.g., VLAN. A compromised TES MUSt not be able to affect the
        integrity, availability or isolation of the network.</t>

        <t>In the latter case, it is also important for the hypervisor and the
        NVE component to keep the isolation of the TESes in different VNIs.
        Although there is no traffic between the TESes and the NVE are
        transported over the network, it is also important for a VM of tenant
        to reach the traffic in the VNI of other tenants.</t>

        <t>There are could be signaling messages exchanged between the NVE and
        the end devices (e.g., VMs or hypervisors) for TES management purposes
        (e.g, VM online detection or VM migration detection). The end devices
        SHOULD be autenticated, only the signalling messages from the
        authorized end device will be accepted. This is also very important in
        keeping the isolation of different VNIs. For instance, if a hypervisor
        reports the migration of a VM not in the VNIs that the hypervisor
        supports, the information cannot be used to update the mapping table
        on the NVE. In addition, </t>

        <t/>

        <t>The authenticaiton on end devices could be very important. For
        instance, in the VXLAN solution <xref
        target="I-D.mahalingam-dutt-dcops-vxlan"/>, an attacker attached to a
        NVE can force the NVE to keep multicast messages by sending ARP
        packets to query the VMs existing or not.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Security Requirements within Overlays">
        <t>This section discusses the security issues within a virtual data
        center overlay in the control plan and the data plan respectively.</t>

        <section title="Control Plan Security">
          <t>Authentication between NVEs are required. Before, two NVEs
          exchange any information, mutual authentication must be
          performed.</t>

          <t>The signaling messages must be transported over the underlay
          network in a secure way, the integrity and original authentication
          of the messages must be guaranteed. The signaling packets should
          also be encrypted if the signaling messages are confidential.</t>

          <t>When a NVE receives an address mapping information, the NVE must
          guarantee the information is from an authorized entity before
          updating its mapping table. For instance, when if a message is about
          the address mapping of a VM inside a VNI but from a NVE which is not
          authorized to serve the VNI, the information must not be input into
          the mapping table.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Data Plan Security">
          <t>A data of a tenant transported between two NVEs should not be
          accessed by any un-authorized principal. If the underlay network can
          potentially be accessed by attackers, the overlay Must be able to
          provide the protection on the integrity, confidentiality, and
          original authentication of the data.</t>

          <t/>

          <t/>

          <t>Comments about Control Plane Overlays: First, sreplace plan with
          plane. Why is authentication important? One answer is that you make
          some authorization requirements. Is mapping update the only thing
          that requires authorization? What's the insider attack model? Are
          there central controllers? Or do NVEs get to generate mapping
          updates as well as receive them? If there are controllers, is it
          important to prevent an NVE from impersonating a controller? Are all
          NVEs equal? Is it important to prevent one NVE from impersonating
          another? Note that the answer can be "sometimes". For example in
          KARP, we've said that you want to be able to isolate trusted zones
          from each other even though inside attacks are not in scope. See the
          top few paragraphs on page 10 of draft-ietf-karp-ops-model. Your
          discussion in the authorization section where you point out that an
          NVE not authorized to hold a given TES should not be able to update
          the mapping for that TES. That's an example of the sort of trusted
          zone thing we are talking about. If you have a lot of that going on,
          you do tend to need to require no impersonation. That tends to
          require strong key management rather than preshared keys. </t>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Security Issues Imposed by the New Overlay Design Characteristics ">
      <t/>

      <section title="Scalability Issues">
        <t>NOV3 assumes all the NVO3 overlay is within a administration
        domain, and so the issues with federated authentication and
        authorization need not to be considered. However, the overlay should
        work in an environment where there could be many thousands of NVEs
        (e.g. residing within the hypervisors), and the scalability issues
        should be considered. In the cases where a NVE only have a limited
        number of NVEs to communicate with, the scalability issue imposed by
        the overhead of generating maintaining the security channels with the
        peers is not serious. However, if a NVE needs to communicate with a
        large number of peers, the scalability issue could be serious. For
        instance, in<xref target="I-D.ietf-ipsecme-ad-vpn-problem"/>, it has
        been demonstrated it is not trivial to enabling a large number of
        systems to communicate directly using IPsec to protect the traffic
        between them.</t>

        <t/>
      </section>

      <section title="Influence on Security Devices">
        <t>In addition, if the packets transported through out overlay are
        encrypted, it is difficult for a security device, e,g., a firewall
        deployed on the path to intercept the contents of the packets. The
        firewall can only know which VNI the packets belong to through the
        VNID transported in the outer header. If a firewall would like to
        identify which end device sends a packets or which end device a packet
        is sent to, the firewall can be deployed in some place where it can
        access the packet before it is encapsulated or un-encapsulated by
        NVEs. However, in this case, the firewall cannot get VN ID from the
        packet. If the firewall is used to process two VNIs concurrently and
        there are IP or MAC addresses of the end devices in the two VNIs
        overlapped, confusion will be caused. If a firewall can generate
        multiple firewalls instances for different tenants respectively, this
        issue can be largely addressed.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Security Issues with VM Migration">
        <t>The support of VM migration is an important issue considered in
        NVO3 WG. The migration may also cause security risks. Because the VMs
        within a VNI may move from one server to another which connects to a
        different NVE, the packets exchanging between two VMs may be
        transferred in a new path. If the security policies deployed on the
        firewalls of the two paths are conflict or the firewalls on the new
        path lack essential state to process the packets. The communication
        between the VMs may be broken. To address this problem, one option is
        to enable the state migration and policy confliction detection between
        firewalls. The other one is to force all the traffic within a VNI are
        process by a single firewall. However this solution may cause traffic
        optimization issues.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="DDOS Attacks">
      <t>T</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>This document makes no request of IANA.</t>

      <t>Note to RFC Editor: this section may be removed on publication as an
      RFC.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t/>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">
      <t/>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119"?>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-nvo3-framework'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-nvo3-overlay-problem-statement'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-ipsecme-ad-vpn-problem'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.4111'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.mahalingam-dutt-dcops-vxlan'?>
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
