<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!-- This template is for creating an Internet Draft using xml2rfc,
     which is available here: http://xml.resource.org. -->
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!-- One method to get references from the online citation libraries.
     There has to be one entity for each item to be referenced. 
     An alternate method (rfc include) is described in the references. -->

<!ENTITY RFC2119 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC1981 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1981.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4084 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4084.xml">
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<!-- used by XSLT processors -->
<!-- For a complete list and description of processing instructions (PIs), 
     please see http://xml.resource.org/authoring/README.html. -->
<!-- Below are generally applicable Processing Instructions (PIs) that most I-Ds might want to use.
     (Here they are set differently than their defaults in xml2rfc v1.32) -->
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<!-- give errors regarding ID-nits and DTD validation -->
<!-- control the table of contents (ToC) -->
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<!-- generate a ToC -->
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<!-- the number of levels of subsections in ToC. default: 3 -->
<!-- control references -->
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<!-- use symbolic references tags, i.e, [RFC2119] instead of [1] -->
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<!-- sort the reference entries alphabetically -->
<!-- control vertical white space 
     (using these PIs as follows is recommended by the RFC Editor) -->
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<!-- do not start each main section on a new page -->
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<!-- keep one blank line between list items -->
<!-- end of list of popular I-D processing instructions -->
<rfc category="info" docName="draft-kawamura-ipv6-isp-listings-00" ipr="trust200902">
  <!-- category values: std, bcp, info, exp, and historic
     ipr values: full3667, noModification3667, noDerivatives3667
     you can add the attributes updates="NNNN" and obsoletes="NNNN" 
     they will automatically be output with "(if approved)" -->

  <!-- ***** FRONT MATTER ***** -->

  <front>
    <!-- The abbreviated title is used in the page header - it is only necessary if the 
         full title is longer than 39 characters -->

    <title abbrev="IPv6 ISP Listings">A Basic Guideline for Listing ISPs that Run IPv6</title>

    <!-- add 'role="editor"' below for the editors if appropriate -->

    <!-- Another author who claims to be an editor -->

    <author fullname="Seiichi Kawamura" initials="S.K." 
            surname="Kawamura">
      <organization>NEC BIGLOBE, Ltd.</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>14-22, Shibaura 4-chome</street>

          <!-- Reorder these if your country does things differently -->

          <city>Minatoku</city>

          <region>Tokyo</region>

          <code>108-8558</code>

          <country>JAPAN</country>
        </postal>

        <phone>+81 3 3798 6085</phone>

        <email>kawamucho@mesh.ad.jp</email>

        <!-- uri and facsimile elements may also be added -->
      </address>
    </author>

    <date month="June" year="2010" />

    <!-- If the month and year are both specified and are the current ones, xml2rfc will fill 
         in the current day for you. If only the current year is specified, xml2rfc will fill 
	 in the current day and month for you. If the year is not the current one, it is 
	 necessary to specify at least a month (xml2rfc assumes day="1" if not specified for the 
	 purpose of calculating the expiry date).  With drafts it is normally sufficient to 
	 specify just the year. -->

    <!-- Meta-data Declarations -->

    <area>General</area>

    <workgroup>Internet Engineering Task Force</workgroup>

    <!-- WG name at the upperleft corner of the doc,
         IETF is fine for individual submissions.  
	 If this element is not present, the default is "Network Working Group",
         which is used by the RFC Editor as a nod to the history of the IETF. -->

    <keyword>IPv6</keyword>
    <keyword>ISP</keyword>

    <!-- Keywords will be incorporated into HTML output
         files in a meta tag but they have no effect on text or nroff
         output. If you submit your draft to the RFC Editor, the
         keywords will be used for the search engine. -->

    <abstract>
      <t>
      There are many web sites that give listings of IPv6 enabled service providers, or rate ISPs according to their IPv6 enabledness. This document intends to gather information about currently known sites and their methods of checking an ISPs enabledness. This document also summarizes a basic guideline that these listings may consider when checking an ISPs IPv6 enabledness.
      </t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>
      There are many web sites that give listings of IPv6 enabled service providers, or rate ISPs according to their IPv6 enabledness. The following are few examples of currently known programs.

      <t><list style="empty">
      <t>IPv6 Enabled Program http://ipv6forum.org/ipv6_enabled/</t>
      <t>IPv6 Ripeness http://labs.ripe.net/content/ipv6-ripeness/</t>
      <t>SixXS http://www.sixxs.net/wiki/IPv6_Enabled_Service_Providers</t>
      <t>IPv6 to Standard http://ipv6-to-standard.org/</t>
      <t>Hurricane Electric Free IPv6 Certification http://ipv6.he.net/certification/</t>
      </list></t>

</t>

      <t>
      There are several motivations for these listings which benefit both the ISPs and the users. It gives ISPs a goal to work for in turning up IPv6. It also can be used by ISPs for publicity (in telling the world that their service is ready for IPv4 address exhaustion). Listings can also be a guide for users when they choose their ISP.
      </t>

      <t>
      This document intends to gather information about currently known listings, and to summarize a basic guideline that can be used when starting a new program of the like. There are many reason (such as localization) that a new listing is started albeit the fact that there already is one. A presence of a guideline would help those that intend to start such programs. It may also help in keeping one listing or rating guideline from being widely different from another, so it would not confuse users who decided to choose ISPs on the basis that the ISP is on one of these IPv6 enabled service provider listings.
      </t>

        <section title="Requirements Language">
          <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
          "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
          document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
          target="RFC2119">RFC 2119</xref>.</t>
        </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Summary of the Current Situation">
          <t>
          The following are the list of currently known programs that list or rate ISPs according to a guideline that each has determined.

      <t><list style="empty">
      <t>IPv6 Enabled Program http://ipv6forum.org/ipv6_enabled/</t>
      <t>IPv6 Ripeness http://labs.ripe.net/content/ipv6-ripeness/</t>
      <t>SixXS http://www.sixxs.net/wiki/IPv6_Enabled_Service_Providers</t>
      <t>IPv6 to Standard http://ipv6-to-standard.org/</t>
      <t>Hurricane Electric Free IPv6 Certification http://ipv6.he.net/certification/</t>
      </list></t>

</t>

    <t>
    note: the following description of each program is not yet complete.
    </t>

      <section title="IPv6 Enabled Program">
          <t>
          The IPv6 enabled program lists ISPs at two levels: basic and advanced. At the time of this writing, the advanced level list has not been started yet. The basic requirements for being listed in the basic list are, to have a prefix assigned or allocated (IPv6 enabled program does not check if the prefix is an assignment or allocation), have a global AS route it, and keep reachability as much as possible.
          </t>
          <t>
The IPv6 Enabled Program checks the following.
          </t>

        <section title="Network Accessibility Ability">
          <t>
        The ISP's AS number is checked against a database to see if the AS exists and is unique.
          </t>
        </section>

        <section title="Active IPv6 Address Requirement">
          <t>
        The ISP's IPv6 prefix is checked against a database to see if the applying ISP is the rightful owner. Actual traffic to the prefix from a customer is also checked. Checking at the time of writing is done by using a script that the ISP will paste to a web site, and the script checks if it was accessed via IPv6.
          </t>
        </section>

        <section title="Persistence of IPv6 service Ability">
          <t>
        The check noted in the previous section is done periodically to check global reachability.
          </t>
        </section>
        </section>

        <section title="IPv6 Ripeness">
          <t>
 IPv6 Ripeness is part of a study conducted by RIPE NCC. Stars are given to LIRs registered in the RIPE NCC service region by checking there status in IPv6 deployment. 
          </t>

        <section title="Criteria">
          <t>
        Stars are earned by checking the following criteria.
          </t>
          <t><list style="symbols">
            <t>Have an IPv6 prefix allocated or a PI assigned.</t>
            <t>Prefix is visible in the Routing Information System(RIS).</t>
            <t>A route6 object is registered in the RIPE database.</t>
            <t>Reverse DNS is setup for the IPv6 prefix.</t>
          </list></t>
        </section>
      </section>

    <section title="Summary of the Checking Criteria">

      <t>The programs discussed in this section share these criteria in common. 
          </t>
          <t><list style="symbols">
            <t>Have an IPv6 prefix allocated or a PI assigned.</t>
            <t>Prefix is visible in a routing database.</t>
          </list></t>

      <t>IPv6 Ripeness also checks if a route6 is registered (have good routing manners), and a reverse DNS is set up. IPv6 Enabled Program checks for actual traffic which requires the presence of an active web server inside the ISP.
      </t>

      </section>

  </section>



    <section title="Guidelines for Listing an IPv6 Enabled ISP">
        <section title="Scope of the Guideline">
  <t>
  This guideline can be used to check any LIR or a PI address holder, that claims to be an ISP. The guideline is only intended to check an ISP's network accessibility. In turn, this guideline can also be used as a minimum requirement checklist by ISPs who want to newly turn up IPv6 in their network.
  </t>

        </section>
        <section title="Levels of the Listing">
          <t>We divide the listing into two levels, basic and advanced. Basic level is what is absolutely necessary for any ISP to claim that they have some form of IPv6 working. The basic level will not guarantee that the ISP has a fully working or production quality IPv6 network. The advanced level will take the requirements one step further in bring the level of deployment closer to the quality of the IPv4 network. It checks for the basics needed to achieve any of the service types defined in the General Terminology section in  <xref target="RFC4084"></xref>.</t>
        </section>
        <section title="Basic">
          <t>The basic level listing checks an ISP to meet the following criteria.</t>
          <t><list style="symbols">
            <t>Have an IPv6 prefix allocated or a PI assigned.</t>
            <t>Prefix is visible in at least one routing database.</t>
            <t>Have at least one server with an IPv6 address where accessibility can be checked.</t>
          </list></t>
        </section>
        <section title="Advanced">
          <t>The advanced level listing checks an ISP to meet the following criteria.</t>
          <t><list style="symbols">
            <t>Reverse DNS for is set up for allocated prefixes.</t>
            <t>DNS cache servers are accessible via IPv6 transport.</t>
            <t>Path MTU discovery <xref target="RFC1981"></xref> is functional and is not filtered.</t>
            <t>Prefix visibility is seen in at least two routing databases belonging in different regions of the world.</t>
          </list></t>

        </section>

        <section title="Considerations">
          <t>The listings can be made more useful if checking is done according to the target users of the ISP service. ISP for residential, ISP for ISPs (transit providers), ISP for enterprises, and ISP for data centers have different requirements. This document does not go into discussing the requirements for each type of services are. This document intends to discuss the requirements that should be common to any services provided by any ISP.
          </t>
        </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>None.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>None.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>The author would like to thank the Task Force on IPv4 Address Exhaustion, Japan. Parts of this document was inspired from work by Brian Carpenter and Sheng Jiang.</t>
    </section>

    <!-- Possibly a 'Contributors' section ... -->

  </middle>

  <!--  *****BACK MATTER ***** -->

  <back>

    <references title="Normative References">

    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      &RFC1981;
      &RFC2119;
      &RFC4084;
    </references>

  </back>
</rfc>



