<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<rfc category="bcp" docName="draft-michaelson-as112-ipv6-00" ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="AS112 for IPv6">AS112 Nameserver Delegations for
    IPv6</title>

    <author fullname="George Michaelson" initials="G." surname="Michaelson">
      <organization abbrev="APNIC">APNIC</organization>

      <address>
        <email>ggm@apnic.net</email>

        <uri>http://www.apnic.net</uri>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Geoff Huston" initials="G." surname="Huston">
      <organization abbrev="APNIC">APNIC</organization>

      <address>
        <email>gih@apnic.net</email>

        <uri>http://www.apnic.net</uri>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date year="2011" />

    <area>Operations Area</area>

    <workgroup>Individual Submission</workgroup>

    <abstract>

      <t>To reduce longterm traffic to the DNS root servers and the
      IP6.ARPA authoritative servers, the IAB is requested to instruct
      the IANA to delegate a set of sub-domains of IP6.ARPA to the
      AS112 Project <xref target="ID.ietf-dnsop-as112-ops" />. These
      domains represent IPv6 address prefixes that are not
      conventionally populated in the global reverse-DNS, including
      IPv6 prefixes that are not globally scoped and certain prefixes
      used in an anycast context.</t>

      <t>The reverse DNS query load associated with these IPv6 address
      prefixes appear to have unacceptable scaling consequences as IPv6
      uptake increases. By delegating these sub-domains to the AS112
      project, the DNS query load can be passed to a distributed sink,
      reducing the query load on the root servers and the IP6.ARPA
      authoritative servers.</t>

    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section anchor="intro"
             title="Reverse DNS Delegation and Local-Use Addresses">
      <t>The IPv6 Addressing Architecture <xref target="RFC4291"></xref>
      includes certain address prefixes that are not intended to be uniquely
      used in the global network as globally-scoped unicast addresses. Such
      addresses include locally-scoped addresses, certain anycast addresses,
      and loopback addresses.</t>

      <t>While such addresses are not intended to be used in the same context
      as globally-scoped unicast addresses, their use in various local and
      global contexts is seen to trigger Domain Name System (DNS) <xref
      target="RFC1034"></xref> queries (of the form of "reverse lookups")
      corresponding to these addresses. Since the addresses concerned
      generally have local rather than global significance, it is good
      practice for site administrators to ensure that such queries are
      answered locally <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-dnsop-default-local-zones"></xref>. However, it is not
      uncommon for such queries to follow the normal delegation path in the
      public DNS instead of being answered within the site. It is not possible
      for public DNS servers to give useful answers to such queries, and the
      response to such reverse lookup queries from the global DNS is the "Name
      Error" RCODE described in <xref target="RFC1035"></xref>, commonly
      termed "NXDOMAIN".</t>

      <t>When the reverse-DNS infrastructure receives a request for
      un-delegated sub-domains, the point of delegation of the last matched
      label along the name path to the root receives the query. In the case of
      the IPv6 reverse delegation structure, this implies that the IP6.ARPA
      authoritative servers will receive the query load. Because the
      sub-domain is not delegated, the server is obliged to answer with an
      NXDOMAIN response. Since negative caching is not widely deployed, a
      large number of these DNS queries are repeated, further increasing the
      DNS query load imposed on the DNS root servers and the IP6.ARPA
      authoritative servers.</t>

      <t>This query load appears to have unacceptable scaling consequences as
      IPv6 uptake increases. By delegating these sub-domains to the AS112
      project <xref target="ID.ietf-dnsop-as112-ops"></xref>, the DNS query
      load can be passed off to a distributed dedicated server set, reducing
      the load on the DNS root and the IP6.ARPA authoritative servers.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>As per the provisions of <xref target="RFC3152"></xref>, this
      document recommends the IAB to direct IANA to delegate the following
      IP6.ARPA reverse DNS zones to the AS112 project <xref
      target="ID.ietf-dnsop-as112-ops"></xref>:</t>

      <figure>
        <artwork><![CDATA[
0.0.0.0.0.0.0.0.0.0.0.0.0.0.0.0.ip6.arpa (Unspecified)
                            f.f.ip6.arpa (Multicast)
                          8.e.f.ip6.arpa (Link-Local Scope)
                          9.e.f.ip6.arpa (Link-Local Scope)
                          a.e.f.ip6.arpa (Link-Local Scope)
                          b.e.f.ip6.arpa (Link-Local Scope)
                          c.e.f.ip6.arpa (Link-Local Scope)
                          d.e.f.ip6.arpa (Link-Local Scope)
                          e.e.f.ip6.arpa (Link-Local Scope)
                          f.e.f.ip6.arpa (Link-Local Scope)
                        0.0.c.f.ip6.arpa (Unique Locally Assigned)
                        0.0.d.f.ip6.arpa (Unique Locally Assigned)
                0.0.0.0.1.0.0.2.ip6.arpa (Teredo)
]]></artwork>
      </figure>

      <t>AS112 project servers should add these zones to their configuration,
      and terminate queries efficiently inside their service
      infrastructure.</t>

      <t>This delegation instruction is subject to further direction in the
      future from the IAB to IANA, as per the provisions of <xref
      target="RFC3152"></xref>.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Security Considerations">
      <t>The Security Considerations described in <xref
      target="ID.ietf-dnsop-as112-ops"></xref> also apply to local-use IPv6
      addresses, and should be considered in the context of the use of these
      addresses.</t>

      <t>DNS queries may well identify the location of deployment of IPv6
      enabled equipment in private contexts, particularly when the reverse
      queries relate to local-use IPv6 addresses. While operators of the DNS
      reverse servers should respect the privacy of data relating to
      individual queries made to these reverse address servers, the
      unintentional leakage of information beyond its intended scope of use
      and circulation represents a potential threat to the security of a local
      private network. This direction to delegate these local-use IPv6 reverse
      address sub-domains does not substantially change the security risks of
      information leakage from private environments.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Acknowledgments">
     <t>The authors acknowledge the work of Joe Abley and William
     Maton and the DNSOPS Working Group in preparing the AS112
     framework document for delegation of the private use address
     blocks in IPv4, and have used parts of their AS112 document as a
     template for these AS112 delegation instructions in IPv6.</t>
   </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include='./rfcs/bibxml/reference.RFC.1034.xml'?>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <?rfc include='./rfcs/bibxml/reference.RFC.1035.xml'?>
<!--      <?rfc include='./rfcs/bibxml/reference.RFC.2375.xml'?> -->
      <?rfc include='./rfcs/bibxml/reference.RFC.3152.xml'?>

<!--      <?rfc include='./rfcs/bibxml/reference.RFC.3879.xml'?> -->

      <?rfc include='./rfcs/bibxml/reference.RFC.4291.xml'?>

<!--      <?rfc include='./rfcs/bibxml/reference.RFC.4380.xml'?> -->

      <reference anchor="ID.ietf-dnsop-as112-ops">
        <front>
          <title>Locally-served DNS Zones</title>

          <author fullname="J. Abley" initials="J" surname="Abley">
            <organization>ICANN</organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="W. Maton" initials="W" surname="Maton">
            <organization>NRC-CNRC</organization>
          </author>

          <date day="12" month="November" year="2010" />
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="Internet Draft"
                    value="draft-ietf-dnsop-default-local-zones" />

        <format target="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/draft-ietf-dnsop-default-local-zones/"
                type="TXT" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="I-D.ietf-dnsop-default-local-zones">
        <front>
          <title>Locally-served DNS Zones</title>

          <author fullname="M. Andrews" initials="M" surname="Andrews">
            <organization>ISC</organization>
          </author>

          <date day="22" month="September" year="2010" />
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="Internet Draft"
                    value="draft-ietf-dnsop-default-local-zones" />

        <format target="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/draft-ietf-dnsop-default-local-zones/"
                type="TXT" />
      </reference>
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
