<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!-- comment -->
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd"[]>
<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="no" ?>
<rfc ipr="trust200811" category="std" docName="draft-ietf-sipcore-proxy-feature-01.txt" obsoletes="" updates="" submissionType="IETF" xml:lang="en">
	<front>
		<title abbrev="proxy feature">
			Indication of features supported by proxy
		</title>
		<author initials="C.H." surname="Holmberg" fullname="Christer Holmberg">
			<organization>Ericsson</organization>
			<address>
				<postal>
					<street>Hirsalantie 11</street>
					<code>02420</code>
					<city>Jorvas</city>
					<country>Finland</country>
				</postal>
				<email>christer.holmberg@ericsson.com</email>
			</address>
		</author>
		<author initials="I.S." surname="Sedlacek" fullname="Ivo Sedlacek">
			<organization>Ericsson</organization>
			<address>
				<postal>
					<street>Scheelevägen 19C</street>
					<code>22363</code>
					<city>Lund</city>
					<country>Sweden</country>
				</postal>
				<email>ivo.sedlacek@ericsson.com</email>
			</address>
		</author>
		<author initials="H.K." fullname="Hadriel Kaplan" initials="H." surname="Kaplan">
			<organization>Acme Packet</organization>
			<address>
				<postal>
					<street>71 Third Ave.</street>
					<city>Burlington</city>
					<region>MA</region>
					<code>01803</code>
					<country>USA</country>
				</postal>
				<email>hkaplan@acmepacket.com</email>        
			</address>
		</author>		
		
		<date year="2012" />
		<area>Transport</area>
		<workgroup>SIPCORE Working Group</workgroup>
		<keyword>SIP</keyword>
		<keyword>proxy</keyword>
		<keyword>feature</keyword>
		<keyword>feature tag</keyword>
		<keyword>feature cap</keyword>
		<keyword>Feature-Caps</keyword>
		<keyword>capabiltiy</keyword>		
		<abstract>
			<t>
				This specification creates a new IANA registry, "SIP Feature Cap Registry",
				which is used to register indicators, "SIP feature caps", used by SIP entities 
				to indicate support of features and capabilities, in cases where the Contact 
				header field contains a URI that does not represent the SIP entity that wants 
				to indicate support of its features and capabilities.
			</t>
			<t>
				This specification also defines a new SIP header field, Feature-Caps, that can
				be used by SIP entities to convey information about supported features and 
				capabilities, using SIP feature caps.
			</t>
		</abstract>
	</front>
	<middle>
		<section title="Introduction" toc="default">
			<t>
				The Session Initiation Protocol (SIP) <xref target="RFC3261" pageno="false" 
				format="default"/> "Caller Preferences" extension, defined in RFC 3840 <xref 
				target="RFC3840" pageno="false" format="default"/>, provides a mechanism that 
				allows a SIP message to convey information relating to the originator's features 
				and capabilities, using the Contact header field.
			</t>
			<t>
				This specification creates a new IANA registry, "SIP Feature Cap Registry",
				which is used to register indicators, "SIP feature caps", that can be used 
				by SIP entities to indicate support of features and capabilities, in cases
				where the Contact header field contains a URI that does not represent the 
				SIP entity that wants to indicate support of its features and capabilities, 
				and media feature tags cannot be used to indicate the support.
				Such cases are:
				<t>
					<list style="symbols">
						<t>
							- The SIP entity acts as a SIP proxy.
						</t>
						<t>
							- The SIP entity acts as a SIP registrar.
						</t>
						<t>
							- The SIP entity acts as a B2BUA, where the 
							Contact header field URI represents another SIP entity.
						</t>					
					</list>
				</t>
			</t>
			<t>
				This specification also defines a new SIP header field, Feature-Caps, that can
				be used by SIP entities to convey information about supported features and 
				capabilities, using SIP feature caps.
			</t>
			<t>
				Unlike media feature tags, SIP feature caps are intended to only be used
				with the SIP protocol.
			</t>
		</section>
		
		<section title="Conventions" toc="default">
			<t>
				The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", 
				"RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in 
				BCP 14, RFC 2119 <xref target="RFC2119" pageno="false" format="default" />.
			</t>
		</section>

		<section title="Definitions" toc="default">
			<t>
				Downstream SIP entity: SIP entity in the direction towards which a SIP request is sent.
			</t>
			<t>
				Upstream SIP entity: SIP entity in the direction from which a SIP request is received.
			</t>
		</section>
		
		<section title="SIP Feature Caps" anchor="sec.fc" toc="default">
			<section title="Introduction" anchor="sec.fc.int" toc="default">
				<t>
					A SIP feature cap can be used by SIP entities to indicate support of features 
					and capabilities, in cases where media feature tags cannot be used, ie if the Contact 
					header field contains a URI that does not represent the SIP entity that wants to 
					indicate support of its features and capabilities. 
				</t>
				<t>
					A value, or a list of values, can be associated with a SIP feature cap.
				</t>
				<t>
					[ref-to-section] defines how SIP feature caps are conveyed using the SIP Feature-Caps 
					header field.
				</t>
			</section>

			<section title="Syntax" anchor="sec.fc.syn" toc="default">
				<section title="General" anchor="sec.fc.syn.gen" toc="default">
					<t>
						In a SIP feature cap name (ABNF: fcap-name), dots can be used to implement a SIP feature 
						cap tree hierarchy (e.g. tree.feature.subfeature). The description of usage of such 
						tree hierarchy must be described when registered.
					</t>
				</section>
				<section title="ABNF" toc="default" anchor="sec.fc.syn.abnf">
					<t>
						The ABNF for the Feature-Caps header field is:
					</t>
					<figure title="ABNF" anchor="fig.fchf.syn.abnf" suppress-title="false" align="left" alt="" width="" height="">
						<artwork xml:space="preserve" name="" type="" align="left" alt="" width="" height=""><![CDATA[ 

					
feature-cap       =  ["+"] fcap-name [EQUAL LDQUOT (fcap-value-list
                     / string-value ) RDQUOT]
fcap-name         =  ALPHA *( ALPHA / DIGIT / "!" / "'"
                     / "." / "-" / "%" )
fcap-value-list   =  fcap-value *("," fcap-value)
fcap-value        =  ["!"] (token-nobang / boolean / numeric)
token-nobang      =  1*(alphanum / "-" / "." / "%" / "*"
                     / "_" / "+" / "`" / "'" / "~" )
boolean           =  "TRUE" / "FALSE"
numeric           =  "#" numeric-relation number
numeric-relation  =  ">=" / "<=" / "=" / (number ":")
number            =  [ "+" / "-" ] 1*DIGIT ["." 0*DIGIT]
string-value      =  "<" *(qdtext-no-abkt / quoted-pair ) ">"
qdtext-no-abkt    =  LWS / %x21 / %x23-3B / %x3D
                     / %x3F-5B / %x5D-7E / UTF8-NONASCII
                     ;;gdtext as defined in RFC 3261			
                   
						]]></artwork>
					</figure>
				</section>
			</section>
					
			<section title="Registration Trees" anchor="sec.fc.reg.tree" toc="default">
				<section title="General" anchor="sec.fc.reg.tree.gen" toc="default">
					<t>
						The following subsections define registration "trees", distinguished
						by the use of faceted names (e.g., names of the form "tree.feature-
						name").
					</t>
					<t>
						The tree definitions are based on the global tree and sip tree defined 
						for media feature tags, in RFC 2506 <xref target="RFC2506" pageno="false" 
						format="default"/> and RFC 3841 <xref target="RFC3841" pageno="false" 
						format="default"/>. 
					</t>
					<t>
						Additional feature caps trees can be created by IANA, following the same 
						rules and procedures as defined for media feature tags in section 3.1.4 
						of RFC 2506 <xref target="RFC2506" pageno="false" format="default"/>.
					</t>
					<t>
						The acceptance of the proposed designation is at the discretion of IANA. 
						If IANA believes that additional information, or clarification, is needed,
						it can request an updated proposal from the proposing organization.
					</t>
					<t>
						When a SIP feature cap is registered in any registration tree, no
						leading "+" is used in the registration.
					</t>
				</section>
				<section title="Global Tree" anchor="sec.fc.reg.tree.glob" toc="default">
				<t>
					The SIP feature cap global tree is based on the media feature tag 
					global tree defined in RFC 2506 <xref target="RFC2506" pageno="false" 
					format="default"/>.
				</t>
				<t>
					A SIP feature cap for the global tree will be registered by the IANA after 
					review by a designated expert. That review will serve to ensure that the 
					SIP feature cap meets the technical requirements of this specification.
				</t>	
				<t>
					A SIP feature cap in the global tree will be distinguished by the leading 
					facet "g.". An organization can propose either a designation indicative 
					of the feature, (e.g., "g.blinktags") or a faceted designation including
					the organization name (e.g., "g.organization.blinktags").
				</t>
				<t>
					When a SIP feature cap is registered in the global tree, it needs to meet
					the "Expert Review" policies defined in RFC 5226 <xref target="RFC5226" 
					pageno="false" format="default"/>. A designated area expert will review 
					the proposed SIP feature cap, and consult with members of related mailing
					lists.
				</t>				
				</section>
				<section title="SIP Feature Cap Registration Tree" anchor="sec.fc.reg.tree.sip" toc="default">
				<t>
					The SIP feature cap sip tree is based on the media feature tag
					sip tree defined in RFC 3840 <xref target="RFC3840" pageno="false" 
					format="default"/>.
				</t>
				<t>
					A SIP feature cap in the sip tree will be distinguished by the leading 
					facet "sip.".
				</t>
				<t>
					When a SIP feature cap is registered in the sip tree, it needs to meet
					the "IETF Consensus" policies defined in RFC 5226 <xref target="RFC5226" 
					pageno="false" format="default"/>. An RFC, which contains the registration
					of the SIP feature cap, must be published.
				</t>				
				</section>
			</section>
		
			<section title="Registration Template" anchor="sec.fc.reg.temp" toc="default">
				<figure title="Registration Template" anchor="fig.fc.reg.temp" suppress-title="false" align="left" alt="" width="" height="">
						<artwork xml:space="preserve" name="" type="" align="left" alt="" width="" height=""><![CDATA[ 

					
To: sip-feature-caps@apps.ietf.org (SIP feature caps mailing list)
Subject: Registration of SIP feature cap XXXX

| Instructions are preceded by `|'.  Some fields are optional.

SIP feature cap name:

Summary of feature indicated by this SIP feature cap:

| The summary should be no longer than 4 lines. More 
| detailed information can be provided in the SIP feature 
| cap specification
				
SIP feature cap specification reference:
				
| The reference MUST contain the information listed in 
| section XX of XXXX (IANA: Replace XXXX with assigned 
| RFC number of this specification
								
Values appropriate for use with this SIP feature cap:

| If no values are defined for the SIP feature cap, 
| indicate "N/A". Details about SIP feature cap values 
| MUST be defined in the SIP feature cap specification.
   
The SIP feature cap is intended primarily for 
use in the following applications, protocols, 
services, or negotiation mechanisms:                    [optional]																

| For applications, also specify the number of the 
| first version which will use the SIP feature cap, 
| if applicable.

Examples of typical use:                               	[optional]

Related standards or documents:                        	[optional]

Considerations particular to use in individual 
applications, protocols, services, or negotiation 
mechanisms:                                             [optional]

Interoperability considerations:                       	[optional]

Security considerations:

Privacy concerns, related to exposure of personal
information:

Denial of service concerns related to consequences 
of specifying incorrect values:

Other:

    Additional information:                         [optional]

    Keywords:                                       [optional]

    Related SIP feature caps:                    	[optional]

    Name(s) & email address(es) of person(s) to 
    contact for	further information:

    Intended usage:

    | one of COMMON, LIMITED USE or OBSOLETE

    Author/Change controller:

    Requested IANA publication delay:                [optional]

    | A delay may only be requested for final placement 
    | in the global or IETF trees, with a maximum of two 
    | months. Organizations requesting a registration 
    | with a publication delay should note that this 
    | delays only the official publication of the SIP
    | feature cap and does not prevent information on 
	| it from being disseminated by the members of the 
	| relevant mailing list.

    Other information:                               [optional]

    | Any other information that the author deems 
    | interesting may be added here.	
                      
						]]></artwork>
					</figure>
			</section>
		
			<section anchor="sec.fc.reqs" title="SIP Feature Cap Specification Requirements">
				<section anchor="sec.fc.reqs.gen" title="General">
				<t>
						A SIP feature cap specification MUST address the issues defined 
						in the following subsections, or document why an issue is not applicable 
						for the specific SIP feature cap. A reference to the specification MUST
						be provided when the SIP feature cap is registered with IANA 
						(see [ref-to-temp]).
				</t>
				<t>
						It is bad practice for SIP feature cap specifications to repeat procedures 
						defined in this specification, unless needed for clarification or emphasis 
						purpose.
				</t>
				<t>
						A SIP feature cap specification MUST NOT weaken any behavior designated 
						with "SHOULD" or "MUST" in this specification.  However, a 
						specification MAY strengthen "SHOULD", "MAY", or "RECOMMENDED" 
						requirements to "MUST" strength if features associated with the SIP 
						feature cap require it.
				</t>
				</section>
				<section anchor="sec.fc.reqs.ove" title="Overall Description">			
					<t>
						The SIP feature cap specification MUST contain an overall description of 
						the SIP feature cap: how it is used to indicate support of a feature, 
						a description of the feature associated with the SIP feature cap, and 
						a description of any additional information (conveyed using one or more
						SIP feature cap values) that can be conveyed together with the SIP feature 
						cap.
					</t>
				</section>
				<section anchor="sec.fc.reqs.value" title="Feature Cap Values">
				<t>
					A SIP feature cap can have an associated value, or a list of
					values. A SIP feature cap value MUST conform to the ABNF defined in 
					<xref target="sec.fc.syn.abnf"/>.
				</t>
				<t>
					The SIP feature cap specification MUST define the syntax and semantics 
					of any value defined for the SIP feature cap, including possible 
					restrictions related to the usage of a specific value.
				</t>
				<t>
					A SIP feature cap value can share the name with a value defined for
					another SIP feature cap. However, a value defined for a SIP feature 
					cap is feature cap specific, and can only be used with a SIP feature
					cap for which the value has explicitly been defined.
				</t>
				<t>
					It is STRONLY RECOMMENDED to not re-use a value name that already has
					been defined for another SIP feature cap, unless the semantics of the
					values are the same.
				</t>			
				</section>
				<section anchor="sec.fc.reqs.rest" title="Usage Restrictions">
				<t>
					If there are restrictions on how SIP entities can insert a SIP feature 
					cap, the SIP feature cap specification MUST document such restrictions.
				</t>
				<t>			
					There might be restrictions related to whether entities are allowed 
					to insert a SIP feature cap in registration related messages, standalone 
					transaction messages, or dialog related messages, whether entities 
					are allowed to insert a SIP feature cap in requests or responses, whether 
					entities also need to support other features in order to insert a 
					SIP feature cap, and whether entities are allowed to indicate support of
					a feature in conjunction with another feature.
				</t>
				</section>
				<section anchor="sec.fc.reqs.imp" title="Implementation Details">			
				<t>
					The SIP feature cap specification SHOULD define the procedure regarding 
					how implementers shall implement and use the Feature Cap, or refer to 
					other locations where implementers can find that information.
				</t>
				<t>
					NOTE: Sometimes a SIP feature cap designer might choose to not
      				reveal the implementation details of a SIP feature cap.  However, 
					in order to allow multiple implementations to support the SIP feature 
					cap, designers are strongly encouraged to provide the implementation
      				details.
				</t>
				</section>
				<section anchor="sec.fc.reqs.ex" title="Examples">
				<t>
					It is RECOMMENDED that the SIP feature cap specification provide
   					demonstrative message flow diagrams, paired with complete messages
   					and message descriptions.
				</t>
				<t>
					Note that example flows are by definition informative, and do not
   					replace normative text.
				</t>
				</section>
			</section>
		</section>


		<section title="Feature-Caps Header Field" anchor="sec.fchf" toc="default">
			<section title="Introduction" anchor="sec.fchf.int" toc="default">
				<t>
					The Feature-Caps header field is used by SIP entities to convey support 
					of features and capabilities, using SIP feature caps. SIP feature caps 
					inserted in a Feature-Caps header field indicate that the SIP entity that 
					inserted the header field supports the associated features.
				</t>
				<t>
					NOTE: It is not possible to convey the address of the SIP entity as a
					Feature-Caps header field parameter. Each feature that requires address 
					information to be conveyed need to define a way to convey that information
					as part of the associated SIP feature cap value.				
				</t>
				<t>	
					The SIP feature cap specification MUST specify for which SIP methods
					and message types, and the associated semantics, the SIP feature cap is 
					applicable. See section [ref-to-reg-temp} for more information. No semantics 
					is defined for SIP feature caps present in SIP methods and message types not 
					covered by the associated SIP feature cap specification.
				</t>
				<t>
					Within a given Feature-Caps header field, SIP feature caps are listed in a 
					non-priority order, and for a given header field any order of listed SIP feature 
					caps have the same meaning. For example, "foo;bar" and "bar;foo" have the same 
					meaning(i.e. that the SIP entity that inserted the feature caps supports the 
					features associated with the "foo" and "bar" SIP feature caps.
				</t>
			</section>	

			<section title="User Agent and Proxy Behavior" anchor="sec.fchf.ua" toc="default">
				<section title="General" anchor="sec.fchf.ua.gen" toc="default">			
							<t>
								If the URI in a Contact header field of a request or response represents 
								a UA, the UA MUST NOT indicate supported features and capabilities using 
								a Feature-Caps header field within that request or response.
							</t>
							<t>
								When a UA receives a SIP request, or response, that contains one or more 
								Feature-Caps header fields, the Feature Caps in the header field inform 
								the UA is about the features supported by the entities that inserted the 
								header fields. Procedures how features are invoked are outside the scope 
								of this specification, and MUST be described by individual Feature Cap 
								specifications.
							</t>
							<t>
								When the UA receives the SIP request or the response, the SIP feature
								caps in the topmost Feature-Caps header field will represent the
								supported features "closest" to the UA.
							</t>				
				</section>
				<section title="B2BUA Behavior" anchor="sec.fchf.ua.b2bua" toc="default">			
							<t>
								The procedures in this section applies to UAs that are part of B2BUAs, but 
								where the URI in the Contact header field does not represent the UA, because 
								the B2BUA is also acting as a proxy and inserts its URI e.g. in a Record-Route 
								header field.
							</t>
							<t>
								When a UA sends a SIP request, if the UA wants to indicate support of features
								towards its downstream SIP entities, it adds a Feature-Caps header field to the 
								request, together with one or more Feature Caps associated with the supported features, 
								before it forwards the request.
							</t>
							<t>
								If the SIP request is triggered by another SIP request that the B2BUA has received, the
								UA MAY forward those Feature-Caps header field by copying them to the outgoing SIP request, 
								similar to a SIP proxy, before it adds its own Feature-Caps header field to the SIP request.				
							</t>
							<t>
								When a UA receives a SIP response, if the UA wants to indicate support of features
								towards its upstream SIP entities, it adds a Feature-Caps header field to the response, 
								together with one or more Feature Caps associated with the supported features, before it 
								forwards the response.
							</t>
							<t>
								If the SIP response is triggered by another SIP response that the B2BUA has received, the
								UA MAY forward those Feature-Caps header field by copying them to the outgoing SIP response, 
								similar to a SIP proxy, before it adds its own Feature-Caps header field to the SIP response.				
							</t>
				</section>
			
				<section title="Registrar Behavior" anchor="sec-ua-reg" toc="default">			
					<t>
						If a SIP registrar wants to indicate support of features towards its upstream SIP entities,
						it can insert a Feature-Caps header field, together with Feature Caps associated with the
						supported features, in a REGISTER response.
					</t>
				</section>
				
				<section title="Proxy behavior" anchor="sec-proxy" toc="default">			
				<t>
					When a SIP proxy receives a SIP request, if the proxy wants to indicate support of features
					towards its downstream SIP entities, it adds a Feature-Caps header field to the request, 
					together with one or more SIP feature caps associated with the supported features, before it 
					forwards the request.
				</t>
				<t>
					When a proxy adds a Feature-Caps header field to a SIP message, it MUST place the header 
					field before any existing Feature-Caps header fields in the request.
				</t>
				<t>
					When a proxy receives a SIP response, if the proxy wants to indicate support of features
					towards its upstream SIP entities, it adds a Feature-Caps header field to the response, 
					together with one or more SIP feature caps associated with the supported features, before it 
					forwards the response.
				</t>
				<t>
					When a proxy adds a Feature-Caps header field to a SIP response, it MUST place the header 
					field before any existing Feature-Caps header field in the response. 
				</t>
				</section>
			</section>

			<section title="SIP Message Type and Response Code Semantics" anchor="sec-fc" toc="default">
				<section title="General" anchor="sec-fc-sip-gen" toc="default">
					<t>
						This section describes the general usage and semantics of the Feature-Caps
						header field for different SIP message types and response codes. 
						The usage and semantics of a specific SIP feature cap MUST be described in
						the associated SIP feature cap specification.
					</t>
					<t>
						NOTE: Future specifications can define usage and semantics of the Feature-Caps 
						header field for SIP methods, response codes and
						request types not specified in this specification.
					</t>
				</section>
				<section title="SIP Dialog" anchor="sec-fc-sip-dia" toc="default">				
					<t>
						The Feature-Caps header field can be used within an initial SIP request for a dialog, 
						within a target refresh SIP request, and within any 18x or 2xx response associated 
						with such requests.
					</t>
					<t>
						If a SIP feature cap is inserted in a Feature-Caps header field of an initial request
						for a dialog, or within a response of such request, it indicates to the receivers of
						the request (or response) that the feature associated with the SIP feature cap is supported 
						for the duration of the dialog, until a target refresh request is sent for the dialog, or 
						the dialog is terminated.
					</t>
					<t>
						Unless a SIP feature cap is inserted in a Feature-Caps header field or a target
						refresh request, or within a response of such request, it indicates to the receivers of
						the request (or response) that the feature is no long supported for the dialog.	
					</t>
					<t>
						For a given dialog a SIP entity MUST insert the same SIP feature caps in all 18x and 
						2xx responses associated with a given transaction.
					</t>
				</section>
				<section title="SIP Registration (REGISTER)" anchor="sec-fc-sip-reg" toc="default">				
					<t>
						The Feature-Caps header field can be used within a SIP REGISTER request, and within 
						the 200 (OK) response associated with such request.
					</t>
					<t>
						If a SIP feature cap is inserted in a Feature-Caps header field of a SIP REGISTER request,
						or within a response of such request, it indicates to the receivers of the request (or response)
						that the feature associated with the SIP feature cap is supported for the duration of
						the registration, and for all SIP transactions associated with the registration, until 
						the registration is re-freshed or terminated.
					</t>
					<t>
						Unless a SIP feature cap is inserted in a Feature-Caps header field or a re-registration,
						or within a response of such request, it indicates to the receivers of the request (or response) 
						that the feature is no long supported for the registration.					
					</t>
				</section>
				<section title="SIP Stand-Alone Transactions" anchor="sec-fc-sip-sa" toc="default">
					<t>
						The Feature-Caps header field can be used within a standalone SIP request, 
						and within any 18x or 2xx response associated with such request.
					</t>
					<t>
						If a SIP feature cap is inserted in a Feature-Caps header field of a standalone
						request, or within a response of such request, it indicates to the receivers of
						the request (or response) that the feature associated with the SIP feature cap
						is supported for the duration of the standalone transaction.
					</t>
				</section>
			</section>
		
			<section title="Syntax" anchor="sec.fchf.syn" toc="default">
				<section title="ABNF" anchor="sec.fchf.syn.abnf" toc="default">
					<t>
						The ABNF for the Feature-Caps header fields is:
					</t>
					<figure title="ABNF" anchor="fig-abnf" suppress-title="false" align="left" alt="" width="" height="">
          			<artwork xml:space="preserve" name="" type="" align="left" alt="" width="" height=""><![CDATA[ 

Feature-Caps = ("Feature-Caps" / "fc") HCOLON fc-value
                *(COMMA fc-value)   
fc-value     = "*" *(SEMI feature-cap) 
 
					]]></artwork>
					</figure>
					<t>
						NOTE: A "*" value means that no information regarding which SIP entity, or 
						domain, that indicate support of features is 
						provided.
					</t>
				</section>
			</section>
		</section>
	    					
		<section title="IANA Considerations" anchor="sec.iana" toc="default">
			<section title="Registration of the Feature-Caps header field" anchor="sec.iana.fchf" toc="default">
				<t>
					This specification registers a new SIP header field, Feature-Caps, according 
					to the process of RFC 3261 <xref target="RFC3261" pageno="false" format="default"/>.
				</t>
				<t>
					The following is the registration for the Feature-Caps header field:
				</t>
				<t>
					RFC Number: RFC XXX
				</t>
				<t>
					Header Field Name: Feature-Caps
					Header Field Name: Feature-Caps
				</t>
				<t>
					Compact Form: fc
				</t>
			</section>
    	</section>

    	<section title="Security Considerations" anchor="sec.seccon" toc="default">
			<t>				
				SIP feature caps can provide sensitive information about a SIP entity.
				RFC 3840 cautions against providing sensitive information to
				another party. Once this information is given out, any use may be 
				made of it.
			</t>
		</section>
		
		<section title="Acknowledgements" anchor="sec.acks" toc="default">
			<t></t>
		</section>
		
		<section title="Change Log">
			<t>[RFC EDITOR NOTE: Please remove this section when publishing]</t>
			<t>
				Changes from draft-holmberg-sipcore-proxy-feature-04/draft-ietf-sipcore-proxy-feature-00
				<list style="symbols">
					<t>
						Media feature tags replaced with SIP feature caps, based on
						SIPCORE consensus at IETF#83 (Paris).
					</t>										
					<t>
						Editorial corrections and modifications.
					</t>
				</list>
			</t>	
			<t>
				Changes from draft-holmberg-sipcore-proxy-feature-03
				<list style="symbols">
					<t>
						Hadriel Kaplan added as co-author.
					</t>
					<t>
						Terminology change: instead of talking of proxies, talk about
						entities which are not represented by the URI in a Contact header
						field 
						(http://www.ietf.org/mail-archive/web/sipcore/current/msg04449.html).
					</t>
					<t>
						Clarification regarding the usage of the header field in 18x/2xx responses
						(http://www.ietf.org/mail-archive/web/sipcore/current/msg04449.html).
					</t>
					<t>
						Specifying that feature support can also be indicated in target
						refresh requests 
						(http://www.ietf.org/mail-archive/web/sipcore/current/msg04454.html).
					</t>
					<t>
						Feature Cap specification registration information added.
					</t>
				</list>
			</t>	
			<t>
				Changes from draft-holmberg-sipcore-proxy-feature-02
				<list style="symbols">
					<t>
						Definition, and usage of, a new header field, instead of
						Path, Record-Route, Route and Service-Route.
					</t>					
				</list>
			</t>	
			<t>
				Changes from draft-holmberg-sipcore-proxy-feature-01
				<list style="symbols">
					<t>Requirement section added</t>					
					<t>Use-cases and examples updated based on work in 3GPP</t>					
				</list>
			</t>	
			<t>
				Changes from draft-holmberg-sipcore-proxy-feature-00
				<list style="symbols">
					<t>Additional use-cases added</t>
					<t>Direction section added</t>
				</list>
			</t>		
		</section>		
	</middle>
	
	<back>
		<references title="Normative References">
			<?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119"?>			
			<?rfc include="reference.RFC.3261"?>						
		</references>
		<references title="Informative References">	  						
			<?rfc include="reference.RFC.2506"?>			
			<?rfc include="reference.RFC.3840"?>
			<?rfc include="reference.RFC.3841"?>				
			<?rfc include="reference.RFC.5226"?>			
			<?rfc include="reference.3GPP.23.237"?>
			<?rfc include="reference.3GPP.24.837"?>
		</references>
	</back>
</rfc>