<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!-- comment -->
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd"[]>
<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="no" ?>
<rfc ipr="trust200811" category="std" docName="draft-ietf-sipcore-proxy-feature-09.txt" obsoletes="" updates="" submissionType="IETF" xml:lang="en">
	<front>
		<title abbrev="proxy feature">
			Mechanism to indicate support of features and capabilities in the Session Initiation Protocol (SIP)
		</title>
		<author initials="C.H." surname="Holmberg" fullname="Christer Holmberg">
			<organization>Ericsson</organization>
			<address>
				<postal>
					<street>Hirsalantie 11</street>
					<code>02420</code>
					<city>Jorvas</city>
					<country>Finland</country>
				</postal>
				<email>christer.holmberg@ericsson.com</email>
			</address>
		</author>
		<author initials="I.S." surname="Sedlacek" fullname="Ivo Sedlacek">
			<organization>Ericsson</organization>
			<address>
				<postal>
					<street>Scheelevägen 19C</street>
					<code>22363</code>
					<city>Lund</city>
					<country>Sweden</country>
				</postal>
				<email>ivo.sedlacek@ericsson.com</email>
			</address>
		</author>
		<author initials="H.K." surname="Kaplan" fullname="Hadriel Kaplan">
			<organization>Acme Packet</organization>
			<address>
				<postal>
					<street>71 Third Ave.</street>
					<city>Burlington</city>
					<region>MA</region>
					<code>01803</code>
					<country>USA</country>
				</postal>
				<email>hkaplan@acmepacket.com</email>        
			</address>
		</author>		
		
		<date year="2012" />
		<area>Transport</area>
		<workgroup>SIPCORE Working Group</workgroup>
		<keyword>SIP</keyword>
		<keyword>proxy</keyword>
		<keyword>feature</keyword>
		<keyword>feature tag</keyword>
		<keyword>feature capability indicator</keyword>
		<keyword>Feature-Caps</keyword>
		<keyword>capabiltiy</keyword>		
		<abstract>
			<t>
				This specification defines a new SIP header field, Feature-Caps, 
				to convey feature capability indicators, which are used by SIP entities 
				not represented by the URI of the Contact header field to indicate 
				support of features and capabilities, where media feature tags cannot 
				be used to indicate the support.
			</t>
			<t>
				This specification also defines feature capability indicators, and creates 
				a new IANA registry, "Proxy-Feature Feature Capability Indicator Trees", for 
				registering feature capability indicators.
			</t>
		</abstract>
	</front>
	<middle>
		<section title="Introduction" toc="default">
			<t>
				The Session Initiation Protocol (SIP) <xref target="RFC3261" pageno="false" 
				format="default"/> "Caller Preferences" extension, defined in RFC 3840 <xref 
				target="RFC3840" pageno="false" format="default"/>, provides a mechanism that 
				allows a SIP message to convey information relating to the originator's features 
				and capabilities, using the Contact header field.
			</t>
			<t>
				This specification defines a new SIP header field, Feature-Caps, 
				to convey feature capability indicators, which are used by SIP entities 
				not represented by the URI of the Contact header field to indicate 
				support of features and capabilities, where media feature tags cannot 
				be used to indicate the support. Such cases are:
				<t>
					<list style="symbols">
						<t>
							- The SIP entity acts as a SIP proxy.
						</t>
						<t>
							- The SIP entity acts as a SIP registrar.
						</t>
						<t>
							- The SIP entity acts as a B2BUA, where the 
							Contact header field URI represents another SIP entity.
						</t>					
					</list>
				</t>
			</t>
			<t>
				NOTE: Unlike media feature tags, feature capability indicators are intended 
				to only be used with the SIP protocol.
			</t>
			<t>
				This specification also defines feature capability indicators, and creates 
				a new IANA registry, "Proxy-Feature Feature Capability Indicator Trees", for 
				registering feature capability indicators.
			</t>
		</section>
		
		<section title="Conventions" toc="default">
			<t>
				The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", 
				"RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in 
				BCP 14, RFC 2119 <xref target="RFC2119" pageno="false" format="default" />.
			</t>
		</section>

		<section title="Definitions" toc="default">
			<t>
				Downstream SIP entity: SIP entity in the direction towards which a SIP request is sent.
			</t>
			<t>
				Upstream SIP entity: SIP entity in the direction from which a SIP request is received.
			</t>
		</section>
								
		<section title="Feature-Caps Header Field" anchor="sec.fchf" toc="default">
			<section title="Introduction" anchor="sec.fchf.int" toc="default">
				<t>
					The Feature-Caps header field is used by SIP entities to convey support 
					of features and capabilities, by setting feature capability indicators. 
					A feature capability indicator conveyed in a Feature-Caps header field indicates 
					that a SIP entity in the SIP message signalling path supports the associated 
					feature and capability.
				</t>
			</section>	

			<section title="User Agent and Proxy Behavior" anchor="sec.fchf.ua" toc="default">
				<section title="General" anchor="sec.fchf.ua.gen" toc="default">			
					<t>
						If the URI in a Contact header field of a request or response represents 
						a SIP entity, the entity MUST NOT indicate supported features and capabilities 
						using a Feature-Caps header field within that request or response.
					</t>
					<t>
						When a SIP entity receives a SIP request, or response, that contains one or more 
						Feature-Caps header fields, the feature capability indicators in the header field inform 
						the entity about the features and capabilities supported by entities in the SIP message
						signalling path. Procedures how features and capabilities are invoked are outside the scope 
						of this specification, and MUST be described by individual feature capability indicator 
						specifications.
					</t>
					<t>
						NOTE: It is not possible to, as a Feature-Caps header field value, convey 
						the address of the SIP entity that inserted the Feature-Caps header field. 
						If additional data about a supported feature needs to be conveyed, such 
						as the address of the SIP entity that indicated support of the feature, then 
						the feature definition needs to define a way to convey that information as 
						a value of the associated feature capability indicator.
					</t>
					<t>
						When a SIP entity adds a Feature-Caps header field to a SIP message, it MUST place
						the header field before any existing Feature-Caps header field in the message to
						be forwarded, so that the added header field becomes the top-most one.
						Then, when another SIP entity receives a SIP request or the response, the SIP 
						feature capability indicators in the top-most Feature-Caps header field will represent the
						supported features and capabilities "closest" to the entity.
					</t>
					<t>
						For a given fc-value, as defined in section 5.3.1, feature capability
						indicators are listed in a non-priority order, and any order of the listed SIP
						feature capability indicators have the same meaning. For example, "foo;bar" and
						"bar;foo" have the same meaning (i.e. that the SIP entity that inserted the feature 
						capability indicator supports the features and capabilities associated with the 
						"foo" and "bar" feature capability indicators.
					</t>
				</section>
				<section title="B2BUA Behavior" anchor="sec.fchf.ua.b2bua" toc="default">			
					<t>
						The procedures in this Section applies to UAs that are part of
						B2BUAs that are referenced in the message by a Record-Route header
						field rather than by the URI of the Contact header field.
					</t>
					<t>
						When such a UA sends a SIP request, if the UA wants to indicate support of 
						features and capabilities towards its downstream SIP entities, it inserts a Feature-Caps 
						header field to the request, containing one or more feature capability indicators 
						associated with the supported features and capabilities, before it forwards the request.
					</t>
					<t>
						If the SIP request is triggered by another SIP request that the B2BUA 
						has received, the UA MAY forward received Feature-Caps header fields by 
						copying them to the outgoing SIP request, similar to a SIP proxy, before 
						it inserts its own Feature-Caps header field to the SIP request.				
					</t>
					<t>
						When such a UA receives a SIP response, if the UA wants to indicate support 
						of features and capabilities towards its upstream SIP entities, it inserts a Feature-Caps 
						header field to the response, containing one or more feature capability indicators 
						associated with the supported features and capabilities, before it forwards the response.
					</t>
					<t>
						If the SIP response is triggered by another SIP response that the B2BUA 
						has received, the UA MAY forward received Feature-Caps header field by 
						copying them to the outgoing SIP response, similar to a SIP proxy, before 
						it inserts its own Feature-Caps header field to the SIP response.				
					</t>
				</section>
			
				<section title="Registrar Behavior" anchor="sec-ua-reg" toc="default">			
					<t>
						If a SIP registrar wants to indicate support of features and capabilities towards its 
						upstream SIP entities, it inserts a Feature-Caps header field, containing 
						one or more feature capability indicators associated with the supported features and capabilities, to 
						a REGISTER response.
					</t>
				</section>
				
				<section title="Proxy behavior" anchor="sec-proxy" toc="default">			
					<t>
						When a SIP proxy receives a SIP request, if the proxy wants to indicate 
						support of features and capabilities towards its downstream SIP entities, it inserts a 
						Feature-Caps header field to the request, containing one or more SIP 
						feature capability indicators associated with the supported features and capabilities, before it 
						forwards the request.
					</t>
					<t>
						When a proxy receives a SIP response, if the proxy wants to indicate 
						support of features and capabilities towards its upstream SIP entities, it inserts a 
						Feature-Caps header field to the response, containing one or more SIP 
						feature capability indicators associated with the supported features and capabilities, before it forwards 
						the response.
					</t>
				</section>
			</section>

			<section title="SIP Message Type and Response Code Semantics" anchor="sec-fc" toc="default">
				<section title="General" anchor="sec-fc-sip-gen" toc="default">
					<t>
						This Section describes the general usage and semantics of the Feature-Caps
						header field for different SIP message types and response codes. 						
					</t>
					<t>
						Section 6.2.1 defines the Feature-Caps header field ABNF.						
					</t>
				</section>
				<section title="SIP Dialog" anchor="sec-fc-sip-dia" toc="default">				
					<t>
						The Feature-Caps header field can be used within an initial SIP request for a dialog, 
						within a target refresh SIP request, and within any 18x or 2xx response associated 
						with such requests.
					</t>
					<t>
						If a feature capability indicator is inserted in a Feature-Caps header field of an initial request
						for a dialog, or within a response of such request, it indicates to the receivers of
						the request (or response) that the feature associated with the feature capability indicator is supported 
						for the duration of the dialog, until a target refresh request is sent for the dialog, or 
						the dialog is terminated.
					</t>
					<t>
						Unless a feature capability indicator is inserted in a Feature-Caps header field of a target
						refresh request, or within a response of such request, it indicates to the receivers of
						the request (or response) that the feature is no longer supported for the dialog.	
					</t>
					<t>
						For a given dialog a SIP entity MUST insert the same feature capability indicators in all 18x and 
						2xx responses associated with a given transaction.
					</t>
					<t>
						NOTE: As it cannot be guaranteed that 2xx responses associated with
						SIP SUBSCRIBE requests will reach the UAC, due to forking of the request,
						entities need to indicate supported features and capabilities in the SIP NOTIFY 
						request that will be sent for each of the created subscription dialogs.
					</t>
				</section>
				<section title="SIP Registration (REGISTER)" anchor="sec-fc-sip-reg" toc="default">				
					<t>
						The Feature-Caps header field can be used within a SIP REGISTER request, and within 
						the 200 (OK) response associated with such request.
					</t>
					<t>
						If a feature capability indicator is conveyed in a Feature-Caps header field of a REGISTER request, or
						within an associated response, it indicates to the receivers of the message that the
						feature associated with the feature capability indicator is supported for the registration, until the 
						registration of the contact that was explicitly conveyed in the REGISTER request expires, 
						or until the registered contact is explicitly refreshed and the refresh REGISTER request 
						does not contain the feature capability indicator associated with the feature.				
					</t>
					<t>
						NOTE: While a REGISTER response can contain contacts that have been
						registered as part of other registration transactions, support of any
						indicated feature only applies to requests sent to the contact(s) that 
						were explicitly conveyed in the associated REGISTER request.
					</t>
					<t>
						This specification does not define any semantics for usage of the Feature-Caps header field
						in pure registration binding fetching messages (see Section 10.2.3 of RFC 3261), where the 
						REGISTER request does not contain a Contact header field. Unless such semantics is defined
						in a future extension, fetching messages will not have any impact on previously indicated 
						support of features and capabilities, and SIP entities MUST NOT insert a Feature-Caps header 
						field to such messages.					
					</t>
					<t>
						If SIP Outbound <xref target="RFC5626" pageno="false" format="default"/> is used, the rules
						above apply. However, supported features and capabilities only apply for the registration 
						flow on which support has been explicitly indicated.						
					</t>
				</section>
				<section title="SIP Stand-Alone Transactions" anchor="sec-fc-sip-sa" toc="default">
					<t>
						The Feature-Caps header field can be used within a standalone SIP request, 
						and within any 2xx response associated with such request.
					</t>
					<t>
						If a feature capability indicator is inserted in a Feature-Caps header field of a standalone
						request, or within a response of such request, it indicates to the receivers of
						the request (or response) that the feature associated with the feature capability indicator
						is supported for the duration of the standalone transaction.
					</t>
				</section>
			</section>		
		</section>
		
		<section title="Feature Capability Indicators" anchor="sec.fc" toc="default">
			<section title="Introduction" anchor="sec.fc.int" toc="default">
				<t>				
					Feature capability indicators are used by SIP entities not
					represented by the URI of the Contact header field to indicate
					support of features and capabilities, where media feature tags cannot
					be used to indicate the support.
				</t>
				<t>
					A value, or a list of values, that provides additional information
					about the supported feature or capability, can be associated with a
					feature capability indicator.
				</t>
			</section>

			<section title="Registration Trees" anchor="sec.fc.reg.tree" toc="default">
				<section title="General" anchor="sec.fc.reg.tree.gen" toc="default">
					<t>
						The following subsections define registration trees, distinguished
						by the use of faceted names (e.g., names of the form "tree.feature-
						name"). The registration trees are defined in the IANA 
						"Proxy-Feature Feature Capability Indicator Trees" registry.
					</t>
					<t>
						The trees defined herein are similar to the global tree and sip tree
						defined for media feature tags, in RFC 2506 <xref target="RFC2506" 
						pageno="false" format="default"/> and RFC 3840. Other registration 
						trees are outside the scope of this specification.
					</t>
					<t>
						NOTE: In contrast to RFC 2506 and RFC 3840, this specification only
						defines a global tree and a sip tree, as they are the only trees
						defined in those RFCs that have been used for defining SIP-specific
						media feature tags.
					</t>
					<t>
						When a feature capability indicator is registered in any registration tree, no
						leading "+" is used in the registration.
					</t>
				</section>
				<section title="Global Tree" anchor="sec.fc.reg.tree.glob" toc="default">
				<t>
					The global feature capability indicator tree is similar to the media feature tag 
					global tree defined in RFC 2506 <xref target="RFC2506" pageno="false" 
					format="default"/>.
				</t>
				<t>
					A feature capability indicator for the global tree will be registered by the IANA after 
					review by a designated expert. That review will serve to ensure that the definition of 
					the feature capability indicator meets the technical requirements of this specification.
				</t>	
				<t>
					A feature capability indicator in the global tree will be distinguished by the leading 
					facet "g.". An organization can propose either a designation indicative 
					of the feature, (e.g., "g.blinktags") or a faceted designation including
					the organization name (e.g., "g.organization.blinktags").
				</t>
				<t>
					When a feature capability indicator is registered in the global tree,
    					it needs to meet the "Specification Required" policies defined in RFC 5226
    					<xref target="RFC5226" pageno="false" format="default"/>.  A designated area 
 					expert will review the proposed feature capability indicator, and consult with members 
					of related mailing lists.
				</t>
				</section>
				<section title="SIP Tree" anchor="sec.fc.reg.tree.sip" toc="default">
				<t>
					The sip feature capability indicator tree is similar to the media feature tag
					sip tree defined in RFC 3840.
				</t>
				<t>
					A feature capability indicator in the sip tree will be distinguished by the leading 
					facet "sip.".
				</t>
				<t>
					When a feature capability indicator is registered in the sip tree, it
    					needs to meet the "IETF Consensus" policies defined in RFC 5226. An 
					RFC, which contains the registration of the feature capability indicator, 
					MUST be published.
				</t>
				</section>
			</section>
				
			<section anchor="sec.fc.reqs" title="Feature Capability Indicator Specification Requirements">
				<section anchor="sec.fc.reqs.gen" title="General">
				<t>
						A feature capability indicator specification MUST address the issues defined 
						in the following subsections, or document why an issue is not applicable 
						for the specific feature capability indicator. A reference to the specification MUST
						be provided when the feature capability indicator is registered with IANA 
						(see <xref target="sec.temp" pageno="false" format="default"/>).
				</t>
				<t>
						It is bad practice for feature capability indicator specifications to repeat procedures 
						(e.g. general procedures on the usage of the Feature-Caps header field 
						and feature capability indicators) defined in this specification, unless needed for 
						clarification or emphasis purpose. A feature capability indicator specification MUST NOT 
						modify the Feature-Caps header field rules and semantics defined in Section 4.
				</t>
				<t>
						A feature capability indicator specification MUST NOT weaken any behavior designated 
						with "SHOULD" or "MUST" in this specification.  However, a 
						specification MAY strengthen "SHOULD", "MAY", or "RECOMMENDED" 
						requirements to "MUST" strength if features and capabilities associated with the SIP 
						feature capability indicator require it.
				</t>
				</section>
				<section anchor="sec.fc.reqs.ove" title="Overall Description">			
					<t>
						The feature capability indicator specification MUST contain an
						overall description of the feature capability indicator: how it is
						used to indicate support of a feature, a description of the feature
						associated with the feature capability indicator, a description of 
						any additional information (conveyed using one or more feature capability 
						indicator values) that can be conveyed together with the feature capability
						indicator, and a description of how the associated feature may be
						exercised/invoked.
					</t>
				</section>
				<section anchor="sec.fc.reqs.value" title="Feature Capability Indicator Values">
				<t>
					A feature capability indicator can have an associated value, or a
					list of values.

					The feature capability indicator specification MUST define the syntax
					and semantics of any value defined for the feature capability
					indicator, including possible restrictions related to the usage of a
					specific value. The feature capability indicator specification MUST 
					define the value(s) in accordance with the ABNF defined in Section
					6.3.2. The feature capability indicator specification MUST define
					whether the feature capability indicator has a default value.
				</t>
				<t>
					If no values are defined for the feature capability indicator, it MUST
					be indicated in the feature capability indicator specification.
				</t>
				<t>
					A feature capability indicator value is only applicable for the
					feature capability indicator for which it has been defined.  For
					other feature capability indicators, the value has to be defined
					explicitly, even if the semantics are identical.
				</t>
				<t>
					It is strongly RECOMMENDED to not re-use a value that already has
					been defined for another feature capability indicator, unless the
					semantics of the values are the same.
				</t>
				</section>
				<section anchor="sec.fc.reqs.rest" title="Usage Restrictions">
				<t>
					If there are restrictions on how SIP entities can insert a feature 
					capability indicator, the feature capability indicator specification MUST
					document such restrictions.
				</t>
				<t>			
					There might be restrictions related to whether entities are allowed
					to insert a feature capability indicator in registration related
					messages, standalone transaction messages, dialog related
					messages, whether entities are allowed to insert a feature capability
					indicator in requests or responses, whether entities also need to
					support other features and capabilities in order to insert a feature
					capability indicator, and whether entities are allowed to indicate
					support of a feature in conjunction with another feature.
				</t>
				</section>
				<section anchor="sec.fc.reqs.ic" title="Interoperability Considerations">
				<t>
					If there are specific interoperability considerations that apply to the 
					feature capability indicator, the feature capability indicator specification
					MUST document such considerations.
				</t>
				</section>
				<section anchor="sec.fc.reqs.sc" title="Security Considerations">
				<t>
					If there are specific security considerations that apply to the feature
					capability indicator, the feature capability indicator specification
					MUST document such considerations.
				</t>
				</section>
				<section anchor="sec.fc.reqs.ex" title="Examples">
				<t>
					It is RECOMMENDED that the feature capability indicator specification provide
   					demonstrative message flow diagrams, paired with complete messages
   					and message descriptions.
				</t>
				<t>
					Note that example message flows are by definition informative, and do not
   					replace normative text.
				</t>
				</section>
				<section anchor="sec.fc.reqs.oi" title="Other Information">
				<t>
					If there is additional information about the feature capability indicator,
					it is RECOMMENDED to describe such information. It can include e.g.
					names of related feature capability indicators.
				</t>
				</section>
			</section>
		</section>
		
		<section title="Syntax" anchor="sec.syn" toc="default">
			<section title="General" anchor="sec.syn.gen" toc="default">
				<t>
					This Section defines the ABNF for the Feature-Caps header field, and for
					the feature capability indicators.					
				</t>
			</section>
									
			<section title="Syntax: Feature-Caps header field" anchor="sec.syn.fchf" toc="default">
				<section title="ABNF" toc="default" anchor="sec.syn.fchf.abnf">
					<t>
						The ABNF for the Feature-Caps header fields is:
					</t>
					<figure title="ABNF" anchor="fig-abnf" suppress-title="false" align="left" alt="" width="" height="">
					<artwork xml:space="preserve" name="" type="" align="left" alt="" width="" height=""><![CDATA[ 

Feature-Caps = "Feature-Caps" HCOLON fc-value
                *(COMMA fc-value)   
fc-value     = "*" *(SEMI feature-cap) 
 
					]]></artwork>
					</figure>
					<t>
						NOTE: The "*" value is present in order to follow the guidelines for syntax 
						in RFC 4485 <xref target="RFC4485" pageno="false" format="default"/> and to maintain a 
						consistent format with RFC 3840 and RFC 3841 <xref target="RFC3841" pageno="false" 
						format="default"/>.
					</t>
				</section>
			</section>
			
			<section title="Syntax: feature capability indicator" anchor="sec.syn.fc" toc="default">
				<section title="General" anchor="sec.syn.fc.gen" toc="default">
					<t>
						In a feature capability indicator name (ABNF: fcap-name), dots can be used to implement a feature 
						capability indicator tree hierarchy (e.g. tree.feature.subfeature). The description of usage of such 
						tree hierarchy must be described when registered.
					</t>
				</section>
				<section title="ABNF" toc="default" anchor="sec.syn.fc.abnf">
					<t>
						The ABNF for the feature capability indicator:
					</t>
					<figure title="ABNF" anchor="fig.syn.fc.abnf" suppress-title="false" align="left" alt="" width="" height="">
						<artwork xml:space="preserve" name="" type="" align="left" alt="" width="" height=""><![CDATA[ 

feature-cap       =  "+" fcap-name [EQUAL LDQUOT (fcap-value-list
                         / fcap-string-value ) RDQUOT]
fcap-name         =  ftag-name
fcap-value-list   =  tag-value-list
fcap-string-value =  string-value
;; ftag-name, tag-value-list, string-value defined in RFC 3840
			            
NOTE: In comparison with media feature tags, the "+" sign in front
of the feature capability indicator name is mandatory.
						
						]]></artwork>
					</figure>
				</section>
			</section>			
    	</section>	
		
		<section title="IANA Considerations" anchor="sec.iana" toc="default">
			<section title="Registration of the Feature-Caps header field" anchor="sec.iana.fchf" toc="default">
				<t>
					This specification registers a new SIP header field, Feature-Caps, according 
					to the process of RFC 3261 <xref target="RFC3261" pageno="false" format="default"/>.
				</t>
				<t>
					The following is the registration for the Feature-Caps header field:
				</t>
				<t>
					RFC Number: RFC &rfc.number;
				</t>
				<t>
					Header Field Name: Feature-Caps
				</t>
			</section>

			<section title="Registration of the Feature-Caps header field parameter" anchor="sec.iana.siphf" toc="default">
				<t>
					This specification adds the Feature-Caps header field to the IANA "Header Field Parameters and
					Parameter Values" registry, according to the process of RFC 3968 <xref target="RFC3968" pageno="false" 
					format="default"/>.
				</t>
				<figure title="SIP Parameter Header Field" anchor="fig.iana.siphf" suppress-title="false" align="left" alt="" width="" height="">
						<artwork xml:space="preserve" name="" type="" align="left" alt="" width="" height=""><![CDATA[ 

                                    Predefined
Header Field      Parameter Name    Values      Reference
------------------------------------------------------------------

Feature-Caps      +<fcap-name> *    No          [RFC XXXX]

       * <fcap-name> denotes parameter names conforming to the
         syntax <fcap-name> defined in RFC XXXX. Valid 
         feature capability indicators are registered in [IANA: 
         insert reference to the new Proxy-Feature Feature 
         Capability Indicator Trees registry].        			  
					  
						]]></artwork>
					</figure>
					<t>
						(IANA: please sort the "Feature-Caps" line into the table and place
						the remainder of the above as a footnote to the table.)
					</t>
			</section>	

			<section title="Proxy-Feature Feature Capability Indicator Trees" anchor="sec.iana.tree" toc="default">
				<section title="Introduction" anchor="sec.iana.tree.int" toc="default">
					<t>
						This specification creates a new sub registry to the IANA "Session Initiation 
						Protocol (SIP) Parameters" Protocol Registry, according to the process of RFC 5226. 
						The name of the sub registry is "Proxy-Feature Feature Capability Indicator Trees".
					</t>
				</section>
				<section title="Global Feature Capability Indicator Registration Tree" anchor="sec.iana.tree.g" toc="default">
					<t>
						This specification creates a new feature capability indicator tree in the IANA "Proxy-Feature Feature 
						Capability Indicator Trees" registry. The name of the tree is "Global Feature Capability Indicator Registration 
						Tree", and its leading facet is "g.". It is used for the registration of 
						feature capability indicators.
					</t>
					<t>
						When a feature capability indicator is registered in the global tree,
    						it needs to meet the "Specification Required" policies defined in RFC 5226.
    						A designated area expert will review the proposed feature capability indicator, 
						and consult with members of related mailing lists. 
						The information required in the registration is defined in Section 5.3 of 
						RFC &rfc.number;.
					</t>
					<t>
						Note that all feature capability indicators registered in the global tree will have names
						with a leading facet "g.". No leading "+" is used in the registrations in 
						any of the feature capability indicator registration trees.
					</t>
					<t>
						The format of the global tree is as described below:
					</t>
					<figure anchor="fig.iana.tree.g" suppress-title="false" align="left" alt="" width="" height="">
						<artwork xml:space="preserve" name="" type="" align="left" alt="" width="" height=""><![CDATA[ 

Name   Description   Reference
------------------------------

Name contains the Feature Capability Indicator Name, provided 
in the registration feature capability indication registration 
template.

Description, provided in the registration feature capability 
indication registration template.

Reference contains the Feature Capability Indicator Specification 
Reference, provided in the registration feature capability 
indication registration template.
					  
						]]></artwork>
					</figure>
				</section>
				<section title="SIP Feature Capability Indicator Registration Tree" anchor="sec.iana.tree.sip" toc="default">
					<t>
						This specification creates a new feature capability indicator tree in the IANA "Proxy-Feature Feature 
						Capability Indicator Trees" registry. The name of the tree is "SIP Feature Capability Indicator Registration Tree", 
						and its leading facet is "sip.". It is used for the registration of feature capability indicators.
					</t>
					<t>
						When a feature capability indicator is registered in the sip tree, it
    						needs to meet the "IETF Consensus" policies defined in RFC 5226. An 
						RFC, which contains the registration of the feature capability indicator, 
						MUST be published. The information required in the registration is defined 
						in Section 5.3 of RFC &rfc.number;.
					</t>
					<t>
						Note that all feature capability indicators registered in the SIP tree will have names
						with a leading facet "sip.".  No leading "+" is used in the
						registrations in any of the feature capability indicator registration trees.
					</t>
					<t>
						The format of the SIP tree is as described below:
					</t>
					<figure anchor="fig.iana.tree.sip" suppress-title="false" align="left" alt="" width="" height="">
						<artwork xml:space="preserve" name="" type="" align="left" alt="" width="" height=""><![CDATA[ 

Name   Description   Reference
------------------------------

Name contains the Feature Capability Indicator Name, provided 
in the registration feature capability indication registration 
template.

Description, provided in the registration feature capability 
indication registration template.

Reference contains the Feature Capability Indicator Specification 
Reference, provided in the registration feature capability 
indication registration template.
					  
						]]></artwork>
					</figure>
				</section>
			</section>
		</section>
		
		<section title="Feature Capability Indicator Registration Template" anchor="sec.temp" toc="default">
			<figure title="Registration Template" anchor="fig.temp" suppress-title="false" align="left" alt="" width="" height="">
					<artwork xml:space="preserve" name="" type="" align="left" alt="" width="" height=""><![CDATA[ 
					
Registration requests for the global tree are submitted 
by e-mail to iana@iana.org.

Registration requests for the sip tree requires submitting 
an Internet-Draft to the IESG.

| Instructions are preceded by '|'.  All fields are mandatory.

Feature capability indicator name:

Description:

| The description should be no longer than 4 lines. More
| detailed information can be provided in the feature
| capability indicator specification.

Feature capability indicator name:

| The referenced specification MUST contain the information
| listed in Section 5.3 of RFC XXXX.

Feature capability indicator specification reference:			

| The referenced specification MUST contain the information 
| listed in Section 5.3 of RFC XXXX.

Contact:

| Name(s) & email address(es) of person(s) to
| contact for further information."

(IANA: Please replace XXXX with the assigned RFC number)


				]]></artwork>
			</figure>
    	</section>

    	<section title="Security Considerations" anchor="sec.seccon" toc="default">
			<t>		
				The security issues for feature capability indicators are similar to
				the ones defined in RFC 3840 for media feature tags. Media
				feature tags can reveal information about end-users and end-user
				equipment, which can be used for industrial espionage. The knowledge
				about end-user equipment capabilities can also be used to influence
				application behavior. As feature capability indicators are not intended
				to convey capability information of end-user devices, such end-user
				security aspects of RFC 3840 do not apply to feature capability indicators.
			</t>
			<t>
				In addition, the RFC 3840 security issue regarding an attacker using the 
				SIP caller preferences extension <xref target="RFC3841" pageno="false" 
				format="default"/> in order to affect routing decisions does not apply, 
				as the mechanism is not defined to be used with feature capability indicators.
			</t>
			<t>
				Feature capability indicators can, however, provide capability and
				characteristics information about the SIP entity, some of which might
				be sensitive. Malicious elements viewing the indicators may be able
				to discern application deployment details or identify elements with 
				exploitable feature implementation weaknesses. The Feature-Caps 
				header field does not convey address information about SIP entities.  
				However, individual feature capability indicators might provide address 
				information as feature capability indicator values. Therefore, mechanisms 
				for guaranteeing confidentiality and authenticity SHOULD be provided.
			</t>
		</section>
		
		<section title="Acknowledgements" anchor="sec.acks" toc="default">
			<t>
				The authors wish to thank everyone in the SIP community that 
				provided input and feedback on the work of this specification.
			</t>
		</section>
		
		<section title="Change Log">
			<t>[RFC EDITOR NOTE: Please remove this Section when publishing]</t>
			<t>
				Changes from draft-holmberg-sipcore-proxy-feature-08
				<list style="symbols">
					<t>
						Comments from Atle Mondrad.
					</t>
				</list>
			</t>	
			<t>
				Changes from draft-holmberg-sipcore-proxy-feature-06
				<list style="symbols">
					<t>
						Editorial changes.
					</t>
				</list>
			</t>	
			<t>
				Changes from draft-holmberg-sipcore-proxy-feature-05
				<list style="symbols">
					<t>
						AD comments from Robert Sparks
					</t>
					<t>
						Additional text added to the Security Considerations section.
					</t>
					<t>
						IANA registration template modified.
					</t>
					<t>
						IANA registration procedures clarified.
					</t>
					<t>
						Feature Capability Indicator specification requirements modified.
					</t>
					<t>
						Note regarding SUBSCRIBE 200 responses added.
					</t>
					<t>
						Editorial modifications.
					</t>
				</list>
			</t>	
			<t>
				Changes from draft-holmberg-sipcore-proxy-feature-04
				<list style="symbols">
					<t>
						WGLC comments from Keith Drage
					</t>
					<t>
						'feature cap' name changed to 'feature capability indicator'.
					</t>
					<t>
						Feature-Caps header field added to IANA Header Field Parameters and Parameter Values registry.
					</t>
					<t>
						Editorial modifications.
					</t>
				</list>
			</t>	
			<t>
				Changes from draft-ietf-sipcore-proxy-feature-03
				<list style="symbols">
					<t>
						Additional Security Considerations text added.
					</t>										
					<t>
						IANA Considerations modified.
					</t>										
					<t>
						Editorial corrections.
					</t>										
				</list>
			</t>
			<t>
				Changes from draft-ietf-sipcore-proxy-feature-02
				<list style="symbols">
					<t>
						Changes based on WGLC comments from Shida Schubert.
					</t>										
					<t>
						- Document title changed
					</t>										
					<t>
						- Terminology alignment
					</t>										
					<t>
						- Note text clarifications
					</t>
					<t>
						Changes based on WGLC comments from Lili Yang.
					</t>								
				</list>
			</t>
			<t>
				Changes from draft-ietf-sipcore-proxy-feature-01
				<list style="symbols">
					<t>
						Changes based on comments from Paul Kyzivat.
					</t>										
					<t>
						IANA Considerations text added.
					</t>										
				</list>
			</t>
			<t>
				Changes from draft-holmberg-sipcore-proxy-feature-04/draft-ietf-sipcore-proxy-feature-00
				<list style="symbols">
					<t>
						Media feature tags replaced with feature caps, based on
						SIPCORE consensus at IETF#83 (Paris).
					</t>										
					<t>
						Editorial corrections and modifications.
					</t>
				</list>
			</t>	
			<t>
				Changes from draft-holmberg-sipcore-proxy-feature-03
				<list style="symbols">
					<t>
						Hadriel Kaplan added as co-author.
					</t>
					<t>
						Terminology change: instead of talking of proxies, talk about
						entities which are not represented by the URI in a Contact header
						field 
						(http://www.ietf.org/mail-archive/web/sipcore/current/msg04449.html).
					</t>
					<t>
						Clarification regarding the usage of the header field in 18x/2xx responses
						(http://www.ietf.org/mail-archive/web/sipcore/current/msg04449.html).
					</t>
					<t>
						Specifying that feature support can also be indicated in target
						refresh requests 
						(http://www.ietf.org/mail-archive/web/sipcore/current/msg04454.html).
					</t>
					<t>
						Feature Cap specification registration information added.
					</t>
				</list>
			</t>	
			<t>
				Changes from draft-holmberg-sipcore-proxy-feature-02
				<list style="symbols">
					<t>
						Definition, and usage of, a new header field, instead of
						Path, Record-Route, Route and Service-Route.
					</t>					
				</list>
			</t>	
			<t>
				Changes from draft-holmberg-sipcore-proxy-feature-01
				<list style="symbols">
					<t>Requirement section added</t>					
					<t>Use-cases and examples updated based on work in 3GPP</t>					
				</list>
			</t>	
			<t>
				Changes from draft-holmberg-sipcore-proxy-feature-00
				<list style="symbols">
					<t>Additional use-cases added</t>
					<t>Direction section added</t>
				</list>
			</t>		
		</section>		
	</middle>
	
	<back>
		<references title="Normative References">
			<?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119"?>			
			<?rfc include="reference.RFC.3261"?>
		</references>
		<references title="Informative References">	  					
			<?rfc include="reference.RFC.2506"?>			
			<?rfc include="reference.RFC.3840"?>			
			<?rfc include="reference.RFC.3841"?>
			<?rfc include="reference.RFC.3968"?>
			<?rfc include="reference.RFC.4485"?>
			<?rfc include="reference.RFC.5226"?>
			<?rfc include="reference.RFC.5626"?>			
			<?rfc include="reference.3GPP.23.237"?>
			<?rfc include="reference.3GPP.24.837"?>
		</references>
	</back>
</rfc>