<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="lib/rfc2629.xslt" ?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
  <!-- Metadata -->
  <!ENTITY title 'The &#x27;file&#x27; URI Scheme'>
  <!ENTITY title-abbrev '&#x27;file&#x27; URI'>
  <!ENTITY rfc 'RFC XXXX'>
  <!ENTITY rfcXXXX '[Note to RFC Editor: please replace XXXX with the number issued to this document.]'>

  <!-- References -->
  <!ENTITY rfc1630 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1630.xml'>
  <!ENTITY rfc1738 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1738.xml'>
  <!ENTITY rfc2119 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml'>
  <!ENTITY rfc3530 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3530.xml'>
  <!ENTITY rfc3629 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3629.xml'>
  <!ENTITY rfc3986 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3986.xml'>
  <!ENTITY rfc4395 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4395.xml'>
  <!ENTITY rfc5234 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5234.xml'>
  <!ENTITY rfc5890 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5890.xml'>
  <!ENTITY rfc5892 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5892.xml'>
  <!ENTITY rfc6874 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6874.xml'>

  <!-- Keywords -->
  <!ENTITY MAY '<bcp14 xmlns="http://purl.org/net/xml2rfc/ext">MAY</bcp14>'>
  <!ENTITY MUST '<bcp14 xmlns="http://purl.org/net/xml2rfc/ext">MUST</bcp14>'>
  <!ENTITY MUST-NOT '<bcp14 xmlns="http://purl.org/net/xml2rfc/ext">MUST NOT</bcp14>'>
  <!ENTITY OPTIONAL '<bcp14 xmlns="http://purl.org/net/xml2rfc/ext">OPTIONAL</bcp14>'>
  <!ENTITY RECOMMENDED '<bcp14 xmlns="http://purl.org/net/xml2rfc/ext">RECOMMENDED</bcp14>'>
  <!ENTITY REQUIRED '<bcp14 xmlns="http://purl.org/net/xml2rfc/ext">REQUIRED</bcp14>'>
  <!ENTITY SHALL '<bcp14 xmlns="http://purl.org/net/xml2rfc/ext">SHALL</bcp14>'>
  <!ENTITY SHALL-NOT '<bcp14 xmlns="http://purl.org/net/xml2rfc/ext">SHALL NOT</bcp14>'>
  <!ENTITY SHOULD '<bcp14 xmlns="http://purl.org/net/xml2rfc/ext">SHOULD</bcp14>'>
  <!ENTITY SHOULD-NOT '<bcp14 xmlns="http://purl.org/net/xml2rfc/ext">SHOULD NOT</bcp14>'>

  <!-- Common entities -->
  <!ENTITY NON-NORMATIVE '<t><spanx>This section is non-normative.</spanx></t>'>

  <!ENTITY file-URI-scheme '&#x27;file&#x27; URI scheme'>
  <!ENTITY file '<spanx>file</spanx>'>
  <!ENTITY ftp '<spanx>ftp</spanx>'>

  <!--ENTITY rfc3986-path '<xref target="RFC3986" x:fmt="of" x:rel="#path"/>'-->
  <!ENTITY rfc3986-path '<eref target="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/html/rfc3986.html#path">Section 3.3</eref> of <xref target="RFC3986"/>'>

  <!--ENTITY rfc3986-reference-resolution '<xref target="RFC3986" x:fmt="of" x:rel="#reference-resolution"/>'-->
  <!ENTITY rfc3986-reference-resolution '<eref target="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/html/rfc3986.html#reference-resolution">Section 5</eref> of <xref target="RFC3986"/>'>

  <!--ENTITY rfc3986-absolutize '<xref target="RFC3986" x:fmt="," x:rel="#absolutize"/>'-->
  <!ENTITY rfc3986-absolutize '<xref target="RFC3986"/>, <eref target="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/html/rfc3986.html#absolutize">Section 5.2</eref>'>
]>
<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc strict="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<?rfc linkmailto="no" ?>
<?rfc editing="no" ?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc rfcedstyle="yes"?>
<?rfc-ext allow-markup-in-artwork="yes" ?>
<?rfc-ext include-index="no" ?>
<rfc ipr="trust200811"
     category="std"
     docName="draft-kerwin-file-scheme-06"
     x:maturity-level="draft"
     xmlns:x="http://purl.org/net/xml2rfc/ext">

  <x:feedback template="https://github.com/phluid61/file-uri-scheme/issues/new?title={docname},%20%22{section}%22&amp;body=&lt;{ref}&gt;:"/>
  <front>
    <title abbrev="&title-abbrev;">&title;</title>
    <author surname="Kerwin" fullname="Matthew Kerwin" initials="M. V.">
      <organization abbrev="QUT">Queensland University of Technology</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Victoria Park Rd</street>
          <city>Kelvin Grove</city>
          <region>QLD</region>
          <code>4059</code>
          <country>Australia</country>
        </postal>
        <email>matthew.kerwin@qut.edu.au</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date month="July" year="2013" />
    <area>Applications</area>
    <keyword>URI</keyword>
    <keyword>scheme</keyword>
    <keyword>file</keyword>
    <abstract>
      <t>This document specifies the file Uniform Resource Identifier (URI) scheme that was originally specified in <xref target="RFC1738"/>.  The purpose of this document is to keep the information about the scheme on standards track, since <xref target="RFC1738"/> has been made obsolete, and to promote interoperability by resolving disagreements between various implementations.</t>
    </abstract>
    <note title="Note to Readers">
      <t>This draft should be discussed on its <xref target="github">github project page</xref>.</t>
    </note>
  </front>
  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction" anchor="intro">
      <t>The &file-URI-scheme; has historically had little or no interoperability between platforms.  Further, implementers on a single platform have often disagreed on the syntax to use for a particular filesystem.  This document attempts to resolve those problems, and define a standard scheme which is interoperable between different extant and future implementations.  Additionally, it aims to ease implementation by conforming to a general syntax that allows existing URI parsing machinery to parse &file; URIs.</t>
      <t>URIs were previously defined in <xref target="RFC1738"/>, which was updated by <xref target="RFC3986"/>.  Those documents also specify how to define schemes for URIs.</t>
      <t>The first definition for many URI schemes appeared in <xref target="RFC1738"/>.  Because that document has been made obsolete, this document copies the &file-URI-scheme; from it to allow that material to remain on standards track.</t>
      <section title="History" anchor="history">
        &NON-NORMATIVE;
        <t>The &file-URI-scheme; was first defined in <xref target="RFC1630"/>, which, being an informational RFC, does not specify an Internet standard.  The definition was standardised in <xref target="RFC1738"/>, and the scheme was registered with the <xref target="IANA-URI-Schemes">Internet Assigned Numbers Authority (IANA)</xref>;  however that definition omitted certain language included by former that clarified aspects such as:
          <list style="symbols">
            <t>the use of slashes to donate boundaries between directory levels of a hierarchical file system; and</t>
            <t>the requirement that client software convert the &file; URI into a file name in the local file name conventions.</t>
          </list>
        </t>
        <t>The Internet draft <xref target="I-D.draft-hoffman-file-uri"/> was written in an effort to keep the &file-URI-scheme; on standards track when <xref target="RFC1738"/> was made obsolete, but that draft expired in 2005.  It enumerated concerns arising from the various, often conflicting implementations of the scheme.  It serves as the basis of this document.</t>
        <t>The &file-URI-scheme; defined in <xref target="RFC1738"/> is referenced three times in the current <xref target="RFC3986">URI Generic Syntax standard</xref>, despite the former's obsoletion:
          <list style="numbers">
            <t><eref target="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/html/rfc3986.html#overview">Section 1.1</eref> uses "file:///etc/hosts" as an example for identifying a resource in relation to the end-user's local context.</t>
            <t><eref target="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/html/rfc3986.html#hierarchical">Section 1.2.3</eref> mentions the "file" scheme regarding relative references.</t>
            <t><eref target="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/html/rfc3986.html#host">Section 3.2.2</eref> says that '...the "file" URI scheme is defined so that no authority, an empty host, and "localhost" all mean the end-user's machine...'.</t>
          </list>
        </t>
        <t>Finally the WHATWG defines a <xref target="WHATWG-URL">living URL standard</xref>, which includes algorithms for interpreting file URIs (as URLs).</t>
      </section>
      <section title="Conventions and Terminology" anchor="conventions">
        <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in <xref target="RFC2119"/>.</t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section title="Scheme Definition" anchor="scheme">
      <t>The &file-URI-scheme; is used to identify and retrieve <spanx>files</spanx> accessible on a particular host computer, where a "file" is a named resource which can be accessed through the computer's filesystem interface.</t>
      <t>The mechanism for retrieving a representation of a dereferenced &file; URI is through the computer's filesystem interface; for example using the POSIX <spanx style="verb">open</spanx>, <spanx style="verb">read</spanx> and <spanx style="verb">close</spanx> functions <xref target="POSIX"/>.</t>
      <t>This scheme, unlike most other URI schemes, does not identify a resource that is universally accessible over the Internet.</t>
      <t>Note well that "file" refers to filesystem names from the perspective of the user of a reference, rather than in relation to a globally-defined naming authority, so care ought to be taken when distributing &file; URIs to ensure that such references are actually intended to be interpreted in relation to the user's filesystem interface.</t>
      <!-- File URLs are rarely used in Web pages on the Internet, since they make the assumption that such a file exists on the client's computer. The host specifier can be used to retrieve a file from an external source, although no specific file-retrieval protocol is specified; and using it ought to result in a message that informs the user that no mechanism to access that machine is available. -->
      <t>Also note that &file; and &ftp; URIs are not the same, even when the target of the &ftp; URI is the local host.</t>
      <section title="Syntax" anchor="syntax">
        <t>The syntax of a &file; URI conforms with the generic syntax presented in <xref target="RFC3986"/>, with the following components:
          <list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="scheme name">The literal value <spanx style="verb">file</spanx></t>
            <t hangText="authority">
              If present, either the fully qualified domain name of the system on which the file is accessible;  or one of the special values <spanx style="verb">localhost</spanx> or the empty string ("").
              <vspace blankLines="1"/>
              If the authority component is omitted, or has either of the special values <spanx style="verb">localhost</spanx> or the empty string (""), it is interpreted as "the machine from which the URI is being interpreted".
              <vspace blankLines="1"/>
              A host name, if supplied, is typically intended to inform a client on a remote machine that it cannot access the file system, or perhaps to use some other mechanism to access the file.  It does not imply that the file ought to be accessible over a network connection.
              <vspace blankLines="1"/>
              No retrieval mechanism for files stored on a remote machine is defined by this specification.
            </t>
            <t hangText="path">
              The hierarchical directory path to the file, using the slash ("/") character to separate directories.  Implementations &SHOULD; translate between the slash-separated URI syntax and the local system's conventions for specifying file paths, where they differ. (See: <xref target="hierarchy"/>)
              <vspace blankLines="1"/>
              Some systems allow &file; URIs to refer to directories.  In this case, the path usually (but not always) includes a terminating slash character, such as in:
              <figure><artwork type="inline">file:///usr/local/bin/</artwork></figure>
              The presence of a terminating slash character always indicates that the &file; URI refers to a directory, but the absence of a slash does not necessarily indicate that it refers to a file.  Implementations ought to use other mechanisms to detect directories, if and when such detection is required.
            </t>
            <t hangText="query">
              The query component contains non-hierarchical data that, along with data in the path component, serves to identify a file.  For example, in a versioning file system, the query component might be used to refer to a specific version of a file.
              <vspace blankLines="1"/>
              Few implementations are known to use or support query components.
            </t>
            <t hangText="fragment">The semantics of a fragment component are undefined by this specification.  A protocol that employs &file; URIs &MAY; define its own semantics for fragment components in the context of that protocol.</t>
          </list>
        </t>
        <t>Systems exhibit different levels of case-sensitivity.  Implementations &SHOULD; maintain the case of file and directory names when translating &file; URIs to and from the local system's representation of file paths, and any systems or devices that transport &file; URIs &SHOULD-NOT; alter the case of &file; URIs they transport.</t>
        <t>See <xref target="iana.syntax"/> for a formal syntax definition.</t>
        <t>Previous definitions of the &file-URI-scheme; required two slashes between the scheme and path, so implementations that wish to remain interoperable with older implementations ought to include an authority component in any &file; URIs they generate.</t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section title="Implementation Notes" anchor="implementation">
      <!-- http://blogs.msdn.com/b/freeassociations/archive/2005/05/19/420059.aspx -->
      <section title="Hierarchical Structure" anchor="hierarchy">
        <t>Most implementations of the &file-URI-scheme; do a reasonable job of mapping the hierarchical part of a directory structure into the slash ("/") delimited hierarchy of the URI syntax, independent of the native platform's delimiter.</t>
        <t>For example, on Microsoft Windows platforms, it is typical that the file system presents backslash ("\") as the file delimeter for file names, yet the URI's forward slash ("/") can be used in &file; URIs interpreted on those platforms.  Similarly, on (some) Macintosh OS versions, at least in some contexts, the colon (":") is used as the delimiter in the native presentation of file path names.  Unix systems natively use the same forward slash ("/") delimiter for hierarchy, so there is a closer mapping between &file; URI paths and native path names.</t>
        <t>In accordance with &rfc3986-path;, the path segments <spanx style="verb">.</spanx> and <spanx style="verb">..</spanx>, also known as dot-segments, are only interpreted within the URI path hierarchy and are removed as part of the resolution process (&rfc3986-absolutize;).  Implementations operating on or interacting with systems that allow dot-segments in their native path representation may be required to escape those segments using some other means when translating to and from &file; URIs.</t>
      </section>
      <section title="Relative file paths" anchor="relative-paths">
        <t>
          As relative references are resolved into their respective (absolute) target URIs according to &rfc3986-reference-resolution;, this document does not describe that resolution.  However, a fully resolved URI may contain a non-absolute path.  For example, using a generic parser, the URI:
          <figure><artwork type="inline">file:a/b/c</artwork></figure>
          would be parsed and interpreted as: file <spanx>c</spanx>, in directory <spanx>b</spanx>, in directory <spanx>a</spanx>, on the machine on which the URI is being interpreted (i.e. localhost); however there is no indication of the location of the directory <spanx>a</spanx> on that machine.  By convention an absolute file path would begin with a slash ("/") character on a Unix-based system, or a drive letter (e.g. "c:\") on a Microsoft Windows system, etc.
        </t>
        <t>Resolution of relative file paths is undefined by this specification.  A protocol that employs &file; URIs &MAY; define its own rules for resolution of relative file paths in the context of that protocol.</t>
      </section>
      <section title="Drives, drive letters, mount points, file system root" anchor="drive-letters">
        <t>Historically there has been considerable difference, in practice, for handling of the syntax for the "top" of the hierarchy.  The &file; URI syntax provides one simple place for designating the root of the file hierachy, and implementations have diverged, even on the same platform, sometimes even within a single application.</t>
        <t>For example, Microsoft DOS- and Windows-based systems support the notion of a "drive letter", a single character which represents a (virtual) drive, mount point, or device.  Native representations of file paths start with the drive letter, a colon, and then the path; e.g., <spanx style="verb">c:\TMP\test.txt</spanx>.</t>
        <t>
          Drive letters are mapped into the top of a &file; URI in various ways.  On systems running some versions of Microsoft Windows, the drive letter may be specified with a colon (":") character, however sometimes the colon is replaced with a pipe ("|") character, and in some implementations the colon is omitted entirely.  The three representations &MAY; be considered equivalent, and any implementation which could interact with a Microsoft Windows environment &SHOULD; interpret a single letter, optionally followed by a colon or pipe character, in the first segment of the path as a drive letter.  For example, the following URIs:
          <figure><artwork type="inline">file:///c:/TMP/test.txt
file:///c|/TMP/test.txt
file:///c/TMP/test.txt</artwork></figure>
          when interpreted on the same machine, would refer to the same file:
          <figure><artwork type="inline">c:\TMP\test.txt</artwork></figure>
        </t>
        <t>Implementations &SHOULD; use a colon (":") character to specify drive letters when generating URIs for Windows- and DOS-based systems.</t>
        <t>Note that some systems running some versions of Microsoft Windows are known to omit the slash before the drive letter, effectively replacing the authority component with the drive specification; for example, <spanx style="verb">file://c:/TMP/test.txt</spanx>.  In line with Postel's robustness principle ("an implementation must be conservative in its sending behavior, and liberal in its receiving behavior" <xref target="RFC791"/>) implementations that are likely to encounter such a URI &MAY; interpret it as a drive letter, but &SHOULD-NOT; generate such URIs.</t>
      </section>
      <section title="UNC File Paths" anchor="unc-file-paths">
        <t>The Microsoft Windows <xref target="MS-DTYP">Universal Naming Convention (UNC)</xref> defines a convention for specifying the location of resources such as shared files or devices, for example Windows shares accessed via the <xref target="MS-SMB2">SMB/CIFS protocol</xref>.  The general structure of a UNC file path, given in <xref target="RFC5234">Augmented Backus-Naur Form (ABNF)</xref>, is:
          <figure><artwork type="inline">
UNC        = "\\" hostname "\" sharename *( "\" objectname )
hostname   = &lt;NetBIOS name, FQDN, or IP address of a server&gt;
sharename  = &lt;name of a share or resource to be accessed&gt;
objectname = &lt;the name of an object&gt;
          </artwork><postamble>Note that this syntax description is non-normative.</postamble></figure>
        </t>
        <t>
          The canonical representation of a UNC file path as a &file; URI copies the UNC <spanx>hostname</spanx> into the URI <spanx>host</spanx> field, and the UNC <spanx>sharename</spanx> and <spanx>objectname</spanx>s, concatenated with forward slash ("/") characters, into the <spanx>path</spanx>.  For example, the following UNC path:
          <figure><artwork type="inline">\\server.example.com\Share\path\to\file.doc</artwork></figure>
          is represented as a &file; URI canonically as:
          <figure><artwork type="inline">
file://server.example.com/Share/path/to/file.doc
       \________________/\_____________________/
            hostname      sharename+objectnames</artwork></figure></t>
      <t>
        Historically some implementations have translated UNC file paths entirely into the <spanx>path</spanx> segment of a &file; URI, including both leading slashes, and the Firefox web browser even prefixes the UNC file path with another slash.  For example, the UNC path given above might be translated as:
        <figure><artwork type="inline">
file:////server.example.com/Share/path/to/file.doc
       \_________________________________________/
                  translated UNC path</artwork></figure>
        or even:
        <figure><artwork type="inline">
file://///server.example.com/Share/path/to/file.doc
        \_________________________________________/
                  translated UNC path</artwork></figure>
        An implementation receiving such a URI &SHOULD; convert it to the canonical representation before processing it.
      </t>
      <t>The &file-URI-scheme; is unusual in that it does not specify an Internet protocol or access method for shared files; as such, its utility in network protocols between hosts is limited.  Examples of file server protocols that do define such access methods include <xref target="MS-SMB2">SMB/CIFS</xref>, <xref target="RFC3530">NFS</xref>, and <xref target="NOVELL">NCP</xref>.</t>
      </section>
      <section title="Namespaces" anchor="namespaces">
        <t>The Microsoft Windows API defines <xref target="Win32-Namespaces">Win32 Namespaces</xref> for interacting with files and devices using Windows API functions.  These namespaced paths are prefixed by <spanx style="verb">\\?\</spanx> for Win32 File Namespaces and <spanx style="verb">\\.\</spanx> for Win32 Device Namespaces.  There is also a special case for UNC file paths <xref target="MS-DTYP"/> in Win32 File Namespaces, referred to as "Long UNC", using the prefix <spanx style="verb">\\?\UNC\</spanx>.</t>
        <t>This specification does not define a mechanism for translating namespaced file paths into &file; URIs.</t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section title="Encoding and Character Set Considerations" anchor="encoding">
      <t>As specified in <xref target="RFC3986"/>, the &file-URI-scheme; allows any character from the <xref target="ISO10646">Universal Character Set (UCS)</xref> encoded as <xref target="RFC3629">UTF-8</xref> and then percent-encoded in valid <xref target="RFC20">ASCII</xref>.</t>
      <t>If the local file system uses a known non-Unicode character encoding, the file path &SHOULD; be converted to a sequence of Unicode characters normalized according to Normalization Form C (NFC, <xref target="UTR15"/>).</t>
      <t>Before applying any percent-encoding, an application MUST ensure the following about the string that is used as input to the URI-construction process:
        <list style="symbols">
          <t>The host, if any, consists only of Unicode code points that conform to the rules specified in <xref target="RFC5892"/>.</t>
          <t>Internationalized domain name (IDN) labels are encoded as A-labels <xref target="RFC5890"/>.</t>
        </list>
      </t>
    </section>
    <section title="Security Considerations" anchor="security">
      <t>There are many security considerations for URI schemes discussed in <xref target="RFC3986"/>.</t>
      <t>File access and the granting of privileges for specific operations are complex topics, and the use of &file; URIs can complicate the security model in effect for file privileges.  Under no circumstance should software using &file; URIs grant greater access than would be available for other file access methods.</t>
    </section>
    <section title="IANA Considerations" anchor="iana-considerations">
      <t>In accordance with the guidelines and registration procedures for new URI schemes <xref target="RFC4395"/>, this section provides the information needed to update the registration of the &file-URI-scheme;.</t>
      <section title="URI Scheme Name" anchor="iana.name">
        <t>file</t>
      </section>
      <section title="Status" anchor="iana.status">
        <t>permanent</t>
      </section>
      <section title="URI Scheme Syntax" anchor="iana.syntax">
        <t>The &file; URI syntax is defined here in <xref target="RFC5234">Augmented Backus-Naur Form (ABNF)</xref>, including the core ABNF syntax rule 'ALPHA' defined by that specifiation, and borrowing the 'host', 'path-absolute' and 'segment' rules from <xref target="RFC3986"/> (updated by <xref target="RFC6874"/>).</t>
        <figure>
          <artwork type="inline"><![CDATA[
fileURI       = "file" ":" ( auth-file / local-file )

auth-file     = "//" ( host-file / no-host-file )
host-file     = hostpart path-absolute
                               ;   file://<host>/<path>
                               ;   file://localhost/<path>

no-host-file  = path-abs       ; begins with "/"
              / path-abs-win   ; begins with drive-letter
                               ;   file:///<path>
                               ;   file:////<bad-UNC-path>
                               ;   file://c:/<path> *

local-file    = path-absolute  ;   file:/<path>
              / path-abs-win   ;   file:c:/<path>

hostpart      = "localhost" / host

path-abs      = 1*( "/" segment )

path-abs-win  = drive-letter path-absolute
drive-letter  = ALPHA [ drive-marker ]
drive-marker  = ":" / "|"
]]></artwork>
          <postamble>* The 'no-host-file' rule allows for dubious URIs that encode a Windows drive letter as the authority component.  See <xref target="drive-letters"/> of &rfc;.  &rfcXXXX;</postamble>
        </figure>
      </section>
      <section title="URI Scheme Semantics" anchor="iana.semantics">
        <t>See <xref target="scheme"/> of &rfc;.  &rfcXXXX;</t>
        <!--t>There is no media type associated with the &file-URI-scheme;.</t-->
      </section>
      <section title="Encoding Considerations" anchor="iana.encoding">
        <t>See <xref target="encoding"/> of &rfc;.  &rfcXXXX;</t>
      </section>
      <section title="Applications/Protocols That Use This URI Scheme Name" anchor="iana.implementations">
        <t>Web browsers:
          <list style="symbols">
            <t>Firefox
              <list style="empty">
                <t>Note: Firefox has a unique interpretation of RFC 1738 (See: <eref target="https://bugzilla.mozilla.org/show_bug.cgi?id=107540">Bugzilla#107540</eref>), which affects UNC paths.</t>
                <!--t><eref target="https://hg.mozilla.org/mozilla-central/file/5976b9c673f8/netwerk/protocol/file">source code repository</eref></t-->
              </list>
            </t>
            <t>Chromium
              <!--list style="empty">
                <t><eref target="http://src.chromium.org/viewvc/chrome/trunk/src/url/url_file.h">source code repository</eref></t>
              </list-->
            </t>
            <t>Internet Explorer <!-- since 4 --></t>
            <t>Opera</t>
          </list>
        </t>
        <t>Other applications/protocols:
          <list style="symbols">
            <t>Windows API
              <list style="empty">
                <t><eref target="http://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/windows/desktop/bb773581(v=vs.85).aspx">PathCreateFromUrl function</eref>, MSDN</t>
                <t><eref target="http://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/windows/desktop/bb773773(v=vs.85).aspx">UrlCreateFromPath function</eref>, MSDN</t>
              </list>
            </t>
            <t>Perl LWP
              <!--list style="empty">
                <t><eref target="http://cpansearch.perl.org/src/GAAS/libwww-perl-6.05/lib/LWP/Protocol/file.pm">source code repository</eref></t>
              </list-->
            </t>
          </list>
        </t>
      </section>
      <section title="Interoperability Considerations" anchor="iana.interop">
        <t>Due to the convoluted history of the &file-URI-scheme; there a many, varied implementations in existence.  Many have converged over time, forming a few kernels of closely-related functionality, and &rfc; attempts to accommodate such common functionality.  &rfcXXXX;  However there will always be exceptions, and this fact is recognised.</t>
        <!--t><eref target="http://blogs.msdn.com/b/ie/archive/2006/12/06/file-uris-in-windows.aspx">IE Blog</eref></t-->
      </section>
      <section title="Security Considerations" anchor="iana.security">
        <t>See Section 4 of &rfc;  &rfcXXXX;</t>
      </section>
      <section title="Contact" anchor="iana.contact">
        <t>Matthew Kerwin, matthew@kerwin.net.au</t>
      </section>
      <section title="Author/Change Controller" anchor="iana.author">
        <t>This scheme is registered under the IETF tree.  As such, the IETF maintains change control.</t>
      </section>
      <section title="References" anchor="iana.references">
        <t>None.</t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>This specification is derived from <xref target="RFC1738">RFC 1738</xref>, <xref target="RFC3986">RFC 3986</xref>, and <xref target="I-D.draft-hoffman-file-uri">I-D draft-hoffman-file-uri (expired)</xref>; the acknowledgements in those documents still apply.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>
  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <reference anchor="RFC20">
        <front>
          <title abbrev="ASCII">ASCII format for Network Interchange</title>
          <author initials="V." surname="Cerf" fullname="Vint Cerf">
            <organization>UCLA</organization>
          </author>
          <date year="1969" month="October"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="20"/>
        <format type="TXT" target="http://tools.ietf.org/rfc/rfc20.txt"/>
      </reference>
      &rfc3629;
      &rfc2119;
      &rfc3986;
      &rfc5890;
      &rfc5892;
      &rfc6874;
      <reference anchor="ISO10646">
        <front>
          <title abbrev="UCS">Information Technology - Universal Multiple-Octet Coded Character Set (UCS)</title>
          <author>
            <organization>International Organization for Standardization</organization>
          </author>
          <date year="2003" month="December"/>
          <seriesInfo name="ISO/IEC" value="10646:2003"/>
        </front>
      </reference>
      <!--reference anchor="UNICODE" target="http://www.unicode.org/versions/Unicode6.2.0/">
        <front>
          <title>The Unicode Standard, Version 6.2</title>
          <author>
            <organization>The Unicode Consortium</organization>
          </author>
          <date year="2012"/>
        </front>
      </reference-->
      <reference anchor="UTR15" target="http://www.unicode.org/reports/tr15/tr15-37.html">
        <front>
          <title>Unicode Normalization Forms</title>
          <author initials='M.' surname='Davis' fullname='Mark Davis'>
            <address>
              <email>mailto:markdavis@google.com</email>
            </address>
          </author>
          <author initials='K.' surname='Whistler' fullname='Ken Whistler'>
            <address>
              <email>ken@unicode.org</email>
            </address>
          </author>
          <date year='2012' month='August' day='31'/>
        </front>
      </reference>
    </references>
    <references title="Informative References">
      <reference anchor='I-D.draft-hoffman-file-uri'>
        <front>
          <title>The file URI Scheme</title>
          <author initials='P.' surname='Hoffman' fullname='Paul Hoffman'>
            <organization>VPN Consortium</organization>
            <address>
              <postal>
                <street>127 Segre Place</street>
                <city>Santa Cruz</city>
                <region>CA</region>
                <code>95060</code>
              </postal>
            </address>
          </author>
          <date month='January' year='2005' />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name='Internet-Draft' value='draft-hoffman-file-uri-03' />
        <format type='TXT' target='http://www.ietf.org/internet-drafts/draft-hoffman-file-uri-03.txt' />
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="RFC791">
        <front>
          <title abbrev="Internet Protocol (IP)">Internet Protocol - DARPA Internet Program, Protocol Specification</title>
          <author initials="J." surname="Postel" fullname="Jon Postel">
            <organization>University of Southern California</organization>
            <address>
              <postal>
                <street>4676 Admiralty Way</street>
                <city>Marina del Rey</city>
                <region>CA</region>
                <code>90291</code>
              </postal>
            </address>
          </author>
          <date month="September" year="1981"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="791"/>
        <format type="TXT" target="http://tools.ietf.org/rfc/rfc791.txt"/>
      </reference>
      &rfc1630;
      &rfc1738;
      &rfc3530;
      &rfc4395;
      &rfc5234;
      <reference anchor="WHATWG-URL" target="http://url.spec.whatwg.org/">
        <front>
          <title>URL Living Standard</title>
          <author>
            <organization>WHATWG</organization>
            <address>
              <uri>http://www.whatwg.org/</uri>
            </address>
          </author>
          <date year='2013' month='May' />
        </front>
        <format type='HTML' target='http://url.spec.whatwg.org/' />
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="MS-DTYP" target="http://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/gg465305.aspx">
        <front>
          <title>Windows Data Types, 2.2.56 UNC</title>
          <author>
            <organization>Microsoft Open Specifications</organization>
            <address>
              <uri>http://www.microsoft.com/openspecifications/en/us/default.aspx</uri>
            </address>
          </author>
          <date year="2013" month="January"/>
        </front>
      </reference>
      <!--reference anchor="MS-SMB" target="http://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/cc246231.aspx">
        <front>
          <title>Server Message Block (SMB) Protocol</title>
          <author>
            <organization>Microsoft Open Specifications</organization>
            <address>
              <uri>http://www.microsoft.com/openspecifications/en/us/default.aspx</uri>
            </address>
          </author>
          <date year="2013" month="January"/>
        </front>
      </reference-->
      <reference anchor="MS-SMB2" target="http://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/cc246482.aspx">
        <front>
          <title>Server Message Block (SMB) Protocol Versions 2 and 3</title>
          <author>
            <organization>Microsoft Open Specifications</organization>
            <address>
              <uri>http://www.microsoft.com/openspecifications/en/us/default.aspx</uri>
            </address>
          </author>
          <date year="2013" month="January"/>
        </front>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="NOVELL" target="http://www.novell.com/developer/ndk/netware_core_protocols.html">
        <front>
          <title>NetWare Core Protocols</title>
          <author>
            <organization>Novell</organization>
            <address>
              <uri>http://www.novell.com/</uri>
            </address>
          </author>
          <date year="2013"/>
        </front>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="IANA-URI-Schemes" target="http://www.iana.org/assignments/uri-schemes/uri-schemes.xml">
        <front>
          <title abbrev='URI Schemes registry'>Uniform Resource Identifier (URI) Schemes registry</title>
          <author>
            <organization abbrev="IANA">Internet Assigned Numbers Authority</organization>
          </author>
          <date year='2013' month='June' />
        </front>
        <format type='TXT' octets='20046' target='http://www.iana.org/assignments/uri-schemes/uri-schemes.txt' />
        <format type='XML' octets='32231' target='http://www.iana.org/assignments/uri-schemes/uri-schemes.xml' />
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="POSIX" target="http://www.unix.org/version4/">
        <front>
          <title abbrev='POSIX.1-2008'>IEEE Std 1003.1, 2013 Edition</title>
          <author>
            <organization>IEEE</organization>
          </author>
          <date year="2013"/>
        </front>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="Win32-Namespaces" target="http://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/windows/desktop/aa365247(v=vs.85).aspx#namespaces">
        <front>
          <title>Naming Files, Paths, and Namespaces</title>
          <author>
            <organization abbrev="MSDN">Microsoft Developer Network</organization>
          </author>
          <date year="2013" month="June"/>
        </front>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="github" target="https://github.com/phluid61/file-uri-scheme">
        <front>
          <title>file-uri-scheme GitHub repository</title>
          <author surname="Kerwin" fullname="Matthew Kerwin" initials="M. V.">
            <address>
              <email>matthew@kerwin.net.au</email>
            </address>
          </author>
          <date year="n.d."/>
        </front>
      </reference>
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
