<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="lib/rfc2629.xslt" ?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY rfc1630 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1630.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc1738 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1738.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc2119 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc3986 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3986.xml">
]>
<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc strict="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<?rfc linkmailto="no" ?>
<?rfc editing="no" ?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc rfcedstyle="yes"?>
<?rfc-ext allow-markup-in-artwork="yes" ?>
<?rfc-ext include-index="no" ?>
<rfc ipr="trust200811" category="std" docName="draft-kerwin-file-scheme-02">

  
  <front>
    <title abbrev="File Scheme">
      The file URI Scheme
    </title>
    <author surname="Kerwin" fullname="Matthew Kerwin" initials="M. V.">
      <address>
        <email>matthew@kerwin.net.au</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date month="June" year="2013"/>
    <area>Applications</area>
    <keyword>URI</keyword>
    <keyword>scheme</keyword>
    <keyword>file</keyword>
    <abstract>
      <t>This document specifies the file Uniform Resource Identifier (URI) scheme that was originally specified in <xref target="RFC1738"/>.  The purpose of this document is to keep the information about the scheme on standards track, since <xref target="RFC1738"/> has been made obsolete.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>
  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction" anchor="intro">
      <t>URIs were previously defined in <xref target="RFC1738"/>, which was updated by <xref target="RFC3986"/>.  Those documents also specify how to define schemes for URIs.</t>
      <t>The first definition for many URI schemes appeared in <xref target="RFC1738"/>.  Because that document has been made obsolete, this document copies the file URI scheme from it to allow that material to remain on standards track.</t>
      <section title="Conventions and Terminology">
        <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in <xref target="RFC2119"/>.</t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section title="History" anchor="history">
      <t>The file URI scheme was first defined in <xref target="RFC1630"/>, and informational RFC which does not specify an Internet standard of any kind.  The definition was standardised in <xref target="RFC1738"/>, and the scheme was registered with IANA, however the latter definition omitted certain language from former that clarified aspects such as:
        <list style="symbols">
          <t>the use of slashes to donate boundaries between directory levels of a hierarchical file system</t>
          <t>the requirement that client software convert the file URL into a file name in the local file name conventions</t>
          <t>a justification for defining the scheme.</t>
        </list>
      </t>
      <t>The Internet draft <xref target="I-D.draft-hoffman-file-uri"/> was written in an effort to keep the file URI scheme on standards track, but it expired in 2005.  That draft enumerated concerns arising from the various, often conflicting implementations.</t>
      <t>Despite lacking a living standard, the file URI scheme is used by way of example in <xref target="RFC3986"/> three times:
        <list style="numbers">
          <t>section 1.1 [p6] uses "file:///etc/hosts" as an example</t>
          <t>section 1.2.3 [p10] mentions the "file" scheme regarding relative references</t>
          <t>section 3.2.2 [p21] says that '...the "file" URI scheme is defined so that no authority, an empty host, and "localhost" all mean the end-user's machine...'.</t>
        </list>
      </t>
      <t>Finally the WHATWG defines a <xref target="WHATWG">living URL standard</xref>, which includes algorithms for interpreting file URIs.</t>
    </section>
    <section title="Scheme Definition" anchor="scheme">
      <t>The file URI scheme is used to designate files accessible on a particular host computer.  This scheme, unlike most other URI schemes, does not designate a resource that is universally accessible over the Internet.</t>
      <t>The file URI scheme has historically had little or no interoperability between platforms.  Further, implementers on a single platform have often disagreed on the syntax to use for a particular filesystem.  This document does not try to resolve those problems, only to show what has been commonly seen in use on the Internet.</t>
      <t>Note that file: and ftp: URIs are not the same, even when the target of the ftp: URI is the local host.</t>
      <t>A file URI conforms with the generic syntax presented in <xref target="RFC3986"/>, with the following components:
        <list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="scheme name">The literal value <spanx style="verb">file</spanx></t>
          <t hangText="authority">If present, either the fully qualified domain name of the system on which the file is accessible;  or one of the special values <spanx style="verb">localhost</spanx> or the empty string, in which case it is interpreted as "the machine from which the URI is being interpreted".  An absent authority component SHOULD be interpreted as if it were present and had the value <spanx style="verb">localhost</spanx>.</t>
          <t hangText="path">The hierarchical directory path to the file, using the slash character ("/") to separate directories.</t>
        </list>
      </t>
      <t>Some systems allow URIs to point to directories.  In this case, there is usually (but not always) a terminating slash character, such as in:
        <figure><artwork type="inline">file:///usr/local/bin/</artwork></figure>
      </t>
      <t>
        On systems running some versions of Microsoft Windows, the local drive specification is sometimes specified with a colon character (":") and sometimes with a pipe ("|").  The two SHOULD be considered equivalent.  For example:
        <figure><artwork type="inline">file:///c:/windows/example.ini
file:///c|/windows/example.ini</artwork></figure>
      </t>
      <t>Note that some systems running some versions of Microsoft Windows are known to omit the slash before the drive letter.</t>
      <t>For Windows shares, there is an additional slash prepeded to the path.  Thus, the file "example.doc" on the shared directory "departments" would have the URI
        <figure><artwork type="inline">file:////department/example.doc</artwork></figure>
      </t>
      <t>The file URL scheme is unusual in that it does not specify an Internet protocol or access method for such files; as such, its utility in network protocols between hosts is limited.</t>
      <section title="Examples" anchor="examples">
        <t>For example, a VMS file
          <figure><artwork type="inline">DISK$USER:[MY.NOTES]NOTE123456.TXT</artwork></figure>
          might become
          <figure><artwork type="inline">file://vms.host.edu/disk$user/my/notes/note12345.txt</artwork></figure>
        </t>
        <t>On a Windows system, the file
          <figure><artwork type="inline">C:\Users\kerwin\Documents\temp.txt</artwork></figure>
          might become
          <figure><artwork type="inline">file:///C:/Users/kerwin/Documents/temp.txt</artwork></figure>
        </t>
        <t>On a Linux system, the file
          <figure><artwork type="inline">/usr/local/lib/ruby/2.0.0/uri.rb</artwork></figure>
          could be referred to by any of the following equivalent URIs:
          <figure><artwork type="inline">file://localhost/usr/local/lib/ruby/2.0.0/uri.rb
file:///usr/local/lib/ruby/2.0.0/uri.rb
file:/usr/local/lib/ruby/2.0.0/uri.rb</artwork></figure>
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section title="Implementation Notes" anchor="implementation">
      <section title="Hierarchical Structure">
        <t>Most implementations of the file URI scheme do a reasonable job of mapping the hierarchical part of a directory structure into the "/" delimited hierarchy of the URI syntax, independent of what the native platform delimiter is.</t>
        <t>For example, on Windows platforms, it is typical that the file system presents backslash "\" as the file delimeter for file names, yet the URI's forward slash "/" can be used in file: URIs.  Similarly, on (some) Macintosh OS versions, at least in some contexts, the colon (":") is used as the delimiter in the native presentation of file path names.  Unix systems natively use the same forward slash "/" delimiter for hierarchy, so there is a closer mapping between file paths and native path names.</t>
      </section>
      <section title="Drives, drive letters, mount points, file system root">
        <t>Historically there has been considerable difference, in practice, for handling of the syntax for the "top" of the hierarchy.  The file URI syntax provides one simple place for designating the root of the file hierachy, and implementations have diverged, even on the same platform, sometimes even within a single application.</t>
        <t>For example, DOS- and Windows-based systems support the notion of a "drive letter", a single character which represents a (virtual) drive, mount point, or device.  Native representations of file paths start with the drive letter, a colon, and then the path; e.g., "c:\tmp\test.txt".</t>
        <t>Drive letters are mapped into the top of a file URI in various ways, depending on the implementation; some applications substitute vertical bar ("|") for the colon after the drive letter, yielding "file:///c|/tmp/test.txt".  In some cases, the colon is left unchanged, as in "file:///c:/tmp/test.txt".  In other cases, the colon is simply omitted, as in "file:///c/tmp/test.txt".</t>
      </section>
      <section title="Character sets and encodings">
        <t>Local file systems sometimes use many different encodings for representing file names.  The URI syntax defined in <xref target="RFC3986"/> provides a method of encoding data, presumably for the sake of identifying a resource, as a sequence of characters.  The URI characters are, in turn, frequently encoded as octets for transport or presentation.  This specification does not mandate any particular character encoding for mapping between URI characters and the octets used to store or transmit those characters, however for interoperability sake, it would be preferable for file: URI libraries to translate the native character encoding for file names to and from Unicode.</t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section title="Security Considerations" anchor="security">
      <t>There are many security considerations for URI schemes discussed in <xref target="RFC3986"/>.</t>
      <t>File access and the granting of privileges for specific operations are complex topics, and the use of file: URIs can complicate the security model in effect for file privileges.  Under no circumstance should software using file: URIs grant greater access than would be available for other file access methods.</t>
    </section>
    <section title="IANA Considerations" anchor="iana">
      <t>This document does not modify the existing entry in the <xref target="IANA">URI Schemes registry</xref>, except by updating its reference RFC.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>
  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      

<reference anchor="RFC2119">

<front>
<title abbrev="RFC Key Words">Key words for use in RFCs to Indicate Requirement Levels</title>
<author initials="S." surname="Bradner" fullname="Scott Bradner">
<organization>Harvard University</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street>1350 Mass. Ave.</street>
<street>Cambridge</street>
<street>MA 02138</street></postal>
<phone>- +1 617 495 3864</phone>
<email>sob@harvard.edu</email></address></author>
<date year="1997" month="March"/>
<area>General</area>
<keyword>keyword</keyword>
<abstract>
<t>
   In many standards track documents several words are used to signify
   the requirements in the specification.  These words are often
   capitalized.  This document defines these words as they should be
   interpreted in IETF documents.  Authors who follow these guidelines
   should incorporate this phrase near the beginning of their document:

<list>
<t>
      The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL
      NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED",  "MAY", and
      "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in
      RFC 2119.
</t></list></t>
<t>
   Note that the force of these words is modified by the requirement
   level of the document in which they are used.
</t></abstract></front>

<seriesInfo name="BCP" value="14"/>
<seriesInfo name="RFC" value="2119"/>
<format type="TXT" octets="4723" target="http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc2119.txt"/>
<format type="HTML" octets="17970" target="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/html/rfc2119.html"/>
<format type="XML" octets="5777" target="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/xml/rfc2119.xml"/>
</reference>

      

<reference anchor="RFC3986">

<front>
<title abbrev="URI Generic Syntax">Uniform Resource Identifier (URI): Generic Syntax</title>
<author initials="T." surname="Berners-Lee" fullname="Tim Berners-Lee">
<organization abbrev="W3C/MIT">World Wide Web Consortium</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street>Massachusetts Institute of Technology</street>
<street>77 Massachusetts Avenue</street>
<city>Cambridge</city>
<region>MA</region>
<code>02139</code>
<country>USA</country></postal>
<phone>+1-617-253-5702</phone>
<facsimile>+1-617-258-5999</facsimile>
<email>timbl@w3.org</email>
<uri>http://www.w3.org/People/Berners-Lee/</uri></address></author>
<author initials="R." surname="Fielding" fullname="Roy T. Fielding">
<organization abbrev="Day Software">Day Software</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street>5251 California Ave., Suite 110</street>
<city>Irvine</city>
<region>CA</region>
<code>92617</code>
<country>USA</country></postal>
<phone>+1-949-679-2960</phone>
<facsimile>+1-949-679-2972</facsimile>
<email>fielding@gbiv.com</email>
<uri>http://roy.gbiv.com/</uri></address></author>
<author initials="L." surname="Masinter" fullname="Larry Masinter">
<organization abbrev="Adobe Systems">Adobe Systems Incorporated</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street>345 Park Ave</street>
<city>San Jose</city>
<region>CA</region>
<code>95110</code>
<country>USA</country></postal>
<phone>+1-408-536-3024</phone>
<email>LMM@acm.org</email>
<uri>http://larry.masinter.net/</uri></address></author>
<date year="2005" month="January"/>
<area>Applications</area>
<keyword>uniform resource identifier</keyword>
<keyword>URI</keyword>
<keyword>URL</keyword>
<keyword>URN</keyword>
<keyword>WWW</keyword>
<keyword>resource</keyword>
<abstract>
<t>
A Uniform Resource Identifier (URI) is a compact sequence of characters
that identifies an abstract or physical resource.  This specification
defines the generic URI syntax and a process for resolving URI references
that might be in relative form, along with guidelines and security
considerations for the use of URIs on the Internet.
The URI syntax defines a grammar that is a superset of all valid URIs,
allowing an implementation to parse the common components of a URI
reference without knowing the scheme-specific requirements of every
possible identifier.  This specification does not define a generative
grammar for URIs; that task is performed by the individual
specifications of each URI scheme.
</t></abstract></front>

<seriesInfo name="STD" value="66"/>
<seriesInfo name="RFC" value="3986"/>
<format type="TXT" octets="141811" target="http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc3986.txt"/>
<format type="HTML" octets="214067" target="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/html/rfc3986.html"/>
<format type="XML" octets="163534" target="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/xml/rfc3986.xml"/>
</reference>

    </references>
    <references title="Informative References">
      

<reference anchor="RFC1630">

<front>
<title abbrev="URIs in WWW">Universal Resource Identifiers in WWW: A Unifying Syntax for the Expression of Names and Addresses of Objects on the Network as used in the World-Wide Web</title>
<author initials="T." surname="Berners-Lee" fullname="Tim Berners-Lee">
<organization>CERN, World-Wide Web project</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street>1211 Geneva 23</street>
<city/>
<region/>
<code/>
<country>CH</country></postal>
<phone>+41 22 7673755</phone>
<facsimile>+41 22 7677155</facsimile>
<email>timbl@info.cern.ch</email></address></author>
<date year="1994" month="June"/></front>

<seriesInfo name="RFC" value="1630"/>
<format type="TXT" octets="57601" target="http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc1630.txt"/>
</reference>

      

<reference anchor="RFC1738">

<front>
<title>Uniform Resource Locators (URL)</title>
<author initials="T." surname="Berners-Lee" fullname="Tim Berners-Lee">
<organization>CERN, World-Wide Web project</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street>1211 Geneva 23</street>
<city/>
<region/>
<code/>
<country>CH</country></postal>
<phone>+41 22 7673755</phone>
<facsimile>+41 22 7677155</facsimile>
<email>timbl@info.cern.ch</email></address></author>
<author initials="L." surname="Masinter" fullname="Larry Masinter">
<organization>Xerox PARC</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street>3333 Coyote Hill Road</street>
<city>Palo Alto</city>
<region>CA</region>
<code>94034</code>
<country>US</country></postal>
<phone>+1 415 812 4365</phone>
<facsimile>+1 415 812 4333</facsimile>
<email>masinter@parc.xerox.com</email></address></author>
<author initials="M." surname="McCahill" fullname="Mark McCahill">
<organization>University of Minnesota, Computer and Information Services</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street>100 Union Street SE, Shepherd Labs</street>
<street>Room 152</street>
<city>Minneapolis</city>
<region>MN</region>
<code>55455</code>
<country>US</country></postal>
<phone>+1 612 625 1300</phone>
<email>mpm@boombox.micro.umn.edu</email></address></author>
<date year="1994" month="December"/>
<abstract>
<t>This document specifies a Uniform Resource Locator (URL), the syntax and semantics of formalized information for location and access of resources via the Internet.</t></abstract></front>

<seriesInfo name="RFC" value="1738"/>
<format type="TXT" octets="51348" target="http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc1738.txt"/>
</reference>

      <reference anchor="I-D.draft-hoffman-file-uri">
        <front>
          <title>The file URI Scheme</title>
          <author initials="P" surname="Hoffman" fullname="Paul Hoffman">
            <organization>VPN Consortium</organization>
            <address>
              <postal>
                <street>127 Segre Place</street>
                <street>Santa Cruz</street>
                <street>CA 95060</street>
              </postal>
            </address>
          </author>
          <date month="January" year="2005"/>
          <abstract>
            <t>
              This document specifies the file Uniform Resource Identifier (URI)
              scheme that was originally specified in RFC 1738.  The purpose of
              this document is to allow RFC 1738 to be made obsolete while keeping
              the information about the scheme on standards track.
            </t>
          </abstract>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-hoffman-file-uri-03"/>
        <format type="TXT" target="http://www.ietf.org/internet-drafts/draft-hoffman-file-uri-03.txt"/>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="IANA" target="http://www.iana.org/assignments/uri-schemes/uri-schemes.xml">
        <front>
          <title abbrev="URI Schemes registry">Uniform Resource Identifier (URI) Schemes registry</title>
          <author>
            <organization>IANA</organization>
          </author>
          <date year="2013" month="June"/>
        </front>
        <format type="TXT" octets="20046" target="http://www.iana.org/assignments/uri-schemes/uri-schemes.txt"/>
        <format type="XML" octets="32231" target="http://www.iana.org/assignments/uri-schemes/uri-schemes.xml"/>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="WHATWG" target="http://url.spec.whatwg.org/">
        <front>
          <title>URL Living Standard</title>
          <author>
            <organization>WHATWG</organization>
            <address>
              <uri>http://www.whatwg.org/</uri>
            </address>
          </author>
          <date year="2013" month="May"/>
        </front>
        <format type="HTML" target="http://url.spec.whatwg.org/"/>
      </reference>
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
