<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY rfc2119 PUBLIC '' 
  'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml'>
]>

<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>

<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc iprnotified="no"?>
<?rfc strict="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?> 
<?rfc subcompact="yes" ?>

<rfc category="info" ipr="trust200902" 
docName="draft-chan-distributed-mobility-ps-03">

<front>
<title abbrev="DMM-PS">
Problem statement for distributed and dynamic mobility management
</title>

<author initials="H" surname="Chan (Ed.)" fullname="H Anthony Chan (editor)">
<organization>Huawei Technologies</organization>
<address>
<postal>

<street>5340 Legacy Dr Building 3, Plano, TX 75024, USA</street>
<street>Email: h.a.chan@ieee.org</street>
<street>-</street>
<street>Dapeng Liu</street>
<street>China Mobile</street>
<street>Unit2, 28 Xuanwumenxi Ave, Xuanwu District, Beijing 100053, China</street>
<street>Email: liudapeng@chinamobile.com</street>
<street>-</street>
<street>Pierrick Seite</street>
<street>France Telecom - Orange</street>
<street>4, rue du Clos Courtel, BP 91226, Cesson-Sevigne 35512, France</street>
<street>Email: pierrick.seite@orange-ftgroup.com</street>
<street>-</street>
<street>Hidetoshi Yokota</street>
<street>KDDI Lab</street>
<street>2-1-15 Ohara, Fujimino, Saitama, 356-8502 Japan</street>
<street>Email: yokota@kddilabs.jp</street>
<street>-</street>
<street>Charles E. Perkins</street>
<street>Tellabs Inc.</street>
<street>4555 Great America Parkway, #S5-130</street>
<street>Email: charliep@computer.org</street>
<street>-</street>
<street>Melia Telemaco</street>
<street>Alcatel-Lucent Bell Labs</street>
<street>Email: telemaco.melia@alcatel-lucent.com</street>
<street>-</street>
<street>Wassim Michel Haddad</street>
<street>Ericsson</street>
<street>300 Holger Dr, San Jose, CA 95134, USA</street>
<street>Email: Wassam.Haddad@ericsson.com</street>
<street>-</street>
<street>Elena Demaria</street>
<street>Telecom Italia</street>
<street>via G. Reiss Romoli, 274, TORINO, 10148, Italy</street>
<street>Email: elena.demaria@telecomitalia.it</street>
<street>-</street>
<street>Seok Joo Koh</street>
<street>Kyungpook National University, Korea</street>
<street>Email: sjkoh@knu.ac.kr</street>
<street>-</street>

</postal>
</address>
</author>

<date month="July" year="2011"></date>
<area></area>
<workgroup></workgroup>
<abstract>
<t>

   The traditional hierarchical structure of cellular networks has led
   to deployment models which are heavily centralized.  Mobility
   management with centralized mobility anchoring in existing
   hierarchical mobile networks is quite prone to suboptimal routing
   and issues related to scalability.  Centralized functions present a
   single point of failure, and inevitably introduce longer delays and
   higher signaling loads for network operations related to mobility
   management.  To make matters worse, there are numerous variants of
   Mobile IP in addition to other protocols standardized outside the
   IETF, making it much more difficult to create economical and
   interoperable solutions.  In this document we examine the problems
   of centralized mobility management and identify requirements for
   distributed and dynamic mobility management.

</t>
</abstract>
</front>


<middle>


<section anchor="intro" title="Introduction">

<t>
Traditional cellular networks have been hierarchical,
so that mobility management has primarily been deployed
according to a centralized architecture.
Mobility solutions deployed with centralized mobility anchoring
in existing hierarchical mobile networks
are more prone to the following problems or limitations
compared with distributed and dynamic mobility management:
<list style="numbers">
<t>
Routing via a centralized anchor is often longer,
so that those mobility protocol deployments
that lack optimization extensions
results in non-optimal routes,
affecting performance;
whereas routing optimization may be an integral part 
of a distributed design.
</t>

<t>
As a mobile network becomes less hierarchical, 
centralized mobility management can become more non-optimal,
especially as the content servers in a content delivery network (CDN)
are moving closer to the access network.
In contrast, distributed mobility management 
can support both hierarchical networks and flat networks
as may be needed to support CDNs.
</t>

<t>
Centralized route maintenance and context maintenance
for a large number of mobile hosts is more difficult to scale.
</t>

<t>
Scalability may worsen if there is no mechanism 
to determine whether mobility support is needed;
dynamic mobility management (i.e., selectively providing mobility support)
may be better implemented with distributed mobility management.
</t>

<t>
Deployment is complicated 
with numerous variants and extensions of mobile IP;
these variants and extensions may be better integrated
in a distributed and dynamic design
which can selectively adapt to the needs. 
</t>

<t>
Excessive signaling overhead should be avoided
when end nodes are able to communicate end-to-end;
capability to selectively turn off signaling not
needed by the end hosts
will reduce the handover delay. 
</t>

<t>
Centralized approaches are generally 
more vulnerable to a single point of failure and attack,
often requiring duplication and backups.
A distributed approach
typically isolates the problem in a single local network
so that the needed protection can be simpler.
</t>

</list>

</t>

<t>
In the past decade a fair number of mobility protocols 
have been standardized. 
Although the protocols differ 
in terms of functions and associated message format, 
we can identify a few key common features:
<list>
<t>
presence of a centralized mobility anchor 
providing global reachability and an always-on experience;
</t>
<t>
extensions to optimize handover performance 
while users roam across wireless cells;
</t>
<t>
extensions to enable the use of heterogeneous wireless interfaces 
for multi-mode terminals (e.g. cellular phones).
</t>
</list>
The presence of the centralized mobility anchor 
allows a mobile device to be reachable 
when it is not connected to its home domain. 
The anchor, among other tasks, 
ensures forwarding of packets destined to or sent from the mobile device. 
Most of the deployed architectures today 
have a small number of centralized anchors 
managing the traffic of millions of mobile subscribers.
Compared with a distributed approach,
a centralized approach is likely to have several issues or limitations 
affecting performance and scalability,
which require costly network dimensioning 
and engineering to resolve.
</t>

<t>
To optimize handovers for mobile users, 
the base protocols have been extended 
to efficiently handle packet forwarding 
between the previous and new points of attachment. 
These extensions are necessary 
when applications impose stringent requirements in terms of delay. 
Notions of localization and distribution of local agents 
have been introduced to reduce signaling overhead. 
Unfortunately today we witness difficulties 
in getting such protocols deployed,
often leading to sub-optimal choices. 
</t>

<t>
Moreover, the availability of multi-mode devices 
and the possibility of using several network interfaces simultaneously 
have motivated the development of more new protocol extensions.
Deployment is further complicated with so many extensions. 
</t>

<t>
Mobile users are, more than ever, consuming Internet content; 
such traffic imposes new requirements 
on mobile core networks for data traffic delivery. 
When the traffic demand exceeds available capacity, 
service providers need to implement new strategies 
such as selective traffic offload (e.g. 3GPP work items LIPA/SIPTO) 
through alternative access networks (e.g. WLAN). 
Moreover, the localization of content providers 
closer to the Mobile/Fixed Internet Service Providers network 
requires taking into account local Content Delivery Networks (CDNs) 
while providing mobility services.  
</t>

<t>
When demand exceeds capacity, 
both offloading and CDN techniques 
could benefit from the development of mobile architectures 
with fewer levels of routing hierarchy 
introduced into the data path by the mobility management system. 
This trend in network flattening is reinforced 
by a shift in users traffic behavior,
aimed at increasing direct communications among peers 
in the same geographical area. 
Distributed mobility management in a truly flat mobile architecture
would anchor the traffic closer to the point of attachment of the user 
and overcome the suboptimal routing issues of a centralized mobility scheme.
<!--  Questionable!!  -->

</t>

<t>
While deploying 
[Paper-Locating.User] 
today's mobile networks, 
service providers face new challenges. 
More often than not, 
mobile devices remain attached to the same point of attachment. 
Specific IP mobility management support is not required for applications 
that launch and complete while the mobile device is connected to the
same point of attachment. 
However, 
the mobility support has been designed to be always on 
and to maintain the context for each mobile subscriber 
as long as they are connected to the network. 
This can result in a waste of resources 
and ever-increasing costs for the service provider. 
Infrequent mobility and intelligence of many applications 
suggest that mobility can be provided dynamically, 
thus simplifying the context maintained 
in the different nodes of the mobile network.
</t>

<t>
The proposed work will address two complementary aspects 
of mobility management procedures: 
the distribution of mobility anchors to achieve a more flat design 
and the dynamic activation/deactivation of mobility protocol support 
as an enabler to distributed mobility management. 
The former has the goal of positioning mobility anchors (HA, LMA) 
closer to the user; 
ideally, these mobility agents could be collocated with the first hop router.
The latter, facilitated by the distribution of mobility anchors, 
aims at identifying when mobility must be activated 
and identifying sessions that do not impose mobility management 
-- thus reducing the amount of state information 
to be maintained in the various mobility agents of the mobile network. 
The key idea is that dynamic mobility management relaxes some constraints 
while also repositioning mobility anchors; 
it avoids the establishment of non optimal tunnels 
between two topologically distant anchors.
</t>

<t>
This document discusses the issues 
with centralized IP mobility management
compared with distributed and dynamic mobility management. 
A companion document 
[dmm-scenario] 
discusses the use case scenarios. 
</t>

</section>


<section title="Conventions used in this document">
<t>
The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL","SHALL NOT", 
"SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" 
in this document are to be interpreted as described 
in <xref target="RFC2119" />.
</t>
</section>


<section title="Centralized versus distributed mobility management">
<t>
Mobility management functions 
may be implemented at different layers 
of the network protocol stack. 
At the IP (network) layer, 
they may reside in the network or in the mobile node. 
In particular, 
a network-based solution resides in the network only.
It therefore enables mobility for existing hosts 
and network applications
which are already in deployment but lack mobility support.
</t>

<t>
At the IP layer, 
a mobility management protocol to achieve session continuity
is typically based on the principle 
of distinguishing between identifier and routing address
and maintaining a mapping between them. 
With Mobile IP, the home address serves as an identifier of the device
whereas the care-of-address takes the role of routing address,
and the binding between them is maintained at the mobility anchor,
i.e., the home agent.
If packets can be continuously delivered 
to a mobile device at its home address, 
then all sessions using that home address can be preserved
even though the routing or care-of address changes.
</t>

<t>
The next two subsections explain centralized and distributed
mobility management functions in the network.
</t>

<section title="Centralized mobility management">
<t>
With centralized mobility management, 
the mapping information between the stable node identifier 
and the changing IP address of an MN 
is kept at a centralized mobility anchor. 
Packets destined to an MN are routed via this anchor. 
In other words, 
such mobility management systems are centralized 
in both the control plane and the data plane.
</t>

<t>
Many existing mobility management deployments 
make use of centralized mobility anchoring 
in a hierarchical network architecture, 
as shown in Figure 1. 
Examples of such centralized mobility anchors 
are the home agent (HA) and local mobility anchor (LMA) 
in Mobile IP <xref target="RFC3775"/> 
and Proxy Mobile IP <xref target="RFC5213"/>, respectively. 
Current mobile networks 
such as the Third Generation Partnership Project (3GPP) 
UMTS networks, CDMA networks, 
and 3GPP Evolved Packet System (EPS) networks 
also employ centralized mobility management, 
with Gateway GPRS Support Node (GGSN) 
and Serving GPRS Support Node (SGSN) 
in the 3GPP UMTS hierarchical network 
and with Packet data network Gateway (P-GW) 
and Serving Gateway (S-GW) in the 3GPP EPS network.
</t>

      <figure>
        <preamble></preamble>
        <artwork><![CDATA[
       UMTS                3GPP SAE              MIP/PMIP
     +------+              +------+              +------+      
     | GGSN |              | P-GW |              |HA/LMA|      
     +------+              +------+              +------+      
        /\                    /\                    /\
       /  \                  /  \                  /  \
      /    \                /    \                /    \ 
     /      \              /      \              /      \
    /        \            /        \            /        \
+------+  +------+    +------+  +------+    +------+  +------+ 
| SGSN |  | SGSN |    | S-GW |  | S-GW |    |FA/MAG|  |FA/MAG| 
+------+  +------+    +------+  +------+    +------+  +------+  
      	]]></artwork>
        <postamble></postamble>
      </figure>

<t>Figure 1. Centralized mobility management.
</t>
</section>

<section title="Distributed mobility management">
<t>Mobility management functions may also be distributed 
to multiple locations in different networks
as shown in Figure 2, 
so that a mobile node in any of these networks
may be served by a closeby mobility function (MF). 
</t>

      <figure>
        <preamble></preamble>
        <artwork><![CDATA[
+------+  +------+  +------+  +------+    
|  MF  |  |  MF  |  |  MF  |  |  MF  |    
+------+  +------+  +------+  +------+    
                       |          
                     ----           
                    | MN |          
                     ----           
      	]]></artwork>
        <postamble></postamble>
      </figure>

<t>Figure 2. Distributed mobility management.
</t>
<t>
Mobility management may be partially distributed,
i.e., only the data plane is distributed,
or fully distributed
where both the data plane and control plane are distributed.
These different approaches are described in detail in 
[I-D.dmm-scenario].
</t>
<t>
A distributed mobility management scheme is proposed in 
[Paper-Distributed.Dynamic.Mobility] 
for future flat IP architecture consisting of access nodes. 
The benefits of this design 
over centralized mobility management 
are also verified through simulations in 
[Paper-Distributed.Centralized.Mobility]
.
</t>
<t>
Before designing new mobility management protocols 
for a future flat IP architecture, 
one should first ask 
whether the existing mobility management protocols 
that have already been deployed 
for the hierarchical mobile networks 
can be extended to serve the flat IP architecture. 
MIPv4 has already been deployed in 3GPP2 networks, 
and PMIPv6 has already been adopted in WiMAX Forum 
and in 3GPP standards. 
Using MIP or PMIP 
for both centralized and distributed architectures 
would ease the migration of the current mobile networks 
towards a flat architecture. 
It has therefore been proposed to adapt MIP or PMIPv6 
to achieve distributed mobility management 
by using a distributed mobility anchor architecture. 
</t>

<t>
In 
[Paper-Migrating.Home.Agents]
, 
the HA functionality is copied to many locations. 
The HoA of all MNs are anycast addresses, 
so that a packet destined to a HoA from any CN from any network 
can be routed via the nearest copy of the HA. 
In addition, 
distributing the function of HA 
using a distributed hash table structure is proposed in 
[Paper-Distributed.Mobility.SAE]
. 
A lookup query to the hash table 
will retrieve the location information of an MN is stored.

</t>

<t>
In 
[Paper-Distributed.Mobility.PMIP]
, 
only the mobility routing (MR) function 
is duplicated and distributed in many locations. 
The location information for any MN 
that has moved to a visited network 
is still centralized 
and kept at a location management (LM) function 
in the home network of the MN. 
The LM function at different networks 
constitutes a distributed database system 
of all the MNs 
that belong to any of these networks 
and have moved to a visited network. 
The location information is maintained 
in the form of a hierarchy: 
the LM at the home network, 
the CoA of the MR of the visited network, 
and then the CoA to reach the MN in the visited network. 
The LM in the home network 
keeps a binding of the HoA of the MN 
to the CoA of the MR of the visited network. 
The MR keeps the binding of the HoA of the MN 
to the CoA of the MN in the case of MIP, 
or the proxy-CoA of the Mobile Access Gateway (MAG) 
serving the MN in the case of PMIP. 
</t>

<t>
	[I-D.PMIP-DMC] discusses two distributed mobility control schemes
	using the PMIP protocol: 
Signal-driven PMIP (S-PMIP) and Signal-driven Distributed PMIP (SD-PMIP). 
S-PMIP is a partially distributed scheme, in which the control plane
(using a Proxy Binding Query to get the Proxy-CoA of the MN) 
is separate from the data plane, 
and the optimized data path is directly between the CN and the MN.
SD-PMIP is a fully distributed scheme, 
in which the Proxy Binding Update is not performed, 
and instead each MAG will multicast a Proxy Binding Query message 
to all of the MAGs in its local PMIP domain 
to retrieve the Proxy-CoA of the MN.
</t>

</section>

</section>


<section title="Problem statement">

<t>This section identifies problems and limitations 
of centralized mobility approaches,
and compares against possible distributed approaches.
</t>

<section title="Non-optimal routes">
<t>Routing via a centralized anchor often results in a longer route.
Figure 3 shows two cases of non-optimized routes.
</t>

      <figure>
        <preamble></preamble>
        <artwork><![CDATA[
      MIP/PMIP                                                
      +------+              
      |HA/LMA|               
      +------+               
        /\ \  \                   +---+
       /  \   \    \              |CDN|
      /    \     \      \         +---+
     /      \       \        \      |
    /        \         \          \ |
+------+  +------+  +------+   +------+    
|FA/MAG|  |FA/MAG|  |FA/MAG|   |FA/MAG|    
+------+  +------+  +------+   +------+    
                       |          |
                     ----       ----
                    | CN |     | MN |
                     ----       ----
      	]]></artwork>
        <postamble></postamble>
      </figure>

<t>Figure 3. Non-optimized route when communicating with CN
and when accessing local content.
</t>

<t>
In the first case, the mobile node and the correspondent node
are close to each other but are both far from the mobility anchor.
Packets destined to the mobile node  
need to be routed via the mobility anchor, 
which is not on the shortest path. 
<!-- CEP: stopped here for now... -->

The second case involves a content delivery network (CDN). 
A user may obtain content from a server, 
such as when watching a video. 
As such usage becomes more popular, 
resulting in an increase in the core network traffic, 
service providers may relieve the core network traffic 
by placing these contents closer to the users 
in the access network in the form of cache or local CDN servers. 
Yet as the MN is getting content 
from a local or cache server of a CDN, 
even though the server is close to the MN, 
packets still need to go through the core network 
to route via the mobility anchor in the home network of the MN, 
if the MN uses the HoA as its identifier. 
</t>

<t>
In a distributed mobility management design, 
mobility anchors are distributed in different access networks 
so that packets may be routed 
via a nearby mobility anchor function, 
as shown in Figure 4.
</t>

      <figure>
        <preamble></preamble>
        <artwork><![CDATA[
                                  +---+
                                  |CDN|
                                  +---+
                                    |
                                    |
+------+  +------+  +------+   +------+    
|  MF  |  |  MF  |  |  MF  |   |  MF  |    
+------+  +------+  +------+   +------+    
                       |          |
                     ----       ----
                    | CN |     | MN |
                     ----       ----
      	]]></artwork>
        <postamble></postamble>
      </figure>

<t>Figure 4. 
Mobile node in any network is served by a close by mobility function.
</t>

<t>
Due to the above limitation, 
with the centralized mobility anchor design, 
route optimization extensions to mobility protocols 
are therefore needed. 
Whereas the location privacy of each MN may be compromised 
when the CoA of an MN is given to the CN, 
those mobility protocol deployments 
that lack such optimization extensions 
will encounter non-optimal routes, 
which affect the performance. 
</t>

<t>
In contrast, 
route optimization may be naturally 
an integral part of a distributed mobility management design.
With the help of such intrinsic route optimization, 
the data transmission delay will be reduced, 
by which the data transmission throughputs can be enhanced. 
Furthermore, the data traffic overhead at the mobility agents 
such as the HA and the LMA in the core network can be alleviated significanly.
</t>

</section>

<section title="Non-optimality in Evolved Network Architecture">
<t>
Centralized mobility management 
is currently deployed 
to support the existing hierarchical mobile data networks. 
It leverages on the hierarchical architecture. 
However, 
the volume of wireless data traffic 
continues to increase exponentially. 
The data traffic increase 
would require costly capacity upgrade 
of centralized architectures. 
It is thus predictable 
that the data traffic increase will soon overload 
the centralized data anchor point, 
e.g., the P-GW in 3GPP EPS. 
In order to address this issue, 
a trend in the evolution of mobile networks 
is to distribute network functions 
close to access networks. 
These network functions can be the content servers 
in a CDN, 
and also the data anchor point. 
</t>
<t>
Mobile networks have been evolving 
from a hierarchical architecture to a more flattened architecture.
In the 3GPP standards, 
the GPRS network has the hierarchy GGSN 每 SGSN 每 RNC 每 NB (Node B).
In  3GPP EPS networks, 
the hierarchy is reduced to P-GW 每 S-GW 每 eNB (Evolved NB). 
In some deployments, 
the P-GW and the S-GW are collocated to further reduce the hierarchy. 
Reducing the hierarchy this way 
reduces the number of different physical network elements in the network, 
contributing to easier system maintenance and lower cost. 
As mobile networks become more flattened, 
the centralized mobility management can become non-optimal. 
Mobility management deployment 
with distributed architecture 
is then needed to support the more flattened network and the CDN networks. 
</t>
</section>

<section title="Low scalability of centralized route and mobility context maintenance">
<t>
Special routes are set up 
to enable session continuity when a handover occurs. 
Packets sent from the CN 
need to be tunneled between the HA and FA in MIP 
and between the LMA and MAG in PMIP. 
However, 
these network elements at the ends of the tunnel 
are also routers 
performing the regular routing tasks 
for ordinary packets not involving a mobile node. 
These ordinary packets need to be directly routed 
according to the routing table in the routers without tunneling. 
Therefore, 
the network must be able to distinguish 
those packets requiring tunneling from the regular packets. 
For each packet that requires tunneling owing to mobility, 
the network will encapsulate it 
with a proper outer IP header 
with the proper source and destination IP addresses. 
The network therefore 
needs to maintain and manage the mobility context of each MN, 
which is the relevant information 
needed to characterize the mobility situation of that MN
to allow the network to distinguish 
their packets from other packets 
and to perform the required tunneling.
</t>

<t>
Setting up such special routes 
and maintaining the mobility context for each MN 
is more difficult to scale 
in a centralized design with a large number of MNs. 
Distributing the route maintenance function 
and the mobility context maintenance function 
among different networks can be more scalable.
</t>
</section>

<section title="Wasting resources to support mobile nodes not needing mobility support">
<t>
The problem of centralized route and mobility context maintenance 
is aggravated 
when the via routes are set up 
for many more MNs 
that are not requiring IP mobility support. 
On the one hand, 
the network needs to provide mobility support 
for the increasing number of mobile devices 
because the existing mobility management 
has been designed to always provide such support 
as long as a mobile device is attached to the network. 
On the other hand, 
many nomadic users connected to a network in an office 
or meeting room.   Such users will not move 
for the entire network session. 
It has been measured that over two-thirds of a
user mobility is local 
[Paper-Locating.User]
. 
In addition, 
it is possible to have the intelligence 
for applications to manage mobility 
without needing help from the network.
Network resources are therefore wasted 
to provide mobility support for the devices 
that do not really need it at the moment.  
</t>
<t>
It is necessary to dynamically set up the via routes 
only for MNs that actually undergo handovers 
and lack higher-layer mobility support. 
With distributed mobility anchors, 
such dynamic mobility management mechanism 
may then also be distributed. 
Therefore, dynamic mobility 
and distributed mobility may complement each other 
and may be integrated.
</t>
</section>

<section title="Complicated deployment with too many variants and extensions of MIP">
<t>
Mobile IP, 
which has primarily been deployed in a centralized manner 
for the hierarchical mobile networks, 
already has numerous variants and extensions 
including PMIP, Fast MIP (FMIP) 
<xref target="RFC4068"/>
<xref target="RFC4988"/>
, Proxy-based FMIP (PFMIP)
<xref target="RFC5949"/>
, hierarchical MIP (HMIP) 
<xref target="RFC5380"/>
, Dual-Stack Mobile IP (DSMIP) 
<xref target="RFC5454"/>
<xref target="RFC5555"/>
and there may be more to come. 
These different modifications or extensions of MIP 
have been developed over the years 
owing to the different needs that are found afterwards. 
Deployment can then become complicated, 
especially if interoperability with different deployments 
is an issue. 
</t>

<t>
A desirable feature of mobility management 
is to be able to work with network architectures 
of both hierarchical networks and flattened networks, 
so that the mobility management protocol 
possesses enough flexibility to support different networks. 
In addition, one goal of dynamic mobility management 
is the capability to selectively turn on and off mobility support 
and certain different mobility signaling. 
Such flexibility in the design 
is compatible with the goal 
to integrate different mobility variants as options. 
Some additional extensions to the base protocols 
may then be needed to improve the integration. 
</t>
</section>

<section title="Mobility signaling overhead with peer-to-peer communication">
<t>
In peer-to-peer communications, 
end users communicate by sending packets 
directly addressed to each other＊s IP address. 
However, they need to find each other＊s IP address first 
through signaling in the network. 
While different schemes for this purpose may be used, 
MIP already has a mechanism to locate an MN 
and may be used in this way.  
In particular, 
MIPv6 Route Optimization (RO) mode 
enables a more efficient data packets exchange 
than the bidirectional tunneling (BT) mode, 
as shown in Figure 5. 
</t>

      <figure>
        <preamble></preamble>
        <artwork><![CDATA[
      MIP/PMIP                                                
      +------+              
      |HA/LMA|               
      +------+               
        /\ \  \               
       /  \   \    \                    
      /    \     \      \     
     /      \       \        \     
    /        \         \          \
+------+  +------+  +------+   +------+    
|FA/MAG|  |FA/MAG|  |FA/MAG|   |FA/MAG|    
+------+  +------+  +------+   +------+    
                       |          |
                     ----       ----
                    | MN |<--->| CN |
                     ----       ----
      	]]></artwork>
        <postamble></postamble>
      </figure>

<t>Figure 5. Non-optimized route when communicating with CN
and when accessing local content.
</t>

<t>
This RO mode is expected to be used whenever possible 
unless the MN is not interested 
in disclosing its topological location, 
i.e., the CoA, to the CN (e.g., for privacy reasons) 
or some other network constraints are put in place. 
However, 
MIPv6 RO mode requires 
exchanging a significant amount of signaling messages 
in order to establish 
and periodically refresh 
a bidirectional security association (BSA) 
between an MN and its CN. 
While the mobility signaling exchange 
impacts the overall handover latency, 
the BSA is needed to authenticate the binding update 
and acknowledgment messages 
(note that the latter is not mandatory). 
In addition, 
the amount of mobility signaling messages increases further 
when both endpoints are mobile.
</t>
<t>
A dynamic mobility management capability 
to turn off these signaling when they are not needed 
will enable the RO mode between two mobile endpoints 
at minimum or no cost. 
It will also reduce the handover latency 
owing to the removal of the extra signaling. 
These benefits for peer-to-peer communications 
will encourage the adoption 
and large-scale deployment of dynamic mobility management.
</t>
</section>

<section title="Single point of failure and attack">
<t>
A centralized anchoring architecture 
is generally more vulnerable 
to a single point of failure or attack,
requiring duplication and backups of the support functions. 
</t>
<t>
On the other hand,
a distributed mobility management architecture 
has intrinsically mitigated the problem 
to a local network which is then of a smaller scope.
In addition,
the availability of such functions in neighboring networks
has already provided the needed architecture to support protection.
</t>
</section>

</section>


<section anchor="security" title="Security Considerations">
<t>TBD</t>
</section>


<section title="IANA Considerations">
<t>None</t>
</section>


<section title="Co-authors and Contributors">
<t>This problem statement document is a joint effort 
among the following participants in a design team. 
Each individual has made significant contributions to this work. 
</t>

<t>Dapeng Liu: liudapeng@chinamobile.com</t>
<t>Pierrick Seite: pierrick.seite@orange-ftgroup.com</t>
<t>Hidetoshi Yokota: yokota@kddilabs.jp</t>
<t>Charles E. Perkins: charliep@computer.org</t>
<t>Melia Telemaco: telemaco.melia@alcatel-lucent.com</t>
<t>Hui Deng: denghui@chinamobile.com</t>
<t>Elena Demaria: elena.demaria@telecomitalia.it</t>
<t>Zhen Cao: caozhen@chinamobile.com</t>
<t>Wassim Michel Haddad: Wassam.Haddad@ericsson.com</t>
<t>Seok Joo Koh: sjkoh@knu.ac.kr</t>

</section>

</middle>


<back>

<references title="Normative References">
  &rfc2119;
</references>

<references title="Informative References">
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.3775" ?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.5213" ?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.5380" ?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.4068" ?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.4988" ?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.5454" ?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.5555" ?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.5949" ?>

<reference anchor="I-D.dmm-scenario">
<front>
<title>Use case scenarios for Distributed Mobility Management</title> 
<author initials="H" surname="Yokota" fullname="Hidetoshi Yokota">
  <organization /> 
</author>
<author initials="P" surname="Seite" fullname="Pierrick Seite">
  <organization /> 
</author>
<author initials="E" surname="Demaria" fullname="Elena Demaria">
  <organization /> 
</author>
<author initials="Z" surname="Cao" fullname="Zhen Cao">
  <organization /> 
</author>
<date month="October" year="2010" /> 
</front>
<seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-yokota-dmm-scenario-00" /> 
<format type="TXT" target="http://www.ietf.org/internet-drafts/draft-yokota-dmm-scenario-00.txt" /> 
</reference>

<reference anchor="I-D.PMIP-dmc">
<front>
<title>Use of Proxy Mobile IPv6 for Distributed Mobility Control</title> 
<author initials="S" surname="Koh" fullname="Seok Joo Koh">
  <organization /> 
</author>
<author initials="J" surname="Kim" fullname="Ji In Kim">
  <organization /> 
</author>
<author initials="H" surname="Jung" fullname="Hee Young Jung">
  <organization /> 
</author>
<author initials="Y" surname="Han" fullname="Youn-Hee Han">
  <organization /> 
</author>
<date month="March" year="2011" /> 
</front>
<seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-sjkoh-mext-pmip-dmc-01" /> 
<format type="TXT" target="http://www.ietf.org/internet-drafts/draft-sjkoh-mext-pmip-dmc-01.txt" /> 
</reference>

<reference anchor="Paper-Locating.User">
<front>
<title>Locating the User</title>
<author initials="G" surname="Kirby">
  <organization />
</author>
<date year="1995" />
</front>
<seriesInfo name="" value="Communication International" />
</reference>

<reference anchor="Paper-Distributed.Dynamic.Mobility">
<front>
<title>A Distributed Dynamic Mobility Management Scheme Designed for Flat IP Architectures</title>
<author initials="P" surname="Bertin">
  <organization />
</author>
<author initials="S" surname="Bonjour">
  <organization />
</author>
<author initials="J-M" surname="Bonnin">
  <organization />
</author>
<date year="2008" />
</front>
<seriesInfo name="" value="Proceedings of 3rd International Conference on New Technologies, Mobility and Security (NTMS)" />
</reference>

<reference anchor="Paper-Distributed.Centralized.Mobility">
<front>
<title>A Distributed or Centralized Mobility</title>
<author initials="P" surname="Bertin">
  <organization />
</author>
<author initials="S" surname="Bonjour">
  <organization />
</author>
<author initials="J-M" surname="Bonnin">
  <organization />
</author>
<date month="December" year="2009" />
</front>
<seriesInfo name="" value="Proceedings of Global Communications Conference (GlobeCom)" />
</reference>

<reference anchor="Paper-Migrating.Home.Agents">
<front>
<title>Migrating Home Agents Towards Internet-scale Mobility Deployments</title>
<author initials="R" surname="Wakikawa">
  <organization />
</author>
<author initials="G" surname="Valadon">
  <organization />
</author>
<author initials="J" surname="Murai">
  <organization />
</author>
<date month="December" year="2006" />
</front>
<seriesInfo name="" value="Proceedings of the ACM 2nd CoNEXT Conference on Future Networking Technologies" />
</reference>

<reference anchor="Paper-Distributed.Mobility.SAE">
<front>
<title>A Distributed IP Mobility Approach for 3G SAE</title>
<author initials="M" surname="Fisher">
  <organization />
</author>
<author initials="F.U" surname="Anderson">
  <organization />
</author>
<author initials="A" surname="Kopsel">
  <organization />
</author>
<author initials="G" surname="Schafer">
  <organization />
</author>
<author initials="M" surname="Schlager">
  <organization />
</author>
<date year="2008" />
</front>
<seriesInfo name="" value="Proceedings of the 19th International Symposium on Personal, Indoor and Mobile Radio Communications (PIMRC)" />
</reference>

<reference anchor="Paper-Distributed.Mobility.PMIP">
<front>
<title>Proxy Mobile IP with Distributed Mobility Anchors</title>
<author initials="H" surname="Chan">
  <organization />
</author>
<date month="December" year="2010" />
</front>
<seriesInfo name="" value="Proceedings of GlobeCom Workshop on Seamless Wireless Mobility" />
</reference>


</references>

</back>
</rfc>
