<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
    <!ENTITY rfc2045 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2045.xml'>
    <!ENTITY rfc2104 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2104.xml'>
    <!ENTITY rfc2119 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml'>
    <!ENTITY rfc3261 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3261.xml'>
    <!ENTITY rfc3263 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3263.xml'>

    <!ENTITY rfc3327 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3327.xml'>
    <!ENTITY rfc3608 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3608.xml'>
    <!ENTITY rfc3680 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3680.xml'>
    <!ENTITY rfc3968 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3968.xml'>
    <!ENTITY rfc3969 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3969.xml'>
    <!ENTITY rfc5626 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5626.xml'>
    <!ENTITY rfc5627 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5627.xml'>
 
    <!ENTITY draft-ietf-martini-reqs PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.draft-ietf-martini-reqs-07.xml'>
    <!ENTITY nbsp "&#x0A0;">
]>

<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>

<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="no" ?>
<?rfc symrefs="no"?>

<rfc ipr="trust200902" docName="draft-ietf-martini-gin-03" category="std">
<front>
    <title abbrev="Globally Identifiable Number Routing">Registration for Multiple Phone Numbers in the Session Initiation Protocol (SIP)</title>

    <author initials="A. B." surname="Roach" fullname="Adam Roach">
      <organization>Tekelec</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>17210 Campbell Rd.</street>
          <street>Suite 250</street>
          <city>Dallas</city> <region>TX</region> <code>75252</code>
          <country>US</country>
        </postal>
        <email>adam@nostrum.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date month="May" day="21" year="2010" />
    <area>Real Time Applications and Infrastructure</area>
    <workgroup>MARTINI WG</workgroup>

  <abstract>
    <t>
      This document defines a mechanism by which a SIP server
      acting as a traditional Private Branch Exchange (PBX)
      can register with a SIP Service Provider (SSP) to receive
      phone calls for terminals designated by phone numbers.
      In order to function properly, this mechanism relies on
      the fact that the phone numbers are fully qualified and
      globally unique.
    </t>
  </abstract>
</front>

<middle>
  <section title="Introduction">
    <t>
      One of SIP's primary functions is providing rendezvous between
      users. By design, this rendezvous has been provided through
      a combination of the server look-up procedures defined in
      RFC 3263 <xref target="RFC3263"/>, and the registrar procedures
      described in RFC 3261 <xref target="RFC3261"/>.
    </t>
    <t>
      The intention of the original protocol design was that any user's
      AOR would be handled by the authority indicated by the hostport
      portion of the AOR. The users registered individual reachability
      information with this authority, which would then route
      incoming requests accordingly.
    </t>
    <t>
      In actual deployments, some SIP servers have been deployed
      in architectures that, for various reasons, have
      requirements to provide dynamic routing information
      for large blocks of AORs, where all of the AORs in
      the block were to be handled by the same server. For
      purposes of efficiency, many of these deployments do
      not wish to maintain separate registrations for each of
      the AORs in the block. This leads to the desire for an
      alternate mechanism for providing dynamic routing
      information for blocks of AORs.
    </t>
    <t>
      Although the use of REGISTER to update reachability
      information for multiple users simultaneously is somewhat
      beyond the original semantics defined for REGISTER, this
      approach has seen significant deployment in certain
      environments. In particular, deployments in which small
      to medium SIP PBX servers are addressed using E.164 numbers
      have used this mechanism to avoid the need to maintain
      DNS entries or static IP addresses for the PBX servers.
    </t>
    <t>
      In recognition of the momentum that REGISTER-based
      approaches have seen in deployments,
      this document defines a REGISTER-based approach that is
      tailored to E.164-addressed terminals in a SIP PBX
      environment. It does not address
      registration of SIP URIs in which the user portion
      is not an E.164 number.
    </t>
  </section>
  <section title="Constraints" anchor="constraints">
    <t>
      The following paragraph is perhaps the most important
      in understanding the reasons for the design decisions
      made in this document.
    </t>
    <t>
      Within the problem space that has been established for
      this work, several constraints shape our solution. These
      are being defined in the MARTINI requirements document
      <xref target="I-D.ietf-martini-reqs"/>.
      In terms of impact to the solution at hand, the following
      two constraints have the most profound effect:
      (1) The PBX cannot be assumed to be assigned a static
          IP address; and 
      (2) No DNS entry can be relied upon to consistently resolve
          to the IP address of the PBX.
    </t>
  </section>

  <section title="Terminology">
    <t> The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL
    NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL"
    in this document are to be interpreted as described in RFC 2119
    <xref target="RFC2119" />.</t>
    <t>Further, the term "SSP" is meant as an acronym for a "SIP Service
    Provider," while the term "PBX" is used to indicate a SIP Private
    Branch Exchange.</t>
    <t><list style="hanging"><t>
      Indented portions of the document, such as this one,
      form non-normative, explanatory sections of the document.
    </t></list></t>
  </section>

  <section title="Mechanism Overview">
    <t>
      The overall mechanism is achieved using a REGISTER
      request with a specially-formatted Contact URI.
      This document also defines an option tag that can be used to
      ensure a registrar and any intermediaries understand the
      mechanism described herein.
    </t>
    <t>
      The Contact URI itself is tagged with a URI parameter
      to indicate that it actually represents a multitude of
      phone-number-associated contacts.
    </t>
    <t>
      We also define some lightweight extensions for Globally Routable
      UA URIs (GRUU) to
      allow the use of public and temporary GRUUs assigned by
      the SSP. 
    </t>
    <t>
      Aside from these extensions, the REGISTER message itself
      is processed by a registrar in the same way as normal
      registrations: by updating its location service with
      additional AOR to Contact bindings.
    </t>
    <t>
      Note that the list of phone numbers associated with a
      PBX is a matter of local provisioning at the SSP and
      at the PBX. The mechanism defined in this document
      does not provide any means to detect or recover from
      provisioning mismatches (although the registration
      event package can be used as a standardized means
      for auditing such phone numbers;
      see <xref target="pbx-reg-event"/>).
    </t>
  </section>

  <section title="Registering for Multiple Phone Numbers">
    <section title="PBX Behavior">
      <t>
        To register for multiple phone numbers, the PBX sends
        a REGISTER message to the SSP. This REGISTER varies
        from a typical register in two important ways. First,
        it must contain an option tag of "gin"
        in both a "Require" header field and a "Proxy-Require"
        header field.  (The option tag "gin" is an acronym for
        "generate implicit numbers".)
        Second, in at least 
        one "Contact" header field, it must include a Contact
        URI that contains the URI parameter "bnc", and no user
        portion (hence no "@" symbol).
        A URI with a "bnc" parameter MUST NOT contain a
        user portion. Except for the SIP URI "user" parameter,
        this URI MAY contain any other parameters that the
        PBX desires. These parameters will be echoed back by
        the SSP in any requests bound for the PBX.
      </t>
      <t>
        Because of the constraints
        discussed in <xref target="constraints"/>, the host
        portion of the Contact URI will generally contain
        an IP address, although nothing in this mechanism
        enforces or relies upon that fact. If the PBX operator
        chooses to maintain DNS entries that resolve to the
        IP address of his PBX via RFC 3263 resolution procedures,
        then this mechanism works just fine with domain names
        in the Contact header field.
      </t>
      <t>
        The URI parameter indicates that special interpretation
        of the Contact URI is necessary: instead of representing
        a single, concrete Contact URI to be inserted into the
        location service, it represents a multitude of Contact
        URIs (one for each associated phone number), semantically
        resulting in a multitude of AOR-to-Contact rows in the
        location service.
      </t>
      <t>
        Any PBX implementing the registration mechanism defined in
        this document MUST also support the Path mechanism defined
        by RFC 3327 <xref target="RFC3327"/>, and MUST include a
        'path' option-tag in the Supported header field of the REGISTER
        request (which is a stronger requirement than imposed by the
        Path mechanism itself).  This behavior is necessary because
        proxies between the PBX and the Registrar may need to insert
        Path header field values in the REGISTER request for this
        document's mechanism to function properly, and per RFC 3327
        <xref target="RFC3327"/>, they can only do so if the UAC
        inserted the option-tag in the Supported header field.  In
        accordance with the procedures defined in RFC 3327 <xref
        target="RFC3327"/>, the PBX is allowed to ignore the Path
        header fields returned in the REGISTER response.
      </t>
    </section>
    <section title="Registrar Behavior">
      <t>
        The registrar, upon receipt of a REGISTER message 
        containing at least one Contact header field with
        a "bnc" parameter will use the value in the "To" header field
        to identify the PBX for which registration is being requested.
        It then authenticates the PBX (using, e.g., SIP Digest
        authentication, mutual TLS, or some other authentication
        mechanism).  After the PBX is authenticated, the registrar
        updates its location service with a unique AOR to Contact
        mapping for each of the phone numbers associated with the
        PBX.  Semantically, each of these mappings will be treated
        as a unique row in the location service.  The actual
        implementation may, of course, perform internal optimizations
        to reduce the amount of memory used to store
        such information.
      </t>
      <t>
        For each of these unique rows, the AOR will be in the format
        that the SSP expects to receive from external parties (e.g.
        "sip:+12145550102@ssp.example.com"), and the corresponding
        Contact will be formed by adding to the REGISTER's Contact
        URI a user portion containing the fully-qualified, E.164-formatted
        phone number (including the preceding "+" symbol) and removing
        the "bnc" parameter. Aside from the initial "+" symbol, this
        E.164-formatted number MUST consist exclusively of digits
        from 0 through 9, and explicitly MUST NOT contain any visual
        separator symbols (e.g., "-", ".", "(", or ")").  For
        example, if the "Contact" header field contains the URI
        &lt;sip:198.51.100.3:5060;bnc>, then the Contact
        value
        associated with the aforementioned AOR will be
        &lt;sip:+12145550102@198.51.100.3:5060>.
      </t>
      <t>
        Although the SSP treats this registration as a number of
        discrete rows for the purpose of re-targeting incoming requests,
        the renewal, expiration, and removal of these rows is bound
        to the registered "bnc" contact. In particular, this means
        that REGISTER requests that attempt to de-register a single
        phone number that has been implicitly registered MUST NOT
        remove that phone number from the bulk registration.  A further
        implication of this property is that an individual extension
        that is implicitly registered may also be explicitly registered
        using a normal, non-bulk registration (subject to SSP policy).
        If such a registration exists, it is refreshed independently
        of the bulk registration, and is not removed when the bulk
        registration is removed.
      </t>
      <t>
        A registrar that receives a URI with both a "bnc"
        parameter and a user portion
        MAY discard the user portion and process the request
        as if it were not present. Alternately, the registrar MAY
        return a 400 (Bad Request) error in response.
      </t>
      <t><list style="hanging">
        <t>
          Note that this requirement is talking about
          the user portion of a URI:<vspace blankLines="1"/>
          sip:+12145550100@example.com;user=phone<vspace/>
          &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;^^^^^^^^^^^^
        </t>
      </list></t>
      <t>
        A Registrar compliant with this document MUST support the
        Path mechanism defined in RFC 3327 <xref target="RFC3327"/>.
      </t>
      <t>
        Aside from the "bnc" and "autouser" parameters, all URI
        parameters present
        on the "Contact" URI in the REGISTER message MUST be copied
        to the Contact value stored in the location service.
      </t>
    </section>
    <section title='SIP URI "user" Parameter Handling'>
      <t>
        Some PBXes require inbound requests containing a phone
        number to include a "user=phone" parameter. Others do
        not function properly when this parameter is present.
        To accommodate this variation in behavior, we define a
        new URI parameter, "autouser", which indicates whether
        the SSP is required to include a "user" indication.
      </t>
      <t>
        To accommodate proper handling of further extensions to this
        mechanism, PBXes MUST NOT include a "user" parameter on a
        URI that also contains a "bnc" parameter.  A registrar that
        receives such a URI MAY discard the "user" parameter and
        process the request as if the parameter were not present.
        Alternately, it MAY return a 400 (Bad Request) error in
        response.
      </t>
      <t><list style="hanging">
        <t>
          Note that this requirement is talking about
          the user parameter of a URI:<vspace blankLines="1"/>
          sip:+12145550100@example.com;user=phone<vspace/>
          &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;^^^^^^^^^^
        </t>
      </list></t>
      <t>
        If the PBX requires arriving Request URIs to be tagged with
        a "user" parameter, it can include an "autouser" parameter
        on its contact URI, with a value of "true." When the SSP
        sends a request to the PBX associated with an "autouser"
        registration, it MUST determine the correct value for the
        "user" parameter in the Request-URI.  (The "correct value"
        will generally be a matter of provisioning, although alternate
        mechanisms for determining this value are also valid.) For
        example, if the the inbound request contains a telephone
        number formatted as a telephone-subscriber -- which will
        always be the case unless additional extensions are employed
        -- this value will be "phone." If the correct value is
        anything other than the default value of "ip", then the SSP
        MUST include a "user" parameter on the Request URI. If the
        value is "ip", then the SSP MAY include it.
      </t>
      <t> <list style="hanging">
        <t>
          Although the mechanism defined in this document only
          deals with phone numbers, future protocol extensions
          may specify behavior for non-phone-number-based
          user portions, which would require the SSP to make
          decisions about the "correct value" for the "user"
          parameter. It is also conceivable that new
          values might be added to the "user" parameter.
        </t>
      </list> </t>
      <t>
        As a corollary,
        if the registering PBX does not include an "autouser=true"
        parameter, any SSP using the procedures defined in this
        document MUST NOT include a "user" parameter on the
        resulting Request-URI.
      </t>
      <t>
        If a URI contains a "bnc" parameter, but no "autouser"
        parameter, the value of "autouser" is presumed to be
        "false."
      </t>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section title="SSP Processing of Inbound Phone Number Requests"
    anchor="ssp-processing">
    <!-- 6 -->
    <t>
      In general, after processing the AOR to Contact mapping
      described in the preceding section, the SSP Proxy/Registrar
      (or equivalent entity) performs traditional Proxy/Registrar
      behavior, based on the mapping.  For any inbound SIP requests
      whose AOR indicates an E.164 number assigned to one of
      the SSP's customers, this will generally involve
      setting the target set to the registered contacts
      associated with that AOR, and performing
      request forwarding as described in section 16.6 of
      RFC 3261 <xref target="RFC3261"/>. An SSP using the mechanism
      defined in this document MUST perform
      such processing for inbound INVITE requests and SUBSCRIBE requests
      to the "reg" event package (see <xref target="reg-terminal"/>),
      and SHOULD perform such processing for all other method types, 
      including unrecognized SIP methods.
    </t>
  </section>

  <section title="Interaction with Other Mechanisms">
    <t>
      The following sections describe the means by which this mechanism
      interacts with relevant REGISTER-related extensions currently
      defined by the IETF.
    </t>
    <t>
      Currently, the descriptions are somewhat informal, and
      omit some details for the sake of brevity. If the MARTINI
      working group expresses interest in furthering the mechanism
      described by this document, they will be fleshed out with
      more detail and formality.
    </t>

    <section title="Globally Routable User-Agent URIs (GRUU)" anchor="gruu">
      <t>
        To enable advanced services to work with terminals
        behind a SIP PBX, it is important that the GRUU
        mechanism defined by RFC 5627 
        <xref target="RFC5627"/> work correctly
        with the mechanism defined by this document -- that is,
        that User Agents services by the PBX can acquire and
        use GRUUs for their own use.
      </t>

      <section title="Public GRUUs">
        <t>
          When a PBX registers a Bulk Number Contact (a Contact with
          a "bnc" parameter), and also invokes GRUU procedures for
          that Contact during registration, then the SSP will
          assign a public GRUU to the PBX in the normal fashion.
          Because the URI being registered contains a "bnc" parameter,
          the GRUU will also contain a "bnc" parameter. In particular,
          this means that the GRUU will not contain a user portion.
        </t>
        <t>
          When a terminal registers with the PBX using GRUU procedures
          for a Contact, the PBX adds an "sg" parameter to the GRUU
          parameter it received from the SSP. This "sg" parameter
          contains a disambiguation token that the PBX can use to
          route the request to the proper user agent.
        </t>
        <t>
          So, for example, when the PBX registers with the following
          contact header field:

          <figure> <artwork>
Contact: &lt;sip:198.51.100.3;bnc>;
  +sip.instance="&lt;urn:uuid:f81d4fae-7dec-11d0-a765-00a0c91e6bf6>"
          </artwork></figure>

          Then the SSP may choose to respond with a Contact header field
          that looks like this:

          <figure> <artwork>
&lt;allOneLine>
Contact: &lt;sip:198.51.100.3;bnc>;
pub-gruu="sip:ssp.example.com;bnc;gr=urn:
uuid:f81d4fae-7dec-11d0-a765-00a0c91e6bf6";
+sip.instance="&lt;urn:uuid:f81d4fae-7dec-11d0-a765-00a0c91e6bf6>"
;expires=7200
&lt;/allOneLine>
          </artwork></figure>

          When its own terminals register, the PBX
          can then add  whatever device identifier it feels appropriate
          in an "sg" parameter, and present this value to its
          own terminals. For example, assume the terminal associated
          with the phone number "+12145550102" sent the following
          Contact header field in its register:

          <figure> <artwork>
Contact: &lt;sip:line-1@10.20.1.17>;
  +sip.instance="&lt;urn:uuid:d0e2f290-104b-11df-8a39-0800200c9a66>"
          </artwork></figure>

          The PBX will add an "sg" parameter to the pub-gruu it
          received from the SSP with a token that uniquely 
          identifies the device (possibly the URN itself; possibly
          some other identifier); insert a user portion containing
          the fully-qualified E.164 number associated with the
          terminal; and return the result to the terminal as its
          public GRUU. The resulting Contact header field would 
          look something like this:

          <figure> <artwork>
&lt;allOneLine>
Contact: &lt;sip:line-1@10.20.1.17>;
pub-gruu="sip:+12145550102@ssp.example.com;bnc;gr=urn:
uuid:f81d4fae-7dec-11d0-a765-00a0c91e6bf6;sg=00:05:03:5e:70:a6";
+sip.instance="&lt;urn:uuid:d0e2f290-104b-11df-8a39-0800200c9a66>"
;expires=3600
&lt;/allOneLine>
          </artwork></figure>
        </t>
        <t>
          When an incoming request arrives at the SSP for a GRUU
          corresponding to a bulk number contact ("bnc"), the SSP
          performs slightly different processing for the GRUU than
          a Proxy/Registrar would. When the GRUU is re-targeted
          to the registered bulk number contact, the SSP MUST
          copy the "sg" parameter from the GRUU to the new target.
          The PBX can then use this "sg" parameter to determine which
          user agent the request should be routed to. For example,
          the first line of an INVITE request that has been re-targeted
          to the PBX for the terminal shown above would look like this:
          <figure> <artwork>
&lt;allOneLine>
INVITE sip:+12145550102@198.51.100.3;gr=urn:uuid:f81d4fae-7dec-
11d0-a765-00a0c91e6bf6;sg=00:05:03:5e:70:a6 SIP/2.0
&lt;/allOneLine>
          </artwork></figure>
        </t>
      </section>

      <section title="Temporary GRUUs" anchor="temp-gruu">
        <t>
          Temporary GRUUs are used to provide anonymity
          for the party creating and sharing the GRUU.
          Being able to correlate two temporary GRUUs as
          having originated from behind the same PBX violates
          this principle of anonymity. Consequently, rather
          than relying upon a single, invariant identifier
          for the PBX in its UA's temporary GRUUs, we define
          a mechanism whereby the SSP provides the PBX with
          sufficient information for the PBX to mint unique
          temporary GRUUs. These GRUUs have the property that
          the SSP
          can correlate them to the proper PBX, but no other
          party can do so. To achieve this goal, we use a
          slight modification of the procedure described
          in appendix A.2 of RFC 5627 <xref target="RFC5627"/>.
        </t>
        <t>
          The PBX must be able to construct a temp-gruu in a way that
          the SSP can decode.
          In order to ensure that the SSP can decode GRUUs,
          we need to standardize the algorithm for creation
          of temp-gruus at the PBX.  This allows the SSP to
          reverse the algorithm to identify
          the registration entry that corresponds to the
          GRUU.
        </t>
        <t>
          It is equally important that no party other than
          the SSP is capable of decoding a temporary GRUU,
          including other PBXes serviced by the SSP.
          To achieve this property, an SSP that supports
          temporary GRUUs MUST create and store an asymmetric key
          pair, {K_e1,K_e2}. K_e1 is kept secret by the
          SSP, while K_e2 is shared with the PBXes via provisioning.
        </t>
        <t>
          All base64 encoding discussed in the following sections MUST 
          use the character set and encoding defined in
          RFC 2045 <xref target="RFC2045"/>, except that
          any trailing "=" characters are discarded on encoding,
          and added as necessary to decode.
        </t>
        <section title="Generation of temp-gruu-cookie by the SSP"
          anchor="ssp-tgc-gen">
          <t>
            An SSP that supports temporary GRUUs 
            MUST include a "temp-gruu-cookie"
            parameter on all "bnc" Contact header fields in a
            200-class REGISTER response. This "temp-gruu-cookie"
            MUST have the following properties:
          </t>
          <t>
            <list style="numbers">
              <t>
                It can be used by the SSP to uniquely identify
                the registration to which it corresponds.
              </t>
              <t>
                It cannot be modified by the recipient to
                hijack calls intended for another PBX.
              </t>
              <t>
                It cannot be replayed at a later date to
                hijack calls intended for another PBX.
              </t>
              <t>
                It is encoded using base64. This allows the
                PBX to decode it into as compact a form as
                possible for use in its calculations.
              </t>
              <t>
                It is of a fixed length. This allows for
                extraction of it once the PBX has concatenated
                a distinguisher onto it.
              </t>
            </list>
          </t>
          <t>
            The above properties can be met using the following
            algorithm, which is non-normative. Implementors may
            chose to implement any algorithm of their choosing for
            generation of the temp-gruu-cookie, as
            long as it fulfills the five properties listed above.
          </t>
          <t><list style="hanging"><t>
            The SSP registrar maintains a counter, I.
            this counter is 48 bits long, and initialized to zero.
            This counter is persistently stored, using a
            back-end database or similar technique. When the
            SSP registrar
            creates the first temporary GRUU for a particular PBX
            and instance ID, the SSP registrar notes the current value
            of the counter, I_i, and increments the counter in the
            database.  The SSP registrar then maps I_i to the 
            "bnc" AOR template and
            instance ID using the database, a persistent hash-map
            or similar technology.  If the registration expires
            such that there are no longer any contacts with that
            particular instance ID bound to the GRUU, the SSP registrar
            removes the mapping.  Similarly, if the temporary GRUUs
            are invalidated due to a change in Call-ID, the SSP registrar
            removes the current mapping from I_i to the AOR and
            instance ID, notes the current value of the counter
            I_j, and stores a mapping from I_j to the "bnc" AOR template and
            instance ID.  Based on these rules, the hash-map will
            contain a single mapping for each "bnc" AOR template and instance ID
            for which there is a currently valid registration.
          </t></list></t>
          <t><list style="hanging"><t>
            The SSP registrar maintains a symmetric key SK_a,
            which is regenerated every time the counter rolls
            over or is is reset. When the counter rolls over or is reset,
            the SSP registrar remembers the old value of SK_a for
            a while. To generate a temp-gruu-cookie, the SSP
            registrar computes:
          <figure> <artwork>

      SA = HMAC-SHA256-80(SK_a, I_i)
      temp-gruu-cookie = base64enc(I_i || SA)

          </artwork></figure>
          </t></list></t>
        </section>
        <section title="Generation of temp-gruu by the PBX"
          anchor = "pbx-tg-gen">
        <t>
          A PBX that issues temporary GRUUs to its terminals
          MUST maintain an HMAC key, PK_a. This value is used
          to validate that incoming GRUUs were generated by
          the PBX.
        </t>
        <t>
          To generate a new temporary GRUU for use by its own
          terminals, the PBX MUST generate a random distinguisher
          value D. The length of this value is up to implementors,
          but MUST be long enough to prevent collisions among
          all the temporary GRUUs issued by the PBX. A size of
          80 bits or longer is RECOMMENDED. The PBX then 
          MUST calculate:
          <figure> <artwork>

  M    = base64dec(SSP-cookie) || D
  E    = RSA-Encrypt(K_e2, M)
  PA   = HMAC(PK_a, E)

  Temp-Gruu-userpart = "tgruu." || base64(E) || "." || base64(PA)

          </artwork></figure>
          where || denotes concatenation. "HMAC" represents
          any suitably strong HMAC algorithm; see RFC 2104
          <xref target="RFC2104"/>
          for a discussion of HMAC algorithms. One suitable
          HMAC algorithm for this purpose is HMAC-SHA256-80.
        </t>
        <t>
           Finally, the PBX adds a "gr" parameter to the temporary
           GRUU that can be used to uniquely identify the UA
           registration record to which the GRUU corresponds.
           The means of generation of the "gr" parameter are
           left to the implementor, as long as they satisfy
           the properties of a GRUU as described in 
           RFC 5627 <xref target="RFC5627"/>.
        </t>
        <t><list style="hanging"><t>
           One valid approach for generation of the "gr"
           parameter is calculation of "E" and "A" as described
           in Appendix A.2 of RFC 5627 <xref target="RFC5627"/>,
           and forming the "gr" parameter as:
          <figure> <artwork>

      gr = base64enc(E) || base64enc(A)

          </artwork></figure>
       </t></list></t>

          <t>
            Using this procedure may result in a temporary GRUU
            returned to the registering UA by the PBX that looks similar
            to this:
          <figure> <artwork>
&lt;allOneLine>
Contact: &lt;sip:line-1@10.20.1.17>
;temp-gruu="sip:tgruu.MQyaRiLEd78RtaWkcP7N8Q.5qVbsasdo2pkKw@
ssp.example.com;gr=YZGSCjKD42ccxO08pA7HwAM4XNDIlMSL0HlA"
;+sip.instance="&lt;urn:uuid:d0e2f290-104b-11df-8a39-0800200c9a66>"
;expires=3600
&lt;/allOneLine>
          </artwork></figure>
          </t>

        </section>
        <section title="Decoding of temp-gruu by the SSP">
          <t>
            When the SSP proxy receives a request in which the
            user part begins with "tgruu.", it extracts
            the remaining portion, and splits it at the
            "." character into E' and PA'. It discards
            PA'. It then computes E by performing a base64
            decode of E'. Next, it computes:
            <figure> <artwork>

  M = RSA-Decrypt(K_e1, E)

            </artwork></figure>
            The SSP proxy extracts the fixed-length
            temp-gruu-cookie information from the
            beginning of this M, and discards the remainder
            (which will be the distinguisher added by
            the PBX). It then validates this temp-gruu-cookie.
            If valid, it uses it to locate the corresponding
            PBX registration record, and routes the message
            appropriately.
          </t>
          <t><list style="hanging"><t>
            If the non-normative, exemplary algorithm
            described in <xref target="ssp-tgc-gen"/>
            is used to generate the temp-gruu-cookie,
            then this identification is performed
            by splitting the temp-gruu-cookie information
            into its 48-bit counter I and 80-bit HMAC.
            It validates that the HMAC matches the counter I,
            and then uses counter I to locate the PBX
            registration record in its map. If the counter
            has rolled over or reset, this computation
            is performed with the current and previous
            SK_a.
          </t></list></t>
        </section>
        <section title="Decoding of temp-gruu by the PBX">
          <t>
            When the PBX receives a request in which the
            user part begins with "tgruu.", it extracts
            the remaining portion, and splits it at the
            "." character into E' and PA'.
            It then computes E and PA by performing a base64
            decode of E' and PA' respectively. Next, it computes:
            <figure> <artwork>

  PAc = HMAC(PK_a, E)

            </artwork></figure>
            where HMAC is the HMAC algorithm used for the steps
            in <xref target="pbx-tg-gen"/>. If this computed value
            for PAc does not match the value of PA extracted
            from the GRUU, then the GRUU is rejected as
            invalid.
          </t>
          <t>
            The PBX then uses the value of the "gr" parameter
            to locate the UA registration to which the GRUU
            corresponds, and routes the message accordingly.
          </t>
        </section>
<!--
        <t>
          PBXes have two options for creating temporary GRUUs
          for use by its terminals.
        </t>
        <section title="Approach 1 - Self Made GRUUs">
          <t>
            If a PBX wishes to provide temporary GRUUs for
            its terminals, it may do so by producing its own
            "Self-made GRUUs" (as defined in section 4.3 of RFC 5627
            <xref target="RFC5627"/>).
            These GRUUs are produced using the PBX's own IP address
            (or domain, if it maintains one in DNS). The temporary
            GRUUs are then propagated to terminals using normal
            GRUU mechanism.
          </t>
          <t>
            The ability to produce temporary GRUUs in this fashion
            is predicated on the conditions described in section
            4.3 of RFC 5627. In particular, it requires PBX to be
            publicly routable, and willing to accept requests destined
            for its own Self-made GRUUs from sources other than the
            SSP.  If these conditions cannot be satisfied (or the PBX operator
            chooses not to satisfy them for policy reasons), then the
            PBX users will not be able to make use of temporary GRUUs.
          </t>
          <t>
            This mechanism is also predicated on the IP address for the
            PBX being relatively stable over a long period of time. This
            is generally a safe assumption to make, as frequent PBX
            IP address changes will result in intermittent connectivity
            issues and interruptions to ongoing calls.
          </t>
          <t>
            On a related note: when used with this extension, the SSP 
            will not return a temporary GRUU in the registration
            response for any contacts that include a "bnc" parameter in
            their URI.
          </t>
          <t>
            For example, using the same setup as in the "Public GRUU"
            section above, a terminal registering with the PBX
            might obtain a temp gruu by receiving a Contact header
            field that looks like:
          </t>
          <figure> <artwork>
&lt;allOneLine>
Contact: &lt;sip:line-1@10.20.1.17>;
pub-gruu="sip:ssp.example.com;bnc;gr=urn:uuid:f81d4fae-7dec-11d0-a765-
00a0c91e6bf6;sg=a0471c99573b877b";
+sip.instance="&lt;urn:uuid:d0e2f290-104b-11df-8a39-0800200c9a66>"
;expires=3600
&lt;/allOneLine>
          </artwork></figure>
        </section>

        <section title="Approach 2 - Anonymous Public GRUUs" anchor="anon-gruu">
          <t>
            If a PBX does not satisfy the criteria for producing
            its own "Self-made GRUUs," then it may create temporary
            GRUUs based on the public GRUUs it received from the
            SSP at registration time. To create Temporary GRUUs of
            this form, the PBX will add an opaque "sg" parameter to
            the public GRUU it received from the SSP, and will
            omit the user portion.
          </t>
          <t>
            Note that, because these GRUUs are temporary GRUUs,
            a unique "sg" parameter will be generated for each
            successful registration attempt. The PBX tracks the
            various "sg" values associated with each user agent, 
            and can re-target to the correct instance when the
            request arrives.
          </t>
          <t>
            For this approach to function, the SSP must be able to
            resolve a GRUU based solely on the value of its "gr"
            parameter, as the user portion of the GRUU will not
            contain an E.164 number. Further, the SSP will not
            know which actual phone number the request is destined
            for, only that it corresponds to an phone number belonging
            to the PBX.
          </t>
          <t>
            Using the same basic setup as the example for the
            public GRUU, a terminal might receive a temporary
            GRUU by getting back a Contact header field that looks
            like this:
          </t>
          <figure> <artwork>
&lt;allOneLine>
Contact: &lt;sip:line-1@10.20.1.17>;
temp-gruu="sip:ssp.example.com;gr=urn:uuid:f81d4fae-7dec-11d0-a765-
00a0c91e6bf6;sg=0UYYRV046P";+sip.instance="&lt;urn:uuid:d0e2f290-104b-
11df-8a39-0800200c9a66>";expires=3600
&lt;/allOneLine>
          </artwork></figure>
        </section>
-->

      </section>
      
    </section>

    <section title="Registration Event Package">
      <t>
        As this mechanism inherently deals with REGISTER behavior,
        it is imperative to consider its impact on the Registration
        Event Package defined by RFC 3680 <xref target="RFC3680"/>.
        In practice, there will be two main use cases for subscribing
        to registration data: learning about the overall registration
        state for the PBX, and learning about the registration state
        for a single PBX phone number.
      </t>
      <section title="PBX Aggregate Registration State" 
       anchor="pbx-reg-event">
        <t>
          If the PBX (or another interested and authorized party)
          wishes to monitor or audit the registration state for
          all of the phone numbers currently registered to that PBX,
          it can subscribe to the SIP registration event package
          at the PBX's main URI -- that is, the URI used in
          the "To" header field of the REGISTER message.
        </t>
        <t>
          The NOTIFY messages for such a subscription will contain
          a body that contains one record for each phone number
          associated with the PBX. The AORs will be in the format
          expected to be received by the SSP (e.g., 
          "sip:+12145550105@ssp.example.com"), and the Contacts
          will correspond to the mapped Contact created by the
          registration (e.g., "sip:+12145550105@98.51.100.3").
        </t>
        <t>
          In particular, the "bnc" parameter is forbidden from
          appearing in the body of a reg-event notify.
        </t>
      </section>
      <section title="Individual Phone Number Registration State"
        anchor="reg-terminal">
        <!-- 7.2.2 -->
        <t>
          OPEN ISSUE (issue #36): Exactly how GIN should handle
          this aspect of the "reg" event is still open for discussion.
          This section will be updated to reflect consensus once
          it has been determined.
        </t>
        <t>
          As described in <xref target="ssp-processing"/>, the
          SSP will generally retarget all requests addressed to
          a phone number owned by a PBX to that PBX according
          to the mapping established at registration time.
          Although policy at the SSP may override this generally
          expected behavior, proper behavior of the registration
          event package requires that all "reg" event SUBSCRIBE
          requests are processed by the PBX. As a consequence,
          the requirements on an SSP for processing registration
          event package SUBSCRIBE requests are not left to policy.
        </t>
        <t>
          If the SSP receives a SUBSCRIBE request for the registration
          event package with a Request-URI that indicates a
          contact registered via the "Bulk Number Contact" mechanism
          defined in this document, then it MUST proxy that SUBSCRIBE
          to the PBX in the same way that is would proxy an INVITE
          bound for that AOR.
        </t>
        <t>
          Defining the behavior in this way is important, since
          the reg-event subscriber is interested in finding out
          about the comprehensive list of devices associated with
          the phone number. Only the PBX will have authoritative
          access to this information.  For example, if the user has
          registered multiple terminals with differing capabilities,
          the SSP will not know about the devices or their capabilities.
          By contrast, the PBX will.
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Client-Initiated (Outbound) Connections">
      <t>
        RFC 5626 <xref target="RFC5626"/>
        -- needs analysis. Some people think it might "just work."
      </t>
    </section>

    <section title="Non-Adjacent Contact Registration (Path) and Service Route Discovery">
      <t>
        RFC 3327 <xref target="RFC3327"/> defines a means by which
        a registrar and its associated proxy can be informed of a
        route that is to be used between the proxy and the registered
        user agent. The scope of the route created by a "Path" header
        field is contact-specific; if an AOR has multiple contacts
        associated with it, the routes associated with each contact
        may be different from each other.
      </t>
      <t>
        At registration time, any proxies between the user agent and
        the registrar may add themselves to the Path. By doing so,
        they request that any requests destined to the user agent
        as a result of the associated registration include them
        as part of the Route towards the User Agent. Although the
        Path mechanism does deliver the final Path value to the
        registering UA, UAs typically ignore the value of the Path.
      </t>
      <t>
        To provide similar functionality in the opposite direction --
        that is, to establish a route for requests sent by a registering
        UA -- RFC 3608 <xref target="RFC3608"/> defines a means
        by which a UA can be informed of a route that is to be used by
        the UA to route all outbound requests associated with the
        AOR used in the registration. This information is scoped to the
        AOR within the UA, and is not specific to the Contact (or Contacts)
        in the REGISTER request.
      </t>
      <t>
        The registrar unilaterally generates the values of the service
        route using whatever local policy it wishes to apply. Although it
        is common to use the Path and/or Route information in the request
        in composing the Service-Route, registrar behavior is not constrained
        in any way that requires it to do so.
      </t>
      <t>
        In considering the interaction between these mechanisms and the
        registration of multiple AORs in a single request, implementors
        of proxies, registrars, and intermediaries must keep in mind
        the following issues, which stem from the fact that GIN effectively
        registers multiple AORs and multiple Contacts. 
      </t>
      <t>
        First, all location service records that result from expanding a
        single "bnc" Contact will necessarily share a single path. Proxies
        will be unable to make policy decisions on a contact-by-contact
        basis regarding whether to include themselves in the path. Second,
        and similarly, all AORs on the PBX that are registered with a
        common REGISTER message will be forced to share a common
        Service-Route.
      </t>
      <t>
        One interesting technique that Path and Service-Route enable
        is the inclusion of a token or cookie in the user portion of the
        Service-Route or Path entries. This token or cookie may convey
        information to proxies about the identity, capabilities, and/or
        policies associated with the user. Since this information will
        be shared among several AORs and several Contacts when multiple
        AOR registration is employed, care should be taken to ensure that
        doing so is acceptable for all AORs and all Contacts registered
        in a single REGISTER message.
      </t>
    </section>

  </section>

  <section title="Examples">
    <section title="Usage Scenario: Basic Registration">
      <t>
        This example shows the message flows for a basic bulk REGISTER
        transaction, followed by an INVITE addressed to one of the
        registered terminals. Example messages are shown after
        the sequence diagram.
      </t>


<figure> <artwork><![CDATA[
Internet                        SSP                              PBX
|                                |                                 |
|                                |(1) REGISTER                     |
|                                |Contact:<sip:198.51.100.3;bnc>   |
|                                |<--------------------------------|
|                                |                                 |
|                                |(2) 200 OK                       |
|                                |-------------------------------->|
|                                |                                 |
|(3) INVITE                      |                                 |
|sip:+12145550105@ssp.example.com|                                 |
|------------------------------->|                                 |
|                                |                                 |
|                                |(4) INVITE                       |
|                                |sip:+12145550105@198.51.100.3    |
|                                |-------------------------------->|
]]></artwork> </figure>

<figure> <artwork><![CDATA[
(1) The PBX registers with the SSP for a range of phone numbers.

REGISTER sip:ssp.example.com SIP/2.0
Via: SIP/2.0/UDP 198.51.100.3:5060;branch=z9hG4bKnashds7
Max-Forwards: 70
To: <sip:pbx@ssp.example.com>
From: <sip:pbx@ssp.example.com>;tag=a23589
Call-ID: 843817637684230@998sdasdh09
CSeq: 1826 REGISTER
Proxy-Require: gin
Require: gin
Supported: path
Contact: <sip:198.51.100.3:5060;bnc>
Expires: 7200
Content-Length: 0
]]></artwork> </figure>

<figure> <artwork><![CDATA[
(3) The SSP receives a request for a phone number assigned 
    to the PBX.

INVITE sip:+12145550105@ssp.example.com SIP/2.0
Via: SIP/2.0/UDP foo.example;branch=z9hG4bKa0bc7a0131f0ad
Max-Forwards: 69
To: <sip:2145550105@some-other-place.example.net>
From: <sip:gsmith@example.org>;tag=456248
Call-ID: f7aecbfc374d557baf72d6352e1fbcd4
CSeq: 24762 INVITE
Contact: <sip:line-1@192.0.2.178:2081>
Content-Type: application/sdp
Content-Length: ...

<sdp body here>
]]></artwork> </figure>

<figure> <artwork><![CDATA[
(4) The SSP retargets the incoming request according to the
    information received from the PBX at registration time.

INVITE sip:+12145550105@198.51.100.3 SIP/2.0
Via: SIP/2.0/UDP foo.example;branch=z9hG4bKa0bc7a0131f0ad
Via: SIP/2.0/UDP ssp.example.com;branch=z9hG4bKa45cd5c52a6dd50
Max-Forwards: 68
To: <sip:2145550105@some-other-place.example.net>
From: <sip:gsmith@example.org>;tag=456248
Call-ID: 7ca24b9679ffe9aff87036a105e30d9b
CSeq: 24762 INVITE
Contact: <sip:line-1@192.0.2.178:2081>
Content-Type: application/sdp
Content-Length: ...

<sdp body here>
]]></artwork> </figure>

    </section>
    <section title="Usage Scenario: Using Path to Control Request URI">
      <t>
        This example shows a bulk REGISTER transaction with
        the SSP making use of the "Path" header field extension
        <xref target="RFC3327"/>.
        This allows the SSP to designate a domain on the incoming
        Request URI that does not necessarily resolve to the
        PBX from when the SSP applies RFC 3263 procedures to it.
      </t>

<figure> <artwork><![CDATA[
Internet                        SSP                              PBX
|                                |                                 |
|                                |(1) REGISTER                     |
|                                |Path:<sip:pbx@198.51.100.3;lr>   |
|                                |Contact:<sip:pbx.example;bnc>    |
|                                |<--------------------------------|
|                                |                                 |
|                                |(2) 200 OK                       |
|                                |-------------------------------->|
|                                |                                 |
|(3) INVITE                      |                                 |
|sip:+12145550105@ssp.example.com|                                 |
|------------------------------->|                                 |
|                                |                                 |
|                                |(4) INVITE                       |
|                                |sip:+12145550105@pbx.example     |
|                                |Route:<sip:pbx@198.51.100.3;lr>  |
|                                |-------------------------------->|
]]></artwork> </figure>

<figure> <artwork><![CDATA[
(1) The PBX registers with the SSP for a range of phone numbers.
    It includes the URI it expects to receive in the Request-URI
    in its "Contact" header field, and includes information that
    routes to the PBX in the "Path" header field.

REGISTER sip:ssp.example.com SIP/2.0
Via: SIP/2.0/UDP 198.51.100.3:5060;branch=z9hG4bKnashds7
Max-Forwards: 70
To: <sip:pbx@ssp.example.com>
From: <sip:pbx@ssp.example.com>;tag=a23589
Call-ID: 843817637684230@998sdasdh09
CSeq: 1826 REGISTER
Proxy-Require: gin
Require: gin
Supported: path
Path: <sip:pbx@198.51.100.3:5060;lr>
Contact: <sip:pbx.example;bnc>
Expires: 7200
Content-Length: 0
]]></artwork> </figure>

<figure> <artwork><![CDATA[
(3) The SSP receives a request for a phone number assigned 
    to the PBX.

INVITE sip:+12145550105@ssp.example.com SIP/2.0
Via: SIP/2.0/UDP foo.example;branch=z9hG4bKa0bc7a0131f0ad
Max-Forwards: 69
To: <sip:2145550105@some-other-place.example.net>
From: <sip:gsmith@example.org>;tag=456248
Call-ID: f7aecbfc374d557baf72d6352e1fbcd4
CSeq: 24762 INVITE
Contact: <sip:line-1@192.0.2.178:2081>
Content-Type: application/sdp
Content-Length: ...

<sdp body here>
]]></artwork> </figure>

<figure> <artwork><![CDATA[
(4) The SSP retargets the incoming request according to the
    information received from the PBX at registration time.
    Per the normal processing associated with "Path," it
    will insert the "Path" value indicated by the PBX at
    registration time in a "Route" header field, and 
    set the request URI to the registered Contact.

INVITE sip:+12145550105@pbx.example SIP/2.0
Via: SIP/2.0/UDP foo.example;branch=z9hG4bKa0bc7a0131f0ad
Via: SIP/2.0/UDP ssp.example.com;branch=z9hG4bKa45cd5c52a6dd50
Route: <sip:pbx@198.51.100.3:5060;lr>
Max-Forwards: 68
To: <sip:2145550105@some-other-place.example.net>
From: <sip:gsmith@example.org>;tag=456248
Call-ID: 7ca24b9679ffe9aff87036a105e30d9b
CSeq: 24762 INVITE
Contact: <sip:line-1@192.0.2.178:2081>
Content-Type: application/sdp
Content-Length: ...

<sdp body here>
]]></artwork> </figure>

    </section>
  </section>

  <section title="Requirements Analysis">
    <t>
      The document "Requirements for multiple address of record
      (AOR) reachability information in the Session Initiation
      Protocol (SIP)" <xref target="I-D.ietf-martini-reqs"/>
      contains a list of requirements and desired properties for a
      mechanism to register multiple AORs with a single SIP
      transaction.  This section evaluates those requirements against
      the mechanism described in this document.
    </t>
    <t>REQ1 - The mechanism MUST allow a SIP-PBX to enter into a trunking arrangement with an SSP whereby the two parties have agreed on a set of telephone numbers deemed to have been assigned to the SIP-PBX.</t>
    <t><list style='empty'><t>The requirement is satisfied.</t></list></t>

    <t>REQ2 - The mechanism MUST allow a set of assigned telephone numbers to comprise E.164 numbers, which can be in contiguous ranges, discrete, or in any combination of the two.</t>
    <t><list style='empty'><t>The requirement is satisfied; the DIDs associated with a registration is established by bilateral agreement between the SSP and the PBX, and is not part of the mechanism described in this document.</t></list></t>

    <t>REQ3 - The mechanism MUST allow a SIP-PBX to register reachability information with its SSP, in order to enable the SSP to route to the SIP-PBX inbound requests targeted at assigned telephone numbers.</t>
    <t><list style='empty'><t>The requirement is satisfied.</t></list></t>

    <t>REQ4 - The mechanism MUST NOT prevent UAs attached to a SIP-PBX registering with the SIP-PBX on behalf of AORs based on assigned telephone numbers in order to receive requests targeted at those telephone numbers, without needing to involve the SSP in the registration process.</t>
    <t><list style='empty'><t>The requirement is satisfied; in the presumed architecture, PBX terminals register with the PBX, an require no interaction with the SSP.</t></list></t>

    <t>REQ5 - The mechanism MUST allow a SIP-PBX to handle internally requests originating at its own UAs and targeted at its assigned telephone numbers, without routing those requests to the SSP.</t>
    <t><list style='empty'><t>The requirement is satisfied; PBXes may recognize their own DID and their own GRUUs, and perform on-PBX routing without sending the requests to the SSP.</t></list></t>

    <t>REQ6 - The mechanism MUST allow a SIP-PBX to receive requests to its assigned telephone numbers originating outside the SIP-PBX and arriving via the SSP, so that the PBX can route those requests onwards to its UAs, as it would for internal requests to those telephone numbers.</t>
    <t><list style='empty'><t>The requirement is satisfied</t></list></t>

    <t>REQ7 - The mechanism MUST provide a means whereby a SIP-PBX knows which of its assigned telephone numbers an inbound request from its SSP is targeted at.</t>
    <t><list style='empty'><t>The requirement is satisfied. For ordinary calls and calls using Public GRUUs, the DID is indicated in the user portion of the Request-URI. For calls using Temp GRUUs constructed with the mechanism described in <xref target="temp-gruu"/>, the "gr" parameter provides a correlation token the PBX can use to identify which terminal the call should be routed to.</t></list></t>

    <t>REQ8 - The mechanism MUST provide a means of avoiding problems due to one side using the mechanism and the other side not.</t>
    <t><list style='empty'><t>The requirement is satisfied through the 'gin' option tag and the 'bnc' Contact parameter.</t></list></t>

    <t>REQ9 - The mechanism MUST observe SIP backwards compatibility principles.</t>
    <t><list style='empty'><t>The requirement is satisfied through the 'gin' option tag.</t></list></t>

    <t>REQ10 - The mechanism MUST work in the presence of intermediate SIP entities on the SSP side of the SIP-PBX-to-SSP interface (i.e., between the SIP-PBX and the SSP's domain proxy), where those intermediate SIP entities need to be on the path of inbound requests to the PBX.</t>
    <t><list style='empty'><t>The requirement is satisfied through the use of the Path mechanism defined in RFC 3327 <xref target="RFC3327"/> </t></list></t>

    <t>REQ11 - The mechanism MUST work when a SIP-PBX obtains its IP address dynamically.</t>
    <t><list style='empty'><t>The requirement is satisfied by allowing the PBX to use an IP address in the Bulk Number Contact URI contained in a REGISTER Contact header field.</t></list></t>

    <t>REQ12 - The mechanism MUST work without requiring the SIP-PBX to have a domain name or the ability to publish its domain name in the DNS.</t>
    <t><list style='empty'><t>The requirement is satisfied by allowing the PBX to use an IP address in the Bulk Number Contact URI contained in a REGISTER Contact header field.</t></list></t>

    <t>REQ13 - For a given SIP-PBX and its SSP, there MUST be no impact on other domains, which are expected to be able to use normal RFC 3263 procedures to route requests, including requests needing to be routed via the SSP in order to reach the SIP-PBX.</t>
    <t><list style='empty'><t>The requirement is satisfied by allowing the domain name in the Request URI used by external entities to resolve to the SSP's servers via normal RFC 3263 resolution procedures.</t></list></t>

    <t>REQ14 - The mechanism MUST be able to operate over a transport that provides integrity protection and confidentiality.</t>
    <t><list style='empty'><t>The requirement is satisfied; nothing in the proposed mechanism prevent the use of TLS between the SSP and the PBX.</t></list></t>

    <t>REQ15 - The mechanism MUST support authentication of the SIP-PBX by the SSP and vice versa.</t>
    <t><list style='empty'><t>The requirement is satisfied; PBXes may employ either SIP digest authentication or mutually-authenticated TLS for authentication purposes.</t></list></t>

    <t>REQ16 - The mechanism MUST allow the SIP-PBX to provide its UAs with public or temporary Globally Routable UA URIs (GRUUs) <xref target="RFC5627"/>.</t>
    <t><list style='empty'><t>The requirement is satisfied via the mechanisms detailed in <xref target="gruu"/>.</t></list></t>

    <t>REQ17 - The mechanism MUST NOT preclude the ability of the SIP-PBX to route on-PBX requests directly, without hair-pinning the signaling through the SSP.</t>
    <t><list style='empty'><t>The requirement is satisfied; PBXes may recognize their own DID and their own GRUUs, and perform on-PBX routing without sending the requests to the SSP. (Note that this requirement duplicates REQ5, and will probably be removed in a future version of the requirements document.)</t></list></t>

    <t>REQ18 - The mechanism MUST work over any existing transport specified for SIP, including UDP.</t>
    <t><list style='empty'><t>The requirement is satisfied to the extent that UDP can be used for REGISTER requests in general. The application of certain extensions and/or network topologies may exceed UDP MTU sizes, but such issues arise both with and without the mechanism described in this document. This document does not exacerbate such issues.</t></list></t>

    <t>DES1 - The mechanism SHOULD allow an SSP to exploit its mechanisms for providing SIP service to ordinary subscribers in order to provide a SIP trunking service to SIP-PBXes.</t>
    <t><list style='empty'><t>The desired property is satisfied; the routing mechanism described in this document is identical to the routing performed for singly-registered AORs.</t></list></t>

    <t>DES2 - The mechanism SHOULD scale to SIP-PBX's of several thousand assigned telephone numbers.</t>
    <t><list style='empty'><t>The desired property is satisfied; nothing in this document precludes DID pools of arbitrary size.</t></list></t>

    <t>DES3 - The mechanism SHOULD scale to support several thousand SIP-PBX's on a single SSP.</t>
    <t><list style='empty'><t>The desired property is satisfied; nothing in this document precludes an arbitrary number of PBXes from attaching to a single SSP.</t></list></t>

    <t>DES4 - The mechanism SHOULD require relatively modest changes to a substantial population of existing SSP and SIP-PBX implementations, in order to encourage a fast market adoption of the standardized mechanism.</t>
    <t><list style='empty'><t>The desired property is difficult to evaluate in the context of any solution. The mechanism proposed in this document uses the REGISTER method, which is the method preferred by many existing PBX deployments. The handling of request routing logic is nearly identical to that of RFC 3261 proxy/registrars, allowing implementors to leverage existing proxy/registrar code.</t></list></t>
  </section>

  <section title="IANA Considerations">
    <t>
      This document registers a new SIP option tag to indicate support
      for the mechanism it defines, plus two new SIP URI parameters.
    </t>
    <section title="New SIP Option Tag">
      <t> This section defines a new SIP option tag per the guidelines
      in Section 27.1 of RFC 3261<xref target="RFC3261"/>.

        <list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="Name:">gin</t>
          <t hangText="Description:"> This option tag is used to identify
          the extension that provides Registration for Multiple Phone
          Numbers in SIP. When present in a Require or Proxy-Require
          header field of a REGISTER request, it indicates that support
          for this extension is required of registrars and proxies,
          respectively, that are a party to the registration transaction.
          </t>
          <t hangText="Reference:">RFCXXXX (this document)</t>
        </list>
      </t>
    </section>
    <section title="New SIP URI Parameters">
      <t>
        This specification defines two new SIP URI parameters, as per the
        registry created by RFC 3969 <xref target="RFC3969"/>.
      </t>
      <section title="'bnc' SIP URI paramter">
        <t>
        <list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="Parameter Name:">bnc</t>
          <t hangText="Predefined Values:">No (no values are allowed)</t>
          <t hangText="Reference:">RFCXXXX (this document)</t>
        </list>
        </t>
      </section>
      <section title="'sg' SIP URI paramter">
        <t>
        <list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="Parameter Name:">sg</t>
          <t hangText="Predefined Values:">No</t>
          <t hangText="Reference:">RFCXXXX (this document)</t>
        </list>
        </t>
      </section>
      <section title="'autouser' SIP URI paramter">
        <t>
        <list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="Parameter Name:">autouser</t>
          <t hangText="Predefined Values:">Yes ('true' and 'false')</t>
          <t hangText="Reference:">RFCXXXX (this document)</t>
        </list>
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section title="New SIP Header Field Parameter">
      <t> This section defines a new SIP header field parameter
      per the registry created by RFC3968 <xref target="RFC3968"/>.
      </t>
      <t>
        <list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="Header field:">Contact</t>
          <t hangText="Parameter name:">temp-gruu-cookie</t>
          <t hangText="Predefined values:">none</t>
          <t hangText="Reference:">RFCXXXX (this document)</t>
        </list>
      </t>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section title="Security Considerations">
    <t>
      There are certainly security implications associated with the
      mechanisms described in this document, mostly dealing with
      the unprecedented semantic inclusion of multiple AORs in a
      single REGISTER request. This section will be formulated
      following an analysis of the security impact of GIN on Path,
      Service-Route, and Outbound.
    </t>
  </section>
  <section title="Acknowledgements">
    <t>
      Thanks to John Elwell for his requirements analysis of the
      mechanism described in this document, and to Dean Willis for
      his analysis of the interaction between this mechanism and
      the Path and Service-Route extensions. Thanks to Eric
      Rescorla, whose text in the appendix of RFC5627 was lifted directly to
      provide substantial portions of <xref target="temp-gruu"/>.
    </t>
  </section>

</middle>

<back>

  <references title='Normative References'>
    &rfc2045;
    &rfc2104;
    &rfc2119;
    &rfc3261;
    &rfc3263;
    &rfc3968;
    &rfc3969;
  </references>

  <references title='Informative References'>
    &draft-ietf-martini-reqs;
    &rfc3327;
    &rfc3608;
    &rfc3680;
    &rfc5626;
    &rfc5627;
  </references>
</back>
</rfc>
