<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<rfc category="info" docName="draft-ietf-bmwg-2544-as-04" ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="RFC 2544 AS">RFC 2544 Applicability Statement: Use on
    Production Networks Considered Harmful</title>

    <author fullname="Scott Bradner" initials="S." surname="Bradner">
      <organization>Harvard University</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>29 Oxford St.</street>

          <city>Cambridge</city>

          <region>MA</region>

          <code>02138</code>

          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>

        <phone>+1 617 495 3864</phone>

        <facsimile></facsimile>

        <email>sob@harvard.edu</email>

        <uri>http://www.sobco.com</uri>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Kevin Dubray" initials="K." surname="Dubray">
      <organization>Juniper Networks</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>

          <city></city>

          <region></region>

          <code></code>

          <country></country>
        </postal>

        <phone></phone>

        <facsimile></facsimile>

        <email>kdubray@juniper.net</email>

        <uri></uri>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Jim McQuaid" initials="J." surname="McQuaid">
      <organization>Turnip Video</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>6 Cobbleridge Court</street>

          <city>Durham</city>

          <region>North Carolina</region>

          <code>27713</code>

          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>

        <phone>+1 919-619-3220</phone>

        <facsimile></facsimile>

        <email>jim@turnipvideo.com</email>

        <uri>www.turnipvideo.com</uri>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Al Morton" initials="A." surname="Morton">
      <organization>AT&amp;T Labs</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>200 Laurel Avenue South</street>

          <city>Middletown,</city>

          <region>NJ</region>

          <code>07748</code>

          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>

        <phone>+1 732 420 1571</phone>

        <facsimile>+1 732 368 1192</facsimile>

        <email>acmorton@att.com</email>

        <uri>http://home.comcast.net/~acmacm/</uri>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date day="12" month="June" year="2012" />

    <abstract>
      <t>Benchmarking Methodology Working Group (BMWG) has been developing key
      performance metrics and laboratory test methods since 1990, and
      continues this work at present. Recent application of the methods beyond
      their intended scope is cause for concern. The methods described in RFC
      2544, where overload is a possible outcome, would no doubt be harmful to
      user traffic performance on a production network. This memo clarifies
      the scope of RFC 2544 and other benchmarking work for the IETF
      community.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>This memo clarifies the scope of RFC 2544 <xref
      target="RFC2544"></xref>, which discusses and defines several tests that
      may be used to characterize the performance of a network interconnecting
      device, and other benchmarking work for the IETF community.</t>

      <t>Benchmarking Methodologies (beginning with <xref
      target="RFC2544"></xref>) have always relied on test conditions that can
      only be produced and replicated reliably in the laboratory. Thus it was
      unfortunate to find that this foundation methodology was being cited in
      several unintended specifications and products performing applications
      such as:</t>

      <t><list style="numbers">
          <t>Validation of telecommunication service configuration, such as
          the Committed Information Rate (CIR).</t>

          <t>Validation of performance metrics in a telecommunication Service
          Level Agreement (SLA), such as frame loss and latency.</t>

          <t>Telecommunication service activation testing, where traffic that
          shares network resources with the test might be adversely
          affected.</t>
        </list>Above, we distinguish "telecommunication service" (where a
      network service provider contracts with a customer to transfer
      information between specified interfaces at different geographic
      locations) from the generic term "service". Below, we use the adjective
      "production" to refer to networks carrying live user traffic. <xref
      target="RFC2544"></xref> used the term "real-world" to refer to
      production networks and to differentiate them from test networks.</t>

      <t>Although RFC 2544 is held up as the standard reference for such
      testing, we believe that the actual methods used vary from RFC 2544 in
      significant ways. Since the only citation is to RFC 2544, the
      modifications are opaque to the standards community and to users in
      general (an undesirable situation). There is risk of harm to user
      traffic from applying the test traffic and methods described in <xref
      target="RFC2544"></xref> on a production network, because overload in
      shared resources is a possible outcome.</t>

      <t>To directly address this situation, the past and present Chairs of
      the IETF Benchmarking Methodology Working Group (BMWG) have prepared
      this Applicability Statement for RFC 2544.</t>

      <section title="Requirements Language">
        <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
        "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
        document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
        target="RFC2119">RFC 2119</xref>.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Scope and Goals">
      <t>This memo clarifies the scope of <xref target="RFC2544"></xref>, with
      the goal to provide guidance to the community on its applicability,
      which is limited to laboratory testing.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="The Concept of an Isolated Test Environment">
      <t>An Isolated Test Environment (ITE) used with <xref
      target="RFC2544"></xref> methods (as illustrated in Figures 1 through 3
      of <xref target="RFC2544"></xref>) has the ability to:<list
          style="symbols">
          <t>contain the test streams to paths within the desired set-up</t>

          <t>prevent non-test traffic from traversing the test set-up</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>These features allow unfettered experimentation, while at the same
      time protecting lab equipment management/control LANs and other
      production networks from the unwanted effects of the test traffic.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Why RFC 2544 Methods are intended for ITE">
      <t>The following sections discuss some of the reasons why RFC 2544 <xref
      target="RFC2544"></xref> methods were intended only for isolated
      laboratory use, and the difficulties of applying these methods outside
      the lab environment.</t>

      <section title="Experimental Control and Accuracy">
        <t>All of the tests described in RFC 2544 require that the tester and
        device under test are the only devices on the networks that are
        transmitting data. The presence of other unwanted traffic on the
        network would mean that the specified test conditions have not been
        achieved.</t>

        <t>If any unwanted traffic appears and the amount varies over time,
        the repeatability of any test result will likely depend to some degree
        on the unwanted traffic.</t>

        <t>The presence of unwanted or unknown traffic makes accurate,
        repeatable, and consistent measurements of the performance of the
        device under test very unlikely, since the complete details of test
        conditions will not be reported.</t>

        <t>For example, the RFC 2544 Throughput Test attempts to characterize
        a maximum reliable load, thus there will be testing above the maximum
        that causes packet/frame loss. Any other sources of traffic on the
        network will cause packet loss to occur at a tester data rate lower
        than the rate that would be achieved without the extra traffic.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Containing Damage">
        <t>RFC 2544 methods, specifically to determine Throughput as defined
        in <xref target="RFC1242"></xref> and other benchmarks, may overload
        the resources of the device under test, and may cause failure modes in
        the device under test. Since failures can become the root cause of
        more wide-spread failure, it is clearly desirable to contain all test
        traffic within the ITE.</t>

        <t>In addition, such testing can have a negative effect on any traffic
        that shares resources with the test stream(s) since, in most cases,
        the traffic load will be close to the capacity of the network
        links.</t>

        <t>Appendix C.2.2 of <xref target="RFC2544"></xref> (as adjusted by
        errata) gives the private IPv4 address range for testing:</t>

        <t>"...The network addresses 198.18.0.0 through 198.19.255.255 have
        been assigned to the BMWG by the IANA for this purpose. This
        assignment was made to minimize the chance of conflict in case a
        testing device were to be accidentally connected to part of the
        Internet. The specific use of the addresses is detailed below."</t>

        <t>In other words, devices operating on the Internet may be configured
        to discard any traffic they observe in this address range, as it is
        intended for laboratory ITE use only. Thus, testers using the assigned
        testing address ranges MUST NOT be connected to the Internet.</t>

        <t>We note that a range of IPv6 addresses has been assigned to BMWG
        for laboratory test purposes, in <xref target="RFC5180"></xref>. Also,
        the strong statements in the Security Considerations Section of this
        memo make the scope even more clear; this is now a standard fixture of
        all BMWG memos.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Advisory on RFC 2544 Methods in Production Networks">
      <t>The tests in <xref target="RFC2544"></xref> were designed to measure
      the performance of network devices, not of networks, and certainly not
      production networks carrying user traffic on shared resources. There
      will be unanticipated difficulties when applying these methods outside
      the lab environment.</t>

      <t>Operating test equipment on production networks according to the
      methods described in <xref target="RFC2544"></xref>, where overload is a
      possible outcome, would no doubt be harmful to user traffic performance.
      These tests MUST NOT be used on production networks and as discussed
      above, the tests will never produce a reliable or accurate benchmarking
      result on a production network.</t>

      <t><xref target="RFC2544"></xref> methods have never been validated on a
      network path, even when that path is not part of a production network
      and carrying no other traffic. It is unknown whether the tests can be
      used to measure valid and reliable performance of a multi-device,
      multi-network path. It is possible that some of the tests may prove
      valid in some path scenarios, but that work has not been done or has not
      been shared with the IETF community. Thus, such testing is
      contra-indicated by the BMWG.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="What to do without RFC 2544?">
      <t>The IETF has addressed the problem of production network performance
      measurement by chartering a different working group: IP Performance
      Metrics (IPPM). This working group has developed a set of standard
      metrics to assess the quality, performance, and reliability of Internet
      packet transfer services. These metrics can be measured by network
      operators, end users, or independent testing groups. We note that some
      IPPM metrics differ from RFC 2544 metrics with similar names, and there
      is likely to be confusion if the details are ignored.</t>

      <t>IPPM has not yet standardized methods for raw capacity measurement of
      Internet paths. Such testing needs to adequately consider the strong
      possibility for degradation to any other traffic that may be present due
      to congestion. There are no specific methods proposed for activation of
      a packet transfer service in IPPM.</t>

      <t>Other standards may help to fill gaps in telecommunication service
      testing. For example, the IETF has many standards intended to assist
      with network operation, administration and maintenance (OAM), and ITU-T
      Study Group 12 has a recommendation on service activation test
      methodology <xref target="Y.1564"></xref>.</t>

      <t>The world will not spin off axis while waiting for appropriate and
      standardized methods to emerge from the consensus process.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Security Considerations">
      <t>This Applicability Statement intends to help preserve the security of
      the Internet by clarifying that the scope of <xref
      target="RFC2544"></xref> and other BMWG memos are all limited to testing
      in a laboratory ITE, thus avoiding accidental Denial of Service attacks
      or congestion due to high traffic volume test streams.</t>

      <t>All Benchmarking activities are limited to technology
      characterization using controlled stimuli in a laboratory environment,
      with dedicated address space and the other constraints <xref
      target="RFC2544"></xref>.</t>

      <t>The benchmarking network topology will be an independent test setup
      and MUST NOT be connected to devices that may forward the test traffic
      into a production network, or misroute traffic to the test management
      network.</t>

      <t>Further, benchmarking is performed on a "black-box" basis, relying
      solely on measurements observable external to the device under
      test/system under test (DUT/SUT).</t>

      <t>Special capabilities SHOULD NOT exist in the DUT/SUT specifically for
      benchmarking purposes. Any implications for network security arising
      from the DUT/SUT SHOULD be identical in the lab and in production
      networks.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>This memo makes no requests of IANA.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>Thanks to Matt Zekauskas, Bill Cerveny, Barry Constantine, Curtis
      Villamizar, and David Newman for reading and suggesting improvements to
      this memo.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.2544'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.1242'?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119"?>

      <?rfc ?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5180"?>

      <?rfc ?>

      <?rfc ?>

      <?rfc ?>

      <?rfc ?>

      <?rfc ?>

      <?rfc ?>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <reference anchor="Y.1564">
        <front>
          <title>Ethernet Service Activation Test Methodology</title>

          <author fullname="" surname="ITU-T Recommendation Y.1564">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date month="March" year="2011" />
        </front>
      </reference>

      <?rfc ?>
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>