<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!-- 
# vim sw=4:sta:
-->
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<!-- give errors regarding ID-nits and DTD validation -->
<!-- control the table of contents (ToC) -->
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<!-- generate a ToC -->
<!--<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>-->
<!-- the number of levels of subsections in ToC. default: 3 -->
<!-- control references -->
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<!-- use symbolic references tags, i.e, [RFC2119] instead of [1] -->
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<!-- sort the reference entries alphabetically -->
<!-- control vertical white space 
     (using these PIs as follows is recommended by the RFC Editor) -->
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<!-- do not start each main section on a new page -->
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<!-- keep one blank line between list items -->
<!-- end of list of popular I-D processing instructions -->
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "C:/Documents%20and%20Settings/kmichiel/My%20Documents/xml2rfc/xml2rfc/dtd/rfc2629.dtd">
<rfc category="info" docName="draft-ietf-bmwg-igp-dataplane-conv-term-19"
     ipr="pre5378Trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="IGP Convergence Benchmark Terminology">Terminology for
    Benchmarking Link-State IGP Data Plane Route Convergence</title>

    <author fullname="Scott Poretsky" initials="S" surname="Poretsky">
      <organization>Allot Communications</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>67 South Bedford Street, Suite 400</street>

          <city>Burlington</city>

          <region>MA</region>

          <code>01803</code>

          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>

        <phone>+ 1 508 309 2179</phone>

        <email>sporetsky@allot.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Brent Imhoff" initials="B" surname="Imhoff">
      <organization>Juniper Networks</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>1194 North Mathilda Ave</street>

          <city>Sunnyvale</city>

          <region>CA</region>

          <code>94089</code>

          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>

        <phone>+ 1 314 378 2571</phone>

        <email>bimhoff@planetspork.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Kris Michielsen" initials="K" surname="Michielsen">
      <organization>Cisco Systems</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>6A De Kleetlaan</street>

          <city>Diegem</city>

          <region>BRABANT</region>

          <code>1831</code>

          <country>Belgium</country>
        </postal>

        <email>kmichiel@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date month="October" year="2009" />

    <area>Benchmarking Working Group</area>

    <abstract>
      <t>This document describes the terminology for benchmarking Interior
      Gateway Protocol (IGP) Route Convergence. The terminology is to be used
      for benchmarking IGP convergence time through externally observable
      (black box) data plane measurements. The terminology can be applied to
      any link-state IGP, such as ISIS and OSPF.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction and Scope">
      <t>This draft describes the terminology for benchmarking Link-State
      Interior Gateway Protocol (IGP) Convergence. The motivation and
      applicability for this benchmarking is provided in <xref
      target="Po09a"></xref>. The methodology to be used for this benchmarking
      is described in <xref target="Po09m"></xref>. The purpose of this
      document is to introduce new terms required to complete execution of the
      IGP Route Methodology <xref target="Po09m"></xref>.</t>

      <t>IGP convergence time is measured on the data plane at the Tester by
      observing packet loss through the DUT. The methodology and terminology
      to be used for benchmarking IGP Convergence can be applied to IPv4 and
      IPv6 traffic and link-state IGPs such as ISIS <xref
      target="Ca90"></xref><xref target="Ho08"></xref>, OSPF <xref
      target="Mo98"></xref><xref target="Co08"></xref>, and others.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Existing Definitions">
      <t>This document uses existing terminology defined in other BMWG work.
      Examples include, but are not limited to:</t>

      <texttable style="none" suppress-title="true">
        <ttcol></ttcol>

        <ttcol></ttcol>

        <c>Frame Loss Rate</c>

        <c>[Ref.<xref target="Br91"></xref>, section 3.6]</c>

        <c>Throughput</c>

        <c>[Ref.<xref target="Br91"></xref>, section 3.17]</c>

        <c>Offered Load</c>

        <c>[Ref.<xref target="Ma98"></xref>, section 3.5.2]</c>

        <c>Forwarding Rate</c>

        <c>[Ref.<xref target="Ma98"></xref>, section 3.6.1]</c>

        <c>Device Under Test (DUT)</c>

        <c>[Ref.<xref target="Ma98"></xref>, section 3.1.1]</c>

        <c>System Under Test (SUT)</c>

        <c>[Ref.<xref target="Ma98"></xref>, section 3.1.2]</c>

        <c>Out-of-order Packet</c>

        <c>[Ref.<xref target="Po06"></xref>, section 3.3.2]</c>

        <c>Duplicate Packet</c>

        <c>[Ref.<xref target="Po06"></xref>, section 3.3.3]</c>

        <c>Packet Reordering</c>

        <c>[Ref.<xref target="Mo06"></xref>, section 3.3]</c>

        <c>Stream</c>

        <c>[Ref.<xref target="Po06"></xref>, section 3.3.2]</c>

        <c>Forwarding Delay</c>

        <c>[Ref.<xref target="Po06"></xref>, section 3.2.4]</c>

        <c>Loss Period</c>

        <c>[Ref.<xref target="Ko02"></xref>, section 4]</c>
      </texttable>

      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
      document are to be interpreted as described in BCP 14, RFC 2119 <xref
      target="Br97"></xref>. RFC 2119 defines the use of these key words to
      help make the intent of standards track documents as clear as possible.
      While this document uses these keywords, this document is not a
      standards track document.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Term Definitions">
      <section title="Convergence Types">
        <section title="Route Convergence">
          <t>Definition:</t>

          <t>The process of updating all components of the router, including
          the Routing Information Base (RIB) and Forwarding Information Base
          (FIB), along with software and hardware tables, with the most recent
          route change(s) such that forwarding for a route entry is successful
          on the Next-Best Egress Interface.</t>

          <t>Discussion:</t>

          <t>Route Convergence MUST occur after a Convergence Event. Route
          Convergence can be observed externally by the rerouting of data
          traffic for a destination matching a route entry to the Next-best
          Egress Interface. Completion of Route Convergence may or may not be
          sustained over time.</t>

          <t>Measurement Units: N/A</t>

          <t>Issues: None</t>

          <t>See Also:</t>

          <t>Network Convergence, Full Convergence, Convergence Event</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Full Convergence">
          <t>Definition:</t>

          <t>Route Convergence for all routes in the FIB.</t>

          <t>Discussion:</t>

          <t>Full Convergence MUST occur after a Convergence Event. Full
          Convergence can be observed externally by the rerouting of data
          traffic to destinations matching all route entries to the Next-best
          Egress Interface. Completion of Full Convergence is externally
          observable from the data plane when the Forwarding Rate of the data
          plane traffic on the Next-Best Egress Interface equals the Offered
          Load.</t>

          <t>Completion of Full Convergence may or may not be sustained over
          time.</t>

          <t>Measurement Units: N/A</t>

          <t>Issues: None</t>

          <t>See Also:</t>

          <t>Network Convergence, Route Convergence, Convergence Event, Full
          Convergence Time, Convergence Recovery Instant</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Network Convergence  ">
          <t>Definition:</t>

          <t>Full Convergence in all routers throughout the network.</t>

          <t>Discussion:</t>

          <t>Network Convergence includes all Route Convergence operations for
          all routers in the network following a Convergence Event.</t>

          <t>Completion of Network Convergence can be observed by recovery of
          the network Forwarding Rate to equal the Offered Load, with no Stale
          Forwarding, and no Blenders <xref target="Ca01"></xref><xref
          target="Ci03"></xref>.</t>

          <t>Completion of Network Convergence may or may not be sustained
          over time.</t>

          <t>Measurement Units: N/A</t>

          <t>Issues: None</t>

          <t>See Also:</t>

          <t>Route Convergence, Full Convergence, Stale Forwarding</t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section title="Instants">
        <section title="Traffic Start Instant">
          <t>Definition:</t>

          <t>The time instant the Tester sends out the first data packet to
          the DUT.</t>

          <t>Discussion:</t>

          <t>If using the Loss-Derived Method or the Route-Specific
          Loss-Derived Method to benchmark IGP convergence time, and the
          applied Convergence Event does not cause instantaneous traffic loss
          for all routes at the Convergence Event Instant then the Tester
          SHOULD collect a timestamp on the Traffic Start Instant in order to
          measure the period of time between the Traffic Start Instant and
          Convergence Event Instant.</t>

          <t>Measurement Units:</t>

          <t>hh:mm:ss:nnn:uuu, where 'nnn' is milliseconds and 'uuu' is
          microseconds.</t>

          <t>Issues: None</t>

          <t>See Also:</t>

          <t>Convergence Event Instant, Route-Specific Convergence Time,
          Loss-Derived Convergence Time.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Convergence Event Instant">
          <t>Definition:</t>

          <t>The time instant that a Convergence Event occurs.</t>

          <t>Discussion:</t>

          <t>If the Convergence Event causes instantaneous traffic loss on the
          Preferred Egress Interface, the Convergence Event Instant is
          observable from the data plane as the instant that the DUT begins to
          exhibit packet loss.</t>

          <t>The Tester SHOULD collect a timestamp on the Convergence Event
          Instant if it is not observable from the data plane.</t>

          <t>Measurement Units:</t>

          <t>hh:mm:ss:nnn:uuu, where 'nnn' is milliseconds and 'uuu' is
          microseconds.</t>

          <t>Issues: None</t>

          <t>See Also: Convergence Event</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Convergence Recovery Instant">
          <t>Definition:</t>

          <t>The time instant that Full Convergence has completed.</t>

          <t>Discussion:</t>

          <t>The Full Convergence completed state MUST be maintained for an
          interval of duration equal to the Sustained Convergence Validation
          Time in order to validate the Convergence Recovery Instant.</t>

          <t>The Convergence Recovery Instant is observable from the data
          plane as the instant the DUT forwards traffic to all destinations
          over the Next-Best Egress Interface.</t>

          <t>When using the Rate-Derived Method, the Convergence Recovery
          Instant falls within the Packet Sampling Interval preceding the
          first interval where the observed Forwarding Rate on the Next-Best
          Egress Interface equals the Offered Load.</t>

          <t>Measurement Units:</t>

          <t>hh:mm:ss:nnn:uuu, where 'nnn' is milliseconds and 'uuu' is
          microseconds.</t>

          <t>Issues: None</t>

          <t>See Also:</t>

          <t>Sustained Convergence Validation Time, Full Convergence</t>
        </section>

        <section title="First Route Convergence Instant">
          <t>Definition:</t>

          <t>The time instant the first route entry completes Route
          Convergence following a Convergence Event</t>

          <t>Discussion:</t>

          <t>Any route may be the first to complete Route Convergence. The
          First Route Convergence Instant is observable from the data plane as
          the instant that the first packet is received from the Next-Best
          Egress Interface.</t>

          <t>Measurement Units:</t>

          <t>hh:mm:ss:nnn:uuu, where 'nnn' is milliseconds and 'uuu' is
          microseconds.</t>

          <t>Issues: None</t>

          <t>See Also: Route Convergence</t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section title="Transitions">
        <section title="Convergence Event Transition">
          <t>Definition:</t>

          <t>A time interval following a Convergence Event in which Forwarding
          Rate on the Preferred Egress Interface gradually reduces to
          zero.</t>

          <t>Discussion:</t>

          <t>The Forwarding Rate during a Convergence Event Transition may not
          decrease linearly.</t>

          <t>The Forwarding Rate observed on all DUT egress interfaces may or
          may not decrease to zero.</t>

          <t>The Offered Load, the number of routes, and the Packet Sampling
          Interval influence the observations of the Convergence Event
          Transition using the Rate-Derived Method. This is further discussed
          with the term "Rate-Derived Method".</t>

          <t>Measurement Units: seconds</t>

          <t>Issues: None</t>

          <t>See Also:</t>

          <t>Convergence Event, Rate-Derived Method</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Convergence Recovery Transition">
          <t>Definition:</t>

          <t>A time interval following the First Route Convergence Instant in
          which Forwarding Rate on the Next-Best Egress Interface gradually
          increases to equal the Offered Load.</t>

          <t>Discussion:</t>

          <t>The Forwarding Rate observed during a Convergence Recovery
          Transition may not increase linearly.</t>

          <t>The Offered Load, the number of routes, and the Packet Sampling
          Interval influence the observations of the Convergence Recovery
          Transition using the Rate-Derived Method. This is further discussed
          with the term "Rate-Derived Method".</t>

          <t>Measurement Units: seconds</t>

          <t>Issues: None</t>

          <t>See Also:</t>

          <t>Full Convergence,First Route Convergence Instant, Rate-Derived
          Method</t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section title="Interfaces ">
        <section title="Local Interface">
          <t>Definition:</t>

          <t>An interface on the DUT.</t>

          <t>Discussion:</t>

          <t>A failure of the Local Interface indicates that the failure
          occurred directly on the DUT.</t>

          <t>Measurement Units: N/A</t>

          <t>Issues: None</t>

          <t>See Also: Remote Interface</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Remote Interface">
          <t>Definition:</t>

          <t>An interface on a neighboring router that is not directly
          connected to any interface on the DUT.</t>

          <t>Discussion:</t>

          <t>A failure of a Remote Interface indicates that the failure
          occurred on a neighbor router's interface that is not directly
          connected to the DUT.</t>

          <t>Measurement Units: N/A</t>

          <t>Issues: None</t>

          <t>See Also: Local Interface</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Preferred Egress Interface">
          <t>Definition:</t>

          <t>The outbound interface from the DUT for traffic routed to the
          preferred next-hop.</t>

          <t>Discussion:</t>

          <t>The Preferred Egress Interface is the egress interface prior to a
          Convergence Event.</t>

          <t>Measurement Units: N/A</t>

          <t>Issues: None</t>

          <t>See Also: Next-Best Egress Interface</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Next-Best Egress Interface">
          <t>Definition:</t>

          <t>The outbound interface from the DUT for traffic routed to the
          second-best next-hop.</t>

          <t>Discussion:</t>

          <t>The Next-Best Egress Interface becomes the egress interface after
          a Convergence Event.</t>

          <t>The Next-Best Egress Interface is of the same media type and link
          speed as the Preferred Egress Interface.</t>

          <t>Measurement Units: N/A</t>

          <t>Issues: None</t>

          <t>See Also: Preferred Egress Interface</t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section title="Benchmarking Methods">
        <section title="Rate-Derived Method">
          <t>Definition:</t>

          <t>The method to calculate convergence time benchmarks from
          observing Forwarding Rate each Packet Sampling Interval.</t>

          <t>Discussion:</t>

          <t><xref target="fig1"></xref> shows an example of the Forwarding
          Rate change in time during convergence as observed when using the
          Rate-Derived Method.</t>

          <figure align="center" anchor="fig1"
                  title="Rate-Derived Convergence Graph">
            <artwork><![CDATA[
     ^         Traffic                      Convergence
Fwd  |         Start                        Recovery
Rate |         Instant                      Instant
     | Offered  ^                             ^
     | Load --> ----------\                   /-----------
     |                     \                 /<--- Convergence
     |                      \     Packet    /      Recovery
     |       Convergence --->\     Loss    /       Transition
     |       Event            \           /
     |       Transition        \---------/ <-- Max Packet Loss
     |
     +--------------------------------------------------------->
                     ^                   ^                 time
                Convergence         First Route
                Event Instant       Convergence Instant
]]></artwork>
          </figure>

          <t>The Offered Load SHOULD consist of a single Stream <xref
          target="Po06"></xref>. If sending multiple Streams, the measured
          traffic rate statistics for all Streams MUST be added together.</t>

          <t>The destination addresses for the Offered Load MUST be
          distributed such that all routes or a statistically representative
          subset of all routes are matched and each of these routes is offered
          an equal share of the Offered Load. It is RECOMMENDED to send
          traffic to all routes, but a statistically representative subset of
          all routes can be used if required.</t>

          <t>At least one packet per route for all routes matched in the
          Offered Load MUST be offered to the DUT within each Packet Sampling
          Interval.</t>

          <t>The Offered Load, the number of routes, and the Packet Sampling
          Interval influence the observations for the Rate-Derived Method. It
          may be difficult to identify the different convergence time instants
          in the Rate-Derived Convergence Graph. For example, it is possible
          that a Convergence Event causes the Forwarding Rate to drop to zero,
          while this may not be observed in the Forwarding Rate measurements
          if the Packet Sampling Interval is too large.</t>

          <t>Metrics measured at the Packet Sampling Interval MUST include
          Forwarding Rate and packet loss.</t>

          <t>Rate-Derived Method is a RECOMMENDED method to measure
          convergence time benchmarks.</t>

          <t>To measure convergence time benchmarks for Convergence Events
          that do not cause instantaneous traffic loss for all routes at the
          Convergence Event Instant, the Tester SHOULD collect a timestamp of
          the Convergence Event Instant and the Tester SHOULD observe
          Forwarding Rate separately on the Next-Best Egress Interface.</t>

          <t>Since the Rate-Derived Method does not distinguish between
          individual traffic destinations, it SHOULD NOT be used for any route
          specific measurements. Therefor Rate-Derived Method SHOULD NOT be
          used to benchmark Route Loss of Connectivity Period.</t>

          <t>Measurement Units: N/A</t>

          <t>Issues: None</t>

          <t>See Also:</t>

          <t>Packet Sampling Interval, Convergence Event, Convergence Event
          Instant, Full Convergence</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Loss-Derived Method">
          <t>Definition:</t>

          <t>The method to calculate the Loss-Derived Convergence Time and
          Loss-Derived Loss of Connectivity Period benchmarks from the amount
          of packet loss.</t>

          <t>Discussion:</t>

          <t>The Offered Load SHOULD consist of a single Stream <xref
          target="Po06"></xref>. If sending multiple Streams, the measured
          traffic rate statistics for all Streams MUST be added together.</t>

          <t>The destination addresses for the Offered Load MUST be
          distributed such that all routes or a statistically representative
          subset of all routes are matched and each of these routes is offered
          an equal share of the Offered Load. It is RECOMMENDED to send
          traffic to all routes, but a statistically representative subset of
          all routes can be used if required.</t>

          <t>Loss-Derived Method SHOULD always be combined with Rate-Derived
          Method in order to observe Full Convergence completion. The total
          amount of Convergence Packet Loss is collected after Full
          Convergence completion.</t>

          <t>To measure convergence time and loss of connectivity benchmarks,
          the Tester SHOULD in general observe packet loss on all DUT egress
          interfaces (Connectivity Packet Loss).</t>

          <t>To measure convergence time benchmarks for Convergence Events
          that do not cause instantaneous traffic loss for all routes at the
          Convergence Event Instant, the Tester SHOULD collect timestamps of
          the Start Traffic Instant and of the Convergence Event Instant, and
          the Tester SHOULD observe packet loss separately on the Next-Best
          Egress Interface (Convergence Packet Loss).</t>

          <t>Since Loss-Derived Method does not distinguish between traffic
          destinations and the packet loss statistics are only collected after
          Full Convergence completion, this method can only be used to measure
          average values over all routes. For these reasons Loss-Derived
          Method can only be used to benchmark Loss-Derived Convergence Time
          and Loss-Derived Loss of Connectivity Period.</t>

          <t>Note that the Loss-Derived Method measures an average over all
          routes, including the routes that may not be impacted by the
          Convergence Event, such as routes via non-impacted members of ECMP
          or parallel links.</t>

          <t>Measurement Units: seconds</t>

          <t>Issues: None</t>

          <t>See Also:</t>

          <t>Loss-Derived Convergence Time, Loss-Derived Loss of Connectivity
          Period, Convergence Packet Loss</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Route-Specific Loss-Derived Method">
          <t>Definition:</t>

          <t>The method to calculate the Route-Specific Convergence Time
          benchmark from the amount of packet loss during convergence for a
          specific route entry.</t>

          <t>Discussion:</t>

          <t>To benchmark Route-Specific Convergence Time, the Tester provides
          an Offered Load that consists of multiple Streams <xref
          target="Po06"></xref>. Each Stream has a single destination address
          matching a different route entry, for all routes or a statistically
          representative subset of all routes. Convergence Packet Loss is
          measured for each Stream separately.</t>

          <t>Route-Specific Loss-Derived Method SHOULD always be combined with
          Rate-Derived Method in order to observe Full Convergence completion.
          The total amount of Convergence Packet Loss for each Stream is
          collected after Full Convergence completion.</t>

          <t>Route-Specific Loss-Derived Method is a RECOMMENDED method to
          measure convergence time benchmarks.</t>

          <t>To measure convergence time and loss of connectivity benchmarks,
          the Tester SHOULD in general observe packet loss on all DUT egress
          interfaces (Connectivity Packet Loss).</t>

          <t>To measure convergence time benchmarks for Convergence Events
          that do not cause instantaneous traffic loss for all routes at the
          Convergence Event Instant, the Tester SHOULD collect timestamps of
          the Start Traffic Instant and of the Convergence Event Instant, and
          the Tester SHOULD observe packet loss separately on the Next-Best
          Egress Interface (Convergence Packet Loss).</t>

          <t>Since Route-Specific Loss-Derived Method uses traffic streams to
          individual routes, it measures packet loss as it would be
          experienced by a network user. For this reason Route-Specific
          Loss-Derived Method is RECOMMENDED to measure Route-Specific
          Convergence Time benchmarks and Route Loss of Connectivity Period
          benchmarks.</t>

          <t>Measurement Units: seconds</t>

          <t>Issues: None</t>

          <t>See Also:</t>

          <t>Route-Specific Convergence Time, Route Loss of Connectivity
          Period, Convergence Packet Loss</t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section title="Benchmarks">
        <section title="Full Convergence Time">
          <t>Definition:</t>

          <t>The time duration of the period between the Convergence Event
          Instant and the Convergence Recovery Instant as observed using the
          Rate-Derived Method.</t>

          <t>Discussion:</t>

          <t>Using the Rate-Derived Method, Full Convergence Time can be
          calculated as the time difference between the Convergence Event
          Instant and the Convergence Recovery Instant, as shown in Equation
          1.</t>

          <figure align="center">
            <artwork><![CDATA[
Full Convergence Time =
    Convergence Recovery Instant - Convergence Event Instant
]]></artwork>

            <postamble>Equation 1</postamble>
          </figure>

          <t>The Convergence Event Instant can be derived from the Forwarding
          Rate observation or from a timestamp collected by the Tester.</t>

          <t>For the testcases described in <xref target="Po09m"></xref>, it
          is expected that Full Convergence Time equals the maximum
          Route-Specific Convergence Time when benchmarking all routes in FIB
          using the Route-Specific Loss-Derived Method.</t>

          <t>It is not possible to measure Full Convergence Time using the
          Loss-Derived Method.</t>

          <t>Measurement Units: seconds</t>

          <t>Issues: None</t>

          <t>See Also:</t>

          <t>Full Convergence, Rate-Derived Method, Route-Specific
          Loss-Derived Method</t>
        </section>

        <section title="First Route Convergence Time">
          <t>Definition:</t>

          <t>The duration of the period between the Convergence Event Instant
          and the First Route Convergence Instant as observed using the
          Rate-Derived Method.</t>

          <t>Discussion:</t>

          <t>Using the Rate-Derived Method, First Route Convergence Time can
          be calculated as the time difference between the Convergence Event
          Instant and the First Route Convergence Instant, as shown with
          Equation 2.</t>

          <figure align="center">
            <artwork><![CDATA[
First Route Convergence Time =
    First Route Convergence Instant - Convergence Event Instant
]]></artwork>

            <postamble>Equation 2</postamble>
          </figure>

          <t>The Convergence Event Instant can be derived from the Forwarding
          Rate observation or from a timestamp collected by the Tester.</t>

          <t>For the testcases described in <xref target="Po09m"></xref>, it
          is expected that First Route Convergence Time equals the minimum
          Route-Specific Convergence Time when benchmarking all routes in FIB
          using the Route-Specific Loss-Derived Method.</t>

          <t>It is not possible to measure First Route Convergence Time using
          the Loss-Derived Method.</t>

          <t>Measurement Units: seconds</t>

          <t>Issues: None</t>

          <t>See Also:</t>

          <t>Rate-Derived Method, Route-Specific Loss-Derived Method, First
          Route Convergence Instant</t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="route_specific_conv_time"
                 title="Route-Specific Convergence Time">
          <t>Definition:</t>

          <t>The amount of time it takes for Route Convergence to be completed
          for a specific route, as calculated from the amount of packet loss
          during convergence for a single route entry.</t>

          <t>Discussion:</t>

          <t>Route-Specific Convergence Time can only be measured using the
          Route-Specific Loss-Derived Method.</t>

          <t>If the applied Convergence Event causes instantaneous traffic
          loss for all routes at the Convergence Event Instant, Connectivity
          Packet Loss should be observed. Connectivity Packet Loss is the
          combined packet loss observed on Preferred Egress Interface and
          Next-Best Egress Interface. When benchmarking Route-Specific
          Convergence Time, Connectivity Packet Loss is measured and Equation
          3 is applied for each measured route. The calculation is equal to
          Equation 7 in <xref target="route_LoC_period"></xref>.</t>

          <figure align="center">
            <artwork><![CDATA[
Route-Specific Convergence Time =
   Connectivity Packet Loss for specific route/Offered Load per route
]]></artwork>

            <postamble>Equation 3</postamble>
          </figure>

          <t>If the applied Convergence Event does not cause instantaneous
          traffic loss for all routes at the Convergence Event Instant, then
          the Tester SHOULD collect timestamps of the Traffic Start Instant
          and of the Convergence Event Instant, and the Tester SHOULD observe
          Convergence Packet Loss separately on the Next-Best Egress
          Interface. When benchmarking Route-Specific Convergence Time,
          Convergence Packet Loss is measured and Equation 4 is applied for
          each measured route.</t>

          <figure align="center">
            <artwork><![CDATA[
Route-Specific Convergence Time =
    Convergence Packet Loss for specific route/Offered Load per route
    - (Convergence Event Instant - Traffic Start Instant)
]]></artwork>

            <postamble>Equation 4</postamble>
          </figure>

          <t>The Convergence Event Instant and Traffic Start Instant SHOULD be
          collected by the Tester.</t>

          <t>The Route-Specific Convergence Time benchmarks enable minimum,
          maximum, average, and median convergence time measurements to be
          reported by comparing the results for the different route entries.
          It also enables benchmarking of convergence time when configuring a
          priority value for route entry(ies). Since multiple Route-Specific
          Convergence Times can be measured it is possible to have an array of
          results. The format for reporting Route-Specific Convergence Time is
          provided in <xref target="Po09m"></xref>.</t>

          <t>Measurement Units: seconds</t>

          <t>Issues: None</t>

          <t>See Also:</t>

          <t>Convergence Event, Convergence Packet Loss, Connectivity Packet
          Loss, Route Convergence</t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="loss_derived_convergence_time"
                 title="Loss-Derived Convergence Time">
          <t>Definition:</t>

          <t>The average Route Convergence time for all routes in FIB, as
          calculated from the amount of packet loss during convergence.</t>

          <t>Discussion:</t>

          <t>Loss-Derived Convergence Time is measured using the Loss-Derived
          Method.</t>

          <t>If the applied Convergence Event causes instantaneous traffic
          loss for all routes at the Convergence Event Instant, Connectivity
          Packet Loss should be observed. Connectivity Packet Loss is the
          combined packet loss observed on Preferred Egress Interface and
          Next-Best Egress Interface. When benchmarking Loss-Derived
          Convergence Time, Connectivity Packet Loss is measured and Equation
          5 is applied.</t>

          <figure align="center">
            <artwork><![CDATA[
Loss-Derived Convergence Time =
    Connectivity Packet Loss/Offered Load
]]></artwork>

            <postamble>Equation 5</postamble>
          </figure>

          <t>If the applied Convergence Event does not cause instantaneous
          traffic loss for all routes at the Convergence Event Instant, then
          the Tester SHOULD collect timestamps of the Start Traffic Instant
          and of the Convergence Event Instant and the Tester SHOULD observe
          Convergence Packet Loss separately on the Next-Best Egress
          Interface. When benchmarking Loss-Derived Convergence Time,
          Convergence Packet Loss is measured and Equation 6 is applied.</t>

          <figure align="center">
            <artwork><![CDATA[
Loss-Derived Convergence Time =
    Convergence Packet Loss/Offered Load
    - (Convergence Event Instant - Traffic Start Instant)
]]></artwork>

            <postamble>Equation 6</postamble>
          </figure>

          <t>The Convergence Event Instant and Traffic Start Instant SHOULD be
          collected by the Tester.</t>

          <t>Measurement Units: seconds</t>

          <t>Issues: None</t>

          <t>See Also:</t>

          <t>Convergence Packet Loss, Connectivity Packet Loss, Route
          Convergence</t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="route_LoC_period"
                 title="Route Loss of Connectivity Period">
          <t>Definition:</t>

          <t>The time duration of traffic loss for a specific route entry
          following a Convergence Event until Full Convergence completion, as
          observed using the Route-Specific Loss-Derived Method.</t>

          <t>Discussion:</t>

          <t>In general the Route Loss of Connectivity Period is not equal to
          the Route-Specific Convergence Time. If the DUT continues to forward
          traffic to the Preferred Egress Interface after the Convergence
          Event is applied then the Route Loss of Connectivity Period will be
          smaller than the Route-Specific Convergence Time. This is also
          specifically the case after reversing a failure event.</t>

          <t>The Route Loss of Connectivity Period may be equal to the
          Route-Specific Convergence Time if, as a characteristic of the
          Convergence Event, traffic for all routes starts dropping
          instantaneously on the Convergence Event Instant. See discussion in
          <xref target="Po09m"></xref>.</t>

          <t>For the testcases described in <xref target="Po09m"></xref> the
          Route Loss of Connectivity Period is expected to be a single Loss
          Period <xref target="Ko02"></xref>.</t>

          <t>When benchmarking Route Loss of Connectivity Period, Connectivity
          Packet Loss is measured for each route and Equation 7 is applied for
          each measured route entry. The calculation is equal to Equation 3 in
          <xref target="route_specific_conv_time"></xref>.</t>

          <figure align="center">
            <artwork><![CDATA[
Route Loss of Connectivity Period =
   Connectivity Packet Loss for specific route/Offered Load per route
]]></artwork>

            <postamble>Equation 7</postamble>
          </figure>

          <t>Route Loss of Connectivity Period SHOULD be measured using
          Route-Specific Loss-Derived Method.</t>

          <t>Measurement Units: seconds</t>

          <t>Issues: None</t>

          <t>See Also:</t>

          <t>Route-Specific Convergence Time, Route-Specific Loss-Derived
          Method, Connectivity Packet Loss</t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="loss_derived_LoC_period"
                 title="Loss-Derived Loss of Connectivity Period">
          <t>Definition:</t>

          <t>The average time duration of traffic loss for all routes
          following a Convergence Event until Full Convergence completion, as
          observed using the Loss-Derived Method.</t>

          <t>Discussion:</t>

          <t>In general the Loss-Derived Loss of Connectivity Period is not
          equal to the Loss-Derived Convergence Time. If the DUT continues to
          forward traffic to the Preferred Egress Interface after the
          Convergence Event is applied then the Loss-Derived Loss of
          Connectivity Period will be smaller than the Loss-Derived
          Convergence Time. This is also specifically the case after reversing
          a failure event.</t>

          <t>The Loss-Derived Loss of Connectivity Period may be equal to the
          Loss-Derived Convergence Time if, as a characteristic of the
          Convergence Event, traffic for all routes starts dropping
          instantaneously on the Convergence Event Instant. See discussion in
          <xref target="Po09m"></xref>.</t>

          <t>For the testcases described in <xref target="Po09m"></xref> each
          route's Route Loss of Connectivity Period is expected to be a single
          Loss Period <xref target="Ko02"></xref>.</t>

          <t>When benchmarking Loss-Derived Loss of Connectivity Period,
          Connectivity Packet Loss is measured for all routes and Equation 8
          is applied. The calculation is equal to Equation 5 in <xref
          target="loss_derived_convergence_time"></xref>.</t>

          <figure align="center">
            <artwork><![CDATA[
Loss-Derived Loss of Connectivity Period =
   Connectivity Packet Loss for all routes/Offered Load
]]></artwork>

            <postamble>Equation 8</postamble>
          </figure>

          <t>Loss-Derived Loss of Connectivity Period SHOULD be measured using
          Loss-Derived Method.</t>

          <t>Measurement Units: seconds</t>

          <t>Issues: None</t>

          <t>See Also:</t>

          <t>Loss-Derived Convergence Time, Loss-Derived Method, Connectivity
          Packet Loss</t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section title="Measurement Terms">
        <section title="Convergence Event">
          <t>Definition:</t>

          <t>The occurrence of a planned or unplanned event in the network
          that will result in a change in the egress interface of the Device
          Under Test (DUT) for routed packets.</t>

          <t>Discussion:</t>

          <t>Convergence Events include but are not limited to link loss,
          routing protocol session loss, router failure, configuration change,
          and better next-hop learned via a routing protocol.</t>

          <t>Measurement Units: N/A</t>

          <t>Issues: None</t>

          <t>See Also: Convergence Event Instant</t>
        </section>

        <section title=" Packet Loss">
          <t>Definition:</t>

          <t>The number of packets that should have been forwarded by a DUT
          under a constant Offered Load that were not forwarded due to lack of
          resources.</t>

          <t>Discussion:</t>

          <t>Packet Loss is a modified version of the term "Frame Loss Rate"
          as defined in <xref target="Br91"></xref>. The term "Frame Loss" is
          intended for Ethernet Frames while "Packet Loss" is intended for IP
          packets.</t>

          <t>Measurement units: Number of offered packets that are not
          forwarded.</t>

          <t>Issues: None</t>

          <t>See Also: Convergence Packet Loss</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Convergence Packet Loss">
          <t>Definition:</t>

          <t>The number of packets lost due to a Convergence Event until Full
          Convergence completes, as observed on the Next-Best Egress
          Interface.</t>

          <t>Discussion:</t>

          <t>Convergence Packet Loss is observed on the Next-Best Egress
          Interface. It only needs to be observed for Convergence Events that
          do not cause instantaneous traffic loss at Convergence Event
          Instant.</t>

          <t>Convergence Packet Loss includes packets that were lost and
          packets that were delayed due to buffering. The magnitude of an
          acceptable Forwarding Delay is a parameter of the methodology. If a
          maximum acceptable Forwarding Delay threshold is applied it MUST be
          reported.</t>

          <t>Measurement Units: number of packets</t>

          <t>Issues: None</t>

          <t>See Also:</t>

          <t>Packet Loss, Full Convergence, Convergence Event, Connectivity
          Packet Loss</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Connectivity Packet Loss">
          <t>Definition:</t>

          <t>The number of packets lost due to a Convergence Event until Full
          Convergence completes.</t>

          <t>Discussion:</t>

          <t>Connectivity Packet Loss is observed on all DUT egress
          interfaces.</t>

          <t>Convergence Packet Loss includes packets that were lost and
          packets that were delayed due to buffering. The magnitude of an
          acceptable Forwarding Delay is a parameter of the methodology. If a
          maximum acceptable Forwarding Delay threshold is applied it MUST be
          reported.</t>

          <t>Measurement Units: number of packets</t>

          <t>Issues: None</t>

          <t>See Also:</t>

          <t>Packet Loss, Route Loss of Connectivity Period, Convergence
          Event, Convergence Packet Loss</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Packet Sampling Interval">
          <t>Definition:</t>

          <t>The interval at which the Tester (test equipment) polls to make
          measurements for arriving packets.</t>

          <t>Discussion:</t>

          <t>At least one packet per route for all routes matched in the
          Offered Load MUST be offered to the DUT within the Packet Sampling
          Interval. Metrics measured at the Packet Sampling Interval MUST
          include Forwarding Rate and received packets.</t>

          <t>Packet Sampling Interval can influence the convergence graph as
          observed with the Rate-Derived Method. This is particularly true
          when implementations complete Full Convergence in less time than the
          Packet Sampling Interval. The Convergence Event Instant and First
          Route Convergence Instant may not be easily identifiable and the
          Rate-Derived Method may produce a larger than actual convergence
          time.</t>

          <t>The recommended value for configuration of the Packet Sampling
          Interval when using the Rate-Derived Method is provided in <xref
          target="Po09m"></xref>. For the other benchmark methods the value of
          the Packet Sampling Interval does not contribute to the measurement
          accuracy.</t>

          <t>Measurement Units: seconds</t>

          <t>Issues: None</t>

          <t>See Also: Rate-Derived Method</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Sustained Convergence Validation Time">
          <t>Definition:</t>

          <t>The amount of time for which the completion of Full Convergence
          is maintained without additional packet loss.</t>

          <t>Discussion:</t>

          <t>The purpose of the Sustained Convergence Validation Time is to
          produce convergence benchmarks protected against fluctuation in
          Forwarding Rate after the completion of Full Convergence is
          observed. The RECOMMENDED Sustained Convergence Validation Time to
          be used is 5 seconds. The BMWG selected 5 seconds based upon RFC
          2544 <xref target="Br99"></xref> which recommends waiting 2 seconds
          for residual frames to arrive (this is the Forwarding Delay
          threshold for the last packet sent) and 5 seconds for DUT
          restabilization.</t>

          <t>Measurement Units: seconds</t>

          <t>Issues: None</t>

          <t>See Also:</t>

          <t>Full Convergence, Convergence Recovery Instant</t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section title="Miscellaneous Terms">
        <section title="Stale Forwarding">
          <t>Definition:</t>

          <t>Forwarding of traffic to route entries that no longer exist or to
          route entries with next-hops that are no longer preferred.</t>

          <t>Discussion:</t>

          <t>Stale Forwarding can be caused by a Convergence Event and can
          manifest as a "black-hole" or microloop that produces packet loss,
          or out-of-order packets, or delayed packets. Stale Forwarding can
          exist until Network Convergence is completed.</t>

          <t>Measurement Units: N/A</t>

          <t>Issues: None</t>

          <t>See Also: Network Convergence</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Nested Convergence Event">
          <t>Definition:</t>

          <t>The occurrence of a Convergence Event while the route table is
          converging from a prior Convergence Event.</t>

          <t>Discussion:</t>

          <t>The Convergence Events for a Nested Convergence Event MUST occur
          with different neighbors. A possible observation from a Nested
          Convergence Event will be the withdrawal of routes from one neighbor
          while the routes of another neighbor are being installed.</t>

          <t>Measurement Units: N/A</t>

          <t>Issues: None</t>

          <t>See Also: Convergence Event</t>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Security Considerations">
      <t>Benchmarking activities as described in this memo are limited to
      technology characterization using controlled stimuli in a laboratory
      environment, with dedicated address space and the constraints specified
      in the sections above.</t>

      <t>The benchmarking network topology will be an independent test setup
      and MUST NOT be connected to devices that may forward the test traffic
      into a production network, or misroute traffic to the test management
      network.</t>

      <t>Further, benchmarking is performed on a "black-box" basis, relying
      solely on measurements observable external to the DUT/SUT.</t>

      <t>Special capabilities SHOULD NOT exist in the DUT/SUT specifically for
      benchmarking purposes. Any implications for network security arising
      from the DUT/SUT SHOULD be identical in the lab and in production
      networks.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>This document requires no IANA considerations.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>Thanks to Sue Hares, Al Morton, Kevin Dubray, Ron Bonica, David Ward,
      Peter De Vriendt and the BMWG for their contributions to this work.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc linefile="1:http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1242.xml"?>

      <reference anchor="Br91">
        <front>
          <title abbrev="Benchmarking Terminology">Benchmarking terminology
          for network interconnection devices</title>

          <author fullname="Scott Bradner" initials="S." surname="Bradner">
            <organization>Harvard University</organization>

            <address>
              <postal>
                <street>33 Kirkland Street</street>

                <street>William James Hall 1232</street>

                <city>Cambridge</city>

                <region>MA</region>

                <code>02138</code>

                <country>US</country>
              </postal>

              <phone>+1 617 495 3864</phone>

              <email>SOB@HARVARD.HARVARD.EDU</email>
            </address>
          </author>

          <date day="1" month="July" year="1991" />

          <abstract>
            <t>This memo discusses and defines a number of terms that are used
            in describing performance benchmarking tests and the results of
            such tests. The terms defined in this memo will be used in
            additional memos to define specific benchmarking tests and the
            suggested format to be used in reporting the results of each of
            the tests. This memo is a product of the Benchmarking Methodology
            Working Group (BMWG) of the Internet Engineering Task Force
            (IETF).</t>
          </abstract>
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="1242" />

        <format octets="22817" target="ftp://ftp.isi.edu/in-notes/rfc1242.txt"
                type="TXT" />
      </reference>

      <?rfc linefile="1093:/tmp/CGI485.1"?>

      <?rfc linefile="1:http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"?>

      <reference anchor="Br97">
        <front>
          <title abbrev="RFC Key Words">Key words for use in RFCs to Indicate
          Requirement Levels</title>

          <author fullname="Scott Bradner" initials="S." surname="Bradner">
            <organization>Harvard University</organization>

            <address>
              <postal>
                <street>1350 Mass. Ave.</street>

                <street>Cambridge</street>

                <street>MA 02138</street>
              </postal>

              <phone>- +1 617 495 3864</phone>

              <email>sob@harvard.edu</email>
            </address>
          </author>

          <date month="March" year="1997" />

          <area>General</area>

          <keyword>keyword</keyword>

          <abstract>
            <t>In many standards track documents several words are used to
            signify the requirements in the specification. These words are
            often capitalized. This document defines these words as they
            should be interpreted in IETF documents. Authors who follow these
            guidelines should incorporate this phrase near the beginning of
            their document: <list>
                <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL",
                "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and
                "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described
                in RFC 2119.</t>
              </list></t>

            <t>Note that the force of these words is modified by the
            requirement level of the document in which they are used.</t>
          </abstract>
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="BCP" value="14" />

        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="2119" />

        <format octets="4723" target="ftp://ftp.isi.edu/in-notes/rfc2119.txt"
                type="TXT" />

        <format octets="17491"
                target="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/html/rfc2119.html"
                type="HTML" />

        <format octets="5777"
                target="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/xml/rfc2119.xml"
                type="XML" />
      </reference>

      <?rfc linefile="1095:/tmp/CGI485.1"?>

      <?rfc linefile="1:http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2544.xml"?>

      <reference anchor="Br99">
        <front>
          <title abbrev="Benchmarking Methodology">Benchmarking Methodology
          for Network Interconnect Devices</title>

          <author fullname="Scott Bradner" initials="S." surname="Bradner">
            <organization>Harvard University</organization>

            <address>
              <postal>
                <street>1350 Mass. Ave</street>

                <street>Room 813</street>

                <city>Cambridge</city>

                <region>MA</region>

                <code>02138</code>

                <country>US</country>
              </postal>

              <phone>+1 617 495 3864</phone>

              <facsimile>+1 617 496 8500</facsimile>

              <email>sob@harvard.edu</email>
            </address>
          </author>

          <author fullname="Jim McQuaid" initials="J." surname="McQuaid">
            <organization>NetScout Systems</organization>

            <address>
              <postal>
                <street>4 Westford Tech Park Drive</street>

                <city>Westford</city>

                <region>MA</region>

                <code>01886</code>

                <country>US</country>
              </postal>

              <phone>+1 978 614 4116</phone>

              <facsimile>+1 978 614 4004</facsimile>

              <email>mcquaidj@netscout.com</email>
            </address>
          </author>

          <date month="March" year="1999" />

          <abstract>
            <t>This document discusses and defines a number of tests that may
            be used to describe the performance characteristics of a network
            interconnecting device. In addition to defining the tests this
            document also describes specific formats for reporting the results
            of the tests. Appendix A lists the tests and conditions that we
            believe should be included for specific cases and gives additional
            information about testing practices. Appendix B is a reference
            listing of maximum frame rates to be used with specific frame
            sizes on various media and Appendix C gives some examples of frame
            formats to be used in testing.</t>
          </abstract>
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="2544" />

        <format octets="66688" target="ftp://ftp.isi.edu/in-notes/rfc2544.txt"
                type="TXT" />
      </reference>

      <?rfc linefile="1097:/tmp/CGI485.1"?>

      <?rfc linefile="1:http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1195.xml"?>

      <reference anchor="Ca90">
        <front>
          <title abbrev="OSI ISIS for IP and Dual Environments">Use of OSI
          IS-IS for routing in TCP/IP and dual environments</title>

          <author fullname="Ross Callon" initials="R." surname="Callon">
            <organization>Digital Equipment Corporation (DEC)</organization>

            <address>
              <postal>
                <street>550 King Street</street>

                <street>LKG 1-2/A19</street>

                <city>Littleton</city>

                <region>MA</region>

                <code>01460-1289</code>

                <country>US</country>
              </postal>

              <phone>+1 508 486 5009</phone>
            </address>
          </author>

          <date day="1" month="December" year="1990" />

          <abstract>
            <t>This RFC specifies an integrated routing protocol, based on the
            OSI Intra-Domain IS-IS Routing Protocol, which may be used as an
            interior gateway protocol (IGP) to support TCP/IP as well as OSI.
            This allows a single routing protocol to be used to support pure
            IP environments, pure OSI environments, and dual environments.
            This specification was developed by the IS-IS working group of the
            Internet Engineering Task Force.</t>

            <t>The OSI IS-IS protocol has reached a mature state, and is ready
            for implementation and operational use. The most recent version of
            the OSI IS-IS protocol is contained in ISO DP 10589. The proposed
            standard for using IS-IS for support of TCP/IP will therefore make
            use of this version (with a minor bug correction, as discussed in
            Annex B). We expect that future versions of this proposed standard
            will upgrade to the final International Standard version of IS-IS
            when available.</t>

            <t>Comments should be sent to "isis@merit.edu".</t>
          </abstract>
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="1195" />

        <format octets="187866"
                target="ftp://ftp.isi.edu/in-notes/rfc1195.txt" type="TXT" />

        <format octets="362052" target="ftp://ftp.isi.edu/in-notes/rfc1195.ps"
                type="PS" />
      </reference>

      <?rfc linefile="1099:/tmp/CGI485.1"?>

      <?rfc linefile="1:http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2285.xml"?>

      <reference anchor="Ma98">
        <front>
          <title abbrev="Benchmarking Terminology">Benchmarking Terminology
          for LAN Switching Devices</title>

          <author fullname="Robert Mandeville" initials="R."
                  surname="Mandeville">
            <organization>European Network Laboratories (ENL)</organization>

            <address>
              <postal>
                <street>2</street>

                <street>rue Helene Boucher</street>

                <street>78286 Guyancourt Cedex</street>

                <country>France</country>
              </postal>

              <phone>+ 33 1 39 44 12 05</phone>

              <facsimile>+ 33 1 39 44 12 06</facsimile>

              <email>bob.mandeville@eunet.fr</email>
            </address>
          </author>

          <date month="February" year="1998" />

          <area>Operations</area>

          <keyword>local area network</keyword>

          <keyword>Benchmarking</keyword>
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="2285" />

        <format octets="43130" target="ftp://ftp.isi.edu/in-notes/rfc2285.txt"
                type="TXT" />

        <format octets="58104"
                target="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/html/rfc2285.html"
                type="HTML" />

        <format octets="42866"
                target="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/xml/rfc2285.xml"
                type="XML" />
      </reference>

      <?rfc linefile="1101:/tmp/CGI485.1"?>

      <?rfc linefile="1:http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2328.xml"?>

      <reference anchor="Mo98">
        <front>
          <title>OSPF Version 2</title>

          <author fullname="John Moy" initials="J." surname="Moy">
            <organization>Ascend Communications, Inc.</organization>

            <address>
              <postal>
                <street>1 Robbins Road</street>

                <city>Westford</city>

                <region>MA</region>

                <code>01886</code>
              </postal>

              <phone>978-952-1367</phone>

              <facsimile>978-392-2075</facsimile>

              <email>jmoy@casc.com</email>
            </address>
          </author>

          <date month="April" year="1998" />

          <area>Routing</area>

          <keyword>open shortest-path first protocol</keyword>

          <keyword>routing</keyword>

          <keyword>OSPF</keyword>

          <abstract>
            <t>This memo documents version 2 of the OSPF protocol. OSPF is a
            link-state routing protocol. It is designed to be run internal to
            a single Autonomous System. Each OSPF router maintains an
            identical database describing the Autonomous System's topology.
            From this database, a routing table is calculated by constructing
            a shortest- path tree.</t>

            <t>OSPF recalculates routes quickly in the face of topological
            changes, utilizing a minimum of routing protocol traffic. OSPF
            provides support for equal-cost multipath. An area routing
            capability is provided, enabling an additional level of routing
            protection and a reduction in routing protocol traffic. In
            addition, all OSPF routing protocol exchanges are
            authenticated.</t>

            <t>The differences between this memo and RFC 2178 are explained in
            Appendix G. All differences are backward-compatible in nature.
            Implementations of this memo and of RFCs 2178, 1583, and 1247 will
            interoperate.</t>

            <t>Please send comments to ospf@gated.cornell.edu.</t>
          </abstract>
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="STD" value="54" />

        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="2328" />

        <format octets="447367"
                target="ftp://ftp.isi.edu/in-notes/rfc2328.txt" type="TXT" />

        <format octets="466915"
                target="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/html/rfc2328.html"
                type="HTML" />

        <format octets="446761"
                target="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/xml/rfc2328.xml"
                type="XML" />
      </reference>

      <?rfc linefile="1103:/tmp/CGI485.1"?>

      <?rfc linefile="1:http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4689.xml"?>

      <reference anchor="Po06">
        <front>
          <title>Terminology for Benchmarking Network-layer Traffic Control
          Mechanisms</title>

          <author fullname="S. Poretsky" initials="S." surname="Poretsky">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="J. Perser" initials="J." surname="Perser">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="S. Erramilli" initials="S." surname="Erramilli">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="S. Khurana" initials="S." surname="Khurana">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date month="October" year="2006" />

          <abstract>
            <t>This document describes terminology for the benchmarking of
            devices that implement traffic control using packet classification
            based on defined criteria. The terminology is to be applied to
            measurements made on the data plane to evaluate IP traffic control
            mechanisms. Rules for packet classification can be based on any
            field in the IP header, such as the Differentiated Services Code
            Point (DSCP), or any field in the packet payload, such as port
            number. This memo provides information for the Internet
            community.</t>
          </abstract>
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="4689" />

        <format octets="62369" target="ftp://ftp.isi.edu/in-notes/rfc4689.txt"
                type="TXT" />
      </reference>

      <?rfc linefile="1105:/tmp/CGI485.1"?>

      <?rfc linefile="1:http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.draft-ietf-bmwg-igp-dataplane-conv-meth-18.xml"?>

      <reference anchor="Po09m">
        <front>
          <title>Benchmarking Methodology for Link-State IGP Data Plane Route
          Convergence</title>

          <author fullname="Scott Poretsky" initials="S" surname="Poretsky">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="Brent Imhoff" initials="B" surname="Imhoff">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date day="8" month="July" year="2009" />

          <abstract>
            <t>This document describes the methodology for benchmarking
            Interior Gateway Protocol (IGP) Route Convergence. The methodology
            is to be used for benchmarking IGP convergence time through
            externally observable (black box) data plane measurements. The
            methodology can be applied to any link-state IGP, such as ISIS and
            OSPF. Link-State IGP Data Plane Route Convergence</t>
          </abstract>
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft"
                    value="draft-ietf-bmwg-igp-dataplane-conv-meth-18" />

        <format target="http://www.ietf.org/internet-drafts/draft-ietf-bmwg-igp-dataplane-conv-meth-18.txt"
                type="TXT" />
      </reference>

      <?rfc linefile="1:http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.draft-ietf-bmwg-igp-dataplane-conv-app-17.xml"?>

      <reference anchor="Po09a">
        <front>
          <title>Considerations for Benchmarking Link-State IGP Data Plane
          Route Convergence</title>

          <author fullname="Scott Poretsky" initials="S" surname="Poretsky">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date day="8" month="March" year="2009" />

          <abstract>
            <t>This document discusses considerations for benchmarking
            Interior Gateway Protocol (IGP) Route Convergence for any
            link-state IGP, such as Intermediate System-Intermediate System
            (ISIS) and Open-Shorted Path first (OSPF). A companion methodology
            document is to be used for benchmarking IGP convergence time
            through externally observable (black box) data plane measurements.
            A companion</t>
          </abstract>
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft"
                    value="draft-ietf-bmwg-igp-dataplane-conv-app-17" />

        <format target="http://www.ietf.org/internet-drafts/draft-ietf-bmwg-igp-dataplane-conv-app-17.txt"
                type="TXT" />
      </reference>

      <?rfc linefile="1111:/tmp/CGI485.1"?>

      <reference anchor="Co08">
        <front>
          <title>OSPF for IPv6</title>

          <author fullname="R. Coltun" initials="R." surname="Coltun">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="D. Ferguson" initials="D." surname="Ferguson">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="J. Moy" initials="J." surname="Moy">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="A. Lindem" initials="A." surname="Lindem">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date month="July" year="2008" />

          <abstract>
            <t>This document describes the modifications to OSPF to support
            version 6 of the Internet Protocol (IPv6). The fundamental
            mechanisms of OSPF (flooding, Designated Router (DR) election,
            area support, Short Path First (SPF) calculations, etc.) remain
            unchanged. However, some changes have been necessary, either due
            to changes in protocol semantics between IPv4 and IPv6, or simply
            to handle the increased address size of IPv6. These modifications
            will necessitate incrementing the protocol version from version 2
            to version 3. OSPF for IPv6 is also referred to as OSPF version 3
            (OSPFv3).&lt;/t&gt;&lt;t&gt; Changes between OSPF for IPv4, OSPF
            Version 2, and OSPF for IPv6 as described herein include the
            following. Addressing semantics have been removed from OSPF
            packets and the basic Link State Advertisements (LSAs). New LSAs
            have been created to carry IPv6 addresses and prefixes. OSPF now
            runs on a per-link basis rather than on a per-IP-subnet basis.
            Flooding scope for LSAs has been generalized. Authentication has
            been removed from the OSPF protocol and instead relies on IPv6's
            Authentication Header and Encapsulating Security Payload
            (ESP).&lt;/t&gt;&lt;t&gt; Even with larger IPv6 addresses, most
            packets in OSPF for IPv6 are almost as compact as those in OSPF
            for IPv4. Most fields and packet- size limitations present in OSPF
            for IPv4 have been relaxed. In addition, option handling has been
            made more flexible.&lt;/t&gt;&lt;t&gt; All of OSPF for IPv4's
            optional capabilities, including demand circuit support and
            Not-So-Stubby Areas (NSSAs), are also supported in OSPF for IPv6.
            [STANDARDS TRACK]</t>
          </abstract>
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="5340" />

        <format octets="225664"
                target="ftp://ftp.isi.edu/in-notes/rfc5340.txt" type="TXT" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="Ho08">
        <front>
          <title>Routing IPv6 with IS-IS</title>

          <author fullname="C. Hopps" initials="C." surname="Hopps">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date month="October" year="2008" />

          <abstract>
            <t>This document specifies a method for exchanging IPv6 routing
            information using the IS-IS routing protocol. The described method
            utilizes two new TLVs: a reachability TLV and an interface address
            TLV to distribute the necessary IPv6 information throughout a
            routing domain. Using this method, one can route IPv6 along with
            IPv4 and OSI using a single intra-domain routing protocol.
            [STANDARDS TRACK]</t>
          </abstract>
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="5308" />

        <format octets="13324" target="ftp://ftp.isi.edu/in-notes/rfc5308.txt"
                type="TXT" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="Mo06">
        <front>
          <title>Packet Reordering Metrics</title>

          <author fullname="A. Morton" initials="A." surname="Morton">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="L. Ciavattone" initials="L." surname="Ciavattone">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="G. Ramachandran" initials="G."
                  surname="Ramachandran">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="S. Shalunov" initials="S." surname="Shalunov">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="J. Perser" initials="J." surname="Perser">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date month="November" year="2006" />
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="4737" />

        <format octets="94699" target="ftp://ftp.isi.edu/in-notes/rfc4737.txt"
                type="TXT" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="Ko02">
        <front>
          <title>One-way Loss Pattern Sample Metrics</title>

          <author fullname="R. Koodli" initials="R." surname="Koodli">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="R. Ravikanth" initials="R." surname="Ravikanth">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date month="August" year="2002" />
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="3357" />

        <format octets="30570" target="ftp://ftp.isi.edu/in-notes/rfc3357.txt"
                type="TXT" />
      </reference>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <reference anchor="Ca01">
        <front>
          <title>A Fine-Grained View of High Performance Networking</title>

          <author fullname="S. Casner" initials="S." surname="Casner">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="C. Alaettinoglu" initials="C."
                  surname="Alaettinoglu">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="C. Kuan" initials="C." surname="Kuan">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date month="June" year="2001" />
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="NANOG" value="22" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="Ci03">
        <front>
          <title>Standardized Active Measurements on a Tier 1 IP
          Backbone</title>

          <author fullname="L. Ciavattone" initials="L." surname="Ciavattone">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="A. Morton" initials="A." surname="Morton">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="G. Ramachandran" initials="G."
                  surname="Ramachandran">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date month="May" year="2003" />
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="IEEE Communications Magazine" value="p90-97" />
      </reference>
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
