<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" >

<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>

<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<?rfc toc="no"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="2"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>


<rfc category="std" docName="draft-ietf-yam-rfc1652bis-01" ipr="trust200902" obsoletes="1652">

   <front>

      <title abbrev="SMTP 8-bit Extension">SMTP Service Extension for 8-bit MIME Transport</title>

      <author fullname="John C Klensin" initials="J.C." surname="Klensin">
         <address>
        <postal>
          <street>1770 Massachusetts Ave, Ste 322</street>
          <city>Cambridge</city> <region>MA</region>
          <code>02140</code>
          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>
        <phone>+1 617 245 1457</phone>
        <email>john+ietf@jck.com</email>
      </address>
      </author>

      <author fullname="Ned Freed" initials="N." surname="Freed">
         <organization>Sun Microsystems</organization>
         <address>
           <postal>
              <street>800 Royal Oaks</street>
              <city>Monrovia</city> <region>CA</region>  <code>91016-6347</code>
              <country>USA</country>
           </postal>
            <phone>+1 909 457 4293</phone>
            <email>ned.freed@mrochek.com</email>
         </address>
      </author>

      <author fullname="M. Rose" initials="M." surname="Rose">
         <organization>Dover Beach Consulting, Inc.</organization>
         <address>
            <postal>
               <street>POB 255268</street>
               <city>Sacramento</city>
               <code>95865-5268</code>
               <region>CA</region>
            </postal>
            
            <phone>+1 916 538 2535</phone>
            <email>mrose17@gmail.com</email>
           
         </address>
      </author>

      <author fullname="D. Crocker" initials="D." role="editor" surname="Crocker">
         <organization>Brandenburg InternetWorking</organization>
         <address>
           <postal>
              <street>675 Spruce Dr.</street>
              <region>CA</region>
              <city>Sunnyvale</city>
              <country>USA</country>
              </postal>
            <phone>+1.408.246.8253</phone>
            <email>dcrocker@bbiw.net</email>
            <uri>http://bbiw.net</uri>
      </address>
      </author>

      <date month="January" year="2010"/>

      <workgroup>YAM</workgroup>

      <abstract>
         <t>This memo defines an extension to the SMTP service whereby an SMTP content body
            consisting of text containing octets outside of the US- ASCII octet range (hex 00-7F)
            may be relayed using SMTP.</t>
      </abstract>

   </front>

   <middle>

      <section title="Introduction">
         <t>Although SMTP is widely and robustly deployed, various extensions have been requested by
            parts of the Internet community. In particular, a significant portion of the Internet
            community wishes to exchange messages in which the content body consists of a MIME
            message <xref target="RFC2045"/><xref target="RFC2046"/> containing arbitrary
            octet-aligned material. This memo uses the mechanism described in <xref target="RFC5321"
            /> to define an extension to the SMTP service whereby such contents may be exchanged.
            Note that this extension does NOT eliminate the possibility of an SMTP server limiting
            line length; servers are free to implement this extension but nevertheless set a line
            length limit no lower than 1000 octets. Given that this restriction still applies, this
            extension does NOT provide a means for transferring unencoded binary via SMTP.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="param" title="Framework for the 8bit MIME Transport Extension">
         <t>The 8bit MIME transport extension is laid out as follows: <list style="numbers">
               <t>the name of the SMTP service extension defined here is 8bit-MIMEtransport;</t>

               <t>the EHLO keyword value associated with the extension is 8BITMIME;</t>

               <t>no parameter is used with the 8BITMIME EHLO keyword;</t>

               <t>one optional parameter using the keyword BODY is added to the MAIL FROM command.
                  The value associated with this parameter is a keyword indicating whether a 7bit
                  message (in strict compliance with <xref target="RFC5321"/>) or a MIME message (in
                  strict compliance with <xref target="RFC2046"/><xref target="RFC2045"/>) with
                  arbitrary octet content is being sent. The syntax of the value is as follows,
                  using the ABNF notation of <xref target="RFC5234"/>: <figure>
                     <artwork><![CDATA[body-value ::= "7BIT" / "8BITMIME"]]></artwork>
                  </figure></t>

               <t>no additional SMTP verbs are defined by this extension; and,</t>

               <t>the next section specifies how support for the extension affects the behavior of a
                  server and client SMTP.</t>
            </list></t>
      </section>

      <section title="The 8bit-MIMEtransport service extension">
         <t>When a client SMTP wishes to submit (using the MAIL command) a content body consisting
            of a MIME message containing arbitrary lines of octet-aligned material, it first issues
            the EHLO command to the server SMTP. If the server SMTP responds with code 250 to the
            EHLO command, and the response includes the EHLO keyword value 8BITMIME, then the server
            SMTP is indicating that it supports the extended MAIL command and will accept MIME
            messages containing arbitrary octet- aligned material.</t>

         <t>The extended MAIL command is issued by a client SMTP when it wishes to transmit a
            content body consisting of a MIME message containing arbitrary lines of octet-aligned
            material. The syntax for this command is identical to the MAIL command in <xref
               target="RFC5321"/>, except that a BODY parameter must appear after the address. Only
            one BODY parameter may be used in a single MAIL command. </t>


         <t>The complete syntax of this extended command is defined in <xref target="RFC5321"/>. The
            esmtp-keyword is BODY and the syntax for esmtp-value is given by the syntax for
            body-value shown above.</t>

         <t>The value associated with the BODY parameter indicates whether the content body which
            will be passed using the DATA command consists of a MIME message containing some
            arbitrary octet-aligned material ("8BITMIME") or is encoded entirely in accordance with
               <xref target="RFC5321"/> ("7BIT"). </t>
         <t>A server which supports the 8-bit MIME transport service extension shall preserve all
            bits in each octet passed using the DATA command. Naturally, the usual SMTP
            data-stuffing algorithm applies so that a content which contains the five-character
            sequence of <figure>
               <artwork><![CDATA[<CR> <LF> <DOT> <CR> <LF>]]></artwork>
            </figure> or a content that begins with the three-character sequence of <figure>
               <artwork><![CDATA[<DOT> <CR> <LF>]]></artwork>
            </figure> does not prematurely terminate the transfer of the content. Further, it should
            be noted that the CR-LF pair immediately preceding the final dot is considered part of
            the content. Finally, although the content body contains arbitrary lines of
            octet-aligned material, the length of each line (number of octets between two CR-LF
            pairs), is still subject to SMTP server line length restrictions (which can allow as few
            as 1000 octets, inclusive of the CR-LF pair, on a single line). This restriction means
            that this extension provides the necessary facilities for transferring a MIME object
            with the 8BIT content-transfer-encoding, it DOES NOT provide a means of transferring an
            object with the BINARY content-transfer-encoding. </t>

         <t>Once a server SMTP supporting the 8bit-MIMEtransport service extension accepts a content
            body containing octets with the high- order (8th) bit set, the server SMTP must deliver
            or relay the content in such a way as to preserve all bits in each octet.</t>

         <t>If a server SMTP does not support the 8-bit MIME transport extension (either by not
            responding with code 250 to the EHLO command, or by not including the EHLO keyword value
            8BITMIME in its response), then the client SMTP must not, under any circumstances,
            attempt to transfer a content which contains characters outside the US-ASCII octet range
            (hex 00-7F).</t>

         <t>A client SMTP has two options in this case: first, it may implement a gateway
            transformation to convert the message into valid 7bit MIME, or second, or may treat this
            as a permanent error and handle it in the usual manner for delivery failures. The
            specifics of the transformation from 8bit MIME to 7bit MIME are not described by this
            RFC; the conversion is nevertheless constrained in the following ways: <list
               style="numbers">
               <t>it must cause no loss of information; MIME transport encodings must be employed as
                  needed to insure this is the case, and</t>

               <t>the resulting message must be valid 7bit MIME.</t>
            </list></t>
      </section>


      <section title="Usage Example">
         <t>The following dialogue illustrates the use of the 8bit-MIMEtransport service extension: <figure>
               <artwork><![CDATA[S: <wait for connection on TCP port 25>
C: <open connection to server>
S: 220 dbc.mtview.ca.us SMTP service ready
C: EHLO ymir.claremont.edu
S: 250-dbc.mtview.ca.us says hello
S: 250 8BITMIME
C: MAIL FROM:<ned@ymir.claremont.edu> BODY=8BITMIME
S: 250 <ned@ymir.claremont.edu>... Sender and 8BITMIME ok
C: RCPT TO:<mrose@dbc.mtview.ca.us>
S: 250 <mrose@dbc.mtview.ca.us>... Recipient ok
C: DATA
S: 354 Send 8BITMIME message, ending in CRLF.CRLF.
 ...
C: .
S: 250 OK
C: QUIT
S: 250 Goodbye]]></artwork>
            </figure></t>
      </section>


      <section title="Security Considerations">
         <t>This RFC does not discuss security issues and is not believed to raise any security
            issues not already endemic in electronic mail and present in fully conforming
            implementations of <xref target="RFC5321"/>.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="IANA Considerations">

         <section title="SMTP service extension registration">

            <t>This document defines an SMTP service extension, and IANA is asked to add an entry to
               the SMTP Service Extensions registry, as follows: <list style="hanging">
                  <t hangText="Keyword: ">8BITMIME</t>
                  <t hangText="Description: ">SMTP transport of 8bit MIME content </t>
                  <t hangText="Reference: ">[[IANA: Insert this RFC number.]]</t>
                  <t hangText="Parameters: ">See <xref target="param"/> in this specification.</t>
               </list></t>

         </section>

         <section title="Acknowledgements">
            <t>E. Stefferud was an original author. This version of the specification was produced
               by the YAM working group.</t>
            <t>
               <list style="hanging">
                  <t hangText="Original acknowledgements:  ">This document represents a synthesis of
                     the ideas of many people and reactions to the ideas and proposals of others.
                     Randall Atkinson, Craig Everhart, Risto Kankkunen, and Greg Vaudreuil
                     contributed ideas and text sufficient to be considered co-authors. Other
                     important suggestions, text, or encouragement came from Harald Alvestrand, Jim
                     Conklin, Mark Crispin, Frank da Cruz, 'Olafur Gudmundsson, Per Hedeland,
                     Christian Huitma, Neil Katin, Eliot Lear, Harold A. Miller, Keith Moore, Dan
                     Oscarsson, Julian Onions, Neil Rickert, John Wagner, Rayan Zachariassen, and
                     the contributions of the entire IETF SMTP Working Group. Of course, none of the
                     individuals are necessarily responsible for the combination of ideas
                     represented here. Indeed, in some cases, the response to a particular criticism
                     was to accept the problem identification but to include an entirely different
                     solution from the one originally proposed. </t>
               </list></t>
         </section>
      </section>

   </middle>

   <back>

      <references title="Normative References">


         <reference anchor="RFC5321">

            <front>
               <title>Simple Mail Transfer Protocol</title>
               <author fullname="J. Klensin" initials="J." surname="Klensin">
                  <organization/>
               </author>
               <date month="October" year="2008"/>
               <abstract>
                  <t>This document is a specification of the basic protocol for Internet electronic
                     mail transport. It consolidates, updates, and clarifies several previous
                     documents, making all or parts of most of them obsolete. It covers the SMTP
                     extension mechanisms and best practices for the contemporary Internet, but does
                     not provide details about particular extensions. Although SMTP was designed as
                     a mail transport and delivery protocol, this specification also contains
                     information that is important to its use as a "mail submission" protocol for
                     "split-UA" (User Agent) mail reading systems and mobile environments.
                     [STANDARDS TRACK]</t>
               </abstract>
            </front>

            <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="5321"/>
            <format octets="225929" target="ftp://ftp.isi.edu/in-notes/rfc5321.txt" type="TXT"/>
         </reference>



         <reference anchor="RFC5322">

            <front>
               <title>Internet Message Format</title>
               <author fullname="Peter W. 
                  Resnick" initials="P." role="editor"
                  surname="Resnick">
                  <organization>Qualcomm Incorporated</organization>
                  <address>
                     <postal>
                        <street>5775 Morehouse Drive</street>
                        <city>San Diego</city>
                        <region>CA</region>
                        <code>92121-1714</code>
                        <country>US</country></postal>
                     <phone>+1 858 651 4478</phone>
                     <email>presnick@qualcomm.com</email>
                     <uri>http://www.qualcomm.com/~presnick/</uri></address>
               </author>
               <date month="October" year="2008"/>
               <abstract>
                  <t>This document specifies the Internet Message Format (IMF), a syntax for text
                     messages that are sent between computer users, within the framework of
                     "electronic mail" messages. This specification is a revision of Request For
                     Comments (RFC) 2822, which itself superseded Request For Comments (RFC) 822,
                     "Standard for the Format of ARPA Internet Text Messages", updating it to
                     reflect current practice and incorporating incremental changes that were
                     specified in other RFCs.</t>
               </abstract>
            </front>

            <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="5322"/>
            <format octets="122322" target="ftp://ftp.isi.edu/in-notes/rfc5322.txt" type="TXT"/>
            <format octets="213342" target="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/html/rfc5322.html"
               type="HTML"/>
            <format octets="174183" target="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/xml/rfc5322.xml"
               type="XML"/>
         </reference>

         <reference anchor="RFC5234">

            <front>
               <title>Augmented BNF for Syntax Specifications: ABNF</title>
               <author initials="D." surname="Crocker" fullname="D. Crocker">
                  <organization/>
               </author>
               <author initials="P." surname="Overell" fullname="P. Overell">
                  <organization/>
               </author>
               <date year="2008" month="January"/>
               <abstract>
                  <t>Internet technical specifications often need to define a formal syntax. Over
                     the years, a modified version of Backus-Naur Form (BNF), called Augmented BNF
                     (ABNF), has been popular among many Internet specifications. The current
                     specification documents ABNF. It balances compactness and simplicity with
                     reasonable representational power. The differences between standard BNF and
                     ABNF involve naming rules, repetition, alternatives, order-independence, and
                     value ranges. This specification also supplies additional rule definitions and
                     encoding for a core lexical analyzer of the type common to several Internet
                     specifications. [STANDARDS TRACK]</t>
               </abstract>
            </front>

            <seriesInfo name="STD" value="68"/>
            <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="5234"/>
            <format type="TXT" octets="26359" target="ftp://ftp.isi.edu/in-notes/rfc5234.txt"/>
         </reference>

         <reference anchor="RFC2045">

            <front>
               <title abbrev="Internet Message Bodies">Multipurpose Internet Mail Extensions (MIME)
                  Part One: Format of Internet Message Bodies</title>
               <author fullname="Ned Freed" initials="N." surname="Freed">
                  <organization>Innosoft International, Inc.</organization>
                  <address>
<postal>
<street>1050 East Garvey Avenue South</street>
<city>West Covina</city>
<region>CA</region>
<code>91790</code>
<country>US</country></postal>
<phone>+1 818 919 3600</phone>
<facsimile>+1 818 919 3614</facsimile>
<email>ned@innosoft.com</email></address>
               </author>
               <author fullname="Nathaniel S. Borenstein" initials="N.S." surname="Borenstein">
                  <organization>First Virtual Holdings</organization>
                  <address>
<postal>
<street>25 Washington Avenue</street>
<city>Morristown</city>
<region>NJ</region>
<code>07960</code>
<country>US</country></postal>
<phone>+1 201 540 8967</phone>
<facsimile>+1 201 993 3032</facsimile>
<email>nsb@nsb.fv.com</email></address>
               </author>
               <date month="November" year="1996"/>
               <abstract>
                  <t>STD 11, RFC 822, defines a message representation protocol specifying
                     considerable detail about US-ASCII message headers, and leaves the message
                     content, or message body, as flat US-ASCII text. This set of documents,
                     collectively called the Multipurpose Internet Mail Extensions, or MIME,
                     redefines the format of messages to allow for</t>
                  <t>(1) textual message bodies in character sets other than US-ASCII,</t>
                  <t>(2) an extensible set of different formats for non-textual message bodies,</t>
                  <t>(3) multi-part message bodies, and</t>
                  <t>(4) textual header information in character sets other than US-ASCII.</t>
                  <t>These documents are based on earlier work documented in RFC 934, STD 11, and
                     RFC 1049, but extends and revises them. Because RFC 822 said so little about
                     message bodies, these documents are largely orthogonal to (rather than a
                     revision of) RFC 822.</t>
                  <t>This initial document specifies the various headers used to describe the
                     structure of MIME messages. The second document, RFC 2046, defines the general
                     structure of the MIME media typing system and defines an initial set of media
                     types. The third document, RFC 2047, describes extensions to RFC 822 to allow
                     non-US-ASCII text data in Internet mail header fields. The fourth document, RFC
                     2048, specifies various IANA registration procedures for MIME-related
                     facilities. The fifth and final document, RFC 2049, describes MIME conformance
                     criteria as well as providing some illustrative examples of MIME message
                     formats, acknowledgements, and the bibliography.</t>
                  <t>These documents are revisions of RFCs 1521, 1522, and 1590, which themselves
                     were revisions of RFCs 1341 and 1342. An appendix in RFC 2049 describes
                     differences and changes from previous versions.</t>
               </abstract>
            </front>

            <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="2045"/>
            <format octets="72932" target="ftp://ftp.isi.edu/in-notes/rfc2045.txt" type="TXT"/>
         </reference>



         <reference anchor="RFC2046">

            <front>
               <title abbrev="Media Types">Multipurpose Internet Mail Extensions (MIME) Part Two:
                  Media Types</title>
               <author fullname="Ned Freed" initials="N." surname="Freed">
                  <organization>Innosoft International, Inc.</organization>
                  <address>
<postal>
<street>1050 East Garvey Avenue South</street>
<city>West Covina</city>
<region>CA</region>
<code>91790</code>
<country>US</country></postal>
<phone>+1 818 919 3600</phone>
<facsimile>+1 818 919 3614</facsimile>
<email>ned@innosoft.com</email></address>
               </author>
               <author fullname="Nathaniel S. Borenstein" initials="N." surname="Borenstein">
                  <organization>First Virtual Holdings</organization>
                  <address>
<postal>
<street>25 Washington Avenue</street>
<city>Morristown</city>
<region>NJ</region>
<code>07960</code>
<country>US</country></postal>
<phone>+1 201 540 8967</phone>
<facsimile>+1 201 993 3032</facsimile>
<email>nsb@nsb.fv.com</email></address>
               </author>
               <date month="November" year="1996"/>
               <abstract>
                  <t>STD 11, RFC 822 defines a message representation protocol specifying
                     considerable detail about US-ASCII message headers, but which leaves the
                     message content, or message body, as flat US-ASCII text. This set of documents,
                     collectively called the Multipurpose Internet Mail Extensions, or MIME,
                     redefines the format of messages to allow for</t>
                  <t>(1) textual message bodies in character sets other than US-ASCII,</t>
                  <t>(2) an extensible set of different formats for non-textual message bodies,</t>
                  <t>(3) multi-part message bodies, and</t>
                  <t>(4) textual header information in character sets other than US-ASCII.</t>
                  <t>These documents are based on earlier work documented in RFC 934, STD 11 and RFC
                     1049, but extends and revises them. Because RFC 822 said so little about
                     message bodies, these documents are largely orthogonal to (rather than a
                     revision of) RFC 822.</t>
                  <t>The initial document in this set, RFC 2045, specifies the various headers used
                     to describe the structure of MIME messages. This second document defines the
                     general structure of the MIME media typing system and defines an initial set of
                     media types. The third document, RFC 2047, describes extensions to RFC 822 to
                     allow non-US-ASCII text data in Internet mail header fields. The fourth
                     document, RFC 2048, specifies various IANA registration procedures for
                     MIME-related facilities. The fifth and final document, RFC 2049, describes MIME
                     conformance criteria as well as providing some illustrative examples of MIME
                     message formats, acknowledgements, and the bibliography.</t>
                  <t>These documents are revisions of RFCs 1521 and 1522, which themselves were
                     revisions of RFCs 1341 and 1342. An appendix in RFC 2049 describes differences
                     and changes from previous versions.</t>
               </abstract>
            </front>

            <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="2046"/>
            <format octets="105854" target="ftp://ftp.isi.edu/in-notes/rfc2046.txt" type="TXT"/>
         </reference>

      </references>

   </back>

</rfc>
