<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY rfc2205 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2205.xml">
]>
<rfc category="std"
     docName="draft-narayanan-tsvwg-rsvp-resource-sharing-01.txt"
     ipr="trust200811">
  <?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>

  <?rfc toc="yes" ?>

  <?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>

  <?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>

  <?rfc iprnotified="no" ?>

  <?rfc strict="yes" ?>

  <front>
    <title abbrev="RSVP Resource Sharing Extensions ">RSVP Extensions for
    Flexible Resource Sharing</title>

    <author fullname="Ashok Narayanan" initials="A." surname="Narayanan">
      <organization abbrev="Cisco">Cisco Systems</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>1414 Massachusetts Ave</street>

          <city>Boxborough</city>

          <region>MA</region>

          <code>01719</code>

          <country>United States</country>
        </postal>

        <email>ashokn@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Francois Le Faucheur" initials="F."
            surname="Le Faucheur">
      <organization abbrev="Cisco">Priority Cisco Systems</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Greenside, 400 Avenue de Roumanille</street>

          <city>Sophia Antipolis</city>

          <code>06410</code>

          <country>France</country>
        </postal>

        <phone>+33 4 97 23 26 19</phone>

        <email>flefauch@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Subha Dhesikan" initials="S." surname="Dhesikan">
      <organization abbrev="Cisco">Cisco Systems</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>170 W. Tasman Drive</street>

          <city>San Jose</city>

          <region>CA</region>

          <code>95134</code>

          <country>United States</country>
        </postal>

        <email>sdhesika@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date day="25" month="October" year="2009" />

    <area>Transport</area>

    <workgroup>TSVWG</workgroup>

    <abstract>
      <t>RSVP signaling can be used to make end-to-end resource reservations
      in an IP network in order to guarantee the QoS required by certain
      flows. ...</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>The RSVP Resource Reservation Protocol <xref target="RFC2205"></xref>
      specifies a mechanism to reserve resources for signalled flows that
      require QoS from the network. One of the features of RSVP is the ability
      to share resources between separate flows. The scope of flows between
      which resources can be shared is currently defined by the SESSION
      object. This object contains the destination L3+L4 transport address of
      the data flow. This means that RSVP currently allows sharing of
      resources between flows with different source transport address but
      sharing the same destination transport. This is useful for multicast
      scenarios, for example when multiple sources can transmit for the same
      multicast application but only one source ever transmit at a given time:
      it is then desirable to share the resource across flows from teh
      multiple senders on all common links. However, RSVP cannot today share
      resources between flows with different destination L3+L4 transport
      addresses. There are certain cases where it is desirable to share
      resources between two flows with different destination L3+L4 transport
      addresses. Two examples are given below.</t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>Voice Call-Waiting: A bidirectional voice call between two
          endpoints A and B is signalled using two separate unidirectional
          RSVP reservations for the flows A-&gt;B and B-&gt;A. If endpoint A
          wishes to put the A-B call on hold and join a separate A-C call, it
          is desirable that network resources on common links be shared
          between the A-B and A-C calls. The B-&gt;A and C-&gt;A subflows of
          the call can share resources using existing RSVP sharing mechanisms,
          but only if they use the same destination L3+L4 addressing. However,
          there is no way in RSVP today to share the resources between the
          A-&gt;B and A-&gt;C subflows of the call since by definition the
          RSVP reservations for these subflows must have different L3
          addresses in the SESSION objects.</t>

          <t>Voice Shared Line: A single number that rings multiple endpoints
          (which may be geographically diverse), such as phone lines on a
          manager's desk and their assistant. A VoIP system that models these
          calls as multiple P2P unicast pre-ring reservations would result in
          significantly overcounting bandwidth on shared links, since today
          unicast reservations to different endpoints cannot share
          bandwidth.</t>

          <t>Symmetric NAT: RSVP permits sharing of resources between multiple
          flows addressed to the same destination D, even from different
          senders S1 and S2. However, if D is behind a NAT operating in
          symmetric mode<xref target="RFC3489"></xref>, it is possible that
          the destination L4 transport addresses of the flows S1-&gt;D and
          S2-&gt;D may be different outside the NAT. In this case, these flows
          cannot share resources using RSVP today, since the SESSION objects
          for these two flows outside the NAT would have different L4
          transport addresses.</t>
        </list>The fundamental problem seen here is due to overloading of the
      semantics of the SESSION object. Specifically, the SESSION object as
      defined in RFC2205 has three separate functions:</t>

      <t><list style="numbers">
          <t>To function as a unique key</t>

          <t>To specify the destination L3+L4 address of the stream</t>

          <t>To define the set of flows that may share resources</t>
        </list>As specified today, the SESSION object must provide all of
      these functions. As RSVP is extended to support additional
      functionality, this combination of functionality imposes undesirable
      constraints. This has already been seen during the development of
      MPLS/TE <xref target="RFC3209"></xref>, where the SESSION object only
      specifies the destination L3 address of the flow, plus a sender-selected
      Tunnel ID. Since this is insufficient to guarantee key uniqueness, a
      further Extended Tunnel ID was added. As described in the examples
      above, requiring flows that share resources to also share their
      destination L3+L4 address is also imposing undesirable constraints.</t>

      <t>This document describes a mechanism to separate the definition of
      flows that can share resources, from flows that share a destination
      L3+L4 address. A new Resource Sharing ID object is defined which
      specifies the scope of resource sharing, independent of the contents of
      the SESSION object. By separating the scope definition of resource
      sharing from the SESSION object, the constraints described above are
      removed and teh sharing scenarios of interest can be supported.</t>

      <section title="Conventions Used in This Document">
        <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
        "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
        document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
        target="RFC2119"></xref>.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Changes since the previous version">
        <t><list style="symbols">
            <t>Further definition of format of Resource Sharing ID object.</t>

            <t>Editorial cleanups</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="extensions"
             title="RSVP Extensions for Flexible Resource Sharing">
      <t>This section describes extensions to existing RSVP procedures to
      support flexible resource sharing between reservations. All these rules
      apply to routers that support the resource sharing extensions described
      here.</t>

      <t>We define a new optional Resource Sharing ID (RSID) object to be
      carried in RSVP signaling messages. In summary, different signaled RSVP
      flows that carry the same RSID object will share resources, regardless
      of the contents of their SESSION objects. The RSID is carried in the
      flow-descriptor section of the Resv message. The RSID, if present, is
      associated with the preceding FILTER_SPEC. No more than one RSID may
      follow each FILTER_SPEC. The flow descriptor may include other
      per-filter objects (like RECORD_ROUTE); implementations MUST accept the
      RSID in any order relative to these objects, as long as they are
      associated with the same FILTER_SPEC. The RSID MAY be inserted by the
      RSVP endpoint generating the message, and all RSVP routers MUST forward
      it unmodified with the associated FILTER_SPEC.</t>

      <t>The proposed RBNF <xref target="RFC5511"></xref> for the Path and
      Resv messages with the new RSID is given below:</t>

      <t><figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[      
      <Resv Message> ::=       <Common Header> [ <INTEGRITY> ]
                               <SESSION>  <RSVP_HOP>
                               <TIME_VALUES>
                               [ <RESV_CONFIRM> ]  [ <SCOPE> ]
                               [ <POLICY_DATA> ... ]
                               <STYLE> <flow descriptor list>

      <flow descriptor list> ::= empty
                               | <FF flow descriptor list>
                               | <SE flow descriptor>
                               | <WF flow descriptor>

      <FF flow descriptor list> ::= <FLOWSPEC> <FILTER_SPEC>
                               | <FF flow descriptor list>
                                 <FF flow descriptor>

      <FF flow descriptor> ::= [ <FLOWSPEC> ] <FILTER_SPEC> 

      <SE flow descriptor> ::= <FLOWSPEC> <SE filter spec list>

      <SE filter spec list> ::= <SE filter spec>
                               | <SE filter spec list> <SE filter spec>

      <SE filter spec> ::= <FILTER_SPEC> [ <RSID> ]
 
      <WF flow descriptor> ::= <FLOWSPEC> [ <RSID> ]

]]></artwork>
        </figure></t>

      <t>The RSID MAY also be included in a Path message, as part of the
      sender descriptor. However, any RSID in a Path message is purely
      advisory to the receiver and SHOULD be ignored by all RSVP routers. A
      receiver proxy as defined in <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-tsvwg-rsvp-proxy-approaches"></xref>, SHOULD reflect
      any RSID received in a Path, in the Resv generated in response to that
      Path. This MAY be overridden by local policy on the receiver proxy.</t>

      <t></t>

      <figure>
        <artwork><![CDATA[
      <Path Message> ::=       <Common Header> [ <INTEGRITY> ]
                               <SESSION> <RSVP_HOP>
                               <TIME_VALUES>
                               [ <EXPLICIT_ROUTE> ]
                               <LABEL_REQUEST>
                               [ <SESSION_ATTRIBUTE> ]
                               [ <POLICY_DATA> ... ]
                               <sender descriptor>

      <sender descriptor> ::=  <SENDER_TEMPLATE> <SENDER_TSPEC>
                               [ <ADSPEC> ] [ <RSID> ]
                              

]]></artwork>
      </figure>

      <t></t>

      <t>RSVP routers MUST share resources across flows (defined by
      &lt;SESSION, FILTER_SPEC&gt; pairs) that are signalled with the same
      RSID in the Resv message. Two different RSVP reservations with different
      SESSION objects may contain the same RSID in their flow descriptors;
      when admitting the second reservation, the RSVP router MUST recognize
      that the RSID is the same as an existing reservation, and MUST share
      resources across these two reservations when admitting the second one.
      RSVP routers MUST NOT share resources between a flow signaled with an
      RSID an a flow signaled without an RSID. With this exception, the
      existing reservation sharing rules described in <xref
      target="RFC2205"></xref> continue to apply for all flows signaled
      without RSID objects. Therefore, flows signaled without RSID objects
      will share bandwidth as per the rules of <xref
      target="RFC2205"></xref>.</t>

      <t>The style of a reservation, as denoted by the STYLE object, continues
      to function as per <xref target="RFC2205"></xref>, as an indicator of
      reservation sharing. Specifically, reservations signaled using a
      Distinct style (Fixed-Filter) MUST NOT share resources. Therefore, the
      RSID MUST NOT be included in any Resv message which contains a STYLE
      object of Fixed-Filter. If a RSVP router receives a Resv with a STYLE
      object indicating Fixed-Filter as well as a flow descriptor containing a
      RSID, the RSVP router MUST reject this message and generate a ResvError
      with error code {Resource Sharing Error, Style Incompatible With RSID
      Object}. For reservations signaled using one of the Shared styles, the
      RSID may be used to join together reservations that would ordinarily not
      have shared resources (e.g. SE or WF-style reservations with different
      SESSION objects but same RSID), or split apart reservations that would
      otherwise have shared resources (e.g. SE-style reservations with the
      same SESSION, but different FILTER_SPEC and RSID objects).</t>

      <t>When processing a Resv received with a RSID, a router looks for other
      installed reservations with the same RSID, irrespective of SESSION
      object. If such reservations are found, the new reservation is merged
      with those existing installed reservations, using the reservation
      merging techniques already described in <xref
      target="RFC2205"></xref>:</t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>If the new incoming reservation caused any component of the
          merged FLOWSPEC to change, the new merged reservation MUST be
          readmitted immediately.</t>

          <t>If readmission succeeds, the reservations are forwarded
          upstream.</t>

          <t>If readmission fails, the router MUST reject the incoming Resv
          and generate a ResvError of the same type as it would ordinarily
          generate if readmission was triggered in a different way (e.g.
          signaled bandwidth change). A failed readmission attempt MUST NOT
          remove existing resources allocated to existing reservations</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>For SE-style reservations, RSVP state pertaining to a single flow (as
      defined by a &lt;SESSION, FILTER_SPEC&gt; pair) MUST NOT have two
      conflicting RSID objects. If a RSVP router receives a Resv message
      pertaining to a &lt;SESSION, FILTER_SPEC&gt; which corresponds to
      previously installed state, the router MUST compare the NHOP of this
      message to the NHOP of the previously installed reservation state.</t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>If these NHOPs are different, the router MUST reject the new Resv
          and generate a ResvError of the form {Admission Control Failure,
          RSID Mismatch}, defined below. The existing reservation MUST be left
          in place.</t>

          <t>If the NHOPs are the same, this is treated as replacement of the
          existing RSID. The reservation MUST be readmitted immediately with
          the new RSID.</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>Note that the presence of the RSID only controls which reservations
      may share resources, not _how_ these resources are shared. The method of
      computing the size and parameters of a pool of shared reservations
      remains unchanged (e.g. for IntServ-style FLOWSPECs, the merged FLOWSPEC
      is computed by taking the envelope of each term of the individual
      FLOWSPECs). RSVP routers continue to support their current mechanisms
      for actually sharing resources, such as a shared packet queue; the
      presence of the RSID only alters the set of reservations that use the
      shared queue. If an implementation is unable to program its traffic
      control subsystem to share resources between a set of reservations with
      the same RSID (for example, a classifier which cannot direct flows with
      different destination IP addresses into the same queue), the
      implementation MUST reject the reservation and issue a ResvError with
      error code {Traffic Control Error, Service conflict}.</t>

      <t>The use of RSID is supported for WF style reservations. The rules
      described above apply, with the flow being defined only by the
      &lt;SESSION&gt; object. Therefore, RSID can only be used to share
      resources between reservations with different SESSION objects. Also, the
      rule preventing conflicting RSID objects now applies for RSVP state with
      the same SESSION only.</t>

      <t>The use of RSID is fully supported for multicast reservations.</t>

      <section title="RSVP Object Definitions">
        <t>We specify a new Resource Sharing ID object as described above. The
        class number of this object will be of the form 11bbbbbb, so RSVP
        implementations that do not support the extensions defined in the
        present document will ignore and forward this object unmodified.</t>

        <t>The RSID object contains a Resource Sharing ID which conditions
        sharing of resources as specified above. Its length is variable, and
        is conveyed to the RSVP implementation receiving the RSID object
        inside the corresponding RSVP object header.</t>

        <t>It is the responsibility of the entity(ies) that allocate(s) the
        Resource Sharing IDs to ensure that those will result in the desired
        resource sharing across all flows. When there are multiple entities
        allocating Resource Sharing IDs, then it is the responsibility of each
        allocating entitity to ensure its allocated RSIDs will not
        unintentionally collide with RSIDs allocated by other entities for
        other flows. Some examples of how implementations can avoid RSID
        collision and achieve proper RSID allocation are:</t>

        <t><list style="symbols">
            <t>By composing the RSID out of a context selector (such as the
            globally unique IP address of the allocating node), combined with
            a locally allocated ID.</t>

            <t>By using a UUID allocation mechanism (such as is specified in
            <xref target="RFC4122"></xref>)</t>

            <t>By using internal application level allocation or signaling
            mechanisms</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>It is possible that different vendors may use different mechanisms
        to generate Resource Sharing IDs that may collide with each other. To
        prevent this, the RSID object includes disambiguating information that
        ensures RSIDs generated by different vendors do not collide. The RSID
        object can include disambiguation of two types:</t>

        <t><list style="symbols">
            <t>Allocator-ID: The RSID object can include the IPv4 or IPv6
            address of the allocating node.</t>

            <t>Vendor Private: The RSID object can include the IANA Private
            Enterprise Number defined in <xref target="RFC2578"></xref> and
            maintained at <xref target="ENT"></xref>.</t>
          </list></t>

        <t><figure>
            <preamble></preamble>

            <artwork><![CDATA[
  o    RESOURCE SHARING ID: 

           Class = TBA, C-Type = 1 (IPv4 Allocator ID)

           +-------------+-------------+-------------+-------------+
           |       Length (bytes)      |  Class=TBA  |   C-Type=1  |
           +-------------+-------------+-------------+-------------+
           |     IPv4 address of allocating node  (32 bits)        |
           +-------------+-------------+-------------+-------------+
           |                                                       |
           .                                                       .
           .         Resource Sharing ID (variable length)         .
           .                                                       .
           |                                                       |
           +-------------+-------------+-------------+-------------+



           Class = TBA, C-Type = 2 (IPv6 Allocator ID)

           +-------------+-------------+-------------+-------------+
           |       Length (bytes)      |  Class=TBA  |   C-Type=2  |
           +-------------+-------------+-------------+-------------+
           |                                                       |
           |            IPv6 address of allocating node            |
           |                     (128 bits)                        |
           |                                                       |
           +-------------+-------------+-------------+-------------+
           |                                                       |
           .                                                       .
           .         Resource Sharing ID (variable length)         .
           .                                                       .
           |                                                       |
           +-------------+-------------+-------------+-------------+



           Class = TBA, C-Type = 3 (Vendor Enterprise Number ID)

           +-------------+-------------+-------------+-------------+
           |       Length (bytes)      |  Class=TBA  |   C-Type=3  |
           +-------------+-------------+-------------+-------------+
           |           Vendor Enterprise Number (32 bits)          |
           +-------------+-------------+-------------+-------------+
           |                                                       |
           .                                                       .
           .         Resource Sharing ID (variable length)         .
           .                                                       .
           |                                                       |
           +-------------+-------------+-------------+-------------+
            ]]></artwork>

            <postamble></postamble>
          </figure></t>

        <t>RSVP midpoints MUST treat the contents of the RSID object as
        opaque. The only operation that RSVP midpoints perform on the RSID is
        an equality test with other RSIDs. Two RSIDs are equal if and only if
        :</t>

        <t><list style="symbols">
            <t>they have the same object length specified in the RSVP object
            header, AND</t>

            <t>a bytewise comparison of both RSIDs, up to the object length
            specified in the RSVP object header, yields an equal result.</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <!-- -->

    <section title="Security Considerations">
      <t>Existing RSVP security concerns and mechanisms apply here. In
      particular, the RSID imposes no new security considerations from the
      perspective of trusted/untrusted RSVP neighbors, since it does not alter
      message processing rules. Neighbor authentication and message integrity
      rules remain unchanged and MUST NOT be affected by the presence of RSID
      objects in messages.</t>

      <t>One possible additional concern with the RSID is the ability for one
      endpoint to share bandwidth with a different reservation. Two potential
      issues with this are:<list style="symbols">
          <t>A flow could piggyback on a different reservation and therefore
          get service that is available to the other flow but should not be
          available to this one. It should be noted that determining allowable
          services offered to a reservation request is done by examining other
          parts of the signaled message, such as policy objects, credentials,
          and application ID (). RSVP implementations MUST continue to
          implement their current policy enforcement rules for messages that
          contain RSID objects.</t>

          <t>A flow could merge with another flow and attempt to deny it
          service by requesting an unreasonably large amount of bandwidth.
          This is similar to the "Killer Reservation" problems outlined in
          <xref target="RFC2205"></xref>. The same solutions described therein
          apply to flows which are merged with RSID.</t>
        </list></t>

      <t></t>
    </section>

    <section title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>IANA is requested to assign a new class number of the form 11bbbbbb
      for the RESOURCE SHARING ID object.</t>

      <t>IANA is also requested (see <xref target="extensions"></xref>) to
      assign a new Error Subcode under the Admission Control Failure code (1)
      for "RSID Mismatch". Also, new Error Code are requested :</t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>"RSID Mismatch"</t>

          <t>"Style Incompatible With RSID Object".</t>
        </list></t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgments">
      <t>This document benefited from discussions with James Polk, Aun Kudur,
      and Adrian Farrel</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      &rfc2205;

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3489"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4122"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2747"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3097"
?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3209"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3182"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2578"?>

      <reference anchor="ENT"
                 target="http://www.iana.org/assignments/enterprise-numbers">
        <front>
          <title>Private Enterprise Numbers</title>

          <author>
            <organization>IANA</organization>
          </author>
        </front>

        <format target="http://www.iana.org/assignments/enterprise-numbers"
                type="TXT" />
      </reference>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5511"?>

      <?rfc ?>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-tsvwg-rsvp-security-groupkeying'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-tsvwg-rsvp-proxy-approaches'?>

      <?rfc ?>

      <?rfc ?>

      <?rfc ?>
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
