<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<rfc category="std" docName="draft-knoll-idr-qos-attribute-09"
     ipr="trust200902" submissionType="IETF">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="BGP QoS Marking Community">BGP Extended Community for QoS
    Marking</title>

    <author fullname="Thomas Martin Knoll" initials="Th. M." surname="Knoll">
      <organization>Chemnitz University of Technology</organization>

      <address>
        <email>knoll@etit.tu-chemnitz.de</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date day="07" month="January" year="2012" />

    <area>Routing Area</area>

    <workgroup>Inter-Domain Routing Working Group</workgroup>

    <keyword>Draft</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>This document specifies a simple signalling mechanism for
      inter-domain QoS marking using several instances of a new BGP Extended
      Community. Class based packet marking and forwarding is currently
      performed independently within ASes. The new QoS marking community makes
      the targeted Per Hop Behaviour within the IP prefix advertising AS and
      the currently applied marking at the interconnection point known to all
      access and transit ASes. This enables individual (re-)marking and
      possibly forwarding treatment adaptation to the original QoS class setup
      of the respective originating AS. The extended community provides the
      means to signal QoS markings on different layers, which are linked
      together in QoS Class Sets. It provides inter-domain and cross-layer
      insight into the QoS class mapping of the source AS with minimal
      signalling traffic.</t>
    </abstract>

    <note title="Requirements Language">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
      document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
      target="RFC2119">RFC 2119</xref>.</t>
    </note>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>A new BGP Extended Community is defined in this document, which
      carries QoS marking information for different network layer technologies
      across ASes. This extended community is called "QoS Marking". This new
      community provides a mechanism within BGP-4 <xref
      target="RFC4271"></xref> for associating all advertised prefixes of the
      AS with its differentiated QoS Class Marking information. It allows for
      the consistent exchange of class encoding values between BGP peers for
      physical, data link and network QoS mechanisms. These labels can be used
      to control the distribution of this information, for the encoding and
      for treatment adjustments within the AS or for other applications. One
      globally seen QoS Class Set per AS is required for scalability reasons.
      It is the AS provider's responsibility to enforce the globally signalled
      Set throughout the AS.</t>

      <t>Several QoS Marking communities MAY be included in a single BGP
      UPDATE message. They are virtually linked together by means of an
      identical "QoS Set Number" field. Each QoS Marking community is encoded
      as 8-octet tuple, as defined in <xref
      target="Attribute_Definition"></xref>. Signalled QoS Class Sets are
      assumed to be valid for traffic crossing this AS. If different QoS
      strategies are used with an AS, its provider is responsible for
      consistent transport of transit traffic across this inhomogeneous
      domain. In all transit forwarding cases, QoS based tunnelling mechanisms
      are the means of choice for transparent traffic transport.</t>

      <t>The availability of the "Best Effort" forwarding class is implied and
      defaults to a zero encoding on all signalled layers. It is therefore not
      necessary to include QoS Marking communities for the Best Effort Class
      as long as the default encoding is in place.</t>

      <t>Class overload prevention can be achieved by means of the signalling
      described in <xref target="I-D.knoll-idr-cos-interconnect"></xref>. It
      is a complementary concept to limit the usage of advertised classes in a
      fair and square manner.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Problem Statement">
      <t>Current inter-domain interconnection is "best effort" interconnection
      only. That is, traffic forwarding between ASes is without traffic class
      differentiation and without any forwarding guarantee. It is common for
      network providers to reset any IP packet class markings to zero, the
      best effort DSCP marking, at the AS ingress router, which eliminates any
      traffic differentiation. Some providers perform higher layer
      classification at the ingress in order to guess the forwarding
      requirements and to match on their AS internal QoS forwarding policy.
      There is no standardized set of classes, no standardized marking (class
      encoding) and no standardized forwarding behaviour, which cross-domain
      traffic could rely on. QoS policy decisions are taken by network
      providers independently and in an uncoordinated fashion.</t>

      <t>This general statement does not cover the existing individual
      agreements, which do offer quality based interconnection with strict QoS
      guarantees. However, such SLA based agreements are of bilateral or
      multilateral nature and do not offer a means for a general "better than
      best effort" interconnection. This draft does not aim for making such
      SLA based agreements become void. On the contrary, those agreements are
      expected to exist for special traffic forwarding paths with strictly
      guaranteed QoS.</t>

      <t>There are many approaches, which propose proper inter-domain QoS
      strategies including inter-domain parameter signalling, metering,
      monitoring and misbehaviour detection. Such complex strategies get close
      to guaranteed QoS based forwarding at the expense of dynamic
      measurements and adjustments, of state keeping on resource usage vs.
      traffic load and in particular of possibly frequent inter-domain
      signalling.</t>

      <t>The proposed QoS Class marking approach dissociates from the complex
      latter solutions and targets the general "better than best effort"
      interconnection in coexistence with SLA based agreements. It enables
      ASes to make their supported Class Sets and their encoding globally
      known. In other words, this support information constitutes a simple map
      of QoS enabled roads in transit and destination ASes.</t>

      <t>Signalling the coarse information about the supported class set and
      its cross-layer encoding within the involved forwarding domains of the
      selected AS path removes the lack of knowledge about the over-all
      available traffic differentiation. AS providers are enabled to make an
      informed decision about supported class encodings and might adopt to
      them. No guarantees are offered by this "better than best effort"
      approach, but as much as easily possible traffic differentiation without
      the need for frequent inter-domain signalling and for costly ingress
      re-classification will be achieved.</t>

      <t>Remarking the class encoding of customer traffic in order to match
      neighbouring class set encodings is reasonable at AS interconnection
      points. For AS internal forwarding, the encapsulation within any kind of
      QoS supporting tunnelling technology is highly recommended. The
      cross-layer signalling of QoS encoding will further ease the setup of
      QoS based inter-domain tunnelling.</t>

      <t>The general confidentiality concern of disclosing AS internal policy
      information is addressed in <xref target="Confidentiality"></xref>. In
      short, network providers can signal a different class set in the QoS
      Marking communities to the one actually used internally. The different
      class sets (externally signalled vs. internally applied one) require an
      undisclosed strictly defined mapping at the AS borders between the two.
      This way, a distinction between internal and external QoS Class Sets can
      be achieved.</t>

      <t>The general need for class based accounting is not addressed by this
      draft. MIB extensions are also required, which separate traffic
      variables by traffic marking. It is expected for both that existing
      procedures can be reused in a class based manner.</t>

      <t></t>
    </section>

    <section title="Related Work">
      <t>A number of QoS improvement approaches have been proposed before and
      a selection will be briefly mentioned in this section.</t>

      <t>Most of the approaches perform parameter signalling. <xref
      target="I-D.jacquenet-bgp-qos"></xref> defines the QOS_NLRI attribute,
      which is used for propagating QoS-related information associated to the
      NLRI (Network Layer Reachability Information) information conveyed in a
      BGP UPDATE message. Single so called "QoS routes" are signalled, which
      fulfil certain QoS requirements. Several information types are defined
      for the attribute, which concentrate on rate and delay type
      parameters.</t>

      <t><xref target="I-D.boucadair-qos-bgp-spec"> </xref> is based on the
      specified QOS_NLRI attribute and introduces some modifications to it.
      The notion of AS-local and extended QoS classes is used, which
      effectively describes the local set of QoS performance parameters or
      their cross-domain combined result. Two groups of QoS delivery services
      are distinguished, where the second group concentrates on ID associated
      QoS parameter propagation between adjacent peers. The first group is of
      more interest for this draft since it concentrates on the "identifier
      propagation" such as the DSCP value for example. However, this
      signalling is specified for the information exchange between adjacent
      peers only and assumes the existence of extended QoS classes and offline
      traffic engineering functions.</t>

      <t>Another approach is described in <xref
      target="I-D.liang-bgp-qos"></xref>. It associates a list of QoS metrics
      with each prefix by extending the existing AS_PATH attribute format.
      Hop-by-hop metric accumulation is performed as the AS_PATH gets extended
      in relaying ASes. Metrics are generically specified as a list of
      TLV-style attribute elements. The metrics such as bandwidth and delay
      are exemplary mentioned in the draft.</t>

      <t>One contribution specialized in the signalling of Type Of Service
      (TOS) values which are in turn directly mapped to DSCP values in section
      3.2 of the draft <xref
      target="I-D.zhang-idr-bgp-extcommunity-qos"></xref>. The TOS value is
      signalled within an Extended Community Attribute and, if it is
      understood correctly, will be applied to a certain route. An additional
      value field is used to identify, which routes belong to which signalled
      TOS community. Who advertises such attributes and whether they are of
      transitive or non-transitive type remains unspecified.</t>

      <t>The most comprehensive analysis (although not an IETF draft) is given
      in <xref target="MIT_CFP"></xref>. This "Inter- provider Quality of
      Service" white paper examines the inter-domain QoS requirements and
      derives a comprehensive approach for the introduction of at least one
      QoS class with guaranteed delay parameters. The implementation aspects
      of metering, monitoring, parameter feedback and impairment allocations
      are all considered in the white paper. However, QoS guarantees and
      parameter signalling is beyond the intention of this QoS Marking
      draft.</t>

      <t>Other drafts may also be considered as related work as long as they
      convey QoS marking information and might be "misused" for QoS class
      signalling.</t>

      <t>One example is the usage of the "Traffic Engineering Attribute" as
      defined in <xref target="RFC5543"></xref>. However, the attribute is
      non-transitive and the LSP encoding types are not generally applicable
      to inter-domain interconnection types. Its usage of the targeted QoS
      Marking signalling is not possible. The included maximum bandwidth of
      each of eight priority classes, could however be used in future draft
      extensions.</t>

      <t>The second example is the current "Dissemination of flow
      specification rules" draft <xref target="RFC5575"></xref>. It defines a
      new BGP NLRI encoding format, which can be used to distribute traffic
      flow specifications. Such flow specification can also include DSCP
      values as type 11 in the NLRI. Furthermore, one could signal
      configuration actions together with the DSCP encoding, which could be
      used for filtering purposes or even trigger remarking and route
      selection with it. Such usage is not defined in the draft and can hardly
      be achieved because of the following reasons. The flow specification is
      focused on single flows, which might even be part of an aggregate. Such
      fine grained specification is counterproductive for the coarse grained
      general QoS Marking approach of this draft. The novel approach of
      cross-layer QoS Marking could also not be incorporated, which might be
      essential for future tunnelled inter-domain interconnection.</t>

      <t><vspace blankLines="12" /></t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Attribute_Definition"
             title="Definition of the QoS Marking Community" toc="default">
      <t></t>

      <section title="Extended Community Type">
        <t>The new QoS Marking community is encoded in a BGP Extended
        Community Attribute <xref target="RFC4360"></xref>. It is therefore a
        transitive optional BGP attribute with Type Code 16. An adoption to
        the simple BGP Community Attribute encoding <xref
        target="RFC1997"></xref> is not defined in this document. The actual
        encoding within the BGP Extended Community Attribute is as
        follows.</t>

        <t>The QoS Marking community is of regular type which results in a 1
        octet Type field followed by 7 octets for the QoS marking structure.
        The Type is IANA-assignable and marks the community as transitive
        across ASes. The type number has been assigned by IANA to 0x04 <xref
        target="IANA_EC"></xref>.</t>

        <t>Optionally, a non-transitive Type value assignment of 0x44 is
        provided, which allows for the AS internal marking information
        exchange. The community format remains untouched for the
        non-transitive version.</t>

        <figure anchor="Figure_1">
          <artwork><![CDATA[ 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0|                                               |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+   7 octet QoS Marking community structure     |
|                                                               |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
]]></artwork>
        </figure>
      </section>

      <section title="Structure of the QoS Marking Community">
        <t>The QoS Marking community provides a flexible encoding structure
        for various QoS Markings on different layers. This flexibility is
        achieved by a Flags, a QoS Set Number and a Technology Type field
        within the 7 octet structure as defined below.</t>

        <figure anchor="Figure_2">
          <artwork><![CDATA[ 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|    Flags      | QoS Set Number|Technology Type| QoS Marking Oh|
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
| QoS Marking Ol| QoS Marking A |0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0|
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
]]></artwork>
        </figure>

        <t><vspace blankLines="12" />Flags:</t>

        <figure anchor="Figure_3">
          <artwork><![CDATA[ 0  1  2  3  4  5  6  7 
+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+
|0  0 |P |R |I |A |0 |0 |
+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+
]]></artwork>
        </figure>

        <t><list style="hanging">
            <t>All used and unused flags default to a value of
            &lsquo;0&rsquo;. The following table shows the bit encoding of the
            Flags field.</t>
          </list></t>

        <texttable align="left" anchor="Table_1">
          <ttcol>Bit</ttcol>

          <ttcol>Flag</ttcol>

          <ttcol>Encoding</ttcol>

          <c>0-1</c>

          <c>unused</c>

          <c>Default to &lsquo;0&rsquo;</c>

          <c>2</c>

          <c>P</c>

          <c>&lsquo;1&rsquo; &hellip; Marking is preserved</c>

          <c>3</c>

          <c>R</c>

          <c>&lsquo;1&rsquo; &hellip; Remarking occurred</c>

          <c>4</c>

          <c>I</c>

          <c>&lsquo;1&rsquo; &hellip; QoS marking ignored</c>

          <c>5</c>

          <c>A</c>

          <c>&lsquo;1&rsquo; &hellip; QoS class aggregation occurred</c>

          <c>6,7</c>

          <c>unused</c>

          <c>Default to &lsquo;0&rsquo;</c>
        </texttable>

        <t></t>

        <t><list style="hanging">
            <t>The 'P' flag indicates the preservation of incoming markings
            during the transit forwarding process. The IP prefix originating
            AS SHOULD set the flag to '1', which is otherwise implied by an
            AS_PATH length of 1 ASN. Transit ASes MUST set the flag to '1', if
            the advertised Marking A is accepted at the ingress and is sent
            out unchanged at the egress. That is, no remarking occurs -
            neither for marking adoption with the neighbouring downstream AS
            nor by resetting the markings. This flag field is set and cleared
            by each relaying AS according to its handling of markings -
            irrespective of the possible ignorance of the particular Marking A
            in the internal per hop forwarding behaviour.</t>

            <t>The Flags "R, I and A" are set to '0' in the advertisement by
            the IP prefix originating AS. Transit ASes MUST change the flag
            value to '1' once the respective event occurred. If the QoS
            marking actively used in the transit AS internal forwarding is
            different from the advertised original one, the 'Remarking (R)'
            flag is set to '1'. This MUST be done separately for each
            technology type community within the community set. The same
            applies to the 'Ignore (I)' flag, if the respective advertised QoS
            marking is ignored in the transit AS internal forwarding.</t>

            <t>The 'Aggregation (A)' flag MUST be set to '1' by the UPDATE
            message relaying transit AS, if the respective IP prefixes will be
            advertised inside an IP prefix aggregate constituted from
            differing Class Sets.</t>

            <t>If the defined "R, I and A" flags are cleared - and by means of
            the cleared 'Partial' flag of the BGP attribute it is shown, that
            no "QoS Class ignorant" AS is involved in the forwarding path - a
            consistent class based overall traffic separated forwarding is
            available along this path.</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>QoS Set Number:</t>

        <t><list style="hanging">
            <t>Several single QoS Marking communities can be logically grouped
            into a QoS Marking community Set characterized by a identical QoS
            Set Number. This grouping of the single QoS Marking communities
            into a set provides cross-layer linking between the QoS class
            encodings. It can also be used for the specification of behaviour
            sets as given in the <xref target="RFC3140"></xref>. The number of
            signalled QoS Marking communities as well as QoS Marking community
            Sets is at the operator&rsquo;s choice of the originating AS. The
            enumerated QoS set numbers have BGP UPDATE message local
            significance starting with set number 0x00.</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>Technology Type:</t>

        <t>The technology type encoding uses the enumeration list <xref
        target="tech_type">in</xref>. Future version of this draft will need
        an extended enumeration list administered by IANA.</t>

        <t>QoS Marking / Enumeration O &amp; A:</t>

        <t>The interpretation of these fields depends on the selected layer
        and technology. ASes, which process the community and support the
        given QoS Class by means of a QoS mechanism using bit encodings for
        the targeted behaviour (e.g. IP DSCP, Ethernet User Priority, MPLS TC
        etc.) MUST use a copy of the encoding in the "QoS Marking A" community
        field. Unused higher order bits default to &lsquo;0&rsquo;. Other
        technologies, which use separate forwarding channels for different
        classes (such as L-LSPs, VPI/VCI inferred ATM classes, lambda inferred
        priority, etc.) SHALL use class enumerations as encoding in this
        community field. The enumeration count starts with zero for the best
        effort traffic class and rises by one with each available higher
        priority class.</t>

        <t>There are two QoS Marking fields within the QoS Marking community
        for the "original (O)" and the "active (A)" QoS marking. Higher order
        bits of those fields, which are not used for the respective behaviour
        encoding, default to zero.</t>

        <t>QoS Marking O (Original QoS Marking):<list style="hanging">
            <t>This field is a 16 bit QoS Marking field, which consists of of
            a high ("Oh") and a low ("Ol") octet. The IP prefix originating AS
            copies the internally associated QoS encoding of the given
            Technology Type into this one octet field. The field value is
            right-aligned depending on the number of encoded bits. For the IP
            technology, the encoding of Per Hop Behaviour Codes has to follow
            the definitions stated in <xref target="RFC3140"></xref>. The
            field MUST remain unchanged in BGP UPDATE messages of relaying
            nodes.</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>QoS Marking A (Active QoS Marking):<list style="hanging">
            <t>QoS Marking A and O MUST be identically encoded by the prefix
            originating AS, except for the case, where IP technology Per Hop
            Behaviours are addressed. "QoS Marking A" will always contain the
            locally applied encoding for the targeted PHB.</t>

            <t>All other ASes use this Active QoS Marking field to advertise
            their locally applied internal QoS encoding of the given class and
            technology at the interconnection point. The field value is
            right-aligned depending on the number of encoded bits. A cleared
            Marking field (all zero) signals that this traffic class
            experiences default traffic treatment within the transit AS
            forwarding technology.</t>
          </list></t>

        <t><vspace blankLines="12" /></t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="tech_type" title="Technology Type Enumeration">
        <t>A small list of technologies is provided in the table below for the
        direct encoding of common technology types. The mapping of all virtual
        channel technologies into a single technology type value is for
        limiting the number of different communities in an UPDATE message. It
        is therefore a contribution to scalability.</t>

        <texttable align="left" anchor="Table_3">
          <ttcol>Value</ttcol>

          <ttcol>Technology Type</ttcol>

          <c>0x00</c>

          <c>DiffServ enabled IP (DSCP encoding)</c>

          <c>0x01</c>

          <c>Ethernet using 802.1q priority tag</c>

          <c>0x02</c>

          <c>MPLS using E-LSP</c>

          <c>0x03</c>

          <c>Virtual Channel (VC) encoding using separate channels for QoS
          forwarding / one channel per class (e.g. ATM VCs, FR VCs, MPLS
          L-LSPs)</c>

          <c>0x04</c>

          <c>GMPLS &ndash; time slot encoding</c>

          <c>0x05</c>

          <c>GMPLS &ndash; lambda encoding</c>

          <c>0x06</c>

          <c>GMPLS &ndash; fibre encoding</c>
        </texttable>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Community Usage">
      <t>Providers MAY choose to process the QoS Marking communities and adopt
      the behaviour encoding and tunnel selection according to their local
      policy. Whether this MAY also lead to different IGP routing decisions or
      even effect BGP update filters is out of scope for the community
      definition.</t>

      <t>Only the IP prefix originating AS is allowed to signal the QoS
      Marking communities and Sets. AS providers, which make use of this
      signalling mechanism MUST make sure, that only one external Class Set
      will be advertised for the AS. All advertised prefixes, which originate
      from that AS will be sent with the same QoS Marking community Set in the
      respective UPDATE message. Transit ASes MUST NOT modify or extend the
      QoS Marking community Set except for the update of each 'QoS Marking A'
      field contained in the community Set and the respective "P, R, I, A"
      flags. Prefixes with associated identical QoS Marking community Sets are
      to be advertised together in common UPDATE messages in relaying
      nodes.</t>

      <t><xref target="Figure_4"></xref> shows an AS interconnection example
      with different Class Sets. It shows the case in AS 5 where different
      Class Sets are used internally and externally. The proposed QoS Class
      Set signalling will always use the external definitions within the
      UPDATE message QoS Marking communities. The example also shows, that IP
      prefixes, which originate in AS 5 and AS 3 can be advertised together
      with the same QoS Marking community Set as long as their Layer 2
      encoding is identical.</t>

      <figure anchor="Figure_4">
        <artwork><![CDATA[                   AS 5 = Transit AS      
+------------+     =================     +------------+
+   AS 1     +      AS internal:         +   AS 3     +
+ 4 classes  +         5 classes         + 3 classes  +
+   L2/L3    +         L2/L3             +   L2/L3    +
+(EF,2xAF,BE)+      AS external:         +(EF,AF1,BE)+
+         [] +         3 classes         +[]          +
+------------+         L3 (EF,AF1,BE)   +------------+
              \    +---------------+    /
               \   |       []      |   /
                \  |      /  \     |  /               
                 \ |  --()---()--  | /        
                  \| /   |    |  \ |/         
                   |[]   |    |  []|         
                  /| \   |    |  / |\         
                 / |  --()---()--  | \        
                /  |      \  /     |  \       
               /   |       []      |   \      
              /    +---------------+    \     
+------------+                           +------------+
+         [] +                           +[]          +
+   AS 2     +                           +   AS 4     +
+ 2 classes  +                           + 6 classes  +
+   L2/L3    +                           +  L1/L2/L3  +
+  (EF,BE)   +                           +(EF,4xAF,BE)+
+------------+                           +------------+
[] ... AS Border Router                 
() ... AS internal Router]]></artwork>
      </figure>

      <section title="QoS Marking Example">
        <t>See <xref target="appendix_a"></xref> for an example QoS Marking
        community Set.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="AS Border Packet Forwarding">
        <t>IP packet forwarding based on packet header QoS encoding might
        require remarking of packets in order to match AS internal policies
        and encodings of neighbouring ASes.</t>

        <t>Identical QoS class sets and encodings between neighbouring ASes do
        not require any remarking. Different encodings will be matched on the
        outgoing traffic.</t>

        <t>Outgoing traffic for a given IP prefix uses the 'QoS Marking A'
        information of the respective BGP UPDATE message QoS Marking community
        for adopted remarking of the forwarded packet.</t>

        <t>If the 'I' flag is set for a given encoding, the outgoing traffic
        remarking SHOULD still be applied despite of the signalled lack of QoS
        Class forwarding support. This is particularly important, if the
        preserve flag 'P' is signalled together with the 'I' flag.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="IP Prefix Aggregation">
        <t>Several IP prefixes of different IP prefix originating ASes MAY be
        aggregated to a shorter IP prefix in transit ASes. If the original
        Class Sets of the aggregated prefixes are identical, the aggregate
        will use the same Set. In all other cases, the resulting IP prefix
        aggregate is handled the same as if the transit AS were the
        originating AS for this aggregated prefix. The transit AS provider MAY
        care for AS internal mechanisms, which map the signalled aggregate QoS
        Class Set to the different original Class Sets in the internal
        forwarding path.</t>

        <t>In case of IP prefix aggregation with different QoS Class Sets, the
        'Aggregation (A)' flag of each QoS Marking community within the Set
        MUST be set to '1'.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Confidentiality" title="Confidentiality Considerations">
      <t>The disclosure of confidential AS intrinsic information is of no
      concern since the signalled marking for QoS class encodings can be
      adopted prior to the UPDATE advertisement of the IP prefix originating
      AS. This way, a distinction between internal and external QoS Class Sets
      can be achieved. AS internal cross-layer marking adaptation and policy
      based update filtering allows for consistent QoS class support despite
      made up QoS Class Set and encoding information within UPDATE
      advertisements. In case of such policy hiding strategy, the required AS
      internal ingress and egress adaptation SHALL be done transparently
      without explicit "Active Marking" and 'R' flag signalling.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>This document defines a new BGP Extended Community, which includes a
      "Technology Type" field. <xref target="tech_type"></xref> enumerates a
      number of popular technologies. This list is expected to suffice for
      first implementations. However, future or currently uncovered
      technologies may arise, which will require an extended "Technology Type"
      enumeration list administered by IANA.</t>

      <t>A new extended community QoS Marking community is defined, which has
      been assigned a Type value of 0x04 for a transitive and 0x44 for a
      non-transitive usage.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>This extension to BGP does not change the underlying security issues
      inherent in the existing BGP.</t>

      <t>Malicious signalling behaviour of QoS Marking community advertising
      ASes can result in misguided neighbours about non existing or
      maliciously encoded Class Sets. Removal of QoS Marking community Sets
      leads to the current best effort interconnection, which is no stringent
      security concern.</t>

      <t>The IP prefix originating AS MAY place a copy of its marking
      information into the Internet Routing Registry (IRR) for global
      reference.</t>

      <t>The strongest threat is the advertisement of numerous very fine
      grained Class Sets, which could limit the scalability of this approach.
      However, neighbouring ASes are free to set the ignore flag of single
      communities or to stop processing the QoS Marking communities of a
      certain routing advertisement, once a self-set threshold has been
      crossed. By means of this self defence mechanism it should not be
      possible to crash neighbouring peers due to the excessive use of the new
      community.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <reference anchor="IANA_EC"
                 target="http://www.iana.org/assignments/bgp-extended-communities">
        <front>
          <title>Border Gateway Protocol (BGP) Data Collection Standard
          Communities</title>

          <author fullname="IANA" initials="" surname="IANA">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date day="10" month="June" year="2008" />
        </front>
      </reference>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.1997"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3140"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4271"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4360"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5543"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5575"?>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.I-D.boucadair-qos-bgp-spec.xml"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.I-D.jacquenet-bgp-qos.xml"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.I-D.liang-bgp-qos.xml"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.I-D.zhang-idr-bgp-extcommunity-qos.xml"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.I-D.knoll-idr-cos-interconnect.xml"?>

      <reference anchor="MIT_CFP"
                 target="http://cfp.mit.edu/docs/interprovider-qos-nov2006.pdf">
        <front>
          <title>Inter-provider Quality of Service - White paper draft
          1.1</title>

          <author fullname="Amante, Shane" initials="S." surname="Amante">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="Bitar, Nabil" initials="N." surname="Bitar">
            <organization></organization>

            <address>
              <postal>
                <street></street>

                <city></city>

                <region></region>

                <code></code>

                <country></country>
              </postal>

              <phone></phone>

              <facsimile></facsimile>

              <email></email>

              <uri></uri>
            </address>
          </author>

          <author fullname="Bjorkman, Nils" initials="N." surname="Bjorkman">
            <organization>N.</organization>

            <address>
              <postal>
                <street></street>

                <city></city>

                <region></region>

                <code></code>

                <country></country>
              </postal>

              <phone></phone>

              <facsimile></facsimile>

              <email></email>

              <uri></uri>
            </address>
          </author>

          <author>
            <organization>others</organization>

            <address>
              <postal>
                <street></street>

                <city></city>

                <region></region>

                <code></code>

                <country></country>
              </postal>

              <phone></phone>

              <facsimile></facsimile>

              <email></email>

              <uri></uri>
            </address>
          </author>

          <date day="17" month="November" year="2006" />
        </front>
      </reference>
    </references>

    <section anchor="appendix_a" title="QoS Marking Example">
      <t>The example AS is advertising several IP prefixes, which experience
      equal QoS treatment from AS internal networks. The IP packet forwarding
      policy within this originating AS defines e.g. 3 traffic classes for IP
      traffic (DSCP1, DSCP2 and DSCP3). These three classes are also
      consistently taken care of within a TC bit supporting MPLS tunnel
      forwarding. The BGP UPDATE message for the announced IP prefixes will
      contain the following QoS Marking community Set together with the IP
      prefix NLRI.</t>

      <figure anchor="Figure_5">
        <artwork><![CDATA[ 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|0 0 1 0 0 0 0 0|0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0|0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0|1 0 1 1 1 0 0 0|
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0|0 0 1 0 1 1 1 0|0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0|  
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|0 0 1 0 0 0 0 0|0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0|0 0 0 0 0 0 1 0|0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0|
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|0 0 0 0 0 1 0 1|0 0 0 0 0 1 0 1|0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0|
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+

+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|0 0 1 0 0 0 0 0|0 0 0 0 0 0 0 1|0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0|0 0 1 0 1 0 0 0|
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|0 0 0 0 0 0 1 0|0 0 0 0 1 0 1 0|0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0|
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|0 0 1 0 0 0 0 0|0 0 0 0 0 0 0 1|0 0 0 0 0 0 1 0|0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0|
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|0 0 0 0 0 0 0 1|0 0 0 0 0 0 0 1|0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0|
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+

+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|0 0 1 0 0 0 0 0|0 0 0 0 0 0 1 0|0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0|0 1 0 0 1 0 0 0|
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|0 0 0 0 0 0 1 0|0 0 0 1 0 0 1 0|0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0|
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|0 0 1 0 0 0 0 0|0 0 0 0 0 0 1 0|0 0 0 0 0 0 1 0|0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0|
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|0 0 0 0 0 0 1 0|0 0 0 0 0 0 1 0|0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0|
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+

The class set as well as the example encodings are arbitrarily chosen.
]]></artwork>
      </figure>
    </section>
  </back>
</rfc>
