<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
    <!ENTITY RFC2045 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2045.xml">
    <!ENTITY RFC2046 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2046.xml">
    <!ENTITY RFC2119 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
    <!ENTITY RFC3629 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3629.xml">
    <!ENTITY RFC3986 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3986.xml">
    <!ENTITY RFC3987 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3987.xml">
    <!ENTITY RFC4395 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4395.xml">
    <!ENTITY RFC5234 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5234.xml">
]>

<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="rfc2629.xslt" ?>

<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<!-- <?rfc editing="yes" ?> -->
<?rfc inline="yes" ?>
<?rfc iprnotified="yes" ?>
<?rfc rfcedstyle="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>

<!--
 1. Update the docName
 2. Update the date
 3. Update the Revision History.
-->


<rfc category="std" ipr="trust200902" docName="draft-lafayette-icon-uri-scheme-00">
    <front>
        <title>The 'icon' URI scheme</title>
        <author initials="P-A." surname="LaFayette" fullname="Pierre-Antoine Benoit LaFayette" >
            <organization>Chromium Project</organization>
            <address>
                <email>pierre@alumni.utoronto.ca</email>
            </address>
        </author>
        <date month="May" year="2010" />
        <area>Internet</area>
        <keyword>I-D</keyword>
        <keyword>Internet-Draft</keyword>
        <keyword>URI</keyword>
        <keyword>Uniform Resource Identifier</keyword>
        <keyword>icon</keyword>
        <abstract>
            <t>This document specifies the <spanx style="verb">icon</spanx> URI scheme.  Icons have a fundamental role in user interaction with computer operating systems.  In a graphical user interface, they may represent a file, folder, application, or device.  They live on the desktop, in toolbars, and in menus.  Most operating systems provide a standard set of icons that match the look and feel of the system.  The <spanx style="verb">icon</spanx> URI scheme lets web page designers leverage these existing platform icons.</t>
        </abstract>
        <note title="Editorial Note (To be removed by RFC Editor)">
            <t>Discussion of this draft should take place on the URI Review mailing list (uri-review@ietf.org).</t>
        </note>
        <note title="URI Scheme versus URN Namespace">
            <t>It has been suggested that a URN namespace may be more appropriate for icon resolution than the new URI scheme. <eref target="http://www.ietf.org/mail-archive/web/uri-review/current/msg01161.html">Discussion</eref> on these matters has been ongoing in the uri-review@ietf.org mailing list. The arguments will be taken into consideration for the final decision as whether this draft should be considered for permanent registration.</t>
        </note>
    </front>
    <middle>
        <section anchor="intro" title="Introduction">
            <t>An <spanx style="verb">icon</spanx> URI is designed to be a web accessible scheme used to resolve operating system icon resources.  <spanx style="verb">Icon</spanx> URIs use either a file extension or an Internet media type to specify the filetype of a platform icon.  Web pages can use <spanx style="verb">icon</spanx> URIs in any place that an image is specifiable by a URI.  In particular, <spanx style="verb">icon</spanx> URIs can be used with <spanx style="verb">&lt;img&gt;</spanx> tags and JavaScript <spanx style="verb">Image</spanx> objects.</t>
            <t>Similar icon URI schemes are currently being used in some modern browsers.  The Mozilla project has a <spanx style="verb">moz-icon://</spanx> URI scheme that is web accessible and provides native and browser themed icons.  The Chromium project has a <spanx style="verb">chrome://fileicon</spanx> scheme that is not web accessible, but does provide native icons for internal pages.  This new scheme is an attempt to standardize icon URIs so that their core functionality may become available to all web pages.</t>
        </section>
        <section title="Terminology">
            <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in <xref target="RFC2119" />.</t>
        </section>
        <section anchor="syntax" title="URI Syntax">
            <figure>
                <preamble>The general syntax of an <spanx style="verb">icon</spanx> URI is defined below using <xref target="RFC5234">ABNF</xref>:</preamble>
                <artwork type="abnf">
iconuri = "icon:" ( fextension / mediatype / "unknown" ) [ ";" size ]
fextension = "." 1*token ; File extension
mediatype = [ type ":" subtype ] ; Internet media type
size = pixels / "small" / "medium" / "large"
pixels = 1*digit ; Size of icon in square pixels
                </artwork>
                <postamble>where <spanx style="verb">token</spanx>, <spanx style="verb">digit</spanx>, <spanx style="verb">type</spanx> and <spanx style="verb">subtype</spanx> rules are defined in <xref target="RFC2045" />.  The sections of an <spanx style="verb">icon</spanx> URI are ALWAYS case-insensitive.</postamble>
            </figure>
        </section>
        <section anchor="encoding" title="Encoding Considerations">
            <t>The encoding of the <spanx style="verb">type</spanx> and <spanx style="verb">subtype</spanx> rules is defined in <xref target="RFC2045" />.  The <spanx style="verb">fextension</spanx> rule may include characters from the <xref target="UCS">Unicode Character Set</xref>, as suggested by <xref target="RFC3986">URI</xref>, by first encoding those characters as octets to the <xref target="RFC3629">UTF-8 character encoding</xref>.  Only those octets that do not correspond to characters in the unreserved set should be percent-encoded.</t>
            <t>By using UTF-8 encoding, there are no known compatibility issues with mapping Internationalized Resource Identifiers to <spanx style="verb">icon</spanx> URIs according to <xref target="RFC3987"/>.  Since <spanx style="verb">icon</spanx> URIs do not use domain names, <spanx style="verb">ireg-name</spanx> conversion is unnecessary.</t>
        </section>
        <section anchor="resolution" title="Resolving &quot;icon&quot; URIs">
            <t>An <spanx style="verb">icon</spanx> URI MUST resolve to an icon image resource.  The <spanx style="verb">fextension</spanx> or the <spanx style="verb">mediatype</spanx> sections of the URI MUST be used to resolve the respective platform icon for a filetype. If an icon is not available for the specified filetype, applications MUST return a default icon.  The icon resource's dimensions MUST match the size indicated in the URI or use the default size.</t>
            <section title="File extension">
               <t>The filetype for an icon is specifiable by the <spanx style="verb">fextension</spanx> rule.  An acceptable value for this section is a file extension for which a platform icon can be retrieved.  Applications are REQUIRED to support <spanx style="verb">icon</spanx> URI resolution by file extension.</t>
               <t>In the event that a platform icon is not available for the provided file extension, the application MUST return a default "unknown file" icon in the appropriate size.</t>
            </section>
            <section title="Internet media type">
                <t>The filetype for an icon is also specifiable by the <spanx style="verb">mediatype</spanx> rule.  An acceptable value for this section is an Internet media type, as defined in <xref target="RFC2045" /> and <xref target="RFC2046" />, for which a platform icon can be retrieved.  Applications are REQUIRED to support <spanx style="verb">icon</spanx> URI resolution by Internet media type.</t>
                <t>In the event that a platform icon is not available for the provided media type, the application MUST return a default "unknown file" icon in the appropriate size.</t>
            </section>
            <section title="Icon Size">
                <t>An <spanx style="verb">icon</spanx> URI MAY specify the size of a requested icon through the <spanx style="verb">size</spanx> rule.  The <spanx style="verb">size</spanx> MUST be either an integer value representing the size of the icon in square pixels or one of: "small", "medium", or "large".  Applications are REQUIRED to support both user-provided integer values and the 3 keyword values.</t>
                <t>If the <spanx style="verb">size</spanx> is specified as "small" the application MUST return a 16x16 pixels icon.</t>
                <t>If the <spanx style="verb">size</spanx> is specified as "medium" the application MUST return a 64x64 pixels icon.</t>
                <t>If the <spanx style="verb">size</spanx> is specified as "large" the application MUST return a 256x256 pixels icon.</t>
                <t>If the <spanx style="verb">size</spanx> is not specified in the URI, the application MUST return a 16x16 pixels icon.</t>
                <t>In the event that the platform does not support one of the keyword icon sizes or a user-provided size, the application SHOULD scale the icon appropriately.</t>
            </section>
            <section anchor="examples" title="Examples">
                <t>icon:.zip &mdash;Displays a 16x16 pixels platform icon for the .zip file extension.</t>
                <t>icon:.MP3;32 &mdash;Displays a 32x32 pixels platform icon for the .mp3 file extension.</t>
                <t>ICON:unknown &mdash;Displays a 16x16 pixels default icon for an unknown filetype.</t>
                <t>icon:image:jpeg;128 &mdash;Displays a 128x128 pixels platform icon for the image/jpeg media type.</t>
                <t>icon:AUDIO:MPEG;large &mdash;Displays a 256x256 platform icon for the audio/mpeg media type.</t>
                <t>icon:.doc;SMALL &mdash;Displays a 16x16 platform icon for the .doc file extension.</t>
                <t>icon:.pdf;medium &mdash;Displays a 64x64 platform icon for the .pdf file extension.</t>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section anchor="normalization" title="Normalization">
            <t><spanx style="verb">Icon</spanx> URIs adhere to the standard <xref target="RFC3986">URI normalization rules</xref>; specifically Simple String Comparison, Case Normalization, and Percent-Encoding Normalization.  Due to the structure of <spanx style="verb">icon</spanx> URIs, the Syntax-Based, Scheme-Based, and Protocol-Based Normalization rules do not apply.  The sections of an <spanx style="verb">icon</spanx> URI are ALWAYS case-insensitive.</t>
        </section>
        <section anchor="security" title="Security Considerations">
            <!-- must play nice with RFC3552 and RFC4949 -->
            <t>There are potential privacy risks that need to be taken into consideration with this new scheme.</t>
            <t><spanx style="verb">Icon</spanx> URIs specify private icon resources located on a user's machine.  Web pages MUST NOT be able to retrieve the platform icons that this scheme provides to the user.  Further, web pages MUST NOT be able to retrieve information about the platform icons that might expose the applications installed on a user's machine.  The following sections explore specific issues that applications MUST address in their respective implementations.</t>
            <section title="Canvas Images">
                <t>HTML5 introduces the canvas element which allows for dynamic scriptable rendering of 2D bitmap images.</t>
                <t>Images can be imported onto the canvas by first retrieving a reference to a JavaScript <spanx style="verb">Image</spanx> object, then drawing the image on the canvas using the <eref target="http://dev.w3.org/html5/canvas-api/canvas-2d-api.html#dom-context-2d-drawimage">drawImage</eref>. Another option involves setting the 2D context's <spanx style="verb">fillStyle</spanx> or <spanx style="verb">strokeStyle</spanx> to a <spanx style="verb">CanvasPattern</spanx> object created from an <spanx style="verb">Image</spanx> object using the <eref target="http://www.whatwg.org/specs/web-apps/current-work/multipage/the-canvas-element.html#dom-context-2d-createpattern">createPattern</eref> method.  There are four ways one can retrieve a handle to an <spanx style="verb">Image</spanx> object:</t>
                <t>1. Retrieve <spanx style="verb">&lt;img&gt;</spanx> elements already on the page using the DOM.</t>
                <t>2. Retrieve other canvas elements using the document.getElementsById method or the document.getElementsByTagName method.</t>
                <t>3. Create an image from scratch, i.e. var img = new Image().</t>
                <t>4. Embed an image using its data URI.</t>
                <t>As a result of #1, an <spanx style="verb">&lt;img&gt;</spanx> tag, whose src attribute is an <spanx style="verb">icon</spanx> URI, can be retrieved as a JavaScript <spanx style="verb">Image</spanx> object.  Considering #3; an <spanx style="verb">Image</spanx> can be created in JavaScript and have its src field is set to an <spanx style="verb">icon</spanx> URI.</t>
                <t>Drawing the <spanx style="verb">Image</spanx> to the canvas provides web pages with two potential means of accessing the images: the <eref target="http://www.whatwg.org/specs/web-apps/current-work/multipage/the-canvas-element.html#dom-context-2d-getimagedata">getImageData</eref> and <eref target="http://www.whatwg.org/specs/web-apps/current-work/multipage/the-canvas-element.html#dom-canvas-todataurl">toDataURL</eref> methods of the canvas's 2D context.  The canvas's 2D drawing API is defined in <xref target="Canvas2D" />.</t>
                <t>An <spanx style="verb">Image</spanx> object with an <spanx style="verb">icon</spanx> URI as its src attribute MUST NOT be considered as same-origin as any other origin.  If an <spanx style="verb">Image</spanx> with an <spanx style="verb">icon</spanx> URI src is drawn to a canvas, the canvas MUST be considered tainted and have its <spanx style="verb">origin-clean</spanx> flag set to false.  As such, if <spanx style="verb">getImageData</spanx> or <spanx style="verb">toDataURL</spanx> is called on a canvas that has been tainted by <spanx style="verb">icon</spanx> URI <spanx style="verb">Image</spanx> data, the method MUST raise a <eref target="http://www.whatwg.org/specs/web-apps/current-work/multipage/urls.html#security_err">SECURITY_ERR</eref> exception.  See <eref target="http://www.whatwg.org/specs/web-apps/current-work/multipage/the-canvas-element.html#security-with-canvas-elements">Security with canvas elements</eref> in the <xref target="HTML5">HTML5 Draft Standard</xref> for further details.</t>
            </section>
            <section title="Image Size">
                <t>Because the width and height of an <spanx style="verb">Image</spanx> object are always accessible, applications MUST use the default size (16x16) for platform icons if the size has not been provided by the <spanx style="verb">icon</spanx> URI.  This is a requirement because evil web pages may be able to use the width and height of icons to infer details about the applications a user has installed.</t>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section title="IANA Considerations">
            <!-- must play nice with RFC2434, RFC4395 -->
            <t>This specification requests the IANA provisionally register the <spanx style="verb">icon</spanx> URI scheme as specified in this document and summarized in the following template, per <xref target="RFC4395" />:</t>
            <t><list style="hanging">
                <t hangText="URI scheme name:">icon</t>
                <t hangText="Status:">Provisional</t>
                <t hangText="URI scheme syntax:">See <xref target="syntax" /></t>
                <t hangText="URI scheme semantics:">See <xref target="intro" /></t>
                <t hangText="Encoding considerations:">See <xref target="encoding" /></t>
                <t hangText="Intended usage:">See <xref target="intro" /> and <xref target="examples" /></t>
                <t hangText="Applications and/or protocols that use this URI scheme name:">Any applications that use URIs as identifiers for private resources, such as web browsers.</t>
                <t hangText="Interoperability considerations:">See <xref target="normalization" /></t>
                <t hangText="Security considerations:">See <xref target="security" /></t>
                <t hangText="Relevant publications:">None</t>
                <t hangText="Contact:">Pierre-Antoine LaFayette (pierre@alumni.utoronto.ca)</t>
                <t hangText="Author/Change controller:">Pierre-Antoine LaFayette</t>
            </list></t>
        </section>
        <section title="Acknowledgements">
            <t>This document was made possible thanks to the input of Adam Barth, Lachlan Hunt, Maciej Stachowiak, Jonas Sicking, Robert O'Callahan, Josh Soref, and Ian Fette.</t>
        </section>
    </middle>
    <back>
        <references title="Normative References">
            &RFC2045; <!-- Mutipurpose Internet Mail Extensions (MIME) pt. 1 -->
            &RFC2046; <!-- Mutipurpose Internet Mail Extensions (MIME) pt. 2 -->
            &RFC2119; <!-- RFC Key Words -->
            &RFC3629; <!-- UTF-8 -->
            &RFC3986; <!-- URI General Syntax -->
            &RFC3987; <!-- IRI -->
            &RFC5234; <!-- ABNF -->
            <reference anchor="UCS">
                <front>
                    <title>Information Technology - Universal Multiple-Octet Coded Character Set (UCS)</title>
                    <author>
                        <organization>International Organization for Standardization</organization>
                    </author>
                    <date month="December" year="2003"/>
                </front>
                <seriesInfo name="ISO/IEC" value="Standard 10646"/>
            </reference>
        </references>
        <references title="Informative References">
            &RFC4395; <!-- New URI Schemes -->
            <reference anchor="HTML5">
                <front>
                    <title>HTML5 Draft Standard</title>
                    <author initials="I." surname="Hickson" fullname="Ian Hickson">
                        <organization>Google, Inc.</organization>
                    </author>
                </front>
                <format type="HTML"
                    target="http://www.whatwg.org/specs/web-apps/current-work/multipage/" />
            </reference>
            <reference anchor="Canvas2D">
                <front>
                    <title>Canvas 2D API Specification 1.0</title>
                    <author initials="I." surname="Hickson" fullname="Ian Hickson">
                        <organization>Google, Inc.</organization>
                    </author>
                    <author initials="D." surname="Hyatt" fullname="David Hyatt">
                        <organization>Apple, Inc.</organization>
                    </author>
                      <author initials="D." surname="Schepers" fullname="Doug Schepers">
                        <organization>W3C</organization>
                    </author>
                      <author initials="E." surname="Graff" fullname="Eliot Graff">
                        <organization>Microsoft Corporation</organization>
                    </author>
                </front>
                <format type="HTML"
                    target="http://dev.w3.org/html5/canvas-api/canvas-2d-api.html" />
            </reference>
        </references>
    </back>
</rfc>

<!--
notes
investigate guidelines
    &RFC2434; BCP26 IANA Considerations
    &RFC3978; BCP78 IETF Rights in Contributions
    &RFC3552; BCP72 Security considerations
validator: http://www.fenron.com/~fenner/ietf/xml2rfc-valid/
citation libraries: http://xml.resource.org/
vim:set ts=4 sw=4 sts=4:
-->
