<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!-- This template is for creating an Internet Draft using xml2rfc,
     which is available here: http://xml.resource.org. -->
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!-- One method to get references from the online citation libraries.
     There has to be one entity for each item to be referenced. 
     An alternate method (rfc include) is described in the references. -->

<!ENTITY RFC1157 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1157.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC1441 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1441.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC1158 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1158.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC1156 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1156.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC1213 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1213.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC2011 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2011.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC2012 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2012.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC2465 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2465.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC2466 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2466.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4292 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4292.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4293 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4293.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC2013 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2013.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3411 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3411.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5102 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5102.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5101 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5101.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3594 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3594.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6555 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6555.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC2452 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2452.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC2454 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2454.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4022 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4022.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4113 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4113.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3176 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3176.xml">
]>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<!-- used by XSLT processors -->
<!-- For a complete list and description of processing instructions (PIs), 
     please see http://xml.resource.org/authoring/README.html. -->
<!-- Below are generally applicable Processing Instructions (PIs) that most I-Ds might want to use.
     (Here they are set differently than their defaults in xml2rfc v1.32) -->

<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>


<rfc category="info" docName="draft-servin-v6ops-monitor-ds-ipv6-01" ipr="trust200902">
  
  <front>
    <!-- The abbreviated title is used in the page header - it is only necessary if the 
         full title is longer than 39 characters -->

    <title abbrev="Abbreviated Title">Monitoring Dual Stack/IPv6-only Networks and Services</title>

      <author fullname="Arturo Servin" initials="A." surname="Servin">
      <organization>LACNIC</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Rambla Republica de Mexico 6125</street>
          <city>Montevideo</city>
          <code>11300</code>
          <country>Uruguay</country>
        </postal>
        <phone>+598 2604 2222</phone>
        <email>aservin@lacnic.net</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    
    <author fullname="Mariela Rocha" initials="M." surname="Rocha">
      <organization>Redes de Interconexion Universitaria Asoc. Civil (ARIU)</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Maipu 645 - 4to Piso</street>
          <city>Buenos Aires</city>
          <country>Argentina</country>
        </postal>
        <email>mrocha@riu.edu.ar </email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date month="July" year="2013" />

    <area></area>

    <workgroup>v6ops</workgroup>

    <keyword>IPv6, operations, monitoring, snmp</keyword>

    <!-- Keywords will be incorporated into HTML output
         files in a meta tag but they have no effect on text or nroff
         output. If you submit your draft to the RFC Editor, the
         keywords will be used for the search engine. -->

    <abstract>
      <t>This document describes a set of recommendations and guidelines to help
      operators to monitor dual stack and IPv6-only networks. The document
      describes how to monitor these networks using SNMP, Flow Analyzers and other means.

      </t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      
      <t>Network and services monitoring become more important as we rely more on them
      for our critical operations. Depending of the complexity of our monitor solution
      we would be able to have more control and information from our network and services.
      Among other things, a good monitor solution allows to:: </t>
      
      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>Detect and avoid network incidents</t>
          <t>Determine which actions may solve a network incident</t>
	  <t>Execute recovery and contingency plans </t>
        </list>
      </t>
	 
      <t>All these make sense when we monitor our network responsibly trying to cover all
      the variables. In the context of this memo, it means that we should monitor our services
      and networks running IPv6 as we have/had done in the IPv4 world.. </t>
      
      <t>There are many documents and guides explaining how to deploy IPv6 networks and services
      but there are so few that describe in detail how to monitor them. This document tries to
      encompass a set of recommendations and guidelines to help network and system administrators
      to monitor dual-stack/IPv6-only network and services. </t>
      
    </section>
    
    <section title="Network Monitoring">
      
      <t>In this section we describe SNMP and IPFIX as protocols able to manage IP devices and
      to monitor a variety of data from dual stack and IPv6-only networks. We also discuss traffic
      analyzers as other tools to monitor IP networks. </t>
      
      
      <section title="Transport vs. Data">
	
      <t> It is important to understand the difference between IPv6 Transport
      vs. IPv6 data. In other words, protocols for monitor network infrastructure such as SNMP
      or IPFIX can send IPv6 collected data (e.g. the count of forwarded packets of an interface,
      flow information) using either IPv4 or IPv6 transport.</t>

      <t>It is important to note that some node implementations would only send data (either IPv4 or IPv6)
      over IPv4 networks. Nevertheless these are implementation limitations not related to the monitoring
      protocol.</t>
      
      </section>
      
      <section title="Simple Network Management Protocol">
	
      <t>Simple Network Management Protocol (SNMP)  defines the protocol suite to monitor and
      manage IP networks. SNMP works over UDP that allows it to work over IPv4 or IPv6 networks.
      However, the definitions that allow SNMP to collect data from IP devices know as "Management
      Information Base" (MIB) had to be modified from the original specifications. The most used versions
      of SNMP are Version 1 and <xref target="RFC1441">Version 2</xref>. Version 3 is defined in
      <xref target="RFC3411"/>.</t>
      
      <t>SNMP MIB was defined in <xref target="RFC1156"/> and extended by
      <xref target="RFC1158"/>. Later it was modified by <xref target="RFC1213"/>
      in 1990 and in 1996 deprecated by RFCs <xref target="RFC2011"/>, <xref target="RFC2012"/>
      and <xref target="RFC2013"/> that separated the MIB in IP, TCP
      and UDP. However all these modifications did not considered IPv6 yet. It was until <xref target="RFC2465"/>
      and <xref target="RFC2466"/> that MIB definitions were specified for IPv6 and
      ICMPv6. These RFCs described a dissociated definition for IPv4 and IPv6. The last MIB definitions came in
      2006 when <xref target="RFC4292"/> (IP-Forwarding) and <xref target="RFC4293"/>
      (IP-MIB) defined an unified set of managed objects independent of the IP version. </t>
      
      <t>Today there are many agent and collector implementations that support <xref target="RFC4292"/>
      and <xref target="RFC4293"/>. Nevertheless not all of them support them over IPv6 transport
      and IPv4 has to be used.</t>
      
      </section>
      
      <section title="Flow Analyzers">
	
      <t>Knowing the packet count that goes in and out from an interface it is very important but many times
      is not enough to detect faults or to get more detailed traffic information about the network.
      Netflow and IP Flow Information Export (IPFIX) <xref target="RFC5101"/> and
      <xref target="RFC5102"/> are protocols that monitor the IP
      flows passing through network devices. An IP flow is a sequence of packets identified by a common
      set of attributes such as IP Source Address, IP Destination Address, Source Port, Destination Port,
      Layer 3 protocol type, Class of service, etc.
      </t>
      
      <section title="Netflow">
	
       <t>Netflow is a protocol developed by Cisco Systems and version 9 is described in the informational
       <xref target="RFC3594"/>. Other vendors have adopted equivalent technology such as Jflow
       (Juniper Networks), Cflowd (Alcatel-Lucent) and SFlow (sFlow.org consortium). </t>

      <t>Netflow defines nine versions from which version 5 is the most common and only versions 9 and 10
      support IPv6. Versions 9 and 10 are commonly known as the base of IPFIX. Although Netflow version 9
      supports the collection of IPv6 flows, not all implementations of agents and collectors support IPv6
      transport and IPv4 has to be used.
      </t>
	
      </section>
      
      <section title="Sflow">
        <t>Sflow is defined in <xref target="RFC3176"/> and it is very similar to netflow and IPFIX.
        It differs basically in the method to collect flow information. In the case of Sflow, it
        uses statistical packet-based sampling of switched flows and time-based sampling.
        The Sflow version described in <xref target="RFC3176"/> supports IPv4 and IPv6 address families.</t>
        
      </section>
      
      <section title="IPFIX">
	
	<t>IPFIX architecture and message format is defined in <xref target="RFC5101">RFC5101</xref>and
        <xref target="RFC5102">RFC5102</xref> defines its information
	model. From the operational standpoint of this document IPFIX and Netflow v9 are not very different
	and there is not much more to say besides that IPFIX as a relatively new protocol has not been
	widely implemented. For this reason finding an implementation supporting IPv6 transport may be
	hard to find.
	</t>
	
      </section>
      
      <section title="Network/Traffic Analyzers">
	
	<t>Besides SNMP and Flow analyzers IPv6 can be monitored using a variety of network/traffic analyzers.
	These devices come in a variety of flavors and some are open source or free and can be installed
	in commodity hardware, some other are expensive and run on specialized equipment. Commonly they
	are installed using promiscuous port that mirror all the network traffic or they are installed
	somewhere in the network where they can inspect most of the traffic.</t>
	
	<t>Network/traffic analyzers are a quick way to inspect IPv6 traffic, however they may have
	scalability and privacy issues which make them unsuitable for large networks.</t>
      
      </section>
      </section>
      
      <section title="Command line interface tools">
	
	<t> When SNMP and flow tools are not available in the network device and traffic analyzers are
	not suitable as a long term solution it may be possible to use in-house development or other tools
	to access networks devices and parse command line instructions that monitor IPv6 traffic. This
	solution could be used as well in IPv6 only networks when the device implementation does not support
	IPv6 transit to deliver monitoring data.
	</t>

      </section>
      
      <section title="Software Defined Networks">
        <t>
        TBD, In this section we will discuss the use of Software Defined Network (SDN) for the purposes
        of gathering data from the network.</t>
        
      </section>
      
      </section>
      
      <section title="Addressing">
        
        <t>TBD. In this section we will discuss the implications to use of link-local, ULAs and Global Unicast
        Addresses for the purpose of monitor network infrastructure.</t>
        
      </section>
      
    
    
    <section title="Application Monitoring">
      
      <t> Beyond the traffic that goes through the network, network operators require to monitor other
      services such HTTP servers, email infrastructure, DNS, sensors, etc.</t>
      
      <section title="Services">
	
	<t>Besides network information, network operators require to know other variables that could
	affect the good operation of the network. Dual stack networks pose an important challenge to
	network and system administrators. In principle we are talking about two different networks that
	may have different paths and users may perceive a difference in quality. Furthermore, thanks to
        Happy Eye Balls <xref target="RFC6555">RFC6555</xref> that improves the user experience,
        service operators may have no idea to which protocol
	users are connected. This impose the need to monitor two networks and two set of services such
	as HTTP servers, email infrastructure, DNS, etc. to guarantee the service expectations from users.
	</t>
	
	<t>In order to monitor service uptime and performance, it is common to use service probes that
	frequently poll a specific service to verify its reachability. Most of the time this probes are
	configured to access a service using a Fully Qualified Domain Name (FQDN) but sometimes literals
	are used as well.
	</t>
	
	<t>To monitor services using FQDNs with A and AAAA records network/system administrator must be
	aware that they do not have a guarantee that the probe is using IPv4 or IPv6 transport unless is
	forced to do so.  Some tools provide configuration or execution flags to force the use of IPv4 or
	IPv6 transport. To guarantee a reliable monitoring strategy, we recommend using those flags to set
	up two monitor instances, one for each address family. Needless to say that in case of using literals
	instead of FQDNs, a new service monitor instance using an IPv6 address must be added.</t>
	
      </section>
      
      <section title="FQDN as connection discriminator">
	
	<t>We mentioned that one possible solution to discriminate between IPv4 and IPv6 services is to use
	some of the flags provided by the monitoring tool to force a connection either in IPv4 or IPv6.
	Depending of the tool used, this option may not be always available. To address this restriction
	it is possible to use a special FQDN with only an A record to force an IPv4 connection and a different
	FQDN with only an AAAA record for IPv6.
	</t>
	
	<t>For example suppose that the main organization website has the name www.example.com. The name
	www.example.com would have A and AAAA records as normally, however it would also contain an A record
	of the form www.v4-test.example.com pointing to its IPv4 address and an AAAA record www.v6-test.example.com
	point to the IPv6 address of the service. Other variants may be www.v6.example.com, www-v4.example.com,
	etc. As these FQDNs are meant to be only internally the selection of which to use is left to the network
	operator. </t>
	
	<t>Bear in mind that using this alternative may introduce an extra overhead related to DNS management
	and should be used only when strictly necessary.</t>
	
      </section>
      
    </section>
      
    <section title="IPv6-Only Networks">
      
      <t>The critical path to monitor IPv6 data on dual-stack networks is the device support of the IPv6
      only MIBs (<xref target="RFC2465"/>, <xref target="RFC2466"/>,
      <xref target="RFC2452"/> and <xref target="RFC2454"/>), the unified MIBs
      (<xref target="RFC4293"/>, <xref target="RFC4022"/>,
      <xref target="RFC4113"/> and <xref target="RFC4292"/> or flow tools
      as Netflow 9 or IPFIX. As long as these protocols are supported, the device can be monitor using IPv4 or
      IPv6 transport. However, in IPv6-only networks supporting IPv6 data monitoring is not enough.
      In order to work it is critical for the device or collector to support the delivery or polling
      data using IPv6 transport.
      </t>
      
      <t>For SNMP data there are a variety of agents and collectors that support IPv6 MIBs (IPv6 and Protocol
      Independent) using IPv6 transport. Nevertheless still exist devices that do not support neither IPv6
      MIBs nor IPv6 transport of monitoring data.</t>
      
      <t>With respect of flow tools, the authors of this document are aware of only a few implementations that
      support IPv6 transport.</t>

	
    </section>
    
    <section title="Operational Challenges">
      
      <t>Even though the end of IPv4 is near, there are still many network devices that cannot provide any
      type of IPv6 monitor data. In other cases the device can provide some sort of data through command
      line interfaces or in the best scenario through out the old IPv6 MIBs and using only IPv4 transit
      for delivery.</t>
      
      <t>Still many network devices do not support to collect or send data related to IPv6. Also, some
      implementations are not widely tested and they may not support IPv6 monitoring correctly. For example,
      there were in the past cases where network devices did not correctly reported data collected from
      interface counters as they only counted packets that were process switched. Eventually this bug was
      fixed to include hardware-processed packets. It will still possible to find more of these types of
      bugs whilst IPv6 support mature. For that reason we recommend to network operators to always
      double check the IPv6 data retrieved from SNMP agents and interface counters at least for
      a short period of time. As the IPv6 support moves forward and matures, this practice would be
      less important in the future.
      </t>

    </section>

    <section title="Security Considerations">
      
      <t>From the security stand point, monitoring IPv4, IPv6 or Dual Stack networks is no different
      and the same preventions have to be taken. In order to protect SNMP agents, Network Monitoring
      Systems (NMS), flow collectors, network analyzers, etc. operators are advised to use a variety
      of methods such as access list, separate networks for management and monitoring, avoid the use of
      clear text access, etc.
      </t>
      
    </section>
    
        <section anchor="iana" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>None.</t>
    </section>
        
     <section title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>We would like to thank Humberto Galiza, Alejandro Acosta, Sofia Silva, Diego Lopez,
      Ariel Weher, and Christian O'Flaherty for their questions, suggestions, reviews
      and comments. Also we would like to thank the LACNOG
      community for the informal comments that gave us during the meetings.</t>
    </section>
    
  </middle>



  <back>
    

    <references title="Informative References">
      <!-- Here we use entities that we defined at the beginning. -->


      &RFC1441;
      &RFC1158;
      &RFC1156;
      &RFC1213;
      &RFC2011;
      &RFC2012;
      &RFC2013;
      &RFC2452;
      &RFC2454;
      &RFC2465;
      &RFC2466;
      &RFC4292;
      &RFC4022;
      &RFC4113;
      &RFC4293;
      &RFC3411;
      &RFC5101;
      &RFC5102;
      &RFC3594;
      &RFC6555;
      &RFC3176;

 
    </references>



  </back>
</rfc>
