<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY RFC2205 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2205.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3031 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3031.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3209 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3209.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4090 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4090.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5036 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5036.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4447 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4447.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3471 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3471.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3472 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3472.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5331 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5331.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5920 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5920.xml">
]>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="no" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<rfc category="std" docName="draft-minto-rsvp-lsp-egress-fast-protection-02"
     ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title>RSVP-TE LSP egress fast-protection</title>

    <author fullname="Jeyananth Minto Jeganathan" initials="J"
            surname="Jeganathan">
      <organization>Juniper Networks</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>1194 N Mathilda Avenue</street>

          <city>Sunnyvale</city>

          <region>CA</region>

          <code>94089</code>

          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>

        <email>minto@juniper.net</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Hannes Gredler" initials="H" surname="Gredler">
      <organization>Juniper Networks</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>1194 N Mathilda Avenue</street>

          <city>Sunnyvale</city>

          <region>CA</region>

          <code>94089</code>

          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>

        <email>hannes@juniper.net</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Yimin Shen" initials="Y" surname="Shen">
      <organization>Juniper Networks</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>10 Technology Park Drive</street>

          <city>Westford</city>

          <region>MA</region>

          <code>01886</code>

          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>

        <email>yshen@juniper.net</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date day="25" month="April" year="2013"/>

    <area>Routing</area>

    <workgroup>Network Working Group</workgroup>

    <keyword>Egress protection</keyword>

    <keyword>Egress fast reroute</keyword>

    <keyword>egress local repair</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>RFC4090 defines a fast reroute mechanism for locally repairing an
      RSVP-TE LSP in the order of 10s of milliseconds, in the event of a
      downstream link or node failure. However, this mechanism does not
      provide node protection for LSP egress nodes, even when an alternate
      egress node (a backup egress) is available that could carry the traffic
      to its ultimate destination. This document addresses this scenario and
      describes how to provide egress protection by establishing a bypass LSP
      from the penultimate-hop node of a LSP to the backup egress node. The
      methods described in this document enable local repair in the order of
      10s of milliseconds, in the event of the egress node failure. These
      methods are only applicable if traffic carried by the LSP can be
      rerouted to its ultimate destination by the backup egress node.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>This document describes procedures for providing fast protection for
      RSVP-TE LSPs in case of the egress node failure. Such protection can
      only be provided when an alternate egress node exists that can carry the
      traffic destined for the protected egress to its ultimate destination.
      The primary egress node of an LSP (the protected egress) terminates the
      LSP in steady state, while the alternate egress node (the backup egress)
      does so when the primary fails. A bypass LSP is established from the
      penultimate-hop node to the backup egress. The penultimate-hop node,
      serving as a PLR (point of local repair), redirects traffic to the
      backup egress node of the LSP using this bypass LSP in the event of
      primary egress node failure.</t>

      <t>The backup egress node forwards the traffic to its ultimate
      destination using methods that are beyond the scope this document. For
      example, backup egress node could use the service specific mechanism
      specified in [pwe3-endpoint-fast-protection] and [l3vpn-egress
      PE-fast-protection] and mirror the inner labels (e.g. layer-2/3 VPN
      service labels) from the primary on the backup. The backup would then
      repair the traffic to its destination based on the mirrored labels. This
      document focuses on the methods for setting up the bypass LSP to the
      backup egress so that service specific mechanism could build top on
      this.</t>

      <figure anchor="Base-topology">
        <artwork>            
                [R1]                       [R8] 
                    \                     /      
               [R2]---[R3]----[R4]-----[R5]---[R6]
                         \             /  \\
                          [R9]-----[R10]   [R7]

                Protected LSP to-R6.x:   [R1-&gt;R3-&gt;R4-&gt;R5-&gt;R6.x]
                Protected LSP to-R6.y:   [R1-&gt;R3-&gt;R4-&gt;R5-&gt;R6.y]
                Protected LSP to-sec-R6.x:   [R1-&gt;R3-&gt;R9-&gt;R10-&gt;R5-&gt;R6.x]    
                Protected LSP to-R8.z:   [R2-&gt;R3-&gt;R4-&gt;R5-&gt;R8.z]
                x, y, z: Tunnel destination addresses. 
                R6 has x,y destination addresses.
                Egress-Bypass LSP Tunnel by-R7.x: [R5-&gt;R7.x]
                Egress-Bypass LSP Tunnel by-R7.y: [R5-&gt;R7.y]
                Egress-Bypass LSP Tunnel by-R7.z: [R5-&gt;R7.z]</artwork>
      </figure>

      <t>In <xref target="Base-topology"/>, four LSPs require egress
      protection. R6 and R8 are the primary egresses. R7 is backup egress for
      both R6 and R8. R5 is the penultimate hop node. R5 establishes a bypass
      LSP to R7 to provide fast protection in case R6 or R8 fail. <xref
      target="Base-topology-lsp-table"/> shows the bypass LSPs for each of the
      protected LSPs at R5.</t>

      <texttable anchor="Base-topology-lsp-table">
        <ttcol align="center">Protected LSP</ttcol>

        <ttcol align="center">Egress Bypass LSP</ttcol>

        <c>to-R6.x</c>

        <c>by-R7.x</c>

        <c>to-R6.y</c>

        <c>by-R7.y</c>

        <c>to-sec-R6.x</c>

        <c>by-R7.x</c>

        <c>to-R8.z</c>

        <c>by-R7.z</c>
      </texttable>

      <t>This draft describes two methods for setting up the bypass LSP to the
      backup egress node, the proxy node method and the alias method.</t>

      <t>In the proxy method, an LSP endpoint address is represented as a
      virtual node in the TE domain, attached to the primary egress node and
      the backup egress node via bidirectional point-to-point TE links.</t>

      <figure anchor="Topology-proxy-method">
        <artwork>              
                [R1]                       [R8] 
                    \                     /      
               [R2]---[R3]----[R4]-----[R5]---[R6]---[x]
                         \             /  \         /
                          [R9]-----[R10]   [R7]---+ 

              x: Tunnel destination addresses in the proxy method.                                                   </artwork>
      </figure>

      <t>With the proxy method, when providing egress protection to the LSPs
      with destination address x, terminating on primary R6, with backup
      egress R7, from <xref target="Base-topology"/>, the topology is modeled
      as shown in <xref target="Topology-proxy-method"/>.</t>

      <t>With this representation, penultimate-hop node R5 could use RFC 4090
      RSVP fast-reroute PLR procedures to set up a bypass LSP to the backup
      egress node R7, by avoiding the primary egress node R6.</t>

      <t>In alias method, an LSP endpoint address is associated with a primary
      egress and a explicit backup egress. The penultimate-hop node of the
      protected LSP may learn the backup for the LSP from backup egress IGP
      advertisement or by a local configuration. With this method, the
      penultimate-hop node can set up a bypass LSP to the backup egress node,
      by avoiding the primary egress node.</t>

      <figure anchor="Topology-alias-method">
        <artwork>               [R1]                       [R8] 
                    \                     /      
               [R2]---[R3]----[R4]-----[R5]---[R6]x
                         \             /  \       
                          [R9]-----[R10]   [R7](x)  
              x: Tunnel destination addresses. 
              R6 x: R6 primary egress for x. 
              R7(x): R7 Backup egress for x.</artwork>
      </figure>

      <t>In <xref target="Topology-alias-method"/>, let say x is tunnel
      destination address and R6 advertise x as secondary loopback address.
      With this alias representation R5 see the x as x{R6,R7} where R6 is
      primary and R7 is backup for x. This primary to backup mapping is either
      learn through R7's IGP backup availability advertisement or by a local
      configuration in R5.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Specification of Requirements">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
      document are to be interpreted as described in RFC 2119.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Terminology">
      <t>PLR: Point of Local Repair. The head-end LSR of a backup tunnel or a
      detour LSP</t>

      <t>PHN: Penultimate Hop Node for an LSP.</t>

      <t>Primary egress node: Node terminates a LSP in steady state.</t>

      <t>Primary: Primary egress node.</t>

      <t>Egress Protected LSP: A Protected LSP that also required protection
      from primary egress node failure</t>

      <t>Backup egress node: Node could rerouted/repaired data carried in a
      protected LSP</t>

      <t>Backup node: Backup egress node.</t>

      <t>Protector: Backup egress node.</t>

      <t>Protector and Backup node are used interchangeably but convey the
      same meaning.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Proxy" title="Proxy method">
      <t>In this method, an LSP endpoint address is represented as a virtual
      TE node connected to a primary egress node and a backup egress node with
      bidirectional TE links, as shown in <xref
      target="Topology-proxy-method"/>. With this model, node protection
      establishment and bypass LSP path computation on the penultimate hop of
      an LSP can follow the procedure described in RFC4090.</t>

      <section anchor="proxy-adv"
               title="Tunnel destination Advertisement in IGP ">
        <t>Advertising the tunnel destination as a stub proxy TE node requires
        two steps: 1) a node representation (proxy-node) and 2)links to and
        from primary egress and backup egress.</t>

        <t>The primary advertises a proxy node with two links, to the primary
        egress and the backup egress, respectively. The router ID of the proxy
        node is LSP end point address. The system-ID of the proxy is derived
        from the LSP end point address with BCD encoding. The resulting
        system-ID and router-ID MUST be unique within the IGP routing
        domain.</t>

        <t>Both stub links are advertised with maximum routable metric and TE
        metric, and zero bandwidth, as shown in <xref
        target="bidir-te-links"/>. This avoids the proxy node serving as a
        transit node for any path. The router-ID or system-ID of the backup
        egress can be dynamically learned from the IGP link state database or
        can be configured on the primary egress.</t>

        <figure anchor="bidir-te-links">
          <artwork>     
     primary egress -
                      \ metric 1, TE metric 1, bandwidth max
                       \
                        \
                         \
                          \ metric max, TE metric max, bandwidth 0
                           |
                       proxy node [stub node]
                           |
                          / metric max, TE metric max, bandwidth 0
                         /
                        /
                       /
                      / metric max, TE metric max, bandwidth 0
       backup egress-

        </artwork>
        </figure>

        <t>The primary egress advertises an unnumbered transit link to the
        proxy node, with metric 1, TE metric 1, and maximum bandwidth. It may
        be necessary for the primary node to have the capabilities to
        advertise multiple TE unnumbered transit links between primary node
        and proxy-node. The upper bound on the number of such links is the
        number of the links the primary node advertises into TE.</t>

        <t>The backup egress advertises an unnumbered transit link to the
        proxy node, with MAX metric, MAX TE metric, and zero bandwidth. Other
        TE characteristic of the links can be configured and advertised as
        well.</t>

        <section anchor="IS-IS-proxy-node"
                 title="IS-IS proxy-node (Non-Normative)">
          <t>When IS-IS is used as IGP to advertise the proxy node, only
          zeroth fragment of the proxy-node advertisement is valid. All other
          fragments SHOULD be ignored. The zeroth fragment MUST include the
          area address TLV and MAY include the hostname TLV.</t>

          <t>The set of area addresses advertised in proxy node zeroth
          fragment link-state PDU MUST be a subset of Area Addresses
          advertised by the primary egress in the zeroth fragment of the
          link-state PDU of the corresponding IS-IS level. The advertisement
          SHOULD be syntactically identical to the primary egress zeroth
          fragment at corresponding IS-IS level. The hostname SHOULD be set as
          &lt;tunnel-destination + primary egress hostname&gt;.</t>

          <t>The Overload (OL) MUST be set to 1. The Attached (ATT), and
          Partition Repair (P) bits MUST be set to 0.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="OSPF proxy-node (Non-Normative)">
          <t>The advertising router and Link State ID of router LSA MUST be
          LSP end point address. All options bits in router LSA MUST be set to
          zero.</t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section title="Ingress Node Behavior">
        <t>The ingress node of an LSP requesting egress protection SHOULD
        follow the procedures described in RFC 2205 and RFC 4090 to signal the
        LSP. In particular, it SHOULD set the destination to the endpoint
        address (i.e. the proxy node), and the "link protection desired" flag
        and the "node protection desired" flag in the SESSION_ATTRIBUTE object
        of the Path message. In path computation, it MAY optionally exclude
        MAX metric links to avoid the link between the backup egress and the
        proxy node.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Primary Egress Node Behavior">
        <t>When the primary egress node receives a Path message for the LSP
        with destination matching the proxy node address, it MUST append two
        entities in the RRO object of Resv message: 1) the proxy node as a
        virtual downstream node, and 2) itself as a virtual transit node. The
        entity for the proxy node is encoded as {proxy node address, proxy
        link ID, implicit NULL}.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Penultimate Hop Node">
        <t>When the penultimate hop node receives a Resv message from the
        primary egress, it sees itself as two hops away from LSP's destination
        rather than one hop, based on the RRO. Thus, it can set up node
        protection for the LSP by following the procedure described in RFC
        4090. It SHOULD set up a bypass LSP to the backup egress node. When
        computing a path for the bypass LSP, it SHOULD avoid the primary
        egress node and choose a path via the backup egress node to reach the
        proxy node.</t>

        <section title="Backup LSP Signaling during Local Repair">
          <t>The penultimate hop node SHOULD uses the same procedure as
          defined RFC4090 to signal the backup Path, in the event of failure
          of the primary egress node.</t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section anchor="Proxy-backup" title="Backup Egress Node Behavior">
        <t>When the backup egress node receives Path message of the bypass
        LSP, it MUST terminate the Path message based on match between the LSP
        destination and the proxy node address. It SHOULD assign a
        non-reserved label to the bypass LSP. This non-reserved label provide
        forwarding context during repair.</t>

        <section title="Backup LSP Signaling during Local Repair">
          <t>During local repair, the backup egress node will receive Path
          message of egress-protected LSP from the penultimate hop node. The
          backup egress node SHOULD terminate the Path message, and respond
          with a Resv message.</t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section title="Proxy method solution characteristics">
        <t>The biggest advantage of the proxy method is that it does not
        require protocol extensions and can be implemented locally at the
        tunnel egress node. Thus, no software upgrades are required in the
        core of the network.</t>

        <t>The proxy method has the following caveats:<list style="numbers">
            <t>To support TE constrains like colors and SRLG for a protected
            LSP the primary needs to have the capability to advertise multiple
            links to between proxy and primary.</t>

            <t>Bypass LSP with constrains cannot be supported.</t>

            <t>If IS-IS is used as the IGP then the Primary node should not be
            configured with overload bit.</t>

            <t>Backup egress could be used as primary end point in the
            forwarding plane if the protected LSP established to backup
            instead of primary in transient condition.</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>Due to its characteristics, the proxy method is suitable for mixed
        environments, where an upgrade of the entire network is not
        feasible.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Alias" title="Alias  model">
      <t>In this model Penultimate hop node (PHN) of a protected LSP
      understands that LSP end point has a backup egress and it could repair
      traffic carried in the protected LSP in the event of primary egress
      failure. After the primary egress failure, the PHN reroutes traffic
      using a bypass tunnel to backup egress. The tunnel endpoint address and
      backup egress mapping could be configured in penultimate hop node or
      signaled through IGP from the backup. <xref target="Alias-Table"/>
      illustrates the PHN mapping primary to backup mapping for the topology
      in <xref target="Base-topology"/>.</t>

      <texttable align="center" anchor="Alias-Table" title="Table mapping">
        <ttcol align="center">Primary Egress Router ID</ttcol>

        <ttcol align="center">Backup egress router ID</ttcol>

        <ttcol align="center">Backup LSP destination address.</ttcol>

        <c>10.1.2.6</c>

        <c>10.1.1.6</c>

        <c>10.1.1.7</c>

        <c>10.1.2.6</c>

        <c>10.1.3.6</c>

        <c>10.1.1.6</c>

        <c>10.1.1.7</c>

        <c>10.1.3.6</c>

        <c>10.1.2.8</c>

        <c>10.1.1.8</c>

        <c>10.1.1.7</c>

        <c>10.1.2.8</c>
      </texttable>

      <section anchor="Alias-Ingress-Behavior" title="Ingress Behavior">
        <t>The ingress should follow the procedure in RFC 3209 with tunnel
        endpoint address. The path computation could use the tunnel endpoint
        address advertised using the procedures of RFC 5786.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Primary Egress node">
        <t>Primary egress node advertises tunnel end points that require
        protection using RFC 5786 in OSPF and/or IP interface addresses
        TLV(132) in IS-IS. These TLVs are defined as Local address
        advertisement in TE. The rest of the behavior is same RFC 4090.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Backup egress node">
        <t>When backup receives a Path message not through a bypass tunnel for
        a destination address it protects with ERO constrains only one self
        sub objects then it MUST accept and respond with RRO objects in Resv
        message. The RRO object {node ID, Ip address, label} for tunnel end
        address set with {Node ID, tunnel endpoint address, non-reserved
        label}. This non-reserved label provide forwarding context during
        local repair.</t>

        <section title="Procedures for the Backup egress during Local Repair">
          <t>The Backup egress sends Resv, ResvTear, and PathErr messages by
          sending them directly to the address in the RSVP_HOP object, as
          specified in [RSVP-TE].</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Processing Backup Tunnel's ERO">
          <t>When backup receive Path message through a bypass tunnel with one
          sub-object for destination address it protects then it should accept
          ERO.</t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section title="Penultimate hop node">
        <t>PLR learns/configured backup egress for tunnel a end point address
        advertised by primary egress. When PLR setup bypass for node
        protection LSP it will also lookup for the backup egress if PLR is
        penultimate hop of the LSP. If backup egress is available for LSP
        tunnel end point address then it setup bypass-LSP to backup egress if
        it is not setup already. The constrains will be exclude egress node.
        PHN could setup bypass-LSP with destination as backup egress node or
        tunnel endpoint address. If the bypass tunnel endpoint address is not
        the protected LSP tunnel endpoint then it also initiates backup LSP
        for tunnel end point address through bypass tunnel to learn the label
        to use in failure.</t>

        <section title="Signaling a Backup Path">
          <t>PHP SHALL uses the same procedure as defined RFC4090 to signal
          the backup Path.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Procedures for Backup Path Computation">
          <t>PLR has to find the desired explicit route for the backup path.
          This can be done using a CSPF computation. If PLR is PHN for the
          protected LSP needs node protection then destination for the backup
          path MUST be backup egress router ID with the constraint that the
          LSP cannot traverse the primary egress node and/or link whose
          failure is being protected against. For other constrains SHOULD
          follow RFC4090.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Signaling for Facility Protection">
          <t>A PHN use one or more bypass tunnels to protect against the
          failure of a egress primary node. This bypass tunnels set up in
          advance or dynamically created as new protected LSPs are
          signaled.</t>

          <section title="Discovering Downstream Labels">
            <t>To support facility backup, the PHN must determine the label
            that will indicate to the backup egress that packets received with
            that label should be processed by primary egress context. This can
            be done by setting up the UHP bypass tunnel to the backup egress
            with tunnel endpoint address as destination.</t>
          </section>

          <section title="Processing Backup Tunnel's ERO ">
            <t>Sub-objects belonging to abstract nodes that precede the tunnel
            endpoint Point are removed. A sub-object identifying the Backup
            Tunnel destination is then added.</t>
          </section>

          <section title="PLR Procedures during Local Repair">
            <t>PHN SHALL uses the procedures defined in RFC4090 during the
            local repair.</t>
          </section>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section title="Alias method solution characterization">
        <t>The alias method will work with arbitrary TE constraints and
        suitable for networks that required LSP with those TE constraints. To
        avoid PLR static backup egress configuration, IGP extension is
        required.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>The security considerations discussed in RFC 5036, RFC 5331, RFC
      3209, and RFC 4090 apply to this document.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="ack" title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>This document leverages work done by Hannes Gredler, Yakov Rekhter
      and several others on LSP tail-end protection. Thanks to Ina Minei,
      Nischal Sheth, Nitin Bahadur, Ashwin Sampath and Kaliraj Vairavakkalai
      for their contribution.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      &RFC5331;

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4364"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5036"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2205"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3209"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4090"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3471"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3031"?>

      <reference anchor="LDP-UPSTREAM">
        <front>
          <title>MPLS Upstream Label Assignment for LDP</title>

          <author fullname="Rahul Aggarwal" initials="R" surname="Aggarwal">
            <organization>Juniper Networks</organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="Jean-Louis Le Roux" initials="J. L. Le"
                  surname="Roux">
            <organization>France Telecom</organization>
          </author>

          <date year="2011"/>
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-ietf-mpls-ldp-upstream"/>

        <format target="http://tools.ietf.org/html/draft-ietf-mpls-ldp-upstream-10"
                type="TXT"/>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RSVP-NON-PHP-OOB">
        <front>
          <title>Non PHP Behavior and out-of-band mapping for RSVP-TE
          LSPs</title>

          <author fullname="Zafar Ali" initials="A" surname="Ali">
            <organization>Cisco Systems, Inc</organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="George Swallow" initials="Z" surname="Swallow">
            <organization>Cisco Systems, Inc</organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="Rahul Aggarwal" initials="R" surname="Aggarwal">
            <organization>Juniper Networks</organization>
          </author>

          <date year="2011"/>
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft"
                    value="draft-ietf-mpls-rsvp-te-no-php-oob-mapping"/>

        <format target="http://tools.ietf.org/html/draft-ietf-mpls-rsvp-te-no-php-oob-mapping-07"
                type="TXT"/>
      </reference>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5286"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5714"?>

      <reference anchor="pwe3-endpoint-fast-protection"
                 target="pwe3-endpoint-fast-protection">
        <front>
          <title>PW Endpoint Fast Failure Protection</title>

          <author fullname="Yimin Shen" initials="Y" role="editor"
                  surname="Shen"/>

          <author fullname="Rahul Aggarwal" initials="R" surname="Aggarwal"/>

          <author fullname="Wim Henderickx"/>

          <date year="2011"/>
        </front>

        <format target="http://tools.ietf.org/html/draft-shen-pwe3-endpoint-fast-protection-02"
                type="TXT"/>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="l3vpn-egress-PE-fast-protection"
                 target="2547-egress-PE-fast-protection">
        <front>
          <title>2547 egress PE Fast Failure Protection</title>

          <author fullname="Jeyananth Minto Jeganathan" initials="J"
                  surname="Jeganathan">
            <address>
              <postal>
                <street>1194 N Mathilda Avenue</street>
              </postal>

              <email>minto@juniper.net</email>
            </address>
          </author>

          <author fullname="Hannes Gredler" initials="G" surname="Gredler">
            <address>
              <postal>
                <street>1194 N Mathilda Avenue</street>
              </postal>

              <email>hannes@juniper.net</email>
            </address>
          </author>

          <date year="2011"/>
        </front>

        <format target="http://tools.ietf.org/html/draft-minto-2547-egress-node-fast-protection-00"
                type="TXT"/>
      </reference>
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
