<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc strict="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<rfc category="std" docName="draft-saintandre-vcard-thing-00" ipr="trust200902">

  <front>
    <title abbrev="vCard KIND:thing">vCard KIND:thing</title>
    <author initials="P." surname="Saint-Andre" fullname="Peter Saint-Andre">
      <organization>Cisco</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>1899 Wyknoop Street, Suite 600</street>
          <city>Denver</city>
          <region>CO</region>
          <code>80202</code>
          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>
        <phone>+1-303-308-3282</phone>
        <email>psaintan@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date year="2011" month="April" day="6"/>
    <keyword>vCard</keyword>
    <abstract>
      <t>This document defines a vCard entity kind of "thing".</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>

    <section title="Rationale" anchor="rationale">
      <t>Version 4 of the vCard specification <xref target='VCARD'/> defines a new KIND property that specifies the kind of object that a vCard represents.  During working group discussion of that specification, the "thing" value of the KIND property was removed, with the expectation that the value might be defined in a vCard extension.  Therefore, this document defines the "thing" value, which is intended to represent non-human entities such as physical objects and software applications.  As one example of the "thing" KIND, vCards are currently used in the Extensible Messaging and Presence Protocol <xref target='XMPP'/> to represent XMPP servers that are deployed on the network.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Properties" anchor="properties">
      <t>The base vCard specification defines a large number of properties, and more properties might be defined in vCard extensions.  The following base properties make sense for vCards that represent things (some of these properties might apply to the administrators of the entity, such as a contact email address, or to the provider of a service, such as a logo).</t>
      <t>
        <list style='symbols'>
          <t>FN</t>
          <t>ADR</t>
          <t>TEL</t>
          <t>EMAIL</t>
          <t>IMPP</t>
          <t>LANG</t>
          <t>TZ</t>
          <t>GEO</t>
          <t>LOGO</t>
          <t>URL</t>
          <t>KEY</t>
        </list>
      </t>
    </section>

    <section title="IANA Considerations" anchor="iana">
      <t>The IANA is requested to add "thing" to its registry of values for the vCard KIND property.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Security Considerations" anchor="security">
      <t>Use of vCards to represent non-human entities is not envisioned to introduce security considerations beyond those specified for vCards in general as described in <xref target='VCARD'/>.</t>
    </section>

  </middle>

  <back>

    <references title="Normative References">

<reference anchor='VCARD'>
<front>
<title>vCard Format Specification</title>
<author initials='S' surname='Perreault' fullname='Simon Perreault'>
    <organization />
</author>
<date month='April' day='6' year='2011' />
<abstract><t>This document defines the vCard data format for representing and exchanging a variety of information about individuals and other entities (e.g., formatted and structured name and delivery addresses, email address, multiple telephone numbers, photograph, logo, audio clips, etc.).</t></abstract>
</front>
<seriesInfo name='Internet-Draft' value='draft-ietf-vcarddav-vcardrev-17' />
<format type='TXT'
        target='http://www.ietf.org/internet-drafts/draft-ietf-vcarddav-vcardrev-17.txt' />
</reference>

    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">

<reference anchor='XMPP'>
<front>
<title>Extensible Messaging and Presence Protocol (XMPP): Core</title>
<author initials='P.' surname='Saint-Andre' fullname='P. Saint-Andre'>
<organization /></author>
<date year='2011' month='March' />
<abstract>
<t>The Extensible Messaging and Presence Protocol (XMPP) is an application profile of the Extensible Markup Language (XML) that enables the near-real-time exchange of structured yet extensible data between any two or more network entities.  This document defines XMPP's core protocol methods: setup and teardown of XML streams, channel encryption, authentication, error handling, and communication primitives for messaging, network availability ("presence"), and request-response interactions.  This document obsoletes RFC 3920. [STANDARDS-TRACK]</t></abstract></front>
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='6120' />
<format type='TXT' octets='451942' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc6120.txt' />
</reference>

    </references>

  </back>

</rfc>
