<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc strict="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<rfc category="std" docName="draft-saintandre-vcarddav-thing-01" ipr="trust200902">

  <front>
    <title abbrev="vCard KIND:thing">vCard KIND:thing</title>
    <author initials="P." surname="Saint-Andre" fullname="Peter Saint-Andre">
      <organization>Cisco</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>1899 Wyknoop Street, Suite 600</street>
          <city>Denver</city>
          <region>CO</region>
          <code>80202</code>
          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>
        <phone>+1-303-308-3282</phone>
        <email>psaintan@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date year="2011" month="May" day="12"/>
    <keyword>vCard</keyword>
    <abstract>
      <t>This document defines a value of "thing" for the vCard KIND property so that vCards can be used to represent physical objects and software applications.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>

    <section title="Introduction" anchor="intro">
      <t>Version 4 of the vCard specification <xref target='VCARD'/> defines a new KIND property for the type of entity that a vCard represents.  The "thing" value of the KIND property was removed from that specification, with the expectation it might be defined in a vCard extension.  This document defines such an extension so that vCards can be used to represent things like physical objects and software applications.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Meaning" anchor="meaning">
      <t>When the KIND property has a value of "thing", the vCard represents a physical object (e.g., a building, a vehicle, or a machine) or a software application (e.g., an application server, client, or bot).  As one example of the "thing" KIND, vCards are currently used in the Extensible Messaging and Presence Protocol <xref target='XMPP'/> to represent instant messaging servers that are deployed on the network.</t>
      <t>Although it might be desirable to define a more fine-grained taxonomy of things (e.g., a KIND of "thing" with a subtype of "vehicle"), such a taxonomy is out of scope for this document.</t>
      <t>The following base properties make sense for vCards that represent things (this list is not exhaustive, and other properties might be applicable as well):</t>
      <t>
        <list style='symbols'>
          <t>ADR</t>
          <t>EMAIL</t>
          <t>FN</t>
          <t>GEO</t>
          <t>IMPP</t>
          <t>KEY</t>
          <t>KIND</t>
          <t>LANG</t>
          <t>LOGO</t>
          <t>NOTE</t>
          <t>ORG</t>
          <t>PHOTO</t>
          <t>REV</t>
          <t>SOURCE</t>
          <t>TEL</t>
          <t>TZ</t>
          <t>URL</t>
        </list>
      </t>
      <t>Because things do not have work places and personal lives, it makes no sense to use the "work" and "home" values of the TYPE parameter in a thing's vCard (see Section 5.6 of <xref target='VCARD'/>).</t>
      <t>The properties in a thing's vCard apply to one of the following:</t>
      <t>
        <list style='symbols'>
          <t>The thing itself (e.g., the FN property might represent the friendly name of an application service, the URL property might represent a website that contains further information about the service, and the ADR, GEO, and TZ properties might represent the physical address, geographical location, and timezone of the machine where the service is hosted).<vspace blankLines='1'/></t>
          <t>An organization or person that owns the thing (e.g., the LOGO property might represent the corporate logo of a service provider).<vspace blankLines='1'/></t>
          <t>A person or role that controls the thing (e.g., the TEL, EMAIL, and IMPP properties might represent ways to contact a server administrator).</t>
        </list>
      </t>
    </section>

    <section title="Example" anchor="example">
      <t>The following example of an XMPP server is borrowed from <xref target='XMPP-VCARD'/> and uses the XML representation of vCard described in <xref target='VCARDXML'/>.</t>
      <figure>
        <artwork><![CDATA[
<vcard xmlns="urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:vcard-4.0"> 
  <fn><text>jabber.org IM service</text></fn>
  <url><uri>http://www.jabber.org/</uri></url>
  <lang>
    <parameters><pref>1</pref></parameters>
    <language-tag>en</language-tag>
  </lang>
  <email><text>xmpp@jabber.org</text></email>
  <impp><uri>xmpp:jabber.org</uri></impp>
  <logo><uri>http://www.jabber.org/images/logo.png</uri></logo>
  <geo><uri>geo:42.25,-91.05</uri></geo>
  <tz><text>America/Chicago</text></tz>
  <source><uri>xmpp:jabber.org?vcard</uri></source>
  <rev><timestamp>19990104T122100Z</timestamp></rev>
  <kind><text>thing</text></kind>
</vcard>
        ]]></artwork>
      </figure>
    </section>

    <section title="IANA Considerations" anchor="iana">
      <t>The IANA is requested to add "thing" to the registry of property values for vCard4.  In conformance with Section 10.2.6 of <xref target='VCARD'/>, the registration is as follows, where the reference is to RFC&rfc.number;.</t>
      <t>
        <list style='hanging'>
          <t hangText='Value:'>thing</t>
          <t hangText='Purpose:'>The entity represented by the vCard is a physical object (e.g., a building, a vehicle, or a machine) or a software application (e.g., an application server, client, or bot).</t>
          <t hangText='Conformance:'>This value can be used with the "KIND" property.</t>
          <t hangText='Example:'>See Section 3 of RFC&rfc.number;.</t>
        </list>
      </t>
    </section>

    <section title="Security Considerations" anchor="security">
      <t>Use of vCards to represent physical objects and software applications is not envisioned to introduce security considerations beyond those specified for vCards in <xref target='VCARD'/>.</t>
    </section>

  </middle>

  <back>

    <references title="Normative References">

<reference anchor='VCARD'>
<front>
<title>vCard Format Specification</title>
<author initials='S' surname='Perreault' fullname='Simon Perreault'>
    <organization />
</author>
<date month='April' day='9' year='2011' />
<abstract><t>This document defines the vCard data format for representing and exchanging a variety of information about individuals and other entities (e.g., formatted and structured name and delivery addresses, email address, multiple telephone numbers, photograph, logo, audio clips, etc.).</t></abstract>
</front>
<seriesInfo name='Internet-Draft' value='draft-ietf-vcarddav-vcardrev-19' />
<format type='TXT'
        target='http://www.ietf.org/internet-drafts/draft-ietf-vcarddav-vcardrev-19.txt' />
</reference>

    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">

<reference anchor='VCARDXML'>
<front>
<title>vCard XML Representation</title>
<author initials='S' surname='Perreault' fullname='Simon Perreault'>
    <organization />
</author>
<date month='April' day='9' year='2011' />
<abstract><t>This document defines the XML schema of the vCard data format.</t></abstract>
</front>
<seriesInfo name='Internet-Draft' value='draft-ietf-vcarddav-vcardxml-09' />
<format type='TXT'
        target='http://www.ietf.org/internet-drafts/draft-ietf-vcarddav-vcardxml-09.txt' />
</reference>

<reference anchor='XMPP'>
<front>
<title>Extensible Messaging and Presence Protocol (XMPP): Core</title>
<author initials='P.' surname='Saint-Andre' fullname='P. Saint-Andre'>
<organization /></author>
<date year='2011' month='March' />
<abstract>
<t>The Extensible Messaging and Presence Protocol (XMPP) is an application profile of the Extensible Markup Language (XML) that enables the near-real-time exchange of structured yet extensible data between any two or more network entities.  This document defines XMPP's core protocol methods: setup and teardown of XML streams, channel encryption, authentication, error handling, and communication primitives for messaging, network availability ("presence"), and request-response interactions.  This document obsoletes RFC 3920. [STANDARDS-TRACK]</t></abstract></front>
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='6120' />
<format type='TXT' octets='451942' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc6120.txt' />
</reference>

<reference anchor="XMPP-VCARD">
  <front>
    <title>vCard4 Over XMPP</title>
    <author initials="S." surname="Mizzi" fullname="Samantha Mizzi">
      <organization/>
      <address>
        <email>samizzi@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author initials="P." surname="Saint-Andre" fullname="Peter Saint-Andre">
      <organization/>
      <address>
        <email>stpeter@jabber.org</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date day="07" month="April" year="2011"/>
  </front>
  <seriesInfo name="XSF XEP" value="0292"/>
  <format type="HTML" target="http://xmpp.org/extensions/xep-0292.html"/>
</reference>

    </references>

  </back>

</rfc>
