<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="rfc2629.xslt" ?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<rfc ipr="trust200902" category="bcp" docName="draft-ietf-ipfix-ie-doctors-07.txt">
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
  <front>
    <title abbrev="IPFIX IE-DOCTORS">
      Guidelines for Authors and Reviewers of IPFIX Information Elements
    </title>
    <author initials="B." surname="Trammell" fullname="Brian Trammell">
      <organization abbrev="ETH Zurich">
        Swiss Federal Institute of Technology Zurich
      </organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Gloriastrasse 35</street>
          <city>8092 Zurich</city>
          <country>Switzerland</country>
        </postal>
        <phone>+41 44 632 70 13</phone>
        <email>trammell@tik.ee.ethz.ch</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author initials="B." surname="Claise" fullname="Benoit Claise">
       <organization abbrev="Cisco Systems, Inc.">
       Cisco Systems, Inc.
       </organization>
       <address>
         <postal>
           <street>De Kleetlaan 6a b1</street>
           <city>1831 Diegem</city>
           <country>Belgium</country>
         </postal>
         <phone>+32 2 704 5622</phone>
         <email>bclaise@cisco.com</email>
       </address>
    </author>

    <date month="October" day="3" year="2012"/>
    <area>Operations</area>
    <workgroup>IPFIX Working Group</workgroup>
    <abstract>

      <t>This document provides guidelines for how to write definitions of new
      Information Elements for the IP Flow Information Export (IPFIX)
      protocol. It provides instructions on using the proper conventions for
      Information Elements to be registered in the IANA IPFIX Information
      Element registry, and provides guidelines for expert reviewers to
      evaluate new registrations.</t>

    </abstract>
  </front>
  <middle>

     <section title="Introduction" anchor="sec-intro">

         <t>This document provides guidelines for the definition of new IPFIX
         Information Elements beyond those currently in the <xref
         target="iana-ipfix-assignments">IANA IPFIX Information Element
         Registry</xref>. Given the self-describing nature of the data export
         format used by IPFIX, the definition of new Information Elements is
         often sufficient to allow the application of IPFIX to new network
         measurement and management use cases.</t>

        <t>We intend this document to enable the application of IPFIX to new
        areas by experts in the IETF Working Group or Area Directorate, or the
        community or organization external to the IETF, concerned with the
        technical details of the protocol or application to be measured or
        managed using IPFIX. This expansion occurs with the consultation
        of IPFIX experts informally called IE-DOCTORS. It provides guidelines
        both for those defining new Information Elements as well as the
        IE-DOCTORS reviewing them.</t>
        
         <t>This document essentially codifies two meta-guidelines: (1)
        "define new Information Elements that look like existing Information
        Elements", and (2) "don't define Information Elements unless you need
        to".</t>

        <section title="Intended Audience and Usage" anchor="sec-audience">

            <t>This document is meant for two separate audiences. For those
            defining new Information Elements, it provides specifications and
            best practices to be used in deciding which Information Elements
            are necessary for a given existing or new application,
            instructions for writing the definitions for these Information
            Elements, and information on the supporting documentation required
            for the new application (up to and including the publication of
            one or more RFCs describing it). For the IPFIX experts appointed
            as IE-DOCTORS, and for IANA personnel changing the <xref
            target="iana-ipfix-assignments">IANA IPFIX Information Element
            Registry</xref>, it defines a set of acceptance criteria against
            which these proposed Information Elements should be evaluated.</t>

            <t>This document is not intended to guide the extension of the
            IPFIX protocol itself, e.g. through new export mechanisms, data
            types, or the like; these activities should be pursued through the
            publication of standards-track RFCs within the IPFIX Working
            Group.</t>

            <t>This document, together with <xref
            target="I-D.ietf-ipfix-information-model-rfc5102bis"/>, defines
            the procedures for management of the <xref
            target="iana-ipfix-assignments">IANA IPFIX Information Element
            Registry</xref>. The practices outlined in this document are
            intended to guide experts when reviewing additions or changes to
            the Information Elements in the registry under Expert Review as
            defined in <xref target="RFC5226"/>.</t>

        </section>

        <section title="Overview of relevant IPFIX documents">
        
            <t><xref target="I-D.ietf-ipfix-protocol-rfc5101bis"/> defines the
            IPFIX Protocol, the IPFIX-specific terminology used by this
            document, and the data type encodings for each of the data types
            supported by IPFIX.</t>

            <t><xref target="I-D.ietf-ipfix-information-model-rfc5102bis"/>
            defines the basis of the IPFIX Information Model, referring to
            <xref target="iana-ipfix-assignments"/> for the specific
            Information Element definitions. It states that new Information
            Elements may be added to the Information Model on Expert Review
            basis, delegates the appointment of experts to an IESG Area
            Director, and refers to this document for details on the extension
            process. This document is intended to further codify the best
            practices to be followed by these experts, in order to improve the
            efficiency of this process. </t>

            <t><xref target="RFC5103"/> defines a method for exporting
            bidirectional flow information using IPFIX; this document should
            be followed when extending IPFIX to represent information about
            bidirectional network interactions in general. Additionally, new
            Information Elements should be annotated for their reversibility
            or lack thereof as per this document.</t>

            <t><xref target="RFC5610"/> defines a method for exporting
            information about Information Elements inline within IPFIX. In
            doing so, it explicitly defines a set of restrictions, implied in
            <xref target="I-D.ietf-ipfix-protocol-rfc5101bis"/> and <xref
            target="I-D.ietf-ipfix-information-model-rfc5102bis"/>, on the use
            of data types and semantic; these restrictions must be observed in
            the definition of new Information Elements, as in <xref
            target="sec-ie-semantics"/>.</t>

       </section>

    </section>

    <section title="Terminology" anchor="terminology-section">

        <t>Capitalized terms used in this document that are defined in the
        Terminology section of <xref
        target="I-D.ietf-ipfix-protocol-rfc5101bis"/> are to be interpreted as
        defined there.</t>

        <t>An "application", as used in this document, refers to a candidate
        protocol, task, or domain to which IPFIX export, collection, and/or
        storage is applied. By this definition, the <xref
        target="RFC5472">IPFIX Applicability statement</xref> definied the
        initial applications of IPFIX, and <xref target="RFC5476">PSAMP</xref>
        was the first new IPFIX application after the publication of the IPFIX
        protocol itself.</t>
        
         <t>"IANA IE registry", as used in this document, unless otherwise
        noted, refers to the <xref target="iana-ipfix-assignments">IANA IPFIX
        Information Element Registry</xref>.</t>

        <!-- <t>The key words "MUST", "must not", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
        "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
        document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
        target="RFC2119"/>.</t> -->

    </section>

    <section title="How to apply IPFIX" anchor="sec-howto">

        <t>Though originally specified for the export of IP flow information,
        the message format, template mechanism, and data model specified by
        IPFIX lead to it being applicable to a wide variety of network
        management situations. In addition to flow information export, for
        which it was designed, and packet information export as specified by
        <xref target="RFC5476">PSAMP</xref>, any application with the
        following characteristics is a good candidate for an IPFIX
        application:</t>

        <t><list style="symbols">

            <t>The application's data flow is fundamentally unidirectional.
            IPFIX is a "push" protocol, supporting only the export of
            information from a sender (an Exporting Process) to a receiver (a
            Collecting Process). Request-response interactions are not
            supported by IPFIX.</t>

            <t>The application handles discrete event information, or
            information to be periodically reported. IPFIX is particularly
            well suited to representing events, which can be scoped in
            time.</t>

            <t>The application handles information about network entities.
            IPFIX's information model is network-oriented, so network
            management applications have many opportunities for information
            model reuse.</t>

            <t>The application requires a small number of arrangements of data
            structures relative to the number of records it handles. The
            template-driven self-description mechanism used by IPFIX excels at
            handling large volumes of identically structured data, compared to
            representations which define structure inline with data (such as
            XML).</t>

        </list></t>

        <t>Most applications meeting these criteria can be supported over
        IPFIX. Once it has been determined that IPFIX is a good fit, the next
        step is determining which Information Elements are necessary to
        represent the information required by the application. Especially for
        network-centric applications, the IANA IE registry
        may already contain all the necessary Information Elements (see <xref
        target="sec-ie-reuse"/> for guidelines on maximizing Information
        Element reuse). In this case, no work within the IETF is necessary:
        simply define Templates and start exporting.</t>

        <t>It is expected, however, that most applications will be able to
        reuse some existing Information Elements, but may need to define some
        additional Information Elements to support all their requirements; in
        this case, see <xref target="sec-iedef"/> for best practices to be
        followed in defining Information Elements.</t>

        <t>Optionally, a Working Group or individual contributor may choose to
        write an Internet-Draft for publication as an RFC, detailing the new
        IPFIX application. Such an RFC should contain discussion of the new
        application, the Information Element definitions as in <xref
        target="sec-iedef"/>, as well as suggested Templates and examples of
        the use of those Templates within the new application as in <xref
        target="sec-templates"/>. <xref target="sec-iespec"/> defines a
        compact textual Information Element notation to be used in describing
        these suggested Templates and/or the use of <xref
        target="RFC6313">IPFIX Structured Data</xref> within the new
        application.</t>

    </section>

    <section title="Defining new Information Elements" anchor="sec-iedef">

        <t>In many cases, a new application will require nothing more than a
        new Information Element or set of Information Elements to be
        exportable using IPFIX. An Information Element meeting the following
        criteria, as evaluated by the IE-DOCTORS, is eligible for
        inclusion in the IANA IE registry:</t>

        <t><list style="symbols">

            <t>The Information Element must be unique within the registry, and
            its description must represent a substantially different meaning
            from that of any existing Information Element. An existing
            Information Element that can be reused for a given purpose should
            be.</t>

            <t>The Information Element should contain as little internal
            structure as possible. Instead of representing complex information
            by overlaying internal structure on a simple data type such as
            octetArray, such information should be represented with multiple
            simple Information Elements to be exported in parallel or using
            <xref target="RFC6313">IPFIX Structured Data</xref>, as in <xref
            target="sec-ie-structure"/>. The internal structure of a proposed
            IE may be evaluated by the IE-DOCTORS with an eye toward
            interoperability and/or backward compatibility with existing
            methods of exporting similar data on a case-by-case basis.</t>

            <t>Information Elements representing information about proprietary
            or nonstandard applications should not be registered in the IANA
            IE registry; these be represented using enterprise-specific
            Information Elements as detailed in section 3.2 [RFC-EDITOR NOTE:
            verify section number] of <xref
            target="I-D.ietf-ipfix-protocol-rfc5101bis"/>, instead.</t>

        </list></t>

        <t>The definition of new Information Elements requires a descriptive
        name, a specification of the data type from the IPFIX Data Type
        subregistry in the IANA IE registry (defined in <xref
        target="I-D.ietf-ipfix-information-model-rfc5102bis"/> as itself
        extensible via Standards Action as per <xref target="RFC5226"/>), and
        a human-readable description written in English. This section provides
        guidelines on each of these components of an Information Element
        definition, referring to existing documentation such as <xref
        target="I-D.ietf-ipfix-information-model-rfc5102bis"/> as
        appropriate.</t>

        <section title="Information Element naming" anchor="sec-ie-names">

            <t>As the name of an Information Element is the first thing a
            potential implementor will use when determining whether it is
            suitable for a given application, it is important to be as precise
            and descriptive as possible. Names of Information Elements:</t>

            <t><list style="symbols"> 

                <t>must be chosen carefully to describe the use of the
                Information Element within the context in which it will be
                used.</t>

                <t>must be unique within the IANA IE registry.</t>

                <t>start with non-capitalized letters.</t>

                <t>use capital letters for the first letter of each component
                except for the first one (aka "camel case"). All other letters
                are non-capitalized, even for acronyms. Exceptions are made
                for acronyms containing non-capitalized letters, such as
                'IPv4' and 'IPv6'. Examples are "sourceMacAddress" and
                "destinationIPv4Address."</t>

            </list></t>

            <t>In addition, new Information Elements pertaining to a specific
            protocol should name the protocol in the first word in order to
            ease searching by name (e.g. "sipMethod" for a SIP method, as
            would be used in a logging format for SIP based on IPFIX).
            Similarly, new Information Elements pertaining to a specific
            application should name the application in the first word.</t>

        </section>

        <section title="Information Element data types" anchor="sec-ie-types">

            <t>IPFIX provides a set of data types covering most primitives
            used in network measurement and management applications. The most
            appropriate data type should be chosen for the Information Element
            type, IPFIX informationElementDataTypes subregistry at <xref
            target="iana-ipfix-assignments"/>. This subregistry may be
            extended from time to time by a Standards Action  <xref
            target="RFC5226"/>, as defined in <xref target="RFC5610"/>.</t>

            <t>Information Elements representing an integral value with a
            natural width should be defined with the appropriate integral data
            type. This applies especially to values taken directly from
            fixed-width fields in a measured protocol. For example,
            tcpControlBits, the TCP flags byte, is an unsigned8, and
            tcpSequenceNumber is an unsigned32.</t>

            <t>Information Elements representing counters or identifiers
            should be defined as signed64 or unsigned64, as appropriate, to
            maximize the range of values available; applications can use
            reduced-size encoding as defined in Section 6.2 [RFC-EDITOR NOTE:
            verify section number] of <xref
            target="I-D.ietf-ipfix-protocol-rfc5101bis"/> in cases where fewer
            than 2^64 values are necessary.</t>

            <t>Information Elements representing time values must be
            defined with appropriate precision. For example, a Information
            Element for a time measured at second-level precision should be
            defined as having a dateTimeSeconds data type, instead of
            dateTimeMilliseconds.</t>

            <t>Information Elements of type string or octetArray which have
            length constraints (fixed length, minimum and/or maximum length)
            must note these constraints in their description.</t>

            <t>The type of an Information Element must match the type of the
            data it represents. More specifically, information that could be
            represented as a string, but which better matches one of the other
            data types (e.g. an integral type for a number or enumerated type,
            an address type for an address) must be represented by the
            best-matching type, even if the data was represented using a
            different type in the source. For example, an IPFIX application
            that exports Options Template Records mapping IP addresses to
            additional information about each host from an external database
            must use Information Elements of an address type to represent the
            addresses, even if the source database represented these as
            strings.</t>

            <t>Strings and octetArrays must not be used to encode data that
            would be more properly represented using multiple Information
            Elements and/or <xref target="RFC6313">IPFIX Structured
            Data</xref>; see <xref target="sec-ie-structure"/> for more.</t>

             <t>This document does not cover the addition of new Data Types or
            Data Type Semantics to the IPFIX Protocol. As such changes have
            important interoperability considerations and require
            implementation on both Collecting and Exporting Processes, they
            require a Standards Action as per <xref target="RFC5610"/>.
            However, note that the set of primitive types provided by IPFIX
            are applicable to almost any appropriate application, so extending
            the type system is generally not necessary.</t>

        </section>
        
        <section title="Information Element numbering" anchor="sec-ie-numbering">

            <t>Each Information Element has a unique identifier in the IANA
            registry.</t>

            <t>When adding newly registered Information Elements
            to the IANA IE registry, IANA should assign the lowest available
            Information Element identifier (the value column in <xref
            target="iana-ipfix-assignments"/>) in the range 128-32767.</t>

            <t>Information Elements with identifiers from 1-127 are reserved
            for compatibility with corresponding fields in NetFlow version 9,
            as described in <xref target="RFC3954"/>.</t>

            <!-- Such Information Elements may ONLY be requested by a NetFlow
            v9 expert, to be designated by the IESG to consult with IANA on
            NetFlow v9 compatibility with IPFIX. These information elements
            are exempt from IE-DOCTORS review; it is the responsibility of the
            NetFlow v9 expert to ensure that the requested IEs substantially
            conform to the guidelines in this document, with consideration
            given for already-implemented and already-deployed features.</t>
            -->

        </section>

        <section title="Ancillary Information Element properties"
            anchor="sec-ie-semantics">

            <t>Information Elements to which special semantics apply should
            refer to one of the values in the Information Element Semantics
            subregistry of the IANA IE registry, as described in Section 3.2
            [RFC-EDITOR NOTE: verify section number] of <xref
            target="I-D.ietf-ipfix-information-model-rfc5102bis"/>, subject to
            the restrictions given in Section 3.10 of <xref
            target="RFC5610"/>; in other words, the semantics and the type
            must be consistent.</t>

            <t>When defining Information Elements representing a dimensioned
            quantity or entity count, the units of that quantity should be
            defined in the units field. This field takes its values from the
            IANA Information Element Units subregistry of the IANA IE
            registry. If an Information Element expresses a quantity in units
            not yet in this subregistry, then the unit must be added to the
            Units subregistry at the same time the Information Element is
            added to the IANA IE registry. Note that the Units subregistry as defined in <xref target="RFC5610"/> is
            maintained on an Expert Review basis.</t>

            <t>Additionally, when the range of values an Information Element
            can take is smaller than the range implied by its data type, the
            range should be defined within the Information Element's entry the
            IANA IE registry.</t>

        </section>

        <section title="Internal structure in Information Elements" anchor="sec-ie-structure">

			<t>The definition of Information Elements with
            internal structure with the structure defined in the Description
            field is not recommended, except in the following cases:</t>

			<t><list style="numbers">

                <t>The Information Element is a direct copy of a structured
                entity in a measured protocol (e.g. the tcpControlBits
                Information Element for the flags byte from the TCP
                header)</t>

                <t>The Information Element represents a section of a packet of
                protocol entity, in raw form as captured from the wire (e.g.
                the mplsLabelStackSection Information Element for the MPLS
                label stack)</t>

                <t>The Information Element represents a set of flags which are
                tightly semantically related, where representing the flags as
                separate one-byte booleans would be inefficient, and which
                should always appear together in a data record (e.g., the
                anonymizationFlags Information Element for specifying optional
                features of anonymization techniques)</t>

                <t>The Information Element contains internal structure by
                reference to an external datatype or specification containing
                internal structure (e.g., a MIME type or URL), for
                interoperability and backward compatibility purposes</t>

              </list></t>

            <t>Additional exceptions to the above list should be made through
            a publication of an RFC.</t>

            <t>In other cases, candidate Information Elements with internal
            structure should be decomposed into multiple primitive Information
            Elements to be used in parallel. For more complicated semantics,
            where the structure is not identical from Data Record to Data
            Record, or where there is semantic dependency between multiple
            decomposed primitive Information Elements, use the <xref
            target="RFC6313">IPFIX Structured
            Data</xref> extension instead.</t>

            <t>As an example of information element decomposition, consider an
            application-level identifier called an "endpoint", which
            represents a {host, port, protocol} tuple. Instead of allocating
            an opaque, structured "source endpoint" Information Element, the
            source endpoint should be represented by three separate
            Information Elements: "source address", "source port", "transport
            protocol". In this example, the required information
            elements already exist in the IANA IE registry:
            sourceIPv4Address or sourceIPv6Address, sourceTransportPort,
            protocolIdentifier. Indeed, as well as being good practice, this
            normalization down to non-structured Information Elements also
            increases opportunities for reuse as in <xref
            target="sec-ie-reuse"/>.</t>

            <t>The decomposition of data with internal structure should avoid
            the definition of Information Elements with a meaning too specific
            to be generally useful, or that would result in a multitude of
            templates to handle different multiplicities. More information on
            multiplicities is given in the following section.</t>
            
          </section>

          <section title="Information Element multiplicity" anchor="sec-ie-multiplicity">

            <t>Some Information Elements may represent information with a
            multiplicity other than one; i.e., items that may occur multiple
            times within the data to be represented in a single IPFIX record.
            In this case, there are several options, depending on the
            circumstances:</t>

			<t><list style="numbers">

                <t>As specified in section 8 [RFC-EDITOR NOTE: verify section
                number] of <xref
                target="I-D.ietf-ipfix-protocol-rfc5101bis"/>: "if an
                Information Element is required more than once in a Template,
                the different occurrences of this Information Element should
                follow the logical order of their treatments by the Metering
                Process." In other words, in cases where the items have a
                natural order (e.g., the order in which they occur in the
                packet), and the multiplicity is the same for each record, the
                information can be modeled by containing multiple instances of
                the Information Element representing a single item within the
                Template Record describing the Data Records.</t>

                <t>In cases where the items have a variable multiplicity, a
                basicList of the Information Element representing a single
                item can be used as in the <xref target="RFC6313">IPFIX
                Structured Data</xref> extension.</t>

                <t>If the multiple-item structure is taken directly from bytes
                observed on the wire by the Metering Process or otherwise
                taken from the application being measured (e.g., a TCP options
                stack), the multiple-item structure can be exported as a
                variable-length octetArray Information Element holding the raw
                content.</t>

			</list></t>

            <t>Specifically, new Information Element should not encode any
            multiplicity or ordinality information into the definition of the
            Information Element itself.</t>

        </section>

        <section title="Enumerated Values and Subregistries" anchor="sec-ie-subreg">

            <t>When defining an Information Element that takes an enumerated
            value from a set of values which may change in the future, this
            enumeration must be defined by an IANA IE registry or subregistry.
            For situations where an existing registry defines the enumeration
            (e.g., the IANA Protocol Numbers registry for the
            protocolIdentifier Information Element), that registry must be
            used. Otherwise, a new subregistry of the IANA IPFIX registry must
            be defined for the enumerated value, to be modified subject to
            <xref target="RFC5226">Expert Review</xref>.</t>

        </section>

        <section title="Reversibility as per RFC 5103" anchor="ie-reversibility">

            <t><xref target="RFC5103"/> defines a method for exporting
            bidirectional flows using a special Private Enterprise Number to
            define reverse-direction variants of IANA Information Elements,
            and a set of criteria for determining whether an Information
            Element may be reversed using this method. Since almost all
            Information Elements are reversible, <xref target="RFC5103"/>
            enumerates those Information Elements which were defined at
            the time of its publication which are NOT reversible.</t>

            <t>New non-reversible Information Elements must contain a note
            in the description stating that they are not reversible. </t>

        </section>

      <!-- <section title="Promotion of Enterprise-Specific Information Elements" anchor="ie-promotion">

        <t>Some Information Elements may start their lifecycle outside the
        IANA IE registry as enterprise-specific Information Elements scoped to a
        Private Enterprise Number. One stated goal of enterprise-specific
        Information Elements is pre-standards product delivery and
        experimentation; should these experiments be successful and the
        Information Elements generally useful, these should subsequently
        registered with IANA.</t>

        <t>In order to support transition from experimental registration to
        IANA registration, the IANA IE registry provides an optional
        "enterprise-specific IE reference" column for each Information
        Element. In cases of promoted enterprise-specific Information
        Elements, this column in the registry MAY contain the private
        enterprise and Information Element numbers of the enterprise-specific
        version(s) of the Information Element.</t>

      </section> -->

      <section title="Avoiding Bad Ideas in Information Element Design" anchor="ie-dont-do-this">

        <t>In general, the existence of a similarly-defined Information
        Element in the IANA IE registry sets a precedent which may be followed
        to determine whether a given proposed Information Element "fits"
        within the registry. Indeed, the rules specified by this document
        could be interpreted to mean "make new Information Elements that look
        like existing Information Elements". However, for reasons of history,
        there are several Information Elements within the IANA IE registry
        which do not follow best practices in Information Element design.
        These Information Elements are not necessarily so flawed so as to
        require deprecation, but they should be explicitly ignored when
        looking for guidance as to whether a new Information Element should be
        added. Here we provide a set of representative examples taken from the
        IANA IE registry; in general, entries in the IANA IE registry which do
        not follow the guidelines in this document should not be used as
        examples for new Information Element definitions.</t>

        <t>Before registering a new Information Element, it must be determined
        that it would be sufficiently unique within the IANA IE registry. This
        evaluation has not always been done in the past, and the existence of
        the Information Elements defined without this evaluation should not be
        taken as an example that such Information Element definition practices
        should be followed in the future. Specific examples of such
        Information Elements include initiatorOctets and responderOctets
        (which duplicate octetDeltaCount and its reverse per <xref
        target="RFC5103"/>) and initiatorPackets and responderPackets (the
        same, for packetDeltaCount).</t>

        <t>As mentioned in <xref target="sec-ie-types"/>, the type of an
        Information Element should match the type of data the Information
        Element represents. An example of how not to do this is presented by
        the p2pTechnology, tunnelTechnology, and encryptedTechnology
        Information Elements: these represent a three-state enumeration using
        a String. The example set by these Information Elements should not be
        followed in the definition of new Information Elements.</t>

        <t>As mentioned in <xref target="sec-ie-multiplicity"/>, an
        Information Element definition should not include any ordinality or
        multiplicity information. The only example of this within the IANA IE
        registry the following list of assigned IPFIX Information Elements:
        mplsTopLabelStackSection, mplsLabelStackSection2,
        mplsLabelStackSection3, mplsLabelStackSection4,
        mplsLabelStackSection5, mplsLabelStackSection6 mplsLabelStackSection7,
        mplsLabelStackSection8, mplsLabelStackSection9, and
        mplsLabelStackSection10. The only distinction between those
        almost-identical Information Elements is the position within the MPLS
        stack. This Information Element design pattern met an early
        requirement of the definition of IPFIX which was not carried forward
        into the final specification -- namely, that no semantic dependency
        was allowed between Information Elements in the same Record -- and as
        such should not be followed in the definition of new Information
        Elements. In this case, since the size of the MPLS stack will vary
        from flow to flow, it should be exported using <xref
        target="RFC6313">IPFIX Structured Data</xref> where supported, as a
        basicList of MPLS label entries, or as a raw MPLS label stack using
        the variable-length mplsLabelStackSection Information Element.</t>

		</section>
    </section>
    
    <section title="The Information Element Lifecycle" anchor="sec-lifecycle">

        <t>Once an Information Element or set of Information Elements has been
        identified for a given application, Information Element specifications
        in accordance with <xref target="sec-iedef"/> are submitted to IANA to
        follow the IE-DOCTORS process, as defined below. This process is also
        used for other changes to the IANA IE registry, such as deprecation or
        revision, as described later in this section.</t>

      <section title="The IE-DOCTORS process" anchor="sec-process">

        <t>Requests to change the IANA IE registry or a linked subregistry are
        submitted to IANA, which forwards the request to a designated group of
        experts (IE-DOCTORS) appointed by the IESG; these are the reviewers
        called for by the Expert Review <xref target="RFC5226"/> policy
        defined for the IANA IE registry by <xref
        target="I-D.ietf-ipfix-information-model-rfc5102bis"/>. The IE-DOCTORS
        review the request for such things as compliance with this document,
        compliance with other applicable IPFIX-related RFCs, and consistency
        with the currently defined set of Information Elements.</t>

        <t>Authors are expected to review compliance with the specifications
        in this document to check their submissions before sending them to
        IANA.</t>

        <t>IE-DOCTORS reviewers should endeavor to complete referred reviews
        in a timely manner. If the request is acceptable, the IE-DOCTORS
        signify their approval to IANA, which changes the IANA IE registry. If
        the request is not acceptable, the IE-DOCTORS can coordinate with the
        requestor to change the request to be compliant. The IE-DOCTORS may
        also choose in exceptional circumstances to reject clearly frivolous
        or inappropriate change requests outright.</t>

         <t>This process should not in any way be construed as allowing the
        IE-DOCTORS to overrule IETF consensus. Specifically, Information
        Elements in the IANA IE registry which were added with IETF consensus
        require IETF consensus for revision or deprecation.</t>

        <t>IE-DOCTORS decisions may be appealed as in section 7 of <xref
        target="RFC5226"/>.</t>

      </section>

        <section title="Revising Information Elements" anchor="sec-revision">

        <t>The Information Element status field in the IANA IE registry is
        defined in <xref
        target="I-D.ietf-ipfix-information-model-rfc5102bis"/> to allow
        Information Elements to be 'current' or 'deprecated'. No Information
        Elements are as of this writing deprecated. <xref target="RFC5102"/>
        additionally specified an 'obsolete' status; however, this has been
        removed on revision as it served no operational purpose.</t>

        <t>In addition, no policy is defined for revising IANA IE registry
        entries or addressing errors therein. To be certain, changes and
        deprecations within the IANA IE registry are not encouraged, and
        should be avoided to the extent possible. However, in recognition that
        change is inevitable, this section is intended to remedy this
        situation.</t>

        <t>Changes are initiated by sending a new Information Element
        definition to IANA, as in <xref target="sec-process"/>, for an
        already-existing Information Element.</t>

        <t>The primary requirement in the definition of a policy for managing
        changes to existing Information Elements is avoidance of
        interoperability problems; IE-DOCTORS must work to maintain
        interoperability above all else. Changes to Information Elements
        already in use may only be done in an interoperable way; necessary
        changes which cannot be done in a way to allow interoperability with
        unchanged implementations must result in deprecation.</t>

        <t>A change to an Information Element is held to be interoperable only
        when:</t>

        <t><list style="numbers">

            <t>it involves the correction of an error which is obviously only
            editorial; or</t>

            <t>it corrects an ambiguity in the Information Element's
            definition, which itself leads to non-interoperability severe
            enough to prevent the Information Element's usage as originally
            defined (e.g., a prior change to ipv6ExtensionHeaders); or</t>

            <t>it expands the Information Element's data type without changing
            how it is represented (e.g., changing unsigned32 to
            unsigned64, as with a prior change to selectorId); or</t>

            <t>it corrects missing information in the Information Element's
            definition without changing its meaning (e.g., the explicit
            definition of 'quantity' semantics for numeric Information
            Elements without a Data Type Semantics value); or</t>

            <t>it defines a previously undefined or reserved enumerated value,
            or one or more previously reserved bits in an Information Element
            with flag semantics; or</t>

            <t>it expands the set of permissible values in the Information
            Element's range; or</t>

            <t>it harmonizes with an external reference which was itself
            corrected.</t>

        </list></t>

<!--
        <t>A non-interoperable Information Element change may also be made if
        it can be reasonably assumed in the eyes of the appointed experts that
        no unchanged implementation of the Information Element exists; this
        can be held to happen if a non-interoperable change to an Information
        Element defined shortly before is proposed to the IPFIX mailing list
        by the original proposer of the Information Element, and no objection
        is raised within a reasonable amount of time, to be defined by the
        expert reviewers. [EDITOR'S NOTE: objection from Dan Romascanu, to
        discuss on list]</t>
-->
        <t>If a change is deemed permissible by the IE-DOCTORS, IANA makes the
        change in the IANA IE registry. The requestor of the
        change is appended to the Requestor in the registry.</t>

        <t>Each Information Element in the IANA IE registry has a Revision
        number, starting at zero. Each change to an Information Element
        following this process increments the Revision number by one. Since
        any revision must be interoperable according to the criteria above,
        there is no need for the IANA IE registry to store information about
        old revisions.</t>

        <t>When a revised Information Element is accepted into the registry,
        the date of acceptance of the most recent revision is placed into the
        revision Date column of the registry for that Information Element.</t>

        <!-- <t>Information Elements with identifiers in the range 1-127 are
        compatible with the NetFlow V9 protocol as described in <xref
        target="RFC3954"/>; to maintain this compatibility, all revisions to
        such Information Elements are subject to additional review by the
        appointed NetFlow V9 expert.</t> -->

      </section>
      
      <section title="Deprecating Information Elements" anchor="sec-deprecation">

        <t>Changes that are not permissible by these criteria may only be
        handled by deprecation. An Information Element MAY be deprecated and
        replaced when:</t>

        <t><list style="numbers">

            <t>the Information Element definition has an error or shortcoming
            which cannot be permissibly changed as in <xref
            target="sec-revision"/>; or</t>

            <t>the deprecation harmonizes with an external reference which was
            itself deprecated through that reference's accepted deprecation
            method; or</t>

            <t>changes in the IPFIX Protocol or its extensions, or in
            community understanding thereof, allow the information represented
            by the Information Element to be represented in a more efficient
            or convenient way. Deprecation in this circumstance requires a
            Standards Action.</t>

        </list></t>

        <t>A request for deprecation is sent to IANA, which passes it to the
        IE-DOCTORS for review, as in <xref target="sec-process"/>. When
        deprecating an Information Element, the Information Element
        description in the IANA IE registry must be updated to explain the
        deprecation, as well as to refer to any new Information Elements
        created to replace the deprecated Information Element.</t>

        <t>The Revision number of an Information Element is incremented upon
        deprecation, and the revision Date updated, as with any revision.</t>

        <!-- <t>Information Elements with identifiers in the range 1-127 are
        compatible with the NetFlow V9 protocol as described in <xref
        target="RFC3954"/>; to maintain this compatibility, all deprecations
        of such Information Elements are subject to additional review by the
        appointed NetFlow V9 expert.</t> -->
        
        <t>Deprecated Information Elements should continue to be supported by
        Collecting Processes, but should not be exported by Exporting
        Processes. The use of deprecated Information Elements should result in
        a log entry or human-readable warning at the Exporting and Collecting
        Processes.</t>

<!--        <t>After a period of time determined in the eyes of the
        IE-DOCTORS experts to be reasonable in order to allow deployed
        Exporting Processes to be updated to account for the deprecation, a
        deprecated Information Element may be made obsolete. Obsolete
        Information Elements must not be supported by either Exporting or
        Collecting Processes. The receipt of obsolete Information Elements
        should be logged by the Collecting Process.</t> -->

        <t>Names and elementIDs of deprecated Information Elements
        must not be reused.</t>

      </section>
<!--
      <section title="Versioning the entire IANA IE registry">

        <t>Consider a typical Collector implementation, which regularly
        downloads the entire registry in order to be compliant with the latest
        of set of supported IEs. While a registry revision number might seems
        advantageous for the Collector at first glance (avoiding the one by
        one comparison of all IE revisions), it is not necessary, as the IPFIX
        IANA IE registry specifies the date at which the registry was last
        updated in the "Last Updated" field. For purposes of identifying the
        latest set of Information Element versions specified in registry, the
        last revision date of the Information Element registry (available in
        the registry XML source, or from the Last-Modified: header of <xref
        target="iana-ipfix-assignments"/>) should be used.</t>

       </section>
-->
    </section>

    <section title="When not to define new Information Elements" anchor="sec-noie">

        <t>Due to the relatively limited number space of Information Elements
        in the IANA IE registry, and the fact that the difficulty of managing
        and understanding the registry increases with its size, avoiding
        redundancy and clutter in the registry is important in defining new
        applications. New Information Elements should not be added to the IANA
        IE registry unless there is an intent to implement and deploy
        applications using them; research or experimental applications should
        use enterprise-specific Information Elements as in <xref
        target="ie-enterprise"/> instead. </t>

        <t>The subsections below provide guidelines for reuse of existing
        Information Elements, as well as guidelines on using
        enterprise-specific Information Elements instead of adding Information
        Elements in the IANA IE registry.</t>

        <section title="Maximizing reuse of existing Information Elements" anchor="sec-ie-reuse">

            <t>Whenever possible, new applications should prefer usage of
            existing IPFIX Information Elements to the creation of new
            Information Elements. IPFIX already provides Information Elements
            for every common Layer 4 and Layer 3 packet header field in the
            IETF protocol suite, basic Layer 2 information, basic counters,
            timestamps and time ranges, and so on. When defining a new
            Information Element similar to an existing one, reviewers should
            ensure that the existing one is not applicable.</t>

            <t>Note that this guideline to maximize reuse does not imply that
            an Information Element that represents the same information from a
            packet as a existing Information Element should not be added to
            the IANA IE registry. For example, consider the ipClassOfService
            (Element ID 5), ipDiffServCodePoint (Element ID 98), and
            ipPrecedence (Element ID 196) Information Elements. These all
            represent subsets of the same field in an IP version 4 packet
            header, but different uses of these bits. The representation in
            one or another of these Information Elements contains information
            in itself as to how the bits were interpreted by the Metering
            Process.</t>

            <t>On the other hand, simply changing the context in which an
            Information Element will be used is insufficient reason for the
            definition of a new Information Element. For example, an extension
            of IPFIX to log detailed information about HTTP transactions
            alongside network-level information should not define
            httpClientAddress and httpServerAddress Information Elements,
            preferring instead the use of sourceIPv[46]Address and
            destinationIPv[46]Address.</t>

            <t>Applications dealing with bidirectional interactions should use
            <xref target="RFC5103">Bidirectional Flow Support for IPFIX</xref>
            to represent these interactions.</t>

            <t>Existing timestamp and time range Information
            Elements should be reused for any situation requiring simple
            time stamping of an event: for single observations, the
            observationTime* Information Elements from PSAMP are provided, and
            for events with a duration, the flowStart* and flowEnd*
            Information Elements suffice. This arrangement allows minimal
            generic time handling by existing Collecting Processes and
            analysis workflows. New timestamp Information Elements should ONLY
            be defined for semantically distinct timing information (e.g., an
            IPFIX-exported record containing information about an event to be
            scheduled in the future).</t>

            <t>In all cases the use of absolute timestamp Information Elements
            (e.g. flowStartMilliseconds) is recommended, as these Information
            Elements allow for maximum flexibility in processing with minimal
            overhead. Timestamps based on the export time header in the
            enclosing IPFIX Message (e.g. flowStartTimeDeltaMicroseconds) MAY
            be used if high-precision timing is important, export bandwidth or
            storage space is limited, timestamps comprise a relatively large
            fraction of record size, and the application naturally groups
            records into IPFIX Messages. Timestamps based on information which
            must be exported in a separate Data Record defined by an Options
            Template (e.g. flowStartSysUpTime) MAY be used only in the context
            of an existing practice of using runtime-defined epochs for the
            given application. New applications should avoid these structures
            when possible.</t>

        </section>

        <section title="Applying enterprise-specific Information Elements" anchor="ie-enterprise">

            <t>IPFIX provides a mechanism for defining enterprise-specific
            Information Elements, as in Section 3.2 [RFC-EDITOR NOTE: verify
            section number] of <xref
            target="I-D.ietf-ipfix-protocol-rfc5101bis"/>. These are scoped to
            a vendor's or organization's Structure of Management Information
            (SMI) Private Enterprise Number, and are under complete control of
            the organization assigning them.</t>

            <t>For situations in which interoperability is unimportant, new
            information should be exported using enterprise-specific
            Information Elements instead of adding new Information Elements to
            the IANA IE registry. These situations include:</t>

            <t><list style="symbols">

                <t>export of implementation-specific information, or</t>

                <t>export of information supporting research or experiments
                within a single organization or closed community, or</t>

                <t>export of information derived in a commercially-sensitive
                or proprietary method, or</t>

                <t>export of information or meta-information specific to a
                commercially-sensitive or proprietary application.</t>

            </list></t>

            <t>While work within the IETF generally does not fall into these
            categories, enterprise-specific Information Elements are also
            useful for pre-standardization testing of a new IPFIX application.
            While performing initial development and interoperability testing
            of a new application, the Information Elements used by the
            application should not be submitted to IANA for inclusion in the
            IANA IE registry. Instead, these experimental Information Elements
            should be represented as enterprise-specific until their
            definitions are finalized.</t>

             <t>As this document contains best practices for defining new
            Information Elements, organizations using enterprise-specific
            Information Elements are advised to follow the guidelines set
            forth here even if not submitting Information Elements
            for inclusion in the IANA IE registry.</t>
            
             <!-- <t>then transitioned from enterprise-specific to
            IANA-defined upon finalization. To support this transition, the
            IANA IE registry provides an experimental IE reference as defined
            in <xref target="ie-promotion"/>.</t> -->

        </section>
        
    </section>

    <section title="Information Element Definition Checklist">

        <t>The following three checklists, condensed from the rest of this
        document, can be used when defining and reviewing Information
        Elements; they refer back to the section of this document from which
        they are taken. These checklists are intended for the definition of
        new Information Elements; revision should follow the process defined
        in <xref target="sec-revision"/>, and deprecation should follow the
        process defined in <xref target="sec-deprecation"/>.</t>

        <t>Though many of the considerations in this document require the
        subjective judgement of Information Element authors, reviewers, and
        IANA, certain parts of the process may be made simpler through tool
        support. Items on these checklists which could be easily automated or
        assisted by tools are annotated with "(tool support)". Other items on
        these checklists require some level of subjective judgement; checks
        for semantic uniqueness may additionally be supported by textual
        analysis of descriptions in the future.</t>

        <t>Checklist 1 contains conditions which must be met by all proposed
        Information Elements:</t>

        <t><list style="numbers">

           <t>The name must be unique within the IANA IE registry, and not
           reuse the name of any current or deprecated Information
           Element. (<xref target="sec-ie-names"/>) (tool support)</t>

           <t>The description must be sufficiently semantically unique within
           the IANA IE registry, representing a substantially different
           meaning from any current or deprecated Information
           Element. (<xref target="sec-iedef"/>)</t>

           <t>The name must start with a non-capitalized letter. (<xref
           target="sec-ie-names"/>) (tool support)</t>

           <t>Names composed of more than on word must use capital letters for
           the first letter of each component except for the first one; all
           other letters are non-capitalized, even for acronyms. Exceptions
           are made for acronyms containing non-capitalized letters, such as
           'IPv4' and 'IPv6'. (<xref target="sec-ie-names"/>) (tool
           support)</t>

           <t>The data type must match the type of the data being represented.
           (<xref target="sec-ie-types"/>)</t>

           <t>Data type semantics must be appropriate for the data type.
           (<xref target="sec-ie-semantics"/>) (tool support)</t>

           <t>The Information Element identifier assigned by IANA must be
           unique. (<xref target="sec-ie-numbering"/>) (tool support)</t>

           <t>The Information Element must be reviewed for the potential of
           information leakage or other misuse that could reduce the security
           of the measured system; security considerations specific to the
           Information Element must be discussed in the description or in a
           supporting RFC. (<xref target="security-section"/>)</t>

           <!-- <t>The Information Element identifier assigned by IANA must not be
           in the range 1-127 unless it is compatible with the counterpart
           Information Element used in NetFlow V9 <xref target="RFC3954"/>.
           (<xref target="sec-ie-numbering"/>)</t> -->

        </list></t>

        <t>Checklist 2 contains conditions which must be met by proposed
        Information Elements with certain properties, as noted:</t>

        <t><list style="numbers">

           <t>Time values must be defined with appropriate precision. (<xref
           target="sec-ie-types"/>)</t>

           <t>Strings and octet arrays with length restrictions must note
           those length restrictions in their descriptions. (<xref
           target="sec-ie-types"/>)</t>

           <t>Enumerations must refer to an IANA IE registry or subregistry,
           or a registry maintained by an external standards organization. If
           no suitable registry or subregistry exists, a new subregistry of
           the IPFIX Information Element registry must be created for the
           enumeration, to be modified subject to <xref
           target="RFC5226">Expert Review</xref>. (<xref
           target="sec-ie-subreg"/>)</t>

        </list></t>

        <t>Checklist 3 contains conditions which should be met by proposed
        Information Elements:</t>

        <t><list style="numbers">

           <t>The name of an Information Element pertaining to a specific
           protocol or application should contain the name of the protocol or
           application as the first word. (<xref target="sec-ie-names"/>)</t>

           <t>Information Elements representing integral values should use a
           data type for the appropriate width for the value. (<xref
           target="sec-ie-types"/>)</t>

           <t>Information Elements representing counters or identifiers should
           be represented as signed64 or unsigned64, unless they are naturally
           represented with narrower integral types, as appropriate. (<xref
           target="sec-ie-types"/>)</t>

           <t>An Information Element should not contain internal structure,
           subject to the exceptions in <xref target="sec-ie-structure"/>;
           candidate Information Elements with internal structure should be
           decomposed into multiple Information Elements. (<xref
           target="sec-ie-structure"/>)</t>

           <t>An Information Element should not contain multiplicity or
           ordinality information within the definition of the Information
           Element itself. (<xref target="sec-ie-multiplicity"/>)</t>

           <t>Data type semantics should be defined, if appropriate. (<xref
           target="sec-ie-semantics"/>) (tool support)</t>

           <t>Units should be defined, if appropriate, with new units added to
           the Information Element Units subregistry if necessary. (<xref
           target="sec-ie-semantics"/>) (tool support)</t>

           <t>Ranges should be defined, if appropriate. (<xref
           target="sec-ie-semantics"/>) (tool support)</t>
           
            <t>Non-reversible Information Elements (see <xref
           target="RFC5103"/>) should note non-reversibility in the
           description. (<xref target="ie-reversibility"/>)</t>

           <!-- <t>Information Elements created to replace enterprise-specific
           Information Elements used for experimental or testing purposes
           should contain a reference to the enterprise-specific Information
           Element they replace. (<xref target="ie-promotion"/>)</t> -->

           <!-- <t>The Information Element Identifier assigned by IANA for IEs not
           compatible with their counterparts in NetFlow V9 should be the
           lowest available identifier above 128. (<xref
           target="sec-ie-numbering"/>) (tool support)</t> -->

           <t>Information Elements to be registered with IANA should be
           intended for implementation and deployment on production
           networks.</t>

         </list></t>

    </section>

    <section title="Applying IPFIX to non-Flow Applications" anchor="sec-nonflow">

        <t>At the core of IPFIX is its definition of a Flow, a set of packets
        sharing some common properties crossing an Observation Point within a
        certain time window. However, the reliance on this definition does not
        preclude the application of IPFIX to domains which are not obviously
        handling flow data according to this definition. Most network
        management data collection tasks, those to which IPFIX is most
        applicable, have at their core the movement of packets from one place
        to another; by a liberal interpretation of the common properties
        defining the flow, then, almost any event handled by these can be held
        to concern data records conforming to the IPFIX definition of a
        Flow.</t>

        <t>Non-flow information defining associations or key-value pairs, on
        the other hand, are defined by IPFIX Options Templates. Here, the
        Information Elements within an Options Template Record are divided
        into Scope Information Elements which define the key, and non-scope
        Information Elements which define the values associated with that key.
        Unlike Flows, Data Records defined by Options Template are not
        necessarily scoped in time; these Data Records are generally held to
        be in effect until a new set of values for a specific set of keys is
        exported. While this mechanism is often used by IPFIX to export
        metadata about the collection infrastructure, it is applicable to any
        association information.</t>

        <t>An IPFIX application can mix Data Records described either type of
        template in an IPFIX Message or Message stream, and exploit
        relationships among the Flow Keys, values, and Scopes to create
        interrelated data structures. See <xref target="RFC5473"/> for an
        example application of this.</t>

    </section>

    <section title="Writing Internet-Drafts for IPFIX Applications" anchor="sec-draft">

        <t>When a new application is complex enough to require additional
        clarification or specification as to the use of the defined
        Information Elements, or has particularly this may be given in an
        Internet-Draft. Internet-Drafts for new IPFIX applications are best
        submitted to a Working Group with expertise in the area of the new
        application, or as independent submissions.</t>

        <t>When defining new Information Elements in an Internet-Draft, the
        Internet-Draft should contain a section (or subsection) for each
        Information Element, which contains the attributes in <xref
        target="sec-iedef"/> in human-readable form. An example subsection is
        given below. These Information Element descriptions should not assign
        Information Element numbers, instead using placeholder identifiers for
        these numbers (e.g. "TBD1", "TBD2", "TBD3") and a note to IANA in the
        IANA Considerations section to replace those placeholders in the
        document with Information Element numbers when the numbers are
        assigned. The use of these placeholder definitions allows references
        to the numbers in e.g. box-and-line diagrams or template definitions
        as in <xref target="sec-iespec"/>.</t>

        <section title="Example Information Element Definition">
            
            <t>This is an example of an Information Element definition which would appear in an Internet-Draft. The name appears in the section title.</t>
            
      	    <t><list style="hanging">
      	        <t hangText="Description: ">
                    Description goes here.; obligatory
                </t>
       	        
       	        <t hangText="Data Type: ">Data type goes here; obligatory</t>
     	        <t hangText="Data Type Semantics: ">Data type semantics, if any, go here; optional</t>
     	        <t hangText="Units: ">Units, if any, go here; optional</t>
     	        <t hangText="Range: ">Range, if not implied by the data type, goes here; optional</t>
     	        <t hangText="References: ">References to other RFCs or documents outside the IETF, in which additional information is given, or which are referenced by the description, go here; optional</t>
       	        <t hangText="ElementId: ">ElementId, if known, or TBD to be filled in by IANA at publication time.</t>
                <!-- <t hangText="Replaces Enterprise-Specific Element:">If the Information Element replaces an existing enterprise-specific Information Element, the PEN and Information Element number go here, separated by a slash (e.g. 35566/123) as in <xref target="sec-iespec"/>.</t> -->

            </list></t>
        </section>

        <section title="Defining Recommended Templates" anchor="sec-templates">

            <t>New IPFIX applications should not, in the general case, define
            fixed templates for export, as this throws away much of the
            flexibility afforded by IPFIX. However, fixed template export is
            permissible in the case that the export implementation must
            operate in a resource constrained environment, and/or that the
            application is replacing an existing fixed-format binary export
            format in a maximally compatible way. In any case, Collecting
            Processes for such applications should support the collection
            Templates with Information Elements in any order, or Templates
            with additional Information Elements.</t>

            <t>An Internet-Draft clarifying the use of new Information
            Elements should include any recommended Template or Options
            Template Records necessary for supporting the application, as well
            as examples of records exported using these Template Records. In
            defining these Template Records, such Internet-Drafts should
            mention, subject to rare exceptions:</t>

            <t><list style="numbers">

                <t>that the order of different Information Elements within a
                Template is not significant;</t>

                <t>that Templates on the wire for the application may also
                contain additional Information Elements beyond those specified
                in the recommended Template;</t>

                <t>that a stream of IPFIX Messages supporting the application
                may also contain Data Records not described by the recommended
                Templates; and</t>

                <t>that any reader of IPFIX Messages supporting the
                application must accept these conditions.</t>

            </list></t>

            <t>Definitions of recommended Template Records for flow-like
            information, where the Flow Key is well-defined, should indicate
            which of the Information Elements in the recommended Template are
            Flow Keys.</t>

             <t>Recommended Templates are defined, for example, in <xref
             target="RFC5476"/> for PSAMP packet reports (section 6.4) and
             extended packet reports (section 6.5). Recommended Options
             Templates are defined extensively throughout the IPFIX documents,
             including in <xref target="I-D.ietf-ipfix-protocol-rfc5101bis">the protocol document
             itself</xref> for exporting export statistics; in the <xref
             target="RFC5655">file format</xref> for exporting file metadata;
             and in Mediator intermediate process definitions such as <xref
             target="RFC6235"/> for intermediate process metadata.
             The discussion in these examples is a good model for recommended
             template definitions.</t>

        </section>
    
    </section>

    <section title="A Textual Format for Specifying Information Elements and
Templates" anchor="sec-iespec">

        <t>Example Templates given in existing IPFIX documents are generally
        expressed using bitmap diagrams of the respective Templates. These are
        illustrative of the wire representation of simple Templates, but not
        particularly readable for more complicated recommended Templates,
        provide no support for rapid implementation of new Templates, and do
        not adequately convey the optional nature of ordering and additional
        Information Elements. Therefore, we define a recommended
        textual format for specifying Information Elements and Templates in
        Internet-Drafts in this section.</t>

        <t>Here we define a simple textual syntax for describing IPFIX
        Information Elements and IPFIX Templates, with human readability,
        human writability, compactness, and ease of parser/generator
        implementation without requiring external XML support as design goals.
        It is intended both for use in human communication (e.g., in new
        Internet-Drafts containing higher-level descriptions of IPFIX
        Templates, or describing sets of new IPFIX Information Elements for
        supporting new applications of the protocol) as well as at runtime by
        IPFIX implementations.</t>

        <section title="Information Element Specifiers">

            <t>The basis of this format is the textual Information Element
            Specifier, or IESpec. An IESpec contains each of the four
            important aspects of an Information Element: its name, its number,
            its type, and its size, separated by simple markup based on
            various types of brackets. Fully-qualified IESpecs may be used to
            specify existing or new Information Elements within an Information
            Model, while either fully-qualified or partial IESpecs may be used
            to define fields in a Template.</t>

            <t>Bare words are used for Information Element names, and each
            aspect of information associated with an Information Element is
            associated with a type of brackets:</t>

            <t><list style="symbols">
                <t>() parentheses for Information Element numbers,</t>
                <t>&lt;&gt; angles for Information Element data types, and</t>
                <t>[] square brackets for Information Element sizes.</t>
                <t>{} curly braces contain an optional space-separated list of
                context identifiers to be associated with an Information
                Element, as described in more detail in <xref
                target="sec-iespec-templates"/></t>
            </list></t>

            <t>The symbol + is reserved for Information Element nesting within
            structured data elements; these are described in <xref
            target="sec-iespec-structured"/>.</t>

            <t>Whitespace in IESpecs is insignificant; spaces can be added
            after each element in order, e.g., to align columns for better
            readability.</t>

            <t>The basic form of a fully-qualified IESpec for an
            IANA-registered Information Element is as follows:</t>

            <t>name(number)&lt;type&gt;[size]</t>

            <t>where 'name' is the name of the Information Element in UTF-8,
            'number' is the Information Element as a decimal integer, 'type'
            is the name of the data type as in the IANA
            informationElementDataTypes registry, and 'size' is the length of
            the Information Element in octets as a decimal integer, where
            65535 or the string 'v' signifies a variable-length Information
            Element. [size] may be omitted; in this case, the data type's
            native or default size is assumed.</t>

            <t>The basic form of a fully-qualified IESpec for an
            enterprise-specific Information Element is as follows:</t>

            <t>name(pen/number)&lt;type&gt;[size]</t>

            <t>where 'pen' is the Private Enterprise Number as a decimal
            integer.</t>

            <t>A fully-qualified IESpec is intended to express enough
            information about an Information Element to decode and display
            Data Records defined by Templates containing that Information
            Element. Range, unit, semantic, and description information, as in
            <xref target="RFC5610"/>, is not supported by this syntax.</t>

            <t>Example fully-qualified IESpecs follow:</t>

            <t><list>
                <t>octetDeltaCount(1)&lt;unsigned64&gt;[8]</t>
                <t>octetDeltaCount(1)&lt;unsigned64&gt; (unsigned64 is natively 8 octets long)</t>
                <t>sourceIPv4Address(8)&lt;ipv4Address&gt;</t>
                <t>wlanSSID(146)&lt;string&gt;[v]</t>
                <t>sipRequestURI(35566/403)&lt;string&gt;[65535]</t>
            </list></t>

            <t>A partial IESpec is any IESpec that is not fully-qualified;
            these are useful when defining templates. A partial IESpec is
            assumed to take missing values from its canonical definition in
            the IANA IE registry. At minimum, a partial IESpec must contain a
            name, or a number. Any name, number, or type information given
            with a partial IESpec must match the values given in the
            Information Model; however, size information in a partial IESpec
            overrides size information in the Information Model; in this way,
            IESpecs can be used to express reduced-length encoding for
            Information Elements.</t>

            <t>Example partial IESpecs follow:</t>

            <t><list style="symbols">
                <t>octetDeltaCount</t>
                <t>octetDeltaCount[4] (reduced-length encoding)</t>
                <t>(1)</t>
                <t>(1)[4] (reduced length encoding; note that this is exactly equivalent to an Information Element specifier in a Template)</t>
            </list></t>

        </section>

        <section title="Specifying Templates" anchor="sec-iespec-templates">

            <t>A Template can then be defined simply as an ordered,
            newline-separated sequence of IESpecs. IESpecs in example
            Templates illustrating a new application of IPFIX should be
            fully-qualified. Flow Keys may be optionally annotated by
            appending the {key} context to the end of each Flow Key specifier.
            A template counting packets and octets per five-tuple with
            millisecond precision in IESpec syntax is shown below.</t>

<figure title="Fig. 1: Sample flow template in IESpec syntax">
<artwork><![CDATA[
flowStartMilliseconds(152)<dateTimeMilliseconds>[8]
flowEndMilliseconds(153)<dateTimeMilliseconds>[8]
octetDeltaCount(1)<unsigned64>[8]
packetDeltaCount(2)<unsigned64>[8]
sourceIPv4Address(8)<ipv4Address>[4]{key}
destinationIPv4Address(12)<ipv4Address>[4]{key}
sourceTransportPort(7)<unsigned16>[2]{key}
destinationTransportPort(11)<unsigned16>[2]{key}
protocolIdentifier(4)<unsigned8>[1]{key}
]]></artwork></figure>


            <t>An Options Template is specified similarly. Scope is specified
            appending the {scope} context to the end of each IESpec for a
            Scope IE. Due to the way Information Elements are represented in
            Options Templates, all {scope} IESpecs must appear before any
            non-scope IESpec. The Flow Key Options Template defined in section
            4.4 [RFC-EDITOR NOTE: verify section number] of <xref target="I-D.ietf-ipfix-protocol-rfc5101bis"/> in IESpec syntax is shown
            below:</t>

<figure title="Fig. 2: Flow Key Options Template in IESpec syntax">
<artwork><![CDATA[
templateId(145)<unsigned16>[2]{scope}
flowKeyIndicator(173)<unsigned64>[8]
]]></artwork></figure>

        </section>

        <section title="Specifying IPFIX Structured Data" anchor="sec-iespec-structured">

            <t>IESpecs can also be used to illustrate the structure of the
            information exported using the <xref
            target="RFC6313">IPFIX Structured Data
            extension</xref>. Here, the semantics of the structured data
            elements are specified using contexts, and the information
            elements within each structured data element follow the structured
            data element, prefixed with + to show they are contained therein.
            Arbitrary nesting of structured data elements is possible by using
            multiple + signs in the prefix. For example, a basic list of IP
            addresses with "one or more" semantics would be expressed using
            partially qualified IESpecs as follows:</t>

<figure title="Fig. 3: Sample basicList in IESpec syntax">
<artwork><![CDATA[
basicList{oneOrMoreOf}
+sourceIPv4Address(8)[4]
]]></artwork></figure>

            <t>And an example subTemplateList itself containing a basicList is
            shown below:</t>

<figure title="Fig. 4: Sample subTemplateList in IESpec syntax">
<artwork><![CDATA[
subTemplateList{allOf}
+basicList{oneOrMoreOf}
++sourceIPv4Address(8)[4]
+destinationIPv4Address(12)[4]
]]></artwork></figure>

            <t>This describes a subTemplateMultilist containing all of the
            expressed set of source-destination pairs, where the source
            address itself could be one of any number in a basicList (e.g., in
            the case of SCTP multihoming).</t>

            <t>The contexts associable with structured data Information
            Elements are the semantics, as defined in section 4.4 of <xref
            target="RFC6313"/>; a structured data
            Information Element without any context is taken to have undefined
            semantics. More information on the application of structured data
            is available in <xref
            target="RFC6313"/>.</t>

        </section>
       
    </section>

    <section title="Security Considerations" anchor="security-section">

        <t>The IE-DOCTORS must evaluate the security aspects of new
        Information Elements in light of the information they could provide to
        support potential attacks against the measured network or entities
        about which information is exported. Specific security aspects to
        evaluate include whether the exported information contains personally
        identifiable information, or information which should be kept
        confidential about the described entities (e.g. partial payload, or
        configuration information which could be exploited). This is not to
        say that such Information Elements should not be defined, but there
        must be an evaluation of the security risk versus the utility of the
        exported information for the intended application. For example, "A
        Framework for Packet Selection and Reporting" <xref target="RFC5474"/>
        concluded in section 12.3.2 that the hash functions private parameters
        should not exported within IPFIX.</t>

        <t>Security considerations specific to an Information Element must be
        addressed in the Security Considerations section of the Internet-Draft
        describing the Information Element, or in the Information Element
        description itself in case the Information Element is not defined in
        an Internet-Draft. Information Elements with specific security
        considerations should be described in an Internet-Draft.</t>
        
         <t>For example, the ipHeaderPacketSection in the IPFIX IE registry
        mentions: "This Information Element, which may have a variable length,
        carries a series of octets from the start of the IP header of a
        sampled packet. With sufficient length, this element also reports
        octets from the IP payload, subject to <xref target="RFC2804"/>. See
        the Security Considerations section." Another example can be seen in
        the "Packet Sampling (PSAMP) Protocols Specification" <xref
        target="RFC5476"/> specifies: "In the basic Packet Report, a PSAMP
        Device exports some number of contiguous bytes from the start of the
        packet, including the packet header (which includes link layer,
        network layer and other encapsulation headers) and some subsequent
        bytes of the packet payload. The PSAMP Device should not export the
        full payload of conversations, as this would mean wiretapping <xref
        target="RFC2804"/>. The PSAMP Device MUST respect local privacy laws."
        </t>

    </section>

    <section title="IANA Considerations" anchor="iana-section">

      <!-- <t>With respect to the management of the IANA IPFIX Information Elements
      Registry and associated subregistries located at <xref
      target="iana-ipfix-assignments"/>, this document defines a process for
      IANA in <xref target="sec-process"/>.</t>

      <t>The actions for IANA in this process are as follows:</t>
        
      <t><list style="symbols">

        <t>When IANA receives a request to add, revise, or deprecate an
        Information Element in the IPFIX Information Elements Registry,
        it forwards the request to the IE-DOCTORS experts for review.</t>

        <t>When IANA receives an approval for a request to add an Information
        Element definition from the IE-DOCTORS experts, it adds that
        Information Element to the registry. The approved request may include
        changes from the original request.</t>

        <t>When IANA receives an approval for a request to revise an
        Information Element definition from the IE-DOCTORS experts, it changes
        that Information Element's definition in the registry, and updates the
        Revision and Date columns as appropriate. The approved request may
        include changes from the original request. If the original Information
        Element was added to the registry with IETF consensus (i.e., was
        defined by an RFC), the revision will require IETF consensus as
        well.</t>

        <t>When IANA receives an approval for a request to deprecate an
        Information Element definition from the IE-DOCTORS experts, it changes
        that Information Element's definition in the registry, and updates the
        Revision and Date columns as appropriate. The approved request may
        include changes from the original request. If the original Information
        Element was added to the registry with IETF consensus (i.e., was
        defined by an RFC), the deprecation will require IETF consensus as
        well.</t>

      </list></t>

      <t>The IE-DOCTORS experts mentioned within this document are to be
      appointed by the IESG.</t> -->

      <!-- <t>In addition, in order to support more effective management of the
       Information Element lifecycle as defined in <xref
       target="sec-lifecycle"/>, this document specifies the addition of two
       new columns for the registry:</t>
        -->
        <!-- <t><list style="hanging">

         <t hangText="Revision: ">a serial revision number for each
         Information Element, beginning at 0 for all newly defined Information
         Elements. This column is to be managed by IANA in order to support
         the process defined in <xref target="sec-revision"/>, and need not be
         present in any Information Element definition. [IANA NOTE: on
         publication of this document, please set the Revision of all existing
         Information Elements to 0.]</t>

        <t hangText="Date: ">the date at which the Information Element was
        created or last modified. This column is to be managed by IANA in
        order to support the process defined in <xref target="sec-revision"/>,
        and need not be present in any Information Element definition. [IANA
        NOTE: on publication of this document, please set the Date of all
        existing Information Elements to the publication date of this
        document.]</t>

       <t hangText="Enterprise-specific reference: ">for Information Elements
         which where deployed as enterprise-specific Information Elements for
         experimentation and testing, and subsequently registered in the IANA
         registry, specifies the private enterprise number (PEN)/IE number
         pair(s) of the equivalent experimental Information Element(s). Note
         that this column may contain more than one entry per Information
         Element. This column should be present in any Information Element
         definition referencing an enterprise-specific Information Element, as
         in <xref target="ie-promotion"/>.</t>
 
      </list></t> -->

      <!-- <t>Any additions to the registry which themselves require subregistries
      of enumerated values must define those subregistries to be subject to
      Expert Review <xref target="RFC5226"/>.</t>

      <t>[IANA NOTE: please update the Reference for the IPFIX Information
      Element Registry to refer to this document, as well as to <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-ipfix-information-model-rfc5102bis"/>.]</t>
 -->
 
     <t>This document has no considerations for IANA.</t>

      <t>[IANA NOTE: IANA considerations for the process outlined in this
      document are given in <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-ipfix-information-model-rfc5102bis"/>]</t>

      <t>[IANA NOTE: Note that the examples in <xref target="sec-examples"/>
      are NOT to be added to the IPFIX Information Element registry upon the
      publication of this document.]</t>

    </section>

    <section title="Acknowledgements">

      <t>Thanks to Paul Aitken, Andrew Feren, Dan Romascanu, and David
      Harrington for their reviews and feedback. Thanks as well to Roni Even
      and Yoav Nir for their area reviews; and to Pete Resnick, Adrian Farrel,
      Stephen Farrell, Stewart Bryant, and Barry Leiba for their contributions
      during IESG discussions. This work is materially supported by the
      European Union Seventh Framework Programme under grant agreement 257315
      (DEMONS).</t>

    </section>

  </middle>

  <back>

    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.I-D.ietf-ipfix-protocol-rfc5101bis" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.I-D.ietf-ipfix-information-model-rfc5102bis" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5103" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5610" ?>
      <!-- <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119" ?> -->
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5226" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6313" ?>
    </references> 

    <references title="Informative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2804" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3261" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3954" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5102" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5472" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5473" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5474" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5476" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5477" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5560" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5655" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6235" ?>
    <reference anchor='iana-ipfix-assignments'>
      <front>
        <title>IP Flow Information Export Information Elements (http://www.iana.org/assignments/ipfix/ipfix.xml)</title>
        <author surname="Internet Assigned Numbers Authority"/>
        <date/>
      </front>
    </reference>
    </references> 

    <section title="Example Information Element Definitions" anchor="sec-examples">

      <t>This section contains a few example Information Element definitions
      as they would appear in an Internet-Draft. Note the conformance of these
      examples to the guidelines in <xref target="sec-iedef"/>.</t>

       <t>The sipResponseStatus Information Element (<xref
      target="ex-ie-sip"/>) illustrates the addition of an Information
      Element representing Layer 7 application information, with a reference
      to the registry containing the allowable values. The
      duplicatePacketDeltaCount Information Element (<xref
      target="ex-ie-ippm"/>) illustrates the addition
      of a new metric, with a reference to the RFC defining the metric. The
      ambientTemperature Information Element (<xref
      target="ex-ie-temp"/>) illustrates the addition of a new
      measured value outside the area of traditional networking
      applications.</t>

        <section title="sipResponseStatus" anchor="ex-ie-sip">
      	    <t><list style="hanging">

                <t hangText="Description: ">The SIP Response code as an
                integer, as in the Response Codes registry at
                http://www.iana.org/assignments/sip-parameters defined in
                <xref target="RFC3261"/> and amended in subsequent RFCs. The
                presence of this Information Element in a SIP Message record
                marks it as describing a SIP response; if absent, the record
                describes a SIP request.</t>
       	        <t hangText="Data Type: ">unsigned16</t>
       	        <t hangText="Data Type Semantics: ">identifier</t>
       	        <t hangText="References: "><xref target="RFC3261"/></t>
       	        <t hangText="ElementId: ">TBD</t>
       	        <t hangText="Replaces Enterprise-Specific Element:">35566 / 412</t>
            </list></t>
        </section>

        <section title="duplicatePacketDeltaCount" anchor="ex-ie-ippm">
      	    <t><list style="hanging">

      	        <t hangText="Description: ">The number of uncorrupted and
                identical additional copies of each individual packet in the
                Flow arriving at the destination since the previous Data
                Record for this Flow (if any), as measured at the Observation
                Point. This is measured as the
                Type-P-one-way-packet-duplication metric defined in section 3
                of <xref target="RFC5560"/>.</t>

       	      <t hangText="Data Type: ">unsigned64</t>
     	        <t hangText="Data Type Semantics: ">deltaCounter</t>
     	        <t hangText="Units: ">packets</t>
     	        <t hangText="References: "><xref target="RFC5560"/></t>
       	        <t hangText="ElementId: ">TBD</t>

            </list></t>
        </section>


        <section title="ambientTemperature" anchor="ex-ie-temp">
      	    <t><list style="hanging">

                <t hangText="Description: ">An ambient temperature observed by
                measurement equipment at an Observation Point, positioned such
                that it measures the temperature of the surroundings (i.e.,
                not including any heat generated by the measuring or measured
                equipment), expressed in degrees Celsius.</t>

       	        <t hangText="Data Type: ">float</t>
       	        <t hangText="Units: ">degrees Celsius</t>
       	        <t hangText="Range: ">-273.15 - +inf</t>
       	        <t hangText="ElementId: ">TBD</t>
            </list></t>
        </section>

    </section>

  </back>
</rfc>
