<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="no" ?> 
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<rfc ipr='trust200902' docName='draft-francois-sr-frr-00' category="std">
<front> 

<title abbrev="SR FRR">Segment Routing Fast Reroute</title>

<author surname="Pierre Francois"  fullname="Pierre Francois">
<organization>IMDEA Networks</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<city>Leganes</city> 
<country>ES</country>
</postal>
<email>pierre.francois@imdea.org</email>
</address>
</author>
<author surname="Clarence Filsfils" fullname="Clarence Filsfils">
<organization>Cisco Systems, Inc.</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<city>Brussels</city> 
<country>BE</country>
</postal>
<email>cfilsfil@cisco.com</email>
</address>

</author>
<author surname="Ahmed Bashandy" fullname="Ahmed Bashandy">
<organization>Cisco Systems, Inc.</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<city>San Jose</city> 
<country>US</country>
</postal>
<email>bashandy@cisco.com</email>
</address>
</author>
<author surname="Stefano Previdi" fullname="Stefano Previdi">
<organization>Cisco Systems, Inc.</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<city>Rome</city> 
<country>IT</country>
</postal>
<email>sprevidi@cisco.com</email>
</address>
</author>


<author surname="Bruno Decraene" fullname="Bruno Decraene">
<organization>Orange</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<city>Issy-les-Moulineaux </city>
<country>FR</country>
</postal>
<email>bruno.decraene@orange.com</email>
</address>
</author>
<date month="July" year="2013" />
<area>General</area>
<keyword>I-D</keyword>
<keyword>Internet-Draft</keyword>

<abstract>
	
	<!-- I just modified slightly this paragraph, we can 
		complete it later -->
	<t>
This document presents a Fast Reroute approach aimed at providing link protection of
nodal and adjacency segments to the Segment Routing framework. This FRR behavior
builds on proven IP-FRR concepts being LFAs, remote LFAs (RLFA), and remote LFAs with
directed forwarding (DLFA). We describe their implementation using SR segments. We
then analyze the benefits brought by Segment Routing to the scalability of
such IP-FRR approaches. 
    </t>

</abstract>

</front>

<middle>
<section title="Introduction">

<t> Segment Routing aims at supporting services with tight SLA guarantees
<xref target="I-D.filsfils-rtgwg-segment-routing"/>. Acknowledging this fact, this document provides local repair
mechanisms capable of restoring end-to-end connectivity in case of a sudden
failure of a link.  The FRR behavior builds on proven IP-FRR concepts; we leverage 
LFAs, remote LFAs (RLFA), and remote LFAs with directed forwarding (DLFA)<xref target="RFC5714"/>.</t>



<t>In the SR context, not all flows are being routed along the shortest paths
defined by the IGP, but also along explicit paths containing Adjacency
Segments. We thus accommodate the IP-FRR behavior for SR Adjacency Segments.
</t>


<t>Through the document, we will observe that performing FRR with SR has the
following benefits: </t>

<t>
<list style="empty"> 
 <t>- The simplicity properties of LFA FRR <xref target="RFC6571"/> are preserved.</t> 

 <t>- The capacity planning properties are preserved <xref target="RFC6571"/>. Unlike SDH and
 other FRR solutions, the repaired packet does not go back to the next-hop or
 next-next-hop but uses shortest-path forwarding from a much closer release
 point.</t>

 <t>- The RLFA operation is simplified: dynamically established directed LDP
 sessions to the repair nodes are no longer required.</t>

 <t>- The scalable support for DLFA provides guaranteed coverage for symmetric
 networks, i.e. networks configured with symmetric link metrics: the repair
 tunnel in a symmetric network can be encoded efficiently with only two
 segments. We will observe that only one segment is needed in most cases. </t>
 </list></t>

<t>A future version of this document will analyze the protection upon node
failure. </t>

       <t><figure anchor="fig_intro_example" title="Link Protection" align="center"><artwork><![CDATA[



        L         ____
   S----------F--{____}--D
  _|_       ___________ /  
 {___}--R--{___________}                                                 
]]>
                                                                                                                   
                                                                                                                   </artwork></figure></t>




<t>We use <xref target="fig_intro_example"/> to illustrate the three objectives that have to be met when
implementing SR FRR.</t> 

<t>First, the protecting router S needs to find a detour path around the protected 
link. Intuitively, the Point of Local Repair (PLR) needs to find a node R (a
repair node) that is capable of safely forwarding the traffic affected by the
failure of the protected link L. We leverage the algorithms defined in the
IP-FRR framework to achieve this first goal, as explained in <xref
target="sec:protection_lists"/>.</t> 

<t>Second, S must ensure proper forwarding behavior once the packet reaches the
repair node R. We define the segment operations to be applied by the protecting
node to ensure consistency with the forwarding state of the repair node in
<xref target="sec:protecting_segments"/>.</t> 

<t>We will observe, in <xref target="sec:benefits"/>, that
the MPLS instantiation of SR improves the scalability and operation of the FRR
solution by not requiring multi-hop LDP sessions to distant repair nodes.</t>

</section>

<section title="Protection lists" anchor="sec:protection_lists">

<t>The protection list is the list of segments encoding a detour path from the
protecting node S to the repair node R, avoiding the protected link L. In this
section, we define how to encode the LFA, RLFA, and DLFA repair paths with
protection lists. These protection lists contain at most two segments.</t>

<section title="LFA based protection list">

<t>According to the LFA FRR approach, if a path to a destination D from a
neighbor N of S does not contain S (i.e. N is a loop-free alternate of S for
the failure of link S-F), then S can pre-install a repair forwarding
information, in order to deviate the packet to N upon the failure of S-F.  </t>

<t>In the case of LFA applicability, the SR protection list is thus empty. All
what a protecting router S needs to do is to send the protected packet as is to
its LFA neighbor N.  </t>

</section>

<section title="RLFA based protection list">


<t>If there is no such LFA neighbor, then S may be able to create a virtual LFA
by using a tunnel to carry the packet to a point in the network that is not a
direct neighbor of S, and from which the packet will be delivered to the
destination without looping back to S. The Remote LFA proposal
<xref target="I-D.ietf-rtgwg-remote-lfa"/> calls such a tunnel a repair tunnel.  The tail-end
of this tunnel (R in figure 1) is called a "remote LFA" or a "PQ node".  We
refer to the RLFA document for the definitions of the P and Q sets.  </t>

<t>In the case of RLFA applicability for the protection of a segment, the
protection list is made of a nodal segment to the PQ node. It thus matches
[nodal(PQ), …]  </t>



</section>

<section title="DLFA based protection list">

<t> There are some cases where there is no remote LFA coverage for some
links/destinations, due to topological properties in the neighborhood of the
protecting node. If there is no such RLFA PQ node, we propose to use a Directed LFA (DLFA)
repair tunnel to a Q node that is adjacent to the P space
<xref target="I-D.bryant-ipfrr-tunnels"/>.</t>


<t>In the case of applicability of RLFA with directed forwarding (DLFA), the
protection list is made of a nodal segment to the P node followed by an
Adjacency segment to the Q node. It thus matches [nodal(P), Adj(P→Q), …]  </t>

<t>In networks with symmetric IGP metrics (the metric of a link AB is the same
as the metric of the reverse link BA), we can prove that either the P and the Q
sets intersect or there is at least one P node that is adjacent to a Q node.
Thanks to the DLFA extension, we thus have a guaranteed LFA-based FRR technique
for any network with symmetric IGP metrics.   </t> 
    
<t>Future versions of the document will describe the solutions leveraging SR
capabilities to provide guaranteed FRR applicability in any IGP topology.</t>

</section>
</section>


<section title="Protecting segments" anchor="sec:protecting_segments" >


<t>In this section, we explain how a protecting router S processes the active
segment of a packet upon the failure of the primary adjacency along which the
packet should be forwarded. The behavior depends on the type of active segment
to be protected.  </t>

<section title="The active segment is a node segment">
  
<t> The definition of the protection of a nodal segment is a direct translation
of IP-FRR behaviors into the SR terminology. That is, traffic for nodal segment
D will be rerouted to a safe node R whose shortest paths for D do not contain
the failed component.</t>

<t> As nodal segments semantics are known by all nodes of the domain, no
specific signaling needs to be done to let R correctly process the detoured
packet. A packet whose active segment matches [nodal(D),…], arriving at a
protecting node S will leave S with a segment list matching [PS(R),
nodal(D),…]. The actual value used to encode nodal(D) is set by S
based on the SRSB obtained from the IGP <xref target="I-D.filsfils-rtgwg-segment-routing"/>. </t>

<t> PS(R) is the computed Protection list to reach R, as discussed in section
2, and depends on the available type of protection: per-prefix LFA, Remote LFA
or Directed LFA. The packet will follow the detour path defined by PS(R), and
will finally reach R. When reaching R, the active segment of the packet is
nodal(D), and the packet resumes its course along the original segment list.</t>

</section>


<section title="The active segment is an adjacency segment">

<t>The operator may forbid protection of an adjacency segment by policy (?-Flag
in [ISIS]/[OSPF]). For example, this is useful when the operator prefers an
end-to-end protection mechanism triggered by the source of a multi-hop
transport conduit. </t>


<t>We define hereafter the FRR behavior applied by S for any packet received
with an active segment L for which protection was enabled.  We distinguish the
case where this active segment is followed by another adjacency segment from
the case where it is followed by a nodal segment.</t>

<section title="Protecting [Adjacency, Adjacency] segment lists">


<t>If the next segment in the list is an Adjacency Segment, then the packet has
to be conveyed to F.</t>

<t>To do so, S applies a “NEXT” operation on Adj(L) and then two consecutive
“PUSH” operations: first it pushes a nodal Segment for F, and then it pushes a
protection list allowing to reach F while bypassing L.  </t>

<t>Upon failure of L, a packet reaching S with a segment list matching
[adj(L),adj(M),…] will thus leave S with a segment list matching
[PS(F),nodal(F),adj(M)]. </t>

<t>The protection list PS(F) will define the course of the packet from S to F,
and F will resume the the course of the original segment list, receiving it
with an active segment list matching [nodal(F), adj(M),…]. </t>

</section>


<section title="Protecting [Adjacency, Nodal] segment lists">


<t>If the next segment in the stack is a nodal segment, say for node T, the
packet segment list matches [adj(L),nodal(T),…].  </t>

<t>A first solution would consist in steering the packet back to F while
avoiding L, similarly to the previous case. To do so, S applies a “NEXT”
operation on Adj(L) and then two consecutive “PUSH” operations: first it pushes
a nodal Segment for F, and then it pushes a protection list allowing to reach F
while bypassing L.  </t>

<t>Upon failure of L, a packet reaching S with a segment list matching
[adj(L),nodal(T),…] will thus leave S with a segment list matching
[PS(F),nodal(F),nodal(T)]. </t>


<t>Another solution is to not steer the packet back via F. In this case, S just
needs to apply a “NEXT” operation on the Adjacency segment related to L, and
push a protection segment list redirecting the traffic to a node R, capable of
whose path to nodal segment T is not affected by the failure.</t>

<t>Upon failure of L, packets reaching S with a segment list matching [adj(L),
nodal(T), …], would leave S with a segment list matching [PS(R),nodal(T), …].
</t>

</section>
</section>
</section>



<section title="SR FRR benefits in LDP environments" anchor="sec:benefits">


<t>In this section, we describe the operational and scaling benefits of SR when
used to implement RLFA and DLFA protection for LDP-based transport. We will
also observe that a partial SR deployment, limited to the network region where
the SR benefits are most desired, already provides the mentioned scaling
benefits. </t>

       <t><figure anchor="fig_benefits" title="Leveraging SR benefits for LDP-based traffic" align="center"><artwork><![CDATA[
        X
        |
 Y--A---B---E--Z
    |   |    \
    D---C--F--G 
            30                          
]]>
                                                                                                                   
                                                                                                                   </artwork></figure></t>




<t>In Figure 2, let us assume:
<list>

<t>- All link costs are 10 except FG which is 30.</t>
<t>- All routers are LDP capable.</t>
<t>- X, Y and Z are PEs participating to an important service S.</t>
<t>- The operator requires 50msec link-based FRR for service S. </t>
<t>- A, B, C, D, E, F and G are SR capable. </t>
<t>- X, Y, Z are not SR capable. As part of a staged migration from LDP to SR, the operator deploys SR first in a sub-part of the network and then everywhere. </t>
</list>
</t>


<t>The operator would like to resolve the following issues:<list>

<t>- to protect the link BA along the shortest-path of the important flow XY, B
requires an RLFA repair tunnel to D and hence a directed LDP session from B to
D. The operator does not like these dynamically established multi-hop LDP
sessions and would seek to eliminate them.</t>

<t>- there is no LFA/RLFA solution to protect the link BE along the shortest
path of the important flow XZ. The operator wants a guaranteed link-based FRR
solution.  </t>

</list></t>

<t>The operator can meet these objectives by deploying SR only on A, B, C, D,
E and F:<list>

<t>- The operator configures A, B, C, D, E, F and G with SRGB [100, 200] and
respective node segments 101, 102, 103, 104, 105, 106 and 107.</t>


<t>- The operator configures D as an SR Mapping Server with the following
policy mapping: (X, 201), (Y, 202), (Z, 203}.  </t>


<t>- Each SR node automatically advertises local adjacency segment for its IGP
adjacencies. Specifically, F advertises adjacency segment 9001 for its
adjacency FG.  </t>

</list></t>

<t>A, B, C, D, E, F and G keep their LDP capability and hence the flows XY and
XZ are transported over end-to-end LDP LSP’s.</t>

<t>For example, LDP at B installs the following MPLS dataplane entries:<list>

<t>- Incoming label: local LDB label bound by B for FEC Y <list>
<t>o Outgoing label: LDP label bound by A for FEC Y</t>
<t>o Outgoing nhop: A</t>
</list>
</t>

<t>- Incoming label: local LDB label bound by B for FEC Z<list>
<t>o Outgoing label: LDP label bound by E for FEC Z</t>
<t>o Outgoing nhop: E</t>
</list></t>
</list></t>


<t>The novelty comes from how the backup chains are computed for these
LDP-based entries. While LDP labels are used for the primary nhop and outgoing
labels, SR information is used for the FRR construction. In steady state, the
traffic is transported over LDP LSP. In transient FRR state, the traffic is
backed up thanks to the SR capabilities.</t>


<t>This helps meet the requirements of the operator:<list>

<t>- Eliminate directed LDP session</t>

<t>- Guaranteed FRR coverage</t>

<t>- Keep the traffic over LDP LSP in steady state</t>

<t>- Partial SR deployment only where needed</t>

</list></t>


<section title="Eliminating Directed LDP Sessions">
<t>B’s MPLS entry to Y becomes:<list>
<t>- Incoming label: local LDB label bound by B for FEC Y<list>
<t>o Outgoing label: LDP label bound by A for FEC Y</t>
<t>  - Backup outgoing label: SR node segment for Y {202}</t>
<t>o Outgoing nhop: A</t>
<t>  - Backup nhop: repair tunnel: node segment to D {104} with outgoing nhop: C</t>
</list></t>
</list></t>

<t>In steady-state, X sends its Y-destined traffic to B with a top label which
is the LDP label bound by B for FEC Y. B swaps that top label for the LDP label
bound by A for FEC Y and forwards to A. A pops the LDP label and forwards to
Y.</t>

<t>Upon failure of the link BA, B swaps the incoming top-label with the node
segment for Y (202) and sends the packet onto a repair tunnel to D (node
segment 104). Thus, B sends the packet to C with the label stack {104, 202}. C
pops the node segment 104 and forwards to D. D swaps 202 for 202 and forwards
to A. A’s nhop to Y is not SR capable and hence A swaps the incoming node
segment 202 to the LDP label announced by its next-hop (in this case, implicit
null).</t>

<t>After IGP convergence, B’s MPLS entry to Y will become:<list>
<t>Incoming label: local LDB label bound by B for FEC Y<list>
<t>Outgoing label: LDP label bound by C for FEC Y </t>
<t>Outgoing nhop: C</t>
</list></t>
</list></t>

<t>And the traffic XY travels again over the LDP LSP.</t>

<t>The operator has eliminated its first problem: dynamically established
directed LDP sessions are no longer required and the steady-state traffic is
still transported over LDP. The SR deployment is confined to the area where
these benefits were required. </t>

</section>

<section title="Guaranteed FRR coverage">

<t>B’s MPLS entry to Z becomes:<list>
<t>- Incoming label: local LDB label bound by B for FEC Z<list>
<t>- Outgoing label: LDP label bound by E for FEC Z</t>
<t>   o Backup outgoing label: SR node segment for Z {203}</t>
<t>- Outgoing nhop: E</t>
<t>   o Backup nhop: repair tunnel to G: {106, 9001}<list>

<t>     - G is reachable from B via the combination of a node segment to F {106} and
an adjacency segment FG {9001}</t>

<t>     - Note that {106, 107} would have equally work. Indeed, in many case, P’s
shortest path to Q is over the link PQ. The adjacency segment from P to Q is
required only in very rare topologies where the shortest-path from P to Q is
not via the link PQ.</t></list></t>
</list>
</t>
</list></t>

<t>In steady-state, X sends its Z-destined traffic to B with a top label which
is the LDP label bound by B for FEC Z. B swaps that top label for the LDP label
bound by E for FEC Z and forwards to E. E pops the LDP label and forwards to
Z.</t>

<t>Upon failure of the link BE, B swaps the incoming top-label with the node
segment for Z (203) and sends the packet onto a repair tunnel to G (node
segment 106 followed by adjacency segment 9001). Thus, B sends the packet to C
with the label stack {106, 9001, 203}. C pops the node segment 106 and forwards
to F. F pops the adjacency segment 9001 and forwards to G. G  swaps 203 for 203
and forwards to E. E’s nhop to Z is not SR capable and hence E swaps the
incoming node segment 203 for the LDP label announced by its next-hop (in this
case, implicit null).</t>

<t>After IGP convergence, B’s MPLS entry to Z will become:<list>
<t>- Incoming label: local LDB label bound by B for FEC Z<list>
<t>o Outgoing label: LDP label bound by C for FEC Z</t>
<t>o Outgoing nhop: C</t>
</list></t></list></t>

<t>And the traffic XZ travels again over the LDP LSP.</t>

<t>The operator has eliminated its second problem: guaranteed FRR coverage is
provided. The steady-state traffic is still transported over LDP. The SR
deployment is confined to the area where these benefits are required. </t>

</section>
</section>


</middle>
<back>
 <references>

<?rfc include="reference.I-D.draft-filsfils-rtgwg-segment-routing-00.xml"?>

<?rfc include="reference.RFC.5714.xml"?>

<?rfc include="reference.RFC.6571.xml"?>


<?rfc include="reference.I-D.draft-ietf-rtgwg-remote-lfa-02.xml"?>

<?rfc include="reference.I-D.bryant-ipfrr-tunnels.xml"?>


	 
 </references>

</back>
</rfc>
