<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!-- This template is for creating an Internet Draft using xml2rfc,
     which is available here: http://xml.resource.org. -->
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!-- One method to get references from the online citation libraries.
     There has to be one entity for each item to be referenced. 
     An alternate method (rfc include) is described in the references. -->

<!ENTITY RFC2119 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC2629 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2629.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3552 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3552.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.narten-iana-considerations-rfc2434bis SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.narten-iana-considerations-rfc2434bis.xml">
]>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<!-- used by XSLT processors -->
<!-- For a complete list and description of processing instructions (PIs), 
     please see http://xml.resource.org/authoring/README.html. -->
<!-- Below are generally applicable Processing Instructions (PIs) that most I-Ds might want to use.
     (Here they are set differently than their defaults in xml2rfc v1.32) -->
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<!-- give errors regarding ID-nits and DTD validation -->
<!-- control the table of contents (ToC) -->
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<!-- generate a ToC -->
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<!-- the number of levels of subsections in ToC. default: 3 -->
<!-- control references -->
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<!-- use symbolic references tags, i.e, [RFC2119] instead of [1] -->
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<!-- sort the reference entries alphabetically -->
<!-- control vertical white space 
     (using these PIs as follows is recommended by the RFC Editor) -->
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<!-- do not start each main section on a new page -->
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<!-- keep one blank line between list items -->
<!-- end of list of popular I-D processing instructions -->
<!--JS modifies the tittle-->
<rfc category="info" docName="draft-suznjevic-tsvwg-mtd-tcmtf-00" ipr="trust200811">

  <!-- category values: std, bcp, info, exp, and historic
     ipr values: full3667, noModification3667, noDerivatives3667
     you can add the attributes updates="NNNN" and obsoletes="NNNN" 
     they will automatically be output with "(if approved)" -->

  <!-- ***** FRONT MATTER ***** -->

  <front>
    <!-- The abbreviated title is used in the page header - it is only necessary if the 
         full title is longer than 39 characters -->

    <title abbrev="MTD-TCMTF">Maximum Tolerable Delays when using Tunneling Compressed Multiplexed Traffic Flows</title>

    <!-- add 'role="editor"' below for the editors if appropriate -->

    <!-- Another author who claims to be an editor -->

	
	<author fullname="Mirko Suznjevic" initials="M." surname="Suznjevic">
      <organization>University of Zagreb</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Faculty of Electrical Engineering and Computing, Unska 3</street>
          <!-- Reorder these if your country does things differently -->
          <city>Zagreb</city>
          <region></region>
          <code>10000</code>
          <country>Croatia</country>
        </postal>
        <phone>+385 1 6129 755</phone>
        <email>mirko.suznjevic@fer.hr</email>
        <!-- uri and facsimile elements may also be added -->
      </address>
    </author>  
	
    <author fullname="Jose Saldana" initials="J." surname="Saldana">
      <organization>University of Zaragoza</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Dpt. IEC Ada Byron Building</street>
          <!-- Reorder these if your country does things differently -->
          <city>Zaragoza</city>
          <region></region>
          <code>50018</code>
          <country>Spain</country>
        </postal>
        <phone>+34 976 762 698</phone>
        <email>jsaldana@unizar.es</email>
        <!-- uri and facsimile elements may also be added -->
      </address>
    </author>
       
    


    <date month="December" year="2012" />

    <!-- If the month and year are both specified and are the current ones, xml2rfc will fill 
         in the current day for you. If only the current year is specified, xml2rfc will fill 
	 in the current day and month for you. If the year is not the current one, it is 
	 necessary to specify at least a month (xml2rfc assumes day="1" if not specified for the 
	 purpose of calculating the expiry date).  With drafts it is normally sufficient to 
	 specify just the year. -->

    <!-- Meta-data Declarations -->

    <area>Transport</area>

    <workgroup>Transport Area Working Group</workgroup>

    <!-- WG name at the upperleft corner of the doc,
         IETF is fine for individual submissions.  
	 If this element is not present, the default is "Network Working Group",
         which is used by the RFC Editor as a nod to the history of the IETF. -->

    <keyword>template</keyword>

    <!-- Keywords will be incorporated into HTML output
         files in a meta tag but they have no effect on text or nroff
         output. If you submit your draft to the RFC Editor, the
         keywords will be used for the search engine. -->

    <abstract>
    
      <t>This document contains recommendations of maximum tolerable delays to be added by methods
      which improve bandwidth utilization through compression, multiplexing, and tunneling over a network path. 
      Recommendations are presented only for real-time network services for which such bandwidth optimization
      techniques are applicable (i.e., services with low payload size to header size ratio).
      
  </t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>This document extends the draft <xref target="TCMTF"></xref> with a set of recommendations
       	of overall tolerable delays which can be added in the processes of compression, multiplexing, and tunneling.
       	These recommendations are needed, since the techniques proposed in <xref target="TCMTF"></xref>, while saving bandwidth,
      	add additional network delay. Network delay is one of the main factors which can degrade the Quality of Experience (QoE) of
      	real-time network services <xref target="TGPP_TR26.944"></xref>. In order to prevent QoE degradation of real-time services using TCMTF, a policy defining 
      	a multiplexing period can be employed. Values of maximum tolerable delays presented here form the base of such policy.
       The recommendations are presented for real-time network services in which TCTMF bandwidth optimization is applicable (i.e., services
       which have low payload to header size ratio which results in high protocol overhead).
      </t>
	
	<t>The second set of recommendations focuses on different multiplexing policies and implementation issues 
	which are service and link specific. 
	 </t>
	 </section>
      <section title="Requirements Language">
        <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
        "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
        document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
        target="RFC2119">RFC 2119</xref>. </t>
      </section>

      <section title="Considered services">
      
      
    <t> Under the term "real-time network services" we consider both conversational and streaming service classes of services 
    as defined in <xref target="TGPP_TS"></xref>. Interactive and background services are considered non real-time.
	Fundamental requirements of real-time network services include 
    conversational pattern (stringent and low delay) and preservation of the time relation (variation) between 
    the information entities of the stream.  </t>
    <t> We are focused on real-time network services which have low payload to header size ratio 
    and therefore are appropriate for  bandwith optimizations presented in TCMTF. We identify the following services:</t>
     <t><list style="symbols">
	<t>Voice over IP </t>
    <t>Online games</t>
    <t>Remote desktop services</t>   
	</list></t>  
	 <t>While video services are considered real-time, they are not suitable for bandwidth optimization techniques  
	proposed in <xref target="TCMTF"></xref>, due to the high payload to header size ratio they present. Therefore, we neither take into account services using an approach in which all the calculations are deployed in the server, 
	which sends a real-time video stream to the client. In these cases, TCMTF optimization is 
	neither interesting nor applicable.
	On the other hand, TCMTF can be applied for web browsing in terms of payload to header size ratio, but since some studies have shown that web browsing delays
	of several seconds are acceptable to users, there is no need for policy limitations in TCMTF, as the multiplexing periods are shorter
	than that <xref target="ITU-T_G.1010"></xref>. 
	
		</t>
	</section>
	
	<section title="Delay recommendations">
		<t>The three normally considered network impairments in the studies related to subjective quality in real-time interactive games are:</t>
		<t><list style="symbols">
			<t>delay - can be reported as one-way-delay (OWD) <xref target="RFC2679"></xref> and two-way-delay (Round Trip Time) <xref target="RFC2681"></xref>. In this document, under the term latency, one way end-to-end
		 day is considered.</t>
			<t>jitter - which is a statistical variance of the data packet inter-arrival time, in other words the variation of the delay.</t>
			<t>packet loss - more important for certain applications, while other include very good algorithms for concealing it (e.g., some game genres).</t>
		</list></t>
	<t>In this document we give recommendations of overal tollerable delays for previously listed real-time network services. In an interactive service, 
	the total delay is composed by the addition of delays as defined in 3GPP TR 26.944 <xref target="TGPP_TR26.944"></xref>. </t> 
	
	<t><list style="symbols">
		<t>Transfer delay -  from Host1 to Host2 at time T is defined by the statement: Host1 sent the first bit of a unit data to Host2 at wire-time T and that Host2 received the last bit of that packet at wire-time T+dT</t>		
		<t>Transaction delay - the sum of the time for a data packet to wait in queue and receive the service during the server transaction.</t>
	</list></t>
<t></t>
<t>Figure 1 shows these delays. The labeled times (S and R) designate the times in which the packet is sent or received by the network card interface.</t>

<figure align="center" anchor="delays_no_mux">
        <preamble></preamble>

        <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
+-----------+                          +-----------+
|   Host1   |                          |   Host 2  | 
+-----------+                          +-----------+
       S-------                                   |   ^       ^
       |       -------                            |   |       |
       |              -------                     |transf.    |
       |                     -------              |   |       |
       |                            -------       |   v       |
       |                                   ------>R   ^       |
       |                                          |   |       |
       |                                          |transac. total RTT
       |                                          |   |       |
       |                                   -------S   v       |
       |                            -------       |   ^       |
       |                     -------              |   |       |
       |              -------                     |transf.    |
       |       -------                            |   |       |
       R<------                                   |   v       v
       |                                          |
                    S: Packet sent
                    R: Packet received           ]]></artwork>
        <postamble></postamble>
      </figure>


	<t>The use of TCMTF requires the addition of a multiplexer and a demultiplexer in the scenario. A number of flows are multiplexed together
	before being sent through the Internet. The packets are demultiplexed and rebuilt before being forwarded to the application server. 
	An scheme of TCMTF is included in Figure 2:</t>

<figure align="center" anchor="tcmtf_scheme">
        <preamble></preamble>

        <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
+------+
|user 1|___
+------+   \
            \            _  _
+------+    +-----+     ( `   )_        +-------+   +------+
|user 2|--->| mux |--> (    )    `) --->| demux |-->|server|
+------+    +-----+   (_   (_ .  _) _)  +-------+   +------+
   .        /            Internet
   .       /
+------+  /     <-----------tcmtf----------->
|user n|_/
+------+
                          ]]></artwork>
        <postamble></postamble>
      </figure>

	<t>This technique groups packets in order to build a multiplexed one. So "multiplexing period" has to be defined in the multiplexer. 
	When it ends, all the arrived packets are sent together in the same bundle. Therefore, multiplexing delay caused by tcmtf optimization techniques can be seen as an increase of transfer delay.
	The delay in the multiplexer is caused by the time the packets are retained until the
	bundled packet is sent, plus processing time. However, in the demultiplexer packets are not retained, so only processing time is considered.</t>

	<t>Figure 3 shows the total delay, when a multiplexer and a demultiplexer are added. It should be noticed that multiplexing can be deployed independently
	in the two directions, or only in one of them, as shown in Figure 3.</t>

<figure align="center" anchor="delays_mux">
        <preamble></preamble>
        <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
+---------+     +--------+      +--------+    +---------+
| Host 1  |     |  mux   |      |  demux |    | Host 2  |
+---------+     +--------+      +--------+    +---------+
    S-------         |               |             |   ^       ^
    |       -------  |               |             |   |       |
    |              --R     ^         |             |   |       |
    |                |     |         |             |   |       |
    |                |    mux        |             |   |       |
    |                |     |         |             |   |       |
    |                |     |         |             | transf.   |
    |                S---- v         |             | (& mux)   |
    |                |    -------    |             |   |       |
    |                            ----R    ^        |   |       |
    |                                |  demux      |   |    total RTT
    |                                |    |        |   |       |
    |                                S--- v        |   v       |
    |                                |   --------->R   ^       |
    |                                              |   |       |
    |                                              |transac.   |
    |                                              |   |       |
    |                                      --------S   v       |
    |                              --------        |   ^       |
    |                      --------                |   |       |
    |              --------                        | transf.   |
    |       -------                                |   |       |
    R<------                                       |   v       v
    |                                              |
                    S: Packet sent
                    R: Packet received  
 ]]></artwork>
        <postamble></postamble>
      </figure>

	<t>If a policy defining a multiplexing period is used, then the average latency added to each packet will be half the multiplexing period. 
	A tradeoff appears: the longer the multiplexing period, the higher the number of packets which can be grouped, thus obtaining better bandwidth savings.

	So in order to calculate the maximum multiplexing period, the rest of the delays have to be considered: if the sum of propagation, 
	processing and transmission delays is under the maximum tolerable delay, then multiplexing will be possible without harming user's experience. The calculation of the
	overal delay may be performed according to the ITU-T Y.1541 reccomendation <xref target="ITU-T_Y.1541"></xref> 
	The difference will give the maximum recommended multiplexing period.
	</t>
	
	<t>Next, we will report the maximum tolerable latencies for the previously listed real-time network services.</t>
	
	<section title="VoIP">
		<t>For conversational audio, the International Telecommunication Union recommends in <xref target="ITU-T_G.114"></xref>  
		less than 150 millisecond one-way end-to-end delay for high-quality real time traffic, but delays between 150ms and 400ms are acceptable. 
		For a streaming audio, delay constraints are much looser, the delay should be less than 10s <xref target="ITU-T_G.1010"></xref>.</t>
	</section>
		
	<section title="Online games">
		<t>Online games are a large area comprising many game genres which have different latency requirements. 
		This draft focuses on real-time online games and endorses the general game categorization proposed in  <xref target="Claypool_Latency"></xref> 
		in which online games have been divided into:</t>
		
		<t><list style="symbols">	
			<t>Omnipresent, with the threshold of acceptable latency (i.e., latency in which performance is 
			above 75% of the unimpaired performance) of 1000 ms. The most representative genre of omnipresent games are Real-Time Strategies.</t>

			<t>Third Person Avatar, with the threshold of acceptable latency of 500ms. These games include include Role Playing Games (RPG) and Massively Multiplayer Online 
			Role-Playing Games (MMORPG).</t>
	
			<t>First Person Avatar, in which threshold of acceptable latency is 100ms. The most popular subgenre of them are First Person Shooters, such as 
			"Call of Duty" or "Halo" series.</t>
		</list></t>
		
		<t>The study <xref target="Claypool_Latency"></xref> evaluated players' performance of certain tasks while increasing latency, and reported latencies in which the performance dropped below 75% of the performance under unimpaired network conditions.
		While measuring objective performance metrics, this method highly underestimates the impact of delays 
		on players' QoE. Further studies accessing a particular game genre reported much lower latency thresholds for unimpaired gameplay.
		</t>
		
		<t>A survey using a large number of First Person Shooter games was carried out in <xref target="Dick_Analysis"></xref>.
		As a result, they stated that latencies about 80ms could be considered as acceptable, since the games were rated as "unimpaired". 
		Besides service QoE, it has been shown that delay has great impact on the user's decision to join a game, but significantly lesser on 
		the decision to leave the game <xref target="Henderson_QoS"></xref>.
		</t>
		
		<t>A study oriented to evaluation of Mean Opinion Score (MOS), based on variation of delay and jitter for MMORPGs, suggested that MOS drops below 4 for 
		delays greater than 120 ms <xref target="Ries_QoEMMORPG"></xref>. The MOS score of 5 indicates excellent quality, while MOS score of 1 indicates bad quality.
		Another study focused on extracting the duration of play sessions for MMORPGs from the network 
		traffic traces showed that the session durations start to decline sharply when latency is between 150ms and 200ms latencies<xref target="Chen_HowSensitive"></xref>.
		</t>
		
		<t>While original classification work <xref target="Claypool_Latency"></xref> states that latencies up to 1s are tolerated by omnipresent games, other studies argued that only latencies 
		up to 200ms are tolerated by players of RTS games <xref target="Cajada_RTS"></xref>.
		</t>
	</section>
	
	<section title="Remote desktop access">	
		<t>	For the services of remote computer access, the delays are dependent on the task performed through the remote desktop, which
			are categorized into audio, video and data (reading, web browsing, document creation). A QoE study indicates that for audio latencies below 225 ms 
			and for data latencies below 200 ms are tolerated <xref target="Dusi_Thin"></xref>. </t>
		<t> We group all the results in the Table 1 indicating the maximum allowed of latencies and proposed multiplexing periods. Proposed
		multiplexing periods are guidelines, since the exact values are dependant of existing the delay in the network.
		It should be noted that multiplexing periods of about 1 second can be considered as enough for non real time services (e.g., web browsing and streaming audio).</t>
		
        <texttable anchor="final_recommendations" title="Final recommendations">
          <preamble></preamble>
          <ttcol align="center">Service</ttcol>
          <ttcol align="center">Tolerable latency (OWD) </ttcol>
		  <ttcol align="center">Mux. period</ttcol>
          <c>Voice communication</c>
          <c>&lt; 400ms</c>
		   <c>&lt; 80ms</c>
          <c>Omnipresent games</c>
          <c>&lt; 300ms</c>
		   <c>&lt; 60ms</c>
          <c>First person avatar games</c>
          <c>&lt; 100ms</c>
		   <c>&lt; 20ms</c>
          <c>Third person avatar games</c>
          <c>&lt; 200ms</c>
		   <c>&lt; 40ms</c>
          <c>Remote desktop</c>
          <c>&lt; 200ms</c>
		   <c>&lt; 40ms</c>
          <postamble></postamble>
        </texttable>
		
		
	</section>
	
	</section>
	 
	 <!-- JS adds this section. It is compulsory-->
	 <section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">
      <t> </t>

     </section>

     <!-- Possibly a 'Contributors' section ... -->

     <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>This memo includes no request to IANA.</t>

     </section>
	 <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>All drafts are required to have a security considerations section.
      See <xref target="RFC3552">RFC 3552</xref> for a guide.</t>
     </section>


	 </middle> 
    <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
	
	<!--JS COMMENTS THIS: This bibliography was used to gather most of the information in the
	sections above as well as for general reference. -->
      &RFC2119;
	  
	  <reference anchor="ITU-T_G.114" target="">
        <front>
          <title>ITU-T  Recommendation  G.114 One-way transmission time</title>
          <author>
            <organization>ITU-T</organization>
          </author>
		  <date year="2003" />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="ITU" value="G.114" />
      </reference>  
	  
  <reference anchor="RFC2681" target="">
        <front>
          <title> A Round-trip Delay Metric for IPPM</title>
          <author initials="G." surname="Almes">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>
		  <author initials="S." surname="Kalidindi">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>
		  <author initials="M." surname="Zekauskas">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>
 		  <date year="September 1999" />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="2681" />
      </reference>

	      <reference anchor="RFC2679" target="">
        <front>
          <title> A One-way Delay Metric for IPPM</title>
          <author initials="G." surname="Almes">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>
		  <author initials="S." surname="Kalidindi">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>
		  <author initials="M." surname="Zekauskas">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>
 		  <date year="September 1999" />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="2679" />
      </reference>
	  
  <reference anchor="ITU-T_G.1010" target="">
        <front>
          <title> End-user multimedia QoS categories </title> 
          <author initials="" surname="">
            <organization>International Telecommunication Union-Telecommunication</organization>
          </author>
		  <date year="2001" />
     
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="SERIES G: TRANSMISSION SYSTEMS AND MEDIA, 
DIGITAL SYSTEMS AND NETWORKS; Quality of service and performance" value="" />
      </reference>
  
    <reference anchor="ITU-T_Y.1541" target="">
        <front>
          <title>; Network performance objectives for IP-based 
services </title> 
          <author initials="" surname="">
            <organization>International Telecommunication Union-Telecommunication</organization>
          </author>
		  <date year="2011" />
             </front>
        <seriesInfo name="SERIES Y: GLOBAL INFORMATION 
INFRASTRUCTURE, INTERNET PROTOCOL ASPECTS 
AND NEXT-GENERATION NETWORKS;
Internet protocol aspects â€“ Quality of service and network 
performance" value="" />
      </reference>
	  

    </references>


    <references title="Informative References">
      <!-- Here we use entities that we defined at the beginning. -->


      &RFC3552;

	  <reference anchor="TCMTF" target="">
        <front>
          <title>Tunneling Compressed Multiplexed Traffic Flows (TCMTF)</title>
          <author initials="J." surname="Saldana">
            <organization>University of Zaragoza</organization>
          </author>
		  <author initials="D." surname="Wing">
            <organization>Cisco Systems</organization>
          </author>
		  <author initials="J." surname="Fernandez Navajas">
            <organization>University of Zaragoza</organization>
          </author>
		  <author initials="M. A. M." surname="Perumal">
            <organization>Cisco Systems</organization>
          </author>
		    <author initials="F." surname="Pascual Blanco">
            <organization>Telefonica I+D</organization>
          </author>
 		  <date year="2012" />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft " value="Jul" />
      </reference>
	  
    

	  <reference anchor="Claypool_Latency" target="">
        <front>
          <title>Latency and player actions in online games</title>
          <author initials="M." surname="Claypool">
            <organization>Worcester Polytechnic Institute</organization>
          </author>
          <author initials="K." surname="Claypool">
            <organization>Oracle Corporation</organization>
          </author>
          <date year="2006" />          
        </front>
        <seriesInfo  name="Communications of the ACM" value="49" />
      </reference>
   
	  <reference anchor="Dick_Analysis" target="">
        <front>
          <title>Analysis of factors affecting players' performance and perception in multiplayer games</title>	
          <author initials="M." surname="Dick">
            <organization>Technische Universität Braunschweig</organization>
          </author>
          <author initials="O." surname="Wellnitz">
            <organization>Technische Universität Braunschweig</organization>
          </author>
		  <author initials="L." surname="Wolf">
            <organization>chnische Universität Braunschweig</organization>
          </author>
          <date year="2005" />        
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="Proceedings of 4th ACM SIGCOMM workshop on Network and system support for games, pp. 1 - 7" value="" />
      </reference>
   
	  <reference anchor="Henderson_QoS" target="">
        <front>
          <title>Networked games: a QoS-sensitive application for QoS-insensitive users?</title>
          <author initials="T." surname="Henderson">
            <organization>University College London</organization>
          </author>
          <author initials="S." surname="Bhatti">
            <organization>University College London</organization>
          </author>        
          <date year="2003" />        
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="Proceedings of the ACM SIGCOMM workshop on Revisiting IP QoS: What have we learned, why do we care?, pp. 141-147 " value=""  />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="Chen_HowSensitive" target="">
        <front>
          <title>How sensitive are online gamers to network quality?</title>
          <author initials="K.-T." surname="Chen">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>
          <author initials="P." surname="Huang">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>
          <author initials="L." surname="Chin-Luang">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>
		  <date year="2006" />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="Communications of the ACM" value="49" />
      </reference>
      
      <reference anchor="Ries_QoEMMORPG" target="">
        <front>
          <title>Empirical Study of Subjective Quality for Massive Multiplayer Games</title>
          <author initials="M." surname="Ries">
            <organization>Inst. of Commun. Radio-Freq., Vienna Univ. of Technol</organization>
          </author>
          <author initials="P." surname="Svoboda">
            <organization>Inst. of Commun. Radio-Freq., Vienna Univ. of Technol</organization>
          </author>
          <author initials="M." surname="Rupp">
            <organization>Inst. of Commun. Radio-Freq., Vienna Univ. of Technol</organization>
          </author>
   
		  <date year="2008" />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="Proceedings of the 15th International Conference on Systems, Signals and Image Processing, pp.181 - 184" value=""/>
      </reference>
      
	   <reference anchor="Dusi_Thin" target="">
        <front>
          <title>A Closer Look at Thin-Client Connections: Statistical Application Identification for QoE Detection</title>
          <author initials="M." surname="Dusi">
            <organization>INEC Laboratories Europe</organization>
          </author>
          <author initials="S." surname="Napolitano">
            <organization>NEC Laboratories Europe</organization>
          </author>
          <author initials="S." surname="Niccolini">
            <organization>NEC Laboratories Europe</organization>
          </author>
		<author initials="S." surname="Longo">
            <organization>University of Napoli Federico II</organization>
          </author>
		  <date year="2012" />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="IEEE Communications Magazine, pp. 195 - 202" value="" />
      </reference>
	  
      <reference anchor="Cajada_RTS" target="">
        <front>
          <title>VFC-RTS: Vector-Field Consistency para Real-Time-Strategy Multiplayer Games</title>
          <author initials="M." surname="Cajada">
            <organization>Instituto Superior Tecnico, Technical University Lisboa</organization>
          </author>
		  <date year="2012" />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="Master of Science Disertation" value="" />
      </reference>
      
      <reference anchor="TGPP_TS" target="">
        <front>
          <title>Quality of Service (QoS) concept and architecture</title> 
          <author initials="" surname="">
            <organization>3rd Generation Partnership Project, European Telecommunications Standards Institute</organization>
          </author>
		  <date year="2012" />
             </front>
        <seriesInfo name="3GPP TS 23.107 version 11.0.0 Release 11" value="" />
      </reference>
	  
	
	  <reference anchor="TGPP_TR26.944" target="">
        <front>
          <title>Technical Specification Group Services and System Aspects;
End-to-end multimedia services performance metrics
</title> 
          <author initials="" surname="">
            <organization>3rd Generation Partnership Project;</organization>
          </author>
		  <date year="2012" />
             </front>
        <seriesInfo name="3GPP TR 26.944  version 9.0.0" value="" />
      </reference>

	  
    </references>
    <!-- Change Log

v00 2006-03-15  EBD   Initial version

v01 2006-04-03  EBD   Moved PI location back to position 1 -
                      v3.1 of XMLmind is better with them at this location.
v02 2007-03-07  AH    removed extraneous nested_list attribute,
                      other minor corrections
v03 2007-03-09  EBD   Added comments on null IANA sections and fixed heading capitalization.
                      Modified comments around figure to reflect non-implementation of
                      figure indent control.  Put in reference using anchor="DOMINATION".
                      Fixed up the date specification comments to reflect current truth.
v04 2007-03-09 AH     Major changes: shortened discussion of PIs,
                      added discussion of rfc include.
v05 2007-03-10 EBD    Added preamble to C program example to tell about ABNF and alternative 
                      images. Removed meta-characters from comments (causes problems).  -->
  </back>
</rfc>