<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- this file is based on
     http://tools.ietf.org/tools/templates/draft-davies-template-bare.xml                    -->

<!-- the following CSS stylesheet makes oxygen author mode happy                             -->
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="XML/rfc2629.css"?>

<!-- this stylesheet is used for xml -> xhtml translation                                    -->
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='XML/rfc2629.xslt' ?>

<!-- if you add an entity here, please remember to checkin a local copy in CATALOG/BIBXML    -->
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "XML/rfc2629/rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY RFC1822 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1822.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC2119 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC2616 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2616.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC2817 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2817.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3986 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3986.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.hamrick-vwrap-authentication SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.draft-hamrick-vwrap-authentication-00.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.lentczner-vwrap-foundation SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.draft-lentczner-vwrap-foundation-00.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.hamrick-vwrap-type-system SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.draft-hamrick-vwrap-type-system-00.xml">
]>

<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<!-- For a complete list and description of processing instructions (PIs), please see        -->
<!-- http://xml.resource.org/authoring/README.html.                                          -->

<!-- give errors regarding ID-nits and DTD validation                                        -->
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>

<!-- generate a ToC                                                                          -->
<?rfc toc="yes"?>

<!-- the number of levels of subsections in ToC. default: 3                                  -->
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>

<!-- use symbolic references tags, i.e, [RFC2119] instead of [1]                             -->
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>

<!-- sort the reference entries alphabetically                                               -->
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>

<!-- control vertical white space (the followign options are recommended by the RFC Editor.) -->
<!-- do not start each main section on a new page                                            -->
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>

<!-- keep one blank line between list items                                                  -->
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>

<!-- category values incude: std, bcp, info, exp, and historic                               -->
<!-- ipr values include: full3667, noModification3667, noDerivatives3667                     -->
<!-- you can add the attributes updates="NNNN" and obsoletes="NNNN". they will automatically -->
<!-- be output with "(if approved)"                                                          -->

<rfc category="info" docName="draft-hamrick-vwrap-intro-01" ipr="trust200902">
  <!-- category values: std, bcp, info, exp, and historic
     ipr values: full3667, noModification3667, noDerivatives3667
     you can add the attributes updates="NNNN" and obsoletes="NNNN" 
     they will automatically be output with "(if approved)" -->

  <!-- ***** FRONT MATTER ***** -->

  <front>
    <!-- The abbreviated title is used in the page header - it is only necessary if the 
         full title is longer than 39 characters -->

    <title abbrev="VWRAP: Introduction and Goals">VWRAP: Introduction and Goals</title>

    <!-- add 'role="editor"' below for the editors if appropriate -->

    <!-- Another author who claims to be an editor -->

    <author fullname="Meadhbh Siobhan Hamrick" initials="M. S." surname="Hamrick">
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>P.O. Box 783</street>
          <city>Boulder Creek</city>
          <region>CA</region>
          <code>95006</code>
          <country>US</country>
        </postal>
        <phone>+1 650 283 0344</phone>
        <email>OhMeadhbh@gmail.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="David W. Levine" initials="D.W." surname="Levine">
      <organization>IBM Thomas J. Watson Research Center</organization>
      <address>
	<postal>
	  <street>19 Skyline Drive</street>
	  <city>Hawthorn</city>
	  <region>NY</region>
	  <code>10532</code>
	  <country>US</country>
	</postal>
	<phone>+1 914 784 7427</phone>
	<email>dwl@us.ibm.com</email>
      </address>
   </author>

    <!-- If the month and year are both specified and are the current ones, xml2rfc will     -->
    <!-- fill in the current day for you. If only the current year is specified, xml2rfc     -->
    <!-- will fill in the current day and month for you. If the year is not the current one, -->
    <!-- it is necessary to specify at least a month (xml2rfc assumes day="1" if not         -->
    <!-- specified for the purpose of calculating the expiry date).  With drafts it is       -->
    <!-- normally sufficient to specify just the year.                                       -->  

    <date month="May" year="2010" day="18"/>
    
    <area>Applications</area>

    <!-- WG name at the upperleft corner of the doc, IETF is fine for individual             -->
    <!-- submissions. If this element is not present, the default is "Network Working        -->
    <!-- Group", which is used by the RFC Editor as a nod to the history of the IETF.        -->
    
    <workgroup>Virtual World Region Agent Protocol</workgroup>

    <!-- Keywords will be incorporated into HTML output files in a meta tag but they have no -->
    <!-- effect on text or nroff output. If you submit your draft to the RFC Editor, the     -->
    <!-- keywords will be used for the search engine.                                        -->
    
    <keyword>VWRAP</keyword>
    <keyword>Virtual World Region Agent Protocol</keyword>
    <keyword>virtual world</keyword>
    
    <abstract>

      <t>The Virtual World Region Agent Protocol (VWRAP) defines interactions between hosts
      collaborating to create an shared, internet scale virtual world experience. This
      document introduces the protocol, the objectives and requirements it imposes on hosts
      implementing the protocol. To the extent it affects protocol interactions, this document
      describes the model assumed by the protocol.</t>

    </abstract>

</front>

  <middle>

    <section title="Introduction and Motivation">
 
      <t>Virtual Worlds are of increasing interest to the internet community. Innumerable
      examples of virtual world implementations exist; most using proprietary protocols.  With
      roots in games and social interaction, virtual worlds are now finding use in business,
      education and information exchange. This document introduces the Virtual World Region
      Agent Protocol (VWRAP) suite. This protocol suite is intended to carry information about
      a virtual world: its shape, its residents and objects existing within it. VWRAP's goal
      is to define an extensible set of messages for carrying state and state change
      information between hosts participating in the simulation of the virtual world.</t>

      <t>Virtual worlds differ in their capabilities and architectural features. The VWRAP
      protocol suite is not appropriate for all massively multi-participant experiences. This
      document provides an introduction to virtual worlds and defines characteristics of
      virtual worlds VWRAP explicitly supports. It also describes the specific objectives of
      the protocol suite. An overview of the protocol is included, including an architectural
      description and list of services defined in a typical virtual world deployment.</t>

      <section title="Requirements Language">

        <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD",
        "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be
        interpreted as described in <xref target="RFC2119">RFC 2119</xref>.</t>

      </section>

    </section>

    <section title="Introducing the Virtual World Region Agent Protocol">
      <section title="A Brief Introduction to Virtual Worlds">

        <t>At its most basic level, the virtual world mirrors the reified world.  It is
	inhabited by people and contains objects. Objects and people have a distinct place in
	the world and respond to external forces.  The social construction of the virtual
	world is also similar to the reified world.  People meet and interact with others to
	complete work tasks or for simple enjoyment. People converse, share media, and even
	sing to each other. A virtual world may allow commerce or enable building of virtual
	assets. Nearly the complete range of human interaction can be replicated in the
	virtual world. Properly rendered, an experience in a virtual world can carry the same
	impact as one in consensus reality.</t>

        <t>To be relevant to the participant's experience, virtual worlds must retain
        characteristics of the "real world."  Objects in the virtual world are models of
        familiar shapes and textures, represented using a common data format so they may be
        easily processed by the human visual cortex. At the same time they must carry
        sufficient information to be consumed by participants with visual impairments or to be
        processed by automated systems.  Though the virtual world's state is maintained by
        abstract collections of data, it is rendered as recognizable (though occasionally
        fantastical) physical objects.</t>

        <t>But virtual worlds are not completly faithful mirrors of the world our physical
        bodies inhabit.  Virtual worlds are not limited by distance.  With appropriate network
        connectivity, users may interact even if they are on opposite sides of the earth.
        Virtual worlds also allow participants to "play" with physical constraints.  They
        provide the subjective experience of things not possible in consensus reality:
        participants can fly, the effects of "death" are temporary, users may call items into
        existence, examine the International Space Station with friends, examine DNA codon by
        codon with co-workers, or experience with a works of interactive art.</t>

	<t>Virtual worlds inherit the intellectual property characteristics of other digital
	media.  Implementers wishing to replicate the economy of scarcity present in the
	reified world must take special measures to avoid or limit the ramifications of
	unauthorized content duplication.</t>

	<t>The VWRAP suite assumes network hosts, likely operated by distinct organizations
        will collaborate to simulate the virtual world.  It also assumes that services
        originally defined for other environments (like the world wide web) will enhance the
        experience of the virtual world. The virtual world is expected to be simulated using
        software from multiple sources; interoperability standards are essential for
        delivering a robust services and compelling user experiences.  VWRAP provides these
        interoperability standaards. It may be used with large arrays of hosts simulating a
        vast virtual world, or small worlds operated for the benefit a few persons.  It
        defines a trust model so hosts from different organizations may limit access to
        sensitive information.</t>

        <t>VWRAP presupposes a virtual world with the following characteristics:

          <list hangIndent="4" style="hanging">

            <t hangText="1. The virtual world exists independent of the participating clients.">
            <vspace blankLines="1"/>This is in contrast to systems that dynamically create
            virtual environments for specific social or task-oriented simulation. VWRAP
            assumes the state virtual world is "always on" and does not require a specific
            protocol to establish new virtual worlds.</t>
        
            <t hangText="2. Avatars have a single, unique presence in the virtual world.">
            <vspace blankLines="1"/>Users are represented in the virtual world by a digital
	    representation called an avatar. A user's avatar has an existence that mirrors the
	    common physical world. Like people, avatars exist in only one place at one
	    time. Avatars have a single identity that persists between user sessions. This
	    identity may be used to render user-specific avatar shape or as the basis for
	    access control.</t>
        
            <t hangText="3. The virtual world contains persistent objects.">
            <vspace blankLines="1"/>Objects in the virtual world are governed by a "rational"
            life-cycle. They are created, persist and are (optionally) destroyed. Absent
	    external forces, they tend to keep their current state.</t>

          </list>

        </t>

      </section>

      <section title="Architectural Objectives">

        <t>The overall objective of the VWRAP suite is to enable a stable, extensible and
	secure virtual world. The protocols defined by this working group do not mandate a
	specific system or network architecture. However, previous implementations of large
	distributed systems can yeild clues as to how VWRAP compliant systems will be
	deployed. Documents produced by this working group reflect the consensus view of best
	common practice for producing large-scale, loosely-coupled distributed systems. VWRAP
	does not require a specific architecture, but it's protocols are defined with a
	specific series of architectural patterns in mind.</t>

	<t>These architectural patterns have the following objectives in mind:
        <list hangIndent="4" style="hanging">

          <t hangText="1. Systems implementing virtual world services should be distributed.">
	  <vspace blankLines="1"/>Virtual worlds are inherently distributed systems. They are
	  collaborative tools intended to reduce the effect of distance on meaningful social,
	  educational and commercial interaction. Typical virtual worlds are envisioned as
	  drawing services from network hosts operated by a wide array of organizational
	  entities. Virtual worlds may also be large enough that a single system or cluster of
	  systems is not capable of providing all services to each client.

	  <vspace blankLines="1"/>Experience with previous virtual world technologies suggests
	  systems implementing the virtual world assume services they depend on are provided
	  by distinct hosts in different administrative domains. The virtual world, it's user
	  base and the constellation of virtual objects they use are simply too vast and
	  varied to assume a single system or a single provider.

	  <vspace blankLines="1"/>This does not mean, however, that virtual worlds simulated
	  by the VWRAP suite must exist on more than one system.  Quite the contrary, all
	  VWRAP components (including the user agent) could operate on a single system. But
	  there is little reason to believe the protocol used to exchange information between
	  virtual world services must differ between small and large systems.

	  <vspace blankLines="1"/>Large virtual worlds with many users are certain to implement
	  virtual world services differently than small ones. But the protocol used to
	  to communicate between systems implementing the virtual world can be the same. To be
	  sure, optimizations may be possible for smaller deployments. Implementers of these
	  "small" systems may find it useful to utilize standard, unoptimized protocols to
	  allow for the possibility of growth.

	  <vspace blankLines="1"/>However large (or small) a virtual world deployment is,
	  or how many distinct organizations contribute to its operation, software implementing
	  virtual world services MUST assume resources required to perform its function are
	  distributed amongst multiple hosts.</t>

	  <t hangText="2. Services supporting collaboration are hosted on 'central' systems.">

	  <vspace blankLines="1"/>The VWRAP suite assumes a collection of authoritative hosts for
	  critical data and services. This applies to digital assets, user accounts, agent
	  presence information and sources for virtual world object updates. This is in
	  contrast to 'peer to peer' systems in which authoritative data may travel between
	  hosts, depending on which hosts are connected to the network at any given moment. It
	  also contrasts with 'client authoritative' or 'co-simulation' architectures in which
	  physics simulation and agent state change occurs on the client.

	  <vspace blankLines="1"/>This does not imply there is a single collection of systems
	  holding authoritative data for the entire connected Internet.On the contrary, it
	  explicitly allows for the simultaneous existance of multiple virtual worlds. It defines
	  the mechanisms by which systems cooperate to simulate a virtual world, but does not
	  specify a specific instance of those protocols as being any more authoritative than
	  any others.

	  <vspace blankLines="1"/>This objective implies that for any given data item, be it a
	  avatar mesh, a region description or object description, there is an authorative URL.
	  Subject to security policy, the data may be cached or transferred between domains, but
	  authority over the data rests with administrative ownership of the host identified
	  by it's URL.

	  <vspace blankLines="1"/>This decision was motivated by the realization that network
	  load in niave peer-to-peer implementations increases proportionally to the factorial
	  of the number of participants. "Client Authoritative" solutions, where clients are
	  first class participants in physics simulation or object presence and differences
	  are explicitly resolved between clients, was thought to introduce undesirable
	  requirements for client connectivity and client system performance.

	  <vspace blankLines="1"/>This is not to say that either peer-to-peer or co-simulation
	  are incompatible with systems that might use VWRAP. But rather, it was believed that
	  their specification should be deferred to a later time when solutions to perceived
	  problems could be explored more fully.
	  </t>

	  <t hangText="3. Hosts cooperating to simulate a virtual world should be composed of loosely coupled systems.">

	  <vspace blankLines="1"/>This document uses the term "loosely coupled" to mean
	  software and systems implementing the virtual world should exhibit strong separation
	  of concerns and resiliance in the presence of version skew. For the purposes of this
	  document, "loosely coupled" implies system developers should expect multiple
	  revisions of message formats to be encountered. Systems implementing these protocols
	  should make a best effort to interpret messages received from remote
	  hosts. Conversely, protocol developers and system implementers should carefully
	  craft new revisions of messages to avoid confusion for systems expecting earlier
	  message formats.

	  <vspace blankLines="1"/>The motivation for emphesizing this pattern stems from the
	  requirement that systems cooperating to simulate the virtual world may be owned by
	  distinct organizations. 
	  </t>

	  <t hangText="4. A persistent, ubituitous identity may accompany requests between hosts.">

	  <vspace blankLines="1"/>Many network services are provided anonymously; the nature
          of the service does not require identity authentication prior to it's use. But with
          the increasing deployment of customizable services delivered on the internet,
          identity is increasingly important. Even services that contain information that
          might not be considered "sensitive" require a representation of digital identity if
          for no other reason than to match service requests with user preferences. For
          example, a web page presenting current weather information may be enhanced by
          remembering locations of interest to each user. Recent work with "web mash ups,"
          where multiple personalized or sensitive resources are used in concert with one
          another points to the utility of a "universal" identity. The representation of this
          universal identity enables independent services to cooperate to present the facade
          of a unified application to the service consumer. This allows service aggregators to
          more easily integrate "best of breed" services into a consistent
          solution.

	  <vspace blankLines="1"/>Universal identity is critical to the virtual world. To
          achieve an internet scale virtual world, user services must be distributed amongst
          multiple hosts. To achieve a compelling experience, it must be easy for service
          providers to deliver their services in the virtual world. To facilitate a compelling
          social experience in the virtual world, all users must have the ability evaluate
          identity information of other users. Domains responsible for virtual world
          simulation MUST use a consistent representation of identity across all their hosts;
          simulation would otherwise be uncoordinated. Service providers who deliver content
          into the virtual world MUST use a consistent representation of identity to maintain
          the persistence of the virtual manifestation of their service; virtual objects used
          in conjunction with these services might otherwise appear to change state without
          apparent cause. Users depend on the persistent, universal identity of other users;
          if an avatar's identity changed unexpectedly, the result would be a suboptimal
          virtual world experience.</t>

	</list>
	</t>

      </section>

      <section title="Protocol Objectives">

        <t>The primary objective of the Virtual World Region Agent Protocol is to provide a
        stable, extensible, secure system for virtual world information interchange with the
        following characteristics:

        <list hangIndent="4" style="hanging">
                    
          <t hangText="1. Flexible presentation of protocol data">

	    <vspace blankLines="1"/>While the primary purpose of the virtual world is to
            simulate a physical or social space, the tools used to access objects in the
            virtual world may be varied. Using a "3d viewer" is the primary mode of
            interaction with the virtual world, but other tools may be better suited for some
            tasks. For instance, it may be easier for a user to use a web browser to review
            avatar profile information, or to change details of virtual objects. Further,
            virtual world "mash ups" may prove to be important to some communities. To support
            the web (where XML and JSON are the lingua franca of information exchange) while
            also supporting tools where binary encodings are more appropriate, VWRAP was
            designed to be "presentation neutral."</t>
          
          <t>VWRAP protocol exchanges are described in terms of an abstract type system using
          an interface description language. Implementations may choose to instantiate actual
          protocol data units using the most appropriate presentation format. Web-based
          applications may choose to use JSON or XML. Server-to-server interactions may use
          the VWRAP specific binary serialization scheme if implementers and deployers view
          binary encoding to be advantageous. The decision of which serialization scheme to
          use is ultimately that of the system implementer. VWRAP has been designed to provide
          this flexibility to system implementers and those tasked with deploying VWRAP
          compatible systems.</t>
  
          <t hangText="2. Flexible decomposition of concerns and ease of extension">

	    <vspace blankLines="1"/>VWRAP has been daesigned to allow meaningful separation of
            concerns. In other words, changes in one part of the protocol should not
            appreciably affect other parts.</t>

          <t>For example, the authentication portion of the protocol is independent of the
          part of the protocol that deals with instant messaging or instantiating objects in
          the virtual world. In addition to defining messages for communicating application
          state, the specification also defines pre- and post-conditions.  Should one
          particular authentication scheme be found to be lacking, it can be modified or
          replaced without affecting other systems.</t>

          <t>This type of separation of concerns in the protocol specification also makes it
          easy to deploy "related solutions." While VWRAP was designed primarily to
          communicate the state of the virtual world between servers and client applications,
          a number of related applications also exist. E-Commerce web sites related to the
          virtual world and mobile chat clients allowing instant messaging between mobile
          networks and virtual world participants are just two examples of such
          applications. Proper separation of concerns allows new services to be specified and
          deployed without the need to redefine existing protocol.
          </t>
          
          <t hangText="3. Resilience in the face of version skew"><vspace blankLines="1"/>Core to
          the VWRAP protocol is the idea that different components and services may be
          operated by different administrative entities; identity management services might be
          operated one business while simulation services are operated by another. In
          environments where many different organizations participate, version skew can be an
          important concern. VWRAP was designed to "degrade gracefully" when two systems
          running different versions of the protocol attempt to communicate.</t>
          
	  <t>VWRAP uses the LLSD abstract type system and the LLIDL interface description
          language to describe the structure and type semantics of elements in messages sent
          between systems.  Because LLSD makes extensive use of variable width, clearly
          delineated data fields, services which consume protocol messages may identify and
          extract only those message elements they know how to handle. While this is not a
          guarantee that message semantics may be preserved in all version skew situations, it
          does eliminate one important cause of interoperability failures.</t>
        </list></t>
      
      </section>

    </section>

    <section title="Virtual World Region Agent Protocol Architecture">

      <section title="Deployment Patterns">
	<t>The VWRAP suite assumes that the services that simulate the virtual world will be hosted
	on multiple network hosts. Client applications that render the virtual world for end users
	are assumed to be on distinct hosts as well.</t>

      <figure>

        <artwork align="center" alt="Figure 1: Typical VWRAP Deployment">
            
                          +---------------------+
                          | organization 1      |
                          |                     |
                          | +----------------+  |     +-------------+
                    +------&gt;| service host 1 |&lt;------&gt;]             |
                    |     | +----------------+  |     |   client    |
                    |     |                     | +--&gt;| application |
+-------------+     |     |                     | |   |             |
|             |&lt;----+     | +----------------+  | |   +-------------+
|   client    |&lt;-----------&gt;| service host 2 |&lt;---+     ^
| application |           | +----------------+  |       |
|             |&lt;----+     +---------------------+       |
+-------------+     |                                   |
                    |     +---------------------+       |
                    |     | organization 2      |       |
                    |     |                     |       |
                    |     | +----------------+  |       |
                    +------&gt;| service host 3 |&lt;---------+
                          | +----------------+  |
                          +---------------------+
                          
        </artwork>
        <postamble>Figure 1: Protocol Flows in VWRAP</postamble>
</figure>

      <t>Figure 1 above demonstrats a typical virtual world deployment. In it we see multiple
      client applications connecting to several servers operated by multiple
      organizations. Each "service host" in this diagram exposes an interface to a collection
      of resources representing the state of objects in the virtual world. It is traditional
      to discuss related resources as exposing "an interface" while related interfaces
      comprise "a service." Typical services are listed in a section below.</t>

      <t>There is no restriction on how services map to hosts. Deployments where all resource
      interfaces are hosted on a single host is just as valid as one where resources are
      spread between a wide array of systems. Client applications should support both.Resource
      interfaces are addressed using URLs. Clients should treat the URLs for resources as
      opaque resource locations.</t>

      <t>Clients use the "service establishment" process to retrieve URLs to various resources.</t>

      </section>

      <section title="Protocol Elements">
        <t>VWRAP utilizes a number of "architectural motifs" or recurring design patterns. Most
        notably they include:
        <list style="symbols">
          <t>exposing application state via RESTful resources</t>
          <t>using URIs to represent the address of application resources</t>
          <t>using HTTP to "carry" message oriented protocol data</t>
          <t>defining application state transitions and accesses with an interface description language</t>
          <t>using an abstract type system to define access semantics of fields in protocol messages</t>
          <t>using multiple "serializations" of the abstract type system to support different categories of consumers; defined serializations include XML, JSON and Binary.</t>
        </list>
        
        </t>

        <section title="Communicating Application State Using REST-Like Resource Accesses">
          <t>Contrary to popular opinion, not ALL virtual world interactions must be real-time
          exchanges. Many common activities like user authentication and texture and object
          transfer do not require "real time" semantics in the same way that applications like
          video-conferencing and Voice Over IP (VOIP) do. While it is generally a better
          experience if textures download quickly, if they are delayed, it does not have the
          same ramifications as if a voice packet in a VOIP system were delayed. Additionally,
          some interactions with the virtual world are strongly reminiscent of the
          request / response semantics used by popular protocols (like HTTP, POP3, etc.)</t>
          
          <t>Because many protocol exchanges in the virtual world may be represented as
            non-real-time request / response interactions, VWRAP "reuses" the messaging
          semantics of HTTP. The justification for this is simple. Were VWRAP to not use HTTP,
          many of the features of HTTP would need to be re-invented or at least re-specified.
          Features like the use of mime types to identify payload structure; the use of message
          headers to modify the request or response and the use of URIs to address and identify
          resources. HTTP also has the benefit of being well supported by tools vendors and
          well understood by manufacturers of networking equipment.
          </t>
          
          <t>Protocol exchanges in VWRAP that utilize request / response semantics are described
          using the LLSD / LLIDL abstract type system <xref target="I-D.hamrick-vwrap-type-system"/>. LLSD
          defines type semantics for elements in a protocol data unit as well as rules for
          converting the data into a serialized form suitable for transmission across the
          network. VWRAP defines HTTP (and HTTPS) as the transports for serialized
          messages.</t>
          
          <t>Addressable protocol endpoints in VWRAP are represented as URIs <xref target="RFC3986"/>.
          Protocol endpoints generally address RESTful resources. The VWRAP protocol uses HTTP
          verbs to provide read and write access to resources which represent the application
          state of the remote peer.</t>
          
          <t>To recap, the objective of VWRAP is to communicate application state about the
          virtual world to all participants. VWRAP messages that communicate request / response
          style messages flow between clients and servers, using HTTP(S) as a message transport.
          Application objects representing the application state expose a RESTful interface and
          are addressed unambiguously
          using URIs. The VWRAP message formats are described using LLIDL, the interface description
          language defined as part of the LLSD abstract type system. LLIDL defines RESTful
          resource accesses in terms of the LLSD abstract type system, which may be serialized 
          using one of three well defined serialization mechanisms: XML, JSON and Binary.
          Protocol participants decide before interacting which serialization mechanism is most
          appropriate or use the content negotiation mechanisms defined in HTTP.</t>
        </section>
        
        <section title="Bi-Directional Messaging with the VWRAP Event Queue">
          <t>Not all protocol interactions are easily represented by HTTP's request / response
          semantics. When the server has a message for the client, there is no widely deployed
          technique for the server to initiate a HTTP request to the client. It is
          interesting to note that this is the same problem developers of "rich web applications"
          see when deploying their applications. Though VWRAP is not targeted for implementation
          exclusively in web browsers, we can utilize some of the techniques common in COMET
          applications.</t>
          
          <t>Work is ongoing to define a general solution for "reverse HTTP," but many of these
          solutions require the definition of new protocol and deploying new code to web
          servers. The current best practice for COMET-style interaction is the use of the
          "long poll."</t>
          
          <t>To avoid "technology lock in," VWRAP defines an Event Queue abstraction that 
          represents the flow of messages from the server to the client. The Event Queue is
          expected to be implemented using the long poll technique. When additional options
          such as Reverse HTTP or web sockets are specified and in general deployment, the
          Event Queue may be re-implemented using these techniques. However, the interface
          defined by the Event Queue in the <xref target="I-D.lentczner-vwrap-foundation">VWRAP Foundation document</xref> should not change.</t>
          
        </section>
        
        <section title="Using Capabilities to Simplify Inter-Domain Access Control">
          <t>Simulated objects and services delivered by VWRAP compliant systems will require some
            level of access control. Unfortunately, distributed access control is a notoriously
            difficult problem. VWRAP seeks to minimize the drawbacks of distributed access control by
            use of capabilities. In this context, a capability is an opaque URL, some portion of which contains a securely generated, cryptographically unguessable
          sequence of digits. Capabilities are used to define service endpoints and are
          intended to only be in the possession of trusted parties.</t>
          
          <t>For example, a system may export the capability:</t>
          <t>http://www.example.org/s/B2A2A445-D234-463A-BE6D-6C54E5854FE4/</t>
          <t>This URL defines the protocol endpoint used to communicate application state
          changes (or query application state) for a specific application object by a 
          specific user (or delegate.)</t>
          
          <t>Capabilities are required to be effectively unguessable as they represent the
          right to perform a set of operations on a particular resource. Additionally, they must
          be kept "secret." While the task of maintaining the confidentiality of a number of 
          web resource addresses may be a burden, it does have the advantage of simplifying
          access delegation. If a subject wishes to delegate access to a third party, they
          simply communicate the capability.</t>
          
          <t>To reduce the likelihood of successful guessing attacks, inadvertent disclosure of
            a capability and "time of check, time of use" attacks, capabilities in VWRAP have
          a fixed lifetime, after which they expire. Systems SHOULD pick capability lifetimes
          commensurate with their security requirements and MUST NOT respond to protocol
          requests directed at a capability's URL after it has expired. Additionally, VWRAP
          capabilities may be "single use" or "one shot," meaning that they may only be used
          once before expiring.</t>
          
          <t>Because capabilities are randomly generated with a short lifetime, VWRAP defines
          a mechanism for securely communicating capabilities and re-requesting expired
          capabilities.</t>
          
          <t>It is important to note that capabilities do not completely replace traditional
          access control models. Systems may still use traditional Subject-Permission-Object
          schemes to represent access control for objects under their control. Capabilities
          provide a mechanism for communicating access control decisions among
          loosely coupled trusted systems.</t>
          
        </section>
        
        <section title="Using LLSD to Avoid Version Skew">
          <t>It is a common practice in large, complicated software systems to divide the
            system into smaller, more manageable pieces. The precise nature of this partitioning
            is beyond the scope of this protocol. However, practical experience has demonstrated
            that services distributed across multiple co-operating hosts MUST contend with the
            issue of version skew. Simply stated, version skew is the condition where multiple
            versions of a service are interoperating simultaneously.</t>
          
          <t>There are many reasons why version skew may be introduced. In VWRAP, agent domain
            hosts and region domain hosts may be operated by different organizations with
            different deployment schedules. Or perhaps a domain operator is required to
            support an obsolete version of a particular service endpoint for a small 
            number of customers. Whatever the cause of version skew, it has, in the past
            introduced difficulties in deploying distributed services.</t>
          
          <t>VWRAP does not seek to eliminate version skew, but it does attempt to reduce it's
            impact. VWRAP services are defined in using the LLIDL interface description
            language. LLIDL defines the type semantics of fields inside a protocol message
            using the LLSD abstract type system. Each of the abstract types defined in LLSD
            has a default value, and common conversions between conformable types are defined.
            LLSD specifies three standard techniques for
            serializing a protocol message prior to transmission across the network. Each of
            the three serialization techniques renders protocol messages into a collection
            of variable length fields. Protocol content is identified by JSON syntax, binary
            tags or XML element semantics, not by it's position in the message. LLIDL does not
            support the concept of a "required field." If a field defined in
            a protocol interaction is not present in the serialized message, it is semantically
            equivalent to the field being present and containing the default value for the
            field's type.</t>
          
          <t>Careful construction of service endpoints allows them to consume messages
            described using LLIDL without fear that version skew induced format differences
            may cause the semantics of the message to be unclear. If a message arrives at
            a service endpoint with extra fields (fields defined in a later revision of the
            protocol exchange), the consumer can still extract those fields it understands.
            If a message arrives lacking a field described in the protocol exchange,
            the service endpoint SHOULD interpret it as if the field was present and contained
            the default value for it's type. This implies the message consumer cannot
            depend on the format of the message to determine validity, but must examine
            the contents of the message, converting missing fields to present fields with
            default values, and then determine if sufficient information is present to
            imply semantics about the protocol exchange.</t>
          
          <t>This technique will not eliminate all ramifications of version skew, but carefully
            constructed service descriptions should be able to avoid the most common problems
            found when services interoperate with minor revision differences. While the
            Virtual World Region Agent Protocol itself does not mandate this style of message interpretation,
            it does require that messages be constructed so that service endpoints may do
            so.</t>
          
        </section>
      </section>
      
    </section>

    <section title="Virtual World Region Agent Protocol Services">

      <t>Simulation and persistence of virtual objects in VWRAP is managed on "central"
	servers. Servers maintain interfaces to shared resources which represent the state of
	the virtual world. Interfaces are grouped by function into "services."  Services are
	available to support the access to and distribution of data representing multiple
	facets of the virtual world. This section defines some services defined by VWRAP.

        <list hangIndent="4" style="hanging">
                        
            <t>Avatar Presence<vspace blankLines="1"/>When a user authenticates themselves and
            wishes to interact with the virtual world, the user's avatar presence must be
            established. Simulating a user's avatar is a task shared by the agent domain,
            the region domain and the client application. The agent domain is responsible for
            establishing the user's presence in the virtual world simulated by the region
            domain, and to provide information about the avatar so it may be properly rendered.</t>

              <t>Object Presence<vspace blankLines="1"/>The state of objects in the virtual world (landscapes,
              avatars, virtual "things") must be communicated to all participants. It is the
              responsibility of the region domain to keep track of each object's state. The
              landscape can change; clouds in the virtual sky may move and change shape; virtual
              people may move around and virtual "things" can undergo any number of state
              changes. The region domain is responsible for receiving input from virtual world
              inhabitants, evaluating how that input changes the state of objects in the
              virtual world, and then communicating those state changes to other observers.</t>
              <t>Physics Simulation<vspace blankLines="1"/>Simulating the physical behavior of
              objects in the virtual world is a core feature of any virtual world. Regions
              may choose "earth like" conditions, or may modify gravity and atmospheric settings
              to create the experience of being on a different planet. Still other options
              include simulating quantum effects seen at very small scales or the large scale
              relativistic effects seen on galactic scales. Whatever the "physics" involved,
              it is the individual hosts in the region domain tasked with the simulation.</t>
              <t>Effects of Programmatic Changes<vspace blankLines="1"/>(aka "scripting.") Some
              virtual worlds allow users to modify the state of objects using simple programming
              languages. The region domain is generally responsible for managing and executing
              scripts that modify the state of objects.</t>
              <t>Region Specific Asset Storage<vspace blankLines="1"/>Though most "assets at rest"
              are associated with an avatar, it is conceptually appropriate for some items to
              be associated with a region; textures associated with landscapes, for instance. Or
              in some situations, the operator of a region may wish to bind "sensitive" resources
              to the location to ensure they do not follow region visitors to regions outside the
              originating region's administrative authority.</t>

          </list></t>

      <section title="Authentication">

        <t>User Authentication in the Virtual World Region Agent Protocol is intended to
        verify the user's authorization to control their avatar in the virtual world and
        associated services.  VWRAP currently defines three methods for authenticating a user,
        as well as recommendations for integrating some third party authentication
        schemes. The inputs to authentication are an avatar or account identifier and a
        related authentication token. Assuming the token is successfully authenticated, the
        output of authentication is a seed capability or "seed cap."</t>
        
        <t>Like most VWRAP protocol exchanges, authentication protocol data is represented as
        LLSD serialized data carried over a secure HTTPS transport. The use of TLS with VWRAP
        authentication is recommended for all deployers who do not employ some other network
        security scheme (IPSec, link encryption, etc.) Implementers are advised that in
        addition to user's password (or other credential,) the seed capability returned after
        successful authentication is also considered "sensitive" and should be protected with
        appropriate network security measures.</t>
        
        <t>The three authentication schemes defined in
        the <xref target="I-D.hamrick-vwrap-authentication">VWRAP Trust Model and User
        Authentication</xref> specification use a cryptographic hashes to demonstrate the user
        is in possession of the shared secret associated with their account. Recommendations
        also exist for using transport authentication mechanisms (such as TLS client
        certificates) in place of shared secrets. Also, work is currently underway to define
        protocol messages for use with Secure Remote Password (SRP).</t>
        
        <t>The authentication mechanisms described above are believed to be sufficient at the
        time of this writing.  It is an unfortunate truth, however, that cryptographic
        primitives are occasionally shown to be less secure than originally believed. For this
        reason, VWRAP Authentication was designed to be extensible; allowing future users to
        define new authentication schemes without invalidating other authentication
        components. A further benefit of flexibility is the ability to integrate other
        authentication schemes into an VWRAP context. OpenID and SAML, for instance, are
        popular identity and user authentication technologies that are defined outside the
        IETF. VWRAP's flexible authentication system allows organizations responsible for
        these standards to define their use with VWRAP without having to change the text of
        the VWRAP Authentication standard.</t>
        
        <t>A typical flow of events for user authentication follows. This is a simplified
        version; readers with an interest in authentication are referred to the
        <xref target="I-D.hamrick-vwrap-authentication">VWRAP Trust Model and User
        Authentication</xref> specification.
        
        <list style="numbers">

          <t>The end user presents their account identifier (either avatar name or account
          name) and an authenticator to the authentication services of the agent
          domain. Endpoints for user authentication protocol messages are typically well
          defined, public URLs.</t>

          <t>The authentication service authenticates the authenticator. If the credentials
          cannot be authenticated, an error condition is returned.</t>

          <t>The authentication service generates a seed capability and returns it to the
          user.</t>

          <t>The user queries the "seed cap," requesting capabilities for other services the
          user is authorized to use.</t>

        </list></t>
        
        <t>It is important to note that in the last step listed above, the client is free to
        request a subset of services offered by the agent domain. This allows the same
        authentication service to be used by restricted clients (for instance, a group-chat
        only client) as well as traditional 3d viewers.</t>

      </section>

      <section title="Text and Voice Chat">

	<t>Virtual worlds are social spaces; efficent communication between users is a
	critical component of the virtual world experience. VWRAP virtual worlds support four
	types of text communication:

	  <list style="hanging" hangIndent="4">

	    <t hangText="1. User to User">Akin to traditional "instant message" systems,
	    User-to-User Text Chat includes two participants, the sender and the receiver.</t>

	    <t hangText="2. Group">Group Text Chat is the process of delivering text messages
	    to members of a pre-defined group. Group Text Chat groups are frequently defined
	    by an external authority and have a well known name, discoverable by a search
	    function.</t>

	    <t hangText="3. Ad Hoc Group">Ad Hoc Group Text Chat involves delivering text
	    message to a group created in an ad-hoc fashion. Membership in an Ad Hoc Text
	    Chat group is defined by the message sender. The group typically does not have
	    an externally locatable name.</t>

	    <t hangText="4. Proximal Chat">When a user "virtually" chats to an avatar near it
	    in the virtual world, it is making use of Proximal Chat. The endpoint for Proximal
	    Chat messages is a location in the virtual world rather than a particular usre or
	    group. Users whose avatars are within the proximity of the chatting user's avatar
	    will receive text chat from that user.</t>
	  </list></t>

	<t>Significant effort has been invested in developing protocols capable of efficiently
	deliverign textual information between users and groups. Protocols such as XMPP, SIMPLE
	and IRC may be used to carry text chat messages while VWRAP defined messages are used
	to establish and destroy text chat sessions.</t>

	<t>Though the protocols used to implement voice communication in the virtual world are
	no doubt different from those that carry text messages, the scenarios for voice
	communication mirror those of for text. Four types of voice chat exist: User-to-User,
	Group, Ad Hoc Group and Proximal.</t>

      </section>
        
      <section title="Agent Presence">

        <t>Once authenticated, the client application has established "agent presence." Once
        in possession of a valid seed capability, the client application may request a set of
        capabilities representing services offered by the agent domain: digital asset
        management, instant message and voice chat support as well as placing the user's
        avatar into the virtual world.</t>
          
        <t>Placing an avatar in the virtual world begins with the client exercising the "place
        my avatar in a region" capability. As part of this transaction, the client provides
        the URI representing a region. Upon receipt of this request, the agent domain
        determines the validity of the URL provided, and if the URL resolves to a trusted
        region domain begins the protocol between the agent domain and the region domain to
        place the user's avatar in the region.</t>
          
        <!-- todo: when the VWRAP Teleport specification is published, remember to put a reference to it here -->
          
        <t>The precise exchange of messages between each party is beyond the scope of this
        document, but is described in the VWRAP Teleport specification But a few important
        points should be noted:
          
        <list style="symbols">

          <t>The protocol endpoint used by the client application to place the user's avatar
          in a region is managed by the agent presence service and provided by the
          authentication service following successful authentication. It is not a publicly
          defined, fixed URL.</t>

          <t>Regions in VWRAP are represented with a URL. After authentication, the client
	  uses this URL to tell the agent presence service where to place the user's
	  avatar.</t>

          <t>The agent presence service MAY apply a local policy to the URI and reject the
          request before attempting to connect with a region. For instance, a "behind the
          firewall" agent presence service may limit clients to regions known to be hosted by
          systems inside the local intranet.</t>

          <t>The agent presence service MAY apply a local policy and reject the request after
          it makes an initial communication request with the remote region. (for example, if
          the region domain is operating servers with expired TLS certificates, or if those
          certificates are issued by a certifying authority the agent domain does not trust,
          it may reject the request.)</t>

          <t>The process of placing the avatar in the region results in capabilities from the
          region being communicated back to the agent presence service and the client
          application.  These capabilities are used to by the client to control the user's
          avatar and to access region-specific services.</t>

          <t>The process also results in the agent presence service issuing capabilities to
          the region, allowing it limited access to information about the avatar such as the
          avatar's shape and appearance.</t>
        </list>        
        </t>
          
        <t>After an avatar is "placed" or "rezzed" in a region, the agent presence service is
        responsible for maintaining it's presence in a single location. That is to say, after
        the avatar has been successfully been placed in a region, the agent presence service
        MUST refuse to allow a second region to "take" the avatar's presence without removing
        the avatar from its current region.</t>
        
	<section title="Moving Presence">

          <t>When an avatar moves between regions, special care must be taken that the agent
          presence service and both the source and destination regions agree where avatar is
          located.</t>

          <t>Moving between regions is typically initiated by the client. The process is
          largely the same as the initial avatar placement, but with the important added step
          of removing the avatar from it's source location before rezzing it in it's
          destination. (In fact, the initial placement of an avatar can be thought of as a
          transfer from "nowhere.")</t>
        
          <!-- todo: when the teleport spec is published, add a reference to it here -->
        
	  <t>The process of moving between regions is described in the VWRAP Teleport
          specification, thought implementers should keep the following important
          considerations in mind:
          
            <list style="symbols">
          
	      <t>The client signals to the agent presence service it's desire to move from one
              region to another by accessing the same capability as is used for initial
              placement of the avatar.</t>

              <t>The agent presence service must again check that local policy allows movement
              to the new destination, and MUST receive a capability for placing the client
              into the new region before it removes the avatar from it's current location.</t>

              <t>The agent presence service MUST also remove the avatar from it's current
              location before placing the avatar in the destination location. Capabilities
              granted to the current region MUST be revoked as part of this process.</t>

              <t>The location of the avatar MUST be unambiguous and the agent presence service
              MUST NOT represent the avatars location as being in two places at once. If
              required, for the short period between removing the avatar from one region and
              placing it in another, the avatar's location may be "in transit."</t>
            </list>
	  </t>
        </section>
      </section>

    <section title="Digital Asset Access">

      <t>The virtual world is filled with virtual objects: conference tables, houses,
      airships, dragons, etc. These objects may or may not be instantiated in the virtual
      world. Digital descriptions of objects to be placed in the virtual world should be made
      available to clients by way of the "Asset Access Protocol." Services that wish to
      display or manipulate digital assets query servers using this protocol.</t>

      <t>The asset access protocol defined in VWRAP differs significantly from legacy
      protocols defined by previous virtual world systems. It has been designed to more easily
      integrate existing collections of digital assets using standard protocols such as
      HTTP. All assets used by VWRAP, including avatar meshes, scene graphs and virtual object
      descriptions are accessed using this protocol.</t>

      <section title="Manipulating Digital Assets">
      
	<t>A number of useful manipulations of digital assets "at rest" are defined by VWRAP.
        Where appropriate, asset metadata may be altered by directly communicating with the
        network host with authority for that asset. This host may be part of the user's agent
        domain, or in the case of region-specific assets, it could be associated with a region
        domain. It is important to note, however, that not all metadata is modifiable by all
        users, even the asset's owner. Specifically, the semantics of the creator metadata do
        not allow the owner to change the creator's identity. Group membership may carry some
        rights like the ability to manipulate the size, shape and texture of an asset, but not
        an asset's owner.</t>
          
        <t>The ability to access or manipulate digital assets is based on the accessor's
        identity. Accessing and manipulating digital assets is performed via capabilities
        which expose the state of the asset to an authorized client. This requires positive
        identification of the accessor prior to access. In the case where an asset service is
        owned by the same authority as the authentication service, this access may be as
        simple as providing the proper capability after user authentication. In cases where
        the asset service is owned by a different authority, systems for deferred
        authentication may be necessary. Work is currently underway to integrate OAuth and
        SAML into VWRAP for this purpose.</t>
          
        <t>At a gross level, the types of resources exposed by a digital asset server would
        include:
 
          <list style="symbols">

            <t>a resource for searching an agent's inventory</t>
	    
            <t>a resource for iterating across an agent's inventory</t>

            <t>a resource for accessing or manipulating a digital asset's metadata</t>

            <t>a resource for uploading new digital assets, or changes to an existing
            asset.</t>
	    
            <t>a resource for removing a digital asset from the authority of the asset
            service</t>
	    
            <t>a resource for transferring the asset or a copy of the asset to a remote asset
            service</t>

            <t>a resource for instantiating (or "rezzing") an object "in world"</t>

          </list>
	</t>  
      </section>
        
      <section title="Establishing Presence for Digital Assets">
      
	<t>Digital assets are intended to be used "in world," meaning there must be a way for
        a user to direct a simulation host to take an asset from an asset store and imbue it
        with presence in the virtual world. The separation between agent based services and
        region based services is fundamental to VWRAP and implies the authority for the system
        maintaining the asset "at rest" may be distinct from that which simulates the asset
        "in world." In practical terms, a region simulator may need to communicate with an
        asset server owned by a different person or company. In situations like this, trust is
        paramount. Because an asset's metadata may limit the owner's right to make copies of
        an asset, the agent domain MUST be able to trust the region domain will honor that
        metadata.</t>
          
        <t>There are two levels of trust defined when working with digital assets: host-based
        trust and user-based trust. The former represents one system's expectation that the
        other will honor the metadata regarding ownership, creatorship and rights and
        restrictions implied by these concepts.  Host based trust is carried by X.509 / PKIX
        certificates and implies a managed PKI. User-based trust represents the expectation
        the asset server will expose sensitive resources only to users with the right to
        access such resources.</t>
          
        <t>Provided trust is established between the asset server and a simulation host, and
        the simulation host can demonstrate it is acting on behalf of a user with rights to
        access a particular resource, VWRAP defines a protocol for transferring a
        representation of the digital asset for simulation. As part of this protocol, access
        to a digital asset may be restricted while the object exists "in world." This is the
        case for objects whose creators or owners specify that only one copy of the asset may
        exist at a time.</t>

      </section>
  
    </section>

    </section>

    <section title="Security Considerations">

      <t>As mentioned previously, the concept of a persistent, ubiquitous identity in the
      virtual world is core to the user experience. Keeping agent based services distinct
      from region or object based services has advantages for scalability and flexibility.
      However, it does have ramifications for the security of the virtual world as a whole.</t>
      
      <t>Most notably, this structure puts the authentication service in the role of a trust
      broker.  As the authentication service must collect capabilities for the benefit of the
      client, is trusted by both client applications and peer services. A transitive trust
      relationship exists between the peer services and end users by way of the authentication
      service.  The administrators of peer services trust the authentication service to
      properly identify end users, and potentially to ensure they are members of a particular
      class. The end users trust the authentication service to properly identify peer services
      and to limit the transfer of digital assets to only those entities that explicitly agree
      to honor asset permissions meta-data.</t>
      
      <t>VWRAP does not REQUIRE services to adhere to any preset policy, however. It instead
      provides a mechanism for communicating identity information so that such a policy MAY be
      enforced.</t>
      
      <section anchor="Capabilities" title="Capabilities">

        <t>VWRAP makes extensive use of RESTful resources accessed via HTTP. Application state
        is communicated and changed by accessing web based resources. One characteristic of
        such resources is they have a well defined URL, many of which are formatted as 
        URL-based capabilities. <xref target="I-D.lentczner-vwrap-foundation"/> Capabilities have
        the characteristic that possession of the URL implies the right to access the resource
        it identifies. It is important that capability URLs are shared only with trusted
        participants. The VWRAP Base document defines the characteristics of URL-based capabilities,
        including the requirement that they include an unpredictable random component in the URL.
        Implementers need also ensure that these URLs are protected using suitable mechanisms
        (such as TLS, IPSec or link encryption.)</t>
      </section>
      
      <section title="User Authentication">
        <t>Prior to granting an end user access to sensitive resources, the client MUST be
        authenticated. The VWRAP Authentication specification defines three techniques for
        using shared secrets to authenticate end users. The agent_login resource used for end
        user authentication provides an extensible mechanism, allowing the development and use
        of additional authentication techniques (SRP, TLS Client Certificates, SASL, etc.)</t>
        
        <t>Again, it should be noted that VWRAP as currently defined does not REQUIRE an
        authentication service to support a particular authentication scheme (shared secret,
        public key, secure remote password, etc.) But it does define the mechanism for three
        shared secret options.</t>
        
        <t>Once a user is successfully authenticated, their client application is passed a seed
        capability (as described in the VWRAP Base specification.) This seed capability is used by
        the client application to request access to resources and services managed by the agent
        domain (including services like "place my avatar in the virtual world.")</t>
      </section>

      <!-- todo: when the x.509 profile doc is written, add a reference to it here -->

      <section title="Service to Service Authentication">
        <t>Authenticating one service to another uses an X.509 PKI. Prior to communicating,
        the originating service generates a key pair for each host under their control and
        requests a certificate from each the peer service with which they wish to
        interact. The peer service returns a signed certificate the originating service uses
        in subsequent communication with the region.</t>
      </section>
      
      <section title="Access Control for Digital Assets">
        <t>In addition to security characteristics addressing traditional network and user security
        issues, the raison d'tre of VWRAP is to communicate state concerning items inhabiting a
        virtual world. Some of these items may have access control restrictions within the scope of
        the applications used to simulate and render the virtual world. VWRAP defines an extensible
        permissions model which allows permissions meta-data to be associated with virtual items.</t>
      </section>

    </section>

    <section title="Accessibility Considerations">

      <t>This document makes extensive reference to the visual properties of objects. It is
      important to note that semantic cues may be more important to persons with visual
      deficits. The VWRAP suite includes the ability to annotate objects with situaltional or
      semantic meta-data to provide a meaningful experience to non-sighted users. Implementers
      are are encouraged to consider that client applications favored by non-blind users may
      query the state of the virtual world differently; the VWRAP suite SHOULD be sufficently
      expressive to support multiple modes of interaction with the virtual world.</t>

      <t>Implementers are also encouraged to consider the wide range of human capability and
      to design interaction experiences applicable to all.</t>

    </section>

    <section title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>This memo includes no request to IANA.</t>
    </section>

  </middle>

  <!--  *****BACK MATTER ***** -->

  <back>
    <!-- References split into informative and normative -->

    <!-- There are 2 ways to insert reference entries from the citation libraries:
     1. define an ENTITY at the top, and use "ampersand character"RFC2629; here (as shown)
     2. simply use a PI "less than character"?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119.xml"?> here
        (for I-Ds: include="reference.I-D.narten-iana-considerations-rfc2434bis.xml")

     Both are cited textually in the same manner: by using xref elements.
     If you use the PI option, xml2rfc will, by default, try to find included files in the same
     directory as the including file. You can also define the XML_LIBRARY environment variable
     with a value containing a set of directories to search.  These can be either in the local
     filing system or remote ones accessed by http (http://domain/dir/... ).-->

    <references title="Normative References">
      <!--?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"?-->
      &RFC2119;

      &I-D.hamrick-vwrap-type-system;
      &I-D.lentczner-vwrap-foundation;
      &I-D.hamrick-vwrap-authentication;

    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <!-- Here we use entities that we defined at the beginning. -->

      &RFC1822;
      
      &RFC2616;

      &RFC2817;
      
      &RFC3986;

    </references>

    <section title="Definitions of Important Terms">
      <t>
        <list  hangIndent="4" style="hanging">
          <t>agent domain<vspace blankLines="1"/>The agent domain is the administrative
          authority responsible for managing services related to avatars and users. Identity
          management, group membership, avatar appearance, profile information, user
          authentication and group messaging are examples of services and information
          maintained by the agent domain.</t>
          
          <t>agent host<vspace blankLines="1"/>A network host maintained by the agent domain
          is called an "agent host."</t>
         
          <t>avatar<vspace blankLines="1"/>The avatar is the representation of a user in
          the virtual world. The avatar's shape and appearance are used by other users to
          render a graphical representation of the inhabited virtual world. The user's
          view of the virtual world is rendered from the perspective of their avatar.</t>
          <t>client application<vspace blankLines="1"/>A client application is any application
          that is operated for the benefit of the user. Common client applications might
          include a "viewer" that renders the virtual world on the user's workstation or a
          web application used to manipulate the user's digital assets. VWRAP does not provide
          a canonical list of client application categories, but if an application is not
          a part of an agent domain or a region domain and it is manipulating user data or
          an avatar on behalf of a user, with the user's permission, it is a client
          application.</t>
          <t>region domain<vspace blankLines="1"/>The region domain is the administrative
          authority responsible for managing services related to presence in the virtual
          world and it's simulation. Typical services exposed by a region domain would
          include physics simulation, avatar presence and virtual object presence lifecycle management (i.e. -
          the creation, manipulation and destruction of objects in the virtual world.)</t>
          <t>region host<vspace blankLines="1"/>A network host maintained by the region domain
          is called a "region host", though the historical term "simulator" is still very
          common.</t>
          <t>user<vspace blankLines="1"/>The entity controlling an avatar in world is the
            "user".
          </t>
        </list>
      </t>
    </section>
    
    <section title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>The author gratefully acknowledges the contributions of:
        Mark Lentczner,
        David Levine,
        David Crocker,
        Larry Mastiner,
        Joshua Bell,
        Barry Leiba,
	Kevin Flynn,
	Morgaine Dinova,
        Joe Hildebrand,
	Lora Baines,
	Alan Bradley,
        Chris Newman,
        Katherine Mancuso
        and Jon Peterson.
      </t>
    </section>

  </back>
</rfc>
