<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629-fixed.xslt' ?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY RFC2119 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
<!ENTITY ADDARCH SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3513.xml">
<!ENTITY GLOBAL SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3587.xml">
<!ENTITY ICMPv6 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4443.xml">
<!ENTITY IPv6 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2460.xml">
<!ENTITY NTP SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1305.xml">
<!ENTITY RANDOM SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4086.xml">
<!ENTITY SHA1 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3174.xml">
<!ENTITY ULA SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4193.xml">
<!ENTITY FIPS SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml2/reference.FIPS.180-1.1995.xml">
]>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="no"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<?rfc iprnotified="no" ?>
<?rfc strict="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc colonspace='yes' ?>
<rfc category="info" docName="draft-kirkham-private-ip-sp-cores-01"
     ipr="trust200902" obsoletes="None" submissionType="IETF" updates=""
     xml:lang="en">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="private-ip-sp-cores">Issues with Private IP Addressing in
    the Internet</title>

    <author fullname="Anthony Kirkham" initials="A." surname="Kirkham">
      <organization>Cisco Systems</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Level 12</street>

          <street>300 Adeliade St</street>

          <city>Brisbane</city>

          <region>Queensland</region>

          <code>4000</code>

          <country>Australia</country>
        </postal>

        <phone>+61 7 32388203</phone>

        <email>tkirkham@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date day="3" month="October" year="2010" />

    <abstract>
      <t>The purpose of this document is to provide a discussion of the
      potential problems of using private, RFC1918, or non-globally-routable
      addressing within the core of an SP network. The discussion focuses on
      link addresses and to a small extent loopback addresses. While many of
      the issues are well recognised within the ISP community, there appears
      to be no document that collectively describes the issues.</t>
    </abstract>

    <note title="Legal">
      <t>This documents and the information contained therein are provided on
      an "AS IS" basis and THE CONTRIBUTOR, THE ORGANIZATION HE/SHE REPRESENTS
      OR IS SPONSORED BY (IF ANY), THE INTERNET SOCIETY, THE IETF TRUST AND
      THE INTERNET ENGINEERING TASK FORCE DISCLAIM ALL WARRANTIES, EXPRESS OR
      IMPLIED, INCLUDING BUT NOT LIMITED TO ANY WARRANTY THAT THE USE OF THE
      INFORMATION THEREIN WILL NOT INFRINGE ANY RIGHTS OR ANY IMPLIED
      WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY OR FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.</t>
    </note>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction" toc="default">
      <t>In the mid to late 90's, some Internet Service Providers (ISPs)
      adopted the practice of utilising private IP (i.e. RFC1918) addresses
      for the infrastructure links and in some cases the loopback interfaces
      within their networks. The reasons for this approach centered on
      conservation of address space (i.e. scarcity of routeable IPv4 address
      space), and security of the core network (also known as core
      hiding).</t>

      <t>However, a number of technical and operational issues occurred as a
      result of using non-routable IP addresses, and as a result, virtually
      all these ISPs moved away from the practice. Tier 1 ISPs are considered
      the benchmark of the industry and today there is no known tier 1 ISP
      that utilises the practice of private addressing within their core
      network.</t>

      <t>The following sections will discuss the various issues (and potential
      issues) associated with deploying private IP (i.e. RFC1918) addresses
      within ISP core networks.</t>

      <t>The intent of this document is not to suggest that private IP can not
      be used with the core of an SP network as some providers use this
      practice and operate successfully. The intent is to outline the
      potential issues or effects of such a practice.</t>

      <t>Note: The practice of ISPs using ‘stolen’ address space has many of
      the same issues (or effects) as that of using private IP address space
      within core networks. The term “stolen IP address space” refers to the
      practice of an ISP using address space for its own infrastructure/core
      network addressing that has been officially allocated by IANA (or an
      RIR) to another provider but that that provider is not currently using
      or advertising within the Internet. Stolen addressing is not discussed
      further in this document. It is simply noted as an associated issue.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Conservation of Address Space">
      <t>One of the original intents for the use of private IP addressing
      within an ISP core was the conservation of routeable IP address space.
      When an ISP is allocated a block of routeable IP addresses (from IANA or
      an RIR), this address block was traditionally split in order to dedicate
      some portion for infrastructure use (i.e. for the core network), and the
      other portion for customer (subscriber) or other address pool use.
      Typically, the number of infrastructure addresses needed is relatively
      small in comparison to the total address count. So unless the ISP was
      only granted a small routable block, dedicating some portion to
      infrastructure links and loopback addresses (/32) is rarely a large
      enough issue to outweigh the problems that are potentially caused when
      the private address space is used as being discussed.</t>

      <t>Additionally, specifications and equipment capability improvements
      now allow for the use of /31s [RFC3021] for link addresses in place of
      the original /30s – further minimises the impact of dedicating routeable
      addresses to infrastructure links by only using two (2) ip address per
      point to point link versus four (4) respectively.</t>

      <t>The use of private or RFC1918 addressing as a conservation technique
      within an Internet Service Provider (ISP) core can cause a number of
      technical and operational issues or effects. The main effects are
      described next.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Breaks Traceroute">
      <t>The single biggest effect with the use of private (RFC1918)
      addressing within an Internet core is the fact that it can disrupt the
      operation of traceroute in some situations. This section provides some
      examples of the issues that can occur.</t>

      <t>Firstly, this general example below shows a traceroute across a
      network that uses privately numbered links. In this example, the string
      of " * * * " in hop numbers 19 to 21 is the result of private addresses
      used on those three links. The reasons for this effect are discussed
      following this example.</t>

      <figure>
        <artwork>
hostname% traceroute x.x.1.11
1  x.x.com (x.x.206.2)  1.081 ms  0.837 ms  0.780 ms
&lt;Part Deleted&gt;
18  x.x.227.82 (x.x.227.82)  213.039 ms  213.407 ms  213.161 ms
19  * * *
20  * * *
21  * * *
22  x.x.1.11 (x.x.1.11)  200.192 ms !X  198.465 ms !X  198.440 ms !X

</artwork>
      </figure>

      <t>Of more relevance is the situation where the traceroute crosses an AS
      boundary and one of the networks has utilised private addressing. The
      following simple network is used for illustrative purposes.</t>

      <figure>
        <artwork>

              AS100                 EBGP                AS200
                    IBGP Mesh &lt;---------------&gt;  IBGP Mesh
  Pool -                                                       Pool -
1.1.2.0/24                                                   2.1.2.0/24
                                 2.1.1.8/30

    10.1.1.0/30  10.1.1.4/30   .9          .10  2.1.1.4/30  2.1.1.0/30
    .1       .2  .5       .6    ------------    .6      .5  .2      .1
  R1-----------R2-----------R3--|          |--R4----------R5----------R6

10.1.1.1    10.1.1.2     10.1.1.3           2.1.1.3    2.1.1.2   2.1.1.1
Loopback Addresses shown at the bottom.

</artwork>
      </figure>

      <t>Using this example, performing the traceroute from AS200 to AS100, we
      can see the private addresses of the infrastructure links in AS100 are
      returned.</t>

      <figure>
        <artwork>
R6#traceroute 1.1.2.1
Type escape sequence to abort.
Tracing the route to 1.1.2.1

  1 2.1.1.2 40 msec 20 msec 32 msec
  2 2.1.1.6 16 msec 20 msec 20 msec
  3 2.1.1.9 20 msec 20 msec 32 msec
  4 10.1.1.5 20 msec 20 msec 20 msec
  5 10.1.1.1 20 msec 20 msec 20 msec 
R6#

</artwork>
      </figure>

      <t>While the previous example may not present a major problem, a
      potentially more severe case exists if the source IP address of the
      traceroute is within a privately numbered part of the network (AS100)
      and the destination is outside of the ISPs AS (AS200). In this situation
      the traceroute will fail completely beyond the AS boundary.</t>

      <figure>
        <artwork>
R1# traceroute 2.1.2.1
Type escape sequence to abort.
Tracing the route to 2.1.2.1

  1 10.1.1.2 20 msec 20 msec 20 msec
  2 10.1.1.6 52 msec 24 msec 40 msec
  3  *  *  * 
  4  *  *  * 
  5  *  *  * 
  6  *  *  *
R1#  

</artwork>
      </figure>

      <t>While it is completely unreasonable to expect a packet with a private
      source address to be successfully returned in a typical SP environment,
      the case is included to show the effect as it can have implications for
      troubleshooting. This case will be referenced in a later section.</t>

      <t>In a complex topology, with multiple paths and exit points from the
      AS, the provider will loose their ability to trace paths through the
      network to other ASs. Such a situation could be a severe troubleshooting
      impediment.</t>

      <t>It should be noted that some solutions to this problem have been
      proposed. They may utilise extensions to ICMP to allow the return of
      some "single public address" on the device, along with an interface
      identifier, possibly the SNMP ID of the interface. However at the time
      of writing, such a solution was not available.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Breaks Path MTU Discovery">
      <t>The Path MTU Discovery (PMTUD) process was designed to allow hosts to
      make an accurate assessment of the maximum size packets that can be sent
      across a path without fragmentation. Path MTU Discovery is supported for
      TCP (and other protocols that support PMTUD such as GRE and IPsec) and
      works as follows:</t>

      <t>• When a router attempts to forward an IP datagram with the Do Not
      Fragment (DF) bit set out a link that has a lower MTU than the size of
      the packet, the router MUST drop the packet and return an Internet
      Control Message Protocol (ICMP) 'destination unreachable - fragmentation
      needed and DF set (type 3, code 4)’ message to the source of the IP
      datagram. This message includes the MTU of that next-hop network. As a
      result, the source station which receives the ICMP message, will lower
      the send Maximum Segment Size (MSS).</t>

      <t>It is obviously desirable that packets be sent between two
      communicating hosts without fragmentation as this process imposes extra
      load on the fragmenting router (process of fragmentation), intermediate
      routers (forwarding additional packets), as well as the receiving host
      (reassembly of the fragmented packets). Additionally, many applications,
      including some web servers, set the DF (do not fragment) bit causing
      undesirable interactions if the path MTU is insufficient. Other TCP
      implementations may set an MTU size of 576 bytes if PMTUD is
      unavailable. In addition, IPsec and other tunneling protocols will often
      require MTUs greater than 1500 bytes and often rely on PMTUD.</t>

      <t>While it is uncommon these days for SP networks not to support a path
      MTUs in excess of 1500 bytes (with 4470 being common), the situation of
      1500 byte path MTUs may still exist in some networks.</t>

      <t>The issue is as follows:</t>

      <t>• When an ICMP Type 3 Code 4 message is issued from an infrastructure
      link that uses a private (RFC1918) address, it must be routed back to
      the originating host. As the originating host will typically be a
      globally routable IP address, its source address is used as the
      destination address of the returned ICMP Type 3 packet. At this point
      there are normally no problems.</t>

      <t>• As the returned packet will have an RFC1918 source address,
      problems can occur when the returned packet passes through an
      anti-spoofing security control (such as Unicast RPF (uRPF)), other
      anti-spoofing ACLs, or virtually any perimeter firewall. These devices
      will typically drop packets with an RFC1918 source address, breaking the
      successful operation of PMTUD.</t>

      <t>As a result, the potential for application level issues may be
      created.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Unexpected interactions with some NAT implementations">
      <t>Private addressing is legitimately used within many enterprise or
      corporate networks for internal network addressing. When users on the
      inside of the network require Internet access, they will typically
      connect through a perimeter router or firewall that provides Network
      Address Translation (NAT) services. Typical NAT deployments assume that
      the internal private address ranges will not exist outside of the
      internal environment.</t>

      <t>However unpredictable interactions could occur if traffic such as
      traceroute and PMTUD was launched from the NAT IPv4 ‘inside address’ and
      it passed over the same address range in the public IP core.</t>

      <t>The discussion may be further complicated with the transition to
      IPv6. Current discussions around the use of NAT444 and LSN (Large Scale
      NAT) would make use of a double NAT process. Within this scheme, another
      private address block (at the time of writing) is being requested for
      ISP NAT 444 so that ISP private backbone space would not conflict with
      customer private backbone space. Again, unpredictable interactions could
      occur if these address ranges conflicted with the ranges assigned in an
      Internet core.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Issues with edge anti-spoofing techniques">
      <t>Denial of service attacks and distributed denial of attacks can make
      use of spoofed source IP addresses in an attempt to obfuscate the source
      of an attack. RFC2827 (Network Ingress Filtering) strongly recommends
      that providers of Internet connectivity implement filtering to prevent
      packets using source addresses outside of their legitimately assigned
      and advertised prefix ranges. Such filtering should also prevent packets
      with private source addresses from egressing the AS.</t>

      <t>Best security practices for ISPs also strongly recommend that packets
      with illegitimate source addresses should be dropped at the AS
      perimeter. Illegitimate source addresses include private IP (RFC1918)
      addresses, addresses within the providers assigned prefix ranges, bogons
      (legitimate but unassigned IP addresses). Additionally, packets with
      private IP destinations addresses should also dropped at the AS
      perimeter.</t>

      <t>If such filtering is properly deployed, then traffic either sourced
      from, or destined for privately addressed portions of the network should
      be dropped. Hence the negative consequences on traceroute, PMTUD and
      regular ping type traffic.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Peering using loopbacks">
      <t>Although not a common technique, some ISPs use loopback addresses of
      border routers (ASBRs) for peering, in particular where multiple
      connections or exchange points exist between the two ISPs. Such a
      technique is used by some ISPs as the foundation of fine grained traffic
      engineering and load balancing through the combination of IGP metrics
      and multi-hop BGP (as opposed to the more common technique of local
      preference). When private or non-globally reachable addresses are used
      as loopback addresses, this technique is not possible.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="DNS Interaction">
      <t>Many ISPs utilise their DNS to perform both forward and reverse
      resolution for the infrastructure devices and infrastructure addresses.
      With a privately numbered core, the ISP itself will still have the
      capability to perform name resolution of their own infrastructure.
      However others outside of the autonomous system will not have this
      capability. At best, they will get a number of unidentified RFC1918 IP
      addresses returned from a traceroute.</t>

      <t>Such a situation can lead to complaints from parties or customers
      outside of the ISP.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Operational and Troubleshooting issues">
      <t>Previous sections of the document have noted issues relating to
      network operations and troubleshooting. In particular when private IP
      addressing within an ISP core is used, the ability to easily
      troubleshoot across the AS boundary may be limited. In some cases this
      may be a serious troubleshooting impediment. In other cases, it may be
      solved through the use of alternative troubleshooting techniques.</t>

      <t>The key point is that the flexibility of initiating an out bound ping
      or traceroute from a privately numbered section of the network is lost.
      In a complex topology, with multiple paths and exit points from the AS,
      the provider may be restricted in their ability to trace paths through
      the network to other ASs. Such a situation could be a severe
      troubleshooting impediment.</t>

      <t>For users outside of the AS, the loss of the ability to use a
      traceroute for troubleshooting is very often a serious issue. As soon as
      many of these people see a row of "* * *" in a traceroute they often
      incorrectly assume that a large part of the network is down or
      inaccessible (e.g. behind a firewall). Operational experience in many
      large providers has shown that significant confusion results. This
      translates directly into difficult (and potentially long and emotional)
      conversations with these users.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Security Arguments">
      <t>One of the arguments often put forward for the use of private
      addressing within an ISP is an improvement in the network security. It
      has been argued that if private addressing is used within the core, the
      network infrastructure becomes unreachable from outside the providers
      autonomous system, hence protecting the infrastructure. There is an
      element of legitimacy to this argument. Certainly if the core is
      privately numbered and unreachable, it potentially provides a level of
      isolation in addition to what can be achieved with other techniques such
      as infrastructure ACLs on their own. This is especially true in the
      event of an ACL misconfiguration, something that does commonly occur as
      the result of human error.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Issues with core network security">
      <t>There are a number of flaws to the argument of using private
      addressing for security.<list>
          <t>• The approach does not protect against reflection attacks. For
          example, if a packet with spoofed source address corresponding to
          the networks infrastructure address range, is sent to a host (or
          other device) attached to the network, that host will send its
          response directly to the infrastructure address. If such an attack
          was performed across a large number of hosts, then a successful
          large scale denial of service attack on the infrastructure could be
          achieved. This is not to say that a publicly numbered core will
          protect from the same attack, it won’t. The key point is that a
          reflection attack does get around the apparent security offered in a
          privately addressed core.</t>

          <t>Even if anti-spoofing is deployed at the AS boundary, the border
          routers will potentially carry routing information for the privately
          addressed network infrastructure. This can mean that packets with
          spoofed addresses, corresponding to the private infrastructure
          addressing, may be considered legitimate by edge anti-spoofing
          techniques such as Unicast Reverse Path Forwarding – Loose Mode, and
          forwarded. To avoid this situation, an edge anti-spoofing algorithm
          such as Unicast Reverse Path Forwarding – Strict Mode, would be
          required. However, such an approach can be problematic in an
          environment where asymmetric traffic paths exist. Alternatively,
          access control lists to block packets with private or RFC1918 source
          addresses could be used.</t>

          <t>• Additionally, in cases where distributed denial of service
          attacks make use of spoofed source addresses large amounts of
          backscatter traffic can be produced. Backscatter traffic is returned
          from hosts, etc when the received packet contained a spoofed source
          address. That traffic, or an ICMP destination unreachable messages
          are sent to an incorrect party as it was assumed to be the
          legitimate source address, which it wasn’t.</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>If the core network is privately numbered, then that backscatter
      traffic may be received by infrastructure devices. As backscatter
      traffic is very common on the Internet, the amount of backscatter
      traffic received by the control and management planes of the network
      infrastructure devices could be significant. Figures in the order of
      hundreds of MBits/s have occurred in some networks. Without suitable
      protection, the network infrastructure devices could be negatively
      impacted in such a situation, in particular if the spoofed address range
      corresponded with the private address range used to number the core.
      Again, a publicly numbered core does not protect from this issue. …but
      is likely to be less of a problem due to the wider address sizes.???</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Alternate approaches to core network security">
      <t>Today, hardware-based ACLs, which have minimal to no performance
      impact, are now widespread. Applying an ACL at the AS perimeter to
      prevent access to the network core may be a far simpler approach and
      provide comparable protection to using private addressing, Such a
      technique is known as an infrastructure ACL (iACL).</t>

      <t>In concept, iACLs provide filtering at the edge network which allows
      traffic to cross the network core, but not to terminate on
      infrastructure addresses within the core. Proper iACL deployment will
      normally allow required network management traffic to be passed, such
      that traceroutes and PMTUD can still operate successfully. For an iACL
      deployment to be practical, the core network needs to have been
      addressed with a relatively small number of contiguous address blocks.
      For this reason, the technique may or may not be practical.</t>

      <t>The other approach to preventing external access to the core is IS-IS
      core hiding. This technique makes use of a fundamental property of the
      IS-IS protocol which allows link addresses to be removed from the
      routing table while still allowing loopback addresses to be resolved as
      next hops for BGP. The technique prevents parties outside the AS from
      being able to route to infrastructure addresses, while still allowing
      traceroutes to operate successfully. IS-IS core hiding does not have the
      same practical requirement for the core to be addressed from a small
      number of contiguous address blocks as with iACLs.</t>

      <t>These techniques may not be suitable for every network, however,
      there are many circumstances where they can be used successfully without
      the associated issues of privately addressing the core.</t>

      <t>MPLS VPN - Yet to be written.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Security Considerations">
      <t>None</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <reference anchor="RFC1918">
        <front>
          <title>RFC1918 Address Allocation for Private Internets, BCP
          5</title>

          <author initials="Y" surname="Rekhter ">
            <organization>Cisco Systems</organization>
          </author>

          <author initials="R" surname="Moskowitz">
            <organization>Chrysler Corporation</organization>
          </author>

          <author initials="D" surname="Karrenberg">
            <organization>RIPE Network Coordination Centre</organization>
          </author>

          <author initials="G" surname="Jan de Groot">
            <organization>RIPE Network Coordination Centre</organization>
          </author>

          <author initials="E" surname="Lear ">
            <organization>Silicon Graphics, Inc.</organization>
          </author>

          <date month="Febuary " year="1996" />
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RFC2728">
        <front>
          <title>RFC 2827 Network Ingress Filtering, BCP 38</title>

          <author initials="P" surname="Ferguson">
            <organization>Cisco Systems, Inc.</organization>
          </author>

          <author initials="D" surname="Senie ">
            <organization>Amaranth Networks Inc.</organization>
          </author>

          <date month="May" year="2000" />
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="NANOG">
        <front>
          <title>Various Nanog mail archives</title>

          <author>
            <organization>Various</organization>
          </author>

          <date />
        </front>
      </reference>
    </references>

    <section title="Acknowledgments">
      <t>The author would like to thank the following people for their input
      and review – Dan Wing (Cisco Systems), Roland Dobbins (Arbor Networks),
      Philip Smith (Cisco Systems), Barry Greene (Juniper Networks), Anton
      Ivanov (kot-begemot.co.uk), Ryan Mcdowell (Cisco Systems), Russ White
      (Cisco Systems), Gregg Schudel (Cisco Systems), Michael Behringer (Cisco
      Systems).</t>
    </section>
  </back>
</rfc>
