<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="rfc2629.xslt" ?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd"> 

<?rfc toc="yes"?>

<?rfc strict="yes"?>

<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>

<?rfc compact="yes"?>

<?rfc subcompact="no"?>

<?rfc tocdepth="2"?>

<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>

<?rfc comments="yes" ?>

<!--<?rfc rfcedstyle="yes"?>-->

<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>



<!-- noModification3978 -->

<rfc category="bcp" ipr="trust200811" docName="draft-vegoda-cotton-rfc5735bis-03" obsoletes="5735">

<front>

        <title abbrev="Special Use IPv4 Addresses">

	Special Use IPv4 Addresses 

</title>

       
<author initials="M." surname="Cotton" fullname="Michelle Cotton">

	<organization abbrev="ICANN">

		Internet Corporation for Assigned Names and Numbers

	</organization>

	<address>

		<postal>

			<street>12025 Waterfront Drive, Suite 300</street>

			<code>90094-2536</code> <city>Los Angeles, CA</city>

			<country>United States of America</country>

		</postal>

		<phone>+310-823-9358</phone>

		<email>michelle.cotton@icann.org</email>

		<uri>

			http://www.icann.org/

		</uri>

	</address>

</author>

        <author initials="L." surname="Vegoda" fullname="Leo Vegoda">
                
                <organization abbrev="ICANN">
                        
                        Internet Corporation for Assigned Names and Numbers
                        
                </organization>
                
                <address>
                        
                        <postal>
                                
                                <street>12025 Waterfront Drive, Suite 300</street>
                                
                                <code>90094-2536</code> <city>Los Angeles, CA</city>
                                
                                <country>United States of America</country>
                                
                        </postal>
                        
                        <phone>+310-823-9358</phone>
                        
                        <email>leo.vegoda@icann.org</email>
                        
                        <uri>
                                
                                http://www.icann.org/
                                
                        </uri>
                        
                </address>
                
        </author>
        
<date month="August" year="2012"/>

<keyword>special</keyword>

<keyword>addresses</keyword>

<keyword>ipv4</keyword>

<abstract>

        <t>
 
This document describes the global and other specialized IPv4 address 
blocks that have been assigned by the Internet Assigned Numbers Authority 
(IANA).  It does not address IPv4 address space assigned to operators and 
users through the Regional Internet Registries, nor does it address IPv4 
address space assigned directly by IANA prior to the creation of the Regional 
Internet Registries.  It also does not address allocations or assignments of 
IPv6 addresses or autonomous system numbers. This document obsoletes RFC 5735 
and updates RFC 6441. 

	</t>

<t>

The substantive change between this document and RFC 5735 is that it includes 
100.64.0.0/10, which was assigned in RFC 6598. 
	
</t>

</abstract>

</front>



<middle>

<section title="Introduction">

    <t>

Throughout its history, the Internet has employed a 
central Internet Assigned Numbers Authority (IANA) responsible 
for the allocation and assignment of various identifiers needed 
for the operation of the Internet <xref target="RFC1174"/>.  In the 
case of the IPv4 address space, the IANA allocates parts of the 
address space to Regional Internet Registries (RIRs) according to their 
established needs.  These RIRs are responsible for the registration 
of IPv4 addresses to operators and users of the Internet within 
their regions.

    </t>

    <t>
                
On an ongoing basis, IANA assignmnets have been made using policies 
established by the IETF to support the Internet Standards Process 
described in Section 4 of <xref target="RFC2860"/>.
                
     </t>

     <t>

Small portions of the IPv4 address space have been allocated or
assigned directly by the IANA for global or other specialized
purposes.  These allocations and assignments have been 
documented in a variety of RFCs and other documents.  This 
document is intended to collect these scattered references and 
provide a current list of special use IPv4 addresses.

</t>

   <t>
                
 This document is a revision of RFC 5735 <xref target="RFC5735"/>, which it
 obsoletes; its primary purpose is to reflect the changes to the list of special
 IPv4 assignments since the publication of RFC 5735. It is a companion to <xref target="RFC5156"/> 
 which describes special IPv6 addresses.

        </t>

 </section>

<section title="Global and Other Specialized Address Blocks">

	<t>

		   0.0.0.0/8 - Addresses in this block refer to source hosts on "this"
		   network.  Address 0.0.0.0/32 may be used as a source address for 
		   this host on this network; other addresses within 0.0.0.0/8 may be
		   used to refer to specified hosts on this network <xref target="RFC1122"/>, section 3.2.1.3.

	</t>


	<t>
		   10.0.0.0/8 - This block is set aside for use in
		   private networks.  Its intended use is documented
		   in <xref target="RFC1918"/>. As described in that
	           RFC, addresses within this block do not legitimately appear
		   on the public Internet. These addresses can be used
		   without any coordination with IANA or an Internet
		   registry.

	</t>

	<t>

		   127.0.0.0/8 - This block is assigned for use as the
		   Internet host loopback address.  A datagram sent by
		   a higher level protocol to an address anywhere
		   within this block loops back inside the host.
		   This is ordinarily implemented using only
		   127.0.0.1/32 for loopback.  As described in
		   <xref target="RFC1122"/>, Section 3.2.1.3,
		   addresses within the entire 127.0.0.0/8 block do
		   not legitimately appear on any network anywhere.

	</t>

<t>
        100.64.0.0/10 - This block is used as Shared Address Space. 
        <xref target="RFC6598"/> states that Shared Address 
        Space can only be used in Service Provider networks or on routing 
        equipment that is able to do address translation across router  
        interfaces when addresses are identical on two different interfaces.
</t>

	<t>

		   169.254.0.0/16 - This is the "link local" block.  As described in 
	           <xref target="RFC3927"/>, it is allocated for communication between hosts 
	           on a single link.  Hosts obtain these addresses by auto-configuration, such 
	           as when a DHCP server cannot be found.

	</t>


	<t>
		   172.16.0.0/12 - This block is set aside for use in
		   private networks.  Its intended use is documented
		   in <xref target="RFC1918"/>.  As described in that
	           RFC, addresses within this block do not legitimately appear
		   the public Internet. These addresses can be used
		   without any coordination with IANA or an Internet
		   registry.
	</t>

        <t>
                   192.0.0.0/24 - This block is reserved for IETF protocol assignments.
		   At the time of writing this document, there are no current assignments.
		   Allocation policy for future assignments is given in <xref target="RFC5736"/>.
        </t>

	<t>

		   192.0.2.0/24 - This block is assigned as
		   "TEST-NET-1" for use in documentation and example
		   code.  It is often used in conjunction with domain
		   names example.com or example.net in vendor and
		   protocol documentation.  As described in
	           <xref target="RFC5737"/>, addresses within this
	           block do not legitimately appear on the public Internet and can
		   be used without any coordination with IANA or an
		   Internet registry. See <xref target="RFC1166"/>.

	</t>


	<t>

		192.88.99.0/24 - This block is allocated for use as
		6to4 relay anycast addresses, in to
		<xref target="RFC3068"/>. In contrast with previously
		described blocks, packets destined to addresses from
		this block do appear in the public
		Internet. <xref target="RFC3068"/>, Section 7
		describes operational practices to prevent the
		malicious use of this block in routing protocols.

	</t>


	<t>

		   192.168.0.0/16 - This block is set aside for use in
		   private networks. Its intended use is documented in
		   <xref target="RFC1918"/>.  As described in that
	           RFC, addresses within this block do not legitimately appear
		   the public Internet. These addresses can be used
		   without any coordination with IANA or an Internet
		   registry.

	</t>


	<t>

		   198.18.0.0/15 - This block has been allocated for use in benchmark
		   tests of network interconnect devices.  <xref target="RFC2544"/> explains
	           that this range was assigned to minimize the chance of conflict in case a 
	           testing device were to be accidentally connected to part of the Internet.
	           Packets with source addresses from this range are not meant to be 
	           forwarded across the Internet.

	</t>

        <t>
                
                198.51.100.0/24 - This block is assigned as
                "TEST-NET-2" for use in documentation and example
                code.  It is often used in conjunction with domain
                names example.com or example.net in vendor and
                protocol documentation.  As described in
                <xref target="RFC5737"/>, addresses within this
                block do not legitimately appear on the public Internet and can
                be used without any coordination with IANA or an
                Internet registry.
                
        </t>

        <t>
                
                203.0.113.0/24 - This block is assigned as
                "TEST-NET-3" for use in documentation and example
                code.  It is often used in conjunction with domain
                names example.com or example.net in vendor and
                protocol documentation.  As described in
                <xref target="RFC5737"/>, addresses within this
                block do not legitimately appear on the public Internet and can
                be used without any coordination with IANA or an
                Internet registry.
                
        </t>

	<t>
		   224.0.0.0/4 - This block, formerly known as the Class D address
		   space, is allocated for use in IPv4 multicast address assignments.
		   The IANA guidelines for assignments from this space are described in
		   <xref target="RFC5771"/>.

	</t>


	<t>
		   240.0.0.0/4 - This block, formerly known as the
		   Class E address space, is reserved for future use,
		   see <xref target="RFC1112"/>, section 4.

		   <vspace blankLines='1'/>

		   The one exception to this is the "limited
		   broadcast" destination address 255.255.255.255. As
		   described in <xref target="RFC0919"/> and
		   <xref target="RFC0922"/>, packets with this
		   destination address are not forwarded at IP layer.

	</t>

</section>



<section title="Summary Table">

	<figure><artwork>

  Address Block       Present Use                Reference
  ------------------------------------------------------------------
  0.0.0.0/8           "This" Network             RFC 1122, sect 3.2.1.3
  10.0.0.0/8          Private-Use Networks       RFC 1918
  100.64.0.0/10       Shared Address Space       RFC 6598
  127.0.0.0/8         Loopback                   RFC 1122, sect 3.2.1.3
  169.254.0.0/16      Link Local                 RFC 3927 
  172.16.0.0/12       Private-Use Networks       RFC 1918
  192.0.0.0/24        IETF Protocol Assignments  RFC 5736
  192.0.2.0/24        TEST-NET-1                 RFC 5737
  192.88.99.0/24      6to4 Relay Anycast         RFC 3068
  192.168.0.0/16      Private-Use Networks       RFC 1918
  198.18.0.0/15       Network Interconnect
                        Device Benchmark Testing RFC 2544
  198.51.100.0/24     TEST-NET-2                 RFC 5737
  203.0.113.0/24      TEST-NET-3                 RFC 5737
  224.0.0.0/4         Multicast                  RFC 5771
  240.0.0.0/4         Reserved for Future Use    RFC 1112, sect 4
  255.255.255.255/32  Limited Broadcast          RFC 919, sect 7


	</artwork></figure>

</section>

<section title="IANA Considerations">

	<t>

This document describes the past and current practices, but does not create any new 
requirements for assignments or allocations by the IANA.

	</t>

</section>

		

<section title="Security Considerations">

		<t>

The particular assigned values of special use IPv4 addresses
cataloged in this document do not directly raise security issues.
However, the Internet does not inherently protect against abuse of
these addresses; if you expect (for instance) that all packets from 
a private address space such as the 10.0.0.0/8 block or the link 
local block 169.254.0.0/16 originate within your subnet, all 
routers at the border of your network should filter such packets 
that originate from outside your network. Attacks have been mounted 
that depend on the unexpected use of some of these addresses.

		</t>
        
        <t>
                
It should also be noted that some of these address blocks may be used 
legitimately outside of a single administrative domain, and may appear 
on the global Internet. Security policy should not blindly filter all 
of these address spaces without due consideration, and network operators 
are encouraged to review this document, and references contained therein, 
and determine what security policies should be associated with each of 
these address blocks within their specific operating environments.

        </t>

</section>



<section title="Acknowledgments">

		<t>

Many people have made comments on draft versions of this document.
The authors would especially like to thank Scott Bradner, Randy Bush,
Harald Alvestrand, Peter Koch, Alfred Hoenes, and Jari Arkko for
their constructive feedback and comments.  They would also like to
offer a special note of thanks to APNIC, which nominated
198.51.100.0/24 and 203.0.113.0/24.

		</t>

</section>

</middle>







    <!-- REFERENCE TEMPLATE

        <reference anchor="reference.XXX">

                <front>

                        <title>XXX</title>

                        <author initials="X." surname="XXX" fullname="XXX">

                                <organization abbrev="XXX">XXX</organization>

                                <address>

                                        <postal>

                                                <street>XXX</street>

                                                <city>XXX</city>

                                                <region>XXX</region>

                                                <code>XXX</code>

                                                <country>XXX</country>

                                        </postal>

                                        <phone>XXX</phone>

                                        <facsimile>XXX</facsimile>

                                        <email>XXX</email>

                                        <uri>XXX</uri>

                                </address>



                        </author>

                        <date month="XXX" year="XXX"/>

                </front>

                <seriesInfo name="XXX" value="XXX"/>

                <format type="XXX" target="XXX"/>                       

        </reference>

        -->





<back>


        <references title='Informative References'> 
          
        <?rfc include="reference.RFC.0919" ?>
                
        <?rfc include="reference.RFC.0922" ?>

        <?rfc include="reference.RFC.1112" ?>
        
        <?rfc include="reference.RFC.1122" ?>

        <?rfc include="reference.RFC.1166" ?>
                
        <?rfc include="reference.RFC.1174" ?>

	<?rfc include="reference.RFC.1918" ?>	

	<?rfc include="reference.RFC.2544" ?>

	<?rfc include="reference.RFC.2860" ?>

	<?rfc include="reference.RFC.3068" ?>

        <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3927" ?>
        
        <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5156" ?>
        
        <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5735" ?>

        <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5736" ?>
                
        <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5737" ?>

        <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5771" ?>
                
       <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6598" ?>
                

</references>
        
</back>

</rfc>

