<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>

<?rfc strict="no" ?>

<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>

<?rfc toc="yes" ?>

<rfc category="std" docName="draft-petithuguenin-mmusic-ice-attributes-level-00" ipr="noModificationTrust200902" updates="5245">
	<front>
		<title abbrev="Media level ICE attributes">Media level ice-options SDP attribute</title>

		<author fullname="Marc Petit-Huguenin" initials="M.P.H" surname="Petit-Huguenin">
			<organization>Stonyfish, Inc.</organization>

			<address>
				<email>petithug@acm.org</email>
			</address>
		</author>

		<date day="2" month="February" year="2011"/>

		<abstract>
			<t>
				This document redefines the ice-options SDP attribute as a session-level and media-level attribute.
			</t>
		</abstract>
	</front>

	<middle>
		<section title="Introduction">
			<t>
				<xref target="RFC5245">ICE</xref> defines the ice-options SDP attribute as session-level only attribute, but when ICE is used with disaggregated media (see section 3 of <xref target="I-D.loreto-splices-disaggregated-media"/>), there is a possibility that different media uses different ICE implementations and/or different networks, and so that differents media in the same SDP require different values for this attribute.
			</t>

			<t>
				As an example, the ice-options attribute value "rtp+ecn" (defined in <xref target="I-D.ietf-avtcore-ecn-for-rtp"/>) signals ECN capability.
				Two aggregated media using two different RTP implementations may want to use different values for this attribute.
			</t>

			<t>Note that there is a similar problem for the ice-lite attribute but unfortunately it does not seem possible to design a way to use the ice-lite attribute at the media level that is compatible with legacy implementations that recognize only the session-level attribute.</t>
		</section>

		<section title="Terminology">
			<t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED",  "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in <xref target="RFC2119"/>.</t>
		</section>

		<section title="ice-options Attribute">
			<t>The ice-options attribute is a session-level and media-level attribute.</t>

			<t>All future new ICE options must also defines how media-level ICE options using this new value are aggregated to eventually generate the value of the session-level ICE option, so legacy implementations that only recognize session-level ICE options can interoperate with implementations that recognize ICE options at both levels.</t>
		</section>

		<section title="rtp+ecn ICE option">
			<t>If all aggregated media contains the "rtp+ecn" ICE option defined by <xref target="I-D.ietf-avtcore-ecn-for-rtp"/>, then an "rtp+ecn" ICE option MUST be inserted at the session-level.</t>
		</section>

		<section title="Security Considerations">
			<t>TBD</t>
		</section>

		<section title="IANA Considerations">
			<t>TBD</t>
		</section>

		<section title="Acknowledgements">
			<t>This document was written with the xml2rfc tool described in <xref target="RFC2629"/>.</t>
		</section>
	</middle>

	<back>
		<references title="Normative References">
			<reference anchor="RFC2119">

<front>
<title abbrev="RFC Key Words">Key words for use in RFCs to Indicate Requirement Levels</title>
<author fullname="Scott Bradner" initials="S." surname="Bradner">
<organization>Harvard University</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street>1350 Mass. Ave.</street>
<street>Cambridge</street>
<street>MA 02138</street>
</postal>
<phone>- +1 617 495 3864</phone>
<email>sob@harvard.edu</email>
</address>
</author>
<date month="March" year="1997"/>
<area>General</area>
<keyword>keyword</keyword>
<abstract>
<t>
   In many standards track documents several words are used to signify
   the requirements in the specification.  These words are often
   capitalized.  This document defines these words as they should be
   interpreted in IETF documents.  Authors who follow these guidelines
   should incorporate this phrase near the beginning of their document:

<list>
<t>
      The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL
      NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED",  "MAY", and
      "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in
      RFC 2119.
</t>
</list>
</t>
<t>
   Note that the force of these words is modified by the requirement
   level of the document in which they are used.
</t>
</abstract>
</front>

<seriesInfo name="BCP" value="14"/>
<seriesInfo name="RFC" value="2119"/>
<format octets="4723" target="http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc2119.txt" type="TXT"/>
<format octets="17491" target="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/html/rfc2119.html" type="HTML"/>
<format octets="5777" target="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/xml/rfc2119.xml" type="XML"/>
</reference>
			<reference anchor="RFC5245">

<front>
<title>Interactive Connectivity Establishment (ICE): A Protocol for Network Address Translator (NAT) Traversal for Offer/Answer Protocols</title>
<author fullname="J. Rosenberg" initials="J." surname="Rosenberg">
<organization/>
</author>
<date month="April" year="2010"/>
<abstract>
<t>This document describes a protocol for Network Address Translator (NAT) traversal for UDP-based multimedia sessions established with the offer/answer model.  This protocol is called Interactive Connectivity Establishment (ICE).  ICE makes use of the Session Traversal Utilities for NAT (STUN) protocol and its extension, Traversal Using Relay NAT (TURN).  ICE can be used by any protocol utilizing the offer/answer model, such as the Session Initiation Protocol (SIP). [STANDARDS-TRACK]</t>
</abstract>
</front>

<seriesInfo name="RFC" value="5245"/>
<format octets="285120" target="http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc5245.txt" type="TXT"/>
</reference>
			<reference anchor="I-D.ietf-avtcore-ecn-for-rtp">
<front>
<title>Explicit Congestion Notification (ECN) for RTP over UDP</title>

<author fullname="Magnus Westerlund" initials="M" surname="Westerlund">
    <organization/>
</author>

<author fullname="Ingemar Johansson" initials="I" surname="Johansson">
    <organization/>
</author>

<author fullname="Colin Perkins" initials="C" surname="Perkins">
    <organization/>
</author>

<author fullname="Ken Carlberg" initials="K" surname="Carlberg">
    <organization/>
</author>

<date day="28" month="January" year="2011"/>

<abstract>
<t>This document specifies how explicit congestion notification (ECN) can be used with RTP/UDP flows that use RTCP as feedback mechanism. It defines one RTCP XR extension for ECN summary, a RTCP transport feedback format for timely reporting of congestion events, and an STUN extension used in the optional initilization method using ICE. Signalling and procedures for negotiation of capabilities and initilization methods are also defined.</t>
</abstract>

</front>

<seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-ietf-avtcore-ecn-for-rtp-00"/>
<format target="http://www.ietf.org/internet-drafts/draft-ietf-avtcore-ecn-for-rtp-00.txt" type="TXT"/>
</reference>
		</references>

		<references title="Informative References">
			<reference anchor="RFC2629">

<front>
<title>Writing I-Ds and RFCs using XML</title>
<author fullname="Marshall T. Rose" initials="M.T." surname="Rose">
<organization>Invisible Worlds, Inc.</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street>660 York Street</street>
<city>San Francisco</city>
<region>CA</region>
<code>94110</code>
<country>US</country>
</postal>
<phone>+1 415 695 3975</phone>
<email>mrose@not.invisible.net</email>
<uri>http://invisible.net/</uri>
</address>
</author>
<date month="June" year="1999"/>
<area>General</area>
<keyword>RFC</keyword>
<keyword>Request for Comments</keyword>
<keyword>I-D</keyword>
<keyword>Internet-Draft</keyword>
<keyword>XML</keyword>
<keyword>Extensible Markup Language</keyword>
<abstract>
<t>This memo presents a technique for using XML
(Extensible Markup Language)
as a source format for documents in the Internet-Drafts (I-Ds) and
Request for Comments (RFC) series.</t>
</abstract>
</front>

<seriesInfo name="RFC" value="2629"/>
<format octets="48677" target="http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc2629.txt" type="TXT"/>
<format octets="71741" target="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/html/rfc2629.html" type="HTML"/>
<format octets="53481" target="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/xml/rfc2629.xml" type="XML"/>
</reference>
			<reference anchor="I-D.loreto-splices-disaggregated-media">
<front>
<title>Disaggregated Media in the Session Initiation Protocol (SIP)</title>

<author fullname="Gonzalo Camarillo" initials="G" surname="Camarillo">
    <organization/>
</author>

<author fullname="Salvatore Loreto" initials="S" surname="Loreto">
    <organization/>
</author>

<date day="16" month="September" year="2010"/>

<abstract>
<t>Disaggregated media refers to the ability for a user to create a multimedia session combining different media streams, coming from different devices under his or her control, so that they are treated by the far end of the session as a single media session.  This document lists several use cases that involve disaggregated media in SIP.  Additionally, this document analyzes what types of disaggregated media can be implemented using existing protocol mechanisms, and the pros and cons of using each of those mechanisms. Finally, this document describes scenarios that are not covered by current mechanisms and proposes new IETF work to cover them.</t>
</abstract>

</front>

<seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-loreto-splices-disaggregated-media-00"/>
<format target="http://www.ietf.org/internet-drafts/draft-loreto-splices-disaggregated-media-00.txt" type="TXT"/>
</reference>
		</references>

		<section title="Release notes">
			<t>This section must be removed before publication as an RFC.</t>

			

			
		</section>
	</back>
</rfc>
