<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" >
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>

<?rfc strict="no"?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="2"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>

<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>

<?rfc inline="yes"?>

<?rfc topblock="yes" ?>
<?rfc autobreaks="yes" ?>



<rfc
   category="bcp"
   docName="draft-crocker-dmarc-bcp-00"
   ipr="trust200902">
   <front>
      <title
         abbrev="dmarcops">Using DMARC</title>
      <author
         fullname="Dave Crocker"
         initials="D."
         role="editor"
         surname="Crocker">
         <organization>Brandenburg InternetWorking</organization>
         <address>
            <postal>
               <street>675 Spruce Drive</street>
               <city>Sunnyvale</city>
               <region>CA</region>
               <code>94086</code>
               <country>USA</country>
            </postal>
            <phone>+1.408.246.8253</phone>
            <email>dcrocker@bbiw.net</email>
         </address>
      </author>
      <date
         day=""
         month=""
         year="2013"></date>
      <area></area>
      <workgroup></workgroup>
      <keyword></keyword>
      <abstract>
         <t>Email abuse often relies on unauthorized use of a domain name, such
            as one belonging to a well-known company (brand). SPF and DKIM
            provide basic domain name authentication methods for email. A recent
            industry effort built an additional authentication-based layer,
            called Domain-based Message Authentication, Reporting &amp;
            Conformance (DMARC). It allows a sender to indicate that their
            emails are protected by SPF and/or DKIM, and tells a receiver what
            to do if neither of those authentication methods passes; it also
            provides a reporting mechanism, from receivers back to domain
            owners. Such capabilities over the public Internet are unusual and
            their use is not yet well-understood. This document formulates a set
            of best practices for the use of DMARC. </t>
      </abstract>
   </front>
   <middle>
      <section
         title="Introduction">
         <t>Email abuse often relies on unauthorized use of a domain name, such
            as one belonging to a well-known company (brand). <xref
               target="RFC4408">SPF</xref> and <xref
               target="RFC6376">DKIM</xref> provide basic domain name
            authentication methods for email. A recent industry effort
            [DMARC.ORG] built an additional authentication-based layer, called
            Domain-based Message Authentication, Reporting &amp; Conformance. <xref
               target="DMARC"></xref> allows a sender to indicate that their
            emails are protected by SPF and/or DKIM, and tells a receiver what
            to do if neither of those authentication methods passes; it also
            provides a reporting mechanism, from receivers back to domain
            owners. Such capabilities over the public Internet are unusual and
            their use is not yet well-understood. This document formulates a set
            of best practices for the use of DMARC. </t>
         <t>Discussion is divided along basic lines of activity: <list
               style="symbols">
               <t>Development</t>
               <t>DNS Configuration</t>
               <t>Receiver Processing</t>
               <t>Report Generation</t>
            </list> This initial version of the document is primarily meant to
            seed discussion, rather than offer complete consideration of the
            topic... Besides obviously soliciting more content and discussion, a
            review of the document's organization is strongly requested.</t>
         <t>An IETF mailing list for discussing DMARC issues has been requested:
            dmarc@ietf.org.</t>
      </section>

      <section
         title="Development">
         <t>{This section is meant for any software development practices,
            relevant to the use of DMARC. -ed}</t>
      </section>

      <section
         title="DNS Configuration">
         <t>
            <list
               style="symbols">
               <t>Malformed DMARC policy TXT records in DNS. <list>
                     <t>Can these be used for anything?</t>
                     <t>Should a policy that does not conform to the spec be
                        ignored?</t>
                     <t>Is there any benefit in attempting to infer meaning
                        (monitor = none, non = ??, rejec = ??)</t>
                     <t>How lenient can one safely be as regards spacing,
                        quotes, separators and slashes?</t>
                     <t>Is there anyway I can report the malformation to the
                        domain owner?</t>
                  </list></t>
            </list>
         </t>
      </section>

      <section
         title="Receiver Processing">
         <t>
            <list
               style="symbols">
               <t>Rapid adoption of DMARC by apparent spammers <list>
                     <t>Thousands upon thousands of DMARC records published by
                        abusive domains -- probably wildcarding, but it works
                        out the same</t>
                     <t>Using data that is several weeks old, we have a handful
                        of domains that are accepting aggregate reports for over
                        20 thousand subdomains each</t>
                     <t>Are the reports (either aggregate or forensic) providing
                        the spammers insight that they did not already have?</t>
                     <t>***POTENTIALLY PROBLEMATIC QUESTION TO FOLLOW*** Should
                        I only send reports to domains that I trust?</t>
                  </list></t>
            </list>
         </t>
      </section>


      <section
         title="Report Generation">
         <t><list
               style="symbols">
               <t>Minimum requirements for aggregate report XML documents <list>
                     <t>What is the bare minimum (in terms of data gleaned from
                        a given email) I need to produce a valid report?</t>
                     <t> What sections of the XML need to be repeated when there
                        is a new aggregation point (email from a different IP,
                        for example)</t>
                     <t>Essentially this could be considered "XML for people who
                        thought they could figure out how to read an XSD but
                        reality crashed that party."</t>
                  </list></t>
               <t>Minimum requirements for forensic reports (soft-fail reports) <list>
                     <t>What is the bare minimum required to produce a forensic
                        report.</t>
                  </list>
               </t>



            </list></t>
      </section>

      <section
         title="Miscellaneous">
         <t>This section is meant as a catch-all, for items that haven't yet
            been assigned to their appropriate section. <list
               style="symbols">

               <t>Performing remote destination checking <list>
                     <t>What happens if I don't?</t>
                  </list>
               </t>

               <t>Identifier alignment<list>
                     <t>{This has been cited, but not yet explained, as a
                        potential BCP issue. -ed}</t>
                  </list></t>

               <t>Owner vs. Operator<list>
                     <t>{It is possible that there are distinctive practices for
                        domain name owners, versus agents that operate DNS or
                        email services on behalf of the name owner. -ed}</t>
                  </list></t>
            </list></t>

      </section>

      <section
         title="Security Considerations">
         <t><list
               style="symbols">
               <t>DNS Abuse <list>
                     <t>Most probably don't see this, but adding potentially
                        multiple new DNS lookups per email multiplies
                        rapidly</t>
                     <t>DNS Cache can only help for so long</t>
                     <t>Agg reports are (probably) created from some other
                        host</t>
                     <t>If Org Domain policy lookups are required, you may get
                        two lookups every time there is a single lookup </t>
                  </list></t>
            </list></t>
      </section>

   </middle>


   <back>

      <references
         title="References - Normative">
         <reference
            anchor="DMARC">
            <front>
               <title
                  abbrev="DMARC">Domain-based Message Authentication, Reporting
                  and Conformance (DMARC)</title>
               <author
                  fullname="M. Kucherawy"
                  initials="M."
                  role="editor"
                  surname="Kucherawy">
                  <organization>Cloudmark</organization>
               </author>
               <date
                  day="30"
                  month="March"
                  year="2013"></date>
            </front>
            <seriesInfo
               name="URL"
               value="http://http://www.dmarc.org/draft-dmarc-base-00-02.txt"></seriesInfo>
         </reference>
      </references>

      <references
         title="References - Informative">



         <reference
            anchor="RFC4408">

            <front>
               <title>Sender Policy Framework (SPF) for Authorizing Use of
                  Domains in E-Mail, Version 1</title>
               <author
                  fullname="M. Wong"
                  initials="M."
                  surname="Wong">
                  <organization></organization>
               </author>
               <author
                  fullname="W. Schlitt"
                  initials="W."
                  surname="Schlitt">
                  <organization></organization>
               </author>
               <date
                  month="April"
                  year="2006"></date>
               <abstract>
                  <t>E-mail on the Internet can be forged in a number of ways.
                     In particular, existing protocols place no restriction on
                     what a sending host can use as the reverse-path of a
                     message or the domain given on the SMTP HELO/EHLO commands.
                     This document describes version 1 of the ender Policy
                     Framework (SPF) protocol, whereby a domain may explicitly
                     authorize the hosts that are allowed to use its domain
                     name, and a receiving host may check such authorization.
                     This memo defines an Experimental Protocol for the Internet
                     community.</t>
               </abstract>
            </front>

            <seriesInfo
               name="RFC"
               value="4408"></seriesInfo>
            <format
               octets="105009"
               target="http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc4408.txt"
               type="TXT"></format>
         </reference>

         <reference
            anchor="RFC6376">

            <front>
               <title>DomainKeys Identified Mail (DKIM) Signatures</title>
               <author
                  fullname="D. Crocker"
                  initials="D."
                  surname="Crocker">
                  <organization></organization>
               </author>
               <author
                  fullname="T. Hansen"
                  initials="T."
                  surname="Hansen">
                  <organization></organization>
               </author>
               <author
                  fullname="M. Kucherawy"
                  initials="M."
                  surname="Kucherawy">
                  <organization></organization>
               </author>
               <date
                  month="September"
                  year="2011"></date>
               <abstract>
                  <t>DomainKeys Identified Mail (DKIM) permits a person, role,
                     or organization that owns the signing domain to claim some
                     responsibility for a message by associating the domain with
                     the message. This can be an author's organization, an
                     operational relay, or one of their agents. DKIM separates
                     the question of the identity of the Signer of the message
                     from the purported author of the message. Assertion of
                     responsibility is validated through a cryptographic
                     signature and by querying the Signer's domain directly to
                     retrieve the appropriate public key. Message transit from
                     author to recipient is through relays that typically make
                     no substantive change to the message content and thus
                     preserve the DKIM signature.&lt;/t>&lt;t> This memo
                     obsoletes RFC 4871 and RFC 5672. [STANDARDS-TRACK]</t>
               </abstract>
            </front>

            <seriesInfo
               name="RFC"
               value="6376"></seriesInfo>
            <format
               octets="176999"
               target="http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc6376.txt"
               type="TXT"></format>
         </reference>
      </references>

      <section
         title="Acknowledgements">
         <t>DMARC and this draft are the result of lengthy efforts by an
            informal industry consortium: dmarc.org.</t>
      </section>
   </back>
</rfc>
