<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" >
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>

<?rfc strict="no"?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="2"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>

<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>

<?rfc inline="yes"?>

<?rfc topblock="yes" ?>
<?rfc autobreaks="yes" ?>



<rfc
   category="bcp"
   docName="draft-crocker-dmarc-bcp-01"
   ipr="trust200902">
   <front>
      <title
         abbrev="dmarcops">Using DMARC</title>
      <author
         fullname="Dave Crocker"
         initials="D."
         role="editor"
         surname="Crocker">
         <organization>Brandenburg InternetWorking</organization>
         <address>
            <postal>
               <street>675 Spruce Drive</street>
               <city>Sunnyvale</city>
               <region>CA</region>
               <code>94086</code>
               <country>USA</country>
            </postal>
            <phone>+1.408.246.8253</phone>
            <email>dcrocker@bbiw.net</email>
         </address>
      </author>
      <date
         day=""
         month=""
         year="2013"></date>
      <area></area>
      <workgroup></workgroup>
      <keyword></keyword>
      <abstract>
         <t>Email abuse often relies on unauthorized use of a domain name, such
            as one belonging to a well-known company (brand). SPF and DKIM
            provide basic domain name authentication methods for email. A recent
            industry effort built an additional authentication-based layer,
            called Domain-based Message Authentication, Reporting &amp;
            Conformance (DMARC). It allows a sender to indicate that their
            emails are protected by SPF and/or DKIM, and tells a receiver what
            to do if neither of those authentication methods passes; it also
            provides a reporting mechanism, from receivers back to domain
            owners. Such capabilities over the public Internet are unusual and
            their use is not yet well-understood. This document formulates a set
            of best practices for the use of DMARC. </t>
      </abstract>
   </front>


   <middle>

      <section
         title="Introduction">
         <t>Email abuse often relies on unauthorized use of a domain name, such
            as one belonging to a well-known company (brand). <xref
               target="RFC4408">SPF</xref> and <xref
               target="RFC6376">DKIM</xref> provide basic domain name
            authentication methods for email. A recent industry effort
            (DMARC.org) built an additional authentication-based layer, called
            Domain-based Message Authentication, Reporting &amp; Conformance. <xref
               target="DMARC"></xref> allows a sender to indicate that their
            emails are protected by SPF and/or DKIM, and tells a receiver what
            to do if neither of those authentication methods passes; it also
            provides a reporting mechanism, from receivers back to domain
            owners. Such capabilities over the public Internet are unusual and
            their use is not yet well-understood. This document formulates a set
            of best practices for the use of DMARC. </t>
         <t>Discussion is divided along basic lines of activity: <list>
               <t><list
                     style="symbols">
                     <t>Development</t>
                     <t>DNS Configuration</t>
                     <t>Report Generation</t>
                     <t>Receiver Processing</t>
                  </list></t>
            </list>
         </t>


         <t>An IETF mailing list for discussing DMARC issues has been
            established: dmarc@ietf.org.<list>
               <t><list
                     style="hanging">
                     <t
                        hangText="Editor's Note:  ">The current version
                        incorporates new sections of relatively raw text from
                        the original DMARC team and edited merely to convert to
                        xml2rfc format. It has not yet received editing for
                        content. The version is being issued as an Internet
                        Draft in order to create an archived snapshot, and
                        possibly to whet more appetites for adding content...
                        /Dave </t>
                  </list></t>
            </list></t>
      </section>


      <section
         title="Development">
         <t>{This section is meant for any any software development practices,
            relevant to the use of DMARC. -ed} <list>
               <t>Core Functionality</t>
               <t>Tools Support</t>
            </list></t>
      </section>


      <section
         title="Barriers to Adoption (or, How I Learned
         to Stop Worrying and Love DMARC)">

         <t>Within this section are discussed various hurdles, either real or
            feared, that might need to be overcome to incorporate DMARC into
            successful operational service. This includes issues that are
            applicable from either a sending perspective, as a receiver, or
            both. When considering DMARC, one must consider the operational and
            technical maturity that would support a successful
            implementation</t>
         <t><list
               style="symbols">

               <t>I don't know where all my email is sent from! <list>
                     <t>One of the first questions that is often raised pertains
                        to having an accurate inventory of all sources that may
                        send email for a given domain as well as having
                        processes to keep such an inventory up-to-date. This is
                        critical as any policy expressed may have implications
                        to mail delivery on that base domain. </t>
                     <t>In addition, it is all too easy to have any source send
                        email on your domain (which is the underlying problem
                        leading to phishing and other similar email
                        threats).</t>
                     <t>Such an inventory must consider sources that include
                        organic or on-site mail capabilities as well as
                        outsourced mail delivery. Also on this list are special
                        purpose emails that are often sent as part broader
                        capability, usually in an outsourcing or 'cloud'
                        capacity</t>
                     <t>In actuality, the deployment of DMARC as a sender can
                        actually help allay such concerns. Through both
                        aggregate and message level feedback, DMARC provides a
                        more regular and reliable reporting capability which can
                        augment an established inventory effort or serve as a
                        core capability in setting such an inventory management
                        regime. Starting with a 'none' policy (p=none) expressed
                        in a published policy, one can achieve that visibility
                        without having any other implications to mail handling
                        behavior.</t>
                  </list><vspace></vspace></t>


               <t>If I publish a DMARC policy, I lose flexibility in email
                  delivery. <list>
                     <t>While DMARC is an important new technology to help
                        address phishing, it is not a strategy of itself. Part
                        of the deployment of DMARC is the consideration of
                        segmentation of various email sources, usually through
                        the use of subdomains. Whereas it is common to send
                        email using a second-level domain (e.g. blah.com),
                        segmenting different email sources and providers (e.g.
                        source1.blah.com, source2.blah.com) can enhance email
                        visibility and diagnostic capability while providing a
                        way out of the 'one-size-fits-all' concern. Furthermore,
                        this allows for a more manageable and incremental
                        approach to deploying DMARC allowing more aggressive
                        policies to be deployed in areas where there is higher
                        confidence in email authentication practices.</t>
                  </list><vspace></vspace></t>


               <t>I use third-party senders for my emails. <list>
                     <t>While the use of third party vendors for email delivery
                        requires some additional consideration, it is not a
                        major hurdle for adoption. Having good Service Level
                        Agreements (SLAs) with your providers that touch upon
                        any changes that might impact email authentication
                        should be explicit if at all possible to include such
                        items as changes to email hosts and addresses (usually
                        impacting SPF) or DKIM key rotations. Providing
                        visibility to vendors of their results via regular
                        aggregate or message level reporting can help
                        tremendously if mail rejection due to
                        'false-negatives'.[*] Applying subdomain segregation as
                        noted previously can also be helpful for reporting
                        purposes when more than one email provider is used.<list>
                           <t>[*]In this context, a false positive is the
                              identification of a valid email failing
                              authentication and having a DMARC policy applied
                              when it should not have.</t>
                        </list>
                     </t>
                  </list><vspace></vspace></t>


               <t>Some of my email is auto-forwarded. <list>
                     <t>The email auto-forwarding scenario has been considered
                        in the deployment of DMARC. It is for that reason that a
                        DMARC policy is only applied if both SPF and DMARC
                        authentication fails. In the auto-forwarding scenario,
                        one can expect SPF to fail at the final destination,
                        while DKIM is more resilient in that regard. But there
                        are those circumstances that in the process of
                        auto-forwarding emails are modified (including changes
                        to message contents through automatic footer insertion
                        such as Anti-Virus stamps). </t>
                     <t>Any time an email is handled, the chance for
                        non-delivery increases. From a sender's point of view
                        though, the email did reach the mailbox as expressed by
                        the individual who supplied the address in the first
                        place.</t>
                  </list><vspace></vspace></t>
            </list></t>


         <t>Additional concerns:<list>
               <t>Reasons for not publishing a DMARC record (yet).</t>
               <t> Concern for incremental deployment.</t>
               <t>Going through mailing lists.</t>
               <t>Variability in receiver processing; creates unpredictability
                  overall.</t>
            </list></t>
      </section>



      <section
         title="Planning for DMARC adoption">

         <t>Distinct from lower-level issues in the specific steps for deploying
            and using DMARC is the approach taken in overall planning for its
            integration and use within the operational email service.</t>

         <section
            title="Decide what you need to do">

            <t>DMARC is intended to protect transactional mail.[*] If you don't
               send transactional mail, you are not in the primary use case for
               DMARC, and you probably do not want to set up domains with
               p=reject. You may, however, want to protect mailboxes by checking
               inbound mail, and you may want information about how your domains
               are showing up at recipients by publishing a p=none record.<list>
                  <t>ISSUE: this is a major assertion and usage constraint. It
                     might be worth a separate discussion in the document, to
                     give guidance on different styles of 'users' and how DMARC
                     is, or is not, appropriate to them. (/ed)</t>
               </list></t>

            <t>So, first you need to determine what domains you own, and sort
               them into piles.</t>

            <t>Sending domains:<list
                  style="numbers">
                  <t>Domains that do not send mail. These should be protected
                     with p=reject, and you can do this quite rapidly -- you
                     might want to set them to p=none briefly to verify that you
                     really don't send mail from them, but otherwise you can
                     move directly to p=reject.</t>
                  <t>Domains that send only transactional mail. These should
                     also be protected at p=reject, but you will need to follow
                     normal roll-out procedures.</t>
                  <t>Domains that send mail, but never send transactional
                     mail. (For instance, if you are a mailbox provider, the
                     customer domains do not send transactional mail.) These can
                     be set to p=none if you want reporting, or left without
                     records.</t>
                  <t>Domains that send both transactional mail and mail for
                     individuals -- for many companies, their main corporate
                     domains are in this situation. They both send transactional
                     mail and contain users who do things like send mail to
                     mailing lists.</t>
               </list>
            </t>

            <t>If you have mixed domains that contain both transactional mail
               and mail from individuals that join mailing lists, you have four
               main choices, in order from best protection of your brand to
               least: <list
                  style="numbers">
                  <t>Make a declaration that these domains officially
                     represent your brand and you do not, as a matter of policy,
                     support forwarding mail from them or joining mailing lists
                     from them. When you have enforced this to the extent
                     appropriate to your environment, roll out p=reject. </t>
                  <t>Move the individuals to another domain, ideally an
                     entirely separate one (so if your original domain is
                     example.com, you might move the individuals to
                     example-employees.com, letting you protect all of
                     example.com at p=reject).</t>
                  <t>Move the transactional mail to another domain, usually a
                     subdomain of the original domain (official.example.com, for
                     instance).</t>
                  <t>Decide not to protect the mail with DMARC directly and
                     use a p=none record to get reporting.</t>
               </list>
            </t>

            <t>Receiving domains: <list
                  style="numbers">
                  <t>Domains that receive transactional mail (for instance,
                     domains where you handle customer inquiries). If you think
                     forged mail from official transactional domains will be a
                     problem here, then you should implement inbound DMARC; in
                     most cases, however, you derive no large benefit from
                     having it on, and may lose mail from misconfigured domains,
                     and might as well leave it off.</t>
                  <t>Domains that receive mail for individuals. These domains
                     should implement inbound DMARC to mitigate phishing
                     problems.</t>
               </list></t>
         </section>

         <section
            title="Picking Alignment and SP Parameter Values">

            <t>Once you know what domains you are trying to protect, you can
               pick values for alignment and for sp.</t>

            <t>If you have a large pile of sending domains like
               shipping.example.com, ordering.example.com,
               todays-promotions.example.com, you probably want to make a
               single, relaxed alignment record for example.com. The same is
               true for any domain in which you know people frequently create
               new sending domains with little coordination.</t>

            <t>If you have a small number of sending domains, you probably want
               to make an entry for each with strict alignment and sp=reject.
               You will also want a sp=reject entry on the parent domain. So,
               for instance, if example.com sends transactional mail only from
               important.example.com and marketing mail from
               marketing.example.com, while the employees hang out on
               example.com, all three domains should be set to strict alignment
               and sp=reject. In theory you could in omit the records for
               important.example.com and marketing.example.com in this
               situation. In practice, you will almost certainly work your way
               up to p=reject on different schedules for them, so at least
               during rollout you will need separate records.</t>
         </section>

         <section
            title="Incremental Roll-Out, Sending">

            <t>The procedure for incrementally rolling out DMARC on an
               individual Sending domain is discussed elsewhere.</t>

            <t>Most senders have multiple domains, however, and will have to
               pick which ones to work on first. Start with some combination of <list
                  style="numbers">
                  <t>Your most attacked domains.</t>
                  <t>The easiest domains to secure.</t>
               </list></t>

            <t>If you can't easily identify domains in either of these
               categories, turn on DMARC with p=none for a wide assortment of
               domains, and see if that clarifies matters. (Often it reveals
               domains that are in both categories at once; domains used for
               sending some particular piece of signed, transactional mail,
               where much more forged mail than good mail is sent.) You can use
               the p=none reporting on a lower domain to substitute for turning
               on p=none on a subdomain (so, for instance, if you have
               example.com at p=none and notice that alerts.example.com sends
               out only DKIM-signed mail, you can move alerts.example.com
               directly to p=quarantine, and senders who are familiar with DMARC
               and their sending environment may choose to move it directly to
               p=reject)</t>
         </section>

         <section
            title="Incremental Roll-Out, Receiving">

            <t>In order to have fully implemented DMARC on the receiving side,
               you must both act on mail and report on mail. In general, you
               will have to pick one of these to do first; do you turn on
               reporting, and report all mail as exempted for local reasons, or
               do you turn on actions first? Both of these are acceptable
               compromises, as long as you are rejecting rather than silently
               discarding mail when p=reject. However, you should not spend very
               long in either state.</t>
         </section>


         <section
            title="[Original bullets]">
            <t><list>
                  <t>How to implement DMARC on a corporate email domain.</t>
                  <t>Choosing the domain name for alignment.</t>
                  <t>Choosing Strict vs. Relaxed.</t>
                  <t>Incremental Roll-Out.</t>
               </list></t>
         </section>
      </section>



      <section
         title="DNS Configuration">
         <t>
            <list
               style="hanging">
               <t
                  hangText="Malformed Policies">DMARC policies published in DNS
                  which are malformed should be ignored by validators with
                  regard to policy assertions.</t>

               <t
                  hangText="Reporting malformed policies">If a malformed record
                  is identified by a validating/reporting entity and that entity
                  wishes to attempt reporting a problem with the record, a
                  report may be sent to the address(s) indicated in the RUA
                  field. As an alternative, a report may be sent to the
                  technical contact indicated in the WHOIS record for the
                  domain.</t>

               <t
                  hangText="Managing DMARC records">Implementers publishing
                  quarantine or reject policies should take care to ensure the
                  integrity of their mail streams when rotating DKIM keys. For
                  owners/administrators that manage large numbers of domains, it
                  is recommended to automate management and configuration of
                  DMARC records as well as underlying DKIM and SPF records to
                  ensure consistency and correct deployment of records.</t>

               <t
                  hangText="Publishing DMARC reject policies for non mailing domains">For
                  domains which never send mail, it is appropriate to publish a
                  DMARC reject policy as a way to prevent abuse.</t>

            </list>[Original listing of issues]<list
               style="symbols">
               <t>Malformed DMARC policy TXT records in DNS. <list>
                     <t>Can these be used for anything?</t>
                     <t>Should a policy that does not conform to the spec be
                        ignored?</t>
                     <t>Is there any benefit in attempting to infer meaning
                        (monitor = none, non = ??, rejec = ??)</t>
                     <t>How lenient can one safely be as regards spacing,
                        quotes, separators and slashes?</t>
                     <t>Is there anyway I can report the malformation to the
                        domain owner?</t>
                  </list></t>
               <t>DMARC records for many domain names.</t>
            </list>
         </t>
      </section>


      <section
         title="Receiver Processing">
         <t>
            <list
               style="symbols">
               <t>Rapid adoption of DMARC by apparent spammers. <list>
                     <t>Thousands upon thousands of DMARC records published by
                        abusive domains -- probably wildcarding, but it works
                        out the same</t>
                     <t>Using data that is several weeks old, we have a handful
                        of domains that are accepting aggregate reports for over
                        20 thousand subdomains each</t>
                     <t>Are the reports (either aggregate or forensic) providing
                        the spammers insight that they did not already have?</t>
                     <t>***POTENTIALLY PROBLEMATIC QUESTION TO FOLLOW*** Should
                        I only send reports to domains that I trust?</t>

                  </list></t>
            </list>
         </t>
      </section>


      <section
         anchor="repgen"
         title="Report Generation">
         <section
            title="DMARC aggregate XML report naming and report metadata">
            <t>The first step most recipients of DMARC aggregate XML reports
               will take, after accepting the compressed files via email, will
               be to uncompress the file and run a script or program to parse
               and store the data contained within the reports. In order for
               this to work properly, the filenames and report metadata must
               work in a standard way from all DMARC compliant report
               generators. </t>
            <t>The correct compression mechanism and filename convention is
               described in <xref
                  target="DMARC">section 12.2.1</xref> for emailed reports. It
               is important to ensure that the uncompressed filename still
               adheres to the specified naming convention. Cases have been noted
               were upon uncompressing a file, the new filename is something
               entirely different than what is specified in section 12.2.1. </t>
            <t>In the report metadata there are several fields that contain
               important information for a report recipient. Here is a brief
               description of each field and some notes on usage and/or problems
               encountered with each. </t>


            <t><list>
                  <t><list
                        style="hanging">
                        <t
                           hangText="&lt;report_metadata&gt;">
                           <list
                              style="hanging">
                              <t
                                 hangText="&lt;org_name&gt;"> This is generally
                                 the domain responsible for producing the data
                                 in the report (i.e. the report generator). In
                                 the example below it is
                                 &lsquo;google.com&rsquo;. The report itself
                                 contains data about messages addressed to users
                                 at gmail.com and many other domains hosted by
                                 Google. </t>
                              <t
                                 hangText="&lt;email&gt;"> The email address
                                 where a report recipient can alert the report
                                 generator to problems related to the DMARC
                                 aggregate report. This can be a mailing list
                                 address or contain multiple email addresses. </t>
                              <t
                                 hangText="&lt;extra_contact_info&gt;"> A place
                                 to point out additional information or
                                 resources provided by the report generator.
                                 This could be the URL of a website with
                                 additional help, a phone number, etc. </t>
                              <t
                                 hangText="&lt;report_id&gt;"> A unique report
                                 identifier. This should be unique across all
                                 reports by the report generator over time,
                                 including reports generated in parallel across
                                 multiple MTA&rsquo;s. </t>
                              <t
                                 hangText="&lt;date_range&gt;"> Date range of
                                 messages included in the report. The
                                 specification says &ldquo;specified in seconds
                                 since epoch&rdquo;. Note that the begin
                                 timestamp for your first report should not be
                                 the value 0, but should instead be the begin
                                 date/time for the interval. <list
                                    style="hanging">
                                    <t
                                       hangText="&lt;begin&gt;"> UNIX timestamp
                                       in UTC. </t>
                                    <t
                                       hangText="&lt;end&gt;"> UNIX timestamp in
                                       UTC. </t>
                                 </list></t>
                           </list></t>
                     </list></t>
               </list></t>


            <t>Below is a sample of report metadata and policy discovery
               sections of DMARC XML report with a the file name:
               google.com!facebook.com!1364169600!1364255999.xml. <list>
                  <t><figure>
                        <artwork type="xml"><![CDATA[<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?> 
<feedback> 
   <report_metadata> 
      <org_name>google.com</org_name> 
      <email>noreply-dmarc-support@google.com</email> 
      <extra_contact_info>http://support.google.com/a/bin/answer.py?answer=2466580</extra_contact_info> 
      <report_id>303460054821571539</report_id> 
      <date_range> 
         <begin>1364169600</begin> 
         <end>1364255999</end> 
         </date_range> 
      </report_metadata> 
   <policy_published> 
      <domain>facebook.com</domain> 
      <adkim>r</adkim> 
      <aspf>r</aspf> 
      <p>reject</p> 
      <sp>reject</sp> 
      <pct>100</pct> 
      </policy_published>]]></artwork>
                     </figure></t>
               </list></t>

         </section>

         <section
            anchor="repminreq"
            title="Minimum requirements for DMARC XML aggregate
            report records">

            <t>The data contained in a DMARC aggregate report, at minimum,
               allows a report recipient to: <list
                  style="numbers">
                  <t> Identify sources sending email purporting to be
                     &ldquo;From&rdquo; its domain and sub-domains. </t>
                  <t> Determine the aligned DMARC results of SPF and DKIM
                     checks. </t>
                  <t> Determine the DMARC disposition of the message. </t>
                  <t> Determine the identities used to check the underlying
                     authentication mechanisms. </t>
                  <t> Determine the results of the underlying authentication
                     mechanism checks. </t>
               </list></t>


            <t>To make this possible, each record in a DMARC report must contain
               a minimum set of data. The fields below are defined in Appendix
               C. DMARC XML Schema and are critical to producing a complete
               aggregate report. Some notes on usage of these fields are
               included to help guide you in your deployment. <list>
                  <t><list
                        style="hanging">
                        <t
                           hangText="&lt;source_ip&gt;"> IP address (IPv4 or
                           IPv6) of the connecting SMTP host. </t>
                        <t
                           hangText="&lt;count&gt;"> The aggregated count of
                           messages represented by this record. The values of
                           all fields contained within the &lt;record&gt; must
                           be identical to be part of the aggregate count in
                           this record. </t>

                        <t
                           hangText="&lt;policy_evaluated&gt;">
                           <list
                              style="hanging">
                              <t
                                 hangText="&lt;disposition&gt;"> The
                                 &lt;disposition&gt; field in DMARC aggregate
                                 data is intended to convey the final DMARC
                                 disposition of the message. This is the result
                                 of the domain&rsquo;s policy combined with the
                                 DKIM and SPF aligned policy results. The
                                 &lt;disposition&gt; field is NOT intended to
                                 convey the ultimate placement of the message by
                                 the receiving MTA, if for example the report
                                 generator decides not to take the DMARC action
                                 based on a local policy (<xref
                                    target="localpolicy"></xref>). The allowable
                                 results are &ldquo;none&rdquo;,
                                 &ldquo;quarantine&rdquo;, or
                                 &ldquo;reject&rdquo;. </t>
                              <t
                                 hangText="&lt;spf&gt;"> The DMARC aligned
                                 result for SPF. This must be either
                                 &ldquo;pass&rdquo; or &ldquo;fail&rdquo;. </t>
                              <t
                                 hangText="&lt;dkim&gt;"> The DMARC aligned
                                 result for DKIM. This must be either
                                 &ldquo;pass&rdquo; or &ldquo;fail&rdquo;. </t>
                           </list></t>

                        <t
                           hangText="&lt;identifiers&gt;">
                           <list
                              style="hanging">
                              <t
                                 hangText="&lt;header_from&gt;"> This is the RFC
                                 5322.From domain in the message(s) for this
                                 record. Note that this is the domain following
                                 the @ in the original address, stripped of all
                                 surrounding non-domain commentary. </t>
                           </list></t>

                        <t
                           hangText="&lt;auth_results&gt;">
                           <list
                              style="hanging">
                              <t
                                 hangText="&lt;dkim&gt;">
                                 <list
                                    style="hanging">
                                    <t
                                       hangText="&lt;domain&gt;"> This is the
                                       DKIM signing domain (d=) in the DKIM
                                       signature that the receiver chose to
                                       validate and report. </t>
                                    <t
                                       hangText="&lt;result&gt;"> This is the
                                       result of the DKIM authentication check.
                                       This is NOT the DMARC aligned result. The
                                       allowable results are specified in the
                                       DMARC XML Schema and refer to RFC 5451.
                                       Note that the correct value to report
                                       when no signature is present is
                                       &ldquo;none&rdquo; as opposed to
                                       &ldquo;neutral&rdquo; or NULL. </t>
                                 </list></t>

                              <t
                                 hangText="&lt;spf&gt;">
                                 <list
                                    style="hanging">
                                    <t
                                       hangText="&lt;domain&gt;"> This is the
                                       domain used for the SPF check. Usually it
                                       will be the RFC 5321.MAILFROM domain. In
                                       cases of a NULL MAILFROM it may be the
                                       EHLO domain, depending on receiver
                                       implementation of SPF. </t>
                                    <t
                                       hangText="&lt;result&gt;"> This is the
                                       result of the SPF authentication check.
                                       This is NOT the DMARC aligned result. The
                                       allowable results are specified in the
                                       DMARC XML Schema. Note that the correct
                                       way to report that no record exists is
                                       &ldquo;none&rdquo; as opposed to a NULL
                                       value. </t>
                                 </list></t>
                           </list></t>
                     </list></t>
               </list></t>


            <t>Below are three examples of real DMARC XML records for a domain
               with a DMARC reject policy in place. </t>
            <t>Example 1. This record indicates a single message matching this
               set of data points. The DMARC disposition for this message was
               &ldquo;reject&rdquo; based on DMARC aligned results for SPF and
               DKIM of &ldquo;fail&rdquo; and the domain&rsquo;s reject policy.
               The empty DKIM domain field and DKIM authentication result of
               &ldquo;none&rdquo; indicates that there was no DKIM signature.
               The result of the SPF authentication check was
               &ldquo;neutral&rdquo;. <list>
                  <t><figure>
                        <artwork type="xml"><![CDATA[<record> 
   <row> 
      <source_ip>91.98.85.94</source_ip> 
      <count>1</count> 
      <policy_evaluated> 
         <disposition>reject</disposition> 
         <dkim>fail</dkim> 
         <spf>fail</spf> 
         </policy_evaluated> 
      </row> 
   <identifiers> 
      <header_from>blog.facebook.com</header_from> 
      </identifiers> 
   <auth_results> 
      <dkim> 
         <domain></domain> 
         <result>none</result> 
         </dkim> 
      <spf> 
         <domain>blog.facebook.com</domain> 
         <result>neutral</result> 
         </spf> 
      </auth_results> 
   </record>]]></artwork>
                     </figure></t>
               </list></t>


            <t>Example 2. This record indicates that 3 messages were represented
               by this set of data points. The disposition for these messages
               was &ldquo;none&rdquo; because the DMARC aligned result for DKIM
               was &ldquo;pass&rdquo;. The DMARC aligned result for SPF was
               &ldquo;fail&rdquo;. The messages passed the DKIM authentication
               check and failed the SPF authentication check. <list>
                  <t><figure>
                        <artwork type="xml"><![CDATA[<record> 
   <row> 
      <source_ip>141.161.2.153</source_ip> 
      <count>3</count> 
      <policy_evaluated> 
         <disposition>none</disposition> 
         <dkim>pass</dkim> 
         <spf>fail</spf> 
         </policy_evaluated> 
      </row> 
   <identifiers> 
      <header_from>facebook.com</header_from> 
      </identifiers> 
   <auth_results> 
      <dkim> 
         <domain>facebook.com</domain> 
         <result>pass</result> 
         </dkim> 
      <spf> 
         <domain>facebook.com</domain> 
         <result>fail</result> 
         </spf> 
      </auth_results> 
   </record>]]></artwork>
                     </figure></t>
               </list></t>


            <t>Example 3. This record indicates a single message matching this
               set of data points. The DMARC disposition for this message was
               &ldquo;reject&rdquo; based on DMARC aligned results for SPF and
               DKIM of &ldquo;fail&rdquo; and the domain&rsquo;s reject policy.
               There was no DKIM signature on this message, as in Example 1. The
               SPF authentication result was &ldquo;pass&rdquo; with a MAILFROM
               domain of &ldquo;classifiedads.com&rdquo;. The SPF domain is not
               aligned with the header From domain, causing the DMARC aligned
               SPF result to be &ldquo;fail&rdquo;. <list>
                  <t><figure>
                        <artwork type="xml"><![CDATA[<record> 
   <row> 
      <source_ip>65.61.105.5</source_ip> 
      <count>1</count> 
      <policy_evaluated> 
         <disposition>reject</disposition> 
         <dkim>fail</dkim> 
         <spf>fail</spf> 
         </policy_evaluated> 
      </row> 
   <identifiers> 
      <header_from>facebook.com</header_from> 
      </identifiers> 
   <auth_results> 
      <dkim> 
         <domain></domain> 
         <result>none</result> 
         </dkim> 
      <spf> 
         <domain>classifiedads.com</domain> 
         <result>pass</result> 
         </spf> 
      </auth_results> 
   </record> ]]></artwork>
                     </figure></t>
               </list></t>

         </section>

         <section
            anchor="localpolicy"
            title="Use and Reporting of Local Policy Overrides">

            <t>The DMARC specification allows for a DMARC compliant receiver to
               take an action that is different than the DMARC disposition for
               the message (see <xref
                  target="DMARC">Section B.3.1, SMTP-time Processing</xref>).
               Reasons that a receiver may choose to do so include overriding a
               reject policy if the message source is a known forwarder or
               mailing list that breaks DKIM and SPF. If a message source has a
               high reputation the receiver may choose to accept and/or analyze
               a message with local rules despite a DMARC disposition of
               &ldquo;reject&rdquo;. While ultimately an email receiver&rsquo;s
               local policy and the final placement of a message cannot be
               standardized by DMARC, the DMARC related reporting of such can. </t>
            <t>The reporting of a &ldquo;PolicyOverrideReason&rdquo; is
               specified in <xref
                  target="DMARC">Appendix C</xref>. A &lt;reason&gt; tag is
               included in the &lt;policy_evaluated&gt; section of the
               &lt;record&gt; with two sub-fields, &lt;type&gt; and
               &lt;comment&gt;. Below are the DMARC XML tags and fields involved
               with a brief explanation of each and two real examples of DMARC
               records with a PolicyOverrideReason. <list>
                  <t><list
                        style="hanging">
                        <t
                           hangText="&lt;policy_evaluated&gt;">
                           <list
                              style="hanging">
                              <t
                                 hangText="&lt;disposition&gt;"> See <xref
                                    target="repminreq"></xref>. </t>
                              <t
                                 hangText="&lt;spf&gt;"> See <xref
                                    target="repminreq"></xref>. </t>
                              <t
                                 hangText="&lt;dkim&gt;"> See <xref
                                    target="repminreq"></xref>.</t>
                              <t
                                 hangText="&lt;reason&gt;"> Present ONLY if the
                                 report generator means to tell the report
                                 recipient that they did not follow the DMARC
                                 disposition. <list
                                    style="hanging">
                                    <t
                                       hangText="&lt;type&gt;"> If a
                                       &lt;reason&gt; is included in the record
                                       the &lt;type&gt; must be present. The
                                       purpose of this field is to explain why
                                       the DMARC policy was overridden.
                                       Allowable values are
                                       &ldquo;forwarded&rdquo;,
                                       &ldquo;sampled_out&rdquo;,
                                       &ldquo;trusted_forwarder&rdquo;,
                                       &ldquo;mailing_list&rdquo;,
                                       &ldquo;local_policy&rdquo;, and
                                       &ldquo;other&rdquo;. DMARC does NOT
                                       attempt to standardize the meaning of
                                       each of these types nor the methodology
                                       by which a report generator determines
                                       the &lt;type&gt; to report. </t>
                                    <t
                                       hangText="&lt;comment&gt;"> Optional. A
                                       report generator may include extra
                                       explanatory text here. </t>
                                 </list></t>
                           </list></t>
                     </list></t>
               </list></t>


            <t>Example 1. In this example the DMARC disposition is reject, based
               on the domain&rsquo;s DMARC reject policy and DMARC aligned SPF
               and DKIM results of &ldquo;fail&rdquo;. But a
               &lt;reason&gt;&lt;type&gt; of &ldquo;mailing_list&rdquo; is
               reported by the report generator. The report recipient can
               interpret this to mean that the domain&rsquo;s reject policy was
               correctly applied, but the receiver chose to override the reject
               action because the message source is a known mailing list which
               cause SPF and DKIM to break. <list>
                  <t><figure>
                        <artwork type="xml">
<![CDATA[<record> 
   <row> 
      <source_ip>132.205.122.20</source_ip> 
      <count>19</count> 
      <policy_evaluated> 
         <disposition>reject</disposition> 
         <dkim>fail</dkim> 
         <spf>fail</spf> 
         <reason> 
            <type>mailing_list</type> 
            <comment></comment> 
            </reason> 
         </policy_evaluated> 
      </row> 
   <identifiers> 
      <header_from>star.c10r.facebook.com</header_from> 
      </identifiers> 
   <auth_results> 
      <dkim> 
         <domain>facebookmail.com</domain> 
         <result>neutral</result> 
         <human_result></human_result> 
         </dkim> 
      <spf> 
         <domain>star.c10r.facebook.com</domain> 
                 <result>neutral</result> 
         </spf> 
      </auth_results> 
   </record>]]></artwork>
                     </figure></t>
               </list></t>

            <t>Example 2. In this example the DMARC disposition is
               &ldquo;none&rdquo; because the DMARC aligned DKIM result is
               &ldquo;pass&rdquo;, thus the domain&rsquo;s DMARC reject policy
               is not applicable. Yet the report generator still chose to report
               a policy override &lt;reason&gt;&lt;type&gt; of
               &ldquo;forwarded&rdquo; in the record. This is perfectly
               acceptable, even though the policy override reason did not impact
               the treatment of the message as far as DMARC is concerned. <list>
                  <t><figure>
                        <artwork type="xml"><![CDATA[<record> 
   <row> 
      <source_ip>195.23.141.86</source_ip> 
      <count>2</count> 
      <policy_evaluated> 
         <disposition>none</disposition> 
         <dkim>pass</dkim> 
         <spf>fail</spf> 
         <reason> 
            <type>forwarded</type> 
            <comment></comment> 
            </reason> 
         </policy_evaluated> 
      </row> 
   <identifiers> 
      <header_from>support.facebook.com</header_from> 
      </identifiers> 
   <auth_results> 
      <dkim> 
         <domain>support.facebook.com</domain> 
         <result>pass</result> 
         <human_result></human_result> 
         </dkim> 
      <spf> 
         <domain>support.facebook.com</domain> 
         </spf>
      </auth_results> 
   </record> ]]></artwork>
                     </figure></t>
               </list></t>

         </section>

         <section
            anchor="minreqfor"
            title="Minimum requirements for DMARC forensic reports">

            <t>DMARC forensic reports serve two primary purposes. First is to
               allow a domain owner to investigate in more detail, legitimate
               sources of their email that are failing one or both modes of
               authentication. For example, from aggregate data one might know
               that a domain&rsquo;s 3rd party email is failing DKIM some
               percentage of the time yet not know which messages are affected.
               Forensic reports could show a consistent From address and Subject
               from the source that are unsigned, indicating a specific campaign
               not being signed by DKIM. Second is to allow a domain owner to
               understand and mitigate specific threat campaigns abusing their
               domain. Examples include early identification of phishing URLs in
               current campaigns for quick takedown or identification of
               Subjects used in current campaigns which can be used by customer
               service call center personnel to handle customer calls. </t>
            <t>The data contained in a DMARC forensic report, at minimum, allows
               a report recipient to: <list
                  style="numbers">
                  <t> Identify the source sending each failed message purporting
                     to be &ldquo;From&rdquo; its domain or sub-domain. </t>
                  <t> Determine the aligned DMARC result of the SPF and DKIM
                     checks. </t>
                  <t> Identify the domain used to check SPF. If this is
                     different than the MailFrom domain or the MailFrom domain
                     is NULL and the receiver checks EHLO, that identifier must
                     be indicated in the failure report. </t>
                  <t> Identify the full DKIM signature checked (if the message
                     was DKIM signed). </t>
                  <t> Identify the results of the SPF and DKIM authentication
                     checks. </t>
                  <t> Identify the URLs in the body of the message. </t>
                  <t> Identify the full RFC5322.From email address in the
                     message. This should include the display name portion of
                     the From. </t>
                  <t> Identify the Subject of the message. </t>
               </list></t>

            <t>Details on the format of failure reports are found in <xref
                  target="DMARC">sections 8.4. and 8.4.1</xref>. </t>


         </section>

         <section
            title="Additional concerns">
            <t><list
                  style="symbols">
                  <t>Minimum requirements for aggregate report XML documents. <list>
                        <t>What is the bare minimum (in terms of data gleaned
                           from a given email) I need to produce a valid
                           report?</t>
                        <t> What sections of the XML need to be repeated when
                           there is a new aggregation point (email from a
                           different IP, for example)</t>
                        <t>Essentially this could be considered "XML for people
                           who thought they could figure out how to read an XSD
                           but reality crashed that party."</t>
                     </list></t>
                  <t>Minimum requirements for forensic reports (soft-fail
                     reports). <list>
                        <t>What is the bare minimum required to produce a
                           forensic report.</t>
                        <t> Whether to request Failure Reports (ruf=)</t>
                     </list>
                  </t>
                  <t>Utility of Local Policy Overrides.</t>
               </list></t>
         </section>
      </section>

      <section
         title="Report Receipt and Analysis">
         <section
            title="Report Receipt">
            <section
               title="Your first DMARC aggregate reports">
               <t>Upon successful publication of a DMARC record for your domain
                  you will soon begin to receive DMARC data. Current report
                  generator practice is to aggregate DMARC data daily. Therefore
                  you should expect to receive your first aggregate data in the
                  range of 12 &ndash; 48 hours after you first publish the
                  record. This can vary depending on the time of day your record
                  was published. DMARC aggregate reports should use UTC day
                  boundaries for the reporting intervals. There is also some
                  time lag while your record propagates through DNS is
                  discoverable by DMARC compliant receivers. </t>
               <t>The aggregate data files will arrive as gzipped email
                  attachments. While the DMARC specification allows for multiple
                  types of URIs to indicate your preference for aggregate data
                  delivery, current report generator practice is to deliver
                  reports via email using the mailto: URI specified in the rua
                  tag. Note that if you list multiple email addresses in your
                  rua tag, you should list them in the order of the highest
                  priority address first, as there have been report generators
                  who do not send to all addresses. In these cases the report
                  generator does send reports to at least the first address
                  listed. Upon receipt of these files you will need to
                  uncompress them for further processing or manual inspection.
               </t>
            </section>


            <section
               title="Your first DMARC failure reports">
               <t>Upon successful publication of a DMARC record for your domain
                  you will also begin to receive DMARC failure data for
                  individual message failures at the email address specified in
                  your DMARC record&rsquo;s ruf tag. You will likely receive
                  your first reports within the first 24 hours of your record
                  being published. There are several factors that will affect
                  the timing and source of your first failure reports. First,
                  the current practice is that only a small number of DMARC
                  receivers are providing failure reports, as it is optional for
                  a DMARC receiver to provide this data. Therefore you should
                  not expect failure reports from all of the same report
                  generators that send you aggregate reports. Next, failure
                  reports are not aggregated and the current practice among
                  report generators is to generate a report near real time when
                  they receive the failed message. </t>
               <t>The failure reports you will receive are specified in <xref
                     target="DMARC">section 8.4. and 8.4.1</xref>.. These
                  reports are intended to be machine readable and it is
                  recommended that you automate the process of parsing and
                  storing the data contained in the reports. The volume of these
                  reports you will receive can be highly variable and it is not
                  limited by the amount of email that you send. Attacks using
                  your domain can happen at any time and their nature is largely
                  outside of your control. Therefore it is also recommended that
                  your report processing infrastructure be able to rate limit or
                  sample the inbound reports in a way that does not negatively
                  impact the sending infrastructure of report generators. </t>
            </section>


            <section
               title="What if I do not receive any DMARC
               reports?">
               <t>If you have published DMARC records and waited 24 to 48 hours
                  yet still received no data you should check the following: <list
                     style="numbers">
                     <t> Check the rua and ruf addresses in your DMARC record.<list>
                           <t> Are they correct without typographical errors? </t>
                           <t> Did you include the "mailto:" prefix? </t>
                        </list></t>
                     <t> Is the domain in your rua and ruf address the same as
                        the domain of your DMARC record? <list>
                           <t>If not, did you follow the process to verify
                              external destinations for data? See <xref
                                 target="DMARC">section 6.2</xref>. for details.
                           </t>
                        </list></t>
                     <t> Check your email receiving infrastructure and mail logs
                        for indications of problems receiving email. <list>
                           <t> Are you accepting email with potentially large
                              attachments? </t>
                           <t> Do you need to whitelist any IP addresses? Or are
                              you checking DMARC on the incoming messages which
                              may be failing? </t>
                        </list></t>
                  </list></t>
            </section>
         </section>


         <section
            title="Report Analysis">
            <section
               title="Data contained in DMARC reports">
               <t>For detailed descriptions on the meaning of different data
                  fields in DMARC aggregate XML files please see the
                  descriptions in subsections .1-.3 of <xref
                     target="repgen"></xref>. For a description of the data
                  contained in a failure report (see <xref
                     target="minreqfor"></xref>). In order to move on to the
                  analysis of DMARC data, it is important to understand what the
                  report generator is telling you in each field. </t>
            </section>


            <section
               title="What should I look for first?">
               <t>There are many ways you can approach the analysis of DMARC
                  data for your domain. The approach you take will likely depend
                  on what you already know about your domain&rsquo;s email
                  sending and abuse of your domain. It is recommended that in
                  general you start with aggregate data. Here are some
                  suggestions on initial things to look for. <list
                     style="symbols">
                     <t>Identify the number of sources (i.e. IP addresses)
                        sending email using your From domain. How many are there
                        and how does that compare to your knowledge of your
                        organization&rsquo;s email sending infrastructure? </t>
                     <t>What is the daily volume of email messages (i.e. sum of
                        all counts) sent using your From domain? What is the
                        volume from your known sources vs. those you did not
                        know about? </t>
                     <t>What is the daily volume that passed DMARC aligned SPF
                        and DKIM? Passed only one but not the other? </t>
                     <t>What is the daily volume of unauthenticated messages,
                        those that failed both DMARC aligned SPF and DKIM? </t>
                     <t>Are any previously unknown sources of email passing
                        either or both of DMARC aligned SPF or DKIM? If so why? </t>
                     <t>What are all of these previously unknown sources of
                        email using your From domain? </t>
                  </list></t>
               <t>As you analyze data and answer some of these questions, it
                  will lead to deeper investigation. At some point you will
                  reach a limit to what you can learn from the aggregate data
                  and likely need to look further using failure reports if they
                  are available. You may want to search for examples of failures
                  coming from a particular IP address to understand what kind of
                  messages are being sent. With the From, Subject, and URLs in
                  failure reports you may be able to identify specific phishing
                  or spam campaigns using your domain. </t>
               <t>Once you have a good understanding of the current state of
                  your domain&rsquo;s email you can use DMARC data to begin
                  remediating problems and tracking the ongoing progress of your
                  changes. Depending on your domain&rsquo;s email
                  characteristics your ultimate goal may be to publish DMARC
                  reject policies or to simply continue collecting intelligence
                  about your email. </t>
            </section>


            <section
               title="Investigating Anomalies in DMARC
               data">
               <t>When analyzing DMARC data you will likely come across results
                  that you want to verify or understand better. In some cases
                  this is possible via further analysis of additional DMARC
                  aggregate data fields. In other cases it is helpful if you
                  have failure reports to analyze. A few examples of common
                  things to explore are noted below. <list
                     style="symbols">
                     <t>Some number of records will indicate that the
                        authentication check (either SPF or DKIM) passed, yet
                        the DMARC aligned value is a failure. If you want to
                        verify that these are all in fact due to misaligned
                        identifiers you can query your data store to show a
                        count of all such cases where the
                        &lt;spf&gt;&lt;domain&gt; or &lt;dkim&gt;&lt;domain&gt;
                        does not match or have a sub-domain match to the
                        &lt;header_from&gt;. </t>
                     <t>If your domain has a reject policy, you may want to
                        check how many records have a &lt;dkim&gt; and
                        &lt;spf&gt; value of &ldquo;fail&rdquo; in the
                        &lt;policy_evaluated&gt; section, but do not have a
                        &lt;disposition&gt; of &ldquo;reject&rdquo;. If that
                        occurs it indicates a problem with the evaluation of
                        your DMARC record. </t>
                     <t>If a message that failed both DKIM and SPF is still
                        delivered and your domain has a reject policy (you may
                        know this if it is reported to you via customer
                        complaint or from your own testing), before assuming
                        receiver error you should check for local policy
                        overrides (<xref
                           target="localpolicy"></xref>). Try to identify
                        records in DMARC data where the &lt;disposition&gt; is
                        correctly designated as &ldquo;reject&rdquo;, but a
                        &lt;reason&gt;&lt;type&gt; is indicated for the policy
                        override. This is not an error on the part of the
                        receiver, but is allowable per the DMARC specification.
                     </t>
                  </list></t>
            </section>
         </section>

         <section
            title="Report Processing and Analysis
            Services">
            <t>Do DMARC.org members think it is appropriate to point out here
               that there are vendor and 3rd party resources that can help with
               report receipt, processing, and analysis? Of course we would not
               mention specifics here, but could point to the
               dmarc.org/resources. I feel it is appropriate to point out that a
               build vs buy decision is possible. </t>
         </section>

         <section
            title="Additional concerns">
            <t><list>
                  <t>When can I expect to receive my first aggregate report?</t>
                  <t>DMARC failure/forensic reports are not being received.</t>
                  <t>Distinguishing mis-processing of DMARC versus local policy
                     variations.</t>
               </list></t>

         </section>
      </section>


      <section
         title="Miscellaneous">
         <t>This section is meant as a catch-all, for items that haven't yet
            been assigned to their appropriate section. <list
               style="symbols">

               <t>Performing remote destination checking <list>
                     <t>What happens if I don't?</t>
                  </list>
               </t>

               <t>Identifier alignment<list>
                     <t>{This has been cited, but not yet explained, as a
                        potential BCP issue. -ed}</t>
                  </list></t>

               <t>Owner vs. Operator<list>
                     <t>{It is possible that there are distinctive practices for
                        domain name owners, versus agents that operate DNS or
                        email services on behalf of the name owner. -ed}</t>
                  </list></t>
            </list></t>

      </section>


      <section
         title="Interaction Issues">
         <t>Some issues come into play when DMARC is used in conjunction with
            one or more other services.</t>
         <t><list
               style="symbols">
               <t> Sender using both DMARC and ADSP.</t>
            </list></t>
      </section>


      <section
         title="DMARC Commentary">
         <t>This section explains a number of choices made for DMARC.</t>
         <t><list
               style="symbols">
               <t>Rationale for choosing ZIP for the aggregate reports.</t>
            </list></t>
      </section>

      <section
         title="Privacy Concerns.">
         <t>
            <list>
               <t>IP Addresses in reports</t>
            </list></t>
      </section>


      <section
         title="Security Considerations">
         <t> In this section we describe several security considerations related
            to the implementation of the DMARC protocol. <list
               style="numbers">
               <t>The authors see DNS as a potential abuse target. According to
                  the DMARC specification, mail receivers read the DMARC policy
                  from the corresponding DNS txt record. Theoretically a wrong
                  or malicious implementation might result in multiple DNS
                  queries per message, resulting in a DoS attack on DNS. Such an
                  attack is unlikely to happen; not only is it expensive, the
                  same result can be achieved by simpler means. To avoid causing
                  accidental DNS DoS attacks, implementers consider using a DNS
                  cache.</t>

               <t>The authors see the volume of aggregated reports generated by
                  other hosts as potential for abuse. Sending a large volume of
                  reports could constitute a DoS attack on the sender domain.
                  Such an attack is also expensive and more theoretical than
                  practical. Nevertheless, to protect against this type of
                  abuse, one should publish a _reports._dmarc DNS txt record to
                  restrict malicious domains from redirecting their aggregate
                  reports to an abuse target. Another related potential risk is
                  excessively large aggregate reports that could be damaging to
                  the recipient, though the same abuse affect can be achieved
                  without the DMARC protocol. The majority of mail recipients
                  enforce message size limits.</t>
            </list> [Original listing of issues] <list
               style="symbols">
               <t>DNS Abuse. <list>
                     <t>Most probably don't see this, but adding potentially
                        multiple new DNS lookups per email multiplies
                        rapidly</t>
                     <t>DNS Cache can only help for so long</t>
                     <t>Agg reports are (probably) created from some other
                        host</t>
                     <t>If Org Domain policy lookups are required, you may get
                        two lookups every time there is a single lookup </t>
                  </list></t>
            </list></t>
      </section>

   </middle>


   <back>

      <references
         title="References - Normative">
         <reference
            anchor="DMARC">
            <front>
               <title
                  abbrev="DMARC">Domain-based Message Authentication, Reporting
                  and Conformance (DMARC)</title>
               <author
                  fullname="M. Kucherawy"
                  initials="M."
                  role="editor"
                  surname="Kucherawy">
                  <organization>Cloudmark</organization>
               </author>
               <date
                  day="30"
                  month="March"
                  year="2013"></date>
            </front>
            <seriesInfo
               name="URL"
               value="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/draft-kucherawy-dmarc-base/"></seriesInfo>
         </reference>
      </references>

      <references
         title="References - Informative">



         <reference
            anchor="RFC4408">

            <front>
               <title>Sender Policy Framework (SPF) for Authorizing Use of
                  Domains in E-Mail, Version 1</title>
               <author
                  fullname="M. Wong"
                  initials="M."
                  surname="Wong">
                  <organization></organization>
               </author>
               <author
                  fullname="W. Schlitt"
                  initials="W."
                  surname="Schlitt">
                  <organization></organization>
               </author>
               <date
                  month="April"
                  year="2006"></date>
               <abstract>
                  <t>E-mail on the Internet can be forged in a number of ways.
                     In particular, existing protocols place no restriction on
                     what a sending host can use as the reverse-path of a
                     message or the domain given on the SMTP HELO/EHLO commands.
                     This document describes version 1 of the ender Policy
                     Framework (SPF) protocol, whereby a domain may explicitly
                     authorize the hosts that are allowed to use its domain
                     name, and a receiving host may check such authorization.
                     This memo defines an Experimental Protocol for the Internet
                     community.</t>
               </abstract>
            </front>

            <seriesInfo
               name="RFC"
               value="4408"></seriesInfo>
            <format
               octets="105009"
               target="http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc4408.txt"
               type="TXT"></format>
         </reference>

         <reference
            anchor="RFC6376">

            <front>
               <title>DomainKeys Identified Mail (DKIM) Signatures</title>
               <author
                  fullname="D. Crocker"
                  initials="D."
                  surname="Crocker">
                  <organization></organization>
               </author>
               <author
                  fullname="T. Hansen"
                  initials="T."
                  surname="Hansen">
                  <organization></organization>
               </author>
               <author
                  fullname="M. Kucherawy"
                  initials="M."
                  surname="Kucherawy">
                  <organization></organization>
               </author>
               <date
                  month="September"
                  year="2011"></date>
               <abstract>
                  <t>DomainKeys Identified Mail (DKIM) permits a person, role,
                     or organization that owns the signing domain to claim some
                     responsibility for a message by associating the domain with
                     the message. This can be an author's organization, an
                     operational relay, or one of their agents. DKIM separates
                     the question of the identity of the Signer of the message
                     from the purported author of the message. Assertion of
                     responsibility is validated through a cryptographic
                     signature and by querying the Signer's domain directly to
                     retrieve the appropriate public key. Message transit from
                     author to recipient is through relays that typically make
                     no substantive change to the message content and thus
                     preserve the DKIM signature.&lt;/t>&lt;t> This memo
                     obsoletes RFC 4871 and RFC 5672. [STANDARDS-TRACK] </t>
               </abstract>
            </front>

            <seriesInfo
               name="RFC"
               value="6376"></seriesInfo>
            <format
               octets="176999"
               target="http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc6376.txt"
               type="TXT"></format>
         </reference>
      </references>

      <section
         title="Acknowledgements">
         <t> DMARC and the version of this document submitted to the IETF were
            the result of lengthy efforts by an informal industry consortium: <eref
               target="http://dmarc.org">DMARC.org</eref>. Participating
            companies included: Agari, American Greetings, AOL, Bank of America,
            Cloudmark, Comcast, Facebook, Fidelity Investments, Google, JPMorgan
            Chase &amp; Company, LinkedIn, Microsoft, Netease, Paypal,
            ReturnPath, Trusted Domain Project, and Yahoo!. Although the number
            of contributors and supporters are too numerous to mention, notable
            individual contributions were made by J. Trent Adams, Michael
            Adkins, Monica Chew, Dave Crocker, Tim Draegen, Murray Kucherawy,
            Steve Jones, Franck Martin, Brett McDowell, and Paul Midgen. The
            contributors would also like to recognize the invaluable input and
            guidance that was provided by J.D. Falk.</t>
      </section>
   </back>
</rfc>
