<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" >
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>

<?rfc strict="no"?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="2"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>

<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>

<?rfc inline="yes"?>

<?rfc topblock="yes" ?>
<?rfc autobreaks="yes" ?>



<rfc
   category="info"
   docName="draft-crocker-id-adoption-01"
   ipr="trust200902">
   <front>
      <title>Creating an IETF Working Group Draft</title>
      <author
         fullname="Adrian Farrel"
         initials="A."
         surname="Farrel">
         <organization>Juniper Networks</organization>
         <address>
            <email>adrian@olddog.co.uk</email>
         </address>
      </author>
      <author
         fullname="Dave Crocker"
         initials="D."
         role="editor"
         surname="Crocker">
         <organization>Brandenburg InternetWorking</organization>
         <address>
            <postal>
               <street>675 Spruce Drive</street>
               <city>Sunnyvale</city>
               <region>CA</region>
               <code>94086</code>
               <country>USA</country>
            </postal>
            <phone>+1.408.246.8253</phone>
            <email>dcrocker@bbiw.net</email>
         </address>
      </author>
      <date
         month="December"
         year="2012"></date>
      <area>General</area>
      <workgroup></workgroup>
      <keyword>IETF process working group draft adoption creation</keyword>
      <abstract>
         <t>The productive output of IETF working groups is documents, as
            mandated by the working group's charter. When a working group is
            ready to develop a particular document it usually "adopts" it as a
            working group draft. The document that a working group adopts and
            then develops further is based on initial input at varying levels of
            maturity. An initial working group draft might be a document already
            in wide use, or it might be a blank sheet, wholly created by the
            working group, or it might represent any level of maturity in
            between. This document discusses the process of creating formal
            working group drafts that are targeted for publication. </t>
      </abstract>

   </front>

   <middle>

      <section
         title="Introduction">
         <t>The productive output of IETF working groups is documents, as
            mandated by the working group's charter. Working groups develop
            these documents based on initial input of varying levels of
            maturity. An initial working group draft might be a document already
            in wide use, or it might be a blank sheet, wholly created by the
            working group, or it might represent any level of maturity in
            between. This document discusses the criteria and process for
            adopting and developing formal working group drafts that are
            targeted for publication. </t>

         <t>Within the general constraints of formal IETF process and the
            specific constraints of a working group's charter, there is
            considerable freedom in the adoption and development of drafts. As
            with most IETF processes, the ultimate arbiter of such choices is
            working group agreement. As with most working group management, this
            agreement might be explicit or implicit, depending upon the process
            efficiencies that are deemed appropriate.</t>

         <t>This draft is intentionally non-normative. It is meant as a guide to
            common practice, rather than as a formal definition of what is
            permissible. <list>
               <t>[[editor's note: Working Group Guidelines and Procedures is a
                  BCP. The current document /could/ serve to amend that
                  document; or it could be left as merely non-normative
                  commentary. /d ]]</t>
            </list></t>

         <section
            title="What is a Working Group Draft?">

            <t>Documents under development in the IETF community are distributed
               as Internet Drafts (I-D). Working groups use this mechanism for
               producing their official output, per Section 7.2 of <xref
                  target="RFC2418"></xref> and Section 8.3 of <xref
                  target="RFC4677"></xref> and <xref
                  target="ID-Info"></xref>. The convention for identifying an
               I-D formally under the ownership of a working group is by the
               inclusion of "ietf" in the second field of the I-D filename and
               the working group name in the third field, per Section 7 of <xref
                  target="ID-Guidelines"></xref>. That is: <figure>
                  <artwork>
                     <![CDATA[draft-ietf-<wgname>-...]]></artwork>
               </figure></t>
            <t>Responsibility for direct revision of a working group I-D is
               assigned to its authors, often called editors, as described in
               Section 6.3 of <xref
                  target="RFC2418"></xref>. <list
                  style="hanging">
                  <t
                     hangText="NOTE:  ">The distinction between an 'author' and
                     an 'editor' is, at best, subjective. Whatever the label, in
                     all cases, formal authority for content in a working group
                     draft remains with the entire working group. Choices are
                     ultimately controlled by the usual working group rough
                     consensus process. At times a document author can appear to
                     have considerable authority over content, but this is
                     (merely) for efficiency.</t>
               </list></t>

         </section>

         <section
            title="Questions Considered in This Document">
            <t>The purpose of this document is to discuss the criteria and
               processes for adopting a document into a working group as a
               formal working group document. Therefore, this document considers
               the following questions that are particularly relevant to working
               group chairs who are charged with running the process: <list>
                  <t><list
                        style="symbols">
                        <t>How do working group chairs decide which drafts to
                           adopt and when? </t>
                        <t>Is it necessary to poll the working group, and what
                           does a working group poll look like?</t>
                        <t>How do working group chairs make the decision?</t>
                        <t>What are the process steps for an I-D to become a WG
                           I-D?</t>
                        <t>Are there any special cases?</t>
                        <t>Can a document be created as a WG I-D from
                           scratch?</t>
                        <t>How should competing drafts be handled?</t>
                        <t>Can an Individual I-D be under the care of a WG?</t>
                     </list></t>
               </list>
            </t>
         </section>


      </section>


      <section
         title="Adoption Process">
         <section
            title="Criteria for Adoption">

            <t>Working group charters often specify documents that are used as
               'input' or as 'a basis' to the working group's efforts, with the
               milestones typically detailing an exact set of documents to be
               produced. In some cases, a charter essentially declares an
               existing document to be the formal start of a working group
               document. The details can vary quite a bit over the life of a
               working group, concerning adoption of drafts. No formal
               specification for working group 'adoption' of a draft exists; the
               current document is meant to provide a description of common
               activities for this, but again note that it is not normative. </t>

            <t>There are some basic considerations when deciding to adopt a draft:<list>
                  <t><list
                        style="symbols">

                        <t>Is there a milestone that explicitly calls for such a
                           document?</t>
                        <t>Is the topic of the I-D within scope for the working
                           group?</t>
                        <t>Is the purpose of the draft sufficiently clear?</t>
                        <t>What are the process or technical objections to
                           pursuing the draft?</t>
                        <t>If not already in scope, is a simple modification to
                           the charter feasible and warranted?</t>
                        <t>Does the draft carry known intellectual property
                           rights issues?</t>
                        <t>Is there strong working group support for the
                           draft?</t>
                        <t>What is the position of the working group chairs,
                           concerning the draft?<list>
                              <t>[[editor note: I am not sure this is relevant.
                                 Indeed is might be specifically not relevant.
                                 /a]]</t>
                           </list></t>

                     </list></t>
               </list></t>

            <t>Some specifically-inappropriate criteria should be noted:<list>
                  <t><list
                        style="symbols">
                        <t>Working group support is not required to be
                           unanimous.</t>
                        <t>The writing quality is not required to be
                           ready-for-publication, although writing quality can
                           be a problem and does need explicit attention;
                           certainly a new working group draft should at least
                           pass <xref
                              target="IDNITS"></xref>.</t>
                        <t>The document is not required to already contain a
                           complete and/or sufficient solution, although of
                           course this can be helpful.</t>
                     </list></t>
               </list></t>

            <t><list
                  style="hanging">
                  <t
                     hangText="REMINDER:  ">Once a working group adopts a draft,
                     the document is owned by the working group and can be
                     changed however the working group decides, within the
                     bounds of IETF process and the working group charter. It is
                     a responsibility of the working group chairs to ensure that
                     document authors make modifications in accord with working
                     group rough consensus.</t>
               </list></t>


            <section
               title="Going Straight to WG I-D">

               <t>Absent charter restrictions, a working group is free to create
                  new documents. It is not required that all drafts start
                  outside the working group. Of course, the criteria for brand
                  new documents needs to be the same as for those imported into
                  the working group with the additional and obvious requirement
                  that the working group chairs will need to appoint
                  authors/editors before any work can progress. Note that from
                  time to time a working group will form a design team to
                  produce the first version of a working group draft. Design
                  teams are discussed in Section 6.5 of <xref
                     target="RFC2418"></xref>.</t>

            </section>

         </section>

         <section
            title="Polling the Working Group">

            <t>Other than for selection of document authors, working group
               decision-making about document management is subject to normal
               IETF process rules. Useful descriptions of this process for a
               working group are in Section 3.3 of <xref
                  target="RFC2418"></xref> and Section 5.2 of <xref
                  target="RFC4677"></xref>.</t>


            <t>Thus, when it is not completely obvious what the opinion of the
               working group is, working group chairs should poll the working
               group to find out. As with any other consensus question, the form
               in which it is asked can make a difference. In particular, a
               general 'yes/no' question often is not as helpful as asking
               supporters and detractors of a draft to provide their reasons,
               not merely their preferences. In effect, this treats the
               consensus process as an on-going discussion. Ideally, that can
               produce changes in the document or in participant views, or
               both.</t>

         </section>

         <section
            title="Chosing Editors">

            <t>For existing documents that are being adopted by a working group,
               there is a special challenge in the selection of document
               editors: The document has already had editors. So the question is
               whether the same people should continue the task? Often the
               answer is yes, but it should not be automatic. The process within
               an IETF working group can be quite different from the process
               that created previous versions. This well might make it
               appropriate to select one or more new editors, either as
               additions to the editor team or as primary pen-holders
               (effectively re-classifying the previous team as co-authors). </t>

            <t>If the original editors will continue, the chairs need to ensure
               that the editors understand IETF working group process; it is
               likely to be quite different from the process that developed
               earlier versions of the document. If additional or new editors
               are assigned, the transition needs to be discussed, including its
               reasons; this should be done as quickly as possible.</t>

         </section>

         <section
            title="Formal Steps">
            <t>To adopt a new working group document, the chairs need to: <list>
                  <t><list
                        style="numbers">
                        <t>Inform the working group of the intent.</t>
                        <t>Obtain working group rough consensus.</t>
                        <t>Choose document editors.</t>
                        <t>Pre-approve the document as an Internet Draft, using <xref
                              target="Approval"></xref>.</t>
                        <t>Tell the editors to submit the -00 version of the
                           document.</t>
                        <t>Enjoy the ensuing working group discussion...</t>
                     </list></t>
               </list></t>
         </section>

      </section>


      <section
         title="Competing Drafts">

         <t>Engineering for interesting topics often produces competing,
            interesting proposals. The reasons can be technical aesthetics,
            engineering tradeoffs, architectural differences, company economics
            and the like. Although it is far more comfortable to entertain only
            one proposal, a working group is free to pursue more than one. Often
            this is necessary until a clear preference develops. Sometimes,
            multiple versions are formally published, absent consensus among the
            alternatives.</t>

         <t>It is appealing to ask authors of competing proposals to find a way
            to merge their work. Where it makes sense to do this, it can produce
            a single, strong specification. On the other hand, some differences
            cannot be resolved and attempting a merge can produce a weaker
            result. <xref
               target="Heli-Sub"></xref> Some would argue that this is the more
            common outcome. At the least, detailed discussions to merge are
            better held in private than amidst the dynamics of an open working
            group mailing list. The working group must approve any decisions,
            but it is not required that it be present for all discussions.</t>

         <t>Various management efforts can facilitate the handling of competing
            proposals. Some examples include: <list>
               <t><list
                     style="symbols">
                     <t>Develop a requirements document that is independent of
                        specific proposals; this can highlight features that are
                        deemed essential, from those that are of secondary
                        importance, and facilitate a discussion about features
                        without reference to specific proposals.</t>
                     <t>Develop a comparison table of the proposals; this can
                        aid understanding of their differences.</t>
                     <t>Discuss the relative importance and effects of having
                        one proposal, versus multiple; this can focus people's
                        efforts at compromise and encourage a willingness to
                        choose a single proposal.</t>
                  </list></t>
            </list></t>

         <t>The problem of competing drafts can be particularly painful when it
            arises in either of two circumstances: <list>
               <t><list
                     style="numbers">
                     <t>If a second proposal appears as a new draft, just as the
                        chairs were ready to poll the working group on adoption
                        of the draft containing the first proposal, then the
                        authors of the first proposal could feel affronted. It
                        does not follow that the second draft was written to be
                        difficult or derail the first: it might even include
                        better ideas. So it should not be disregarded. However,
                        automatically asking the authors to merge their work
                        will not necessarily produce a more solid solution and
                        will not guarantee faster progress. This situation will
                        be a judgement call in each case, and it may help to ask
                        the working group for their opinion: should the working
                        group adopt one document as a starting point and fold in
                        the ideas from the second under the control of
                        consensus, or should the working group wait until the
                        authors of both documents have reached agreement? </t>
                     <t>If the working group has already adopted an I-D on a
                        specific topic, the posting of a new individual I-D on
                        the same topic could be seen as an attack on the working
                        group processes or decisions. However, posting an I-D is
                        often a good way to put new ideas into concrete form and
                        into the public domain for consideration and discussion.
                        The working group chairs will want to encourage the
                        working group to consider the new proposal. Should it be
                        adopted and entirely replace the current working group
                        draft? Should the new ideas be incorporated into the
                        work of the working group through the normal editorial
                        process? Should the working group adopt a second
                        competing solution? Or should the new draft be rejected
                        and not adopted by the working group?</t>
                  </list></t>
            </list></t>

      </section>


      <section
         title="Individual I-Ds Under WG Care">
         <t><list>
               <t>[[Editor's note: I can't find an explicit description of
                  Individual vs. Working group draft. Some pages/docs imply the
                  distinction, but not define it. /d]]</t>
            </list></t>

         <t>Sometimes, a working group facilitates a draft, but does not own it.
            These are "individual" drafts, with a common filename convention of
            the working group name following the personal name: <figure>
               <artwork><![CDATA[draft-<lastname>-<wgname>...]]></artwork>
            </figure></t>

         <t>Typically such documents are subject to normal working group
            process. However ownership stays with the original author and the
            document is not formally working group output. In these situations,
            when publication is requested, it may be the case that the working
            group has consensus that the document should be published as an RFC,
            but not have agreement about the text in the document.</t>

         <t>This is a rare situation and working group chairs can be assured
            that the Area Directors will want to understand why the document
            could not be adopted and owned by the working group.</t>

      </section>

      <section
         title="Security Considerations">

         <t>Beyond the credibility of the IETF, this document raises no security
            concerns.</t>
      </section>


   </middle>

   <back>

      <references
         title="References - Informative">
         <reference
            anchor="Farrel-Chairs">
            <front>
               <title>What is a Working Group ID (and when to adopt one)</title>
               <author
                  fullname="A. Farrel"
                  initials="A."
                  surname="Farrel">
                  <organization>Huawei</organization>
                  <address>
            <email>adrian.farrel@huawei.com</email>
         </address>
               </author>
               <date
                  month="July"
                  year="2010"></date>
            </front>
            <seriesInfo
               name="Web"
               value="http://wiki.tools.ietf.org/group/edu/wiki/IETF78#"></seriesInfo>
         </reference>

         <reference
            anchor="RFC2418">

            <front>
               <title
                  abbrev="IETF Guidelines">IETF Working Group Guidelines and
                  Procedures</title>
               <author
                  fullname="Scott Bradner"
                  initials="S."
                  surname="Bradner">
                  <organization>Harvard University</organization>
                  <address>
<postal>
<street>1350 Mass Ave.</street>
<street>Cambridge</street>
<country>MA</country></postal>
<phone>+1 617 495 3864</phone>
<email>sob@harvard.edu</email></address>
               </author>
               <date
                  month="September"
                  year="1998"></date>
               <area>General</area>
               <keyword>Internet Engineering Task Force</keyword>
               <abstract>
                  <t> The Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF) has
                     responsibility for developing and reviewing specifications
                     intended as Internet Standards. IETF activities are
                     organized into working groups (WGs). This document
                     describes the guidelines and procedures for formation and
                     operation of IETF working groups. It also describes the
                     formal relationship between IETF participants WG and the
                     Internet Engineering Steering Group (IESG) and the basic
                     duties of IETF participants, including WG Chairs, WG
                     participants, and IETF Area Directors. </t>
               </abstract>
            </front>

            <seriesInfo
               name="BCP"
               value="25"></seriesInfo>
            <seriesInfo
               name="RFC"
               value="2418"></seriesInfo>
            <format
               octets="62857"
               target="http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc2418.txt"
               type="TXT"></format>
            <format
               octets="77010"
               target="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/html/rfc2418.html"
               type="HTML"></format>
            <format
               octets="62422"
               target="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/xml/rfc2418.xml"
               type="XML"></format>
         </reference>


         <reference
            anchor="RFC4677">

            <front>
               <title>The Tao of IETF - A Novice's Guide to the Internet
                  Engineering Task Force</title>
               <author
                  fullname="P. Hoffman"
                  initials="P."
                  surname="Hoffman">
                  <organization></organization>
               </author>
               <author
                  fullname="S. Harris"
                  initials="S."
                  surname="Harris">
                  <organization></organization>
               </author>
               <date
                  month="September"
                  year="2006"></date>
               <abstract>
                  <t>This document describes the inner workings of IETF meetings
                     and Working Groups, discusses organizations related to the
                     IETF, and introduces the standards process. It is not a
                     formal IETF process document but instead an informational
                     overview. This memo provides information for the Internet
                     community.</t>
               </abstract>
            </front>

            <seriesInfo
               name="RFC"
               value="4677"></seriesInfo>
            <format
               octets="127383"
               target="http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc4677.txt"
               type="TXT"></format>
         </reference>

         <reference
            anchor="ID-Info">
            <front>
               <title>Checklist for Internet-Drafts (IDs) submitted for RFC
                  publication</title>
               <author
                  fullname="B. Wijnen"
                  initials="B."
                  role="editor"
                  surname="Wijnen"></author>
               <date
                  day="12"
                  month="May"
                  year="2009"></date>
            </front>

            <seriesInfo
               name="IESG"
               value="https://www.ietf.org/id-info/checklist.html"></seriesInfo>
         </reference>

         <reference
            anchor="IDNITS">
            <front>
               <title>IDNITS Tool</title>
               <author>
                  <organization>IETF</organization>
               </author>
               <date></date>
            </front>
            <seriesInfo
               name="IETF"
               value="https://www.ietf.org/tools/idnits/"></seriesInfo>
         </reference>

         <reference
            anchor="ID-Guidelines">
            <front>
               <title>Guidelines to Authors of Internet-Drafts</title>
               <author
                  fullname="R. Housley"
                  initials="R."
                  role="editor"
                  surname=" Housley">
                  <organization>Vigil Security</organization>
               </author>
               <date
                  day="7"
                  month="December"
                  year="2010"></date>
            </front>
            <seriesInfo
               name="IETF"
               value="http://www.ietf.org/ietf-ftp/1id-guidelines.txt"></seriesInfo>
         </reference>

         <reference
            anchor="Approval">
            <front>
               <title>IETF Internet-Draft Initial Version Approval
                  Tracker</title>
               <author>
                  <organization>IESG</organization>
               </author>
               <date></date>
            </front>
            <seriesInfo
               name="IETF"
               value="https://datatracker.ietf.org/cgi-bin/wg/wg_init_rev_approval.cgi"></seriesInfo>
         </reference>

         <reference
            anchor="Heli-Sub">
            <front>
               <title>On Helicopters and Submarines</title>
               <author
                  fullname="M. Rose"
                  initials="M."
                  surname="Rose">
                  <organization>Invisible Worlds</organization>
               </author>
               <date></date>
            </front>
            <seriesInfo
               name="ACM Queue - Instant Messaging"
               value="Vol 1, Issue 8, Page 10"></seriesInfo>
            <seriesInfo
               name="ACM"
               value="http://dl.acm.org/ft_gateway.cfm?id=966726"></seriesInfo>
         </reference>

      </references>

      <section
         title="Acknowledgements">
         <t>This document was based on a presentation made at an IETF Working
            Group Chairs lunch. <xref
               target="Farrel-Chairs"></xref>)</t>
      </section>
   </back>
</rfc>
