<?xml version='1.0' encoding='US-ASCII'?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM 'rfc2629.dtd' >
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>

<?rfc strict='no'?>
<?rfc toc='yes'?>
<?rfc tocdepth='2'?>
<?rfc tocindent='yes'?>
<?rfc symrefs='yes'?>
<?rfc sortrefs='yes' ?>
<?rfc compact='yes' ?>
<?rfc subcompact='yes' ?>


<rfc
   docName="draft-crocker-ietf-twostage-00"
   ipr="trust200902">
   <front>
      <title
         abbrev="Two Stage">Two-Stage IETF Standardization</title>

      <author
         fullname="Spencer Dawkins"
         initials="S."
         surname="Dawkins">
         <organization
            abbrev="Huawei USA">Huawei Technologies (USA)</organization>
         <address>
     <phone>+1 214 755 3870</phone>
     <email>spencer@wonderhamster.org</email>
   </address>
      </author>

      <author
         fullname="Dave Crocker"
         initials="D."
         surname="Crocker">
         <organization>Brandenburg InternetWorking</organization>
         <address>
            <email>dcrocker@bbiw.net</email>
         </address>

      </author>

      <author
         fullname="Eric W. Burger"
         initials="E.W."
         surname="Burger">
         <organization>Georgetown University</organization>
         <address>
         <email>eburger@standardstrack.com</email>
         <uri>http://www.standardstrack.com</uri>
            </address>
      </author>

      <author
         fullname="Peter Saint-Andre"
         initials="P."
         surname="Saint-Andre">
         <organization>Cisco</organization>
         <address>
        <postal>
          <street>1899 Wyknoop Street, Suite 600</street>
          <city>Denver</city>
          <region>CO</region>
          <code>80202</code>
          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>
        <phone>+1-303-308-3282</phone>
        <email>psaintan@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
      </author>




      <date
         year="2010" />


      <abstract>
         <t>RFC 2026 specifies a three-stage Standards Track. As currently
            practiced, IETF standards track documents typically attain only the
            first stage. This proposal discusses the problems caused by the
            disparity between documented procedures and actual practice, and
            proposes a simplified, two-step standard track, which will
            streamline the IETF standardization process, with distinct benefits
            for each stage. Clarification of the criteria for handling documents
            re-submitted as Proposed Standard is also provided.</t>
      </abstract>

   </front>


   <middle>

      <section
         title="Introduction">
         <t>Officially, the IETF uses a three-stage standards track, roughly
            defined in terms of completed specification, initial implementation,
            and successful deployment and use.<xref
               target="RFC2026" /> In practice the Internet has been running
            primarily on entry level (Proposed Standard) specifications for many
            years. Furthermore, the periodic IESG review of "immature" standards
            that is called for in section 6.2 of <xref
               target="TwoStage" /> seldom happens. This can cause confusion for
            implementers who fear that a Proposed Standard is unstable and
            subject to change. This also fails to distinguish established
            protocols from those that are newer. More generally, a standards
            organization ought to have meaningful labels and it ought to use
            them. The proposed change recommended here will streamline the
            formal IETF standardization process, remove confusion, improve
            transparency and clarify the benefits for each stage. </t>


         <t>Current IETF standards labeling has a number of harmful properties: <list
               style="symbols">
               <t>Our documented process isn't what we use in practice. This
                  disparity creates opportunities for miscommunication, which in
                  turn can produce mistrust. At the least, a new implementor or
                  product planner has poor guidance from the IETF, concerning
                  what is and is not viable. </t>
               <t>Consumers of IETF specifications have learned to disregard our
                  formal process. For example RFC 2026 recommends in clear
                  language that Draft Standard, not Proposed Standard, is the
                  proper maturity level for justifying widespread deployment.
                  Any vendor that waits for this status is left far behind in
                  the marketplace - in most cases, "infinitely far behind". </t>
               <t>We are almost assured that the IETF inventory of standards
                  contains specifications which do not reflect the corresponding
                  protocols in use on the Internet today, because the protocols
                  require modifications based on implementation or deployment
                  experience, or simply because "standard" protocols may not be
                  used at all. </t>
            </list>
         </t>


         <t>This proposal is derived from <xref
               target="TwoStage" />. The current proposal's core recommendation
            has basic differences from <xref
               target="HousleyTwoLevel" />, but incorporates a number of useful
            recommendations from it.</t>

         <t>If adopted, this proposal will require specific changes to <xref
               target="RFC2026" />. These are TBD.</t>


      </section>

      <section
         title="Proposed Changes">
         <t>This proposal specifies a discrete set of changes, and each is
            separately motivated. Some are drawn from <xref
               target="HousleyTwoLevel" />.</t>

         <section
            title="Standards Levels">
            <t>The core changes that are proposed in labeling are quite simple: <list
                  style="symbols">
                  <t>Retain the Proposed Standard</t>
                  <t>Clarify the handling of documents that are already at
                     Proposed Standard, undergo revision, and are then
                     re-submitted for Proposed Standard.</t>
                  <t>Drop Draft Standard</t>
                  <t>Retain (full) Internet Standard</t>
               </list>
            </t>
            <t>This proposal differs significantly from <xref
                  target="HousleyTwoLevel" />, which retains Proposed and Draft,
               while dropping the existing (full) Internet Standard. Although
               that proposal seeks to reduce barriers for achieving these
               levels, there is nothing in the proposal to effect such
               changes.</t>

            <t>In contrast, the current proposal eliminates a
               technically-oriented status level (Draft) that has proved
               problematic to achieve and is deemed a specific example of a more
               general requirement: the ability to make revisions to a document
               already at Proposed Standard.</t>

            <t> There are different theories about the reasons it is problematic
               to achieve Draft Status, but objectively it requires specific
               technical work and significant effort, including Implementation
               Reports, to document it. Although it is generally deemed
               advisable to find ways for achieving Proposed Standard more
               quickly and more easily, the current proposal defers that task.
               Instead it seeks to create a clear distinction, with
               fundamentally different criteria: <list>
                  <t><list
                        style="hanging">
                        <t
                           hangText="Proposed Standard:  ">The IETF community
                           achieves rough consensus -- on the technical adequacy
                           of a specification.</t>
                        <t
                           hangText="(Full) Internet Standard:  ">The Internet
                           community achieves rough consensus -- on using the
                           running code of a specification.</t>
                     </list></t>
               </list>
            </t>

            <t>A surprising aspect of the current proposal is its elimination of
               a milestone reflecting basic interoperability demonstration,
               including interoperability reports. Interoperability testing is
               fundamental to the success of Internet standardization: <list
                  style="symbols">
                  <t>It verifies the clarity of the specification, because
                     independent, compatible implementations are made to
                     work</t>
                  <t>It demonstrates that the associated Intellectual Property
                     Rights rules can be applied acceptably.</t>
               </list>
            </t>

            <t>In fact the underlying interoperability requirement has not been
               eliminated by the current proposal. Arguably it has been made
               more stringent! <list>
                  <t>Achieving widespread use -- not just implementation or
                     deployment, but actual use -- is the ultimate test of
                     interoperability. If the Internet community finds a
                     specification useful, it will already have done the
                     necessary testing. </t>
                  <t>Note that "useful" is a more stringent requirement than
                     "implementation" or "deployment". Writing code and
                     distributing it are necessary, but not sufficient,
                     activities. The core requirement is that the mechanism gain
                     extensive use; use means that it demonstrates value to
                     users.</t>
               </list> What is being changed, then, is not the underlying
               requirement but rather the timing and manner by which it is
               reported: It is no longer an independent step. It is folded into
               a formal step that relies solely on the far more essential
               reports of community adoption. </t>

            <t>Another concern with elimination of Draft Standard is the
               handling of improvements to specifications that are not yet ready
               for full Internet Standard. The presence of Draft Standard has
               afforded authors a mechanism for resolving this need. Note,
               however, that it can resolve only one turn of the revision crank
               and that it only permits changes that entail clarification or
               removal; it does not cover semantic or syntactic additions or
               replacements to the specification; these require re-issuance at
               Proposed Standard. There is a long-standing concern that such
               re-submission will invite a fresh set of review and approval
               negotiations for the entire work, often with a new set of IETF
               management bringing their a new set of criteria to the
               negotiation.</t>

            <t>To provide a more general means of handling a document that
               modifies, adds or removes syntactic or semantic detail, this
               proposal clarifies rules for the handling of documents that are
               already at Proposed Standard and are submitted for re-publication
               at that level. The critical requirement for this is that the
               review and approval process must be limited to consideration of
               the changes, only. It cannot be taken as an opportunity to
               reconsider the portions that were previously approved by the
               IETF. </t>
         </section>

         <section
            title="Status Review">
            <t>This change is taken from <xref
                  target="HousleyTwoLevel" />.</t>
            <t>Section 6.2 of <xref
                  target="RFC2026" /> calls for an IESG review of standards
               track documents that have not yet attained full Internet
               Standards status. That requirement is hereby dropped.</t>

            <t>For specifications that have not achieved significant levels of
               actual use, there remains the option to have them declared
               Historic. </t>
         </section>

         <section
            title="Downward References Permitted">
            <t>This change is taken from <xref
                  target="HousleyTwoLevel" />.</t>

            <t> Internet Standards are allowed to make normative references to
               Proposed Standards. The rules that make references to documents
               at lower maturity levels are a major cause of stagnation in the
               advancement of documents. This change allows an Internet Standard
               to freely reference features in any standards track RFC. The
               intent of this change is to enable expeditious promotion of
               Proposed Standards to Internet Standards.</t>

            <t>Downward references to Internet-Draft documents continue to be
               prohibited. </t>
         </section>

      </section>

      <section
         title="Two IETF Standards Levels">

         <t>The premise of IETF standardization is a pragmatic sequence of
            diligent specification, serious review, and then publication for
            community testing and adoption. Long cycles of specification or
            review limit the ability of the community to benefit from the work
            and to gain experience that permits iterating improvements based on
            observed need.</t>

         <section
            title="Proposed Standard (PS)">
            <t>Proposed Standard is an established construct and practice in the
               IETF. Any attempt to change its criteria or handling should be a
               separate effort. The current proposal is to retain Proposed
               Standard in its current form. Implementations are sometimes
               offered or even required, prior to gaining PS status. No changes
               are required by this proposal. </t>
         </section>

         <section
            title="Resubmission of a PS Document for PS">
            <t>Experience with a specification often leads to revision efforts
               that clarify, modify, enhance or remove features. A document that
               is already assigned PS status can be revised and submitted for
               republication at that level. Review and approval of such
               documents is limited to the changes. Reconsideration of the
               portions that were previously approved for PS status is
               prohibited. </t>
         </section>

         <section
            title="[Full] Internet Standard (IS)">
            <t>This is the existing final standards status, based on attainment
               of significant community acceptance, as demonstrated by use, as
               well as product implementation and deployment. In other words, it
               must have demonstrated that it is useful in the real world.
               Advancement should merely require documenting this basic fact.
               Acceptable changes to the specification are for clarity and
               improved readability, and may include dropping unused features.
               No other changes or enhancements to specification syntax or
               semantics are permitted.</t>

            <t>There are two incentives for seeking Internet Standard: <list
                  style="symbols">
                  <t>It provides the IETF community with an explicit mark of
                     success for a specific piece of its work.</t>
                  <t>It can facilitate wider adoption. Over the full course of a
                     standard's adoption, there often is a point at which the
                     success of a standard is real, and even definitive, but
                     this success might not yet be adequately perceived by the
                     entire community. Having an IS label will remove any
                     question of stability and utility of a specification. This
                     signal can help to overcome organizational hesitance about
                     using the specification.</t>
               </list>
            </t>
         </section>

      </section>

      <section
         title="Differences from HousleyTwoLevel">
         <t>The core differences between the current proposal and
            draft-housley-two-maturity-levels are that the current proposal: <list
               style="symbols">
               <t>Drops Draft Standard, while <xref
                     target="HousleyTwoLevel" /> drops (full) IS. The core
                  requirements for these two different levels are quite
                  different. Draft is a second technical evaluation. Internet
                  Standard is a mark of extensive, production-level use.</t>
               <t>Drops Implementation Reports, while <xref
                     target="HousleyTwoLevel" /> retains them.</t>
               <t>Clarifies the handling of revised documents that are
                  re-submitted for Proposed Standard.</t>
            </list>
         </t>

      </section>


      <section
         title="Security Considerations">
         <t>This document contains to text with security issues, except perhaps
            the security of the IETF standards process.</t>
      </section>


   </middle>

   <back>

      <references
         title="Normative References">

         <!-- 
         <t>>[GUIDE]Bradner, S., "Working Group Guidelines", RFC 2418, September
            1998</t>
         -->

         <reference
            anchor="RFC2026">
            <front>
               <title>The Internet Standards Process -- Revision 3</title>
               <author
                  fullname="S. Bradner"
                  initials="S."
                  surname="Bradner"> </author>
               <date
                  month="October"
                  year="1996" />
            </front>
            <seriesInfo
               name="RFC"
               value="2026" />
         </reference>

      </references>


      <!--
         <reference anchor="">
         <front>
         <title></title>
         <author fullname="" initials="" role="" surname="">
         </author>
         <date month="" year=""/>
         </front>
         <seriesInfo name="" value=""/>
         </reference>
      -->


      <references
         title="Informative">

         <reference
            anchor="TwoStage">
            <front>
               <title>Two Stage Standardization Approach</title>
               <author
                  fullname="S. Dawkins"
                  initials="S."
                  surname="Dawkins"> </author>
               <date
                  month="September"
                  year="1998" />
            </front>
            <seriesInfo
               name="I-D"
               value="draft-dawkins-pstmt-twostage-00" />
         </reference>

         <reference
            anchor="AltTrack">
            <front>
               <title>An Idea for an Alternate IETF Standards Track</title>
               <author
                  fullname="S. Bradner"
                  initials="S."
                  surname="Bradner"> </author>
               <date
                  month="July"
                  year="2003" />
            </front>
            <seriesInfo
               name="I-D"
               value="draft-bradner-ietf-stds-trk-00" />
         </reference>


         <reference
            anchor="HousleyTwoLevel">
            <front>
               <title>Reducing the Standards Track to Two Maturity
                  Levels</title>
               <author
                  fullname="R. Housley"
                  initials="R."
                  surname="Housley"> </author>
               <date
                  month="September"
                  year="2010" />
            </front>
            <seriesInfo
               name="I-D"
               value="draft-housley-two-maturity-levels-02.txt" />
         </reference>

      </references>

   </back>

</rfc>
