<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<rfc category="std" docName="draft-shen-interaction-ind-07"
     ipr="noModificationTrust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="Service Interaction Indicator">Private Extensions to the
    Session Initiation Protocol (SIP) for Service Interaction
    Indicator</title>

    <author fullname="Yuzhong Shen" initials="Y" surname="Shen">
      <organization></organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>

          <city>Stuttgart</city>

          <code>70499</code>

          <country>Germany</country>
        </postal>

        <phone>+49-711-50886832</phone>

        <email>yuzhongshen@gmail.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date day="13" month="July" year="2010" />

    <workgroup>SIPPING</workgroup>

    <keyword>Draft</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>In SIP-based networks, a SIP session MAY involve several application
      servers on the originating and terminating side. In a certain case, an
      application server needs to set some indications in SIP message to
      indicate service information (what are invoked, what can be allowed and
      what should blocked). This kind of information will be also required for
      composition of SIP applications. There is a need to provide indicators
      for service interaction between SIP application servers or other SIP
      endpoints.</t>

      <t>This document describes a mechanism of service interaction indicator
      for the Session Initiation Protocol (SIP) that enhances service
      interaction between SIP application servers in a trusted network.</t>
    </abstract>

    <note title="Requirements Language">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
      document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
      target="RFC2119">RFC 2119</xref>.</t>
    </note>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>In SIP-based networks (<xref target="RFC3261">RFC3261</xref>), there
      are several mechanisms for feature interactions. They may be grouped in
      three categories:</t>

      <t>- Identification interaction (who is calling, who will be called)</t>

      <t>- History interaction (what happened in this request: it was
      forwarded. And reasons for these happens)</t>

      <t>- Capability interaction (Indicating user agent capabilities)</t>

      <t>There is also a need to provide interaction indicator for further
      actions of involving applications. For example, for a session between
      user A and B, there is an application server AS1 at originating side and
      an application server AS2 at the terminating side. The AS1 has launched
      an application for user A like alarm call (alerting users in a certain
      physical location for a emergence case). It makes no sense if this call
      will be forwarded. The "alarm call" application want to indicate that a
      call diversion on terminating side is not wished.</t>

      <t>A sip application server can also have the role of Service Capability
      Interaction Manager (SCIM) as defined in 3GPP IMS. This application
      server can coordinate applications in different sip application servers.
      Additional service information will be required for keeping service
      context in the SCIM server.</t>

      <t>Interaction of services is depending on behavior of services on a SIP
      node like application server and proxy. This document describes a
      mechanism for service interaction in SIP. It is extensible if certain
      applications need more indicators.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Mechanisms">
      <t>One private SIP header field "P-Interaction-Indicator" is defined in
      this document.</t>

      <t>The "P-Interaction-Indicator" header is for transporting interaction
      indicator that indicates application behaviors in SIP nodes in the next
      steps. Next steps mean time after the setting of
      "P-Interaction-Indicator".</t>

      <t>It has also an indication of direction. If an indicator is in INVITE
      and ACK, it is applicable for application after the application that
      sets the indicator. It has the forward direction. If an indicator in 18X
      and 20x responses, it is applicable for application before the
      application that sets the indicator. It has the backward direction.</t>

      <t>Typical use cases for "P-Interaction-Indicator" are a configuration
      with an application server on originating side and an application server
      on terminating side for a call. The originating application can use the
      forward "P-Interaction-Indicator" to indicate the terminating
      application server what SHALL be allowed or not allowed. The terminating
      application can use the backward "P-Interaction-Indicator" to indicate
      the originating application server what are allowed or not allowed.</t>

      <t>The "P-Interaction-Indicator" can also be used in case of multiple
      application servers on terminating or originating side. For example, one
      application server on the terminating can also set a forward indicator
      for other application server behind him.</t>

      <t>The "P-Interaction-Indicator" can also be used for applications in
      other SIP UA and SIP Proxy.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Syntax">
      <t>The following syntax specification uses the augmented Backus-Naur
      Form (BNF) as described in <xref target="RFC2234">RFC2234</xref>.</t>

      <t>PIndicator =</t>

      <t>"P-Interaction-Indicator" HCOLON indicatorEntry</t>

      <t>*(COMMA Indicator-entry)</t>

      <t>indicatorEntry = "&lt;" as-uri *( SEMI indicatorParam )"&gt;"</t>

      <t>as-uri= name-addr</t>

      <t>indicatorParam = indToken *(HCOLON application)</t>

      <t>indToken = "allow" / "block" / "invoked"</t>

      <t>application = application-string *(COMMA application-string)</t>

      <t>application-string = token/application-extension</t>

      <t>The P-Interaction-Indicator fully describes the interaction
      indicator. Its parameters are described below:</t>

      <t>"as-uri" specifies the URI of a SIP end point (a application server
      or other) that sets the interaction indicator. It is an optional</t>

      <t>"inToken" specifies the attribute of a set of "application". "allow"
      means certain "application" SHALL be enabled. "invoked" means certain
      "application" are already executed. "block" means certain "application"
      MUST be blocked to execute.</t>

      <t>"application-string" specifies name of applications, which MUST be
      understood from end to end.</t>

      <t>There are several predefined name for supplementary services:</t>

      <t>ACRCB for Anonymous Communication Rejection and Communication
      Barring</t>

      <t>CCBS for Call Completion on Busy Subscriber (monitoring busy
      subs)</t>

      <t>CDIV for Communication Diversion Services</t>

      <t>CFU for Communication Forwarding Unconditional</t>

      <t>CFB for Communication Forwarding Busy</t>

      <t>CFNR for Communication Forwarding No Reply</t>

      <t>CFNL for Communication Forwarding on Not Logged-In</t>

      <t>CD for Communication Deflection</t>

      <t>CO for Call Offering CONF for Conference</t>

      <t>CW for Call Waiting</t>

      <t>ECT for Explicit Communication Transfer</t>

      <t>HOLD for Communication Hold</t>

      <t>OIP for Originating Identification Presentation</t>

      <t>OIR for Originating Identification Restriction</t>

      <t>TIP for Terminating Identity Presentation</t>

      <t>Other application name can be added here.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Forward Indicator">
      <t>A forward indicator is used to inform application server on
      terminating side, which services MUST be blocked or SHALL be
      activated.</t>

      <t>Originating application server MAY set a forward indicator to
      indicate terminating application.</t>

      <t>Invite: marc@anywhere.com</t>

      <t>...</t>

      <t>P-Interaction-Indicator: &lt;SIP:as1.xxx.com; block:"CFU,CFU"; allow:
      "CCBS"; invoked: "OIP"&gt;</t>

      <t>The application server "as1.xxx.com" sets a forward indicator in
      "P-Interaction-Indicator", which indicates that requests for call
      completion SHALL be accepted, call forwarding CFU and CFB MUST be
      blocked, Originating Identification Presentation OIP is invoked.</t>

      <t>Invite: marc@anywhere.com</t>

      <t>...</t>

      <t>P-Interaction-Indicator: &lt;SIP:as1.xxx.com;invoked: " CONF
      "&gt;</t>

      <t>The application server "as1.xxx.com" sets a forward indicator in
      "P-Interaction-Indicator", which indicates that a conference service is
      already happen. This means this is an invite to join a conference.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Backward Indicator">
      <t>A backward indicator is used to inform application server on
      originating side, which services MUST NOT be allowed or SHALL be
      activated.</t>

      <t>Terminating application server MAY sets a backward indicator to
      indicate originating application.</t>

      <t>200 OK</t>

      <t>P-Interaction-Indicator: &lt;SIP:as2.xxx.com; block:"CONF"&gt;</t>

      <t>The application server "as2.xxx.com" sets a backward indicator, which
      indicates that conference treatment on the originating side MUST be
      blocked.</t>

      <t>Note: Backward indicator is in 18x and 20x responses.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Proxy Behavior">
      <t>A proxy in a Trust Domain can receive a message from a node that it
      trusts, or a node that it does not trust. When a proxy receives a
      message from a node it does not trust and it contains a P-
      Interaction-Indicator header field, the proxy MUST remove
      P-Interaction-Indicator header field. If the proxy receives a message
      (request or response) from a node that it trusts, it does not remove the
      P-Interaction-Indicator header field.</t>

      <t>When a proxy forwards a message to another node, it must first
      determine if it trusts that node or not. If it does not trust the
      element, then the proxy MUST remove the P-Interaction-Indicator header
      field. If it trusts the node, the proxy does not remove the P-
      Interaction-Indicator header field.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>This document defines one new SIP private header field
      "P-Interaction-Indicator" that should be registered by the IANA in the
      SIP header registry.</t>

      <t>The following are registration information: RFC Number: RFC XXXX
      [Note to IANA: Fill in with the RFC number of this specification.]</t>

      <t>Header Field Name: P-Interaction-Indicator</t>

      <t>Compact Form: none</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>The mechanism provided in this document is a partial consideration of
      the problem of service interaction in SIP. Some interactions in this
      document result in the transfer of confidential information.</t>

      <t>Any intermediaries participating in the Trust Domain can inspect
      P-Interaction-Indicator. This information is secured by transitive
      trust, which is only as reliable as the weakest link in the chain of
      trust. It MUST be removed at border of the trusted domain.</t>

      <t>When a trusted entity sends a message to any destination the
      P-Interaction-Indicator header field, the entity MUST take precautions
      to protect the identity information from eavesdropping and interception
      to protect the confidentiality and integrity of that identity
      information. The use of transport or network layer hop-by-hop security
      mechanisms, such as TLS or IPSec with appropriate cipher suites, can
      satisfy this requirement.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">
      <t></t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2234"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3261"?>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References"></references>
  </back>
</rfc>
