<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<rfc category="info" docName="draft-morton-ippm-testplan-rfc2679-00"
     ipr="pre5378Trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="Stds Track Tests RFC2679">Test Plan and Results for
    Advancing RFC 2679 on the Standards Track</title>

    <author fullname="Len Ciavattone" initials="L." surname="Ciavattone">
      <organization>AT&amp;T Labs</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>200 Laurel Avenue South</street>

          <city>Middletown</city>

          <region>NJ</region>

          <code>07748</code>

          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>

        <phone>+1 732 420 1239</phone>

        <facsimile></facsimile>

        <email>lencia@att.com</email>

        <uri></uri>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Ruediger Geib" initials="R." surname="Geib">
      <organization>Deutsche Telekom</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Heinrich Hertz Str. 3-7</street>

          <!-- Reorder these if your country does things differently -->

          <code>64295</code>

          <city>Darmstadt</city>

          <region></region>

          <country>Germany</country>
        </postal>

        <phone>+49 6151 628 2747</phone>

        <email>Ruediger.Geib@telekom.de</email>

        <!-- uri and facsimile elements may also be added -->
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Al Morton" initials="A." surname="Morton">
      <organization>AT&amp;T Labs</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>200 Laurel Avenue South</street>

          <city>Middletown</city>

          <region>NJ</region>

          <code>07748</code>

          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>

        <phone>+1 732 420 1571</phone>

        <facsimile>+1 732 368 1192</facsimile>

        <email>acmorton@att.com</email>

        <uri>http://home.comcast.net/~acmacm/</uri>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Matthias Wieser" initials="M." surname="Wieser">
      <organization>University of Applied Sciences Darmstadt</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Birkenweg 8 Department EIT</street>

          <!-- Reorder these if your country does things differently -->

          <code>64295</code>

          <city>Darmstadt</city>

          <region></region>

          <country>Germany</country>
        </postal>

        <phone></phone>

        <email>matthias.wieser@stud.h-da.de</email>

        <!-- uri and facsimile elements may also be added -->
      </address>
    </author>

    <date day="6" month="March" year="2011" />

    <abstract>
      <t>This memo proposes to advance a performance metric RFC along the
      standards track, specifically RFC 2679 on One-way Delay Metrics.
      Observing that the metric definitions themselves should be the primary
      focus rather than the implementations of metrics, this memo describes
      the test procedures to evaluate specific metric requirement clauses to
      determine if the requirement has been interpreted and implemented as
      intended. Two completely independent implementations have been tested
      against the key specifications of RFC 2679.</t>
    </abstract>

    <note title="Requirements Language">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
      document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
      target="RFC2119">RFC 2119</xref>.</t>
    </note>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>The IETF (IP Performance Metrics working group, IPPM) has considered
      how to advance their metrics along the standards track since 2001, with
      the initial publication of Bradner/Paxson/Mankin's memo [ref to work in
      progress, draft-bradner-metricstest-]. The original proposal was to
      compare the results of implementations of the metrics, because the usual
      procedures for advancing protocols did not appear to apply. It was found
      to be difficult to achieve consensus on exactly how to compare
      implementations, since there were many legitimate sources of variation
      that would emerge in the results despite the best attempts to keep the
      network paths equal, and because considerable variation was allowed in
      the parameters (and therefore implementation) of each metric.
      Flexibility in metric definitions, essential for customization and broad
      appeal, made the comparison task quite difficult.</t>

      <t>A renewed work effort sought to investigate ways in which the
      measurement variability could be reduced and thereby simplify the
      problem of comparison for equivalence.</t>

      <t>There is *preliminary* consensus <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-ippm-metrictest"></xref> that the metric definitions
      should be the primary focus of evaluation rather than the
      implementations of metrics, and equivalent results are deemed to be
      evidence that the metric specifications are clear and unambiguous. This
      is the metric specification equivalent of protocol interoperability. The
      advancement process either produces confidence that the metric
      definitions and supporting material are clearly worded and unambiguous,
      OR, identifies ways in which the metric definitions should be revised to
      achieve clarity.</t>

      <t>The process should also permit identification of options that were
      not implemented, so that they can be removed from the advancing
      specification (this is an aspect more typical of protocol advancement
      along the standards track).</t>

      <t>This memo's purpose is to implement the current approach for <xref
      target="RFC2679"></xref>. It was prepared to help progress discussions
      on the topic of metric advancement, both through e-mail and at the
      upcoming IPPM meeting at IETF.</t>

      <t>In particular, consensus is sought on the extent of tolerable errors
      when assessing equivalence in the results. In discussions, the IPPM
      working group agreed that test plan and procedures should include the
      threshold for determining equivalence, and this information should be
      available in advance of cross-implementation comparisons. This memo
      includes procedures for same-implementation comparisons to help set the
      equivalence threshold.</t>

      <t>Another aspect of the metric RFC advancement process is the
      requirement to document the work and results. The procedures of <xref
      target="RFC2026"></xref> are expanded in<xref target="RFC5657"></xref>,
      including sample implementation and interoperability reports. This memo
      follows the template in <xref
      target="I-D.morton-ippm-advance-metrics"></xref> for the report that
      accompanies the protocol action request submitted to the Area Director,
      including description of the test set-up, procedures, results for each
      implementation and conclusions.</t>

      <section title="RFC 2679 Coverage">
        <t>This plan, in it's first draft version, does not cover all critical
        requirements and sections of <xref target="RFC2679"></xref>. Material
        will be added as it is "discovered" (not all requirements use
        requirements language).</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="A Definition-centric metric advancement process">
      <t>The process described in Section 3.5 of <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-ippm-metrictest"></xref> takes as a first principle
      that the metric definitions, embodied in the text of the RFCs, are the
      objects that require evaluation and possible revision in order to
      advance to the next step on the standards track.</t>

      <t>IF two implementations do not measure an equivalent singleton or
      sample, or produce the an equivalent statistic,</t>

      <t>AND sources of measurement error do not adequately explain the lack
      of agreement,</t>

      <t>THEN the details of each implementation should be audited along with
      the exact definition text, to determine if there is a lack of clarity
      that has caused the implementations to vary in a way that affects the
      correspondence of the results.</t>

      <t>IF there was a lack of clarity or multiple legitimate interpretations
      of the definition text,</t>

      <t>THEN the text should be modified and the resulting memo proposed for
      consensus and advancement along the standards track.</t>

      <t>Finally, all the findings MUST be documented in a report that can
      support advancement on the standards track, similar to those described
      in <xref target="RFC5657"></xref>. The list of measurement devices used
      in testing satisfies the implementation requirement, while the test
      results provide information on the quality of each specification in the
      metric RFC (the surrogate for feature interoperability).</t>

      <t>The figure below illustrates this process:</t>

      <t><figure>
          <preamble></preamble>

          <artwork><![CDATA[     ,---.
    /     \
   ( Start )
    \     /    Implementations
     `-+-'        +-------+
       |         /|   1   `.
   +---+----+   / +-------+ `.-----------+      ,-------.
   |  RFC   |  /             |Check for  |    ,' was RFC `.  YES
   |        | /              |Equivalence.....  clause x   -------+
   |        |/    +-------+  |under      |    `. clear?  ,'       |
   | Metric \.....|   2   ....relevant   |      `---+---'    +----+---+
   | Metric |\    +-------+  |identical  |       No |        |Report  |
   | Metric | \              |network    |      +---+---.    |results+|
   |  ...   |  \             |conditions |      |Modify |    |Advance |
   |        |   \ +-------+  |           |      |Spec   +----+  RFC   |
   +--------+    \|   n   |.'+-----------+      +-------+    |request?|
                  +-------+                                  +--------+
                                                               ]]></artwork>

          <postamble></postamble>
        </figure></t>
    </section>

    <section title="Test configuration">
      <t></t>

      <t>&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt; This section needs to be updated
      &lt;&lt;&lt;&lt;</t>

      <t>One metric implementation used was NetProbe version 5.8.5, (an
      earlier version is used in the WIPM system and deployed world-wide).
      NetProbe uses UDP packets of variable size, and can produce test streams
      with periodic or Poisson sample distributions.</t>

      <t>&gt;&gt;&gt; Add DT's Perfas Description</t>

      <t>Figure 2 shows a view of the test path as each Implementation's test
      flows pass through the Internet and the L2TPv3 tunnel IDs (1 and 2),
      based on Figure 1 of <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-ippm-metrictest"></xref>.</t>

      <t><figure align="center" anchor="L2TPv3 tunnel">
          <preamble />

          <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[
       
        Implementations                  ,---.       +--------+
                            +~~~~~~~~~~~/     \~~~~~~| Remote |
         +------->-----F2->-|          /       \     |->---+  |
         | +---------+      | Tunnel  (         )    |     |  |  
         | | transmit|-F1->-|   ID 1  (         )    |->+  |  |
         | | Imp 1   |      +~~~~~~~~~|         |~~~~|  |  |  |
         | | receive |-<--+           (         )    | F1  F2 |
         | +---------+    |           |Internet |    |  |  |  |
         *-------<-----+  F2          |         |    |  |  |  |
           +---------+ |  | +~~~~~~~~~|         |~~~~|  |  |  |
           | transmit|-*  *-|         |         |    |--+<-*  |
           | Imp 2   |      | Tunnel  (         )    |  |     |
           | receive |-<-F1-|   ID 2   \       /     |<-*     |     
           +---------+      +~~~~~~~~~~~\     /~~~~~~| Router |
                                         `-+-'       +--------+
        ]]></artwork>

          <postamble>Illustration of a test setup with a bi-directional
          tunnel. For simplicity, only two measurement implementations and two
          flows (F#) between them are shown.</postamble>
        </figure></t>

      <t>The testing employs the Layer 2 Tunnel Protocol, version 3 (L2TPv3)
      <xref target="RFC3931"></xref> tunnel between test sites on the
      Internet. The tunnel IP and L2TPv3 headers are intended to conceal the
      test equipment addresses and ports from hash functions that would tend
      to spread different test streams across parallel network resources, with
      likely variation in performance as a result.</t>

      <t>At each end of the tunnel, VLANs encapsulated in the tunnel are
      looped-back so that test traffic is returned to each test site. Thus,
      test streams traverse the L2TP tunnel twice, but appear to be one-way
      tests from the test equipment point of view.</t>

      <t>The network emulator is a host running Fedora Core Linux
      [http://fedoraproject.org/] with IP forwarding enabled and the NIST Net
      emulator 2.0.12b [http://snad.ncsl.nist.gov/nistnet/] loaded and
      operating.</t>

      <t>The links between NetProbe hosts and the NIST Net emulator host were
      100baseTx-FD (100Mbps full duplex) as reported by "mii-tool", except as
      noted below.</t>

      <t>&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt; We need to decide on common packet rates,
      Poisson/Periodic, packet sizes, etc.</t>

      <t>For these tests, a stream of at least 30 packets were sent from
      Source to Destination in each implementation. Periodic streams (as per
      <xref target="RFC3432"></xref>) with 1 second spacing were used, except
      as noted.</t>

      <t>Thus, the metric name for the testing configured here, with respect
      to the IP header exposed to Internet processing, is:</t>

      <t>Type-IP-protocol-115-One-way-Delay-&lt;StreamType&gt;-Stream</t>

      <t>With (Section 4.2. <xref target="RFC2679"></xref>) Metric Parameters:
      + Src, the IP address of a host + Dst, the IP address of a host + T0, a
      time + Tf, a time + lambda, a rate in reciprocal seconds</t>

      <t>+ Thresh, a maximum waiting time in seconds (see Section 3.82 of
      <xref target="RFC2679"></xref>) And (Section 4.3. <xref
      target="RFC2679"></xref>)Metric Units: A sequence of pairs; the elements
      of each pair are: + T, a time, and + dT, either a real number or an
      undefined number of seconds. The values of T in the sequence are
      monotonic increasing. Note that T would be a valid parameter to
      Type-P-One-way-Delay, and that dT would be a valid value of
      Type-P-One-way-Delay.</t>

      <t>Also, Section 3.8.4 of <xref target="RFC2679"></xref> recommends that
      the path SHOULD be reported. In this test set-up, most of the path
      details will be concealed from the implementations by the L2TPv3
      tunnels, thus a more informative path trace route can be conducted by
      the routers at each location.</t>

      <t>When NetProbe is used in production, a trace route is conducted in
      parallel at the outset of measurements.</t>

      <t>In Perfas, ???</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Error Calibration, RFC 2679">
      <t>An implementation is required to report on its error calibration in
      Section 3.8 of <xref target="RFC2679"></xref> (also required in Section
      4.8 for sample metrics). Sections 3.6, 3.7, and 3.8 of <xref
      target="RFC2679"></xref> give the detailed formulation of the errors and
      uncertainties for calibration. In summary, Section 3.7.1 of <xref
      target="RFC2679"></xref> describes the total time-varying uncertainty
      as:</t>

      <t>Esynch(t)+ Rsource + Rdest</t>

      <t>where:</t>

      <t>Esynch(t) denotes an upper bound on the magnitude of clock
      synchronization uncertainty.</t>

      <t>Rsource and Rdest denote the resolution of the source clock and the
      destination clock, respectively.</t>

      <t>Further, Section 3.7.2 of <xref target="RFC2679"></xref> describes
      the total wire-time uncertainty as</t>

      <t>Hsource + Hdest</t>

      <t>referring to the upper bounds on host-time to wire-time for source
      and destination, respectively.</t>

      <t>Section 3.7.3 of <xref target="RFC2679"></xref> describes a test with
      small packets over an isolated minimal network where the results can be
      used to estimate systematic and random components of the sum of the
      above errors or uncertainties. In a test with hundreds of singletons,
      the median is the systematic error and when the median is subtracted
      from all singletons, the remaining variability is the random error.</t>

      <t>&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt; The RFC text indicates that the clock-related
      errors are not included in this analysis, but a sufficiently long test
      (under full test load) should include all forms of error, IAO (in Al's
      opinion).</t>

      <t>The test context, or Type-P of the test packets, must also be
      reported, as required in Section 3.8 of <xref target="RFC2679"></xref>
      and all metrics defined there. Type-P is defined in Section 13 of <xref
      target="RFC2330"></xref> (as are many terms used below).</t>

      <section title="NetProbe Error and Type-P">
        <t>Type-P for this test was IP-UDP with Best Effort DCSP. These
        headers were encapsulated according to the L2TPv3 specifications <xref
        target="RFC3931"></xref>, and thus may not influence the treatment
        received as the packets traversed the Internet.</t>

        <t>In general, NetProbe error is dependent on the specific version and
        installation details.</t>

        <t>NetProbe operates using host time above the UDP layer, which is
        different from the wire-time preferred in <xref
        target="RFC2330"></xref>, but can be identified as a source of error
        according to Section 3.7.2 of <xref target="RFC2679"></xref>.</t>

        <t>Accuracy of NetProbe measurements is usually limited by NTP
        synchronization performance (which is typically taken as ~+/-1ms error
        or greater), although the installation used in this testing often
        exhibits errors much less than typical for NTP. The primary stratum 1
        NTP server is closely located on a sparsely utilized network
        management LAN, thus it avoids many concerns raised in Section 10
        of<xref target="RFC2330"></xref> (in fact, smooth adjustment,
        long-term drift analysis and compensation, and infrequent adjustment
        all lead to stability during measurement intervals, the main
        concern).</t>

        <t>The resolution of the reported results is 1us (us = microsecond) in
        the version of NetProbe tested here, which contributes to at least
        +/-1us error.</t>

        <t>NetProbe implements a time-keeping sanity check on sending and
        receiving time-stamping processes. When the significant process
        interruption takes place, individual test packets are flagged as
        possibly containing unusual time errors, and are excluded from the
        sample used for all "time" metrics.</t>

        <t>We performed a NetProbe calibration of the type described in
        Section 3.7.3 of <xref target="RFC2679"></xref>, using 64 Byte packets
        over a cross-connect cable. The results estimate systematic and random
        components of the sum of the Hsource + Hdest errors or uncertainties.
        In a test with 300 singletons conducted over 30 seconds (periodic
        sample with 100ms spacing), the median is the systematic error and the
        remaining variability is the random error. One set of results is
        tabulated below:</t>

        <t><figure>
            <preamble>(Results from the "R" software environment for
            statistical computing and graphics - http://www.r-project.org/
            )</preamble>

            <artwork><![CDATA[> summary(XD4CAL) 
      CAL1            CAL2             CAL3          
 Min.   : 89.0   Min.   : 68.00   Min.   : 54.00   
 1st Qu.: 99.0   1st Qu.: 77.00   1st Qu.: 63.00   
 Median :110.0   Median : 79.00   Median : 65.00  
 Mean   :116.8   Mean   : 83.74   Mean   : 69.65   
 3rd Qu.:127.0   3rd Qu.: 88.00   3rd Qu.: 74.00    
 Max.   :205.0   Max.   :177.00   Max.   :163.00    
> boxplot(XD4CAL$CAL1,XD4CAL$CAL2,XD4CAL$CAL3) ]]></artwork>

            <postamble>NetProbe Calibration with Cross-Connect Cable, one-way
            delay values in microseconds (us)</postamble>
          </figure></t>

        <t>The median or systematic error can be as high as 110 us, and the
        range of the random error is also on the order of 110 us for all
        streams.</t>

        <t>Also, anticipating the Anderson-Darling K-sample (ADK) comparisons
        to follow, we corrected the CAL2 values for the difference between
        means between CAL2 and CAL3 (as specified in <xref
        target="I-D.ietf-ippm-metrictest"></xref>), and found strong support
        for the (Null Hypothesis that) the samples are from the same
        distribution (resolution of 1 us and alpha equal 0.05 and 0.01)<figure>
            <preamble></preamble>

            <artwork><![CDATA[> XD4CVCAL2 <- XD4CAL$CAL2 - (mean(XD4CAL$CAL2)-mean(XD4CAL$CAL3))
> boxplot(XD4CVCAL2,XD4CAL$CAL3) 
> XD4CV2_ADK <- adk.test(XD4CVCAL2, XD4CAL$CAL3)
> XD4CV2_ADK
Anderson-Darling k-sample test.

Number of samples:  2
Sample sizes: 300 300
Total number of values: 600
Number of unique values: 97

Mean of Anderson Darling Criterion: 1
Standard deviation of Anderson Darling Criterion: 0.75896

T = (Anderson Darling Criterion - mean)/sigma

Null Hypothesis: All samples come from a common population.

                     t.obs P-value extrapolation
not adj. for ties  0.71734 0.17042             0
adj. for ties     -0.39553 0.44589             1
> ]]></artwork>

            <postamble></postamble>
          </figure></t>
      </section>

      <section title="Perfas Error and Type-P">
        <t></t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Pre-determined Limits on Equivalence">
      <t>&gt;&gt;&gt;&gt; This section contains many proposals
      &lt;&lt;&lt;&lt;&lt;</t>

      <t>In this section, we provide the numerical limits on comparisons
      between implementations, in order to declare that the results are
      equivalent and therefore, the tested specification is clear.</t>

      <t>A key point is that the allowable errors, corrections, and confidence
      levels only need to be sufficient to detect mis-interpretation of the
      tested specification resulting in diverging implementations.</t>

      <t>Also, the allowable error must be sufficient to compensate for
      measured path differences. It was simply not possible to measure fully
      identical paths in the VLAN-loopback test configuration used, and this
      practical compromise must be taken into account.</t>

      <t>For Anderson-Darling K-sample (ADK) comparisons, the required
      confidence factor for the cross-implementation comparisons SHALL be the
      smallest of:</t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>0.95 confidence factor at 1ms resolution, or</t>

          <t>the smallest confidence factor (in combination with resolution)
          of the two same-implementation comparisons for the same test
          conditions.</t>
        </list>A constant time accuracy error of as much as +/-0.5ms MAY be
      removed from one implementation's distributions (all singletons) before
      the ADK comparison is conducted.</t>

      <t>A constant propagation delay error (due to use of different sub-nets
      between the switch and measurement devices at each location) of as much
      as +2ms MAY be removed from one implementation's distributions (all
      singletons) before the ADK comparison is conducted.</t>

      <t>For comparisons involving the mean of a sample or other central
      statistics, the limits on both the time accuracy error and the
      propagation delay error constants given above also apply.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Tests to evaluate RFC 2679 Specifications">
      <t>This section describes some results from real-world (cross-Internet)
      tests with measurement devices implementing IPPM metrics and a network
      emulator to create relevant conditions, to determine whether the metric
      definitions were interpreted consistently by implementors.</t>

      <t>The procedures are slightly modified from the original procedures
      contained in Appendix A.1 of <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-ippm-metrictest"></xref>. The modifications include the
      use of the mean statistic for comparisons.</t>

      <t>Note that there are only five instances of the requirement term
      "MUST" in <xref target="RFC2679"></xref> outside of the boilerplate and
      <xref target="RFC2119"></xref> reference.</t>

      <section title="One-way Delay, ADK Sample Comparison - Same Implementation">
        <t>This test determines if implementations produce results that appear
        to come from the same delay distribution, as an overall evaluation of
        Section 4 of <xref target="RFC2679"></xref>, "A Definition for Samples
        of One-way Delay". Same-implementation comparison results help to set
        the threshold of equivalence that will be applied to
        cross-implementation comparisons.</t>

        <t>This test is intended to evaluate measurements in sections 3 and 4
        of <xref target="RFC2679"></xref>.</t>

        <t>By testing the extent to which the distributions of one-way delay
        singletons from two implementations of <xref target="RFC2679"></xref>
        appear to be from the same distribution, we economize on comparisons,
        because comparing a set of individual summary statistics (as defined
        in Section 5 of <xref target="RFC2679"></xref>) would require another
        set of individual evaluations of equivalence. Instead, we can simply
        check which statistics were implemented, and report on those
        facts.</t>

        <t><list style="numbers">
            <t>Configure an L2TPv3 path between test sites, and each pair of
            measurement devices to operate tests in their designated pair of
            VLANs.</t>

            <t>Measure a sample of one-way delay singletons with 2 or more
            implementations, using identical options.</t>

            <t>Measure a sample of one-way delay singletons with *five*
            additional instances of the *same* implementations, using
            identical options, noting that connectivity differences SHOULD be
            the same as for the cross implementation testing.</t>

            <t>Apply the ADK comparison procedures (see Appendix C of <xref
            target="I-D.ietf-ippm-metrictest"></xref>) and determine the
            resolution and confidence factor for distribution equivalence of
            each same-implementation comparison and each cross-implementation
            comparison.</t>

            <t>Take the coarsest resolution and confidence factor for
            distribution equivalence from the same-implementation pairs, or
            the limit defined in Section 5 above, as a limit on the
            equivalence threshold for these experimental conditions.</t>

            <t>Apply constant correction factors to all singletons of the
            sample distributions, as described and limited in Section 5
            above.</t>

            <t>Compare the cross-implementation ADK performance with the
            equivalence threshold determined in step 5 to determine if
            equivalence can be declared.</t>
          </list></t>

        <section title="NetProbe Same-implementation results">
          <t>To be provided,</t>

          <t><figure title="NetProbe ADK Results for same-implementation">
              <preamble></preamble>

              <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[  ]]></artwork>

              <postamble></postamble>
            </figure></t>

          <t></t>
        </section>

        <section title="Perfas Same-implementation results">
          <t>To be provided,</t>

          <t><figure title="Perfas ADK Results for same-implementation">
              <preamble></preamble>

              <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[  ]]></artwork>

              <postamble></postamble>
            </figure></t>

          <t></t>
        </section>

        <section title="One-way Delay, Cross-Implementation ADK Comparison">
          <t></t>
        </section>

        <section title="Conclusions on the ADK Results for One-way Delay">
          <t>&gt;&gt;&gt; Comment: this section is a placeholder</t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section title="One-way Delay, Loss threshold, RFC 2679">
        <t>This test determines if implementations use the same configured
        maximum waiting time delay from one measurement to another under
        different delay conditions, and correctly declare packets arriving in
        excess of the waiting time threshold as lost.</t>

        <t>See Section 3.5 of <xref target="RFC2679"></xref>, 3rd bullet point
        and also Section 3.8.2 of <xref target="RFC2679"></xref>.</t>

        <t><list style="numbers">
            <t>configure an L2TPv3 path between test sites, and each pair of
            measurement devices to operate tests in their designated pair of
            VLANs.</t>

            <t>configure the network emulator to add 0.5 sec one-way constant
            delay to each direction of transmission (or 1 second one-way).</t>

            <t>measure (average) one-way delay with 2 or more implementations,
            using identical waiting time thresholds (Thresh) for loss set at 2
            seconds</t>

            <t>configure the network emulator to add 1 sec one-way constant
            delay to each direction of transmission equivalent to 2 seconds of
            additional one-way delay, or change the path delay while test is
            in progress, when there are sufficient packets at the first delay
            setting)</t>

            <t>repeat/continue measurements</t>

            <t>observe that the increase measured in step 5 caused all packets
            with 2 sec additional delay to be declared lost, and that all
            packets that arrive successfully in step 3 are assigned a valid
            one-way delay.</t>
          </list></t>

        <section title="NetProbe results for Loss Threshold">
          <t>In NetProbe, the Loss Threshold is implemented uniformly over all
          packets as a post-processing routine. With the Loss Threshold set at
          2 seconds, all packets with one-way delay &gt;2 seconds are marked
          "Lost" and included in the Lost Packet list with their transmission
          time (as required in Section 3.3 of <xref target="RFC2680"></xref>).
          22 of 38 packets were declared lost.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Perfas Results for Loss Threshold">
          <t>&gt;&gt;&gt; Comment: this section is a placeholder</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Conclusions on Lab Results for Loss Threshold">
          <t>&gt;&gt;&gt; Comment: this section is a placeholder</t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section title="One-way Delay, First-bit to Last bit, RFC 2679">
        <t>This test determines if implementations register the same relative
        increase in delay from one measurement to another under different
        delay conditions. This test tends to cancel the sources of error which
        may be present in an implementation.</t>

        <t>See Section 3.7.2 of <xref target="RFC2679"></xref>, and Section
        10.2 of <xref target="RFC2330"></xref>.</t>

        <t><list style="numbers">
            <t>configure an L2TPv3 path between test sites, and each pair of
            measurement devices to operate tests in their designated pair of
            VLANs, and ideally including a low-speed link</t>

            <t>measure (average) one-way delay with 2 or more implementations,
            using identical options and equal size small packets (e.g., 100
            octet IP payload)</t>

            <t>maintain the same path with X ms one-way delay</t>

            <t>measure (average) one-way delay with 2 or more implementations,
            using identical options and equal size large packets (e.g., 1500
            octet IP payload)</t>

            <t>observe that the increase measured in steps 2 and 4 is
            equivalent to the increase in ms expected due to the larger
            serialization time for each implementation. Most of the
            measurement errors in each system should cancel, if they are
            stationary.</t>
          </list></t>

        <section title="NetProbe Lab results for Serialization">
          <t>For this test only, the link between the NetProbe Source host and
          the NIST Net emulator host was changed to 10baseT-FD (10Mbps full
          duplex) as configured by "mii-tool".</t>

          <t>When the UDP payload size was increased from 32 octets to 1400
          octets, the NIST Net emulator exhibited a bi-modal delay
          distribution. Investigation confirmed that the NetProbe
          implementations tested did not exhibit bi-modal delay on an
          alternate (network management) path.</t>

          <t><figure
              title="Average Delay over 60 packets for different payload sizes with Delay computations and comparison with expected delay difference for serialization.">
              <preamble></preamble>

              <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[1400 byte payload   32 byte payload
Delay for each mode   (one mode)     Delay Diff    Expected Diff
  microseconds        microseconds   microseconds  microseconds
    1001621             1000356         1265         1094.4
    1002735             1000356         2379         1094.4]]></artwork>

              <postamble></postamble>
            </figure></t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section title="One-way Delay, Difference Sample Metric (Lab)">
        <t>This test determines if implementations register the same relative
        increase in delay from one measurement to another under different
        delay conditions. This test tends to cancel the sources of error which
        may be present in an implementation.</t>

        <t>This test is intended to evaluate measurements in sections 3 and 4
        of <xref target="RFC2679"></xref>.</t>

        <t><list style="numbers">
            <t>configure an L2TPv3 path between test sites, and each pair of
            measurement devices to operate tests in their designated pair of
            VLANs.</t>

            <t>measure (average) one-way delay with 2 or more implementations,
            using identical options</t>

            <t>configure the path with X+Y ms one-way delay</t>

            <t>repeat measurements</t>

            <t>observe that the (average) increase measured in steps 2 and 4
            is ~Y ms for each implementation. Most of the measurement errors
            in each system should cancel, if they are stationary.</t>
          </list></t>

        <section title="NetProbe Lab results for Differential Delay">
          <t>In this test, X=1000ms and Y=2000ms.</t>

          <t><figure title="Average delays before/after 2 second increase">
              <preamble></preamble>

              <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[Average pre-increase delay, microseconds        1000276.6
Average post 2s additional, microseconds        3000282.6
Difference (should be ~= Y = 2s)                2000006]]></artwork>

              <postamble></postamble>
            </figure></t>

          <t>The NetProbe implementation exhibited a 2 second increase with a
          6 microsecond error (assuming that the NIST Net emulated delay
          difference is exact).</t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section title="Implementation of Statistics for One-way Delay">
        <t>The ADK tests the extent to which the sample distributions of
        one-way delay singletons from two implementations of <xref
        target="RFC2679"></xref> appear to be from the same overall
        distribution. By testing this way, we economize on the number of
        comparisons, because comparing a set of individual summary statistics
        (as defined in Section 5 of <xref target="RFC2679"></xref>) would
        require another set of individual evaluations of equivalence. Instead,
        we can simply check which statistics were implemented, and report on
        those facts, noting that Section 5 of <xref target="RFC2679"></xref>
        does not specify the calculations exactly, and gives only some
        illustrative examples.<figure>
            <preamble></preamble>

            <artwork><![CDATA[                                              NetProbe    Perfas

5.1. Type-P-One-way-Delay-Percentile            yes

5.2. Type-P-One-way-Delay-Median                yes

5.3. Type-P-One-way-Delay-Minimum               yes

5.4. Type-P-One-way-Delay-Inverse-Percentile    no


]]></artwork>

            <postamble>Implementation of Section 5 Statistics</postamble>
          </figure></t>

        <t>5.1. Type-P-One-way-Delay-Percentile 5.2.
        Type-P-One-way-Delay-Median 5.3. Type-P-One-way-Delay-Minimum 5.4.
        Type-P-One-way-Delay-Inverse-Percentile</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>The security considerations that apply to any active measurement of
      live networks are relevant here as well. See <xref
      target="RFC4656"></xref> and <xref target="RFC5357"></xref>.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>This memo makes no requests of IANA, and hopes that IANA will be as
      accepting of our new computer overlords as the authors intend to be.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>The authors thank Lars Eggert for his continued encouragement to
      advance the IPPM metrics during his tenure as AD Advisor.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119"?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.2026'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.2330'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.2679'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.2680'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.3432'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.4656'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.4814'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.5226'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.5357'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.5657'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-ippm-metrictest'?>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.morton-ippm-advance-metrics'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.3931'?>
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>