<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl'
href='http://xml.resource.org/authoring/rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<rfc category="std" docName="draft-wu-avt-retransmission-supression-rtp-04"
     ipr="pre5378Trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="Feedback Suppression">RTCP Report Extension for Feedback
    Suppression</title>

    <author fullname="Qin Wu" initials="Q." surname="Wu">
      <organization>Huawei</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>101 Software Avenue, Yuhua District</street>

          <city>Nanjing</city>

          <region>Jiangsu</region>

          <code>210012</code>

          <country>China</country>
        </postal>

        <email>sunseawq@huawei.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Frank Xia" initials="F." surname="Xia">
      <organization>Huawei</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>1700 Alma Dr. Suite 500</street>

          <city>Plano</city>

          <region>TX 75075</region>

          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>

        <phone>+1 972-509-5599</phone>

        <email>xiayangsong@huawei.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Roni Even" initials="R." surname="Even">
      <organization>Huawei</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>14 David Hamelech</street>

          <region>Tel Aviv 64953</region>

          <country>Israel</country>
        </postal>

        <email>even.roni@huawei.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date month="October" year="2010" />

    <workgroup>Network Working Group</workgroup>

    <abstract>
      <t>When packet loss close to the media source or intermediary of the
      session is detected as a loss by a large number of receivers, large
      number of feedback requests used to ask for the lost RTP packets are all
      addressed to the same media source, or a designated feedback target.
      This may result in a phenomenon known variously as a "feedback storm "
      or "feedback implosion ". </t>

      <t>This document specifies an extension to the RTCP feedback messages
      defined in the Audio-Visual Profile with Feedback (AVPF). This extension
      allows an intermediate node in the network (such as an RTP translator)
      inform downstream receivers that packet loss was detected and sending a
      feedback message concerning a specified set of RTP packets may be
      unnecessary, or even harmful. Receivers respond to receipt of a feedback
      suppression message by not sending a feedback message (e.g. a NACK) that
      they otherwise would, This in turn reduces load on both the feedback
      target and on the network. The proposed extension is useful for
      single-source multicast sessions. In addition, it can be applied to any
      other types of RTP sessions and topologies that might benefit from
      feedback suppression mechanism.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>RTCP feedback messages <xref target="RFC4585"></xref>allow the
      receivers in an RTP session to report events and ask for action from the
      media source (or a delegated feedback target). There are cases where
      multiple receivers may initiate the same, or an equivalent message
      towards the same media source. When the receiver count is large, this
      behavior may overload the media source or the network or both. One
      common case is receivers utilizing RTP retransmission as a packet loss
      recovery technique in a real-time application such as streaming video or
      audio.<xref target="RFC4585"></xref>Feedback is accomplished using the
      RTCP NACK message which conveys the RTP sequence number(s) of the lost
      packet(s). This information can then be used by the media or
      distribution source to retransmit the missing RTP packets using the RTP
      retransmission payload format<xref target="RFC4588"></xref>.</t>

      <t>However, in topologies utilizing transport translators
      (Topo-Trn-Translator) or large-scale multicast transmission
      (Topo-Multicast) as defined in <xref target="RFC5117"></xref>, packet
      loss can occur on either an upstream link or a downstream aggregate link
      of the intermediate network element (e.g., Retransmission server,
      Distribution Source). Where there are many receivers, this may result in
      a Feedback implosion <xref target="RFC5740"></xref> towards the media or
      distribution source, i.e., large number of feedback requests to the same
      multicast sender for retransmission of the same RTP packets. This
      phenomenon goes by a number of alternate names, such as the "feedback
      storm" or the “NACK storm” terminology of <xref
      target="DVB-IPTV"></xref>. In an attempt to increase its robustness
      against the loss of a feedback message or of retransmission packets, a
      receiver may send multiple feedbacks for the same detected packet loss,
      which may aggravate the feedback implosion.</t>

      <t>Another use case involves video Fast Update requests. A storm of
      these feedback messages can occur in conversational multimedia scenarios
      like Topo-Video-switch-MCU <xref target="RFC5117"></xref>. In this
      scenario, packet loss may happen on an upstream link of an intermediate
      network element such as a Multipoint Control Unit(MCU). Receivers
      missing the packets issue fast update requests (i.e., Full Intra
      Request(FIR) described in [RFC5104]), which results in an implosion of
      FIR requests from receivers to the same media source.</t>

      <t>As these feedback storms propagate (e.g., NACK implosion or Fast
      update implosion), the network may be permeated with more and more
      feedback traffic, resulting in a positive feedback loop as the network
      is also saturated with media traffic. RTCP feedback storms may cause
      short term overload and, and in extreme cases to pose a possible risk of
      increasing network congestion on the control channel (e.g. RTCP
      feedback), the data channel (i.e. RTP retransmission), or Both if the
      receivers are not correctly implemented </t>

      <t>In order to mitigate these behaviors, the current text in <xref
      target="RFC5760"></xref> allows the distribution source to filter out
      the NACK messages and <xref target="DVB-IPTV"></xref> suggests sending a
      NACK message from server to the client (or receiver). However NACK is
      defined as a receiver report sent from a client to the server and
      therefore exhibits a semantic mismatch when used as a suppression
      indication from the server (or intermediary) to the client. This
      document instead specifies a newly message for this function. It further
      is more precise in the intended uses and less likely to be confusing to
      receivers. It tells receivers explicitly that feedback for a particular
      packet loss is not needed and can provide an early indication before the
      receiver reacts to the loss and invokes its packet loss repair
      machinery.</t>

      <t>Receivers respond to receipt of a feedback suppression message by not
      sending a feedback message (e.g. a NACK) that they otherwise would, This
      in turn reduces load on both the feedback target and on the network.
      </t>

      <t>Also the intermediate node may initiate its own feedback toward the
      media source to provoke a retransmission. When the media source receives
      the request from the intermediate node, the media source resends the
      lost packets to the receivers by using the RTP retransmission payload
      format <xref target="RFC4588"></xref> or resends a new refresh point for
      FIR Initiator <xref target="RFC5104"></xref>, depending on the type of
      feedback it received.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Terminology">
      <t>The keywords "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
      document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
      target="RFC2119"></xref>.</t>

      <t><list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="Loss Detector:"><vspace blankLines="1" /> The Loss
          Detector is one logical function which is used to detect the packet
          loss at the RTP layer and report it to the distribution source. The
          function of the loss reporter may be collocated with or integrated
          into the same entity. In this case, for a session defined as having
          a distribution source A, on ports n for the RTP channel and k for
          the RTCP channel, the Loss Detector are identified by an IP address
          of distribution source A on port k. The Loss Detector MAY also be
          implemented in one or more entities different from the distribution
          source. </t>
        </list></t>
    </section>

    <section title="Protocol Overview">
      <t> This document extend the RTCP feedback messages defined in the
      Audio-Visual Profile with Feedback (AVPF) and define the Feedback
      Suppression message. The Feedback Suppression message asks a receiver to
      not send feedback messages for particular packets (indicated by their
      RTP sequence numbers) independent of whether the receiver detected the
      packet loss or detected a need for a decoder refresh point).</t>

      <t>In order to detect packet loss before the receivers perceive it, one
      or more intermediate nodes are placed between the media source and
      receiver (e.g., Distribution server, MCU, RTP translator). These
      intermediaries monitor for packet loss upstream of themselves by
      checking RTP sequence numbers, just as receivers do. Upon detecting (or
      suspecting) an upstream loss, the intermediary may send Feedback
      Suppression message towards the receivers as defined in this
      specification.</t>

      <t>Instead of using specialized intermediaries, another possibility is
      to instantiate one or more RTP receivers upstream of the loss region to
      act as immediate reporters as described in<xref
      target="DVB-IPTV"></xref>. These intermediate nodes need to take into
      account such factors as the tolerable application delay, the network
      dynamics, and the media type. When the packet loss is detected upstream
      of the intermediary and additional latency is tolerable, the
      intermediate node may itself send a feedback message asking for the
      suspected lost packet or ask for the correct decoder refresh point.
      Because it has already provided the necessary feedback toward the
      source, the intermediate node can be reasonably certain that it will
      help the situation by sending a Feedback Suppression message to all the
      relevant receivers, thereby indicating that the receivers should not
      themselves transmit feedback messages. </t>

      <t>RTCP Feedback Storm Suppression follows the same semantic model as
      RTCP NACK - it conveys the packet receipt/loss events at the sequence
      number level and considers missing packets as unrepaired. But unlike
      RTCP NACK, the Feedback Suppression messages can be generated at
      intermediate nodes who are not RTP receivers and sent to the
      corresponding receivers. Intermediaries downstream of an intermediary
      detecting loss obviously SHOULD NOT initiate their own additional
      feedback suppression messages for the same packet sequence numbers. They
      may either simply forward the Feedback Suppression message received from
      upstream, or augment (or replace) it with a feedback suppression message
      that reflects the loss pattern they have themselves seen.</t>

      <t>Since feedback suppression interacts strongly with repair timing, it
      has to work together with feedback to not adversely impact the repair of
      lost source packets. In some cases where the loss was detected and
      repair initiated much closer to the source, the delay for the receiver
      to recover from packet loss can be reduced through the combination of
      intermediary feedback to the source and feedback suppression downstream.
      In all (properly operating) cases, the risk of increasing network
      congestion is decreased. A receiver may still have sent a Feedback
      message before receiving a feedback suppression message, but further
      feedback messages for those sequence numbers will be suppressed by this
      technique.</t>

      <t>This document registers two new RTCP Feedback messages for Feedback
      Suppression. Applications that are employing one or more loss-repair
      methods MAY use Feedback Suppression together with their existing
      loss-repair methods either for every packet they expect to receive, or
      for an application-specific subset of the RTP packets in a session. In
      other words, receivers MAY ignore Feedback Suppression messages, but
      SHOULD react to them unless they have good reason to still send feedback
      messages despite having been requested to suppress them.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="RTCP Feedback Report Extension">
      <section title="Transport Layer Feedback:  NACK Suppression Report">
        <t>The NACK implosion Suppression message is an extension to the RTCP
        feedback report and identified by RTCP packet type value PT=RTPFB and
        FMT=TBD.</t>

        <t>The FCI field MUST contain one or more NACK Suppression Early
        Indication (NSEI) entries. Each entry applies to a different media
        source, identified by its SSRC.</t>

        <t>The Feedback Control Information (FCI) for NSEI uses the similar
        format of message Types defined in the section 4.3.1.1 of <xref
        target="RFC5104"></xref>. The format is shown in <xref
        target="fig2"></xref>.</t>

        <figure align="center" anchor="fig2"
                title="Message Format for the NSEI report">
          <artwork>
     0                   1                   2                   3
    0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |                              SSRC                             |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |            PID                |             BLP               |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
</artwork>
        </figure>

        <t><list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="SSRC (32 bits):"><vspace blankLines="1" />The SSRC
            value of the media source that is requested to send the lost
            packet.<vspace blankLines="1" /></t>

            <t hangText="Packet ID (PID): 16 bits"><vspace blankLines="1" />
            The PID field is used to specify a lost packet. The PID field
            refers to the RTP sequence number of the lost packet.<vspace
            blankLines="1" /></t>

            <t
            hangText="bitmask of following lost packets (BLP): 16 bits"><vspace
            blankLines="1" /> The BLP allows for reporting losses of any of
            the 16 RTP packets immediately following the RTP packet indicated
            by the PID. The BLP's definition is identical to that given in
            <xref target="RFC4585"></xref>.<vspace blankLines="1" /></t>
          </list></t>
      </section>

      <section title="Payload Specific Feedback: FIR suppression report">
        <t>The FIR implosion Suppression message is an extension to the RTCP
        receiver feedback report and identified by RTCP packet type value
        PT=PSFB and FMT=TBD.</t>

        <t>The FCI field MUST contain one or more FIR suppression Early
        Indication (FSEI) entries. Each entry applies to a different media
        source, identified by its SSRC.</t>

        <t>The Feedback Control Information (FCI) for FSEI uses the similar
        format of message Types defined in the section 4.3.1.1 of <xref
        target="RFC5104"></xref>. The format is shown in <xref
        target="fig3"></xref>.</t>

        <figure align="center" anchor="fig3"
                title="Message Format for the FSEI report">
          <artwork>
     0                   1                   2                   3
    0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |                              SSRC                             |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |     Seq nr.   |                   Reserved                    |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+ 
</artwork>
        </figure>

        <t><list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="SSRC (32 bits): "><vspace blankLines="1" />The SSRC
            value of the media source that is requested to send a decoder
            refresh point.<vspace blankLines="1" /></t>

            <t hangText="Seq nr:8bits">Command sequence number. The sequence
            number space is unique for each pairing of the SSRC of command
            source and the SSRC of the command target. The sequence number
            SHALL be increased by 1 modulo 256 for each new command.<vspace
            blankLines="1" /></t>

            <t hangText="Reserved: 24 bits"><vspace blankLines="1" />All bits
            SHALL be set to 0 by the media source and SHALL be ignored on
            reception.<vspace blankLines="1" /></t>
          </list></t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="SDP Signaling">
      <t>A new feedback value “fss” needs to be defined for the Feedback Storm
      Suppression message to be used with Session Description Protocol
      (SDP)<xref target="RFC4566"></xref> using the Augmented Backus-Naur Form
      (ABNF)<xref target="RFC4585"></xref>.</t>

      <t>The "fss" feedback value SHOULD be used with parameters that indicate
      the feedback suppression supported. In this document, we define two such
      parameters, namely:<vspace blankLines="1" /><list style="symbols">
          <t>"fsei" denotes support of fir suppression early indication
          (fsei).<vspace blankLines="1" /></t>

          <t>“nsei” denotes support of NACK suppression early indication.</t>
        </list><vspace blankLines="1" />In the ABNF for rtcp-fb-val defined in
      <xref target="RFC4585"></xref>, there is a placeholder called rtcp-fb-id
      to define new feedback types. "fss" is defined as a new feedback type in
      this document, and the ABNF for the parameters for fss is defined here
      (please refer to section 4.2 of <xref target="RFC4585"></xref> for
      complete ABNF syntax).</t>

      <figure align="center">
        <artwork>
rtcp-fb-val        =/ "fss" rtcp-fb-fss-param
rtcp-fb-fss-param  = SP "nsei";nack suppression early indication
                    / SP “fsei”;fir suppression early indication
                    / SP token [SP byte-string]
                              ; for future commands/indications
   byte-string = &lt;as defined in section 4.2 of [RFC4585] &gt;
</artwork>
      </figure>

      <t>Refer to Section 4.2 of <xref target="RFC4585"></xref> for a detailed
      description and the full syntax of the "rtcp-fb" attribute.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Example Use Cases">
      <t>The operation of feedback suppression is similar for all types of RTP
      sessions and topologies <xref target="RFC5117"></xref>, however the
      exact messages used and the scenarios in which suppression is employed
      differ for various use cases. The following sections outline the
      intended use cases for feedback suppression and give an overview of the
      particular mechanisms.</t>

      <section title="Source Specific Multicast (SSM) use case">
        <t>In SSM RTP sessions as described in <xref target="RFC5760"></xref>,
        one or more Media Sources send RTP packets to a Distribution Source.
        The Distribution Source relays the RTP packets to the receivers using
        a source-specific multicast group.</t>

        <t>In order to avoid the forms of NACK implosion described in section
        1, the Loss Detector is introduced. The Loss Detector detects and
        reports packet loss, on both the upstream link and the downstream
        aggregate link. How the loss detector SHOULD detect the packet loss is
        beyond of scope of this document. When upstream link or downstream
        aggregate link packet loss occurs, the Loss Detector MAY inform
        distribution source of the detected packet loss using Feedback
        Suppression messages. In response, the distribution source either
        forwards packet loss suppression report received from Loss Detector or
        creates a Feedback Suppression report and sends it to all the RTP
        receivers, over the multicast channel. This loss suppression report
        tells the receivers that the lost packet will either be forthcoming
        from distribution source, or it irretrievably lost such that there is
        nothing to be gained by the receiver sending a NACK to the media
        source. The distribution source then can (optionally) ask for the lost
        packets from the media source on behalf of all the RTP receivers. </t>

        <t>When the Loss Detector(s) are part of a feedback target collocated
        with the distribution source, redistribution of the feedback
        suppression report is trivial. In such cases, the Loss Detector
        function in the feedback target detects packet loss coming from an
        upstream link and informs the collocated distribution source. Also the
        Loss Detector may detect packet loss occurring within distribution
        source itself and report to distribution source using the same method.
        When the Loss Detector(s) are physically and(or) topologically
        distinct from distribution source, each Loss Detector MUST create a
        packet loss report using the similar format as conventional RTCP NACK
        packets at the RTP layer and send it to the distribution source . </t>

        <t>The distribution source must be able to communicate with all group
        members in order for either mechanism to be effective at suppressing
        feedback. The general architecture is displayed below in Figure 1.</t>

        <t>The distribution Source must be able to communicate with all group
        members in order for either mechanism to be effective at suppressing
        feedback. The general architecture is displayed below in <xref
        target="fig1"></xref><figure align="center" anchor="fig1"
            title="System Architecture">
            <artwork>
+--------+         +------------+       Source-specific
|Media   |         |            |          Multicast
|Source 1|&lt;-------&gt;|            |     +----------------&gt; R(1)
+--------+         |Distribution|     |
                   |  SOURCE    |  +--+
+--------+         |            |  |  |
|Media   |&lt;-------&gt;|            |  |  +-----------&gt; R(2)
|Source 2|         | Feedback   |-&gt;+  +---- :
+--------+         |+ Target --+|  |  +------&gt; R(n-1)
    :              || +---+    ||  |  |
    :              || |  D|    ||  +--+--&gt; R(n)
                   || |  E|    ||
+--------+         || |L T|    ||
|Media   |         || |O E|    ||
|Source M|&lt;---- --&gt;|| |S C|    ||
+--------+         || |S T|    ||
                   || |  O|    ||
                   || |  R|    ||
                   || +---+    ||
                   |+----------+|
                   +------------+         
      Transport of packet loss informationfrom the Loss Detector to the 
      Feedback Target is via unicast RTCP feedback if the two are not
      co-located.

</artwork>
          </figure>In this figure, we assume the distribution source is
        separated from a particular media source and the Loss Detector is part
        of feedback target collocated with Distribution source. The
        communication between the media source and the distribution source is
        compliant with the methods described in <xref
        target="RFC5760"></xref>. Configuration information also follows <xref
        target="RFC5760"></xref>, with the following additional
        considerations:<vspace blankLines="1" /><list style="symbols">
            <t>The Loss Detectors know the addresses of their respectively
            responsible Feedback Targets.</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>As outlined in the <xref target="RFC5760"></xref>, there are two
        Unicast Feedback models that may be used for reporting, - the Simple
        Feedback model and the Distribution Source Feedback Summary Model. The
        RTCP Feedback Suppression report extension specified in the section 4
        of this document will work in both Feedback models. Details of
        operation in each are specified below.</t>

        <section title="Simple Feedback Model">
          <t> In the simple Feedback Model, the Loss reporter instance(s)are
          distributed into two different distribution sources. e.g., upstream
          distribution source may act as the loss detector of downstream of
          distribution source. </t>

          <t> The Loss Detector MUST listen on the corresponding RTP session
          for data. When the Loss Detector observes that a sequence of RTP
          packets from a media source contains gaps (by checking the sequence
          number of packets), the Loss Detector MUST use the same packet types
          as traditional RTCP feedback described in <xref
          target="RFC3550"></xref> and create one new RTCP Feedback Report
          with information on the RTP sequence number of the lost packets and
          suppression early indication event. When the Loss Detector is
          eligible to transmit, it MUST send this Report packet to the
          distribution source via feedback. </t>

          <t> The Distribution Source (unicast Feedback Target) MUST listen
          for RTCP data sent to the RTCP port. Upon receiving the RTCP
          Feedback Report packet from the Loss Detector, the Distribution
          Source MUST forward it to the group on the multicast RTCP session.
          Every RTCP packet from each Loss Detector MUST be reflected
          individually. </t>

          <t>If there are multiple Loss Detectors looking at the same RTP
          stream, then the loss may be identified by more than one and those
          detecting the loss will all send requests for the same packet loss.
          In this case, the distribution source MUST filter the duplicated
          packet loss request out and only forward one copy of the RTCP
          Feedback report packet from the first Loss Detector to the group
          impacted by packet loss.</t>

          <t>This RTCP Feedback Report lets the receivers know that feedback
          for this packet loss is not needed and SHOULD NOT be sent to the
          media source(s). If the media source(s) are part of the SSM group
          for RTCP packet reflection, the Distribution Source MUST filter this
          packet out. If the media source(s) are not part of the SSM group for
          RTCP packets, the Distribution Source MUST not forward this RTCP
          packets received from the receivers to the media source(s).</t>

          <t>When the receiver receives the RTCP packet, if the receiver
          understands the message it will not send feedback (e.g., NACK) for
          the missing packets reported in the message and will accept a
          retransmission packet (if forthcoming) transmitted from the
          Distribution Source. If it did not understand the Feedback
          Suppression report the receiver MAY of course still send feedback
          messages to the specified media source. When the distribution source
          receives a feedback message reporting loss from one or more
          receivers after it has already detected packet loss or gotten a NACK
          feedback message from Loss Detector, the distribution source MUST
          filter them out until proactive recovery is complete.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Distribution Source Feedback Summary Model">
          <t> In the distribution source feedback summary model, the Loss
          Detector instances may be distributed into different distribution
          sources. In some cases, several Loss Detector instances for the same
          session can exist at the same time, e.g., one Loss Detector instance
          (Loss Detector A) is implemented in the upstream distribution source
          A, one Loss Detector instance (Loss Detector B) is implemented in
          the upstream distribution source B, another Loss Detector instance
          for the same session (Loss Detector C) is part of feedback target
          within the distribution source C. In this section, we focus on this
          generic case to discuss the distribution Source Feedback Summary
          Model. </t>

          <t>The Loss Detector A and the Loss Detector B MUST listen on the
          RTP channel for data. When the Loss Detector observes RTP packets
          from a media source are not consecutive by checking the sequence
          number of packets, the Loss Detector generates NACK message
          described in<xref target="RFC4585"></xref> or generates the new RTCP
          Feedback Report packet described in the section 6, and then send
          either of them to the distribution source via feedback.</t>

          <t>The Distribution Source (unicast Feedback Target) MUST listen for
          unicast RTCP data sent to the RTCP port. Upon receiving the unicast
          RTCP Feedback Report packet from the Loss Detector, the distribution
          source needs to filter them out, i.e., identify these unicast RTCP
          packets coming from the Dedicated receivers (i.e.,Loss Detector A
          and Loss Detector B)based on the IP address of Loss Detectors or
          dedicated RTCP port for loss report, then summarize the information
          received from all the RTCP Feedback Reports generated by the
          Dedicated receivers together with the information generated by the
          Loss Detector integrated in the feedback target and then create the
          summary report to include all these information. In order to reduce
          the processing load at the distribution source, the individual
          instance of Loss Detector MAY provide preliminary summarization
          report.</t>

          <t>During the summary report creating, the Distribution Source MUST
          use its own SSRC value for transmitting summarization information
          and MUST perform proper SSRC collision detection and resolution.</t>

          <t>In some case, the distribution source MAY receive RTCP NACK
          messages from the receivers behind the Distribution Source before
          the distribution source detects the packet loss which may cause
          potential Feedback implosion. In such case, the distribution source
          MAY filter them out if it already sent a packet loss request for the
          missing packet to the media source. When the distribution source
          confirms packet loss reported by the receiver, the distribution
          source generates the summary report to include the packet loss
          information from the corresponding receiver (e.g., upstream Loss
          Detector).</t>

          <t>The distribution source MAY send this new RTCP summary report
          described in the section 6 to the group on the multicast RTCP
          channel and in the meanwhile sending a packet loss request to the
          media source.</t>

          <t>If there are a couple of loss reporters looking at the same RTP
          stream, then the loss may be identified by all and they will all
          send requests for the same packet loss. In this case, the
          distribution source MUST filter out the duplicated information from
          various Loss Detectors and only append one copy of such information
          to the summary report.</t>

          <t>When the host receives the RTCP packet, if the host understands
          this message it will not send packet loss request (e.g., NACK) for
          the missing packets reported in the message. If it did not
          understand this new message, the host MAY send packet loss
          request(e.g., NACK messages) to the specified media source. When the
          distribution source receives the packet loss request from the hosts
          after it has already detected packet loss, the distribution source
          MUST filter it out until proactive recovery is complete.</t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section title="RTP transport translator use case">
        <t>A Transport Translator (Topo-Trn-Translator), as defined in <xref
        target="RFC5117"></xref> is typically forwarding the RTP and RTCP
        traffic between RTP clients, for example converting between multicast
        and unicast for domains that do not support multicast. The translator
        can identify packet loss from the upstream and send the Feedback
        Suppression message to the unicast receivers. The translator can also
        serve as a loss reporter on the multicast side as described in the SSM
        case.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Multipoint Control Unit (MCU) use case">
        <t>In point to multipoint topologies using video switching MCU
        (Topo-Video-switch-MCU) <xref target="RFC5117"></xref>, the MCU
        typically forwards a single media stream to each participant, selected
        from the available input streams. The selection of the input stream is
        often based on voice activity in the audio-visual conference, but
        other conference management mechanisms (like presentation mode or
        explicit floor control) exist as well.</t>

        <t>In this case the MCU MAY detect packet loss from the sender or may
        decide to switch to a new source. In both cases the receiver MAY lose
        synchronization with the video stream and MAY send a FIR request. If
        the MCU itself can detect the mis-synchronization of the video, the
        MCU can send the FIR suppression message to the receivers and send a
        FIR request to the video source.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Security Considerations">
      <t>The defined messages have certain properties that have security
      implications. These must be addressed and taken into account by users of
      this protocol.</t>

      <t>Spoofed or maliciously created feedback messages of the type defined
      in this specification can have the following implications:</t>

      <t>Sending NACK Suppression Report with wrong sequence number of lost
      packet that makes missing RTP packets can not be compensated.</t>

      <t>Sending FIR Suppression Report with wrong sequence number of lost
      packet that makes missing RTP packets can not be compensated by update
      request mechanism.</t>

      <t>To prevent these attacks, there is a need to apply authentication and
      integrity protection of the feedback messages. This can be accomplished
      against threats external to the current RTP session using the RTP
      profile that combines Secure RTP <xref target="RFC3711"></xref> and AVPF
      into SAVPF <xref target="RFC5124"></xref>.</t>

      <t>Note that middleboxes that are not visible at the RTP layer that wish
      to send NACK/FIR suppression reports on behalf of the media source can
      only do so if they spoof the SSRC of the media source. This is difficult
      in case SRTP is in use. If the middlebox is visible at the RTP layer,
      this is not an issue, provided the middlebox is part of the security
      context for the session.</t>

      <t>Also note that endpoints that receive a NACK/FIR suppression request
      would be well-advised to ignore it, unless it is authenticated via SRTCP
      or similar. Accepting un-authenticated NACK/ FIR suppression requests
      can lead to a denial of service attack, where the endpoint accepts poor
      quality media that could be repaired. </t>
    </section>

    <section title="IANA Consideration">
      <t>New feedback type and New parameters for RTCP FSS receiver feedback
      report are subject to IANA registration. For general guidelines on IANA
      considerations for RTCP feedback, refer to <xref
      target="RFC4585"></xref>.</t>

      <t>This document assigns one new feedback type value x in the RTCP
      feedback report registry to “Feedback Storm Suppression” with the
      following registrations format:</t>

      <figure align="center">
        <artwork>
    Name:            FSS
    Long Name:       Feedback Storm Suppression
    Value:           TBD
    Reference:       This document.
</artwork>
      </figure>

      <t>This document also assigns the parameter value y in the RTCP FSS
      feedback report Registry to "NACK Suppression Early Indication ", with
      the following registrations format:</t>

      <figure>
        <artwork align="center">
     Name:           NSEI
     Long name:      NACK Suppression Early Indication
     Value:          TBD
     Reference:      this document.
</artwork>
      </figure>

      <t>This document also assigns the parameter value z in the RTCP FSS
      feedback report Registry to "FIR Suppression Early Indication ", with
      the following registrations format:</t>

      <figure align="center">
        <artwork>
     Name:           FSEI
     Long name:      FIR Suppression Early Indication
     Value:          TBD
     Reference:      this document.
</artwork>
      </figure>

      <t>The contact information for the registrations is: <figure>
          <artwork> 
  Qin Wu
  sunseawq@huawei.com
  101 Software Avenue, Yuhua District
  Nanjing, Jiangsu  210012, China
</artwork>
        </figure></t>
    </section>

    <section title="Acknowledgement">
      <t>The authors would like to thank David R Oran, Ali C. Begen, Colin
      Perkins,Tom VAN CAENEGEM, Ingemar Johansson S, Bill Ver Steeg, WeeSan
      Lee for their valuable comments and suggestions on this document.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5760"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4585"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3550"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5117"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4588"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4566"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5234"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5104"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3711"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5124"?>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <reference anchor="RFC5740">
        <front>
          <title>NACK-Oriented Reliable Multicast (NORM) Transport
          Protocol</title>

          <author fullname="Brian Adamson" initials="B." surname="Adamson">
            <organization>Naval Research Laboratory</organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="Carsten Bormann" initials="C." surname="Bormann">
            <organization>Universitaet Bremen TZI</organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="Mark Handley " initials="M." surname="Handley">
            <organization>University College London</organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="Joe Macker" initials="J." surname="Macker">
            <organization>Naval Research Laboratory</organization>
          </author>

          <date month="November" year="2009" />
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="DVB-IPTV">
        <front>
          <title>Digital Video Broadcasting(DVB); Transport of MPEG-2 TS Based
          DVB Services over IP Based Networks</title>

          <author>
            <organization>ETSI Standard</organization>
          </author>

          <date month="August" year="2009" />
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="ETSI TS 102 034, V1.4.1" value="" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="I-D.hunt-avt-monarch-01">
        <front>
          <title>Monitoring Architectures for RTP</title>

          <author fullname="Geoff Hunt" initials="G." surname="Hunt">
            <organization>BT</organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="Philip Arden" initials="P." surname="Arden">
            <organization>BT</organization>
          </author>

          <date month="August" year="2008" />
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="I-D.ietf-pmol-metrics-framework-02">
        <front>
          <title>Framework for Performance Metric Development</title>

          <author fullname="Alan Clark " initials="A." surname="Clark">
            <organization>Telchemy Incorporated</organization>
          </author>

          <date />
        </front>
      </reference>
    </references>

    <section anchor="P-1" title="Example scenarios for NACK Implosion">
      <t>In SSM RTP sessions as described in <xref target="RFC5760"></xref>,
      there may have more than one distribution source between the media
      source and the receivers. In order for loss repair, the distribution
      source may choose to include the support for retransmission as part of
      the offered SDP and will expect such support from the media source.The
      following section outline several example scenarios for NACK Implosion.
      </t>

      <section anchor="S-1"
               title="Scenario 1: One or more media source, One distribution source">
        <t>The scenario 1 is displayed below in <xref target="F-A-1"></xref>.
        In this scenario, one or more Media Sources send RTP packets to the
        RTP Receivers through the same Distribution Source. The Distribution
        Source relays the RTP packets to the receivers using a source-specific
        multicast channel. In the reverse direction, the receivers transmit
        RTCP packets via unicast to the distribution source. The Distribution
        Source in turn relays RTCP packets to the media souce and then
        transmits the RTCP packets back to the receivers, using
        source-specific multicast. <figure anchor="F-A-1"
            title="One media Source, one Distribution Source">
            <artwork>
                                              +-------+
                                        |----&gt;|RTP_Rx1|
+--------+                              |     +-------+
|        |       +--------------+       |
|        |       |              |       |     +-------+
| Media  |-------| Distribution |-------|----&gt;|RTP_Rx2|
|        |       |   Source     |       |     +-------+
| Source |       |              |       |         .
|        |       +--------------+       |         .
|        |                              |         .
+--------+                              |     +-------+
                                        |----&gt;|RTP_Rxn|
                                              +-------+
</artwork>
          </figure></t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="S-2"
               title="Scenario 2:One media source, Two distribution sources in cascade">
        <figure anchor="F-A-2"
                title="One media source, Two distribution sources in cascade">
          <artwork>
                                               +-------+
                                         |----&gt;|RTP_Rx1|
                                         |     +-------+
+------+                                 |
|      | +------------+  +------------+  |     +-------+
|Media |-+Distribution+--|Distribution+--|----&gt;|RTP_Rx2|
|Source| |  Source1   |  |  Source2   |  |     +-------+
|      | +------------+  +------------+  |         .
+------+                                 |         .
                                         |         .
                                         |     +-------+
                                         |----&gt;|RTP_Rxn|
                                               +-------+

</artwork>
        </figure>

        <t>The scenario 2 is displayed below in <xref target="F-A-2"></xref>.
        In this scenario, One media source passes through two distribution
        source in cascading and sends RTP packets to all the RTP receivers. In
        this case, the distribution source 2 is located in the downstream
        direction of distribution source 1. </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="S-3"
               title="Scenario 3:One media source, Two distribution sources in parallel">
        <t>The scenario 3 is displayed below in <xref target="F-A-3"></xref>.
        In this scenario, the Media Sources send RTP packets to all the RTP
        receivers through two different path respectively. In each path, there
        is a distribution source. The distribution source1 is a neighboring
        node of distribution source 2.<figure anchor="F-A-3"
            title="One Media Source, more distribution sources">
            <artwork>
                                             +--------+
                                       |----&gt;|RTP_Rx11|
                                       |     +--------+
                   +--------------+    |
                   |              |    |     +--------+
              |---&gt;| Distribution |----|----&gt;|RTP_Rx12|
              |    |   Source1    |    |     +--------+
              |    |              |    |         .
 +--------+   |    +--------------+    |         .
 |        |   |                        |         .
 |        |   |                        |     +--------+
 | Media  |   |                        |----&gt;|RTP_Rx1k|
 |        |---|                              +--------+
 | Source |   |                              +--------+
 |        |   |                        |----&gt;|RTP_Rx21|
 |        |   |                        |     +--------+
 +--------+   |    +--------------+    |
              |    |              |    |     +--------+
              |    | Distribution |----|----&gt;|RTP_Rx22|
              |---&gt;|   Source2    |    |     +--------+
                   |              |    |         .
                   +--------------+    |         .
                                       |         .
                                       |     +--------+
                                       |----&gt;|RTP_Rx2j|
                                             +--------+
</artwork>
          </figure></t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="P-2" title="Applicability of Feedback Suppression">
      <t> This document defines new RTCP feedback Report, which we refer to as
      Feedback Suppression to deal with NACK Implosion mentioned above. Here
      we give two examples to show how this new RTCP feedback report is
      applied into three scenarios described in <xref
      target="P-1"></xref>.</t>

      <t>Applicability of Feedback Suppression in Scenario 1 described in
      <xref target="F-A-1"></xref> is shown in the <xref
      target="F-A-4"></xref>. In this figure, the distribution source detect
      the packet loss before the receiver perceive it and ask for
      retransmission of the lost packets from the media source on behalf of
      all the RTP receivers. , in the meanwhile, the distribution source
      transmits the RTCP Feedback Suppression Indication back to the receivers
      using source-specific multicast channel. Upon receiving the lost packet
      via the RTP retransmission payload format, the distribution source
      forwards the retransmitted packet to all the receivers. The receiver
      will accept a retransmission stream transmitted from the Distrbituion
      Source. </t>

      <t>When the distribution source receives a feedback message reporting
      loss from one or more receivers after it has already detected packet
      loss, the distribution source MUST filter them out until the
      Retransmission stream is ready in the Distrbitution Source. In this way,
      the delay for the receiver to recover from the packet loss can be
      reduced and the risk of increasing network congestion can be mitigated.
      </t>

      <figure anchor="F-A-4"
              title="Applicability of NACK Suppression Early Indication">
        <artwork>
+------+         +--------------+            +--------+
|Media |         | Distribution |            |        |
|Source|         |   Source     |            | RTP_Rx |
+--+---+         +------+-------+            +---+----+
   |                    |                        |
   |                    |                        |
   |-------------------&gt;|------RTP Multicast----&gt;|
   |                    |                        |
   |                    |                        |
   |           +--------+----------+             |
   |           |Detect Packet Loss |             |
   |           |and Identify the SN|             |
   |           |of missing Packets |             |
   |           +--------+----------+             |
   |&lt;-----RTCP NACK-----|                        |
   |                    |                        |
   |                    +--Multicast RTCP FSS---&gt;|
   | RTP Retransmission |                        |
   |-------------------&gt;|                        |
   |                    |------RTP Multicast----&gt;|
   |                    |     Retransmission     |
   |                    |                        |
   |                    |                        |
   |                    |                        |

</artwork>
      </figure>

      <t>Applicability of Feedback Suppression in Scenario 2 or 3 described in
      <xref target="F-A-2"></xref> and <xref target="F-A-3"></xref> is shown
      in the <xref target="F-A-5"></xref>. The procedure in the <xref
      target="F-A-5"></xref> is similar to the one in the figure <xref
      target="F-A-4"></xref>. The only difference is distribution source
      should not only notify all the receiver behind itself not to send NACK
      but also propagate the retransmission suppression indication to the
      neighboring distribution sources. In this way, all the receivers behind
      all the neighboring distribution source can avoid sending massive
      retransmission request to the media source.<figure anchor="F-A-5"
          title="Applicability of NACK Suppression Early Indication">
          <artwork>
+------+                   +--------+                     +--------+
|Media |     +-----+       | RTP_Rx |        +-----+      | RTP_Rx |
|Source|     | DS1 |       | served |        | DS2 |      | served |
+--+---+     +-----+       | by DS1 |        +-----+      | by DS2 |
   |            |          ----+----+           |         ----+----+
   |            |RTP Multicast |                |             |
   |-----------&gt;|-------------&gt;|                |             |
   |            |              |                |             |
   |            |              |                |RTP Multicast|
   |-------------------------------------------&gt;|------------&gt;|
   |            |              |                |             |
   |   +--------+------------+ |                |             |
   |   |Detect Packet Loss   | |                |             |
   |   |and Identify the SN  | |                |             |
   |   |of the missing Packets |                |             |
   |   +--------+------------+ |                |             |
   |            |              |                |             |
   |&lt;-RTCP NACK-| Multicast RTCP FSS            |             |
   |            |-------------&gt;|                |             |
   |            |              |                |             |
   |            |-----Unicast RTCP FSS --------&gt;|Multicast RTCP FSS
   |            |              |                |------------&gt;|
   |RTP Retransmission         |                |             |
   |-----------&gt;|              |                |             |
   |            |              |                |             |
   |            |  RTP Retransmission           |             |
   |------------+--------------+---------------&gt;|             |
   |            |              |                |             |
   |            | RTP Multicast|                | RTP Multicast
   |            |Retransmission|                |Retransmission
   |            |-------------&gt;|                |------------&gt;|
   |            |              |                |             |
DS1: Distribution Source 1
DS2: Distribution Source 2                   </artwork>
        </figure></t>
    </section>
  </back>
</rfc>
