<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl'
href='http://xml.resource.org/authoring/rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<rfc category="std" docName="draft-wu-avt-retransmission-supression-rtp-07"
     ipr="pre5378Trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="Feedback Suppression">RTCP Report Extension for Feedback
    Suppression</title>

    <author fullname="Qin Wu" initials="Q." surname="Wu">
      <organization>Huawei</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>101 Software Avenue, Yuhua District</street>

          <city>Nanjing</city>

          <region>Jiangsu</region>

          <code>210012</code>

          <country>China</country>
        </postal>

        <email>sunseawq@huawei.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Frank Xia" initials="F." surname="Xia">
      <organization>Huawei</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>1700 Alma Dr. Suite 500</street>

          <city>Plano</city>

          <region>TX 75075</region>

          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>

        <phone>+1 972-509-5599</phone>

        <email>xiayangsong@huawei.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Roni Even" initials="R." surname="Even">
      <organization>Huawei</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>14 David Hamelech</street>

          <region>Tel Aviv 64953</region>

          <country>Israel</country>
        </postal>

        <email>even.roni@huawei.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date month="November" year="2010" />

    <workgroup>Network Working Group</workgroup>

    <abstract>
      <t>In a large RTP session using the RTCP feedback mechanism defined in
      RFC 4585, a media source or middlebox may experience transient overload
      if some event causes a large number of receivers to send feedback at
      once. This feedback implosion can be mitigated if the device suffering
      from overload can send a feedback suppression message to the receivers
      to inhibit further feedback. This memo defines RTCP extensions for
      feedback suppression, to suppress NACK and FIR feedback requests. It
      also defines associated SDP signalling."</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>RTCP feedback messages <xref target="RFC4585"></xref> allow the
      receivers in an RTP session to report events and ask for action from the
      media source (or a delegated feedback target). There are cases where
      multiple receivers may initiate the same, or an equivalent message
      towards the same media source. When the receiver count is large, this
      behavior may cause transient overload of the media source,the network or
      both. This is known as a "feedback storm" or a "NACK storm". One common
      cause of such a feedback storm is receivers utilizing RTP retransmission
      <xref target="RFC4588"></xref> as a packet loss recovery technique
      based, sending feedback using RTCP NACK messages <xref
      target="RFC4585"></xref> without proper dithering of the retransmission
      requests.</t>

      <t>Another use case involves video Fast Update requests. A storm of
      these feedback messages can occur in conversational multimedia scenarios
      like Topo-Video-switch-MCU <xref target="RFC5117"></xref>. In this
      scenario, packet loss may happen on an upstream link of an intermediate
      network element such as a Multipoint Control Unit(MCU). Poorly designed
      receivers that blindly issue fast update requests (i.e., Full Intra
      Request (FIR) described in <xref target="RFC5104"></xref>), can cause an
      implosion of FIR requests from receivers to the same media source.</t>

      <t>RTCP feedback storms may cause short term overload and, and in
      extreme cases to pose a possible risk of increasing network congestion
      on the control channel (e.g. RTCP feedback), the data channel, or both.
      It is therefore desirable to provide a way of suppressing unneeded
      feedback.</t>

      <t>One approach to this, suggested in <xref target="DVB-IPTV"></xref>,
      involves sending a NACK message from server to the client (or receiver).
      However NACK is defined as a receiver report sent from a client to the
      server and therefore exhibits a semantic mismatch when used as a
      suppression indication from the server (or intermediary) to the client.
      This document instead specifies a newly message for this function. It
      further is more precise in the intended uses and less likely to be
      confusing to receivers. It tells receivers explicitly that feedback for
      a particular packet or frame loss is not needed for a period of time 
      and can provide an early indication before the receiver reacts to the loss 
      and invokes its packet loss repair machinery.</t>

      <t>Since feedback suppression interacts strongly with repair timing, it
      has to work together with feedback to not adversely impact the repair of
      lost source packets. One example is the middle box gets the retransmitted 
      packet by sending a NACK upstream and sent it downstream. This retransmitted
      packet was lost on the downstream link.In order to deal with this, the 
      downstream receiver can start a timeout in which it expected to get a 
      retransmission packet. When this timeout expires and there is no retransmitted 
      packet or a new suppression message, it can take its normal behavior as if there
      is no current retransmission suppression.In some cases where the loss was detected 
      and repair initiated much closer to the source, the delay for the receiver to 
      recover from packet loss can be reduced through the combination of intermediary 
      feedback to the source and feedback suppression downstream. In all (properly operating) 
      cases, the risk of increasing network congestion is decreased.</t>
      
    </section>

    <section title="Terminology">
      <t>The keywords "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
      document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
      target="RFC2119"></xref>.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Protocol Overview">
      <t>This document extends the RTCP feedback messages defined in the
      Audio-Visual Profile with Feedback (AVPF) and define the Feedback
      Suppression message. The Feedback Suppression message asks a receiver to
      not send feedback messages for particular packets (indicated by their
      RTP sequence numbers) independent of whether the receiver detected the
      packet loss or detected a need for a decoder refresh point).</t>

      <t>In order to detect packet loss before the receivers perceive it, one
      or more intermediate nodes may be placed between the media source and
      receiver. These intermediates are variously referred to as Distribution
      servers, MCUs, RTP translator, or RTP mixers, depending on the precise
      use case. These intermediaries monitor for packet loss upstream of
      themselves by checking RTP sequence numbers, just as receivers do. Upon
      detecting (or suspecting) an upstream loss, the intermediary may send
      Feedback Suppression message towards the receivers as defined in this
      specification.</t>

      <t>These intermediate nodes need to take into account such factors as
      the tolerable application delay, the network dynamics, and the media
      type. When the packet loss is detected upstream of the intermediary and
      additional latency is tolerable, the intermediate node may itself send a
      feedback message asking for the suspected lost packet or ask for the
      correct decoder refresh point. Because it has already provided the
      necessary feedback toward the source, the intermediate node can be
      reasonably certain that it will help the situation by sending a Feedback
      Suppression message to all the relevant receivers, thereby indicating
      that the receivers should not themselves transmit feedback messages for a
      period of time.</t>

      <t>Alternatively, the media source may directly monitor the amount of
      feedback requests it receives, and send feedback suppression messages to
      the receivers.</t>

      <t>When a receiver gets such a feedback suppression message, it should
      refrain from sending a feedback request (e.g., NACK or FIR) for the
      missing packets reported in the message for a period of time. A receiver
      may still have sent a Feedback message before receiving a feedback 
      suppression message, but further feedback messages for those sequence 
      numbers will be suppressed by this technique for a period time.Nodes 
      that do not understand the feedback suppression message will ignore it,
      and might therefore still send feedback. The media source or intermediate
      nodes cannot assume that the use of a feedback suppression request actually
      reduces the amount of feedback it receives.</t>

      <t>RTCP Feedback Suppression follows the same semantic model as RTCP
      NACK - it conveys the packet receipt/loss events at the sequence number
      level and considers missing packets as unrepaired. But unlike RTCP NACK,
      the Feedback Suppression messages can be generated at RTP middleboxs and
      sent to the corresponding receivers. Intermediaries downstream of an
      intermediary detecting loss obviously SHOULD NOT initiate their own
      additional feedback suppression messages for the same packet sequence
      numbers. They may either simply forward the Feedback Suppression message
      received from upstream, or augment (or replace) it with a feedback
      suppression message that reflects the loss pattern they have themselves
      seen.</t>

    </section>

    <section title="RTCP Feedback Report Extension">
      <t>This document registers two new RTCP Feedback messages for Feedback
      Suppression. Applications that are employing one or more loss-repair
      methods MAY use Feedback Suppression together with their existing
      loss-repair methods either for every packet they expect to receive, or
      for an application-specific subset of the RTP packets in a session. In
      other words, receivers MAY ignore Feedback Suppression messages, but
      SHOULD react to them unless they have good reason to still send feedback
      messages despite having been requested to suppress them.</t>

      <section title="Transport Layer Feedback:  NACK Suppression Report">
        <t>The NACK implosion Suppression message is an extension to the RTCP
        feedback report and identified by RTCP packet type value PT=RTPFB and
        FMT=TBD.</t>

        <t>The FCI field MUST contain one or more NACK Suppression Early
        Indication (NSEI) entries. Each entry applies to a different media
        source, identified by its SSRC.</t>

        <t>The Feedback Control Information (FCI) for NSEI uses the similar
        format of message Types defined in the section 4.3.1.1 of <xref
        target="RFC5104"></xref>. The format is shown in <xref
        target="fig2"></xref>.</t>

        <figure align="center" anchor="fig2"
                title="Message Format for the NSEI report">
          <artwork>
     0                   1                   2                   3
    0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |                              SSRC                             |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |            PID                |             BLP               |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
</artwork>
        </figure>

        <t><list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="SSRC (32 bits):"><vspace blankLines="1" />The SSRC
            value of the media source that is requested to send the lost
            packet.<vspace blankLines="1" /></t>

            <t hangText="Packet ID (PID): 16 bits"><vspace blankLines="1" />
            The PID field is used to specify a lost packet. The PID field
            refers to the RTP sequence number of the lost packet.<vspace
            blankLines="1" /></t>

            <t
            hangText="bitmask of proceeding lost packets (BLP): 16 bits"><vspace
            blankLines="1" /> The BLP allows for reporting losses of any of
            the 16 RTP packets immediately following the RTP packet indicated
            by the PID. The BLP's definition is identical to that given in
            <xref target="RFC4585"></xref>.<vspace blankLines="1" /></t>
          </list></t>
      </section>

      <section title="Payload Specific Feedback: FIR suppression report">
        <t>The FIR implosion Suppression message is an extension to the RTCP
        receiver feedback report and identified by RTCP packet type value
        PT=PSFB and FMT=TBD.</t>

        <t>The FCI field MUST contain one or more FIR suppression Early
        Indication (FSEI) entries. Each entry applies to a different media
        source, identified by its SSRC.</t>

        <t>The Feedback Control Information (FCI) for FSEI uses the similar
        format of message Types defined in the section 4.3.1.1 of <xref
        target="RFC5104"></xref>. The format is shown in <xref
        target="fig3"></xref>.</t>

        <figure align="center" anchor="fig3"
                title="Message Format for the FSEI report">
          <artwork>
     0                   1                   2                   3
    0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |                              SSRC                             |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |     Seq nr.   |                   Reserved                    |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+ 
</artwork>
        </figure>

        <t><list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="SSRC (32 bits): "><vspace blankLines="1" />The SSRC
            value of the media source that is requested to send a decoder
            refresh point.<vspace blankLines="1" /></t>

            <t hangText="Seq nr:8bits">Command sequence number. The sequence
            number space is unique for each pairing of the SSRC of command
            source and the SSRC of the command target. The sequence number
            SHALL be increased by 1 modulo 256 for each new request.<vspace
            blankLines="1" /></t>

            <t hangText="Reserved: 24 bits"><vspace blankLines="1" />All bits
            SHALL be set to 0 by the media source and SHALL be ignored on
            reception.<vspace blankLines="1" /></t>
          </list></t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="SDP Signaling">
      <t>A new feedback value "fss" needs to be defined for the Feedback Storm
      Suppression message to be used with Session Description Protocol
      (SDP)<xref target="RFC4566"></xref> using the Augmented Backus-Naur Form
      (ABNF)<xref target="RFC4585"></xref>.</t>

      <t>The "fss" feedback value SHOULD be used with parameters that indicate
      the feedback suppression supported. In this document, we define two such
      parameters, namely:<vspace blankLines="1" /><list style="symbols">
          <t>"fsei" denotes support of fir suppression early indication
          (fsei).<vspace blankLines="1" /></t>

          <t>"nsei" denotes support of NACK suppression early indication.</t>
        </list><vspace blankLines="1" />In the ABNF for rtcp-fb-val defined in
      <xref target="RFC4585"></xref>, there is a placeholder called rtcp-fb-id
      to define new feedback types. "fss" is defined as a new feedback type in
      this document, and the ABNF for the parameters for fss is defined here
      (please refer to section 4.2 of <xref target="RFC4585"></xref> for
      complete ABNF syntax).</t>

      <figure align="center">
        <artwork>
      rtcp-fb-val        =/ "fss" rtcp-fb-fss-param
      rtcp-fb-fss-param  = SP "nsei";nack suppression early indication
                          / SP "fsei";fir suppression early indication
                          / SP token [SP byte-string]
                                    ; for future commands/indications
   byte-string = &lt;as defined in section 4.2 of [RFC4585] &gt;
</artwork>
      </figure>

      <t>Refer to Section 4.2 of <xref target="RFC4585"></xref> for a detailed
      description and the full syntax of the "rtcp-fb" attribute.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Example Use Cases">
      <t>The operation of feedback suppression is similar for all types of RTP
      sessions and topologies <xref target="RFC5117"></xref>, however the
      exact messages used and the scenarios in which suppression is employed
      differ for various use cases. The following sections outline the
      intended use cases for feedback suppression and give an overview of the
      particular mechanisms.</t>

      <section title="Source Specific Multicast (SSM) use case">
        <t>In SSM RTP sessions as described in <xref target="RFC5760"></xref>,
        one or more Media Sources send RTP packets to a Distribution Source.
        The Distribution Source relays the RTP packets to the receivers using
        a source-specific multicast group.</t>

        <t>In order to avoid the forms of NACK implosion described in section
        1,the distribution source should choose to include the support for
        loss detection. How the packet loss detection works is beyond of scope
        of this document. When upstream link or downstream aggregate link
        packet loss occurs, the distribution source creates a Feedback
        Suppression report and sent it to all the RTP receivers, over the
        multicast channel. Another possibility is when there may have multiple
        distribution source placed between the media source and the receivers,
        the upstream distribution source may inform downstream distribution
        source of the detected packet loss using Feedback Suppression
        messages. In response, the distribution source forwards packet loss
        suppression report received from upstream to all the RTP receivers,
        over the multicast channel. This loss suppression report tells the
        receivers that the lost packet will either be forthcoming from
        distribution source, or it irretrievably lost such that there is
        nothing to be gained by the receiver sending a NACK to the media
        source. The distribution source then can (optionally) ask for the lost
        packets from the media source on behalf of all the RTP receivers.</t>

        <t>When there is only one distribution source with loss detection
        support between the media source and the receivers, redistribution of
        the feedback suppression report to all the receivers is trivial. When
        there are multiple distribution sources between the media source and
        the receiver, , each distribution source with loss detection support
        may create a Feedback Suppression Report using the similar format as
        conventional RTCP NACK packets at the RTP layer and send it to its
        downstream distribution source or forward one Feedback Suppression
        Report from upstream to its downstream distribution source or the
        receivers. Also each distribution source at the downstream of the
        other distribution source may also create additional Feedback
        Suppression Report and send it to the receivers.</t>

        <t>The distribution source must be able to communicate with all group
        members in order for either mechanism to be effective at suppressing
        feedback.</t>

        <t>As outlined in the <xref target="RFC5760"></xref>, there are two
        Unicast Feedback models that may be used for reporting, - the Simple
        Feedback model and the Distribution Source Feedback Summary Model. The
        RTCP Feedback Suppression report extension specified in the section 4
        of this document will work in both Feedback models. Details of
        operation in each are specified below.</t>

        <section title="Simple Feedback Model">
          <t>In the simple Feedback Model, there may have one distribution
          source with loss detection support. The distribution source must
          listen on the corresponding RTP session for data. When the
          distribution source observes that a sequence of RTP packets from
          upstream contains gaps (by checking the sequence number of packets),
          the distribution source must use the same packet types as
          traditional RTCP feedback described in <xref
          target="RFC3550"></xref> and create one new RTCP Feedback Report
          with information on the RTP sequence number of the lost packets and
          suppression early indication event. When the distribution source is
          eligible to transmit, it must send this Report packet to the the
          group on the multicast RTCP session.</t>

          <t>Alternatively the distribution source should pass through any
          feedback suppression requests it receives from the upstream
          direction. Such a distribution source can also choose to not send
          feedback suppression messages if it's already seen similar messages
          with identical packet loss from upstream.</t>

          <t>This RTCP Feedback Report lets the receivers know that feedback
          for this packet loss is not needed and should not be sent to the
          media source(s). If the media source(s) are part of the SSM group
          for RTCP packet reflection, the Distribution Source must filter this
          packet out. If the media source(s) are not part of the SSM group for
          RTCP packets, the Distribution Source must not forward this RTCP
          packets received from the receivers to the media source(s).</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Distribution Source Feedback Summary Model">
          <t>In the distribution source feedback summary model, there may have
          multiple distribution sources and the Loss Detection instances are
          distributed into different distribution sources. In some cases,
          these Loss Detection instances for the same session can exist at the
          same time, e.g., one Loss Detection instance is implemented in the
          upstream distribution source A, another two Loss Detection instances
          for the same session is part of feedback target A and feedback
          target B respectively within the distribution source B. In this
          section, we focus on this generic case to discuss the distribution
          Source Feedback Summary Model.</t>

          <t>The distribution source A must listen on the RTP channel for
          data. When the distribution source A observes RTP packets from a
          media source are not consecutive by checking the sequence number of
          packets, the distribution source A generates the new RTCP Feedback
          Suppression Report packet described in the section 6, and then send
          it to the distribution source B.</t>

          <t>Two loss detection instances within the Distribution Source B
          must listen for RTCP data sent to the RTCP port. Upon receiving the
          RTCP Feedback Report packet from the Distribution Source A, the
          distribution source B needs to summarize the information received
          from all the RTCP Feedback Reports generated by the upstream
          distribution source together with the information generated by two
          loss detection instances witin the Distribution Source B and then
          create the summary report to include all these information. In order
          to reduce the processing load at the distribution source, each loss
          detection instance may provide preliminary summarization report.</t>

          <t>During the summary report creating, the Distribution Source B
          must use its own SSRC value for transmitting summarization
          information and MUST perform proper SSRC collision detection and
          resolution.</t>

          <t>In some case, the distribution source B may receive RTCP NACK
          messages from the receivers behind the Distribution Source before
          the distribution source detects the packet loss which may cause
          potential Feedback implosion. In such case, the distribution source
          B may filter them out if it already sent a packet loss request for
          the missing packet to the media source. When the distribution source
          B confirms packet loss reported by the receiver, the distribution
          source B generates the summary report to include the packet loss
          information from the corresponding receiver or upstream distribution
          source.</t>

          <t>The distribution source B may send this new RTCP summary report
          described in the section 6 to the group on the multicast RTCP
          channel and in the meanwhile sending a packet loss request to the
          media source.</t>

          <t>If there are a couple of distribution sources with loss detection
          support looking at the same RTP stream, then the loss may be
          identified by all and they will all send requests for the same
          packet loss. In this case, the distribution source must filter out
          the duplicated information from various distribution source and only
          append one copy of such information to the summary report.</t>

          <t>When the host receives the RTCP Feedback Suppression message, if
          the host understands this message it will not send packet loss
          request (e.g., NACK) for the missing packets reported in the
          message. If it did not understand this new message, the host MAY
          send packet loss request(e.g., NACK messages) to the specified media
          source. When the distribution source receives the packet loss
          request from the hosts after it has already detected packet loss,
          the distribution source MUST filter it out until proactive recovery
          is complete.</t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section title="Unicast based Rapid Acquisition of Multicast Stream (RAMS) use case">
        <t>In the typical RAMS architecture, there may have one distribution
        source placed between media source and BRS for relaying SSM stream
        from media source. The BRS will receive the SSM stream from the DS.
        Suppose there are several BRSes behind the distribution source or
        media source, there may be just one BRS that detects packet loss on
        its upstream link between the distribution source and BRS, but the
        others will perhaps not, as the packet loss took place on SSM tree
        branch that does not impact the other BRSes. In such case, the
        distribution source with loss detection functionality support can not
        detect packet loss at the downstream of itself, therefore the
        distribution source SHOULD NOT create new Feedback Suppression message
        and send it to all the BRS. If BRS impacted by packet loss has loss
        detection support, the BRS MAY choose to create new Feedback
        Suppression message and send it to the receivers behind this BRS.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="RTP transport translator use case">
        <t>A Transport Translator (Topo-Trn-Translator), as defined in <xref
        target="RFC5117"></xref> is typically forwarding the RTP and RTCP
        traffic between RTP clients, for example converting between multicast
        and unicast for domains that do not support multicast. The translator
        can identify packet loss from the upstream and send the Feedback
        Suppression message to the unicast receivers. The translator can also
        serve as a loss reporter on the multicast side as described in the SSM
        case.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Multipoint Control Unit (MCU) use case">
        <t>In point to multipoint topologies using video switching MCU
        (Topo-Video-switch-MCU) <xref target="RFC5117"></xref>, the MCU
        typically forwards a single media stream to each participant, selected
        from the available input streams. The selection of the input stream is
        often based on voice activity in the audio-visual conference, but
        other conference management mechanisms (like presentation mode or
        explicit floor control) exist as well.</t>

        <t>In this case the MCU may detect packet loss from the sender or may
        decide to switch to a new source. In both cases the receiver may lose
        synchronization with the video stream and may send a FIR request. If
        the MCU itself can detect the mis-synchronization of the video, the
        MCU can send the FIR suppression message to the receivers and send a
        FIR request to the video source.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Security Considerations">
      <t>The defined messages have certain properties that have security
      implications. These must be addressed and taken into account by users of
      this protocol.</t>

      <t>Spoofed or maliciously created feedback messages of the type defined
      in this specification can have the following implications:</t>

      <t>Sending NACK Suppression Report with wrong sequence number of lost
      packet that makes missing RTP packets can not be compensated.</t>

      <t>Sending FIR Suppression Report with wrong sequence number of lost
      packet that makes missing RTP packets can not be compensated by update
      request mechanism.</t>

      <t>To prevent these attacks, there is a need to apply authentication and
      integrity protection of the feedback messages. This can be accomplished
      against threats external to the current RTP session using the RTP
      profile that combines Secure RTP <xref target="RFC3711"></xref> and AVPF
      into SAVPF <xref target="RFC5124"></xref>.</t>

      <t>Note that middleboxes that are not visible at the RTP layer that wish
      to send NACK/FIR suppression reports on behalf of the media source can
      only do so if they spoof the SSRC of the media source. This is difficult
      in case SRTP is in use. If the middlebox is visible at the RTP layer,
      this is not an issue, provided the middlebox is part of the security
      context for the session.</t>

      <t>Also note that endpoints that receive a NACK/FIR suppression request
      would be well-advised to ignore it, unless it is authenticated via SRTCP
      or similar. Accepting un-authenticated NACK/ FIR suppression requests
      can lead to a denial of service attack, where the endpoint accepts poor
      quality media that could be repaired.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="IANA Consideration">
      <t>New feedback type and New parameters for RTCP FSS receiver feedback
      report are subject to IANA registration. For general guidelines on IANA
      considerations for RTCP feedback, refer to <xref
      target="RFC4585"></xref>.</t>

      <t> This document assigns one new feedback type value x in the RTCP
      feedback report registry to "Feedback Storm Suppression" with the
      following registrations format: </t>

      <figure align="center">
        <artwork>
    Name:            FSS
    Long Name:       Feedback Storm Suppression
    Value:           TBD
    Reference:       This document.
</artwork>
      </figure>

      <t>This document also assigns the parameter value y in the RTCP FSS
      feedback report Registry to "NACK Suppression Early Indication ", with
      the following registrations format:</t>

      <figure>
        <artwork align="center">
     Name:           NSEI
     Long name:      NACK Suppression Early Indication
     Value:          TBD
     Reference:      this document.
</artwork>
      </figure>

      <t>This document also assigns the parameter value z in the RTCP FSS
      feedback report Registry to "FIR Suppression Early Indication ", with
      the following registrations format:</t>

      <figure align="center">
        <artwork>
     Name:           FSEI
     Long name:      FIR Suppression Early Indication
     Value:          TBD
     Reference:      this document.
</artwork>
      </figure>

      <t>The contact information for the registrations is: <figure>
          <artwork> 
  Qin Wu
  sunseawq@huawei.com
  101 Software Avenue, Yuhua District
  Nanjing, Jiangsu  210012, China
</artwork>
        </figure></t>
    </section>

    <section title="Acknowledgement">
      <t>The authors would like to thank David R Oran, Ali C. Begen, Colin
      Perkins,Tom VAN CAENEGEM, Ingemar Johansson S, Bill Ver Steeg, WeeSan
      Lee for their valuable comments and suggestions on this document.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5760"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4585"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3550"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5117"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4588"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4566"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5234"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5104"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3711"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5124"?>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <reference anchor="RFC5740">
        <front>
          <title>NACK-Oriented Reliable Multicast (NORM) Transport
          Protocol</title>

          <author fullname="Brian Adamson" initials="B." surname="Adamson">
            <organization>Naval Research Laboratory</organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="Carsten Bormann" initials="C." surname="Bormann">
            <organization>Universitaet Bremen TZI</organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="Mark Handley " initials="M." surname="Handley">
            <organization>University College London</organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="Joe Macker" initials="J." surname="Macker">
            <organization>Naval Research Laboratory</organization>
          </author>

          <date month="November" year="2009" />
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="DVB-IPTV">
        <front>
          <title>Digital Video Broadcasting(DVB); Transport of MPEG-2 TS Based
          DVB Services over IP Based Networks</title>

          <author>
            <organization>ETSI Standard</organization>
          </author>

          <date month="August" year="2009" />
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="ETSI TS 102 034, V1.4.1" value="" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="I-D.hunt-avt-monarch-01">
        <front>
          <title>Monitoring Architectures for RTP</title>

          <author fullname="Geoff Hunt" initials="G." surname="Hunt">
            <organization>BT</organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="Philip Arden" initials="P." surname="Arden">
            <organization>BT</organization>
          </author>

          <date month="August" year="2008" />
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="I-D.ietf-pmol-metrics-framework-02">
        <front>
          <title>Framework for Performance Metric Development</title>

          <author fullname="Alan Clark " initials="A." surname="Clark">
            <organization>Telchemy Incorporated</organization>
          </author>

          <date />
        </front>
      </reference>
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
