<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- edited with XMLSPY v5 rel. 3 U (http://www.xmlspy.com)
     by Daniel M Kohn (private) -->
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY rfc2119 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
]>
<rfc category="std" docName="draft-wu-pce-dns-pce-discovery-00"
     ipr="trust200902">
  <?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>

  <?rfc toc="yes" ?>

  <?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>

  <?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>

  <?rfc iprnotified="no" ?>

  <?rfc strict="yes" ?>

  <front>
    <title abbrev="DNS based PCED">Path Computation Element (PCE) Discovery
    using DNS</title>

    <author fullname="Qin Wu" initials="Q." surname="Wu">
      <organization>Huawei</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>101 Software Avenue, Yuhua District</street>

          <city>Nanjing</city>

          <region>Jiangsu</region>

          <code>210012</code>

          <country>China</country>
        </postal>

        <email>sunseawq@huawei.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date year="2013" />

    <area>Routing Area</area>

    <workgroup>Path Computation Element Working Group</workgroup>

    <keyword>RFC</keyword>

    <keyword>Request for Comments</keyword>

    <keyword>I-D</keyword>

    <keyword>Internet-Draft</keyword>

    <keyword>Path Computation Element</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>Discovery of the (Path Computation Element (PCE) within an IGP area
      or domain is possible using OSPF [RFC5088] and IS-IS [RFC5089]. However,
      in some deployment scenarios PCEs may not wish, or be able, to
      participate within the IGP process. Therefore it would be beneficial for
      the Path Computation Client (PCC) to discover PCEs via an alternative
      mechanism to those proposed in [RFC5088] and [RFC5089].</t>

      <t>This document specifies the requirements, use cases, procedures and
      extensions to support DNS for PCE discovery.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section anchor="intro" title="Introduction">
      <t>The Path Computation Element Communication Protocol (PCEP) is a
      transaction-based protocol carried over TCP. In order to be able to
      direct path computation requests to the Path Computation Element (PCE),
      a Path Computation Client (PCC) needs to know the location and
      capability of a PCE.</t>

      <t>In a network where an IGP is used and where the PCE participates in
      the IGP, discovery mechanisms exist for PCC to learn the identify and
      capability of each PCE. [RFC5088] defines a PCE Discovery (PCED) TLV
      carried in an OSPF Router LSA. Similarly, [RFC5089] defines the PCED
      sub-TLV for use in PCE Discovery using IS-IS.</t>

      <t>However in certain scenarios not all PCEs will participate in the IGP
      instance, section 3 (Motivation) outlines a number of use cases. In
      these cases, current PCE Discovery mechanisms are therefore not
      appropriate and another PCE announcement and discovery function would be
      required.</t>

      <section title="Requirements">
        <t>As described in [RFC4674], the PCE Discovery information should at
        least be composed of: <list style="symbols">
            <t>The PCE location: an IPv4 and/or IPv6 address that is used to
            reach the PCE. It is RECOMMENDED to use an address that is always
            reachable if there is any connectivity to the PCE;</t>

            <t>The PCE path computation scope (i.e., intra-layer, inter-area,
            inter-AS, or inter-layer);</t>

            <t>The set of one or more PCE-Domain(s) into which the PCE has
            visibility and for which the PCE can compute paths;</t>

            <t>The set of zero, one, or more neighbor PCE-Domain(s) toward
            which the PCE can compute paths;</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>that allows PCCs to select appropriate PCEs:</t>

        <t>This document specifies an extension to DNS for the above PCE
        information discovery, which is complimentary to IS-IS extension and
        OSPF extension that describe the support of PCE discovery.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Conventions used in this document">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
      document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
      target="RFC2119">RFC2119</xref>.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Motivation">
      <t>This section discusses in more detail the motivation and use cases
      for an alternative DNS based PCE discovery mechanism.</t>

      <section title="Load Sharing of Path Computation Requests">
        <t>Inherent DNS based load balancing may be used for inbound load
        balancing and implemented at the application level in both servers and
        clients. Multiple host IP addresses are configured in DNS for a single
        host server name. Also DNS is capable of automatically detecting and
        reacting to errors. These allow you to provide load balancing across
        two separate Systems and facilitate PCE system failover and
        recovery.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Network Address Translation Gateway">
        <t>Network address translation breaks end-to-end connectivity. The
        internal network devices communicate with hosts on the external
        network by changing the source address of outgoing requests to that of
        the NAT device and relaying replies back to the originating device.
        This poses a problem for PCEs that is behind the NAT devices, as PCE
        information carried by PCE that is behind NAT devices in the outgoing
        IGP advertisement doesn't require substitution or special traversal
        techniques for NAT traversal and can not be used by PCC that is on the
        external network to reach the PCE.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Multiple-Provider Domains">
        <t>In the case of multiple ASes within different service provider
        networks, the H-PCE [RFC6805] architecture does not require disclosure
        of internals of a child domain to the parent PCE. It may be necessary
        for a third party to manage the parent PCEs according to commercial
        and policy agreements from each of the participating service
        providers.</t>

        <t>[RFC6805] specifies that a child PCE must be configured with the
        address of its parent PCE in order for it to interact with its parent
        PCE. However handling changes in parent PCE identities and coping with
        failure events would be an issue for a configured system.</t>

        <t>There is no scope for parent PCEs to advertise their presence,
        however there is potential for directory systems (such as DNS
        [RFC4848] as used in the ALTO discovery function [I-D.ietf-alto-
        server-discovery]).</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Discovering a Path Computation Element">
      <t>The Dynamic Delegation Discovery System (DDDS) [RFC3401] is used to
      implement lazy binding of strings to data, in order to support
      dynamically configured delegation systems. The DDDS functions by mapping
      some unique string to data stored within a DDDS database by iteratively
      applying string transformation rules until a terminal condition is
      reached. When DDDS uses DNS as a distributed database of rules, these
      rules are encoded using the Naming Authority Pointer (NAPTR) Resource
      Record (RR). One of these rules is the First Well Known Rule, which says
      where the process starts.</t>

      <t>In current specifications, the First Well Known Rule in a DDDS
      application [RFC3403] is assumed to be fixed, i.e., the domain in the
      tree where the lookups are to be routed to, is known. This document
      proposes the input to the First Well Known Rule to be dynamic, based on
      the search path the resolver discovers or is configured to use.</t>

      <t>The search path of the resolver can either be pre-configured, or
      discovered using DHCP.</t>

      <t>When the PCC needs to discover PCEs in the domain into which the PCC
      has visibility (e.g.,local domain), the input to the First Well Known
      Rule MUST be the domain the PCC knows, which is assumed to be
      pre-configured in the PCC or discovered using DHCP.</t>

      <t>When the PCC needs to discover PCE in the other domain (e.g., Parent
      PCE in the parent domain)into which the PCC has no visibility, it SHOULD
      know the domain name of that domain and use DHCP to discover IP address
      of the PCE in that domain that provides path computation service along
      with some PCE location information useful to a PCC for PCE selection,
      and contact it directly. In some instances, the discovery may result in
      a per protocol/application list of domain names that are then used as
      starting points for the subsequent NAPTR lookups. If neither the IP
      address or PCE location information can be discovered with the above
      procedure, the PCC MAY request a domain search list, as described in
      [RFC3397] and [RFC3646], and use it as input to the DDDS application.
      </t>

      <t>When the PCC does not find valid domain names using the procedures
      above, it MUST stop the attempt to discover any PCE.</t>

      <t>The dynamic rule described above SHOULD NOT be used for discovering
      services other than Path computation services described in this
      document, unless stated otherwise by a future specification.</t>

      <t>The procedures defined here result in an IP address, PCE domain,
      neighboring PCE domain and PCE Computation Scope where the PCC can
      contact the PCC that hosts the service the PCC is looking for.</t>

      <section title="Determining the PCE Service and transport protocol">
        <t>The PCC should know the service identifier for the Path Computation
        Discovery service. The service identifier for the Path Computation
        Discovery service is defined as "PCED", The PCE supporting "PCED"
        service MUST support only TCP as transport, as described in
        [RFC5440].</t>

        <t>The services relevant for the task of transport protocol selection
        are those with NAPTR service fields with values "ID+M2X", where ID is
        the service identifier defined in the previous section, and X is a
        letter that corresponds to a transport protocol supported by the
        domain. This specification only defines M2T for TCP. This document
        also establishes an IANA registry for mappings of NAPTR service name
        to transport protocol.</t>

        <t>These NAPTR [RFC3403] records provide a mapping from a domain to
        the SRV [RFC2782] record for contacting a PCE with the specific
        transport protocol in the NAPTR services field. The resource record
        MUST contain an empty regular expression and a replacement value,
        which indicates the domain name where the SRV record for that
        particular transport protocol can be found. As per [RFC3403], the
        client discards any records whose services fields are not
        applicable.</t>

        <t>The PCC MUST discard any service fields that identify a resolution
        service whose value is not "M2T", for values of T that indicate TCP
        transport protocols supported by the client. The NAPTR processing as
        described in RFC 3403 will result in the discovery of the most
        preferred transport protocol of the PCE that is supported by the
        client, as well as an SRV record for the PCE.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Determining the IP Address of the PCE">
        <t>As an example, consider a client that wishes to find “PCED” service
        in the example.com domain. The client performs a NAPTR query for that
        domain, and the following NAPTR records are returned: <figure>
            <artwork>
Order Pref Flags  Service     Regexp       Replacement
 IN NAPTR  50   50   "s"  "PCED"    ""   
 _PCED._tcp.example.com
 IN NAPTR  90   50   "s"  "PCED+M2T"    ""  
 _PCED._udp.example.com
</artwork>
          </figure></t>

        <t>This indicates that the domain does have a PCE providing Path
        Computation services over TCP, in that order of preference. Since the
        client only supports TCP, TCP will be used, targeted to a host
        determined by an SRV lookup of _PCED._tcp.example.com. That lookup
        would return: <figure>
            <artwork>
   ;;  Priority  Weight    Port        Target
IN  SRV    0        1      XXXX   server1.example.com
IN  SRV    0        2      XXXX   server2.example.com
</artwork>
          </figure></t>

        <t>where XXXX represents the port number at which the service is
        reachable.</t>

        <t>Note that the regexp field in the NAPTR example above is empty. The
        regexp field MUST NOT be used when discovering path computation
        services, as its usage can be complex and error prone. Also, the
        discovery of the path computation service does not require the
        flexibility provided by this field over a static target present in the
        TARGET field.</t>

        <t>If the client is already configured with the information about
        which transport protocol is used for a path computation service in a
        particular domain, it can directly perform an SRV query for that
        specific transport using the service identifier of the path
        computation Service. For example, if the client knows that it should
        be using TCP for path computation service, it can perform a SRV query
        directly for_PCED._tcp.example.com.</t>

        <t>Once the server providing the desired service and the transport
        protocol has been determined, the next step is to determine the IP
        address.</t>

        <t>According to the specification of SRV RRs in [RFC2782], the TARGET
        field is a fully qualified domain name (FQDN) that MUST have one or
        more address records; the FQDN must not be an alias, i.e., there MUST
        NOT be a CNAME or DNAME RR at this name. Unless the SRV DNS query
        already has reported a sufficient number of these address records in
        the Additional Data section of the DNS response (as recommended by
        [RFC2782]), the PCC needs to perform A and/or AAAA record lookup(s) of
        the domain name, as appropriate. The result will be a list of IP
        addresses, each of which can be contacted using the transport protocol
        determined previously.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Determining path computation scope,the PCE domains and Neighbor PCE domains">
        <t>DNS servers MAY add new RRsets to the additional information
        section that are relevant to the answer and have the same authenticity
        as the data (the IP Address of the PCE)in the answer section. RRsets
        include path computation scope, the PCE domains and Neighbor PCE
        domains associated with. path information Applications on the PCC MAY
        inspect those Additional Information section and be capable of
        handling responses from nameservers that never fill in the Additional
        Information part of a response.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>The usage of NAPTR records described here requires well-known values
      for the service fields for the transport supported by Path Computation
      Services. The table of mappings from service field values to transport
      protocols is to be maintained by IANA.</t>

      <t>The registration in the RFC MUST include the following
      information:<figure>
          <artwork>
Service Field: The service field being registered.

Protocol: The specific transport protocol associated with that
service field.  This MUST include the name and acronym for the
protocol, along with reference to a document that describes the
transport protocol.

Name and Contact Information: The name, address, email address,
and telephone number for the person performing the registration.
</artwork>
        </figure></t>

      <t>The following values have been placed into the registry:<figure>
          <artwork>
Service Fields                    Protocol
   PCED+M2T                        TCP
</artwork>
        </figure></t>

      <t>New Service Fields are to be added via Standards Action as defined in
      [RFC5226].</t>

      <t>IANA is also requested to register PCED as service name in the
      Protocol and Service Names registry.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Security Considerations">
      <t>It is believed that this proposed DNS extension introduces no new
      security considerations (i.e., A list of known threats to services using
      DNS) beyond those described in [RFC3833]. For most of those identified
      threats, the DNS Security Extensions [RFC4033] does provide protection.
      It is therefore recommended to consider the usage of DNSSEC [RFC4033]
      and the aspects of DNSSEC Operational Practices [RFC4641] when deploying
      Path Computation Services.</t>

      <t>In deployments where DNSSEC usage is not feasible, measures should be
      taken to protect against forged DNS responses and cache poisoning as
      much as possible. Efforts in this direction are documented in
      [RFC5452].</t>

      <t>Where inputs to the procedure described in this document are fed via
      DHCP, DHCP vulnerabilities can also cause issues. For instance, the
      inability to authenticate DHCP discovery results may lead to the Path
      Computation service results also being incorrect, even if the DNS
      process was secured.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <reference anchor="RFC2119">
        <front>
          <title abbrev="RFC Key Words">Key words for use in RFCs to Indicate
          Requirement Levels</title>

          <author fullname="Scott Bradner" initials="S." surname="Bradner">
            <organization>Harvard University</organization>

            <address>
              <postal>
                <street>1350 Mass. Ave.</street>

                <street>Cambridge</street>

                <street>MA 02138</street>
              </postal>

              <phone>- +1 617 495 3864</phone>

              <email>sob@harvard.edu</email>
            </address>
          </author>

          <date month="March" year="1997" />

          <area>General</area>

          <keyword>keyword</keyword>

          <abstract>
            <t>In many standards track documents several words are used to
            signify the requirements in the specification. These words are
            often capitalized. This document defines these words as they
            should be interpreted in IETF documents. Authors who follow these
            guidelines should incorporate this phrase near the beginning of
            their document: <list>
                <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL",
                "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and
                "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described
                in RFC 2119.</t>
              </list></t>

            <t>Note that the force of these words is modified by the
            requirement level of the document in which they are used.</t>
          </abstract>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RFC2782">
        <front>
          <title>A DNS RR for specifying the location of services (DNS
          SRV)</title>

          <author fullname="A.Gulbrandsen" initials="A." surname="Gulbrandsen">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date month="February" year="2000" />
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="2782" />

        <format target="http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc2782.txt" type="TXT" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RFC3397">
        <front>
          <title>Dynamic Host Configuration Protocol (DHCP) Domain Search
          Option</title>

          <author fullname="B.Aboba" initials="B." surname="Aboba">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date month="November" year="2002" />
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="3397" />

        <format target="http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc3397.txt" type="TXT" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RFC3403">
        <front>
          <title>Dynamic Delegation Discovery System (DDDS) Part Three: The
          Domain Name System (DNS) Database</title>

          <author fullname="M.Mealling" initials="M." surname="Mealling">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date month="October" year="2002" />
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="3403" />

        <format target="http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc3403.txt" type="TXT" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RFC3646">
        <front>
          <title>DNS Configuration options for Dynamic Host Configuration
          Protocol for IPv6 (DHCPv6)</title>

          <author fullname="R.Droms" initials="R." surname="Droms">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date month="December" year="2003" />
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="3646" />

        <format target="http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc3646.txt" type="TXT" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RFC5226">
        <front>
          <title>Guidelines for Writing an IANA Considerations Section in
          RFCs</title>

          <author fullname="T.Narten" initials="T." surname="Narten">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date month="May" year="2008" />
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="5226" />

        <format target="http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc5226.txt" type="TXT" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RFC4674">
        <front>
          <title>Requirements for Path Computation Element (PCE)
          Discovery</title>

          <author fullname="R.Droms" initials="R." surname="Droms">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date month="December" year="2003" />
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="4674" />

        <format target="http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc4674.txt" type="TXT" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RFC6805">
        <front>
          <title>The Application of the Path Computation Element Architecture
          to the Determination of a Sequence of Domains in MPLS and
          GMPLS</title>

          <author fullname="D.King" initials="D." surname="King">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="A.Farrel " initials="A." surname="Farrel">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date month="November" year="2012" />
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="6805" />

        <format target="http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc6805.txt" type="TXT" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RFC4848">
        <front>
          <title>Domain-Based Application Service Location Using URIs and the
          Dynamic Delegation Discovery Service (DDDS)</title>

          <author fullname="L. Daigle" initials="D." surname="Daigle">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date month="April" year="2007" />
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="4848" />

        <format target="http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc4848.txt" type="TXT" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RFC5440">
        <front>
          <title>Path Computation Element (PCE) Communication Protocol
          (PCEP)</title>

          <author fullname="JL. Le Roux" initials="JL." surname="Le Roux">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date month="April" year="2007" />
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="5440" />

        <format target="http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc5440.txt" type="TXT" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RFC4641">
        <front>
          <title>DNSSEC Operational Practices</title>

          <author fullname="O. Kolkman" initials="O." surname="Kolkman">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date month="September" year="2006" />
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="4641" />

        <format target="http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc4641.txt" type="TXT" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RFC4033">
        <front>
          <title>DNS Security Introduction and Requirements</title>

          <author fullname="R. Arends" initials="R." surname="Arends">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date month="March" year="2005" />
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="4033" />

        <format target="http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc4033.txt" type="TXT" />
      </reference>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <reference anchor="RFC5088">
        <front>
          <title>OSPF Protocol Extensions for Path Computation Element (PCE)
          Discovery</title>

          <author fullname="JL. Le Roux" initials="JL." surname="Le Roux">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date month="January" year="2008" />
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="5088" />

        <format target="http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc5088.txt" type="TXT" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RFC5089">
        <front>
          <title>IS-IS Protocol Extensions for Path Computation Element (PCE)
          Discovery</title>

          <author fullname="JL. Le Roux" initials="JL." surname="Le Roux">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date month="January" year="2008" />
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="5089" />

        <format target="http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc5089.txt" type="TXT" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RFC3401">
        <front>
          <title>Dynamic Delegation Discovery System (DDDS) Part One: The
          Comprehensive DDDS</title>

          <author fullname="M.Mealling" initials="M." surname="Mealling">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date month="October" year="2002" />
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="3401" />

        <format target="http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc3401.txt" type="TXT" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RFC3833">
        <front>
          <title>Threat Analysis of the Domain Name System (DNS)</title>

          <author fullname="D.Atkins" initials="D." surname="Atkins">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date month="August" year="2004" />
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="3833" />

        <format target="http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc3833.txt" type="TXT" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RFC5452">
        <front>
          <title>Measures for Making DNS More Resilient against Forged
          Answers</title>

          <author fullname="A.Hubert" initials="A." surname="Hubert">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date month="January" year="2009" />
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="5452" />

        <format target="http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc5452.txt" type="TXT" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="ALTO">
        <front>
          <title>ALTO Server Discovery</title>

          <author fullname="S. Kiesel" initials="S." surname="Kiesel">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date month="March" year="2013" />
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="ID" value="draft-ietf-alto-server-discovery-08" />
      </reference>
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
