<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!-- One method to get references from the online citation libraries.
     There has to be one entity for each item to be referenced. 
     An alternate method (rfc include) is described in the references. -->
<!ENTITY RFC2473 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2473.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC2827 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2827.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3704 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3704.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6092 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6092.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6204 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6204.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6583 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6583.xml">
<!--ENTITY v6ops-simple-security PUBLIC "" 
	"http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-v6ops-cpe-simple-security.xml"-->
]>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="no"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<?rfc iprnotified="yes" ?>
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc colonspace='yes' ?>
<rfc category="info"
     docName="draft-v6ops-vyncke-balanced-ipv6-security-00.txt"
     ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="Balanced-CPEv6-security">Balanced Security for IPv6
    CPE</title>

    <author fullname="Martin Gysi" initials="M" surname="Gysi">
      <organization>Swisscom</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street/>

          <city/>

          <country>Switzerland</country>

          <code/>
        </postal>

        <phone/>

        <email>Martin.Gysi@swisscom.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Guillaume Leclanche" initials="G" surname="Leclanche">
      <organization>Swisscom</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street/>

          <city/>

          <country>Switzerland</country>

          <code/>
        </postal>

        <phone/>

        <email>Guillaume.Leclanche@swisscom.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Eric Vyncke" initials="E" surname="Vyncke" role="editor">
      <organization>Cisco Systems</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>De Kleetlaan 6a</street>

          <city>Diegem</city>

          <country>Belgium</country>

          <code>1831</code>
        </postal>

        <phone>+32 2 778 4677</phone>

        <email>evyncke@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Ragnar Anfinsen" initials="R" surname="Anfinsen">
      <organization>Altibox</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street/>

          <city/>

          <country>Norway</country>

          <code/>
        </postal>

        <phone/>

        <email>Ragnar.Anfinsen@altibox.no</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date day="25" month="January" year="2013"/>

    <area>Operations</area>

    <workgroup>IPv6 Operations</workgroup>

    <keyword>CPE</keyword>

    <keyword>IPv6</keyword>

    <keyword>Security</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>This document describes how an IPv6 residential Customer Premise
      Equipment (CPE) can have a balanced security policy that allows for a
      mostly end-to-end connectivity while keeping the major threats outside
      of the home. It is based on an actual IPv6 deployment by Swisscom and
      proposes to allow all packets inbound/outbound EXCEPT for some layer-4
      ports where attacks and vulnerabilities (such as weak passwords) are
      well-known.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>
  
  <middle>
    <section anchor="intro" title="Introduction">
      <t>Internet access in residential IPv4 deployments generally consist of
      a single IPv4 address provided by the service provider for each home.
      Residential CPE then translates the single address into multiple private
      IPv4 addresses allowing more than one device in the home, but at the
      cost of losing end-to-end reachability. IPv6 allows all devices to have
      a unique, global, IP address, restoring end-to-end reachability directly
      between any device. Such reachability is very powerful for ubiquitous
      global connectivity, and is often heralded as one of the significant
      advantages to IPv6 over IPv4. Despite this, concern about exposure to
      inbound packets from the IPv6 Internet (which would otherwise be dropped
      by the address translation function if they had been sent from the IPv4
      Internet) remain. This document describes firewall functionality for an
      IPv6 CPE which departs from the "simple security" model described in
      <xref target="RFC6092"/> . The intention is to provide an example of a
      security model which allows most traffic, including incoming unsolicited
      packets and connections, to traverse the CPE unless the CPE identifies
      the traffic as potentially harmful based on a set of rules. This model
      has been deployed successfully in Switzerland by Swisscom without any
      known security incident.</t>

      <t>This document is applicable to off-the-shelves CPE as well to managed
      Service Provider CPE.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="threat" title="Threats">
      <t>For a typical residential network connected to the Internet over a
      broadband connection, the threats can be classified into: <list
          style="symbols">
          <t>denial of service by packet flooding: overwhelming either the
          access bandwidth or the bandwidth of a slower link in the
          residential network (like a slow home automation network) or the CPU
          power of a slow IPv6 host (like networked thermostat or any other
          sensor type nodes);</t>

          <t>denial of service by Neighbor Discovery cache exhaustion <xref
          target="RFC6583"/>: the outside attacker floods the inside
          prefix(es) with packets with a random destination address forcing
          the CPE to exhaust its memory and its CPU in useless Neighbor
          Sollicitations;</t>

          <t>denial of service by service requests: like sending print jobs
          from the Internet to an ink jet printer until the ink cartridge is
          empty or like filing some file server with junk data;</t>

          <t>unauthorized use of services: like accessing a webcam or a file
          server which are open to anonymous access within the residential
          network but should not be accessed from outside of the home network
          or accessing to remote desktop or SSH with weak password
          protection;</t>

          <t>exploiting a vulnerability in the host in order to get access to
          data or to execute some arbitrary code in the attacked host such as
          several against old versions of Windows;</t>

          <t>trojanized host (belonging to a Botnet) can communicate via a
          covert channel to its master and launch attacks to Internet
          targets.</t>
        </list></t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="overview" title="Overview">
      <t>The basic goal is to provide a fixed security policy which aims to
      block known harmful traffic and allow the rest, restoring as much of
      end-to-end communication as possible.</t>

      <section anchor="rules" title="Rules for Balanced Security Policy">
        <t>These are an example set of generic rules to be applied. Each would
        normally be configurable, either by the user directly or on behalf of
        the user by a subscription service.</t>

        <t>If we name all nodes on the residential side of the CPE as 'inside'
        and all nodes on the Internet as 'outside', and any packet sent from
        outside to inside as being 'inbound' and 'outbound' in the other
        direction, then the behavior of the CPE is described by a small set or
        rules: <list style="numbers">
            <t>Rule RejectBogon: apply ingress filtering in both directions
            per <xref target="RFC3704"/> and <xref target="RFC2827"/> for
            example with unicast reverse path forwarding (uRPF) checks
            (anti-spoofing) for all inbound and outbound traffic (implicitly
            blocking link-local and ULA in the same shot), this is basically
            the Section 2.1 Basic Sanitation and Section 3.1 Stateless Filters
            of <xref target="RFC6092"/>;</t>

            <t>Rule ProtectWeakServices: drop all inbound and outbound packets
            whose layer-4 destination is part of a limited set (see <xref
            target="layer4-ACL"/>), the intent is to protect against the most
            common unauthorized access and avoid propagation of worms (even if
            the latter is questionable in IPv6); an advanced residential user
            should be able to modify this pre-defined list;</t>
          
          
            <t>Rule Openess: allow all unsolicited inbound packets with rate
            limiting the initial packet of a new connection (such as TCP SYN,
            SCTP INIT or DCCP-request not applicable to UDP) to provide very
            basic protection against SYN port and address scanning attacks.
            All transport protocols and all non-deprecated extension headers
            are accepted. This a the major deviation from REC-11, REC-17 and
            REC-33 of <xref target="RFC6092"/>.</t>

            <t>All requirements of <xref target="RFC6092"/> except REC-11,
            REC-18 and REC-33 must be supported.</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="layer4-ACL"
               title="Rules example for Layer-4 Protection as Used by Swisscom">
        <t>The rule ProtectWeakService can be implemented by using the
        following suggestions as implemented by Swisscom in 2013:</t>

        <texttable anchor="inbound_drops" title="Drop Inbound">
          <ttcol align="center">Transport</ttcol>

          <ttcol align="center">Port</ttcol>

          <ttcol align="center">Description</ttcol>

          <c>tcp</c>

          <c>22</c>

          <c>Secure Shell (SSH)</c>

          <c>tcp</c>

          <c>23</c>

          <c>Telnet</c>

          <c>tcp</c>

          <c>80</c>

          <c>HTTP</c>

          <c>tcp</c>

          <c>3389</c>

          <c>Microsoft Remote Desktop Protocol</c>

          <c>tcp</c>

          <c>5900</c>

          <c>VNC remote desktop protocol</c>
        </texttable>

        <texttable anchor="inbound_outbound_drops"
                   title="Drop Inbound and Outbound">
          <ttcol align="center">Transport</ttcol>

          <ttcol align="center">Port</ttcol>

          <ttcol align="center">Description</ttcol>

          <c>tcp-udp</c>

          <c>88</c>

          <c>Kerberos</c>

          <c>tcp</c>

          <c>111</c>

          <c>SUN Remote Procedure Call</c>

          <c>tcp</c>

          <c>135</c>

          <c>MS Remote Procedure Call</c>

          <c>tcp</c>

          <c>139</c>

          <c>NetBIOS Session Service</c>

          <c>tcp</c>

          <c>445</c>

          <c>Microsoft SMB Domain Server</c>

          <c>tcp</c>

          <c>513</c>

          <c>Remote Login</c>

          <c>tcp</c>

          <c>514</c>

          <c>Remote Shell</c>

          <c>tcp</c>

          <c>548</c>

          <c>Apple Filing Protocol over TCP</c>

          <c>tcp</c>

          <c>631</c>

          <c>Internet Printing Protocol</c>

          <c>udp</c>

          <c>1900</c>

          <c>Simple Service Discovery Protocol</c>

          <c>tcp</c>

          <c>2869</c>

          <c>Simple Service Discovery Protocol</c>

          <c>udp</c>

          <c>3702</c>

          <c>Web Services Dynamic Discovery</c>

          <c>udp</c>

          <c>5353</c>

          <c>Multicast DNS</c>

          <c>udp</c>

          <c>5355</c>

          <c>Link-Lcl Mcast Name Resolution</c>
        </texttable>

        <t>This list should evolve with the time as new protocols and new
        threats appear, <xref target="DSHIELD"/> is used by Swisscom to keep
        those filters up to date. Another source of information could be the
        appendix A of <xref target="TR124"/>. The above proposal does not block GRE
        tunnels (<xref target="RFC2473"/>) so this is a deviation from <xref
        target="RFC6092"/>.</t>

        <t>Note: the authors believe that with this set the usual residential
        subscriber, the proverbial grand-ma, is protected. Of course,
        technical susbcribers should be able to open other applications
        through their CPE through some kind of user interface.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>There are no extra IANA consideration for this document.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Security Considerations">
   <t>The authors of the documents believe and the Swisscom deployment
        shows that the following attack are mostly stopped:<list
            style="symbols">
            <t>Unauthorized access because vulnerable ports are blocked</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>This proposal cannot help with the following attacks: <list
            style="symbols">
            <t>Flooding of the CPE access link;</t>

            <t>Malware which is fetched by inside hosts on a hostile web site
            (which is in 2012 the majority of infection sources).</t>
          </list></t>
           </section>

    <section title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>The authors would like to thank several people who initiated the
      discussion on the ipv6-ops@lists.cluenet.de mailing list, notably: Tore
      Anderson, Lorenzo Colitti, Merike Kaeo, Martin Millnert, Benedikt
      Stockebrand.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <!-- =============================================================== -->

  <back>
    <!--references title="Normative References"-->

    <!--/references-->

    <references title="Informative References">
      &RFC2473;

      &RFC2827;

      &RFC3704;

      &RFC6092;

      &RFC6583;

      <reference anchor="DSHIELD" target="https://secure.dshield.org/portreport.html?sort=records">
        <front>
          <title>Port report: DShield</title>

          <author>
            <organization>DShield</organization>
          </author>
          <date/>
        </front>

       </reference>

     <reference anchor="TR124" target="http://www.broadband-forum.org/technical/download/TR-124.pdf" >
        <front>
          <title>Functional Requirements for Broadband Residential Gateway Devices</title>

          <author>
            <organization>Broadband Forum</organization>
          </author>
          <date month="December" year="2006"/>
        </front>

      </reference>

    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
