<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?rfc linefile="1:/tmp/CGI3357.1"?><?rfc linefile="1:/tmp/CGI3357.1"?>
<!-- automatically generated by xml2rfc v1.35pre1 on 2010-01-20T08:38:41Z -->
<!-- automatically generated by xml2rfc v1.35pre1 on 2010-01-20T08:38:41Z -->
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='http://xml.resource.org/authoring/rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [

<!--
--><!-- xml2rfc-processed-entity RFC3061 -->  

<!--
--><!-- xml2rfc-processed-entity RFC3454 -->  

<!--
--><!-- xml2rfc-processed-entity RFC3490 -->  

<!--
--><!-- xml2rfc-processed-entity RFC3492 -->  

<!--
--><!-- xml2rfc-processed-entity RFC3629 -->  

<!--
--><!-- xml2rfc-processed-entity RFC3986 -->  

<!--
--><!-- xml2rfc-processed-entity RFC3987 -->  

<!--
--><!-- xml2rfc-processed-entity RFC4395 -->  

<!--
--><!-- xml2rfc-processed-entity RFC5226 -->  

<!--
--><!-- xml2rfc-processed-entity RFC5234 -->  

]>
<!-- To make some modification in References which is IETF RFC, change here and add &RFC number in Reference tag at the end-->


<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>

<rfc category="std" docName="draft-larmouth-oid-iri-04" ipr="trust200902">
<!-- To change the file name, change here -->
<front>
  <title abbrev="IRI/URI Namespace for International OIDs">
    An IRI/URI Namespace for International Object Identifiers (OIDs)
  </title>
  <author fullname="John Larmouth" initials="J." surname="Larmouth">
    <organization abbre="ISO/IEC JTC 1/SC 6/WG 9">ISO/IEC JTC 1/SC 6/WG 9</organization>
    <address>
      <email>j.larmouth@btinternet.com</email>
    </address>
  </author>
  <author fullname="Olivier Dubuisson" initials="O." surname="Dubuisson">
    <organization abbre="ITU-T SG17 ASN.1 &amp; OID">ITU-T SG17 ASN.1 &amp; OID</organization>
    <address>
      <email>olivier.dubuisson@orange-ftgroup.com</email>
    </address>
  </author>
  
  <date month="January" year="2010"></date>
<!-- Change here for month and year of submission. -->
  <workgroup>Network Working Group</workgroup>
<!-- Change here for target working group. -->

  <abstract>
    <t>This internet draft defines the IRI/URI scheme for International Object Identifiers.
  The syntax and semantics of the IRI is specified below using the International Object Identifier
 tree specified in ITU-T X.660: "International Object Identifiers".</t>
  </abstract>
</front>

<middle>

<!-- To make section 2.n under section 2, just put section tag within the section tag for section 2. -->
<!-- During the conversion from xml to txt, line break(enter key) will be ignored. -->

  <section title="Introduction">
    <t>The International Object Identifier tree [ITU-T X.660] provides a hierarchically based identification scheme for objects/resources,
 using almost all Unicode/ISO 10646 characters to identify arcs in the tree.  The OID tree has been in existence since about 1984 in a
 numerical form, but the ability to have arcs identified by Unicode labels to identify arcs of the International Object Identifier
 tree was only standardized in 2008.  The first identifier in the sequence can be the name
 of any standards body or any other organization that requests an unambiguous identification of that organization, with subsequent
 identifications in the hierarchy being allocated by that organization.</t>

   <t>There are just under 100,000 allocated Object Identifiers that are recorded in the OID Repository at http://www.oid-info.com </t>

   <t>The URN namespace "urn:oid" as defined in [RFC3061] is based entirely
 on numeric identification of each arc.  For ITU-T purposes, it is essential to be able to use names in any language as well as numbers,
 without resort to any % encoding or restriction to numeric values where an IRI can be used.  This form of URI/IRI provides that facility
 for communications that accept an IRI.  In other circumstances there is a well-specified mapping to a URI.  Consideration was given to
 extending the "urn:oid" scheme to allow names as well as numbers, but this was considered complicated and confusing for existing uses
 of "urn:oid".  A separate new 'oid' IRI scheme was considered far preferable.</t> 

   <t>This form of URI/IRI commences with "oid:/" and is followed by a series of Unicode labels separated by the SOLIDUS '/' character,
 identifying a node in the hierarchical International Object Identifier tree.</t>

    <t>NOTE - The SOLIDUS '/' character is not permitted in Unicode labels.</t>

    <t>An IRI can contain most of the Unicode characters, and in particular can contain all the characters allowed in a Unicode label.
 A URI is restricted to the ASCII character set, but Section 3.1 of [RFC3987] specifies the conversion of the characters allowed in an IRI
 into the characters allowed in a URI, enabling both an IRI and a URI to carry the same semantics for the identification.  This mapping
 is an integral part of the "oid" URI/IRI scheme for [ORS] look-up via the Domain Name System (DNS). This enables names
 based on the Unicode labels in the International OID tree to be used
 wherever an IRI or a URI is required.</t>

    <t>The ORS specifies how an IRI expressed as a series of (abstract) Unicode characters is to be mapped into an ASCII
 form suitable for DNS lookup and transformation to the canonical numeric form.  The mapping performed in the ORS uses the
 transformation specified in Section 4 of [RFC 3490] which references [RFC 3454] (case folding) and [RFC 3492] (punycode
 encoding).  It also uses the Compatibility Decomposition, followed by Canonical Composition (KFCD) specified by Unicode
 5.2.</t>  

    <t>The resource designated by an 'oid' IRI is a set of URLs for multi-media information associated with the node of the International
 OID Tree, and returned by the OID Resolution System [ORS] when given that IRI.</t>
  </section>

  <section title="URI/IRI scheme syntax and semantics for 'oid'">
  
    <section title="URI/IRI scheme syntax">
      <t>This Section uses the ABNF notation commonly used in IETF RFCs (see [RFC 5234]). An IRI in the 'oid' scheme is syntactically
 the ABNF construct &lt;oidiri&gt; defined as follows (with the semantics specified in Section 2.2), and with no white-space between lexical items:</t>
      <t>
        <list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="oidiri = &quot;oid:/&quot; firstarcid subsequentarcid"></t>
          <t hangText="firstarcid = unicodelabel"></t>
          <t hangText="subsequentarcid = 0*(&quot;/&quot; unicodelabel)"></t>
          <t hangText="unicodelabel = 1*(iunreserved)"></t>
        </list>
      </t>
      <t>The external rule name &lt;iunreserved&gt; is defined in Section 2.2 of [RFC3987].</t>      
      <t>When used as a URI, the transformations specified in Section 3.1 of [RFC 3987] are applied.</t>
    </section>
  
    <section title="URI/IRI scheme semantics">
      <t>The &lt;firstarcid&gt; is required to be a Unicode label assigned to one of the arcs from the root of the International OID tree
 specified in [ITU-T X.660] (including long arcs) that identifies a node in the International OID tree.</t>

      <t>The next &lt;unicodelabel&gt; in the &lt;subsequentarcid&gt; (if there is one) is required to be a Unicode label that identifies an arc from that node to a lower level node.</t>
   
     <t>This repeats until the final &lt;unicodelabel&gt; identifies an arc, and hence a node of the International OID tree, that is the referenced resource.</t>

      <t>NOTE - The last identified node is not necessarily a leaf of the tree, but it identifies the designated resource.</t>
    </section>
  
    <section title="Encoding considerations">
      <t>The internationalized resource identifier is specified as an abstract sequence of Unicode characters.  The encoding of those characters
 depends on the specification of the protocol in which they are carried, but will normally be UTF-8 [RFC3629].</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Applications and/or protocols that use this scheme">
      <t>This scheme can be used by any specification requiring an IRI or URI based on the international OID tree to identify an object or to retrieve information associated with that object.</t>
      <t>The 'oid' IRIs are used for two purposes.</t>
      <t>The first is identification of objects such as XSD or ASN.1 specifications, where the only operation is obtaining the identified
 object from a repository, known by context.  In this case, there will normally be only a single 'oid' IRI value that will identify the
 object in the repository.</t>
      <t>The second is the retrieval of information associated with any node of the object identifier tree using the OID Resolution System [ORS].</t>.

    </section>
  
     <section title="Operations on the 'oid' IRIs">
    <t>Operations are transformation to a canonical form (using the [ORS]), and comparison of the canonical forms
 (where exact equality is required for a match) and retrieval of information identified by the 'oid' IRI.</t>
    <t>These operations are expected to be used by applications specifically related to the object in question, and are not
 expected to be supported by general-purpose software.</t>
     </section>


    <section title="Interoperability considerations">
      <t>Equality of 'oid' URIs/IRIs shall be based on exact equality of the slash-separated sequence
of &lt;unicodelabel&gt;s building up the canonical form of the IRI, obtainable by the [ORS] DNS look-up.  The IRI scheme name itself ('oid') is not case sensitive.</t>
  <t>There are no other known interoperability issues.</t>
    </section>

</section>
   
<section title="Security considerations">
    <section title="General">
   <t>An 'oid' IRI does not in itself pose a security threat.  However, care
 must be taken to properly interpret the data referenced by an 'oid' IRI, to 
 prevent that data from causing unintended access, and to avoid
 including data that should not be revealed in plain text.  These  security considerations are addressed by [ORS] through availability
 of DNSSEC in the resolution process, and optional return of encrypted data, with an established trust anchor.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Reliability and Consistency">
    <t>There is no guarantee that once an OID IRI has been used to retrieve information, the same information
 will be retrievable by that IRI in
 the future.  Nor is there any guarantee that the information
 retrievable via that IRI in the future will be observably similar to that retrieved in the past.</t>
     </section>

    <section title="Spoofing">
   <t>The ability to include effectively the full range of Unicode characters in an OID IRI may make it easier to execute
 certain forms of address mimicking (also called "spoofing").  However, OID IRIs are no different from other IRIs
 in this regard, and applications that will present OID IRIs to human users must adhere to best practices regarding
 address mimicking in order to help prevent attacks that result from spoofed addresses (e.g., the phenomenon known as
 "phishing").  For details, refer to the Security Considerations of [RFC3987].</t>

    </section>
</section>

<section title="IANA Considerations">
    <section title="General">
   <t>(The IANA Registration Template is in 4.2)</t>
   <t>Having the 'oid' IRI scheme registered with IANA ensures that there is no duplication of the 'oid' IRI scheme.</t>
   <t>The introduction to [RFC 5226] (para 4) states that "Object Identifiers (OIDs) as defined by the ITU are also
 delegated.  When a name space is delegated, the scope of IANA is limited to the parts of the namespace where IANA has authority"</t>
   <t>Thus the only IANA responsibility is the registration of the scheme name,
 except that it has a long-standing registration responsibility for the sub-tree 1.3.6.1 (oid:/ISO/org/dod/internet), and has
 made many sub-allocations.  This is not affected by this provision of an 'oid' IRI scheme.</t>
     </section>
   <section title="IANA Registration Template">
	<t>This filled-out template should be added to the URI Schemes registry</t>
      <t><list style="hanging">
            	<t>URI/IRI scheme name:			oid</t>
		<t>Status:				permanent</t>
		<t>URI/IRI scheme syntax:		See Section 2.1 of RFC xxxx</t>
		<t>URI/IRI scheme semantics:		See Section 2.2 of RFC xxxx</t>
		<t>Encoding considerations: 		See Section 2.3 of RFC xxxx</t>
		<t>Applications and/or protocols which use this scheme:</t>
                <t>                                     See Section 2.4 of RFC xxxx</t>
		<t>Operations on the 'oid' IRIs:	See Section 2.5 of RFC xxxx</t>
		<t>Interoperability considerations:	See Section 2.6 of RFC xxxx</t>
		<t>Security considerations:		See Section 3 of RFC xxxx</t>
		<t>Contact:
<list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="  J. Larmouth"></t>
          <t hangText="  Rapporteur, ITU-T SG17 ASN.1 &amp; OID"></t>
          <t hangText="  Convenor, ISO/IEC JTC 1/SC 6/WG 9"></t>
          <t hangText="  International Telecommunication Union (ITU)"></t>
          <t hangText="  Place des Nations"></t>
          <t hangText="  CH-1211 Geneva 20"></t>
          <t hangText="  Switzerland"></t>
          <t hangText="  E-mail: tsbmail@itu.int"></t>
</list> </t>
		<t>Author/Change controller:            Same as Contact</t>
                <t>References:                          See Section 6 of RFC xxxx</t>
<t>[[ RFC Editor: Please replace 'xxxx' in all the above IANA Registration Template entries by the RFC number assigned to this
 document. ]]</t>
        </list></t>
    </section>
</section>

  <section title=" Acknowledgements">
    <t>This document is a product of the joint ISO/IEC and ITU-T ASN.1 &amp; OID group. All members of the group are thanked for their
 efforts in this work.</t>
  </section>

</middle>

<back>
  <references title="Normative References">
    <?rfc linefile="1:http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3629.xml"?>

<reference anchor='RFC3629'>

<front>
<title>UTF-8, a transformation format of ISO 10646</title>
<author initials='F.' surname='Yergeau' fullname='F. Yergeau'>
<organization /></author>
<date year='2003' month='November' />
<abstract>
<t>ISO/IEC 10646-1 defines a large character set called the Universal Character Set (UCS) which encompasses most of the world's writing systems.  The originally proposed encodings of the UCS, however, were not compatible with many current applications and protocols, and this has led to the development of UTF-8, the object of this memo.  UTF-8 has the characteristic of preserving the full US-ASCII range, providing compatibility with file systems, parsers and other software that rely on US-ASCII values but are transparent to other values.  This memo obsoletes and replaces RFC 2279.</t></abstract></front>

<seriesInfo name='STD' value='63' />
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='3629' />
<format type='TXT' octets='33856' target='ftp://ftp.isi.edu/in-notes/rfc3629.txt' />
</reference>
<?rfc linefile="254:/tmp/CGI3357.1"?>
    <?rfc linefile="1:http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3986.xml"?>

<reference anchor='RFC3986'>

<front>
<title abbrev='URI Generic Syntax'>Uniform Resource Identifier (URI): Generic Syntax</title>
<author initials='T.' surname='Berners-Lee' fullname='Tim Berners-Lee'>
<organization abbrev='W3C/MIT'>World Wide Web Consortium</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street>Massachusetts Institute of Technology</street>
<street>77 Massachusetts Avenue</street>
<city>Cambridge</city>
<region>MA</region>
<code>02139</code>
<country>USA</country></postal>
<phone>+1-617-253-5702</phone>
<facsimile>+1-617-258-5999</facsimile>
<email>timbl@w3.org</email>
<uri>http://www.w3.org/People/Berners-Lee/</uri></address></author>
<author initials='R.' surname='Fielding' fullname='Roy T. Fielding'>
<organization abbrev='Day Software'>Day Software</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street>5251 California Ave., Suite 110</street>
<city>Irvine</city>
<region>CA</region>
<code>92617</code>
<country>USA</country></postal>
<phone>+1-949-679-2960</phone>
<facsimile>+1-949-679-2972</facsimile>
<email>fielding@gbiv.com</email>
<uri>http://roy.gbiv.com/</uri></address></author>
<author initials='L.' surname='Masinter' fullname='Larry Masinter'>
<organization abbrev='Adobe Systems'>Adobe Systems Incorporated</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street>345 Park Ave</street>
<city>San Jose</city>
<region>CA</region>
<code>95110</code>
<country>USA</country></postal>
<phone>+1-408-536-3024</phone>
<email>LMM@acm.org</email>
<uri>http://larry.masinter.net/</uri></address></author>
<date year='2005' month='January' />
<area>Applications</area>
<keyword>uniform resource identifier</keyword>
<keyword>URI</keyword>
<keyword>URL</keyword>
<keyword>URN</keyword>
<keyword>WWW</keyword>
<keyword>resource</keyword>
<abstract>
<t>
A Uniform Resource Identifier (URI) is a compact sequence of characters
that identifies an abstract or physical resource.  This specification
defines the generic URI syntax and a process for resolving URI references
that might be in relative form, along with guidelines and security
considerations for the use of URIs on the Internet.
The URI syntax defines a grammar that is a superset of all valid URIs,
allowing an implementation to parse the common components of a URI
reference without knowing the scheme-specific requirements of every
possible identifier.  This specification does not define a generative
grammar for URIs; that task is performed by the individual
specifications of each URI scheme.
</t></abstract></front>

<seriesInfo name='STD' value='66' />
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='3986' />
<format type='TXT' octets='141811' target='ftp://ftp.isi.edu/in-notes/rfc3986.txt' />
<format type='HTML' octets='213584' target='http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/html/rfc3986.html' />
<format type='XML' octets='163534' target='http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/xml/rfc3986.xml' />
</reference>
<?rfc linefile="255:/tmp/CGI3357.1"?>
    <?rfc linefile="1:http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3987.xml"?>

<reference anchor='RFC3987'>

<front>
<title>Internationalized Resource Identifiers (IRIs)</title>
<author initials='M.' surname='Duerst' fullname='M. Duerst'>
<organization /></author>
<author initials='M.' surname='Suignard' fullname='M. Suignard'>
<organization /></author>
<date year='2005' month='January' />
<abstract>
<t>This document defines a new protocol element, the Internationalized Resource Identifier (IRI), as a complement of the Uniform Resource Identifier (URI). An IRI is a sequence of characters from the Universal Character Set (Unicode/ISO 10646). A mapping from IRIs to URIs is defined, which means that IRIs can be used instead of URIs, where appropriate, to identify resources.&lt;/t>&lt;t> The approach of defining a new protocol element was chosen instead of extending or changing the definition of URIs. This was done in order to allow a clear distinction and to avoid incompatibilities with existing software. Guidelines are provided for the use and deployment of IRIs in various protocols, formats, and software components that currently deal with URIs.</t></abstract></front>

<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='3987' />
<format type='TXT' octets='111190' target='ftp://ftp.isi.edu/in-notes/rfc3987.txt' />
</reference>
<?rfc linefile="256:/tmp/CGI3357.1"?>
    <?rfc linefile="1:http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4395.xml"?>

<reference anchor='RFC4395'>

<front>
<title>Guidelines and Registration Procedures for New URI Schemes</title>
<author initials='T.' surname='Hansen' fullname='T. Hansen'>
<organization /></author>
<author initials='T.' surname='Hardie' fullname='T. Hardie'>
<organization /></author>
<author initials='L.' surname='Masinter' fullname='L. Masinter'>
<organization /></author>
<date year='2006' month='February' />
<abstract>
<t>This document provides guidelines and recommendations for the definition of Uniform Resource Identifier (URI) schemes.  It also updates the process and IANA registry for URI schemes.  It obsoletes both RFC 2717 and RFC 2718.  This document specifies an Internet Best Current Practices for the Internet Community, and requests discussion and suggestions for improvements.</t></abstract></front>

<seriesInfo name='BCP' value='35' />
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='4395' />
<format type='TXT' octets='31933' target='ftp://ftp.isi.edu/in-notes/rfc4395.txt' />
</reference>
<?rfc linefile="257:/tmp/CGI3357.1"?>
    <?rfc linefile="1:http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5226.xml"?>

<reference anchor='RFC5226'>

<front>
<title>Guidelines for Writing an IANA Considerations Section in RFCs</title>
<author initials='T.' surname='Narten' fullname='T. Narten'>
<organization /></author>
<author initials='H.' surname='Alvestrand' fullname='H. Alvestrand'>
<organization /></author>
<date year='2008' month='May' />
<abstract>
<t>Many protocols make use of identifiers consisting of constants and other well-known values. Even after a protocol has been defined and deployment has begun, new values may need to be assigned (e.g., for a new option type in DHCP, or a new encryption or authentication transform for IPsec). To ensure that such quantities have consistent values and interpretations across all implementations, their assignment must be administered by a central authority. For IETF protocols, that role is provided by the Internet Assigned Numbers Authority (IANA).&lt;/t>&lt;t> In order for IANA to manage a given namespace prudently, it needs guidelines describing the conditions under which new values can be assigned or when modifications to existing values can be made. If IANA is expected to play a role in the management of a namespace, IANA must be given clear and concise instructions describing that role. This document discusses issues that should be considered in formulating a policy for assigning values to a namespace and provides guidelines for authors on the specific text that must be included in documents that place demands on IANA.&lt;/t>&lt;t> This document obsoletes RFC 2434. This document specifies an Internet Best Current Practices for the Internet Community, and requests discussion and suggestions for improvements.</t></abstract></front>

<seriesInfo name='BCP' value='26' />
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='5226' />
<format type='TXT' octets='66160' target='ftp://ftp.isi.edu/in-notes/rfc5226.txt' />
</reference>
<?rfc linefile="258:/tmp/CGI3357.1"?>
    <?rfc linefile="1:http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5234.xml"?>

<reference anchor='RFC5234'>

<front>
<title>Augmented BNF for Syntax Specifications: ABNF</title>
<author initials='D.' surname='Crocker' fullname='D. Crocker'>
<organization /></author>
<author initials='P.' surname='Overell' fullname='P. Overell'>
<organization /></author>
<date year='2008' month='January' />
<abstract>
<t>Internet technical specifications often need to define a formal syntax.  Over the years, a modified version of Backus-Naur Form (BNF), called Augmented BNF (ABNF), has been popular among many Internet specifications.  The current specification documents ABNF.  It balances compactness and simplicity with reasonable representational power.  The differences between standard BNF and ABNF involve naming rules, repetition, alternatives, order-independence, and value ranges.  This specification also supplies additional rule definitions and encoding for a core lexical analyzer of the type common to several Internet specifications. [STANDARDS TRACK]</t></abstract></front>

<seriesInfo name='STD' value='68' />
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='5234' />
<format type='TXT' octets='26359' target='ftp://ftp.isi.edu/in-notes/rfc5234.txt' />
</reference>
<?rfc linefile="259:/tmp/CGI3357.1"?>   
 <reference anchor="ITU-T X.660">
      <front>
        <title>ITU-T X.660 | ISO/IEC 9834-1: Procedures for the operation of OSI Registration Authorities:
 General procedures and top arcs of the International Object Identifier tree (http://www.itu.int/rec/T-REC-X-660/en)</title>
      </front>
    </reference>
  <reference anchor="ORS">
      <front>
        <title>ISO/IEC 29168: Information Technology - Object Identifier Resolution System</title>
      </front>
    </reference>
 </references>
 <references title="Informative References">
    <?rfc linefile="1:http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3061.xml"?>

<reference anchor='RFC3061'>

<front>
<title>A URN Namespace of Object Identifiers</title>
<author initials='M.' surname='Mealling' fullname='M. Mealling'>
<organization /></author>
<date year='2001' month='February' />
<abstract>
<t>This document describes a Uniform Resource Name (URN) namespace that contains Object Identifiers (OIDs).  This memo provides information for the Internet community.</t></abstract></front>

<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='3061' />
<format type='TXT' octets='8387' target='ftp://ftp.isi.edu/in-notes/rfc3061.txt' />
</reference>
<?rfc linefile="273:/tmp/CGI3357.1"?>
    <?rfc linefile="1:http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3454.xml"?>

<reference anchor='RFC3454'>

<front>
<title>Preparation of Internationalized Strings ("stringprep")</title>
<author initials='P.' surname='Hoffman' fullname='P. Hoffman'>
<organization /></author>
<author initials='M.' surname='Blanchet' fullname='M. Blanchet'>
<organization /></author>
<date year='2002' month='December' />
<abstract>
<t>This document describes a framework for preparing Unicode text strings in order to increase the likelihood that string input and string comparison work in ways that make sense for typical users throughout the world.  The stringprep protocol is useful for protocol identifier values, company and personal names, internationalized domain names, and other text strings.  This document does not specify how protocols should prepare text strings.  Protocols must create profiles of stringprep in order to fully specify the processing options. [STANDARDS TRACK]</t></abstract></front>

<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='3454' />
<format type='TXT' octets='138684' target='ftp://ftp.isi.edu/in-notes/rfc3454.txt' />
</reference>
<?rfc linefile="274:/tmp/CGI3357.1"?>
    <?rfc linefile="1:http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3490.xml"?>

<reference anchor='RFC3490'>

<front>
<title>Internationalizing Domain Names in Applications (IDNA)</title>
<author initials='P.' surname='Faltstrom' fullname='P. Faltstrom'>
<organization /></author>
<author initials='P.' surname='Hoffman' fullname='P. Hoffman'>
<organization /></author>
<author initials='A.' surname='Costello' fullname='A. Costello'>
<organization /></author>
<date year='2003' month='March' />
<abstract>
<t>Until now, there has been no standard method for domain names to use characters outside the ASCII repertoire.  This document defines internationalized domain names (IDNs) and a mechanism called Internationalizing Domain Names in Applications (IDNA) for handling them in a standard fashion.  IDNs use characters drawn from a large repertoire (Unicode), but IDNA allows the non-ASCII characters to be represented using only the ASCII characters already allowed in so-called host names today.  This backward-compatible representation is required in existing protocols like DNS, so that IDNs can be introduced with no changes to the existing infrastructure.  IDNA is only meant for processing domain names, not free text. [STANDARDS TRACK]</t></abstract></front>

<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='3490' />
<format type='TXT' octets='51943' target='ftp://ftp.isi.edu/in-notes/rfc3490.txt' />
</reference>
<?rfc linefile="275:/tmp/CGI3357.1"?>
    <?rfc linefile="1:http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3492.xml"?>

<reference anchor='RFC3492'>

<front>
<title>Punycode: A Bootstring encoding of Unicode for Internationalized Domain Names in Applications (IDNA)</title>
<author initials='A.' surname='Costello' fullname='A. Costello'>
<organization /></author>
<date year='2003' month='March' />
<abstract>
<t>Punycode is a simple and efficient transfer encoding syntax designed for use with Internationalized Domain Names in Applications (IDNA).  It uniquely and reversibly transforms a Unicode string into an ASCII string.  ASCII characters in the Unicode string are represented literally, and non-ASCII characters are represented by ASCII characters that are allowed in host name labels (letters, digits, and hyphens).  This document defines a general algorithm called Bootstring that allows a string of basic code points to uniquely represent any string of code points drawn from a larger set.  Punycode is an instance of Bootstring that uses particular parameter values specified by this document, appropriate for IDNA. [STANDARDS TRACK]</t></abstract></front>

<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='3492' />
<format type='TXT' octets='67439' target='ftp://ftp.isi.edu/in-notes/rfc3492.txt' />
</reference>
<?rfc linefile="276:/tmp/CGI3357.1"?>
 </references>
</back>

</rfc>

