<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?rfc linefile="1:draft-kolkman-rse-2011.xml"?>
<!-- automatically generated by xml2rfc v1.35pre1 on 2011-02-21T14:02:22Z -->
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">





<?rfc rfcedstyle="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<?rfc symrefs="no" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="no" ?>
<rfc ipr="trust200902" 
     category="info"
     docName="draft-kolkman-rse-2011-03"
     >
  
  
  
  <front>
    <title abbrev="RSE 2011">RFC Editor: RSE consensus documentation</title>
    
    <author role='editor' initials="O." surname="Kolkman" fullname="Olaf M. Kolkman">
      <organization></organization>
      <address><email>olaf@nlnetlabs.nl</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date month="February" year="2011" day="21" />
    
    
    <keyword>RFC Editor</keyword>
    
    <abstract>
      <t>
	This memo serves as a temporary placeholder for the
	documentation of consensus around the role and
	responsibilities surrounding the RFC Series Editor as
	developed on the rfc-interest list.
      </t>
    </abstract>
  </front>
  
  <!-- +++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++  -->
  <middle>
    
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>
	This memo tries to cast what I believe the consensus to be in
	language that is close to being the basis for text in
	5620bis. This is supposed to be (or quickly evolve into) the
	basis from which we will develop job descriptions and write an
	update to <xref target="RFC5620">RFC5620</xref>.
      </t>
      <t>
	In other words, once we converged this memo will be used as
	the basis for other documents and is not intended to be
	published as RFC.
      </t>
      <t>
	Editorial and other comments appear in [square brackets].
      </t>
    </section>
    
    <section title="The RFC Series Editor">
      <t>
	The RFC Series Editor(RSE) is an individual who assumes serval
	responsibilities.
      </t>
      <section title="Executive Management of the Publication and Production function.">
      <list style="symbols">
	<t> 
	  With respect to the Publication and Production functions,
	  the RSE provides input to the IASA budget, statements of
	  work, and manages vendor selection processes. The RSE
	  performs annual reviews of the Production and Publication
	  function which are then provided to IASA.
	</t>
	<t>
	  Vendor selection is done in cooperation with the streams and
	  under final authority of the IASA.
	</t>

	<t>
	  Concretely:
	  <list style="symbols">
	    <t> 
	      The RSE owns and develops the work definition (the SOW)
	      and manages the vendor search processes. The work
	      definition is created within the (budgetary) boundary
	      condition that are negotiated with IASA and takes into
	      account the RSE's requirements and community input.
	    </t>
	    <t>
	      The RSE manages the evaluation process (the bids agains
	      the SOW) which leads to a recommendation to IASA
	    </t>
	    <t>
	      Final vendor selection is done by the IASA in close
	      consultation with the RSE to ensure that contract terms
	      and other arrangements are consistent with the SOW,
	      consistent with the both RSE's and contractor's
	      requirements to satisfy the contract, and do not
	      conflict with the role of the RSE.
	    </t>
	  
	  </list>
	</t>
	<t>
	  The IASA has the responsibility to approve the total RSE
	  budget (and the authority to deny it) The RSE has the
	  responsibility to manage all the series functions within
	  that budget. It is assumed that there is a level of
	  cooperation between RSE and IASA that allows decisions by
	  the IASA to be 'pro forma'.  In case of disagreement, the
	  IAB will attempt to mediate the issue.  If no mutual
	  agreement can be reached, the IAB will make the final
	  decision.

	</t>
	
	<t>
	  When budgets have been assigned by IASA the RSE is
	  responsible for managing the RFC Editor to operate within
	  those budgets.
	</t> 
	<t>
	  The RSE primaraly supervises the on-going performance of the
	  vendors whitout asserting operational responsibilities.
	  However, the RSE has operational responsibilities for issues that
	  raise above the responsibilities of the publication or
	  publication functions such as cross stream coordination of
	  priorities and other issues.  When the RSE needs to take
	  extra-budgetary or out-of contract measures those actions
	  will be coordinated with IASA.
	</t>
	<t>
	  Create documentation and structures that will allow for the
	  RFC Series' continuity when circumstances engender the need
	  for the execution of the publication and/or production
	  functions by other vendors.
	</t>	    
      </list>
      <t>
	For this type of responsibility the RSE is expected to
	cooperate closely with the IASA and the various streams.
      </t>
      <t>
	To prevent actual or apparent problems with conflicts of
	interest or judgment, the RSE is barred from having any
	ownership, advisory, or other relationship to the vendors
	executing the Publication or Production functions except as
	specified elsewhere in this document.  If necessary, an
	exception can be made after public disclosure of those
	relationships and with the explicit permission of the IAB and
	IASA.
      </t>
      </section>
      <section title="Development of the RFC Publication series.">
	<t>
	  In order to develop the RFC Publication series the RSE is
	  expected to develop a relationships with the Internet
	  technical community.  With that community, the Editor is
	  expected to engage in a process of articulating and refining
	  a vision for the Series and its continuous evolution.
	</t>
	<t>
	  Concretely: 
	  <list style="hanging">
	    <t>
	      The RSE is responsible for the coordination of
	      discussion on Series evolution among the Series' Stream
	      participants and the broader Internet technical
	      community.
	    </t>
	    <t>
	      In time the RSE is expected to develop and refine a
	      vision on
	      <list style="hanging">
		<t>
		  the technical specification series, as it
		  continues to evolve beyond the historical 'by engineers
		  for engineers' emphasis; and
		</t>
		<t>
		  its publication-technical
		  environment: slowly changing in terms of publication and
		  archiving techniques; the communities that produce and
		  depend on the RFC Series.  All of those communities have
		  been slowly changing to include significant
		  multi-lingual non-native-English populations.Some of
		  them also have a primary focus on the constraints and
		  consequences of network engineering, rather than a
		  primary interest in the engineering issues themselves.
		</t>
	      </list>
	    </t>
	    <t>
	      The RSE will develop consensus versions of vision and
	      policy documents which will be approved by the RFC
	      Series Oversight Committee (RSOC, see <xref
	      target="oversight"/>).
	    </t>
	    
	  </list>	      
	</t>
	
	<t>	   
	  
	  For this type of responsibility the RSE cooperates closely with the
	  community and under oversight of the RSOC and thus ultimately under
	  oversight of the IAB.
	</t>
	<t>
	  Consensus is to hire someone with publication experience and grow
	  their knowledge of the community they will serve.
	</t>
      </section>
      <section title="Workload">
	<t>
	  The job is expected to take on average half of an FTE
	  (approx 20 hrs per week) whereby the workload per week is
	  expected to be near full time during IETF weeks, be over 20
	  hours per week in the first few months of the engagement,
	  and higher during special projects.
	</t>
      </section>
    </section>
    
    
    <section anchor="oversight" title="RSE oversight">
      <t>
	The IAB is responsible for oversight over the RFC Series. 
      </t>
      <t>
	In order to provide continuity over periods longer than the nomcom
	appointment cycle and assure that oversight is informed through
	subject matter experts the IAB will establish a group that implements
	oversight for the IAB, the RFC Series Oversight Committee
	(RSOC).
      </t>
      <t>
	The RSOC will act with authority delegated from the IAB: In general it
	will be the RSOC that will approve consensus policy and vision
	documents as developed by the RSE in collaboration with the community.
      </t>
      <t>
	In those general cases the IAB is ultimately responsible for oversight
	and acts as a body for appeal and resolution.
      </t>
      <t>
	For all aspects that affect the RSE itself (e.g. hiring and firing)
	the RSOC prepares recommendations for the IAB but final decision is
	the responsibility of the IAB. For instance the RSOC would:
	<list style="symbols">
	  <t>
	    perform annual reviews of the RSE and reports to the IAB.
	  </t>
	  <t> 
	    manage RSE candidate selection and advises the IAB on
	    candidate appointment (in other words select the RSE,
	    subject to IAB approval)
	  </t>
	</list>      
	It is expected that such oversight by the IAB is a matter of
	due diligence and that the reports and recommendations from
	the RSOC are approached as if they are binding.
      </t>
      <t>
	RSOC as a body should abstain from direct participation
	in policy-making or formation of policy-making committees, which
	would conflict with RSOC's oversight role. If individual members
	of RSOC participate in policy-making, they should be aware of
	possible conflict with their RSOC role and should be prepared
	to recuse themselves from subsequent RSOC decisions if appropriate.
      </t>

      <t>      
	There is one aspect in which the RSOC will work with the IASA:
	the renumeration of the RSE itself. The RSOC will propose a
	budget for approval to the IASA.
      </t>
      <t>      
	The RSOC will be responsible to ensure that the RFC Series is
	run in a transparent and accountable manner.
      </t>
      <t>
	The RSOC shall develop and publish its own rules of order.
      </t>
      
      <section title="RSOC composition">

	<t>

	  The RSOC will operate as a Program of the IAB, with the IAB
	  retaining final responsibility.  The IAB will delegate
	  authority and responsibility to the RSOC as appropriate and
	  as RSOC and RSE relationships evolve. Like other IAB
	  Programs, the RSOC will include people who are not current
	  IAB members.  The IAB will designate the membership of the
	  RSOC with the goals of preserving effective stability,
	  keeping it small enough to be effective, but large enough to
	  provide general Internet Community expertise, specific IETF
	  expertise, Publication expertise, and stream
	  expertise. Members serve at the pleasure of the IAB and are
	  expected to bring a balance between short and long term
	  perspective. Specific input about, and recommendations of,
	  members will be sought from the streams, the IASA, and the
	  RSE.
	</t>
	<t>      
	  
	  The RSE and a person designated to represent the IASA will
	  serve as ex-officio members of the RSOC but either or both
	  can be excluded from its discussions if necessary.
	</t>
      </section>  
    </section>
  </middle>
  
  <back>
    
    
    
    <references title='Normative References'>
      <t>[NONE]</t>
    </references>
    
    <references title='Informative References'>
      <?rfc?><?rfc linefile="1:bibxml/reference.RFC.5620.xml"?>

<reference anchor='RFC5620'>

<front>
<title>RFC Editor Model (Version 1)</title>
<author initials='O.' surname='Kolkman' fullname='O. Kolkman'>
<organization /></author>
<author>
<organization>IAB</organization></author>
<date year='2009' month='August' />
<abstract>
<t>The RFC Editor performs a number of functions that may be carried out by various persons or entities.  The RFC Editor model presented in this document divides the responsibilities for the RFC Series into four functions: The RFC Series Editor, the Independent Submission Editor, the RFC Production Center, and the RFC Publisher.  It also introduces the RFC Series Advisory Group and an (optional) Independent Submission Stream Editorial Board.  The model outlined here is intended to increase flexibility and operational support options, provide for the orderly succession of the RFC Editor, and ensure the continuity of the RFC series, while maintaining RFC quality and timely processing, ensuring document accessibility, reducing costs, and increasing cost transparency.  This memo provides information for the Internet community.</t></abstract></front>

<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='5620' />
<format type='TXT' octets='40744' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc5620.txt' />
</reference>
<?rfc linefile="330:draft-kolkman-rse-2011.xml"?> 
      
    </references>
    
    
    
    
    
  </back>
  
</rfc>

