<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY RFC1195 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1195.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC2119 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC2328 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2328.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC2453 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2453.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5036 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5036.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3618 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3618.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3562 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3562.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3973 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3973.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.ietf-tcpm-tcp-auth-opt SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-tcpm-tcp-auth-opt.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.ietf-pim-sm-linklocal SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-pim-sm-linklocal.xml">
<!-- !ENTITY I-D.lebovitz-ietf-tcpm-tcp-ao-crypto SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.lebovitz-ietf-tcpm-tcp-ao-cypto.xml"-->
<!ENTITY RFC4086 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4086.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4107 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4107.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4593 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4593.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4271 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4271.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4301 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4301.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4303 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4303.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4601 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4601.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4615 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4615.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4306 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4306.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4948 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4948.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4949 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4949.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5226 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5226.xml">
]>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc iprnotified="no" ?>
<?rfc strict="no"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<rfc category="info" docName="draft-lebovitz-kmart-roadmap-03"
     ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="KARP Roadmap">Roadmap for Cryptographic Authentication of
    Routing Protocol Packets on the Wire</title>

    <author fullname="Gregory Lebovitz" initials="G.L." surname="Lebovitz">
      <organization abbrev="Juniper">Juniper Networks, Inc.</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>1194 North Mathilda Ave.</street>

          <city>Sunnyvale</city>

          <region>CA</region>

          <code>94089-1206</code>

          <country>US</country>
        </postal>

        <phone></phone>

        <email>gregory.ietf@gmail.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="" initials="" surname="">
      <organization></organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>

          <region></region>

          <code></code>

          <country></country>
        </postal>

        <phone></phone>

        <email></email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date day="05" month="November" year="2009" />

    <area>Routing, Security</area>

    <workgroup>KARP</workgroup>

    <abstract>
      <t>In the March of 2006 the IAB held a workshop on the topic of
      "Unwanted Internet Traffic". The report from that workshop is documented
      in <xref target="RFC4948">RFC 4948</xref>. Section 8.2 of RFC 4948 calls
      for "[t]ightening the security of the core routing infrastructure." Four
      main steps were identified for improving the security of the routing
      infrastructure. One of those steps was "securing the routing protocols'
      packets on the wire." One mechanism for securing routing protocol
      packets on the wire is the use of per-packet cryptographic message
      authentication, providing both peer authentication and message
      integrity. Many different routing protocols exist and they employ a
      range of different transport subsystems. Therefore there must
      necessarily be various methods defined for applying cryptographic
      authentication to these varying protocols. Many routing protocols
      already have some method for accomplishing cryptographic message
      authentication. However, in many cases the existing methods are dated,
      vulnerable to attack, and/or employ cryptographic algorithms that have
      been deprecated. This document creates a roadmap of protocol
      specification work for the use of modern cryptogrpahic mechanisms and
      algorithms for message authentication in routing protocols. It also
      defines the framework for a key management protocol that may be used to
      create and manage session keys for message authentication and integrity.
      This roadmap reflects the input of both the security area and routing
      area in order to form a jointly agreed upon and prioritized work list
      for the effort.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section anchor="Introl" title="Introduction">
      <t>In March 2006 the Internet Architecture Board (IAB) held a workshop
      on the topic of "Unwanted Internet Traffic". The report from that
      workshop is documented in <xref target="RFC4948">RFC 4948</xref>.
      Section 8.1 of that document states that "A simple risk analysis would
      suggest that an ideal attack target of minimal cost but maximal
      disruption is the core routing infrastructure." Section 8.2 calls for
      "[t]ightening the security of the core routing infrastructure." Four
      main steps were identified for that tightening:</t>

      <t><list hangIndent="3" style="symbols">
          <t anchor="o" hangText="3">More secure mechanisms and practices for
          operating routers. This work is being addressed in the OPSEC Working
          Group.</t>

          <t>Cleaning up the Internet Routing Registry repository [IRR], and
          securing both the database and the access, so that it can be used
          for routing verifications. This work should be addressed through
          liaisons with those running the IRR's globally.</t>

          <t>Specifications for cryptographic validation of routing message
          content. This work will likely be addressed in the SIDR Working
          Group.</t>

          <t>Securing the routing protocols' packets on the wire</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>This document addresses the last bullet, securing the packets on the
      wire of the routing protocol exchanges. The document addresses Keying
      and Authentication for Routing Protocols, aka "KARP".</t>

      <t>It is unlikely that this document, in its current form, will become
      an RFC. More likely is that this document will be split up into several
      smaller documents which may look something like:</t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>Scope &amp; Goals sections will likely become part of the KARP WG
          charter</t>

          <t>Threat document</t>

          <t>Requirements document (may be combined with Threat document)</t>

          <t>Framework document</t>

          <t>RoutingProtocol Design Team Work Plan document. This would
          include sections like Work Phases, Priorities, Security
          Considerations, etc.</t>
        </list>For now, the document serves as the catch all for the set of
      thoughts around the KARP effort. As a working group is formed, decisions
      will be made about the creation of specific documents.</t>

      <t></t>

      <t>Editor's Note on "KMART" vs "KARP": The first few versions of this
      document were called "draft-lebovitz-kmart-roadmap-xx". Upon the
      creation of the BoF for IETF76, the IESG requested the name of the
      effort change so as to avoid any potential trademark issues. The new
      name of the effort is KARP. Version -03 will go out titled
      "draft-lebovitz-kmart-roadmap-03", so as to avoid confusion. As soon as
      the I-D editor queue opens again (Monday, 09 Nov) the document will be
      submitted with s/kmart/karp/ in the title.</t>

      <t></t>

      <t></t>

      <section anchor="TerminologyKmart" title="Terminology">
        <t>Within the scope of this document, the following words, when
        beginning with a capital letter, or spelled in all capitals, hold the
        meanings described to the right of each term. If the same word is used
        uncapitalized, then it is intended to have its common english
        definition.</t>

        <t><list hangIndent="15" style="hanging">
            <t hangText="PSK">Pre-Shared Key. A key used by both peers in a
            secure configuration. Usually exchanged out-of-band prior to a
            first connection.</t>

            <t></t>

            <t hangText="Routing Protocol">When used with capital "R" and "P"
            in this document the term refers the Routing Protocol for which
            work is being done to provide or enhance its peer authentication
            mechanisms.</t>

            <t></t>

            <t hangText="PRF">Pseudorandom number function, or sometimes
            called pseudorandom number generator (PRNG). An algorithm for
            generating a sequence of numbers that approximates the properties
            of random numbers. The sequence is not truly random, in that it is
            completely determined by a relatively small set of initial values
            that are passed into the function. An exmaple is SHA-256.</t>

            <t></t>

            <t hangText="KDF">Key derivation function. A particular specified
            use of a PRF that takes a PSK, combines it with other inputs to
            the PRF, and produces a result that is suitable for use as a
            Traffic Key.</t>

            <t></t>

            <t hangText="Identifier">The type and value used by one peer of an
            authenticated message exchange to signify to the other peer who
            they are. The Identifier is used by the receiver as a lookup index
            into a table containing further information about the peer that is
            required to continue processing the message, for example a
            Security Association (SA) or keys.</t>

            <t></t>

            <t hangText="Identity Proof">A cryptographic proof for an asserted
            identity, that the peer really is who they assert themselves to
            be. Proof of identity can be arranged between the peers in a few
            ways, for example PSK, raw assymetric keys, or a more
            user-friendly representation of assymetric keys, like a
            certificate.</t>

            <t></t>

            <t hangText="Security Association or SA">The parameters and keys
            that together form the required information for processing secure
            sessions between peers. Examples of items that may exist in an SA
            include: Identifier, PSK, Traffic Key, cryptographic algorithms,
            key lifetimes.</t>

            <t hangText=""></t>

            <t hangText="KMP">Key Management Protocol. A protocol used between
            peers to exchange SA parameters and Traffic Keys. Examples of KMPs
            include IKE, TLS, and SSH.</t>

            <t></t>

            <t hangText="KMP Function">Any actual KMP used in the general KARP
            solution framework</t>

            <t></t>

            <t hangText="Peer Key">Keys that are used between peers as the
            identity proof. These keys may or may not be connection specific,
            depending on who they were established, and what form of identity
            and identity proof is being used in the system.</t>

            <t></t>

            <t hangText="Traffic Key">The actual key used on each packet of a
            message.</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>Definitions of items specific to the general KARP framework are
        described in more detail in the Framework section <xref
        target="CommonFramework"></xref>.</t>

        <t></t>

        <t></t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="TerminologyReqs" title="Requirements Language">
        <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
        "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
        document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
        target="RFC2119">RFC2119</xref>.</t>

        <t>When used in lower case, these words convey their typical use in
        common language, and are not to be interpreted as described in <xref
        target="RFC2119">RFC2119</xref>.</t>

        <t></t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="Scope" title="Scope">
        <t></t>

        <t>Four basic tactics may be employed in order to secure any piece of
        data as it is transmitted over the wire: privacy (or encryption),
        authentication, message integrity, and non-repudiation. The focus for
        this effort, and the scope for this roadmap document, will be message
        authentication and packet integrity only. This work explicitly
        excludes, at this point in time, the other two tactics: privacy and
        non-repudiation. Since the objective of most routing protocols is to
        broadly advertise the routing topology, routing messages are commonly
        sent in the clear; confidentiality is not normally required for
        routing protocols. However, ensuring that routing peers truly are the
        trusted peers expected, and that no roque peers or messages can
        compromise the stability of the routing environment is critical, and
        thus our focus. The other two explicitly excluded tactics, privacy and
        non-repudiation, may be addressed in future work.</t>

        <t>It is possible for routing protocol packets to be transmitted
        employing all four security tactics mentioned above using existing
        standards. For example, one could run unicast, layer 3 or above
        routing protocol packets through <xref target="RFC4303">IPsec
        ESP</xref>. This would provide the added benefit of privacy, and
        non-repudiation. However, router platforms and systems have been fine
        tuned over the years for the specific processing necessary for routing
        protocols' non-encapsulated formats. Operators are, therefore, quite
        reluctant to explore new packet encapsulations for these tried and
        true protocols.</t>

        <t>In addition, at least in the case of BGP and LDP, these protocols
        already have existing mechanisms for cryptographically authenticating
        and integrity checking the packets on the wire. Products with these
        mechanisms have already been produced, code has already been written
        and both have been optimized for the existing mechanisms. Rather than
        turn away from these mechanisms, we want to enhance them, updating
        them to modern and secure levels.</t>

        <t>There are two main work phases for this roadmap, and for any
        Routing Protocol work undertaken as part of this roadmap (discussed
        further in the <xref target="WorkPhases">Work Phases</xref> section).
        The first is to enhance the Routing Protocol's current authentication
        mechanism, ensuring it employs modern cryptographic algorithms and
        methods for its basic operational model, fulfilling the requirements
        defined in the <xref target="Ph1Reqs">Requirements</xref> section, and
        protecting against as many of the threats as possible as defined in
        the <xref target="ThreatInScope">Threats </xref> section. Many of the
        Routing Protocols' current mechanisms use manual keys, so the first
        phase updates will focus on shoring up the manual key mechanisms that
        exist.</t>

        <t>The second work phase is to define the use of a key management
        protocol (KMP) for creating and managing session keys used in the
        Routing Protocols' message authentication and data integrity
        functions. It is intended that a general KMP framework -- or a small
        number of frameworks -- can be defined and leveraged for many Routing
        Protocols.</t>

        <t>Therefore, the scope of this roadmap of work includes:</t>

        <t></t>

        <t><list hangIndent="3" style="hanging">
            <t hangText="o">Making use of existing routing protocol security
            protocols, where they exist, and enhancing or updating them as
            necessary for modern cryptographic best practices,</t>

            <t></t>

            <t hangText="o">Developing a framework for using automatic key
            management in order to ease deployment, lower cost of operation,
            and allow for rapid responses to security breaches, and</t>

            <t></t>

            <t hangText="o">Specifying the automated key management protocol
            that may be combined with the bits-on-the-wire mechanisms.</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>The work also serves as an agreement between the Routing Area and
        the Security Area about the priorities and work plan for incrementally
        delivering the above work. This point is important. There will be
        times when the best-security-possible will give way to
        vastly-improved-over-current-security-but-admittedly-not-yet-best-security-possible,
        in order that incremental progress toward a more secure Internet may
        be achieved. As such, this document will call out places where
        agreement has been reached on such trade offs.</t>

        <t>This document does not contain protocol specifications. Instead, it
        defines the areas where protocol specification work is needed and sets
        a direction, a set of requirements, and a relative priority for
        addressing that specification work.</t>

        <t>There are a set of threats to routing protocols that are considered
        in-scope for this document/roadmap, and a set considered out-of-scope.
        These are described in detail in the <xref
        target="Threats">Threats</xref> section below.</t>

        <t></t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="Goals" title="Goals">
        <t>The goals and general guidance for this work roadmap follow:</t>

        <t></t>

        <t><list hangIndent="3" style="hanging">
            <t hangText="1.">Provide authentication and integrity protection
            for packets on the wire of existing routing protocols</t>

            <t></t>

            <t hangText="2.">Deliver a path to incrementally improve security
            of the routing infrastructure. The principle of crawl, walk, run
            will be in place. Routing protocol authentication mechanisms may
            not go immediately from their current state to a state containing
            the best possible, most modern security practices. Incremental
            steps will need to be taken for a few very practical reasons.
            First, there are a considerable number of deployed routing devices
            in operating networks that will not be able to run the most modern
            cryptographic mechanisms without significant and unacceptable
            performance penalties. The roadmap for any one routing protocol
            MUST allow for incremental improvements on existing operational
            devices. Second, current routing protocol performance on deployed
            devices has been achieved over the last 20 years through extensive
            tuning of software and hardware elements, and is a constant focus
            for improvement by vendors and operators alike. The introduction
            of new security mechanisms affects this performance balance. The
            performance impact of any incremental step of security improvement
            will need to be weighed by the community, and introduced in such a
            way that allows the vendor and operator community a path to
            adoption that upholds reasonable performance metrics. Therefore,
            certain specification elements may be introduced carrying the
            "SHOULD" guidance, with the intention that the same mechanism will
            carry a "MUST" in the next release of the specification. This
            gives the vendors and implementors the guidance they need to tune
            their software and hardware appropriately over time. Last, some
            security mechanisms require the build out of other operational
            support systems, and this will take time. An example where these
            three reasons are at play in an incremental improvement roadmap is
            seen in the improvement of <xref target="RFC4271">BGP's</xref>
            security via the update of the TCP Authentication Option <xref
            target="I-D.ietf-tcpm-tcp-auth-opt">(TCP-AO)</xref> effort. It
            would be ideal, and reflect best common security practice, to have
            a fully specified key management protocol for negotiating TCP-AO's
            authentication material, using certificates for peer
            authentication in the keying. However, in the spirit of
            incremental deployment, we will first address issues like
            cryptographic algorithm agility, replay attacks, TCP session
            resetting in the base TCP-AO protocol before we layer key
            management on top of it.</t>

            <t></t>

            <t hangText="3.">The deploy-ability of the improved security
            solutions on currently running routing infrastructure equipment.
            This begs the consideration of the current state of processing
            power available on routers in the network today.</t>

            <t></t>

            <t hangText="4.">Operational deploy-ability - A solutions
            acceptability will also be measured by how deployable the solution
            is by common operator teams using common deployment processes and
            infrastructures. I.e. We will try to make these solutions fit as
            well as possible into current operational practices or router
            deployment. This will be heavily influenced by operator input, to
            ensure that what we specify can -- and, more importantly, will --
            be deployed once specified and implemented by vendors. Deployment
            of incrementally more secure routing infrastructure in the
            Internet is the final measure of success. Measurably, we would
            like to see an increase in the number of surveyed respondents who
            report deploying the updated authentication mechanisms anywhere
            across their network, as well as a sharp rise in usage for the
            total percentage of their network's routers.</t>

            <t></t>

            <t>Interviews with operators show several points about routing
            security. First, over 70% of operators have deployed transport
            connection protection via TCP-MD5 on their EBGP <xref
            target="ISR2008"></xref> . Over 55% also deploy MD5 on their IBGP
            connections, and 50% deploy MD5 on some other IGP. The survey
            states that "a considerable increase was observed over previous
            editions of the survey for use of TCP MD5 with external peers
            (eBGP), internal peers (iBGP) and MD5 extensions for IGPs." Though
            the data is not captured in the report, the authors believe
            anecdotally that of those who have deployed MD5 somewhere in their
            network, only about 25-30% of the routers in their network are
            deployed with the authentication enabled. None report using IPsec
            to protect the routing protocol, and this was a decline from the
            few that reported doing so in the previous year's report.</t>

            <t>From my personal conversations with operators, of those using
            MD5, almost all report deploying with one single manual key
            throughout the entire network. These same operators report that
            the one single key has not been changed since it was originally
            installed, sometimes five or more years ago. When asked why,
            particularly for the case of BGP using TCP MD5, the following
            reasons are often given:</t>

            <t></t>

            <t><list style="letters">
                <t>Changing the keys triggers a TCP reset, and thus bounces
                the links/adjacencies, undermining Service Level Agreements
                (SLAs).</t>

                <t>For external peers, difficulty of coordination with the
                other organization is an issue. Once they find the correct
                contact at the other organization (not always so easy), the
                coordination function is serialized and on a per peer/AS
                basis. The coordination is very cumbersome and tedious to
                execute in practice.</t>

                <t>Keys must be changed at precisely the same time, or at
                least within 60 seconds (as supported by two major vendors) in
                order to limit connectivity outage duration. This is
                incredibly difficult to do, operationally, especially between
                different organizations.</t>

                <t>Relatively low priority compared to other operatoinal
                issues.</t>

                <t>Lack of staff to implement the changes device by
                device.</t>

                <t>There are three use cases for operational peering at play
                here: peers and interconnection with other operators, Internal
                BGP and other routing sessions within a single operator, and
                operator-to-customer-CPE devices. All three have very
                different properties, and all are reported as cumbersome. One
                operator reported that the same key is used for all customer
                premise equipment. The same operator reported that if the
                customer mandated, a unique key could be created, although the
                last time this occurred it created such an operational
                headache that the administrators now usually tell customers
                that the option doesn't even exist, to avoid the difficulties.
                These customer-uniqe keys are never changed, unless the
                customer demands so.</t>
              </list></t>

            <t>The main threat at play here is that a terminated employee from
            such an operator who had access to the one (or few) keys used for
            authentication in these environments could easily wage an attack
            -- or offer the keys to others who would wage the attack -- and
            bring down many of the adjacencies, causing destabilization to the
            routing system.</t>

            <t></t>

            <t>Whatever mechanisms we specify need to be easier than the
            current methods to deploy, and should provide obvious operational
            efficiency gains along with significantly better security and
            threat protection. This combination of value may be enough to
            drive much broader adoption.</t>

            <t></t>

            <t hangText="5.">Address the threats enumerated above in the <xref
            target="Threats">"Threats" section</xref> for each routing
            protocol, along a roadmap. Not all threats may be able to be
            addressed in the first specification update for any one protocol.
            Roadmaps will be defined so that both the security area and the
            routing area agree on how the threats will be addressed completely
            over time.</t>

            <t></t>

            <t hangText="6.">Create a re-usable architecture, framework, and
            guidelines for various IETF working teams who will address these
            security improvements for various Routing Protocols. The crux of
            the KARP work is to re-use that framework as much as possible
            across relevant Routing Protocols. For example, designers should
            aim to re-use the key management protocol that will be defined for
            BGP's TCP-AO key establishment for as many other routing protocols
            as possible. This is but one example.</t>

            <t></t>

            <t hangText="7.">Bridge any gaps between IETF's Routing and
            Security Areas by recording agreements on work items, roadmaps,
            and guidance from the Area leads and Internet Architecture Board
            (IAB, www.iab.org).</t>

            <t></t>
          </list></t>

        <t></t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="NonGoals" title="Non-Goals">
        <t>The following two goals are considered out-of-scope for this
        effort:</t>

        <t><list hangIndent="3" style="hanging">
            <t hangText="o">Privacy of the packets on the wire, at this point
            in time. Once this roadmap is realized, we may revisit work on
            privacy.</t>

            <t></t>

            <t hangText="o">Message content security. This work is being
            addressed in other IETF efforts, like SIDR.</t>
          </list></t>

        <t></t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="Audience" title="Audience">
        <t>The audience for this roadmap includes:<list hangIndent="5"
            style="hanging">
            <t hangText=""></t>

            <t
            hangText="o  Routing Area working group chairs and participants - ">These
            people are charged with updates to the Routing Protocol
            specifications. Any and all cryptographic authentication work on
            these specifications will occur in Routing Area working groups,
            with close partnership with the Security Area. Co-advisors from
            Security Area may often be named for these partnership
            efforts.</t>

            <t></t>

            <t
            hangText="o  Security Area reviewers of routing area documents - ">These
            people are delegated by the Security Area Directors to perform
            reviews on routing protocol specifications as they pass through
            working group last call or IESG review. They will pay particular
            attention to the use of cryptographic authentication and
            corresponding security mechanisms for the routing protocols. They
            will ensure that incremental security improvements are being made,
            in line with this roadmap.</t>

            <t></t>

            <t hangText="o  Security Area engineers - ">These people partner
            with routing area authors/designers on the security mechanisms in
            routing protocol specifications. Some of these security area
            engineers will be assigned by the Security Area Directors, while
            others will be interested parties in the relevant working
            groups.</t>

            <t></t>

            <t hangText="o  Operators - ">The operators are a key audience for
            this work, as the work is considered to have succeeded if the
            operators deploy the technology, presumably due to a perception of
            significantly improved security value coupled with relative
            similarity to deployment complexity and cost. Conversely, the work
            will be considered a failure if the operators do not care to
            deploy it, either due to lack of value or perceived (or real)
            over-complexity of operations. And as such, the GROW and OPSEC WGs
            should be kept squarely in the loop as well.</t>

            <t></t>

            <t></t>
          </list></t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Threats" title="Threats">
      <t>In RFC4949<xref target="RFC4949" />, a threat is defined as a
      potential for violation of security, which exists when there is a
      circumstance, capability, action, or event that could breach security
      and cause harm. This section defines the threats that are in scope for
      this roadmap, and those that are explicitly out of scope. This document
      leverages the "Generic Threats to Routing Protocols" model, <xref
      target="RFC4593">RFC 4593</xref> , capitalizes terms from that document,
      and offers a terse definition of those terms. (More thorough description
      of routing protocol threats sources, motivations, consequences and
      actions can be found in <xref target="RFC4593">RFC 4593</xref> itself).
      The threat listings below expand upon these threat definitions.</t>

      <section anchor="ThreatInScope" title="Threats In Scope">
        <t />

        <t>The threats that will be addressed in this roadmap are those from
        OUTSIDERS, attackers that may reside anywhere in the Internet, have
        the ability to send IP traffic to the router, may be able to observe
        the router's replies, and may even control the path for a legitimate
        peer's traffic. These are not legitimate participants in the routing
        protocol. Message authentication and integrity protection specifically
        aims to identify messages originating from OUTSIDERS.</t>

        <t>The concept of OUTSIDERS can be further refined to include
        attackers who are terminated employees, and those sitting
        on-path.<list hangIndent="3" style="hanging">
            <t hangText="" />

            <t hangText="o">On-Path - attackers with control of a network
            resource or a tap along the path of packets between two routers.
            An on-path outsider can attempt a man-in-the-middle attack, in
            addition to several other attack classes. A man-in-the-middle
            (MitM) attack occurs when an attacker who has access to packets
            flowing between two peers tampers with those packets in such a way
            that both peers think they are talking to each other directly,
            when in fact they are actually talking to the attacker only.
            Protocols conforming to this roadmap will use cryptographic
            mechanisms to prevent a man-in-the-middle attacker from situating
            himself undetected.</t>

            <t />

            <t hangText="o">Terminated Employees - in this context, those who
            had access router configuration that included keys or keying
            material like pre-shared keys used in securing the routing
            protocol. Using this material, the attacker could send properly
            MAC'd spoofed packets appearing to come from router A to router B,
            and thus impersonate an authorized peer. The attacker could then
            send false traffic that changes the network behavior from its
            operator's design. The goal of addressing this source specifically
            is to call out the case where new keys or keying material becomes
            necessary very quickly, with little operational expense, upon the
            termination of such an employee. This grouping could also refer to
            any attacker who somehow managed to gain access to keying
            material, and said access had been detected by the operators such
            that the operators have an opportunity to move to new keys in
            order to prevent an attack.</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>These ATTACK ACTIONS are in scope for this roadmap:</t>

        <t>
          <list hangIndent="3" style="hanging">
            <t hangText="o">SPOOFING - when an unauthorized device assumes the
            identity of an authorized one. Spoofing can be used, for example,
            to inject malicious routing information that causes the disruption
            of network services. Spoofing can also be used to cause a neighbor
            relationship to form that subsequently denies the formation of the
            relationship with the legitimate router.</t>

            <t />

            <t hangText="o">FALSIFICATION - an action whereby an attacker
            sends false routing information. To falsify the routing
            information, an attacker has to be either the originator or a
            forwarder of the routing information. Falsification may occur by
            an ORIGINATOR, or a FORWARDER, and may involve OVERCLAIMING,
            MISCLAIMING, or MISTATEMENT of network resource reachability. We
            must be careful to remember that in this work we are only
            targeting falsification from outsiders as may occur from tampering
            with packets in flight. Falsification from BYZANTINES (see the
            <xref target="ThreatsOutScope">Threats Out of Scope section</xref>
            below) are not addressed by the KARP effort.</t>

            <t />

            <t hangText="o">INTERFERENCE - when an attacker inhibits the
            exchanges by legitimate routers. The types of interference
            addressed by this work include: <list style="symbols">
                <t>ADDING NOISE</t>

                <t>REPLAYING OUT-DATED PACKETS</t>

                <t>INSERTING MESSAGES</t>

                <t>CORRUPTING MESSAGES</t>

                <t>BREAKING SYNCHRONIZATION</t>

                <t>Changing message content</t>
              </list></t>

            <t hangText="" />

            <t hangText="o">DoS attacks on transport sub-systems - This
            includes any other DoS attacks specifically based on the above
            attack types. This is when an attacker sends spoofed packets aimed
            at halting or preventing the underlying protocol over which the
            routing protocol runs, for example halting a BGP session by
            sending a TCP FIN or RST packet. Since this attack depends on
            spoofing, operators are encouraged to deploy</t>

            <t />

            <t hangText="o">DoS attacks using the authentication mechanism -
            This includes an attacker sending packets which confuse or
            overwhelm a security mechanism itself. An example is initiating an
            overwhelming load of spoofed authenticated route messages so that
            the receiver needs to process the MAC check, only to discard the
            packet, sending CPU levels rising. Another example is when an
            attacker sends an overwhelming load of keying protocol initiations
            from bogus sources. All other possible DoS attacks are out of
            scope (see next section).</t>

            <t />

            <t hangText="o">Brute Foce Attacks Against Password/Keys - This
            includes either online or offline attacks where attempts are made
            repeatedly using different keys/passwords until a match is found.
            While it is impossible to make brute force attacks on keys
            completely unsuccessful, proper design can make such attacks much
            harder to succeed. For exmaple, the key length should be
            sufficiently long so that covering the entire space of possible
            keys is improbable using computational power expected to be
            available 10 years out or more. Also, frequently changing the keys
            may render useless a successful guess some time in the future, as
            those keys may no longer be in use.</t>
          </list>
        </t>

        <t />
      </section>

      <section anchor="ThreatsOutScope" title="Threats Out of Scope">
        <t />

        <t>Threats from BYZANTINE sources -- faulty, misconfigured, or
        subverted routers, i.e., legitimate participants in the routing
        protocol -- are out of scope for this roadmap. Any of the attacks
        described in the above <xref target="ThreatInScope">section</xref>
        that may be levied by a BYZANTINE source are therefore also out of
        scope.</t>

        <t>In addition, these other attack actions are out of scope for this
        work:</t>

        <t>
          <list style="symbols">
            <t>SNIFFING - passive observation of route message contents in
            flight</t>

            <t>FALSIFICATION by BYZANTINE sources - unauthorized message
            content by a legitimate authorized source.</t>

            <t>INTERFERENCE due to:<list style="symbols">
                <t>NOT FORWARDING PACKETS - cannot be prevented with
                cryptographic authentication</t>

                <t>DELAYING MESSAGES - cannot be prevented with cryptographic
                authentication</t>

                <t>DENIAL OF RECEIPT - cannot be prevented with cryptographic
                authentication</t>

                <t>UNAUTHORIZED MESSAGE CONTENT - the work of the IETF's SIDR
                working group
                (http://www.ietf.org/html.charters/sidr-charter.html).</t>

                <t>Any other type of DoS attack. For example, a flood of
                traffic that fills the link ahead of the router, so that the
                router is rendered unusable and unreachable by valid packets
                is NOT an attack that this work will address. Many other such
                examples could be contrived.</t>
              </list></t>
          </list>
        </t>
      </section>

      <t />
    </section>

    <section anchor="Categories" title="Categorizing Routing Protocols">
      <t></t>

      <t>For the purpose of this security roadmap definition, we will
      categorize the routing protocols into groups and have design teams focus
      on the specification work within those groupings. It is believed that
      the groupings will have like requirements for their authentication
      mechanisms, and that reuse of authentication mechanisms will be greatest
      within these grouping. The work items placed on the roadmap will be
      defined and assigned based on these categorizations. It is also hoped
      that, down the road in the Phase 2 work, we can create one KMP per
      category (if not for several categories) so that the work can be easily
      leveraged by the various Routing Protocol teams. KMPs are useful for
      allowing simple, automated updates of the traffic keys used in a base
      protocol. KMPs replace the need for humans, or OSS routines, to
      periodically replace keys on running systems. It also removes the need
      for a chain of manual keys to be chosen or configured. When configured
      properly, a KMP will enforce the key freshness policy of two peers by
      keeping track of the key lifetime and negotiating a new key at the
      defined interval.</t>

      <t></t>

      <section anchor="CategoryMsgType"
               title="Category: Messaging Transaction Type">
        <t>The first categorization defines four types of messaging
        transactions used on the wire by the base Routing Protocol. They
        are:</t>

        <t><list hangIndent="15" style="hanging">
            <t hangText=""></t>

            <t hangText="One-to-One">One peer router directly and
            intentionally delivers a route update specifically to one other
            peer router. Examples are BGP and LDP. Point-to-point modes of
            both IS-IS and OSPF, when sent over both traditional
            point-to-point links and when using multi-access layers, may both
            also fall into this category. [question to reviewers: Should we
            list all protocols into these categories right here, or just give
            a few examples?]</t>

            <t hangText=""></t>

            <t hangText="One-to-Many">A router peers with multiple other
            routers on a single network segment -- i.e. on link local -- such
            that it creates and sends one route update message which is
            intended for consumption by multiple peers. Examples would be OSPF
            and IS-IS in their broadcast, non-point-to-point modes.</t>

            <t hangText=""></t>

            <t hangText="Client-Server">A client-server routing protocol is
            one where one router initiates a request for route information
            from another router, who then formulates a response to that
            request, and replies with the requested data. Examples are a BGP
            Route Reflector and [???? Are there other examples? Is this the
            right example? Do discovery protocols fall under this
            category?].</t>

            <t hangText=""></t>

            <t hangText="Multicast">Multicast protocols have unique security
            properties because of the fact that they are inherently
            group-based protocols and thus have group keying requirements at
            the routing level where link-local routing messages are
            multicasted. Also, at least in the case of PIM-SM, some messages
            are are sent unicast to a given peer(s), as is the case with
            router-close-to-sender and the "Rendezvous Point". Some work for
            application layer message security has been done in the Multicast
            Security working group (MSEC,
            http://www.ietf.org/html.charters/msec-charter.html) and may be
            helpful to review, but is not directly applicable.</t>

            <t></t>
          </list>[author's note: I think the above definitions need clean up.
        Routing area folks, especially ADs, PLEASE suggest new text.]</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="CategoryPeerVsGrp"
               title="Category: Peer vs. Group Keying">
        <t>The second axis of categorization groups protocols by the keying
        mechanism that will be necessary for distributing session keys to the
        actual Routing Protocol transports. They are:</t>

        <t><list hangIndent="15" style="hanging">
            <t hangText=""></t>

            <t hangText="Peer keying">One router sends the keying messages
            directly and only to one other router, such that a one-to-one,
            unique keying security association (SA) is established between the
            two routers</t>

            <t hangText=""></t>

            <t hangText="Group Keying">One router creates and distributes a
            single keying message to multiple peers. In this case an group SA
            will be established and used between multiple peers
            simultaneously. Group keying exists for protocols like <xref
            target="RFC2328">OSPF</xref> , and also for multicast protocols
            like <xref target="RFC4601">PIM-SM</xref>.</t>

            <t></t>
          </list></t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="CategoryDiscoveryVsUpdate"
               title="Category:  Update vs. Discovery Protocol">
        <t>The third category group considers protocols by the contents of the
        messages being exchanged in the Routing Protocol. They are:</t>

        <t><list hangIndent="15" style="hanging">
            <t hangText=""></t>

            <t hangText="Updates">Messages that carry route advertisements or
            update information from peer to peer</t>

            <t hangText=""></t>

            <t hangText="Discovery">Messages sent as part of a policy, peer,
            or service discovery process. These messages are normally
            exchanged prior to any adjacency being formed, and before any
            updates are sent. For example, end-point discovery mechanisms are
            common in L2VPN and L3VPN solutions.</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>[QUESTION TO REVIEWERS: is this really just what's described in 3.1
        as "Client-Server" and/or "One-to-One"? Is there really such a
        different in discovery protocols that they need their own category to
        figure out how to authenticate them? Can someone provide a few
        examples?</t>

        <t></t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="SecurityCharacterizations"
               title="Security Characterization Vectors">
        <t>A few more considerations must be made about the protocol and its
        use when initially categorizing the protocol and scoping the
        authentication work.</t>

        <section anchor="InternalVsExternal"
                 title="Internal vs. External Operation">
          <t>The designers must consider whether the protocol is an internal
          routing protocol or an external one, i.e. Does it primarily run
          between peers within a single domain of control or between two
          different domains of control? Some protocols may be used in both
          cases, internally and externally, and as such various modes of
          authentication operation may be required for the same protocol.
          While it is preferred that all routing exchanges run with the utmost
          security mechanisms enabled in all deployments, this exhortation is
          greater for those protocols running on inter-domain point-to-point
          links, and greatest for those on shared access link layers with
          several different domains interchanging together, because the volume
          of attackers are greater from the outside. Note however that the
          consequences of internal attacks maybe no less severe -- in fact
          they may be quite a bit more severe -- than an external attack. An
          example of this internal versus external consideration is BGP which
          has both EBGP and IBGP modes. Another example is a multicast
          protocol where the neighbors are sometimes within a domain of
          control and sometimes at an inter-domain exchange point. In the case
          of PIM-SM running on an internal multi-access link, It would be
          acceptable to give up some security to get some convenience by using
          a group key between the peers on the link. On the other hand, in the
          case of PIM-SM running over a multi-access link at a public exchange
          point, operators may favor security over convenience by using unique
          pair-wise keys for every peer. Designers must consider both modes of
          operation and ensure the authentication mechanisms fit both.</t>

          <t>Operators are encouraged to run cryptographic authentication on
          all their adjacencies, but to work from the outside in, i.e. The
          EBGP links are a higher priority than the IBGP links because they
          are externally facing, and, as a result, more likely to be targeted
          in an attack.</t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="UniqueVsSharedKeys" title="Unique versus Shared Keys">
          <t>This section discusses security considerations regarding when it
          is appropriate to use the same authentication key inputs for
          multiple peers and when it is not. This is largely a debate of
          convenience versus security. It is often the case that the best
          secured mechanism is also the least convenient mechanism. For
          example, an air gap between a host and the network absolutely
          prevents remote attacks on the host, but having to copy and carry
          files using the "sneaker net" is quite inconvenient and
          unscalable.</t>

          <t>Operators have erred on the side of convenience when it comes to
          securing routing protocols with cryptographic authentication. Many
          do not use it at all. Some use it only on external links, but not on
          internal links. Those that do use it often use the same key for all
          peers across their entire network. It is common to see the same key
          in use for years, and that being the same key that was entered when
          authentication was originally configured, or the routing gear
          deployed.</t>

          <t>The goal for designers is to create authentication mechanisms
          that are easy for the operators to deploy and manage, and still use
          unique keys between peers (or small groups on multi-access links),
          and within between sessions. Operators have the impression that they
          NEED one key shared across the network, when in fact they do not.
          What they need is the relative convenience they experience from
          deploying cryptographic authentication with one (or few) key,
          compared to the inconvenience they would experience if they deployed
          the same authentication mechanism using unique pair-wise keys. An
          example is BGP Route Reflectors. Here operators often use the same
          authentication key between each client and the route reflector. The
          roadmaps defined from this guidance document will allow for unique
          keys to be used between each client and the peer, without
          sacrificing much convenience. Designers should strive to deliver
          peer-wise unique keying mechanisms with similar ease-of-deployment
          properties as today's one-key method.</t>

          <t>Operators must understand the consequences of using the same keys
          across many peers. Unique keys are more secure than shared keys
          because they reduce both the attack target size and the attack
          consequence size. In this context, the attack target size represents
          the number of unique routing exchanges across a network that an
          attacker may be able to observe in order to gain security
          association credentials, i.e. crack the keys. If a shared key is
          used across the entire internal domain of control, then the attack
          target size is very large. The larger the attack target, the easier
          it is for the attacker to gain access to analysis data, and greater
          the volume of analysis data he can access in a given time frame,
          both of which make his job easier. Using the same key across the
          network makes the attack vulnerability surface more penetrable than
          unique keys. Consider also the attack consequence size, the amount
          of routing adjacencies that can be negatively affected once a breach
          has occurred, i.e. once the keys have been acquired by the attacker.
          Again, if a shared key is used across the internal domain, then the
          consequence size is the whole network. Ideally, unique key pairs
          would be used for each adjacency.</t>

          <t>In some cases designers may need to use shared keys in order to
          solve the given problem space. For example, a multicast packet is
          sent once but then observed and consumed by several routing
          neighbors. If unique keys were used per neighbor, the benefit of
          multicast would be erased because the casting peer would have to
          create a different announcement packet/stream for each listening
          peer. Though this may be desired and acceptable in some small amount
          of use cases, it is not the norm. Shared group keys are an
          acceptable solution here, and much work has been done already in
          this area (see MSEC working group).</t>

          <t></t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="OutVsInLine_Keying"
                 title="Out-of-Band vs. In-line Key Management">
          <t></t>

          <t>This section discusses the security and use case considerations
          for keys placed on devices through out-of-band configurations versus
          through one routing peer-to-peer key management protocol exchanges.
          Note, when we say here "Peer-to-Peer KMP" we do not mean in-band to
          the Routing Protocol. Instead, we mean that the exchange occurs
          in-line, over IP, between the two routing peers directly. In in-line
          KMP the peers themselves handle the key and security association
          negotiation between themselves directly, whereas in an out-of-band
          system the keys are placed onto the device through some other
          configuration or management method or interface.</t>

          <t>An example of an out-of-band mechanism could be an administrator
          who makes a remote management connection (e.g. using SSH) to a
          router and manually enters the keying information -- like the
          algorithm, the key(s), the lifetimes, etc. Another example could be
          an OSS system which inputs the same information via a script over an
          SSH connection, or by pushing configuration through some other
          management connection, standard (Netconf-based) or proprietary.</t>

          <t>The drawbacks of an out-of-band mechanism include: lack of
          scale-ability, complexity and speed of changing if a breach is
          suspected. For example, if an employee who had access to keys was
          was terminated, or if a machine holding those keys was belived
          compromised, then the system would be considered insecure and
          vulnerable until new keys were defined by a human. Those keys then
          need to be placed into the OSS system, manually, and the OSS system
          then needs to push the change -- often during a very limited change
          window -- into the relevant devices. If there are multiple
          organizations involved in these connections, this process is greatly
          complicated.</t>

          <t>The benefits of out-of-band mechanism is that once the new
          keys/parameters are set in OSS system they can be pushed
          automatically to all devices within the OSS's domain of control.
          Operators have mechanisms in place for this already. In small
          environments with few routers, a manual system is not difficult to
          employ.</t>

          <t>We further define an in-line key exchange as using
          cryptographicly protected identity verification, session key
          negotiation, and security association parameter negotiation between
          the two routing peers. The KMP between the two peers may also
          include the negotiation of parameters, like algorithms,
          cryptographic inputs (e.g. initialization vectors), key life-times,
          etc.</t>

          <t>The benefits an in-line KMP are several. An in-line KMP results
          in key(s) that are privately generated, and not recorded permanently
          anywhere. Since the traffic keys used in a particular connection are
          not a fixed part of a device configuration no steal-able data exists
          anywhere else in the operator's systems which can be stolen, e.g. in
          the case of a terminated or turned employee. If a server or other
          data store is stolen or compromised, the thieves gain no access to
          current traffic keys. They may gain access to key derivation
          material, like a PSK, but not current traffic keys in use. In this
          example, these PSKs can be updated into the device configurations
          (either manually or through an OSS) without bouncing or impacting
          the existing session at all. In the case of using raw assymetric
          keys or certificates, instead of PSKs, the data theft would likely
          not even result in any compromise, as the key pairs would have been
          generated on the routers, and never leave those routers. In such a
          case no changes are needed on the routers; the connections will
          continue to be secure, uncompromised. Additionally, with a KMP
          regular re-keys operations occur without any operator involvement or
          oversight. This keeps keys fresh.</t>

          <t>The drawbacks to using a KMP are few. First, a KMP requires more
          cryptographic processing for the router at the very beginning of a
          connection. This will add some minor start-up time to connection
          establishment versus a purely manual key approach. Once a connection
          with traffic keys have been established via a KMP, the performance
          is the same in the KMP and the out-of-band case. KMPs also add
          another layer of protocol and configuration complexity which can
          fail or be misconfigured. This was more of an issue when these KMPs
          were first deployed, but less so as these implementaitons and
          operational experience with them has matured.</t>

          <t>The desired end goal is in-line KMPs.</t>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Roadmap" title="The Roadmap">
      <t></t>

      <section anchor="WorkPhases"
               title="Work Phases on any Particular Protocol">
        <t>The desired endstate for the KARP work contains several items.
        First, the people desiring to deploy securely authenticated and
        integrity validated packets between routing peers have the tools
        specified, implemented and shipping in order to deploy. These tools
        should be fairly simple to implement, and not more complex than the
        security mechanisms to which the operators are already accustomed.
        (Examples of security mechanisms to which router operators are
        accustomed include: the use of assymetric keys for authentication in
        SSH for router configuration, the use of pre-shared keys (PSKs) in TCP
        MD5 for BGP protection, the use of self-signed certificates for HTTPS
        access to device Web-based user interfaces, the use of strongly
        constructed passwords and/or identity tokens for user identification
        when logging into routers and management systems.) While the tools
        that we intend to specify may not be able to stop a deployment from
        using "foobar" as an input key for every device across their entire
        routing domain, we intend to make a solid, modern security system that
        is not too much more difficult than that. In other words, simplicity
        and deployability are keys to success. The Routing Protocols will
        specify modern cryptographic algorithms and security mechanisms.
        Routing peers will be able to employ unique, pair-wise keys per
        peering instance, with reasonable key lifetimes, and updating those
        keys on a somewhat regular basis will be operationally easy, causing
        no service interruption.</t>

        <t>Achieving the above described end-state using manual keys may only
        be pragmatic in very small deployments. In larger deployments, this
        end state will be much more operationally difficult to reach with only
        manual keys. Thus, there will be a need for key life cycle management,
        in the form of a key management protocol, or KMP. We expect that the
        two forms, manual key usage and KMP usage, will co-exist in the real
        world. For example, a provider's edge router at a public exchange
        peering point will want to use a KMP for ensuring unique and fresh
        keys with external peers, while a manual key may be used between a
        provider's access edge router and each of the same provider's customer
        premise routers with which it peers.</t>

        <t>In accordance with the desired end state just described, we define
        two main work phases for each Routing Protocol:</t>

        <t><list hangIndent="4" style="hanging">
            <t hangText="1.">Enhance the Routing Protocol's current
            authentication mechanism. This work involves enhancing a Routing
            Protocol's current security mechanisms in order to achieve a
            consistent, modern level of security functionality within its
            existing keying framework. It is understood and accepted that the
            existing keying frameworks are largely based on manual keys. Since
            many operators have already built operational support systems
            (OSS) around these manual key implementations, there is some
            automation available for an operator to leverage in that way, if
            the underlying mechanisms are themselves secure. In this phase, we
            explicitly exclude embedding or creating a KMP. A list of the
            requirements for Phase 1 work are below in the section <xref
            target="Ph1Reqs">"Requirements for Phase 1 Routing Protocols'
            Security Updates</xref>.</t>

            <t></t>

            <t hangText="2.">Develop an automated keying framework. The second
            phase will focus on the development of an automated keying
            framework to faciliate unique pair-wise (or perhaps group-wise,
            where applicable) keys per peering instance. This involves the use
            of a KMP. A KMP is helpful because it negotiates unique, pair
            wise, random keys without administrator involvement. It also
            negotiates several of the SA parameters required for the secure
            connection, including key life times. It keeps track of those
            lifetimes using counters, and negotiates new keys and parameters
            before they expire, again, without administrator interaction.
            Additionally, in the event of a breach, changing the KMP key will
            immediately cause a rekey to occur for the Traffic Key, and those
            new Traffic Keys will be installed and used in the current
            connection. In summary, a KMP provides a protected channel between
            the peers through which they can negotiate and pass important data
            required to exchange proof of key identifiers, derive Traffic
            Keys, determine re-keying, synchronize their keying state, signal
            various keying events, notify with error messages, etc. To address
            brute force attacks <xref target="RFC3562"></xref> recommends a
            key management practice to minimize the possibility of successful
            attack-- frequent key rotation, limited key sharing, key length
            restrictions, etc. Advances in computational power due to Moore's
            law are making that management burden untenable-- keys must be of
            a size and composition that makes configuration and maintance
            difficult or keys must be rotated with an unreasonable frequency.
            A KMP will help immensely with this growing problem.</t>

            <t></t>

            <t>The framework for any one Routing Protocol will fall under, and
            be able to leverage, the generic framework described below in
            section <xref target="CommonFramework"></xref>.</t>
          </list></t>

        <t></t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="Ph1Reqs"
               title="Requirements for Phase 1 Routing Protocols' Security Update">
        <t>Here is a proposed list of requirements that SHOULD be addressed by
        Phase 1 (according to "1." above) security updates to Routing
        Protocols [to be reviewed after -01 is released]:</t>

        <t><list hangIndent="5" style="numbers">
            <t>Clear definitions of which elements of the transmission (frame,
            packet, segment, etc.) are protected by the authentication
            mechanism</t>

            <t>Strong algorithms, and defined and accepted by the security
            community, MUST be specified. The option should use algorithms
            considered accepted by the security community, which are
            considered appropriately safe. The use of non-standard or
            unpublished algorithms SHOULD BE avoided.</t>

            <t>Algorithm agility for the cryptograhpic algorithms used in the
            authentication MUST be specified, i.e. more than one algorithm
            MUST be specified and it MUST be clear how new algorithms MAY be
            specified and used within the protocol. This requirement exists in
            case one algorithm gets broken suddenly. Research to identify
            weakness in algorithms is constant. Breaking a cipher isn't a
            matter of if, but when it will occur. t's highly unlikely that two
            different algorithms will be broken simultaneously. So, if two are
            supported, and one gets broken, we can use the other until we get
            a new one in place. Having the ability within the protocol
            specification to support such an event, having algorithm agility,
            is essential. Mandating two algorithms provides both a redundancy,
            and a mechanism for enacting that redundancy when needed.</t>

            <t>Secure use of simple PSKs, offering both operational
            convenience as well as building something of a fence around
            stupidity, MUST be specified.</t>

            <t>Inter-connection replay protection. Packets captured from one
            connection MUST NOT be able to be re-sent and accepted during a
            later connection.</t>

            <t>Intra-connection replay protection. Packets captured during a
            connection MUST NOT be able to be re-sent and accepted during that
            same connection, to deal with long-lived connections.</t>

            <t>A change of security parameters REQUIRES, and even forces, a
            change of session traffic keys</t>

            <t>Intra-connection re-keying which occurs without a break or
            interruption to the current peering session, and, if possible,
            without data loss, MUST be specified.</t>

            <t>Efficient re-keying SHOULD be provided. The specificaion SHOULD
            support rekeying during a connection without the need to expend
            undue computational resources. In particular, the specification
            SHOULD avoid the need to try/compute multiple keys on a given
            packet.</t>

            <t>Prevent DoS attacks as those described as in-scope in the
            threats section <xref target="ThreatInScope"></xref> above.</t>

            <t>Default mechanisms and algorithms specified and defined as
            REQUIRED for all implementations</t>

            <t>Manual keying MUST be supported.</t>

            <t>Convergence times of the Routing Protocols SHOULD NOT be
            materially affected. Materially here is defined as anything
            greater than a 5% convergence time increase. Note that convergence
            is different than boot time. Also note that convergence time has a
            lot to do with the speed of processors used on individual routing
            peers, and this increases by Moore's law over time. Therefore,
            this requirement should be considered only in terms of total
            number of messages that must be exchanged, and less for the
            computational intensity of processing any one message.</t>

            <t>The changes or addition of security mechanisms SHOULD NOT cause
            a refresh of route updates or cause additional route updates to be
            generated</t>

            <t>Architecture of the specification MUST consider and allow for
            future use of a KMP.</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="CommonFramework" title="Common Framework">
        <t>Each of the categories of routing protocols above will require
        unique designs for authenticating and integrity checking their
        protocols. However, a single underlying framework for delivering
        automatic keying to those solutions will be pursued. Providing such a
        single framework will significantly reduce the complexity of each step
        of the overall roadmap. For example, if each Routing Protocol needed
        to define it's own key management protocol this would balloon the
        total amount of different sockets that are needed to be opened and
        processes that are needed to be simultaneously running on an
        implementation. It would also significantly increase the run-time
        complexity and memory requirements of such systems running multiple
        Routing Protocols, causing perhaps slower performance of such systems.
        However, if we can land on a very small set (perhaps one or two) of
        automatic key management protocols, KMPs, that the various Routing
        Protocols can use, then we can reduce this implementation and run-time
        complexity. We can also decrease the total amount of time implementers
        need to deliver the KMPs for the Routing Protocols that will provide
        better threat protection.</t>

        <t>The components for the framework are listed here, and described
        below:</t>

        <t></t>

        <t><list style="symbols">
            <t>Routing Protocol security mechanism</t>

            <t>KMP</t>

            <t>KeyStore</t>

            <t>Traffic Key</t>

            <t>RoutingProtocol-to-KMP API</t>

            <t>RoutingProtocol-to-KeyStore API</t>

            <t>KMP-to-KeyStore API</t>

            <t>Common Routing Protocol mechanisms</t>

            <t>Identifiers</t>

            <t>Proof of identity</t>

            <t>Profiles</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>The framework is modularized for how keys and security association
        (SA) parameters generally get passed from a KMP to a transport
        protocol. It contains three main blocks and APIs.</t>

        <t><figure anchor="figure1" title="Automatic Key Management Framework">
            <artwork><![CDATA[ 
   +------------+   +--------------------+
   |            |   |                    | Check     +-----------+
   | Identifier +-->|                    +---------->|           |
   |            |   |    KMP Function    |           |  Identity |
   +----------- +   |                    |<----------+   Proof   |
                    |                    |  Approve  |           |
                    +-+--------------+---+           +-----------+
                      |              |
      KMP-to-KeyStore |              |
         API          |              |
                     \|/             |
              +-------+-------+      |
              |               |      | KMP-to-RoutingProtocol
              |               |      |  API
              |    KeyStore   |      |
              |               |      |
              +-------+-------+      |
                      |              |
                      |              |
        KeyStore-to-  |              |
 RoutingProtocol API  |              |
                      |             \|/
          +--------------------------+-------------+
          |           |                            |
          |          \|/          Common RtgProto  |
          |   +-------+-------+   Authentication   |
          |   |               |   Mechanisms       |
          +---|  Traffic      |-----+--------------+
          |   |   Key(s)      |                    |
          |   |               |                    |
          |   +---------------+   Specific         |
          |                       RoutingProtocol  |
          |                       Authentication   |
          |                       Security         |
          |                       Mechanism        |
          +----------------------------------------+

]]></artwork>
          </figure></t>

        <t></t>

        <t>Each element of the framework is described here:</t>

        <t></t>

        <t><list hangIndent="8" style="hanging">
            <t hangText=""></t>

            <t hangText="o  Routing Protocol -">Routing protocol security
            mechanism - In each case, the Routing Protocol will contain a
            mechanism for using session keys in their security option. When
            the Routing Protocol uses a transport substrate, e.g. the way BGP,
            LDP and MSDP use TCP, then this applies to the security mechanism
            the includes that substrate.</t>

            <t hangText=""></t>

            <t hangText="o  KeyStore - ">Each implementation will also contain
            a protocol independent mechanism for storing keys, called
            KeyStore. The KeyStore will have multiple different logical
            containers, one container for each session key that any given
            Routing Protocol will need. Keys stored here may be a Peer Key or
            a Traffic Key. There may also be associated parameters as required
            by the SA for any given Routing Protocol.</t>

            <t hangText=""></t>

            <t hangText="o  Peer Key">A key used between peers from which a
            traffic key is derived. An example is a PSK.</t>

            <t></t>

            <t hangText="o  Traffic Key">The actual key used on each packet of
            a message. This key may be derived from the key existing in the
            KeyStore. This will depend on whether the key in KeyStore was a
            manual PSK for the peers, or whether a connection-aware KMP
            created the key. Further, it will be connection specific, so as to
            provide inter- and intra-connection replay protection.</t>

            <t></t>

            <t hangText="o  RoutingProtocol-KeyStore API - ">There will be an
            API for Routing Protocol to retrieve (or receive; it could be a
            push or a pull) the keys from the KeyStore. This will enable
            implementers to reuse the same API calls for all their Routing
            Protocols. The API will necessarily include facility to retrieve
            other SA parameters required for the construction of the Routing
            Protocol's packets, like key IDs or key lifetimes, etc.</t>

            <t></t>

            <t hangText="o  KMP - ">There will be an automated key management
            protocol, KMP. This KMP will run between the peers. The KMP serves
            as a protected channel between the peers, through which they can
            negotiate and pass important data required to exchange proof of
            key identifiers, derive session keys, determine re-keying,
            synchronize their keying state, signal various keying events,
            notify with error messages, etc. As an analogy, in the IPsec
            protocol (<xref target="RFC4301">RFC4301</xref>, <xref
            target="RFC4303">RFC4303</xref> and <xref
            target="RFC4306">RFC4306</xref>) IKEv2 is the KMP that runs
            between the two peers, while AH and ESP are two different base
            protocols that take session keys from IKEv2 and use them in their
            transmissions. In the analogy, the Routing Protocol, say BGP and
            LDP, are analogous to ESP and AH, while the KMP is analogous to
            IKEv2 itself.</t>

            <t></t>

            <t hangText="o  RoutingProtocol-KMP API - ">There will be an API
            for the Routing Protocol to request a session key of the KMP, and
            be notified when the keys are available for it. The API will also
            contain a mechanism for the KMP to notify the Routing Protocol
            that there are new keys that it must now use, even if it didn't
            request those keys. The API will also include a mechanism for the
            KMP to receive requests for session keys and other parameters from
            the routing protocol. The KMP will also be aware of the various
            Routing Protocols and each of their unique parameters that need to
            be negotiated and returned.</t>

            <t hangText=""></t>

            <t hangText="o  KMP-KeyStore API - ">There will be an API for the
            KMP to place keys and parameters into the KeyStore after their
            negotiation and derivation with the other peer. This will enable
            the implementers to reuse the same calls for multiple KMPs that
            may be needed to address the various categories of Routing
            Protocols as described in the section defining<xref
            target="Categories"> categories</xref>.</t>

            <t></t>
          </list></t>

        <t>[after writing this all up, I'm not sure we really need the
        key_store in the middle. As long as we standardize fully all the calls
        needed from any Routing Protocol to any KMP, then there can be a
        generic hand-down function from the KMP to the Routing Protocol when
        the key and parameters are ready. Let's sleep on it.]</t>

        <t>[will need state machines and function calls for these APIs, as one
        of the work items. In essence, there is a need for a core team to
        develop the APIs out completely in order for the Routing Protocol
        teams to use them. Need to get this team going asap.]</t>

        <t></t>

        <t><list hangIndent="8" style="hanging">
            <t hangText=""></t>

            <t hangText="o Identifiers - ">A KMP is fed by identities. The
            identities are text strings used by the peers to indicate to each
            other that each are known to the other, and authorized to
            establish connections. Those identities must be represented in
            some standard string format, e.g. an IP address -- either v4 or
            v6, an FQDN, an RFC 822 email address, a Common Name [RFC PKI],
            etc. Note that even though routers do not normally have email
            addresses, one could use an RFC 822 email address string as a
            formatted identifier for a router. They would do so simply by
            putting the router's reference number or name-code as the "NAME"
            part of the address, left of the "@" symbol. They would then place
            some locational context in the "DOMAIN" part of the string, right
            of the "@" symbol. An example would be
            "rtr0210@sf.ca.us.company.com". This document does not suggest
            this string value at all. Instead, the concept is used only to
            clarify that the type of string employed does not matter. It also
            does not matter what specific text you chose to place in that
            string type. It only matters that the type of string -- and it's
            format -- must be agreed upon by the two endpoints. Further, the
            string can be used as an identifier in this context, even if the
            string is not actually provisioned in it's source domain. For
            example, the email address "rtr0210@sf.ca.us.company.com" may not
            actually exist as an email address in that domain, but that string
            of characters may still be used as an identifier type(s) in the
            routing protocol security context. What is important is that the
            community decide on a small but flexible set of Identifiers they
            will all support, and that they decide on the exact format of
            those string. The formats that will be used must be standardized
            and must be sensible for the routing infrastructure.</t>

            <t hangText=""></t>

            <t hangText="o  Identity Proof - ">Once the form of identity is
            decided, then there must be a cryptographic proof of that
            identity, that the peer really is who they assert themselves to
            be. Proof of identity can be arranged between the peers in a few
            ways, for example pre-shared keys, raw assymetric keys, or a more
            user-friendly representation of assymetric keys, like a
            certificate. Certificates can be used in a way requiring no
            additional supporting systems -- e.g. public keys for each peer
            can be maintained locally for verification upon contact.
            Certificate management can be made more simple and scalable with
            the use minor additional supporting systems, as is the case with
            self-signed certificates and a flat file list of "approved
            thumbprints". Self-signed certificates will have somewhat lower
            security properties than Certificate Authority signed certificates
            [RFC Certs]. The use of these different identity proofs vary in
            ease of deployment, ease of ongoing management, startup effort,
            ongoing effort and management, security strength, and consequences
            from loss of secrets from one part of the system to the rest of
            the system. For example, they differ in resistance to a security
            breach, and the effort required to remediate the whole system in
            the event of such a breach. The point here is that there are
            options, many of which are quite simple to employ and deploy.</t>

            <t hangText=""></t>

            <t hangText="o  Profiles - ">Once the KMP, Identifiers and Proofs
            mechanisms are converged upon, they must be clearly profiled for
            each Routing Protocol, so that implementors and deployers alike
            understand the different pieces of the solution, and can have
            similar configurations and interoperability across multiple
            vendors' devices, so as to reduce management difficulty. The
            profiles SHOULD also provide guidance on when to use which various
            combinations of options. This will, again, simplify use and
            interoperability.</t>
          </list></t>

        <t></t>

        <t>In addition to other business, administrative, and operational
        terms they must already exchange prior to forming first adjacencies,
        it is assumed that two parties deploying message authentication on
        their routing protocol will also need to decide upon acceptable
        security parameters for the connection. This will include the form and
        content of the identity each use to represent the other. It will also
        include the type of keys to be used, e.g. PSK, raw assymetric keys,
        certificate. And it will include the acceptable cryptographic
        algorithms, or algorithm suite. This agreement is necessary in order
        for each to properly configure the connection on their respective
        devices. The manner in which they agree upon and exchange this policy
        information is normally via phone call or written exchange, and is
        outside the scope of the KARP effort, but assumed to have occured. We
        take as a given that each party knows the identity types and values,
        key types and values, and acceptable cryptographic algorithms for both
        their own device and the peer that form the security policy for
        configuration on their device.</t>

        <t>Common Mechanisms - In as much as they exist, the framework will
        capture mechanisms that can be used commonly not only within a
        particular category of Routing Protocol and Routing Protocol to KMP,
        but also between Routing Protocol categories. Again, the goal here is
        simplifying the implementations and runtime code and resource
        requirements. There is also a goal here of favoring well vetted,
        reviewed, operationally proven security mechanisms over newly brewed
        mechanisms that are less well tried in the wild.</t>

        <t></t>

        <t></t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="WorkItems" title="Work Items Per Routing Protocol">
        <t></t>

        <t>Each Routing Protocol will have a team (the [Routing_Protocol]-KARP
        team) working on incrementally improving their Routing Protocol's
        security, These teams will have the following main work items:</t>

        <t>PHASE 1:</t>

        <t><list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="Characterize the RP"></t>

            <t>Assess the Routing Protocol to see what authentication
            mechanisms it has today. Does it needs significant improvement to
            its existing mechanisms or not? This will include determining if
            modern, strong security algorithms and parameters are present.</t>

            <t></t>

            <t hangText="Define Optimal State"></t>

            <t>List the requirements for the Routing Protocol's session key
            usage and format to contain to modern, strong security algorithms
            and mechanisms, per the <xref target="Ph1Reqs">Requirements
            </xref> section above. The goal here is to determine what is
            needed for they Routing Protocol alone to be used securely with at
            least manual keys.</t>

            <t></t>

            <t hangText="Gap Analysis"></t>

            <t>Enumerate the requirements for this protocol to move from its
            current security state, the first bullet, to its optimal state, as
            listed just above.</t>

            <t></t>

            <t hangText="Transition and Deployment Considerations">Document
            the operational transition plan for moving from the old to the new
            security mechanism. Will adjacencies need to bounce? What new
            elements/servers/services in the infrastructure will be required?
            What is an example work flow that an operator will take? The best
            possible case is if the adjacency does not break, but this may not
            always be possible.</t>

            <t></t>

            <t hangText="Define, Assign, Design"></t>

            <t>Create a deliverables list of the design and specification
            work, with milestones. Define owners. Release a document(s)</t>

            <t></t>
          </list></t>

        <t></t>

        <t>PHASE 2:</t>

        <t></t>

        <t><list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="KMP Analysis"></t>

            <t>Review requirements for KMPs [RFC????]. Identify any nuances
            for this particular protocol&rsquo;s needs and its use cases for
            KMP. List the requirements that this Routing Protocol has for
            being able to be use in conjunctions with a KMP. Define the
            optimal state.</t>

            <t></t>

            <t hangText="Gap Analysis"></t>

            <t>Enumerate the requirements for this protocol to move from its
            current security state to its optimal state.</t>

            <t></t>

            <t hangText="Define, Assign, Design"></t>

            <t>Create a deliverabels list of the design and specification
            work, with miletsones. Define owners. Do the design and document
            work for a KMP to be able to generate the Routing Protocol's
            session keys for the packets on the wire. These will be the
            arguments passed in the API to the KMP in order to bootstrap the
            session keys to the Routing Protocol.</t>
          </list></t>

        <t></t>

        <t>There will also be a team formed to work on the base framework
        mechanisms for each of the main categories, i.e. the blocks and API's
        represented in <xref target="figure1">figure 1</xref>.</t>

        <t></t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="ProtocolsInCategories" title="Protocols in Categories">
        <t>This section groups the Routing Protocols into like categories,
        according to attributes set forth in <xref
        target="Categories">Categories Section</xref>. Each group will have a
        design team tasked with improving the security of the Routing Protocol
        mechanisms and defining the KMP requirements for their group, then
        rolling both into a roadmap document upon which they will execute.</t>

        <t></t>

        <t><list hangIndent="4" style="hanging">
            <t hangText="BGP, LDP and MSDP"></t>

            <t>The Routing Protocol's that fall into the category of the
            one-to-one peering messages, and will use peer keying protocols,
            AND are all transmitted over TCP include BGP <xref
            target="RFC4271">RFC 4271</xref>, <xref
            target="RFC5036">LDP</xref> and <xref
            target="RFC3618">MSDP</xref>. A team will work on one mechanism to
            cover these three protocols. Much of the work on the Routing
            Protocol update for its existing authentication mechanism is
            already occuring in the TCPM Working Group, on the <xref
            target="I-D.ietf-tcpm-tcp-auth-opt">TCP-AO </xref> document, as
            well as its cryptography-helper document, <xref
            target="I-D.ao-crypto">TCP-AO-CRYPTO</xref>. The exception is the
            mode where LDP is used directly on the LAN [RFC????]. The work for
            this may go into the Group keying category (w/ OSPF) mentioned
            below.</t>

            <t></t>
          </list><list hangIndent="4" style="hanging">
            <t hangText="OSPF, ISIS, and RIP"></t>

            <t>The Routing Protocols that fall into the category Group keying
            with one-to-many peering messages includes <xref
            target="RFC2328">OSPF</xref>, <xref target="RFC1195">ISIS</xref>
            and <xref target="RFC2453">RIP</xref>. Not surprisingly, all these
            routing protocols have two other things in common. First, they are
            run on a combination of the OSI datalink layer 2, and the OSI
            network layer 3. By this we mean that they have a component of how
            the routing protocol works which is specified in Layer 2 as well
            as in Layer 3. Second, they are all internal gateway protocols, or
            IGPs. The keying mechanisms and use will be much more complicated
            to define for these than for a one-to-one messaging protocol.</t>

            <t></t>

            <t hangText="BFD"></t>

            <t>Because it is less of a routing protocol, per se, and more of a
            peer aliveness detection mechanism, Bidirectional Forwarding
            Detection (BFD) [RFC????] will have its own team.</t>

            <t></t>

            <t hangText="RSVP [RFC????], RSVP-TE [RFC????], and PCE"></t>

            <t>These three protocols will be handled together. [what more
            characterisation should we give here? Routing AD's, provide text
            pls?]</t>

            <t></t>

            <t hangText="PIM-SM and PIM-DM"></t>

            <t>Finally, the multicast protocols of <xref
            target="RFC4601">PIM-SM</xref> and <xref
            target="RFC3973">PIM-DM</xref> will be handled together. PIM-SM
            multicasts routing information (Hello, Join/Prune, Assert) on a
            link-local basis, using a defined multicast address. In addition,
            it specifies unicast communication for exchange of information
            (Register, Register-Stop) between the router closest to a group
            sender and the "rendezvous point" (RP). The RP is typically not
            "on-link" for a particular router. While much work has been done
            on multicast security for application-layer groups, little has
            been done to address the problem of managing hundreds or thousands
            of small one-to-many groups with link-local scope. Such an
            authentication mechanism should be considered along with the
            router-to-Rendezvous Point authentication mechanism. The most
            important issue is ensuring that only the "authorized neighbors"
            get the keys for (S,G), so that rogue routers cannot participate
            in the exchanges. Another issue is that some of the communication
            may occur intra-domain, e.g. the link-local messages in an
            enterprise, while others for the same (*,G) may occur
            inter-domain, e.g. the router-to-Rendezvous Point messges may be
            from one enterprise's router to another. One possible solution
            proposes a region-wide "master" key server (possibly replicated),
            and one "local" key server per speaking router. There is no issue
            with propagating the messages outside the link, because link-local
            messages, by definition, are not forwarded. This solution is
            offered only as an example of how work may progress; further
            discussion should occur in this work team. Specification of a
            link-local protection mechanism for PIM-SM occurred in <xref
            target="RFC4601">RFC 4601</xref>, and this work is being updated
            in <xref
            target="I-D.ietf-pim-sm-linklocal">PIM-SM-LINKLOCAL</xref>.
            However, the KMP part is completely unspecified, and will require
            work outside the expertise of the PIM working group to accomplish,
            which is why this roadmap is being created.</t>

            <t></t>
          </list>These protocols are deemed out-of-scope for this current
        iteration of the work roadmap. Once all of the protocols listed above
        have had their work completed, or are clearly within site of
        completion, then the community will revisit the need and interest for
        working on these:</t>

        <t></t>

        <t><list style="symbols">
            <t>MANET</t>

            <t>FORCES</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>[need text from routing ADs on why these are out of scope]</t>

        <t></t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="Priorities" title="Priorites">
        <t>Resources from both the routing area and the security area will be
        applied to work on these problem spaces as quickly as possible.
        Realizing that such resources are far from unlimited, a rank order
        priority for addressing the work of incrementally securing these
        groups of routing protocols is provided:</t>

        <t></t>

        <t><list style="symbols">
            <t>Priority 1 - BGP / LDP / MSDP - almost done with Phase 1 on
            these, via TCP-AO <xref
            target="I-D.ietf-tcpm-tcp-auth-opt"></xref> .</t>

            <t>Priority 2 - PIM-SM</t>

            <t>Priority 3 - OSPF / ISIS / RIP</t>

            <t>Priority 4 - BFD</t>

            <t>Priority 5 - RSVP and RSVP-TE</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>By far the most important group is the Priority 1 group as these
        are the protocols used on the most public and exposed segments of the
        networks, at the peering points between operators and between
        operators and their customers. BFD, as a detection mechanism
        underlying the Priority 1 protocols is therefore second.</t>

        <t></t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t></t>

      <t>As mentioned in the Introduction , RFC4948 identifies additional
      steps needed to achieve the overall goal of improving the security of
      the core routing infrastructure. Those include validation of route
      origin announcements, path validation, cleaning up the IRR databases for
      accuracy, and operational security practicies that prevent routers from
      being compromised devices. The KARP work is but one step in a necessary
      system of security improvements.</t>

      <t>The security of cryptographic-based systems depends on both the
      strength of the cryptographic algorithms chosen and the strength of the
      keys used with those algorithms. The security also depends on the
      engineering of the protocol used by the system to ensure that there are
      no non-cryptographic ways to bypass the security of the overall
      system.</t>

      <t>Care should also be taken to ensure that the selected key is
      unpredictable, avoiding any keys known to be weak for the algorithm in
      use. <xref target="RFC4086"></xref> contains helpful information on both
      key generation techniques and cryptographic randomness.</t>

      <t>In addition to using a stong key/PSK of appropriate length and
      randomness, deployers of KARP protocols SHOULD use different keys
      between different routing peers whenever operationally possible. <xref
      target="RFC3562">RFC3562</xref> provides some very sound guidance. It
      was meant specifically for the use of TCP MD5 for BGP, but it is more or
      less applicable to Routing Protocol authentication work that would
      result from KARP. It states three main points: (1) key lengths SHOULD be
      between 12 and 24 bytes (this will vary depending on the MAC/KDF in
      use), with larger keys having effectively zero additional computational
      costs when compared to shorter keys, (2) key sharing SHOULD be limited
      so that keys aren't shared among multiple BGP peering arrangements, and
      (3) Keys SHOULD be changed at least every 90 days (this could be longer
      for stronger MAC algorithms, but it is generally a wise idea).</t>

      <t>This is especially true when the Routing Protocol takes a static
      Traffic Key as opposed to a Traffic Key derived per-connection by a KDF.
      The burdon for doing so is understandable much higher than for using the
      same static Traffic Key across all peering routers. This is why use of a
      KMP network-wide increases peer-wise security so greatly, because now
      each set of peers can enjoys a unique Traffic Key, and if an attacker
      sitting between two routers learns or guesses the Traffic Key for that
      connection, she doesn't gain access to all the other connections as
      well.</t>

      <t>However, whenever using manual keys, it is best to design a system
      where a given PSK will be used in a KDF, mixed with connection specific
      material, in order to generate session unique -- and therefore peer-wise
      -- Traffic Keys. Doing so has the following advantages: the Traffic Keys
      used in the per-message MAC operation are peer-wise unique, it provides
      inter-connection replay protection, and, if the per-message MAC covers
      some connection counter, intra-connection replay protection.</t>

      <t>Note that in the composition of certain key derivation functions
      (e.g. KDF_AES_128_CMAC, as used in TCP-AO <xref
      target="I-D.ao-crypto"></xref>), the pseudorandom function (PRF) used in
      the KDF may require a key of a certain fixed size as an input. For
      example, AES_128_CMAC requires a 128 bit (16 byte) key as the seed.
      However, for convenience to the administrators/deployers, a
      specification may not want to force the deployer to enter a PSK of
      exactly 16 bytes. Instead, a specification may call for a sub-key
      routine that could handle a variable length PSK, one that might be less
      than 16 bytes (see <xref target="RFC4615"></xref>, section 3, as an
      example). That sub-key routine would act as a key extractor to derive a
      second key of exactly the required length, and thus suitable as a seed
      to the PRF. This does NOT mean that administrators are safe to use weak
      keys. Administrators are encouraged to follow <xref
      target="RFC4086"></xref> as listed above. We simply attempted to "put a
      fence around stupidity", in as much as possible.</t>

      <t>A better option, from a security perspective, is to use some
      representation of a device-specific assymetric key pair as the identity
      proof, as described in <xref target="UniqueVsSharedKeys"></xref>.</t>

      <t>When it comes time for the KARP WG to design the re-usable model for
      a KMP, <xref target="RFC4107">The Guidelines for Cryptographic Key
      Management, RFC4107</xref> should be will be consulted.</t>

      <t>[[QUESTION TO REVIEWERS: it may be worthwhile to pull the last few
      paragraphs, along with some guidance along the same lines, into section
      4, in a new sub-section with a title something like "Security tips for
      KARP design teams working on Routing Protocol reviews and updates". Or
      maybe even into its own info document, "Security Guidelines for KARP
      Design Teams".Thoughts?]]</t>

      <t>The mechanisms that will be defined under this roadmap aim to improve
      the security, better protect against more threats, and provider far
      greater operational efficiencies than the state of things at the time of
      this writing. However, none of these changes will improve Internet
      security unless they are implemented and deployed. Other influences must
      be brought to bare upon operators and organizations to create incentives
      for deployment. Such incentives may take the form of PCI-like industry
      compliance/certifications, well advertised BCPs profiling the use of
      this roadmap's output, end-user demand or insistance.</t>

      <t></t>
    </section>

    <section title="IANA Considerations">
      <t></t>

      <t>This document has no actions for IANA.</t>

      <t></t>
    </section>

    <section title="Acknowledgements">
      <t></t>

      <t>The outline for this draft was created from discussions and
      agreements with Routing AD's Ross Callon and Dave Ward, Security AD's
      Tim Polk and Pasi Eronen, and IAB members Danny McPherson and Gregory
      Lebovitz.</t>

      <t>Mat Ford and Bill Atwood provided reviews to -00.</t>

      <t>Danny McPherson provided an extremely detailed and useful review of
      -01.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="ChangeHistory"
             title="Change History (RFC Editor: Delete Before Publishing)">
      <t>[NOTE TO RFC EDITOR: this section for use during I-D stage only.
      Please remove before publishing as RFC.]</t>

      <t>-00-00 original rough rough rough draft for review by routing and
      security AD's</t>

      <t>-00- original submission</t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>adds new category = multicast protocols in category section and
          mentions mcast in group keying category description.</t>

          <t>add a lot of references where they did not exist before, or where
          there were only place holders. Still more work needed on this.</t>

          <t>abstract filled in</t>

          <t>changed from standards track to informational (this was an
          oversight in last draft).</t>

          <t>filled out threats section with detailed descriptions, and linked
          to RPsec threats RFC</t>

          <t>made ascii art for the basic KMP framework</t>

          <t>added section on internal versus external peering and the
          requirements decisions for them</t>

          <t>added security characterization section in sect 2, added sections
          discussing internal vs external protocols, shared vs unique keys,
          oob vs in-band keying</t>

          <t>incorporates all D Ward's feedback from his initial skim of the
          document.</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>-01-</t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>Updated <xref target="figure1">framework</xref> diagram to
          include all listed and described elements. Needs review and honing.
          Gregory Lebovitz (GL).</t>

          <t>Added comment in <xref
          target="ProtocolsInCategories">protocols</xref> section that much of
          the BGP/LDP Phase 1 work is already being done in tcp-ao and
          ao-crypto. GL.</t>

          <t>Updated Scope making the 2 work phases more clear earlier in the
          document. GL.</t>

          <t>Broke <xref target="WorkItems">work items</xref> section into two
          Phases, 1 for manual key update, and second for KMP work. GL.</t>

          <t>Re-org'd doc. Brought <xref target="Threats">Threats</xref>
          section out into its own top-level section. Did same with <xref
          target="Categories">Categorization</xref> section, leaving Roadmap
          section more focused. Moved ToDo list and Change History to end of
          doc, after Acknowledgements. GL.</t>

          <t>added new <xref target="WorkPhases">sect 2.3</xref> on main
          roadmap phases. Previous section <xref
          target="CommonFramework">Common Framework</xref> moved to 2.4. Tim
          Polk (TP).</t>

          <t>Added Section 2.3.1 <xref target="Ph1Reqs">Requirements for Phase
          1 Routing Protocols' Security Update</xref>. This provides a nice
          starter set of requirements for any work team. GL.</t>

          <t>Filled out text for <xref target="OutVsInLine_Keying">Out vs
          In-band Key Mgmt</xref> section, significantly. Changed the term
          from "in-band" to "in-line".</t>

          <t>Section <xref target="Threats">Threats</xref> Clarified DoS
          threats in and out of scope better. We are not preventing all DoS
          attacks. Just those we can reasonably via authentication. TP.</t>

          <t>Sect <xref target="OutVsInLine_Keying">In-band vs
          Out-of-Band</xref>clarified that In-band does not mean in-band to
          Routing Protocol, but rather over IP between the Routing Protocols,
          rather than pushed down by some external management entity. TP.</t>

          <t>In <xref target="Categories">roadmap</xref> section, added "it is
          also hoped that we can create one kmp per category..." Also
          explained value of a KMP. TP.</t>

          <t>Added "operators" to <xref target="Audience">audience</xref>
          list. Matt Ford (MF).</t>

          <t>Described why BGP (and LDP) security is not deployed very often.
          Added this <xref target="Scope">Scope</xref> section, point 4. If
          mechanisms aren't being deployed, why is that? What, if anything,
          could be done to improve deployment? Tried to address these. Need
          references (see To Do list below). MF.</t>

          <t>Added some text to security section to address this from MF: say
          something here about the limitations of this approach, if any - and
          refer back to the need for other pieces of the puzzle. May need more
          work.</t>

          <t>Cleaned up text for multicast part of <xref
          target="CategoryMsgType">Message Type</xref> section and <xref
          target="ProtocolsInCategories">Protocols</xref> section, clarifying
          PIM's two message types, mcast and unicast, in both places. Bill
          Atwood (BA).</t>

          <t>In section <xref target="ProtocolsInCategories">Protocols</xref>,
          added references to 4601 and PIM-SM-LINKLOCAL. BA.</t>

          <t>Editorial changes pointed out various folks.</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>-02-</t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>Re-submitted due to expiration. Text did not change. Substantive
          update coming shortly.</t>

          <t></t>

          <t></t>
        </list></t>

      <t>- 03 -</t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>changed "BaseRP" to "Routing Protocol" throughout the doc -
          man</t>

          <t>filled out the Terminology section</t>

          <t>changed "KMART" to "KARP" in everything but the title, since the
          -00 deadline had long since passed. Will change the title of the doc
          to KARP as soon as the window re-opens.</t>

          <t>priorities in sect 4.6 changed. Added PIM-SM. Lowered OSPF and
          BFD, based on feedback by a few people.</t>

          <t>many edits resulting from Danny McPherson's review.</t>

          <t>added "Brute Foce Attacks Against Password/Keys" to Threats <xref
          target="ThreatInScope"></xref> section.</t>

          <t>Significant updates to Security Considerations section</t>

          <t>Added a few references throughout to RFC3562</t>

          <t>4.3 2nd to last P - added a comment to clarify that two parties
          (or an org) must discuss ahead of time what they want their
          connections' secruity properties to be. - dward</t>

          <t>added to 4.4 Phase 1 - New Section: Transition and Deployment
          Considerations. ea wg must call out the operational transition plan
          from old to new security. Best if don't bounce link. - dward</t>

          <t>added 3.3 (but not sure if this is right)- endpoint discovery
          mechanisms? endpoint discovery mechanism (L2VPN, L3VPN, etc).
          Discovery is much different security properties than passing Routing
          updates. - dward</t>

          <t>More requirements: Added to 4.2: X - convergence SHOULD not be
          affected by what we choose; adding security SHOULD not cause a
          refresh of route updates or cause additional route updates to be
          generated; adding auth should not be an attack vector itself. AKA,
          the use of MD5 is so expensive that spoofing BGP packets w/ MD5
          causes the control plane to be attacked because CPU went to 100% -
          dward</t>

          <t>updated stats on MD5 usage, and cited [ISR2008]. - mchpherson</t>
        </list></t>

      <t></t>

      <t></t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="ToDo"
             title="Needs Work in Next Draft (RFC Editor: Delete Before Publishing)">
      <t>[NOTE TO RFC EDITOR: this section for use during I-D stage only.
      Please remove before publishing as RFC.]</t>

      <t>List of stuff that still needs work<list style="symbols">
          <t>RTG AD's or delegates: clean up the three definitions of route
          message type categories. Need RTG Area folks input on this.</t>

          <t>More clarity on the work items for those defining and specifying
          the framework elements and API's themselves.</t>

          <t>RTG AD's or delegates: text justifying RSVP and RSVP-TE and what
          we think solving that problem may look like</t>

          <t>RTG AD's or delegates: more justification for why MANET and
          FORCES are out of scope. Need ref for those RFCs.</t>

          <t>Danny McPherson: Get reference for BGP auth usage stats in <xref
          target="Scope">Scope</xref> section, item 4.</t>

          <t></t>

          <t>security section: pull out security guidance to routing protocol
          design teams stuff and place into its own section?</t>

          <t></t>

          <t></t>
        </list></t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      &RFC2119;

      &RFC4593;

      &RFC4948;
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <reference anchor="I-D.ao-crypto"
                 target="http://tools.ietf.org/html/draft-lebovitz-ietf-tcpm-tcp-ao-crypto-00">
        <!-- bibxml3 wasn't happy, so entered this manually. Replace before publish as RFC -->

        <front>
          <title>Cryptographic Algorithms, Use and Implementation Requirements
          for TCP Authentication Option</title>

          <author initials="G. M." surname="Lebovitz">
            <organization>Juniper Networks, Inc.</organization>
          </author>

          <date month="March" year="2009" />
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="ISR2008"
                 target="http://www.arbornetworks.com/dmdocuments/ISR2008_US.pdf">
        <front>
          <title>Worldwide Infrastructure Security Report</title>

          <author initials="D." surname="McPherson">
            <organization>Arbor Networks, Inc.</organization>
          </author>

          <author initials="C." surname="Labovitz">
            <organization>Arbor Networks, Inc.</organization>
          </author>

          <date month="October" year="2008" />
        </front>
      </reference>

      &I-D.ietf-tcpm-tcp-auth-opt;

      <!-- &I-D.lebovitz-ietf-tcpm-tcp-ao-crypto; -->

      &I-D.ietf-pim-sm-linklocal;

      &RFC4271;

      &RFC2328;

      &RFC3562;

      &RFC4086;

      &RFC4107;

      &RFC4301;

      &RFC4303;

      &RFC4306;

      &RFC4601;

      &RFC4615;

      &RFC3973;

      &RFC2453;

      &RFC5036;

      &RFC3618;

      &RFC4949;

      &RFC1195;

      &RFC5226;
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
