<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">

<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
    <!-- try to enforce the ID-nits conventions and DTD validity -->
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>    <!-- items used when reviewing the document -->
<?rfc comments="no" ?>  <!-- controls display of <cref> elements -->
<?rfc inline="no" ?>    <!-- when no, put comments at end in comments section,
                                otherwise, put inline -->
<?rfc editing="no" ?>   <!-- when yes, insert editing marks -->

    <!-- create table of contents (set it options).
           Note the table of contents may be omitted
         for very short documents -->

<?rfc toc="yes"?><?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>

    <!-- choose the options for the references. Some like
         symbolic tags in the references (and citations)
         and others prefer numbers. --> 
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?><?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
    <!-- these two save paper: start new paragraphs from the same page etc. -->
<?rfc compact="yes" ?><?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<!-- end of list of processing instructions -->
    <!-- Information about the document.
         categories values: std, bcp, info, exp, and historic
         For Internet-Drafts, specify attribute "ipr".
         (ipr values are: full3667, noModification3667, noDerivatives3667),
         Also for Internet-Drafts, can specify values for
         attributes "iprExtract", and "docName".  Note
         that the value for iprExtract is the anchor attribute
         value of a section that can be extracted, and is only
         useful when the value of "ipr" is not "full3667". -->
    <!-- TODO: verify which attributes are specified only
            by the RFC editor.  It appears that attributes
            "number", "obsoletes", "updates", and "seriesNo"
            are specified by the RFC editor (and not by
            the document author). -->

<rfc	category="std"
	ipr="trust200902"
	docName="draft-johansson-dane-sip-00"
	updates="5922"
>
<front>
    <title abbrev="SIP TLS connection setup using DANE">TLS sessions in SIP using DNS-based Authentication of Named Entities (DANE) TLSA records</title>

    <!-- add 'role="editor"' below for the editors if appropriate -->    

    <author fullname="Olle E. Johansson" initials="O.E." surname="Johansson">
      <organization>Edvina AB</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Runbovägen 10</street>
          <city>Sollentuna</city>
          <code>SE-192 48</code>
          <country>SE</country>
        </postal>
        <email>oej@edvina.net</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date year="2013" />
<!-- month="May" is no longer necessary note also, day="30" is optional -->
    
    <area>Real Time Applications and Infrastructure (RAI)</area>    
    
    <!-- WG name at the upperleft corner of the doc, IETF fine for individual submissions -->
    
    <workgroup>Dispatch</workgroup>
    
    <keyword>I-D</keyword>

    <keyword>Internet-Draft</keyword>
	
    <abstract>
	<t>
	Use of TLS in the SIP protocol is defined in multiple documents, starting with RFC 3261.
	The actual verification that happens when setting up a SIP TLS connection to a SIP
	server based on a SIP URI is described in detail in RFC 5922 - SIP Domain Certificates.</t>
	<t>In this document, an alternative method is defined, using 
	DNS-Based Authentication of Named Entities (DANE).
	By looking up TLSA DNS records and using DNSsec protection of the required queries,
	including lookups for NAPTR and SRV records, a SIP Client can verify
	the identity of the TLS SIP server in a different way, matching on the SRV host name
	in the X.509 PKIX certificate instead of the SIP domain. This provides more scalability
	in hosting solutions and make it easier to use standard CA certificates (if needed at all).
	</t>
	<t>
	This document updates RFC 5922.
	</t>
    </abstract>

</front>

<middle>

    <section anchor="Introduction" title="Introduction">
	<t>
	RFC 3261 <xref target="RFC3261"/> defines how to use TLS in the SIP protocol, but
	doesn't describe the actual verification between a SIP request and a TLS server
	certificate in detail.
	RFC 5922 <xref target="RFC5922"/> updates RFC 3261 with a definition of how a SIP 
	client matches a PKIX X.509 <xref target="RFC5280"/> certificate provided by a
	TLS-enabled SIP server with the domain of a SIP request that caused the connection
	to be set up. Verification is done using the domain part of the SIP URI and the
	X.509 SubjectAltName extension of type dNSName or uniformResourceIdentifier.
	This is called "domain verification" as opposed to "host verification" in RFC 5922.
	</t>
	<t>
	Including all domains hosted by a server in a server's certificate doesn't provide for a 
	scalable and easy-managed solution. Every time a service adds a domain, a new certificate
	will need to be provided, unless TLS Server Name Identification (SNI) is used,
	where each domain can have it's own certificate. Having one certificate per domain
	and subdomain adds to the administration of a service. In addition, no known 
	commercial CA offers certificate services with SIP URI's in the certificates.
	</t>
	<t>
	Using DNSsec and DNS-based Authentication of Named Entities (DANE)<xref target="RFC6698"/>
	the chain from a SIP uri to a TLS certificate changes, as outlined in this document.
	With DNSsec, the DNS lookups are authenticated and can be verified and trusted.
	<xref target="I-D.ietf-dane-srv"/> describes a DANE-based chain of trust, matching
	the SRV host name with the contents of the certificate.
	</t>
	<t>
	This document describes how a SIP implementation can use DANE to set up a secure
	connection to a SIP server with TLS support. In addition, we describe how a server
	can provide support for RFC 5922-style clients with the same certificate, if needed.
	</t>
	<t>
	This document updates RFC5922 so that SIP implementations supporting DANE 
	can validate a SIP domain identity using secure DNS queries and the identity
	of the SIP host by verifying the certificate using the SRV host name found in
	a SubjectAltName extension of type DNSName in the certificate.
	The domain verification will now happen based on DNSsec and the 
	TLS verification will be based on host names (host verification in RFC 5922).
	</t>
	<t>In order to learn about DANE and the different ways a TLSA record can
	be constructed, readers of this document needs to also read RFC 6698 <xref target="RFC6698"/>.</t>

    </section>

    <section anchor="Conventions" title="Terminology and Conventions Used in This Document">
		<t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
		"SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this 
		document are to be interpreted as described in RFC 2119 <xref target="RFC2119"/>.</t>
		
		<t>RFC 3261 <xref target="RFC3261"/> defines additional terms used in this 
		document that are specific to the SIP domain such as "proxy"; "registrar";
		"redirect server"; "user agent server" or "UAS"; "user agent client" or "UAC";
		"back-to-back user agent" or "B2BUA"; "dialog"; "transaction"; "server transaction".</t>

   		<t>This document uses the term "SIP Server" that is defined to include the following
		SIP entities: user agent server (UAS), registrar, redirect server, a SIP proxy in the role
		of user agent server, and a B2BUA in the role of a user agent server.</t>

   		<t>This document uses the term "SIP client" that is defined to include the following
		SIP entities: user agent client(UAC), a SIP proxy in the role
		of user agent client, and a B2BUA in the role of a user agent client.</t>
   		
	</section>
	
	<section anchor="FromUriToSRV" title="Using DNS in the SIP protocol"> 
	<t>RFC 3263<xref target="RFC3263"/> describes how a SIP implementation use DNS
	to find the next hop server. The first step is to look up a DNS NAPTR record for
	the domain part of the URI. NAPTR records are used by the target domain to
	indicate reachability using different transports. NAPTR may be used to indicate
	a preference for TLS/TCP connections.</t>
	<t>The result of the NAPTR lookup is a DNS name used to query for DNS SRV records.
	The list of DNS SRV records indicate host names that are queried for to find
	A or AAAA records with IP addresses.
	</t>
	<t>SIP SRV records for TLS/TCP are using the prefix _sips._tcp, as in the DNS name
	_sips._tcp.example.com.</t>
	<t>A SIP implementation with no support for NAPTR may, based on configuration
	or URI scheme, choose to set up a TLS session to the target domain.</t>
	<t>
	<list style='empty'>
		<t>In rare cases, no SRV lookup is done. This means that the implementation
		lacks capability to do load balancing and failover based on the information
		in the DNS. These type of clients are not considered in this document.</t>
	</list>
	</t>
	</section>

	<section anchor="ReasonsForDnssec" title="Why DNSsec is important for SIP">
	<t>
	DNS relies on DNS lookups not only to find the next hop server, but also for
	server administrators to provide failover and to load balance clients. The
	result of querying for one domain may need to SRV records or host names in
	another domain. Without DNSsec, an attacker can forge DNS replies and issue
	bogus DNS records, directing traffic to a bad server. This applies to
	calls as well as instant messaging, chat and presense.
	</t>
	</section>

	<section anchor="DaneSecureDelegation" title="Secure delegation is required for DANE to apply"> 
	<t>
	It is important for implementors to understand the concept of "secure" DNSsec validation 
	according to RFC 4033<xref target="RFC4033"/>. For this specification to take effect,
	all DNS RRsets in the chain from SIP URI to IP address and TLSA record must be secure.
	(This corresponds to the A.D. bit being set in the responses).
	</t>
	<t>
	If any RRset is not secure, this specification doesn't apply and the implementation
	should fall back to RFC 5922<xref target="RFC5922"/> behaviour. If any of the responses
	are "bogus" according to DNSsec validation, the client MUST abort the connection.
	</t>
	</section>

	<section anchor="TlsaName" title="TLSA record name"> 
	<t>
	For the SIP protocol DANE usage, TLSA records are to be found in 
	accordance with <xref target="I-D.ietf-dane-srv"/>. If the domain example.com's
	TLS SRV records points to sip01.example.com port 5042 then the corresponding
	TLSA record will be found using the name _5042._tcp.sip01.example.com.
	</t>
	</section>

	<section anchor="FallbackTLSA" title="Procedures for DANE-capable SIP implementations">
	<t>
	DANE capable SIP implementations follow the procedures above to find a 
	SRV host name and look for a TLSA record. If no TLSA record is found,
	the client should fall back to RFC 5922 behaviour.
	</t>
	<t>If a TLSA record is found, the client should never fall back to
	RFC 5922 behaviour. If TLSA-based validation fails, the client
	MUST abort the connection attempt.
	</t>
	</section>

	<section anchor="CertificateContents" title="X.509 certicate validation"> 
	<t>When using DANE-based validation the client validates the SRV hostname 
	with the certificate using RFC 5922 rules. A DANE-capable SIP implementation
	looks for the SRV hostname in the list of SubjAltName DNSName extension fields.
	Only if there are no SubjAltName extension fields may the client look in 
	the CN of the X.509 certificate (according to RFC 5922).</t>
	<t>If the SRV host name is not found in the certificate, DANE validation
	fails and the client MUST abort the connection.</t>
	<t>Using the SRV host name for validation of a SIP domain identity is an
	update to RFC 5922</t>
	
	</section>

	<section anchor="BackwardComp" title="Backward Compatibility with RFC 5922"> 
	<t>
	RFC 5922<xref target="RFC5922"/> implementations with no DANE support
	will be able to connect with the matching described in that document.
	SIP Servers can use certificates that are compatible with both this 
	specification and RFC5922.
	</t>
	<t><xref target="I-D.ietf-dane-srv"/> requires use of the TLS Server Name
	Indication (SNI) extension <xref target="RFC6066"/>. This is not a requirement
	in this document, since SIP certificates can support both RFC 5922
	style validation and DANE-based validation with the same certificate.
	</t>
	</section>

	<section anchor="CertExamples" title="Examples on certificate content">
	<t>
	This section gives examples on certificate content and how the match
	a given URI. The X.509 PKIX Subject field CN value is abbreviated as "CN",
	the SubjectAltName extension DNSName and uniformResourceIdentifier are 
	abbreviated as "SAN-DNS" and "SAN-URI". The certificates are tested
	with three different clients. A DANE-aware client, a RFC 5922 client
	with no DANE support and a client that matches the SIP domain
	with the Common Name in the Subject of the certificate. The last
	example is not really covered by any SIP-related RFC and should
	be avoided.
	</t>
	<section anchor="Example1" title="Example 1: johansson.example.com">
	<t>
	<list style="symbols">
	<t>Domain: johansson.example.com</t>
	<t>DNS SRV host for TLS: siphosting.example.net</t>
	</list>
	
	Certificate content:
	<list style="symbols">
	<t>CN: siphosting.example.net</t>
	<t>SAN-URI: -</t>
	<t>SAN-DNS: -</t>
	</list>
	</t>
	<t>
	<list style="symbols">
	<t>Matching for DANE-aware SIP clients: Yes</t>
	<t>Matching for only RFC 5922 SIP clients: No</t>
	<t>Matching on CNAME only: No</t>
	</list>
	</t>
	</section><!-- Example Johansson -->

	<section anchor="Example2" title="Example 2: lundholm.example.com">
	<t>
	<list style="symbols">
	<t>Domain: lundholm.example.com</t>
	<t>DNS SRV host for TLS: sipcrew.example.net</t>
	</list>
	
	Certificate content:
	<list style="symbols">
	<t>CN: randomname.example.net</t>
	<t>SAN-URI: sip:lundholm.example.com</t>
	<t>SAN-DNS: lundholm.example.com</t>
	</list>
	</t>
	<t>
	<list style="symbols">
	<t>Matching for DANE-aware SIP clients: Yes</t>
	<t>Matching for only RFC 5922 SIP clients: Yes</t>
	</list>
	</t>
	<t>Note: More examples is coming here.</t>
	</section><!-- Example Lundholm -->
	</section>

	<section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations"> 
		<t>
		This document use already published solutions for providing credentials
		for setting up a secure connection to a SIP server. By depending on secure
		lookups of DNS NAPTR and SRV records as well as using TLSA records to 
		verify a SIP servers TLS certificate it describes a secure method for
		making sure that a SIP request for a domain is sent to an authoritative 
		server.
		</t>
		<t>In addition to this document, many security considerations are covered
		in ID.ietf-dane-srv.</t>
	</section>
	
	<section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations"> 
  		<t>This document does not require actions by IANA.</t>
	</section>

	<section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">
    	<t>
	The author wishes to acknowledge Jakob Schlyter for inspiration and .SE for promoting
	DNSsec and DANE. Victor Dubovn
	</t>
	</section>
    
</middle>

<back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3261" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3263" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4033" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4346" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5246" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5280" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5922" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6698" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6066" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.I-D.ietf-dane-srv" ?>
	 	 
    </references>
    
    <references title="Informative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5589" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.I-D.ogud-dane-vocabulary" ?>
   </references>
	<section anchor="appendixa" title="Appendix A. Implementation notes">
	<t>
	Developers of SIP implementations are strongly encouraged to implement
	RFC 5922 and this document for secure verification of a SIP domain
	with a TLS server. This document also encourages implementation of TLS SNI
	both in client and server implementations. In order to get support of
	this function, update to new versions of the TLS libraries and make sure that
	the implementation supports new versions of TLS - 
	TLS 1.1 <xref target="RFC4346"/> and TLS 1.2 <xref target="RFC5246"/>.
	</t>
	<t>
	Implementatinos that do support TLS are encouraged to always start
	with attempting TLS, even if the URI is a SIP: uri. If there are NAPTR
	records for the domain and the domain indicates support of TLS, use it.
	If there are no NAPTR records, start SRV lookup with the _sips._tcp 
	prefix. This way, the SIP network will gradually shift to always using
	secure and authenticated TLS sessions.
	</t>

	</section>
  </back>
</rfc>
