<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<rfc category="info" docName="draft-johansson-loa-registry-00"
     ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="SAML 2.0 LoA Registry">An IANA registry for SAML 2.0 Level
    of Assurance Context Classes</title>

    <author fullname="Leif Johansson" initials="L." surname="Johansson">
      <organization>NORDUNet</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Tulegatan 11</street>

          <city>Stockholm</city>

          <country>Sweden</country>
        </postal>

        <email>leifj@nordu.net</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date day="2" month="April" year="2011" />

    <keyword>Identity</keyword>

    <keyword>Assurance</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>This document establishes an IANA registry for Level of Assurance
      Context Classes for SAML 2.0. The registry is intended to be used as an
      aid to discovering such LoA definitions.</t>
    </abstract>

    <note title="Requirements Language">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
      document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
      target="RFC2119">RFC 2119</xref>.</t>
    </note>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>This document establishes an IANA registry for Level of Assurance
      Context Profiles for SAML 2.0. Such objects are XML schema definitions
      that fulfil the requirements of <xref
      target="OASIS.sstc.saml-loa-authncontext-profile-draft-01">sstc-saml-loa-authncontext-profile-draft-01</xref>.
      Quoting from this specification we find the following definition of the
      concept of level of assurance:</t>

      <t><spanx>Many existing (and potential) SAML federation deployments have adopted a &ldquo;levels of assurance&rdquo; (or LOA) model for categorizing the wide variety of authentication methods into a small number of levels, typically based on some notion of the strength of the authentication. Federation members (service providers or &ldquo;relying parties&rdquo;) then decide which level of assurance is required to access specific protected resources, based on some assessment of &ldquo;value&rdquo; or &ldquo;risk&rdquo;.</spanx></t>

      <t>Several so called trust frameworks and identity federations now
      exist, some of which define one or more LoAs. The purpose of this
      specification is to create an IANA registry where such LoA definitions
      can be discovered.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Name of Registry">
      <t>The name of the registry shall be "SAML 2.0 LoA Context Class", in
      plural "SAML LoA Context Classes". The term LoA is an abbreviation of
      Level of Assurance.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Registration Template">
      <t>The following information MUST be provided with each
      registration:</t>

      <t><list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="URI:">A URI referencing a SAML 2.0 LoA Context Class.
          This is the registry key.</t>

          <t hangText="Context Class:">A valid XML schema definition for the
          SAML 2.0 LoA Context Class fulfilling the requirements of <xref
          target="OASIS.sstc.saml-loa-authncontext-profile-draft-01">sstc-saml-loa-authncontext-profile-draft-01</xref>.</t>

          <t hangText="Informational URL:">A URL containing auxilliary
          information. This URL SHOULD minimally point to contact information
          for the administrative authority of the SAML 2.0 LoA Context
          Class.</t>
        </list>Note that it is not uncommon for a single XML Schema to contain
      definitions of multiple URIs. In that case the registration MUST be
      repeated for each URI. Since the registry key (the URI) is unique by
      design there is no need for namespace management for this registry.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Registration Policy">
      <t>The registry is to be operated under the "Designated Expert Review"
      policy from <xref target="RFC5226">RFC5226</xref> employing a pool of
      experts. IANA is kindly asked to do rough randomized load-balancing
      among the experts. The initial pool of expert and the review criteria
      are outlined below.</t>

      <section title="Reviewer Expectations">
        <t>The intent is that the IANA LoA Registry contain URIs that
        represent bona fide SAML 2.0 LoA Context Class definitions while not
        presenting a very high bar for entry. Expert reviewers SHOULD not
        place undue value in any percieved or actual quality of the associated
        trust framework or federation and SHOULD only exclude those
        registrations that in the view of the experts do not represent a bona
        fide attempt at defining an LoA.</t>

        <t>The designated experts are also expected to verify that the
        registration is consistent and that the XML is schema valid and
        fulfills the requirements of <xref
        target="OASIS.sstc.saml-loa-authncontext-profile-draft-01">sstc-saml-loa-authncontext-profile-draft-01</xref>.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Designated Experts Pool">
        <t>TBD</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Registry Semantics">
      <t>The intended use for this registry is to serve as a basis for
      discovery of LoA definitions for instance in SAML tools. Consumers of
      the registry MUST NOT treat it as a complete list of all LoA definitions
      and MUST provide a way for the user to provide additional LoA Context
      Class definitions by other means. It is not expected that all LoA
      definitions will want to be registered with IANA.</t>

      <t>The presense of an entry in the registy MUST NOT be taken to imply
      any semantics beyond the review done by the expert reviewers as part of
      the registration process.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>This document sets up a registry with IANA making the whole document
      a set of considerations for IANA.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>An implementor of SAML MUST NOT treat the list of Level of Assurance
      URIs as a trust framework and MUST NOT make any assumptions about the
      quality or properties of any of the listed Level of Assurance URIs.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>Bob 'RL' Morgan, Scott Cantor, Lucy Lynch and John Bradley were
      involved in the initial discussions around this idea and contributed to
      the semantics of the registry.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"?>

      <?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5226.xml"?>

      <reference anchor="OASIS.sstc.saml-loa-authncontext-profile-draft-01">
        <front>
          <title>Level of Assurance Authentication Context Profiles for SAML
          2.0</title>

          <author fullname="Erik Tiffany" initials="E." surname="Tiffany">
            <organization>Liberty Alliance</organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="Paul Madsen" initials="P." surname="Madsen">
            <organization>NTT</organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="Scott Cantor" initials="S." surname="Cantor">
            <organization>Internet2</organization>
          </author>

          <date day="01" month="July" year="2008" />
        </front>
      </reference>
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
