<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="no" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<rfc category="bcp" docName="draft-ietf-behave-lsn-requirements-03" ipr="trust200902">

 <!-- ***** FRONT MATTER ***** -->

 <front>
   <title abbrev="CGN Requirements">Common requirements for Carrier Grade NAT
     (CGN)</title>

   <author fullname="Simon Perreault" initials="S." surname="Perreault"
     role="editor">
     <organization>Viagénie</organization>
     <address>
       <postal>
         <street>2875 boul. Laurier, suite D2-630</street>
         <city>Québec</city>
         <region>QC</region>
         <code>G1V 2M2</code>
         <country>Canada</country>
       </postal>
       <phone>+1 418 656 9254</phone>
       <email>simon.perreault@viagenie.ca</email>
       <uri>http://www.viagenie.ca</uri>
     </address>
   </author>

  <author fullname="Ikuhei Yamagata" initials="I." surname="Yamagata">
     <organization abbrev="NTT Communications">
     NTT Communications Corporation</organization>
     <address>
       <postal>
         <street>Gran Park Tower 17F, 3-4-1 Shibaura, Minato-ku</street>
         <city>Tokyo</city>
         <code>108-8118</code>
         <country>Japan</country>
       </postal>
       <phone>+81 50 3812 4704</phone>
       <email>ikuhei@nttv6.jp</email>
     </address>
   </author>

    <author fullname="Shin Miyakawa" initials="S." surname="Miyakawa">
     <organization abbrev="NTT Communications">
     NTT Communications Corporation</organization>
     <address>
       <postal>
         <street>Gran Park Tower 17F, 3-4-1 Shibaura, Minato-ku</street>
         <city>Tokyo</city>
         <code>108-8118</code>
         <country>Japan</country>
       </postal>
       <phone>+81 50 3812 4695</phone>
       <email>miyakawa@nttv6.jp</email>
     </address>
   </author>

   <author fullname="Akira Nakagawa" initials="A." surname="Nakagawa">
     <organization abbrev="Japan Internet Exchange (JPIX)">
	 Japan Internet Exchange Co., Ltd. (JPIX)</organization>
     <address>
       <postal>
         <street>Otemachi Building 21F, 1-8-1 Otemachi, Chiyoda-ku</street>
         <city>Tokyo</city>
         <code>100-0004</code>
         <country>Japan</country>
       </postal>
       <phone>+81 90 9242 2717</phone>
       <email>a-nakagawa@jpix.ad.jp</email>
     </address>
   </author>

    <author fullname="Hiroyuki Ashida" initials="H." surname="Ashida">
     <organization>IS Consulting G.K.</organization>
     <address>
       <postal>
         <street>12-17 Odenma-cho Nihonbashi Chuo-ku</street>
         <city>Tokyo</city>
         <code>103-0011</code>
         <country>Japan</country>
       </postal>
       <email>assie@hir.jp</email>
     </address>
   </author>


   <date year="2011" />

   <!-- Meta-data Declarations -->

   <area>Transport</area>
   <workgroup>Internet Engineering Task Force</workgroup>
   <keyword>CGN, NAT</keyword>

   <abstract>
     <t>This document defines common requirements for Carrier-Grade NAT
       (CGN).</t>
   </abstract>
 </front>

 <middle>
   <section title="Introduction">
     <t>With the shortage of IPv4 addresses, it is expected that more ISPs may
       want to provide a service where a public IPv4 address would be shared by
       many subscribers.  Each subscriber is
       assigned a private address, and a NAT situated in the ISP's network
       translates between private and public addresses. This is known as NAT444
       <xref target="I-D.shirasaki-nat444-isp-shared-addr"/> when the CPE
       includes a NAT function.</t>

     <t>This is not to be considered a solution to the shortage of IPv4
       addresses. It is a service that can conceivably be offered alongside
       others, such as IPv6 services or regular, un-NATed IPv4 service. Some
       ISPs started offering such a service long before there was a shortage of
       IPv4 addresses, showing that there are driving forces other than the
       shortage of IPv4 addresses.</t>

     <t>This document describes behavioral requirements that are to be expected
       of those ISP-controlled NAT. Meeting this set of requirements
       will greatly increase the likelihood that subscribers' applications will
       function properly.</t>

     <t>Readers should be aware of potential issues that may arise when sharing
       a public address between many subscribers. See <xref
         target="I-D.ford-shared-addressing-issues"/> for details.</t>

     <t>This document builds upon previous works describing requirements for
       generic NATs <xref target="RFC4787"/><xref target="RFC5382"/><xref
         target="RFC5508"/>. These documents still apply in this context. What
       follows are additional requirements, to be satisfied on top of previous
       ones.</t>
   </section>

   <section title="Terminology">

	<t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
	"SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
	document are to be interpreted as described in <xref target="RFC2119" />.
	</t>

  <t>
    Readers are expected to be familiar with <xref target="RFC4787" /> and the 
    terms defined there. The following additional term is used in this document:


    <list style='hanging'>
      <t hangText="Carrier-Grade NAT (CGN):">A NAT-based <xref
          target="RFC2663"/> functional element operated by an administrative
        entity (e.g. operator) to share the same address among several
        subscribers. A CGN is managed by the administrative entity, not the
        subscribers.
        <list style="empty">
          <t>Note that the term "carrier-grade" has nothing to do with the
            quality of the NAT; that is left to discretion of implementers.
            Rather, it is to be understood as a topological qualifier: the NAT
            is placed in an ISP's network and translates the traffic of
            potentially many subscribers. Subscribers have limited or no control
            over the CGN, whereas they typically have full control over a NAT
            placed on their premises.</t>
        </list>
      </t>
    </list>
  </t>

  <t><xref target="topology"/> summarizes a common network topology in which a
    CGN operates.</t>

<figure anchor="topology" title="CGN network topology" align="center">
	<artwork><![CDATA[
                .
                :
                |       Internet     
............... | ...................
                |       ISP network
                |
                |
            ++------++  External realm
........... |  CGN   |...............
            ++------++  Internal realm            
              |    |               
              |    |
              |    |    ISP network
............. | .. | ................
              |    |  Customer premises
      ++------++  ++------++
      |  CPE1  |  |  CPE2  |  etc.
      ++------++  ++------++
]]></artwork>
  </figure>

  <t>Another possible topology is one for hotspots, where there is no customer
    premise or CPE, but where a CGN serves a bunch of customers who don't trust
    each other and hence fairness is an issue. One important difference with the
    previous topology is the absence of NAT444. This, however, has no impact on
    CGN requirements since they are driven by fairness and robustness in the
    service provided to customers, which applies in both cases.</t>

</section>





<section title="Requirements for CGNs">

	<t>What follows is a list of requirements for CGNs. They are in
    addition to those found in other documents such as <xref target="RFC4787"/>,
    <xref target="RFC5382"/>, and <xref target="RFC5508"/>.</t>

  <t>
    <list style="format REQ-%d:" counter="Requirements">
      <t>A CGN MUST support at least the following transport protocols: TCP
        (MUST support <xref target="RFC5382"/>), UDP (MUST support <xref
          target="RFC4787"/>), and ICMP (MUST support <xref target="RFC5508"/>).
        Support for additional transport protocols is OPTIONAL.</t>
    </list>
    <list style="hanging">
      <t hangText="Justification:">These protocols are the ones that NATs
        traditionally support. The IETF has documented the best current
        practices for them.</t>
    </list>
  </t>

  <t>
    <list style="format REQ-%d:" counter="Requirements">
      <t>A CGN MUST have a default "IP address pooling" behavior of "Paired".
        The CGN administrator MAY change this behavior on an application
        protocol basis.
        <list style="symbols">
          <t>When multiple overlapping internal address ranges share the same
            external address pool (e.g. DS-Lite <xref
              target="I-D.ietf-softwire-dual-stack-lite"/>), external addresses
            are paired with subscribers rather than internal addresses.</t>
        </list>
      </t>
    </list>
    <list style="hanging">
      <t hangText="Justification:">This stronger form of REQ-2 from <xref
          target="RFC4787"/> is justified by the stronger need for not breaking
        applications that depend on the external address remaining constant.</t>
      <t>Note that this requirement applies regardless of the transport
        protocol. In other words, a CGN must use the same external IP address
        mapping for all sessions associated with the same internal IP address,
        be they TCP, UDP, ICMP, something else, or a mix of different
        protocols.</t>
      <t>The justification for allowing other behaviors is to allow the
        administrator to save external addresses and ports for application
        protocols that are known to work fine with other behaviors in practice.
        However, the default behavior MUST be "Paired".</t>
    </list>
  </t>

  <t>
    <list style="format REQ-%d:" counter="Requirements">
      <t>A CGN SHOULD limit the number of external ports (or, equivalently,
        "identifiers" for ICMP) that are assigned per subscriber.
        <list style="letters">
          <t>Limits SHOULD be configurable by the CGN administrator.</t>
          <t>Limits MAY be configured and applied independently per transport
            protocol.</t>
          <t>Additionally, it is RECOMMENDED that the CGN include
            administrator-adjustable thresholds to prevent a single subscriber
            from consuming excessive CPU resources from the CGN (e.g. rate limit
            the subscriber's creation of new mappings).</t>
        </list>
      </t>
    </list>
    <list style="hanging">
      <t hangText="Justification:">A CGN can be considered a network resource
        that is shared by competing subscribers. Limiting the number of external
        ports assigned to each subscriber mitigates the DoS attack that a
        subscriber could launch against other subscribers through the CGN in
        order to get a larger share of the resource. It ensures fairness among
        subscribers. Limiting the rate of allocation mitigates a similar attack
        where the CPU is the resource being targeted instead of port
        numbers.</t>
    </list>
  </t>

  <t>
    <list style="format REQ-%d:" counter="Requirements">
      <t>A CGN SHOULD limit the amount of state memory allocated per mapping and
        per subscriber. This may include limiting the number of TCP sessions,
        the number of filters, etc., depending on the NAT implementation.
        <list style="letters">
          <t>Limits SHOULD be configurable by the CGN administrator.</t>
          <t>Additionally, it SHOULD be possible to limit the rate at which
            memory-consuming state elements are allocated.</t>
        </list>
      </t>
    </list>
    <list style="hanging">
      <t hangText="Justification:">A NAT needs to keep track of TCP sessions
        associated to each mapping. This state consumes resources for which, in
        the case of a CGN, subscribers may compete. It is necessary to ensure
        that each subscriber has access to a fair share of the CGN's resources.
        Limiting TCP sessions per subscriber and per time unit is an effective
        mitigation against inter-subscriber DoS attacks. Limiting the rate of
        allocation is intended to prevent against CPU resource exhaustion.</t>
    </list>
  </t>

  <t>
    <list style="format REQ-%d:" counter="Requirements">
      <t>It SHOULD be possible to administratively turn off translation for
        specific destination addresses and/or ports.</t>
    </list>
    <list style="hanging">
      <t hangText="Justification:">It is common for a CGN administrator to
        provide access for subscribers to servers installed in the ISP's
        network, in the external realm. When such a server is able to reach the
        internal realm via normal routing (which is entirely controlled by the
        ISP), translation is unneeded. In that case, the CGN may forward packets
        without modification, thus acting like a plain router.  This may
        represent an important efficiency gain.</t>
      <t><xref target="passthrough"/> illustrates this use-case.</t>
    </list>
  </t>

	<figure anchor="passthrough" title="CGN pass-through" align="center">
	<artwork><![CDATA[ 
X1:x1            X1':x1'            X2:x2    
+---+from X1:x1  +---+from X1:x1    +---+
|   |  to X2:x2  |   |  to X2:x2    | S |
| C |>>>>>>>>>>>>| C |>>>>>>>>>>>>>>| e |
| P |            | G |              | r |
| E |<<<<<<<<<<<<| N |<<<<<<<<<<<<<<| v |
|   |from X2:x2  |   |from X2:x2    | e |
|   |  to X1:x1  |   |  to X1:x1    | r |
+---+            +---+              +---+
]]></artwork>
  </figure>

  <t>
    <list style="format REQ-%d:" counter="Requirements">
      <t>It is RECOMMENDED that a CGN have an "Endpoint-Independent Filtering"
        behavior.</t>
    </list>
    <list style="hanging">
      <t hangText="Justification:">This is a stronger form of REQ-8 from <xref
          target="RFC4787"/>. An "Address-Dependent Filtering" behavior is NOT
        RECOMMENDED. This is based on the observation that some games and
        peer-to-peer applications require EIF for the NAT traversal to work. In
        the context of a CGN it is important to minimise application
        breakage.</t>
    </list>
  </t>

  <t>
    <list style="format REQ-%d:" counter="Requirements">
      <t>When a CGN loses state (due to a crash, reboot, failover to a cold
        standby, etc.), it MUST NOT reuse the same external address+port pairs
        for new dynamic mappings for at least 120 seconds, except for the
        following cases:
        <list style="letters">
          <t>If the CGN tracks TCP sessions (e.g. with a state machine,
            as in <xref target="RFC6146"/> section 3.5.2.2), TCP ports MAY be
            reused immediately.</t>
          <t>If the allocated external ports used address-dependent or
            address-and-port-dependent filtering before state loss, they MAY be
            reused immediately.</t>
        </list>
      </t>
    </list>
    <list style="hanging">
      <t hangText="Justification:">This is necessary in order to prevent
        collisions between old and new mappings and sessions. It ensures that
        all established sessions are broken instead of redirected to a different
        peer.</t>
      <t>The exceptions are for cases where reusing a port immediately does not
        create a possibility that packets would be redirected to the wrong
        peer.</t>
      <t>The 120 seconds value corresponds to the Maximum Segment Lifetime (MSL)
        from <xref target="RFC0793"/>.</t>
      <t>One way that this requirement could be satisfied would be have two
        distinct address pools: one dormant and one active. When rebooting, the
        CGN would swap the dormant pool with the active pool. Another way would
        be simply to wait 120 seconds before resuming NAT activity.</t>
    </list>
  </t>

  <t>
    <list style="format REQ-%d:" counter="Requirements">
      <t>Once an external port is deallocated, it SHOULD NOT be reallocated to a
        new mapping until at least 120 seconds have passed. The length of time
        and the maximum number of ports in this state SHOULD be configurable by
        the CGN administrator. The following exceptions apply:
        <list style="letters">
          <t>If the CGN tracks TCP sessions (e.g. with a state machine,
            as in <xref target="RFC6146"/> section 3.5.2.2), TCP ports MAY be
            reused immediately.</t>
          <t>If the allocated external ports used address-dependent or
            address-and-port-dependent filtering before state loss, they MAY be
            reused immediately.</t>
        </list>
      </t>
    </list>
    <list style="hanging">
      <t hangText="Justification:">This is to prevent users from receiving
        unwanted traffic. It also helps prevent against clock skew when mappings
        are logged.</t>
      <t>The exceptions are for cases where reusing a port immediately does not
        create a possibility that packets would be redirected to the wrong
        peer.</t>
      <t>The 120 seconds value corresponds to the Maximum Segment Lifetime (MSL)
        from <xref target="RFC0793"/>.</t>
    </list>
  </t>

  <t>
    <list style="format REQ-%d:" counter="Requirements">
      <t>A CGN SHOULD include a Port Control Protocol server <xref
          target="I-D.ietf-pcp-base"/>.</t>
    </list>
    <list style="hanging">
      <t hangText="Justification:">Allowing subscribers to manipulate the NAT
        state table with PCP greatly increases the likelihood that applications
        will function properly.</t>
    </list>
  </t>

  <t>
    <list style="format REQ-%d:" counter="Requirements">
      <t>A CGN SHOULD support <xref target="RFC4008"/>.</t>
    </list>
    <list style="hanging">
      <t hangText="Justification:">It is anticipated that CGNs will be primarily
        deployed in ISP networks where the need for management is critical.</t>
      <t>Note also that there are efforts within the IETF toward creating a MIB
        specifically for CGNs <xref target="I-D.jpdionne-behave-cgn-mib"/>.</t>
    </list>
  </t>

  <t>
    <list style="format REQ-%d:" counter="Requirements">
      <t>When packets pass from one side to the other, the DSCP values MUST be
        preserved. If the CGN also includes diffserv classifier and marker
        functionality it MAY change the DSCP values.</t>
    </list>
    <list style="hanging">
      <t hangText="Justification:">See <xref target="RFC2983"/>, in particular
        section 6.</t>
    </list>
  </t>

  <t>
    <list style="format REQ-%d:" counter="Requirements">
      <t>When a CGN is unable to create a mapping due to resource constraints
        or administrative restrictions (i.e. quotas)...
        <list style="letters">
          <t>it MUST drop the original packet;</t>
          <t>it SHOULD send an ICMP Destination Unreachable message with code 3
            (Port Unreachable) to the session initiator;</t>
          <t>it SHOULD send a notification (e.g.  SNMP trap) towards a
            management system (if configured to do so);</t>
          <t>and it SHOULD NOT delete existing mappings in order to "make room"
            for the new one.</t>
        </list>
      </t>
    </list>
    <list style="hanging">
      <t hangText="Justification:">This is a slightly different form of REQ-8
        from <xref target="RFC5508"/>. Code 3 is preferred to code 13 because it
        is listed as a "soft error" in <xref target="RFC5461"/>, which is
        important because we don't want TCP stacks to abort the connection
        attempt in this case. Sending an ICMP error may be rate-limited for
        security reasons, which is why requirement B is a SHOULD, not a
        MUST.</t>
      <t>Applications generally handle connection establishment failure better
        than established connection failure. This is why dropping the packet
        initiating the new connection is to preferred to deleting existing
        mappings. See also the rationale in <xref target="RFC5508"/> section
        6.</t>
    </list>
  </t>

</section>

<section title="Logging">
  <t>It may be necessary for CGN administrators to be able to identify a
    subscriber based on external IPv4 address, port, and timestamp in order to
    deal with abuse and lawful intercept requests. When multiple subscribers
    share a single external address, the source address and port that are
    visible at the destination host have been translated from the ones
    originated by the subscriber.</t>

  <t>In order to be able to do this, the CGN would need to log the following
    information for each mapping created:
    <list style="symbols">
      <t>subscriber identifier (e.g. internal source address or tunnel endpoint
        identifier)</t>
      <t>external source address</t>
      <t>external source port</t>
      <t>destination address (but see below)</t>
      <t>destination port (but see below)</t>
      <t>timestamp</t>
    </list>
  </t>
  <t>By "subscriber identifier" we mean information that uniquely identifies a
    subscriber. For example, in a traditional NAT scenario, the internal source
    address would be sufficient. In the case of DS-Lite, many subscribers share
    the same internal address and the subscriber identifier is the tunnel
    endpoint identifier (i.e. the B4's IPv6 address).</t>
  <t>A disadvantage of logging mappings is that CGNs under heavy usage may
    produce large amounts of logs, which may require large storage volume.</t>
  <t>Readers should be aware of logging recommendations for Internet-facing
    servers <xref target="I-D.ietf-intarea-server-logging-recommendations"/>.
    With compliant servers, the destination address and port do not need to be
    logged by the CGN. This can help reduce the amount of logging.</t>
</section>

<section title="Bulk Port Allocation">
  <t>So far we have assumed that a CGN allocates one external port for every
    outgoing connection. In this section, the impacts of allocating multiple
    external ports at a time are discussed.</t>
  <t>There is a range of things a CGN can do:
    <list style="hanging">
      <t hangText="Traditional:">For every outgoing connection, allocate one
        external port.</t>
      <t hangText="Scattered port set:">For an outgoing connection, create a set
        of several non-consecutive external ports. Subsequent outgoing
        connections will use ports from the set.  When the set is exhausted, a
        new connection causes a new set to be created.  A set is smaller or
        equal to the user's maximum port limit.</t>
      <t hangText="Consecutive port set:">Same as the scattered port set, but
        the ports allocated to a set are consecutive.</t>
    </list>
  </t>
  <t>Note that this list is not exhaustive. There is a continuum of behavior
    that a CGN may choose to implement. For example, a CGN could use scattered
    port sets of consecutive port sets.</t>

  <t>The impacts of bulk port allocation are as follows.
    <list style="hanging">
      <t hangText="Port Utilization:">The mechanisms at the top of the list are
        very efficient in their port utilization.  In that sense, they have good
        scaling properties (nothing is wasted).  The mechanisms at the bottom of
        the list will waste ports.  The number of wasted ports is proportional
        to size of the "bin".</t>

      <t hangText="Logging:">Traditional allocation creates a lot of log entries
        as compared to allocation by port sets create much fewer entries.
        Scattered and consecutive port sets generate the same number of log
        entries. In the case of consecutive port sets, entries can be expressed
        very compactly by indicating a range (e.g.  "12000-12009"). Some
        scattered port set allocation schemes can also generate small log
        entries containing the parameters and algorithm used for the port set
        generation (see e.g. <xref
          target="I-D.boucadair-pppext-portrange-option"/>).</t>
      <t>With large set sizes, the logging frequency for scattered and
        consecutive port sets can approach that of DHCP servers.</t>
      <t>Logging destination addresses and ports can only be done on a
        per-session basis. This means that destination logging for a CGN
        implementing bulk port allocation would create one log entry per session
        containing the destination address and port. Other information could
        still be logged in one entry per port set.</t>
      <t hangText="Security:">Traditional and scattered port sets provide very
        good security in that ports numbers are not easily guessed.  Easily
        guessed port numbers put subscribers at risk of the attacks described in
        <xref target="RFC6056"/>.  Consecutive port sets provides poor security
        to subscribers, especially if the set size is small.</t>
    </list>
  </t>
</section>

<section title="Deployment Considerations">
  <t>Several issues are encountered when CGNs are used <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-intarea-shared-addressing-issues"/>. There is current
    work in the IETF toward alleviating some of these issues. For example, see
    <xref target="I-D.boucadair-intarea-nat-reveal-analysis"/>.</t>

  <t>The address sharing ratio is the ratio between the number of external
    addresses and the number of internal addresses that a CGN is configured to
    handle. See <xref target="I-D.ietf-intarea-shared-addressing-issues"/>
    section 26.2 for guidance on picking an appropriate ratio.</t>
</section>

   <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
     <t>There are no IANA considerations.</t>
   </section>
	
   <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
     <t>If a malicious subscriber can spoof another subscriber's CPE, it may
       cause a DoS to that subscriber by creating mappings up to the allowed
       limit. Therefore, the CGN administrator SHOULD ensure that spoofing is
       impossible. This can be accomplished with ingress filtering, as described
       in <xref target="RFC2827"/>.</t>
   </section>
   <section title="Acknowledgements">
	<t>
    Thanks for the input and review by
    Arifumi Matsumoto,
    Benson Schliesser,
    Dai Kuwabara,
    Dan Wing,
    Dave Thaler,
    Francis Dupont,
    Joe Touch,
    Lars Eggert,
    Kousuke Shishikura,
    Mohamed Boucadair,
    Nejc Skoberne,
    Reinaldo Penno,
    Senthil Sivakumar,
    Takanori Mizuguchi,
    Takeshi Tomochika,
    Tomohiro Fujisaki,
    Tomohiro Nishitani,
    Tomoya Yoshida,
    and
    Yasuhiro Shirasaki.
    Dan Wing also contributed much of section 5.
	</t>
   </section>

 </middle>


 <back>
   <references title="Normative References">
     <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119"?>
     <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4008"?>
     <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4787"?>
     <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5382"?>
     <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5508"?>
     <?rfc include="reference.I-D.ietf-pcp-base"?>
   </references>
   <references title="Informative Reference">
     <?rfc include="reference.RFC.0793"?>
     <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2663"?>
     <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2827"?>
     <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2983"?>
     <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5461"?>
     <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6056"?>
     <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6146"?>
     <?rfc include="reference.I-D.ietf-intarea-server-logging-recommendations"?>
     <?rfc include="reference.I-D.ietf-intarea-shared-addressing-issues"?>
     <?rfc include="reference.I-D.ietf-softwire-dual-stack-lite"?>
     <?rfc include="reference.I-D.boucadair-intarea-nat-reveal-analysis"?>
     <?rfc include="reference.I-D.boucadair-pppext-portrange-option"?>
     <?rfc include="reference.I-D.ford-shared-addressing-issues"?>
     <?rfc include="reference.I-D.jpdionne-behave-cgn-mib"?>
     <?rfc include="reference.I-D.shirasaki-nat444-isp-shared-addr"?>
   </references>

   <section title="Change Log (to be removed by RFC Editor prior to
     publication)">
     <section title="Changed in -03">
       <t>
         <list style="symbols">
           <t>Added exceptions for which it is not necessary to wait 120 seconds
             before reusing a port.</t>
           <t>Renamed "random port set" to "scattered port set", which is more
             accurate.</t>
           <t>Log "subscriber identifier" instead of internal address+port to
             allow for overlapping internal address ranges (DS-Lite).</t>
           <t>Adjusted logging text and added reference to
             I-D.boucadair-pppext-portrange-option.</t>
           <t>Adjusted destination logging text for bulk port allocation
             schemes.</t>
           <t>Removed requirement for I-D.ietf-intarea-ipv4-id-update.</t>
           <t>Made PCP support a SHOULD-level requirement.</t>
           <t>Lowered the level of requirement for not dropping existing
             mappings in order to "make room" to SHOULD level, and added
             rationale.</t>
         </list>
       </t>
     </section>
     <section title="Changed in -02">
       <t>
         <list style="symbols">
           <t>CGNs MUST support at least TCP, UDP, and ICMP.</t>
           <t>Add requirement from I-D.ietf-intarea-ipv4-id-update.</t>
           <t>Add informative reference to <xref
               target="I-D.ietf-intarea-shared-addressing-issues"/>.</t>
           <t>Add requirement (SHOULD level) for a port forwarding protocol.</t>
           <t>Allow any pooling behavior on a per-application protocol
             basis.</t>
           <t>Adjust wording for external port allocation rate limiting.</t>
           <t>Add requirement for RFC4008 support (SHOULD level).</t>
           <t>Adjust wording for swapping address pools when rebooting.</t>
           <t>Add DSCP requirement (stolen from draft-jennings-behave-nat6).</t>
           <t>Add informative reference to
             draft-boucadair-intarea-nat-reveal-analysis.</t>
           <t>Add requirement for hold-down pool.</t>
           <t>Change definition of CGN.</t>
           <t>Avoid usage of "device" loaded word throughout the document.</t>
           <t>Add requirement about resource exhaustion.</t>
           <t>Change title.</t>
           <t>Describe additional CGN topology where there is no NAT444.</t>
           <t>Better justification for "Paired" pool behavior.</t>
           <t>Make it clear that rate limiting allocation is for preserving CPU
             resources</t>
           <t>Generalize the requirement for limiting the number of TCP sessions
             per mapping so that it applies to all memory-consuming state
             elements.</t>
           <t>Change CPE to subscriber where it applies throughout the text.</t>
           <t>Better terminology for bulk port allocation mechanisms.</t>
           <t>Explain how external address pairing works with DS-Lite.</t>
         </list>
       </t>
     </section>
     <section title="Changed in -01">
       <t>
         <list style="symbols">
           <t>Terminology: LSN is now CGN.</t>
           <t>Imported all requirements from RFCs 4787, 5382, and 5508. This
             allowed us to eliminate some duplication.</t>
           <t>Added references to
             draft-ietf-intarea-server-logging-recommendations
             and draft-ford-shared-addressing-issues.</t>
           <t>Incorporated a requirement from
             draft-xu-behave-stateful-nat-standby-06.</t>
         </list>
       </t>
     </section>
   </section>

 </back>
</rfc>
