<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>     
<!-- edited with ultraedia -->     

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
    <!ENTITY rfc1918 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1918.xml'>
    <!ENTITY rfc2119 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml'>
    <!ENTITY rfc2553 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2553.xml'>
    <!ENTITY rfc2767 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2767.xml'>
    <!ENTITY rfc2893 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2893.xml'>
    <!ENTITY rfc2460 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2460.xml'>
    <!ENTITY rfc3338 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3338.xml'>

    <!ENTITY I-D.ietf-behave-v6v4-xlate SYSTEM 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-behave-v6v4-xlate.xml'>
    <!ENTITY I-D.ietf-behave-v6v4-xlate-stateful SYSTEM 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-behave-v6v4-xlate-stateful.xml'>

]>     

<rfc category="std" ipr="pre5378Trust200902" 
     obsoletes="3338, 2767" docName="draft-ietf-behave-v4v6-bih-00">     

<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>     

<?rfc toc="yes" ?>     
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>     
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>     
<?rfc iprnotified="no" ?>     
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>     

    <front>     
        <title abbrev="BIH">     
          Dual Stack Hosts Using "Bump-in-the-Host" (BIH)</title>     

    <author initials="B.Huang" surname="Huang" fullname="Bill Huang" >     
      <organization>China Mobile</organization>     
      <address>     
        <postal>     
          <street>53A,Xibianmennei Ave., </street>     
          <street>Xuanwu District,</street>     
          <city>Beijing</city>     
          <code>100053</code>     
          <country>China</country>     
        </postal>     
        <email>bill.huang@chinamobile.com</email>     
      </address>     
    </author>     


    <author initials="H.Deng" surname="Deng" fullname="Hui Deng">     
      <organization>China Mobile</organization>     
      <address>     
        <postal>     
          <street>53A,Xibianmennei Ave., </street>     
          <street>Xuanwu District,</street>     
          <city>Beijing</city>     
          <code>100053</code>     
          <country>China</country>     
        </postal>     
        <email>denghui02@gmail.com</email>     
      </address>     
    </author>         

    <author initials="T.Savolainen" surname="Savolainen" fullname="Teemu Savolainen">     
      <organization>     Nokia</organization>     
      <address>     
        <postal>     
          <street>     Hermiankatu 12 D </street>     
          <street>     FI-33720 TAMPERE</street>     
          <country>     Finland</country>     
        </postal>     
        <email>     teemu.savolainen@nokia.com</email>     
      </address>     
    </author>     
    
    <date month="October" year="2010"/>
    <workgroup>Behave WG</workgroup>
      
      <abstract>     
      <t>This document describes the "Bump-In-the-Host" (BIH), a host based
      protocol translation mechanism that allows a subset of applications
      supporting only one IP address family to communicate with peers that are
      reachable or supporting only the other address family. 
      </t>     

      <t>This specification addresses scenarios where a host is provided dual
      stack or IPv6 only network connectivity. In the dual stack
      network case, single address family applications in the host sometime will
      communicate directly with other hosts using the different address family.
      In the case of IPv6 only network or IPv6 only destination, IPv4 originated 
      communications have to be translated into IPv6. The BIH makes the IPv4 
      applications think they talk to IPv4 peers and hence hides the IPv6 from
      those applications.
       </t>     
       
        <t>     Acknowledgement of previous work</t>     
         <t>     This document is an update to and directly derivative from 
   Kazuaki TSHUCHIYA, Hidemitsu HIGUCHI, and Yoshifumi ATARASHI [RFC2767] and 
   from Seungyun
   Lee, Myung-Ki Shin, Yong-Jin Kim, Alain Durand, and Erik Nordmark's
   [RFC3338], which similarly provides a dual stack host means to
   communicate with other IPv6 host using existing IPv4 appliations.
   This document combines and updates both [RFC2767] and [RFC3338].</t>     
   
      <t>     The changes in this document reflect five components
          <list>       
            <t>       1. Supporting IPv6 only network connections </t>     
            <t>       2. IPv4 address pool use private address instead of the unassigned IPv4 addresses (0.0.0.1 - 0.0.0.255)</t>     
            <t>       3. Extending ENR and address mapper to operate differently </t>  
            <t>       4. Adding an alternative way to implement the ENR </t> 
            <t>       5. Going for standards track instead of experimental/informational</t>
          </list>     
        </t>     
    </abstract>     
    </front>     
  
    <middle>     

    <section title="Introduction">     

       <t>While IPv6 support is being widely introduced throughout the Internet, classes of
         applications are going to remain IPv4-only. This document describes a 
         Bump-in-the-Host (BIH), successor and combination of Bump-in-the-Stack (BIS) 
         <xref target="RFC2767"/> and
         Bump-in-the-API (BIA) <xref target="RFC3338"/>
         technologies, which enables accommodation of significant set of the legacy IPv4-only
         applications in the IPv6-world.</t>

       <t>Bump-In-the-Host is not a general purpose translation solution. The class of IPv4-only
         applications the described host-based NAT46 protocol translation solution provides Internet
         connectivity over IPv6-only network access includes those applications that use DNS for IP address
         resolution and that do not embed IP address literals in protocol payloads. This includes essentially
         all DNS using legacy client-server model applications, which are agnostic on IP address family used by
         the destination, but not other classes of applications. The transition towards IPv6-only Internet
         is made easier by decreasing number of key applications that must be updated to IPv6.</t>

       <t>BIH technique includes two major implementation options: inserts a protocol translator 
         between the IPv4 and the IPv6 stacks of
         a host or between the socket API module and the TCP/IP module. Essentially,
         IPv4 is translated into IPv6 at the socket API level or at the IP level.</t> 

       <t>When the BIH is implemented at the socket API layer, and IPv4 applications
        communicate with IPv6 peers, the API translator intercepts the socket API
        functions from IPv4 applications and invokes the IPv6 
        socket API functions to communicate with the IPv6 hosts, and
        vice versa. </t>

       <t>When the BIH is implemented at the networking layer, the IPv4 packets
        are intercepted and converted to IPv6 using the IP conversion mechanism
         defined in SIIT <xref target="I-D.ietf-behave-v6v4-xlate"/>.
        The translation has the same benefits and drawbacks as SIIT.</t>
        
       <t>In order to support communication between IPv4
        applications and the target IPv6 hosts, pooled IPv4
        addresses will be assigned through the extension name resolver.</t>     

       <t>The BIH can be used whenever an IPv4-only application needs to 
        communicate with an IPv6 peer, independently of the address families supported
        by the access network. Hence the access network can be IPv6-only or
        dual-stack capable.</t>

      <t>     
        The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
        "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
        document are to be interpreted as described in <xref target="RFC2119"/> .</t>     

      <t>     
        This document uses terms defined in <xref target="RFC2460"/> , <xref target="RFC2893"/> , 
        <xref target="RFC2767"/> and <xref target="RFC3338"/>. </t>     
      
    </section>     

   <section title="Components of the Bump-in-the-Host">     
     
    <t>     
      Figure 1 shows the architecture of the host in which BIH is
      implemented as socket API layer translator, i.e. as the original 
      "Bump-in-the-API".
    </t>     
        
 <figure title="Architecture of the dual stack host using BIH at socket layer" anchor="fig1">     <artwork>     
   <![CDATA[
               +----------------------------------------------+
               | +------------------------------------------+ |
               | |                                          | |
               | |            IPv4 applications             | |
               | |                                          | |
               | +------------------------------------------+ |
               | +------------------------------------------+ |
               | |           Socket API (IPv4, IPv6)        | |
               | +------------------------------------------+ |
               | +-[ API translator]------------------------+ |
               | | +-----------+ +---------+ +------------+ | |
               | | | Ext. Name | | Address | | Function   | | |
               | | | Resolver  | | Mapper  | | Mapper     | | |
               | | +-----------+ +---------+ +------------+ | |
               | +------------------------------------------+ |
               | +--------------------+ +-------------------+ |
               | |                    | |                   | |
               | |    TCP(UDP)/IPv4   | |   TCP(UDP)/IPv6   | |
               | |                    | |                   | |
               | +--------------------+ +-------------------+ |
               +----------------------------------------------+
    ]]>     </artwork>     </figure>     

    <t>     
      Figure 2 shows the architecture of the host in which BIH is
      implemented as network layer translator, i.e. as the original 
      "Bump-in-the-Stack".
    </t>     

   <figure title="Architecture of the dual-stack host using BIH at network layer" anchor="fig2"><artwork><![CDATA[
     +-------------------------------------------------------------+
     |  +-------------------------------------------------------+  |
     |  | IPv4 applications                                     |  |
     |  +-------------------------------------------------------+  |
     |  +-------------------------------------------------------+  |
     |  | TCP/IPv4                                              |  |
     |  |   +---------------------------------------------------+  |
     |  |   |  +-----------+    +---------+  +---------------+     |
     |  |   |  | extension |    | address |  |  translator   |     |
     |  |   |  | name      |    | mapper  |  +---------------+     |
     |  |   |  | resolver  |    |         |  +---------------+     |
     |  |   |  |           |    |         |  |     IPv6      |     |
     |  +---+  +-----------+    +---------+  +---------------+     |
     |  +-------------------------------------------------------+  |
     |  |                  Network card drivers                 |  |
     |  +-------------------------------------------------------+  |
     +-------------------------------------------------------------+
     +-------------------------------------------------------------+
     |                        Network cards                        |
     +-------------------------------------------------------------+
     ]]></artwork></figure>

    <t> Dual stack hosts defined in RFC2893 <xref target="RFC2893"/> need applications,
      TCP/IP modules and addresses for both IPv4 and IPv6. The proposed
      hosts in this document have an API or network layer translator to communicate with
      other IPv6 hosts using existing IPv4 applications.  The BIH translator
      consists of an extension name resolver, an address mapper, and depending on
      implementation either a function mapper or a protocol translator.
    </t>     

     <section title="Function Mapper">     
       
       <t>     
         Function mapper translates an IPv4 socket API function into an IPv6 socket API
         function, and vice versa.
       </t>     

       <t>     
         When detecting IPv4 socket API function calls from IPv4 applications,
         function mapper intercepts the function calls and invokes new IPv6 socket API
         functions which correspond to the IPv4 socket API functions.  Those
         IPv6 API functions are used to communicate with the target IPv6
         peers.  When detecting IPv6 socket API function calls triggered by the data
         received from the IPv6 peers, function mapper works symmetrically in relation to
         the previous case.
       </t>     

     </section> 

     <section title="Translator">
     	
       <t>Translator translates IPv4 into IPv6 and vice versa using the IP conversion
          mechanism defined in SIIT <xref target="I-D.ietf-behave-v6v4-xlate"/>.
       </t>
     	
       <t>When receiving IPv4 packets from IPv4 applications, translator
          converts IPv4 packet headers into IPv6 packet headers, then, if
          required, fragments the IPv6 packets (because header length of IPv6
          is typically 20 bytes larger than that of IPv4), and sends them to
          IPv6 networks. When receiving IPv6 packets from the IPv6 networks,
          translator works symmetrically to the previous case, except that
          there is no need to fragment the packets.
       </t>       
     </section>     
     
     <section title="Extension Name Resolver">     
       
       <t>     
         Extension Name Resolver returns a proper answer in response to the IPv4 or IPv6
         application's name resolution request.
       </t>     

       <t>     
         In the case of socket API implementation option, when an IPv4 application in
         an IPv6 only network tries to do forward lookup to resolve names via the resolver
         library (e.g. gethostbyname()), BIH intercept the function call and
         instead calls the IPv6 equivalent functions (e.g. getnameinfo()) that
         will resolve both A and AAAA records.
       </t>     

       <t>     
         If only AAAA record is available for the name queried, ENR requests the
         address mapper to assign an IPv4 address corresponding to the IPv6 address, 
         creates an A record for the assigned IPv4 address, and returns the A
         record to the IPv4 application.
       </t>     

       <t>     
         If both A and AAAA record are available in the IPv6 only network, 
         ENR does not require address mapper to assign IPv4 address, but instead
         asks address mapper to store relationship between the A and AAAA records, 
         and then directly passes the received A record to the IPv4 application.
       </t>     

       <figure title="ENR behaviour illustration" anchor="Table 1"><artwork><![CDATA[
     Application | Network  | ENR behaviour
     query       | response |  
     ------------+----------+---------------------
        A        |   A      |  <return A record>
        A        |   AAAA   |  <synthesize A record>
        A        |  A/AAAA  |  <return A record>
     ]]></artwork></figure>

       <t>NOTE: An implementation option is to have ENR support in host's
         (stub) DNS resolver itself as described in [DNS64], in which case
         record synthesis is not needed and advanced functions such as
         DNSSEC are possible. If the ENR is implemented at the network layer, same
         limitations arise as when DNS record synthesis is done on the network.
         A host also has an option to implement recursive DNS server function.
       </t>
       <section title="Reverse DNS lookup">
       <t>When an application initiates a reverse DNS query for a PTR record, to find a name for
       an IP address, the ENR MUST check whether the queried IP address
       can be found in the cache of the Address Mapper and is a local IP address. If an entry is found 
       and queried address is locally generated, the ENR must initiate corresponding 
       reverse DNS query for the real IP address.</t>
       <t>For example, when application initiates reverse DNS query for a synthesized
       locally valid IPv4 address, the ENR needs to intercept that query. The
       ENR shall perform reverse query procedure for the destination's IPv6 address and return
       the name received as response to IPv6 reverse query to application that 
       initiated the IPv4 query.</t>
       </section>   
     </section>     

     <section title="Address Mapper">     

     <t>Address mapper ("the mapper" later on), maintains an IPv4 address
       pool in the case of dual stack network and IPv6 only network. The
       pool consists of private IPv4 addresses as per <xref target="RFC1918"/>. Also, mapper
       maintains a table consisting of pairs of these locally selected
       IPv4 addresses and destinationss' IPv6 addresses.</t>

     <t>     
       When the extension name resolver, translator, or the function mapper requests 
       mapper to assign an IPv4 address corresponding to an IPv6 address, mapper selects and
       returns an IPv4 address out of the pool, and registers a new entry
       into the table dynamically.  The registration occurs in the following
       3 cases:
     </t>     
       <t>     
         (1) When the extension name resolver gets only an 'AAAA' record for the target
         host name in the dual stack or IPv6 only network and 
         there is not a mapping entry for the IPv6 address.
       </t>     

       <t>     
         (2) When the extension name resolver gets both an 'A' record and an 'AAAA' record 
         for the target host name in the IPv6 only network and 
         there is not a mapping entry for the IPv6 address. But ENR does not need an IPv4
         address out of the pool, just to register both IPv4 and IPv6 addresses from 'A' and 'AAAA'
         records into a new entry into the table.
       </t>     

       <t>     
         (3) When the function mapper gets a socket API function call from the
         data received and there is not a mapping entry for the IPv6
         source address.
       </t>     

     	<t>When the resolver, translator, or the function mapper requests mapper to assign an
     IPv4 address corresponding to an IPv6 address, mapper, if required,
     selects and returns an IPv4 address out of the pool, and registers a new entry into the table
     dynamically. The following table describes how mappings are created
     into the table in each possible scenario:</t>
     
     <figure title="Address Mapper's mapping table illustration" anchor="Table 2"><artwork><![CDATA[
        Mapping table | Access    | Peer   | Created 
        entry for     |link type  | support| address mapping
     -------------------+-------------+-------------------------------
     (1) real IPv4    |IPv4 or DS | v4     | < no mapping needed >
     (2) real IPv6    |IPv6 or DS | v6     | < no mapping needed >
     (3) real IPv4    |IPv6       | v4 & v6| real IPv4 -> real IPv6
     (4) real IPv6    |IPv4       | v4 & v6| < out of scope >
     (5) local IPv4   |IPv6 or DS | v6     | local IPv4 -> real IPv6
     (6) local IPv6   |IPv4 or DS | v4     | < out of scope >
     (7) real IPv4    |IPv6       | v4     | < out of scope >
     (8) real IPv6    |IPv4       | v6     | < out of scope >
     ]]></artwork></figure>
     
     	
     	<t>Below are examples for all eight scenarios:</t>
     	
     	<t>(1) When the resolver gets an 'A' reply for application's 'A' query
       on access network supporting IPv4, there is no need to create
       mapping (or just stub mapping real IPv4 -> real IPv4).</t>
     	
     	<t>(2) When the resolver gets an 'AAAA' reply for application's 'AAAA'
       query on access network supporting IPv6, there is no need to
       create mapping (or just stub mapping real IPv6 -> real IPv6).</t>
     	
     	<t>(3) When the resolver gets both 'A' and 'AAAA' replies for
       application's 'A' query on IPv6-only access, there shall be
       mapping for real IPv4 to real IPv6.</t>
     	
     	<t>(4) The scenario where the resolver gets both 'A' and 'AAAA' replies for
       application's 'AAAA' query on IPv4-only access is out of scope.</t>
     	
     	<t>(5) When the resolver gets only an 'AAAA' record for the target host
       name for application's 'A' request on IPv6 only or DS access
       network, a local IPv4 address will be given to application and
       mapping for local IPv4 address to real IPv6 address is created.</t>
     	
     	<t>(6) The scenario where the resolver gets only an 'A' record for the target host
       name for application's 'AAAA' request on IPv4 only or DS access
       network is out of scope.</t>
     	
     	<t>(7) The scenario where the resolver gets only an 'A' record for the target host
       name for application's 'A' request on IPv6 only access network is out of scope.</t>
     	
     	<t>(8) The scenario where the resolver gets only an 'AAAA' record for the target host
       name for application's 'AAAA' request on IPv4 only access network is out of scope.</t>
     	
     	<t>NOTE: There is only one exception. When initializing the table, mapper registers 
   a pair of its own IPv4 address and IPv6 address into
   the table statically.</t>
    </section>     
   </section>     
      
  <section title="Behavior and network Examples">      

    <t>Figure 5 illustrates the very basic network scenario. An IPv4-only
    application is running on a host attached to IPv6-only Internet and
    is talking to IPv6 enabled server. A communication is made possible
    by bump in the host.</t>

 <figure title="Network Scenario #1" anchor="fig5"><artwork><![CDATA[
  +----+                                   +-------------+
  | H1 |----------- IPv6 Internet -------- | IPv6 server |
  +----+                                   +-------------+
  v4 only
  application
    ]]></artwork></figure>

    <t>     
    Figure 6 illustrates a possible network scenario where an IPv4-only 
    application is running on a host attached to a dual-stack network,
    but the destination server is running on a private site that is
    numbered with public IPv6 addresses and private IPv4 addresses 
    without port forwarding setup on NAT44. The only means to contact
    to server is to use IPv6.</t>

 <figure title="Network Scenario #2" anchor="fig6"><artwork><![CDATA[
  +----------------------+  +------------------------------+
  | Dual Stack Internet  |  | IPv4 Private site (Net 10)   |
  |                      |  |                              |
  |                      |  |                 +----------+ |
  |                      |  |                 |          | | 
  |  +----+           +---------+             |          | |
  |  | H1 |--------   |  NAT44  |-------------|  Server  | |
  |  +----+           +---------+             |          | |
  | v4 only              |  |                 +----------+ |
  | application          |  |                  Dual Stack  |
  |                      |  |                etc. 10.1.1.1 |
  |                      |  |                 AAAA:2009::1 |
  |                      |  |                              |
  +----------------------+  +------------------------------+
    ]]></artwork></figure>
    <t>
    Illustrations of host behavior in both implementation options are given here.
    Figure 7 illustrates the setup where BIH is implemented as a bump in the API, and
    figure 8 illustrates the setup where BIH is implemented as a bump in the stack.
    </t>    

     <figure title="Example of BIH as API addition" anchor="fig7"><artwork><![CDATA[   
"dual stack"                                                "host6"
IPv4    Socket |     [ API Translator ]    | TCP(UDP)/IP          Name
appli-  API    | ENR      Address  Function| (v6/v4)             Server
cation         |          Mapper   Mapper  |
 |        |        |        |        |         |              |       |
<<Resolve an IPv4 address for "host6".>>       |              |       |
 |        |        |        |        |         |              |       |
 |--------|------->|  Query of 'A' records for host6.         |       |
 |        |        |        |        |         |              |       |
 |        |        |--------|--------|---------|--------------|------>|
 |        |        |  Query of 'A' records and 'AAAA' for host6       |
 |        |        |        |        |         |              |       |
 |        |        |<-------|--------|---------|--------------|-------|
 |        |        |  Reply with the 'AAAA' record.           |       |
 |        |        |        |        |         |              |
 |        |        |<<The 'AAAA' record is resolved.>>        |
 |        |        |        |        |         |              |
 |        |        |+++++++>|  Request one IPv4 address       |
 |        |        |        |  corresponding to the IPv6 address.
 |        |        |        |        |         |              |
 |        |        |        |<<Assign one IPv4 address.>>     |
 |        |        |        |        |         |              |
 |        |        |<+++++++|  Reply with the IPv4 address.   |
 |        |        |        |        |         |              |
 |        |        |<<Create 'A' record for the IPv4 address.>>
 |        |        |        |        |         |              |
 |<-------|--------| Reply with the 'A' record.|              |
 |        |        |        |        |         |              |
 |        |        |        |        |         |              |
<<Call IPv4 Socket API function >>   |         |              |
 |        |        |        |        |         |              |
 |========|========|========|=======>|An IPv4 Socket API function Call
 |        |        |        |        |         |              |
 |        |        |        |<+++++++|  Request IPv6 addresses|
 |        |        |        |        |  corresponding to the  |
 |        |        |        |        |  IPv4 addresses.       |
 |        |        |        |        |         |              |
 |        |        |        |+++++++>| Reply with the IPv6 addresses.
 |        |        |        |        |         |              |
 |        |        |        |        |<<Translate IPv4 into IPv6.>>
 |        |        |        |        |         |              |
 |  An IPv6 Socket API function call.|=========|=============>|
 |        |        |        |        |         |              |
 |        |        |        |        |<<Reply an IPv6 data    |
 |        |        |        |        |  to dual stack.>>      |
 |        |        |        |        |         |              |
 |  An IPv6 Socket API function call.|<========|==============|
 |        |        |        |        |         |              |
 |        |        |        |        |<<Translate IPv6 into IPv4.>>
 |        |        |        |        |         |              |
 |        |        |        |<+++++++|  Request IPv4 addresses|
 |        |        |        |        |  corresponding to the  |
 |        |        |        |        |  IPv6 addresses.       |
 |        |        |        |        |         |              |
 |        |        |        |+++++++>| Reply with the IPv4 addresses.
 |        |        |        |        |         |              |
 |<=======|========|========|========|  An IPv4 Socket function call.
 |        |        |        |        |         |              |
    ]]></artwork></figure>

     <figure title="Example of BIH at network layer" anchor="fig8"><artwork><![CDATA[   
   "dual stack"                                            "host6"
   IPv4    TCP/    ENR     address  translator  IPv6
   appli-  IPv4            mapper
   cation        
     |      |       |         |       |           |         |
   <<Resolve an IPv4 address for "host6".>>       |         |
     |      |       |         |       |           |         |
     |------|------>|  Query of 'A' records for "host6".    | Name
     |      |       |         |       |           |         | Server
     |      |       |---------|-------|-----------|---------|--->|
     |      |       |  Query of 'A' records and 'AAAA' for "host6"
     |      |       |         |       |           |         |    |
     |      |       |<--------|-------|-----------|---------|----|
     |      |       |  Reply only with 'AAAA' record.       |
     |      |       |         |       |           |         |
     |      |       |<<Only 'AAAA' record is resolved.>>    |
     |      |       |         |       |           |         |
     |      |       |-------->|  Request one IPv4 address   |
     |      |       |         |  corresponding to the IPv6 address.
     |      |       |         |       |           |         |
     |      |       |         |<<Assign one IPv4 address.>> |
     |      |       |         |       |           |         |
     |      |       |<--------|  Reply with the IPv4 address.
     |      |       |         |       |           |         |
     |      |       |<<Create 'A' record for the IPv4 address.>>
     |      |       |         |       |           |         |
     |<-----|-------|  Reply with the 'A' record. |         |
     |      |       |         |       |           |         |
     |      |       |         |       |           |         |
   <<Send an IPv4 packet to "host6".>>|           |         |
     |      |       |         |       |           |         |
     |======|=======|=========|======>|  An IPv4 packet.    |
     |      |       |         |       |           |         |
     |      |       |         |<------|  Request IPv6 addresses
     |      |       |         |       |  corresponding to the IPv4
     |      |       |         |       |  addresses.         |
     |      |       |         |       |           |         |
     |      |       |         |------>|  Reply with the IPv6|
     |      |       |         |       |  addresses.         |
     |      |       |         |       |           |         |
     |      |       |         |       |<<Translate IPv4 into IPv6.>>
     |      |       |         |       |           |         |
     |      |       |An IPv6 packet.  |===========|========>|
     |      |       |         |       |           |         |
     |      |       |         |     <<Reply an IPv6 packet to
     |      |       |         |       "dual stack".>>       |
     |      |       |         |       |           |         |
     |      |       |An IPv6 packet.  |<==========|=========|
     |      |       |         |       |           |         |
     |      |       |         |       |<<Translate IPv6 into IPv4.>>
     |      |       |         |       |           |         |
     |<=====|=======|=========|=======|  An IPv4 packet.    |
     |      |       |         |       |           |         |
    ]]></artwork></figure>

  </section>     

    <section title="Considerations">     

    <section title="Socket API Conversion">
     <t>
      IPv4 socket API functions are translated into semantically as same
      IPv6 socket API functions as possible and vice versa. See Appendix B for the API
      list intercepted by BIH. However, 
      IPv4 socket API functions are not fully compatible with IPv6 since the IPv6 has new advanced features.
     </t>

    </section>

    <section title="ICMP Message Handling">
     <t>
      When an application needs ICMP messages values (e.g., Type, Code,
      etc.) sent from a network layer, ICMPv4 message values MAY be
      translated into ICMPv6 message values based on SIIT <xref target="I-D.ietf-behave-v6v4-xlate"/>, and vice
      versa.  It can be implemented using raw socket.
     </t>
    </section>

        <section title="IPv4 Address Pool and Mapping Table">     
          <t>     
            The address pool consists of the private IPv4 addresses as per <xref target="RFC1918"/>.
            This pool can be implemented at different
            granularity in the node e.g., a single pool per node, or at some
            finer granularity such as per user or per process.  However, if a
            number of IPv4 applications communicate with IPv6 hosts, the available address
            spaces may be exhausted.  As a result, it will be impossible for
            IPv4 applications to communicate with IPv6 nodes. It requires smart management
            techniques for address pool.  For example, it is desirable for the
            mapper to free the oldest entry and reuse the IPv4 address or IPv6
            address for creating a new entry.
            In case of a per-node address mapping table, it MAY cause a larger
            risk of running out of address.
          </t>     
          <t>
            The RFC1918 address space was chosen because generally legacy
            applications understand that as a private address space. A new dedicated
            address space would run a risk of not being understood by applications as
            private. The RFC1918 addresses have a risk of conflicting with other interfaces. The 
            conflicts can be mitigated by using least commonly used network number of the
            RFC1918 address space (TO BE SELECTED) and, if possible, cease using BIH on IPv6-interface
            after an IPv4-enabled interface is activated. 
          </t>
        </section>
        
        <section title="Internally Assigned IPv4 Addresses">     
          <t>     
            The IPv4 addresses, which are internally assigned to IPv6 target
            hosts out of the pool, are the private IPv4 addresses. 
            IPv4 addresses, which are internally assigned to IPv6 target hosts
            out of the spool, never flow out from the host, and so do not
            negatively affect other hosts.          
          </t>
          <t>
            The internally assigned IPv4 address, which applications see as the source address, MUST be from
            different subnet than the IPv4 addresses used by the address synthesis function. This approach ensures legacy
            applications realize they are not on the same link with their destination node and if needed, will 
            trigger NAT traversal procedures such
            as keep-alive message sending. 
          </t>      
        </section>     

      </section>     

      <section title="Considerations due ALG requirements">     

       <t>	
        No ALG functionality is specified herein as ALG design is generally not encouraged
        for host based translation and as BIH is intended for applications not including IP 
	addresses in protocol payloads.
       </t>

      </section>     
      
      <section title="Security Considerations">     

        <t>The security consideration of BIH mostly relies on that of <xref target="I-D.ietf-behave-v6v4-xlate-stateful"/>.
        </t>
 
        <t>In the socket layer implementation approach the differences are due to the
          address translation occurring at the API and not in the network layer.  
          That is, since the mechanism uses the API translator at the socket API level, 
          hosts can utilize the security of the network layer (e.g., IPSec) when they
          communicate with IPv6 hosts using IPv4 applications via the mechanism.  As well,
          there is no need for DNS ALG as in NAT-PT, so there is no interference with
          DNSSEC either.
        </t>
          
        <t>In the network layer implementation approach hosts cannot utilize the security
        above network layer when they communicate with IPv6 hosts using IPv4
        applications via BIH and encrypt embedded IP addresses, or when the
        protocol data is encrypted using IP addresses as keys. In these cases it is
        impossible for the mechanism to translate the IPv4 data into IPv6 and
        vice versa. Therefore it is highly desirable to upgrade to the
        applications modified into IPv6 for utilizing the security at
        communication with IPv6 hosts.
        </t>
  
        <t>
        The use of address pooling may open a denial of service attack
        vulnerability.  So BIH should employ the same sort of protection
        techniques as NAT64 <xref target="I-D.ietf-behave-v6v4-xlate-stateful"/> does.
        </t>     

      </section>     

      <section title="Acknowledgments">     

        <t>The author thanks the discussion from Gang Chen, Dapeng Liu, Bo Zhou, 
        Hong Liu, Tao Sun, Zhen Cao, Feng Cao et al. in the development of this document.</t>

        <t>The efforts of Suresh Krishnan, Mohamed Boucadair, Yiu L. Lee, James Woodyatt, 
        Lorenzo Colitti, Qibo Niu, Pierrick Seite, Dean Cheng, Christian Vogt, Jan M. Melen, 
        in reviewing this document are gratefully acknowledged.</t>
        
        <t>Advice from Dan Wing, Dave Thaler and Magnus Westerlund are greatly appreciated</t>
  
        <t>The authors of RFC2767 acknowledged WIDE Project, Kazuhiko YAMAMOTO, 
        Jun MURAI, Munechika SUMIKAWA, Ken WATANABE, and Takahisa MIYAMOTO. The authors
        of RFC3338 acknowledged implementation contributions by
        Wanjik Lee (wjlee@arang.miryang.ac.kr) and i2soft Corporation
        (www.i2soft.net).</t>

      
      </section>     
      
   </middle>     

   <back>     
        <references title='Normative References'>     
        	&rfc1918;
        	&rfc2119;
        	&rfc2460;
        	&rfc2767;        	
        	&rfc2893;  
        	&rfc3338;
	        &I-D.ietf-behave-v6v4-xlate;
	        &I-D.ietf-behave-v6v4-xlate-stateful;
       </references>       
   
       <references title="Informative References">
                &rfc2553;
       </references>

<section title="Implementation option for the ENR">

   <t>It is not necessary to implement the ENR at the kernel level, but it can be implemented instead
   at the user space by setting the host's default DNS server to point to 127.0.0.1. DNS queries would then always 
   be sent to the ENR, which furthermore ensures both A and AAAA queries are sent to the actual
   DNS server and A queries are always answered and required mappings created. </t>
 </section>
           
 <section anchor="app-additional" title="API list intercepted by BIH">
 
   <t>The following functions are the API list which SHOULD be intercepted
   by BIH module when implemented at socket layer.
   </t>

   <t>The functions that the application uses to pass addresses into the
   system are:

      <list style="empty">
        <t>bind()</t>
        <t>connect()</t>
        <t>sendmsg()</t>
        <t>sendto()</t>
      </list>
   </t>

   <t>The functions that return an address from the system to an
   application are:

      <list style="empty">
      <t>accept()</t>
      <t>recvfrom()</t>
      <t>recvmsg()</t>
      <t>getpeername()</t>
      <t>getsockname()</t>
     </list>
   </t>

   <t>The functions that are related to socket options are:

      <list style="empty">
      <t>getsocketopt()</t>
      <t>setsocketopt()</t>
      </list>
   </t>

   <t>The functions that are used for conversion of IP addresses embedded
   in application layer protocol (e.g., FTP, DNS, etc.) are:

      <list style="empty">
      <t>recv()</t>
      <t>send()</t>
      <t>read()</t>
      <t>write()</t>
      </list>
   </t>

   <t>As well, raw sockets for IPv4 and IPv6 MAY be intercepted.</t>

   <t>
   Most of the socket functions require a pointer to the socket address
   structure as an argument.  Each IPv4 argument is mapped into
   corresponding an IPv6 argument, and vice versa.</t>

   <t>According to <xref target="RFC2553"/>, the following new IPv6 basic APIs and
   structures are required.</t>

     <figure title="" anchor="figappendix1"><artwork><![CDATA[   
      IPv4                     new IPv6
      ------------------------------------------------
      AF_INET                  AF_INET6
      sockaddr_in              sockaddr_in6
      gethostbyname()          getaddrinfo()
      gethostbyaddr()          getnameinfo()
      inet_ntoa()/inet_addr()  inet_pton()/inet_ntop()
      INADDR_ANY               in6addr_any
    ]]></artwork></figure>

   <t>BIH MAY intercept inet_ntoa() and inet_addr() and use the address
   mapper for those.  Doing that enables BIH to support literal IP
   addresses.</t>

   <t>The gethostbyname() call return a list of addresses.  When the name
   resolver function invokes getaddrinfo() and  getaddrinfo() returns
   multiple IP addresses, whether IPv4 or IPv6, they SHOULD all be
   represented in the addresses returned by gethostbyname().  Thus if
   getaddrinfo() returns multiple IPv6 addresses, this implies that
   multiple address mappings will be created; one for each IPv6 address.
   </t>

   </section>
         
   </back>     
</rfc>     

