<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [

 <!ENTITY rfc4649  PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4649.xml'>

 <!ENTITY rfc4862  PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4862.xml'>

 <!ENTITY rfc4941  PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4941.xml'>


]>

<rfc ipr="trust200902" category="info" docName="draft-chown-v6ops-address-accountability-00">
	<front>
		<title abbrev="IPv6 Address Accountability">IPv6 Address Accountability Considerations</title>
		<author fullname="Tim Chown" initials="T.J." surname="Chown">
			<organization> University of Southampton </organization>
			<address>
				<postal>
					<street> Highfield </street>
					<city> Southampton </city>
					<code> SO17 1BJ </code>
					<region> Hampshire </region>
					<country> United Kingdom </country>
				</postal>
				<email> tjc@ecs.soton.ac.uk </email>
			</address>
		</author>

		<date month="July" year="2011"/>
		<area>Operations</area>
		<workgroup>IPv6 Operations</workgroup>
		<abstract>
<t>
Hosts in IPv4 networks typically acquire addresses by use of DHCP,
and retain that address and only that address while the DHCP lease
remains valid.  In IPv6 networks, hosts may use DHCPv6, but may
instead autoconfigure their own global addresses, and potentially
use many privacy addresses over time.  This behaviour places an
additional burden on network operators who require address
accountability for their users and devices.  There has been some
discussion of this issue on various mail lists; this text attempts
to capture the issues to encourage further discussion.
</t>
		</abstract>
	</front>
	<middle>

<section title="Introduction">
	<t>
Administrators of IPv4 networks are used to an address accountability model
where devices acquire a single global address using DHCP and then use
that address while the DHCP lease is valid. The model allows an
administrator to track back an IP address to a user or device, in
the event of some incident or fault requiring investigation. While by
no means foolproof, this model, which may include use of DHCP option 82,
is one that IPv4 network administrators are generally comfortable with.
	</t>
	<t>
There are many reasons why address stability is desirable, e.g.
DNS mappings, ACLs using IP addresses, and logging.  However, such 
stability may not typically exist in IPv6 client networks, particularly 
where clients are user managed.
	</t>
	<t>
In IPv6 networks, where hosts may use SLAAC <xref target="RFC4862"/>
and Privacy Addresses <xref target="RFC4941"/>, it is quite possible
that a host may use multiple IPv6 addresses over time, possibly changing
addresses used frequently, or using multiple addresses concurrently.
Where privacy addresses are used, a host may choose to generate and
start using a new privacy address at any time, and will also
typically generate a new privacy address after rebooting.  Clients may
use different IPv6 addresses per application, while servers may have 
multiple addresses configured, one per service offered.
	</t>
	<t>
It is also worth noting that in an IPv4 network, it is more difficult
for a user to pick and use an address manually without clashing with
an existing device on the network, while in IPv6 networks, picking an
unused address is simple to do without an address clash.  Source address
validation is a topic being handled in the IETF SAVI WG.
	</t>
</section>

<section anchor="Approaches" title="Accountability Approaches">
	<t>
There are various approaches to address accountability, which
have different costs, benefits and trade-offs.
	</t>

	<section title="Switch-router polling">
	<t>
By polling network switch and router devices for IPv4 ARP tables and 
IPv6 ND tables, and correlating the results with switch port MAC
tables, it should be possible to determine which IP addresses are in
use at any specific point in time and which addresses are being used
on which switch ports (and thus users or devices).
	</t>
	<t>
This is the approach adopted by tools such as NAV and Netdot, but
there is some concern expressed at the load that may be placed on
devices by frequent SNMP or other polling.  The polling frequency
needs to be rapid enough to ensure that cached ND/ARP data on devices is
not expired between polling intervals, i.e. the ND/ARP data should not be
expired more frequently than the device is polled.
	</t>
	</section>

	<section title="Record all ND traffic">
	<t>
If all ND traffic observed on a link can be captured, it should be
possible for IPv6 address usage to be recorded.  This would 
require appropriate capability on a device on any given subnet, e.g.
as is currently achieved for RAmond or NDPmon, or a reporting
mechanism for the subnet router.  There may also be mechanisms
such as a (filtered) RSPAN that may be suitable; at least one
implementation of this has been published.
	</t>
	<t>
A benefit of this approach is that collecting all ND traffic would
allow additional accounting and fault detection to be undertaken,
e.g. rogue RA detection, or DAD DoS detection. 
	</t>
	</section>

	<section title="Force use of DHCPv6 only">
	<t>
One approach to accountability is to attempt to force devices to
only use DHCPv6, which would in principle give the same address
accountability model as exists for IPv4 today.  <xref target="RFC4649"/>
for DHCPv6 appears to give at least some of the functionality of DHCP 
option 82.
	</t>
	<t>
While it is possible to craft IPv6 Router Advertisements that give
'hints' to hosts that DHCPv6 should be used ('M' bit set), there
is no obligation on the host to honour that hint, or to not use
privacy addressing as well. In addition, the user running the device may
still pick and manually configure their own address, with very little
chance of clashing with an existing address.
	</t>
	</section>

</section>

<section anchor="Conclusions" title="Conclusions">
	<t>
This text is an initial draft attempting to capture the issues
related to IPv6 address accountability models. If an all-DHCPv6 model
is not viable, 
IPv6 network administrators will need to deploy management and
monitoring tools to allow them to account for hosts that will have
multiple IPv6 addresses that may also change rapidly over time.
	</t>
	<t>
Feedback on the issues discussed here is welcomed.
	</t>

</section>

<section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
	<t>
There are no extra security consideration for this document.
	</t>
</section>

<section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
	<t>
There are no extra IANA consideration for this document.
	</t>
</section>

<section anchor="Acknowledgments" title="Acknowledgments">
	<t>
To be added.
	</t>
</section>


</middle>
<back>

<references title="Informative References">

	&rfc4649;
	&rfc4862;
	&rfc4941;

</references>
	</back>
</rfc>
