<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<rfc category="std" docName="draft-schmidt-multimob-pmipv6-source-00"
     ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="Multicast Senders in PMIPv6">Mobile Multicast Sender
    Support in PMIPv6 Domains</title>

    <author fullname="Thomas C. Schmidt" initials="T C."
            surname="Schmidt, Ed.">
      <organization>HAW Hamburg</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Berliner Tor 7</street>

          <city>Hamburg</city>

          <code>20099</code>

          <country>Germany</country>
        </postal>

        <email>schmidt@informatik.haw-hamburg.de</email>

        <uri>http://inet.cpt.haw-hamburg.de/members/schmidt</uri>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Shuai Gao" initials="S." surname="Gao">
      <organization>Beijing Jiaotong University</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>

          <city>Beijing</city>

          <region></region>

          <code></code>

          <country>China</country>
        </postal>

        <phone></phone>

        <facsimile></facsimile>

        <email>shgao@bjtu.edu.cn</email>

        <uri></uri>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Hong-Ke Zhang" initials="H." surname="Zhang">
      <organization>Beijing Jiaotong University</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>

          <city>Beijing</city>

          <region></region>

          <code></code>

          <country>China</country>
        </postal>

        <phone></phone>

        <facsimile></facsimile>

        <email>hkzhang@bjtu.edu.cn</email>

        <uri></uri>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Matthias Waehlisch" initials="M." surname="Waehlisch">
      <organization>link-lab &amp; FU Berlin</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Hoenower Str. 35</street>

          <city>Berlin</city>

          <code>10318</code>

          <country>Germany</country>
        </postal>

        <email>mw@link-lab.net</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date />

    <workgroup>MULTIMOB Group</workgroup>

    <abstract>
      <t>Multicast communication can be enabled in Proxy Mobile IPv6 domains
      by deploying MLD Proxy functions at Mobile Access Gateways and multicast
      routing functions at Local Mobility Anchors, or by additional route
      optimization schemes. This document describes the support of mobile
      multicast senders in Proxy Mobile IPv6 domains that is provided by this
      base deployment scenario, as well as in settings of further
      optimization. Mobile sources remain agnostic of multicast mobility
      operations.</t>
    </abstract>

    <note title="Requirements Language">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
      document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
      target="RFC2119">RFC 2119</xref>.</t>
    </note>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>Proxy Mobile IPv6 (PMIPv6) <xref target="RFC5213"></xref> extends
      Mobile IPv6 (MIPv6) <xref target="RFC6275"></xref> by network-based
      management functions that enable IP mobility for a host without
      requiring its participation in any mobility-related signaling.
      Additional network entities called the Local Mobility Anchor (LMA), and
      Mobile Access Gateways (MAGs), are responsible for managing IP mobility
      on behalf of the mobile node (MN). An MN connected to a PMIPv6 domain,
      which only operates according to the base specifications of <xref
      target="RFC5213"></xref>, cannot participate in multicast communication,
      as MAGs will discard group packets.</t>

      <t>Multicast support for mobile listeners can be enabled within a PMIPv6
      domain by deploying MLD Proxy functions at Mobile Access Gateways, and
      multicast routing functions at Local Mobility Anchors <xref
      target="RFC6224"></xref>. This base deployment option is the simplest
      way to PMIPv6 multicast extensions in the sense that it neither requires
      new protocol operations nor additional infrastructure entities. Standard
      software functions need to be activated on PMIPv6 entities, only, on the
      price of possibly non-optimal multicast routing.</t>

      <t>Alternate solutions leverage performance optimization by providing
      multicast routing at the access routers directly, or by other dedicated
      schemes.</t>

      <t>This document describes the support of mobile multicast senders in
      Proxy Mobile IPv6 domains as it is provided by the base deployment
      scenario <xref target="RFC6224"></xref>, as well as optimizations
      throughout the access network infrastructure to efficiently solve the
      source mobility problem as discussed in <xref target="RFC5757"></xref>.
      Mobile Nodes in this setting remain agnostic of multicast mobility
      operations.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Terminology">
      <t>This document uses the terminology as defined for the mobility
      protocols <xref target="RFC6275"></xref>, <xref target="RFC5213">
      </xref> and <xref target="RFC5844"></xref>, as well as the multicast
      edge related protocols <xref target="RFC3376"></xref>, <xref
      target="RFC3810"></xref> and <xref target="RFC4605"></xref>.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Base Solution for Source Mobility: Overview">
      <t>The reference scenario for multicast deployment in Proxy Mobile IPv6
      domains is illustrated in <xref target="fig1"></xref>.</t>

      <figure anchor="fig1"
              title="Reference Network for  Multicast Deployment in PMIPv6 with Source Mobility">
        <artwork><![CDATA[                       +-------------+
                       | Multicast   |
                       | Listeners   |
                       +-------------+
                              |
                     ***  ***  ***  ***
                    *   **   **   **   *
                   *                    *
                    *  Fixed Internet  *
                   *                    *
                    *   **   **   **   *
                     ***  ***  ***  ***
                      /            \
                  +----+         +----+
                  |LMA1|         |LMA2|                 Multicast Anchor
                  +----+         +----+
             LMAA1  |              |  LMAA2
                    |              |
                    \\           //\\
                     \\         //  \\
                      \\       //    \\                 Unicast Tunnel
                       \\     //      \\ 
                        \\   //        \\
                         \\ //          \\
               Proxy-CoA1 ||            ||  Proxy-CoA2
                       +----+          +----+
                       |MAG1|          |MAG2|           MLD Proxy
                       +----+          +----+
                        |  |             |
                MN-HNP1 |  | MN-HNP2     | MN-HNP3
                       MN1 MN2          MN3
                 Multicast Sender + Listener(s)
      ]]></artwork>
      </figure>

      <t>An MN in a PMIPv6 domain will decide on multicast data transmission
      completely independent of its current mobility conditions. It will send
      packets as initiated by applications, using its source address with Home
      Network Prefix (HNP) and a multicast destination addresses chosen by
      application needs. Multicast packets will arrive at the currently active
      MAG via one of its downstream local (wireless) links. A multicast
      unaware MAG would simply discard these packets in the absence of a
      multicast forwarding information base (MFIB).</t>

      <t>An MN can successfully distribute multicast data in PMIPv6, if MLD
      proxy functions are deployed at the MAG as described in <xref
      target="RFC6224"></xref>. In this set-up, the MLD proxy instance serving
      a mobile multicast source has configured its upstream interface at the
      tunnel towards MN's corresponding LMA. For each LMA, there will be a
      separate instance of an MLD proxy.</t>

      <t>According to the specifications given in <xref
      target="RFC4605"></xref>, multicast data arriving from a downstream
      interface of an MLD proxy will be forwarded to the upstream interface
      and to all but the incoming downstream interfaces with appropriate
      forwarding states for this group. Thus multicast streams originating
      from an MN will arrive at the corresponding LMA and directly at all
      mobile receivers co-located at the same MAG. Serving as the designated
      multicast router or an additional MLD proxy, the LMA forwards data to
      the fixed Internet, if forwarding states are maintained through
      multicast routing. If the LMA is acting as another MLD proxy, it will
      forward the multicast data to its upstream interface, and based upon the
      downstream interfaces' subscriptions accordingly.</t>

      <t>In case of a handover, the MN (unaware of IP mobility) can continue
      to send multicast packets as soon as network connectivity is
      reconfigured. At this time, the MAG has determined the corresponding
      LMA, and IPv6 unicast address configuration with PMIPv6 bindings have
      been performed. Multicast packets arriving at the MAG are discarded
      until the MAG has completed the following steps.</t>

      <t><list style="numbers">
          <t>The MAG SHOULD determine whether the MN is admissible to
          multicast services, and stop here otherwise.</t>

          <t>The MAG adds the new downstream link to the MLD proxy instance
          with up-link to the corresponding LMA.</t>
        </list>As soon as the MN's uplink is associated with the corresponding
      MLD proxy instance, multicast packets are forwarded again to the LMA and
      eventually to receivers within the PMIP domain (see the call flow in
      <xref target="fig-callflow"></xref>). In this way, multicast source
      mobility is transparently enabled in PMIPv6 domains that deploy the base
      scenario for multicast.</t>

      <figure anchor="fig-callflow"
              title="Call Flow for Group Communication in Multicast-enabled PMIP">
        <artwork><![CDATA[MN1             MAG1             MN2             MAG2             LMA
|                |                |               |                |
|                | Mcast Data     |               |                |
|                |<---------------+               |                |
|                |     Mcast Data |               |                |
|  Join(G)       +================================================>|
+--------------> |                |               |                |
| Mcast Data     |                |               |                |
|<---------------+                |               |                |
|                |                |               |                |
|           <  Movement of MN 2 to MAG2  &  PMIP Binding Update  > |
|                |                |               |                |
|                |                |--- Rtr Sol -->|                |
|                |                |<-- Rtr Adv ---|                |
|                |                |               |                |
|                |                |   < MLD Proxy Configuration >  |
|                |                |               |                |
|                |                |   MLD Query   |                |
|                |                |<--------------+                |
|                |                |  Mcast Data   |                |
|                |                +-------------->|                |
|                |                |               | Mcast Data     |   
|                |                |               +===============>|
|                |                |               |                |
|                |   Mcast Data   |               |                |
|                |<================================================+
|  Mcast Data    |                |               |                |
|<---------------+                |               |                |
|                |                |               |                |
]]></artwork>
      </figure>

      <t></t>

      <t>These multicast deployment considerations likewise apply for mobile
      nodes that operate with their IPv4 stack enabled in a PMIPv6 domain.
      PMIPv6 can provide IPv4 home address mobility support <xref
      target="RFC5844"></xref>. IPv4 multicast is handled by an IGMP proxy
      function at the MAG in an analogous way.</t>

      <t>Following these deployment steps, multicast traffic distribution
      transparently inter-operates with PMIPv6. It is worth noting that a MN -
      while being attached to the same MAG as the mobile source, but
      associated with a different LMA, cannot receive multicast traffic on a
      shortest path. Instead, multicast streams flow up to the LMA of the
      mobile source, are transferred to the LMA of the mobile listener and
      tunneled downwards to the MAG again (see <xref target="A-Eval"></xref>
      for further considerations).</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Base Solution for Source Mobility: Details">
      <t>Incorporating multicast source mobility in PMIPv6 requires to deploy
      general multicast functions at PMIPv6 routers and to define their
      interaction with the PMIPv6 protocol in the following way.</t>

      <section title="Operations of the Mobile Node">
        <t>A Mobile Node willing to send multicast data will proceed as if
        attached to the fixed Internet. No specific mobility or other
        multicast related functionalities are required at the MN.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Operations of the Mobile Access Gateway">
        <t>A Mobile Access Gateway is required to have MLD proxy instances
        deployed corresponding to each LMA, taking the corresponding tunnel as
        its unique upstream link, cf., <xref target="RFC6224"></xref>. On the
        arrival of a MN, the MAG decides on the mapping of downstream links to
        a proxy instance and the upstream link to the LMA based on the regular
        Binding Update List as maintained by PMIPv6 standard operations. When
        multicast data is received from the MN, the MAG MUST identify the
        corresponding proxy instance from the incoming interface and forwards
        multicast data upstream according to <xref
        target="RFC4605"></xref>.</t>

        <t>The MAG MAY apply special admission control to enable multicast
        data transition from a MN. It is advisable to take special care that
        MLD proxy implementations do not redistribute multicast data to
        downstream interfaces without appropriate subscriptions in place.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Operations of the Local Mobility Anchor">
        <t>For any MN, the Local Mobility Anchor acts as the persistent Home
        Agent and at the same time as the default multicast upstream for the
        corresponding MAG. It will manage and maintain a multicast forwarding
        information base for all group traffic arriving from its mobile
        sources. It SHOULD participate in multicast routing functions that
        enable traffic redistribution to all adjacent LMAs within the PMIPv6
        domain and thereby ensure a continuous receptivity while the source is
        in motion.</t>

        <section title="Local Mobility Anchors Operating PIM">
          <t>Local Mobility Anchors that operate the PIM routing protocol
          <xref target="RFC4601"></xref> will require sources to be directly
          connected for sending PIM registers to the RP. This does not hold in
          a PMIPv6 domain, as MAGs are routers intermediate to MN and the LMA.
          In this sense, MNs are multicast sources external to the PIM-SM
          domain.</t>

          <t>To cure this defect common to all set-ups of subsidiary domains
          not running PIM, the LMA should act as a PIM Border Router and
          activate the Border-bit. In this case, the DirectlyConnected(S) is
          treated as being TRUE for mobile sources and the PIM-SM forwarding
          rule "iif == RPF_interface(S)" is relaxed to be TRUE, as the
          incoming tunnel interface from MAG to LMA is considered as not part
          of the PIM-SM component of the LMA (see A.1 of <xref
          target="RFC4601"></xref> ).</t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section title="IPv4 Support">
        <t>An MN in a PMIPv6 domain may use an IPv4 address transparently for
        communication as specified in <xref target="RFC5844"></xref>. For this
        purpose, LMAs can register IPv4-Proxy-CoAs in its Binding Caches and
        MAGs can provide IPv4 support in access networks. Correspondingly,
        multicast membership management will be performed by the MN using
        IGMP. For multicast support on the network side, an IGMP proxy
        function needs to be deployed at MAGs in exactly the same way as for
        IPv6. <xref target="RFC4605"></xref> defines IGMP proxy behaviour in
        full agreement with IPv6/MLD. Thus IPv4 support can be transparently
        provided following the obvious deployment analogy.</t>

        <t>For a dual-stack IPv4/IPv6 access network, the MAG proxy instances
        SHOULD choose multicast signaling according to address configurations
        on the link, but MAY submit IGMP and MLD queries in parallel, if
        needed. It should further be noted that the infrastructure cannot
        identify two data streams as identical when distributed via an IPv4
        and IPv6 multicast group. Thus duplicate data may be forwarded on a
        heterogeneous network layer.</t>

        <t>A particular note is worth giving the scenario of <xref
        target="RFC5845"></xref> in which overlapping private address spaces
        of different operators can be hosted in a PMIP domain by using GRE
        encapsulation with key identification. This scenario implies that
        unicast communication in the MAG-LMA tunnel can be individually
        identified per MN by the GRE keys. This scenario still does not impose
        any special treatment of multicast communication for the following
        reasons.</t>

        <t>Multicast streams from and to MNs arrive at a MAG on point-to-point
        links (identical to unicast). between the routers and independent of
        any individual MN. So the MAG-proxy and the LMA SHOULD NOT use GRE key
        identifiers, but plain GRE encapsulation in multicast communication
        (including MLD queries and reports). Multicast traffic sent upstream
        and downstream of MAG-to-LMA tunnels proceeds as router-to-router
        forwarding according to the multicast forwarding information base
        (MFIB) of the MAG or LMA and independent of MN's unicast addresses,
        while the MAG proxy instance re-distributes multicast data down the
        point-to-point links (interfaces) according to its own MFIB,
        independent of MN's IP addresses.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Efficiency of the Distribution System">
        <t>In the following efficiency-related issues are enumerated.</t>

        <t><list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="Multicast reception at LMA">In the current deployment
            scenario, the LMA will receive all multicast traffic originating
            from its associated MNs. There is no mechanism to suppress
            upstream forwarding in the absence of receivers.</t>

            <t hangText="MNs on the same MAG using different LMAs">For a
            mobile receiver and a source that use different LMAs, the traffic
            has to go up to one LMA, cross over to the other LMA, and then be
            tunneled back to the same MAG, causing redundant flows in the
            access network and at the MAG.</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Multicast Routing Throughout the Access Network">
      <t>There are deployment scenarios, where multicast services are
      available throughout the access network independent of the PMIPv6
      infrastructure. Direct multicast access can be supported by<list
          style="symbols">
          <t>native multicast routing provided by one multicast router within
          a flat access network and MLD proxies deployed at MAGs,</t>

          <t>a multicast routing protocol such as PIM-SM <xref
          target="RFC4601"></xref> or BIDIR-PIM <xref target="RFC5015"></xref>
          deployed at the MAGs.</t>
        </list>Multicast traffic distribution can be simplified in these
      scenarios. A single proxy instance at MAGs with up-link into the
      multicast cloud will serve as a first hop gateway into the multicast
      routing domain and avoid traffic duplication or detour routing.
      Multicast routing functions at MAGs will seemlessly embed PMIP mobility
      gateways within a multicast cloud. However, mobility of the multicast
      source in this scenario will require some multicast routing protocols to
      rebuild distribution trees. This can cause significant service
      disruptions or delays (see <xref target="RFC5757"></xref> for further
      aspects). Deployment details are specific to the multicast routing
      protocol in use, in the following described for common protocols.</t>

      <t></t>

      <section title="PIM-SM">
        <t>TODO</t>
      </section>

      <section title="BIDIR PIM">
        <t>TODO</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Extended Source Mobility Schemes in PMIPv6">
      <t>In this section, specific optimization approaches to multicast source
      mobility are introduced. </t>

      <section title="Multiple Upstream Interface Proxy">
        <t>Although multicast communication can be enabled in PMIPv6 domains
        by deploying MLD Proxy functions at MAG, some disadvantages still
        exist. Firstly, for a proxy device performing IGMP/MLD-based
        forwarding has a single upstream interface and one or more downstream
        interfaces as described in RFC4605, there should be many MLD Proxy
        functions deployed at one MAG, which is complicated and then is
        difficult for implementation and management. And then when the
        multicast packets arrive at the MAG running multiple parallel MLD
        proxy functions, there may be confusions for the data if there is no
        extra processing or filtering scheme at the MAG. In addition, the
        route optimization issue is still up in the air, that is, for a mobile
        receiver and a source on the same MAG using different LMAs, the
        traffic has to go up to one LMA, cross over to the other LMA, and then
        be tunneled back to the same MAG, causing redundant flows in the
        access network and at the MAG. Therefore, the MLD Proxy function
        should be extended to accommodate the PMIPv6 protocol. As same as
        described in <xref target="RFC6224"></xref> and this document (s.
        abobe), the MLD proxy functions are deployed at the MAG, while only
        one MLD Proxy function is required to run at the MAG and multiple
        upstream interfaces can be set for the MLD Proxy instance, which is
        called Multi-Upstream Interfaces MLD Proxy (MUIMP).</t>

        <t>.... TODO details.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>TODO.</t>

      <t>Note to RFC Editor: this section may be removed on publication as an
      RFC.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>This draft does not introduce additional messages or novel protocol
      operations. Consequently, no new threats are introduced by this document
      in addition to those identified as security concerns of <xref
      target="RFC3810"></xref>, <xref target="RFC4605"></xref>, <xref
      target="RFC5213"></xref>, and <xref target="RFC5844"></xref>.</t>

      <t>However, particular attention should be paid to implications of
      combining multicast and mobility management at network entities. As this
      specification allows mobile nodes to initiate the creation of multicast
      forwarding states at MAGs and LMAs while changing attachments, threats
      of resource exhaustion at PMIP routers and access networks arrive from
      rapid state changes, as well as from high volume data streams routed
      into access networks of limited capacities. In addition to proper
      authorization checks of MNs, rate controls at replicators MAY be
      required to protect the agents and the downstream networks. In
      particular, MLD proxy implementations at MAGs SHOULD carefully procure
      for automatic multicast state extinction on the departure of MNs, as
      mobile multicast listeners in the PMIPv6 domain will not actively
      terminate group membership prior to departure.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>The authors would like to thank (in alphabetical order) Muhamma Omer
      Farooq, Jouni Korhonen, He-Wu Li, Stig Venaas Li-Li Wang, Qian Wu,
      Zhi-Wei Yan for advice, help and reviews of the document.</t>

      <t></t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6275"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5213"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3810"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4601"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4605"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5015"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2710"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5844"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3376"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6224"?>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5757"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5845"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2236"?>
    </references>

    <section anchor="A-Eval" title="Evaluation of Traffic Flows">
      <t>TODO</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Change Log ">
      <t>The following changes have been made from version
      draft-schmidt-multimob-pmipv6-source-00:</t>
    </section>
  </back>
</rfc>
