<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!-- One method to get references from the online citation libraries.
     There has to be one entity for each item to be referenced. 
     An alternate method (rfc include) is described in the references. -->

<!ENTITY rfc1918 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1918.xml'>
<!ENTITY rfc2011 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2011.xml'>
<!ENTITY rfc2096 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2096.xml'>
<!ENTITY rfc2827 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2827.xml'>
<!ENTITY rfc3315 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3315.xml'>
<!ENTITY rfc3971 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3971.xml'>
<!ENTITY rfc3972 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3972.xml'>
<!ENTITY rfc4057 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4057.xml'>
<!ENTITY rfc4193 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4193.xml'>
<!ENTITY rfc4213 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4213.xml'>
<!ENTITY rfc4293 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4293.xml'>
<!ENTITY rfc4296 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4296.xml'>
<!ENTITY rfc4364 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4364.xml'>
<!ENTITY rfc4443 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4443.xml'>
<!ENTITY rfc4659 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4659.xml'>
<!ENTITY rfc4861 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4861.xml'>
<!ENTITY rfc4862 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4862.xml'>
<!ENTITY rfc4890 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4890.xml'>
<!ENTITY rfc4941 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4941.xml'>
<!ENTITY rfc5095 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5095.xml'>
<!ENTITY rfc5102 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5102.xml'>
<!ENTITY rfc5157 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5157.xml'>
<!ENTITY rfc5211 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5211.xml'>
<!ENTITY rfc5375 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5375.xml'>
<!ENTITY rfc5722 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5722.xml'>
<!ENTITY rfc5798 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5798.xml'>
<!ENTITY rfc5952 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5952.xml'>
<!ENTITY rfc6052 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6052.xml'>
<!ENTITY rfc6104 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6104.xml'>
<!ENTITY rfc6105 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6105.xml'>
<!ENTITY rfc6144 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6144.xml'>
<!ENTITY rfc6145 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6145.xml'>
<!ENTITY rfc6146 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6146.xml'>
<!ENTITY rfc6147 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6147.xml'>
<!ENTITY rfc6192 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6192.xml'>
<!ENTITY rfc6302 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6302.xml'>
<!ENTITY rfc6434 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6434.xml'>

<!ENTITY I-D.ietf-savi-threat-scope
        PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-savi-threat-scope.xml'>

<!ENTITY I-D.gashinsky-v6ops-v6nd-problems
        PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.gashinsky-v6ops-v6nd-problems.xml'>

<!ENTITY I-D.xli-behave-divi
        PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.xli-behave-divi.xml'>

]>

<?rfc toc="yes"?> <?rfc symrefs="yes"?> <?rfc autobreaks="yes"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?> <?rfc compact="yes"?> <?rfc subcompact="no"?>

<!-- keep one blank line between list items -->

<rfc category="info" docName="draft-chkpvc-enterprise-incremental-ipv6-00"
     ipr="trust200902">

  <!-- ***** FRONT MATTER ***** -->

  <front>
    <title abbrev="enterprise-incremental-ipv6">Enterprise Incremental IPv6</title>

    <author fullname="Lee Howard" initials="L" surname="Howard">
      <organization>Time Warner Cable</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>13820 Sunrise Valley Drive</street>

          <!-- Reorder these if your country does things differently -->

          <city>Herndon</city>

          <region>VA</region>

          <code>20171</code>

          <country>US</country>
        </postal>

        <phone>+1 703 345 3513</phone>

        <email>lee.howard@twcable.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

	<author fullname="Tim Chown" initials="T.J." surname="Chown">
	<organization> University of Southampton </organization>
	<address>
	<postal>
	<street> Highfield </street>
	<city> Southampton </city>
	<code> SO17 1BJ </code>
	<region> Hampshire </region>
	<country> United Kingdom </country>
	</postal>
	<email> tjc@ecs.soton.ac.uk </email>
	</address>
	</author>

    <author fullname="Kiran K. Chittimaneni" initials="K"
            surname="Chittimaneni">
      <organization>Google Inc.</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>1600 Amphitheater Pkwy</street>
          <city>Mountain View, California</city>
          <country>USA</country>
          <code>CA 94043</code>
        </postal>
        <email>kk@google.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Yanick Pouffary" initials="Y" surname="Pouffary">
      <organization>Hewlett Packard</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>950 Route Des Colles</street>
          <city>Sophia-Antipolis</city>
          <country>France</country>
          <code>06901</code>
        </postal>
        <email>Yanick.Pouffary@hp.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

     <author initials="E" surname="Vyncke" fullname="Eric Vyncke">
      <organization>Cisco Systems</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>De Kleetlaan 6a</street>
          <city>Diegem</city>
          <country>Belgium</country>
          <code>1831</code>
        </postal>
        <phone>+32 2 778 4677</phone>
        <email>evyncke@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>


    <author fullname="Victor Kuarsingh" initials="V" surname="Kuarsingh">
      <organization>Rogers Communications</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>8200 Dixie Road</street>
          <city>Brampton, Ontario</city>
          <country>Canada</country>
          <code></code>
        </postal>
        <email>victor.kuarsingh@rci.rogers.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date month="February" year="2012" />

    <!-- Meta-data Declarations -->

    <area>Ops</area>

    <workgroup></workgroup>

    <!-- WG name at the upperleft corner of the doc,
         IETF is fine for individual submissions.  
	 If this element is not present, the default is "Network Working Group",
         which is used by the RFC Editor as a nod to the history of the IETF. -->

    <keyword>IPv6 transition enterprise</keyword>

    <!-- Keywords will be incorporated into HTML output
         files in a meta tag but they have no effect on text or nroff
         output. If you submit your draft to the RFC Editor, the
         keywords will be used for the search engine. -->

    <abstract>
      <t>Enterprise network administrators worldwide are in various stages of
      preparing for or deploying IPv6 into their networks. The administrators
      face different challenges than operators of Internet access providers,
      and have reasons for different priorities. The overall problem for many
      administrators will be to offer Internet-facing services over IPv6,
      while continuing to support IPv4, and while introducing IPv6 access
      within the enterprise IT network. The overall transition will take most
      networks from an IPv4-only environment to a dual stack network
      environment and potentially an IPv6-only operating mode. This document
      helps provide a framework for enterprise network architects or 
	administrators who may
      be faced with many of these challenges as they consider their IPv6
      support strategies.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section anchor="Introduction" title="Introduction">
      <t>An Enterprise Network as defined in <xref target="RFC4057"></xref>
      as: a network that has multiple internal links, one or more router
      connections to one or more Providers, and is actively managed by a
      network operations entity (the "administrator", whether a single person
      or department of administrators). Adminstrators generally support an
      internal network, consisting of users' computers and related
      peripherals, a server network, consisting of accounting and business
      application servers, and an external network, consisting of
      Internet-accessible services such as web servers, email servers, VPN
      systems, and customer applications. This document is intended as
      guidance for network architects and 
	administrators in planning their IPv6 deployments.</t>

      <t>The business reasons for spending time, effort, and money on IPv6
      will be unique to each enterprise. The most common drivers are due to
      the fact that when Internet service providers, including mobile wireless
      carriers, run out of IPv4 addresses, they will provide native IPv6 and
      non-native IPv4. The non-native IPv4 service may be NAT64, NAT444,
      Dual-stack Lite, or other transition technology, but whether tunneled or
      translated, the native traffic will be perform better and more reliably
      than non-native. It is thus in the enterprise's interests to deploy
	native IPv6 itself.</t>

      <t></t>

      <section title="Enterprise Assumptions">
        <t>For the purposes of this document, assume: </t>

        <t><list style="symbols">
            <t>The administrator is considering deploying IPv6 (but see <xref
            target="IPv4-only"></xref> below).</t>

            <t>The administrator has existing IPv4 networks and devices which
            will continue to exist. </t>

            <t>The administrator will want to minimize the level of disruption
            to the users and services by minimizing number of technologies and
            functions that are needed to mediate any given application. In
            other words, provide native IP wherever possible.</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>Based on these assumptions, an administrator will want to use
        technologies which minimize the number of flows being tunnelled,
        translated or intercepted at any given time. The administrator will
        choose transition technologies or strategies which allow most traffic
        to be native, and will manage non-native traffic. This will allow the
        administrator to minimize the cost of IPv6 transition technologies, by
        containing the number and scale of transition systems.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="IPv4-only" title="IPv4-only Considerations">
        <t>As described in <xref target="RFC6302"></xref> administrators
        should take certain steps even if they are not considering IPv6.
        Specifically, Internet-facing servers should log the source port
        number, timestamp (from a reliable source), and the transport
        protocol. This will allow investigation of malefactors behind
        address-sharing technologies such as NAT44 or Dual-stack Lite.
        Enabling this additional logging will take a few minutes on each
        server, and will probably require restarting the service.</t>
	<t>
	Other IPv6 considerations may impact ostensibly IPv4-only networks,
	e.g. <xref target="RFC6104"></xref> describes the rogue IPv6 RA
	problem, which may cause problems in IPv4-only networks where IPv6
	is enabled in end systems on that network.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Reasons for a Phased Approach">
        <t>Given the challenges of migrating user workstations, corporate
        systems, and Internet-facing servers, a phased approach allows
        incremental deployment of IPv6, based on the administrator's own
        determination of priorities. The Preparation Phases is highly
        recommended to all administrators, as it will save errors and
        complexity in later phases. Each administrator must decide whether to
        begin with the External Phase (as recommended in <xref
        target="RFC5211"></xref>) or the Internal Phase. There is no "correct"
	answer here; the decision is one for each enterprise to make.</t>
	<t>Some considerations:</t>

        <t><list style="symbols">
            <t>In many cases, customers outside the network will have IPv6
            before the internal enterprise network. For these customers, IPv6
            may well perform better, especially for certain applications, than
            translated or tunneled IPv4, so the administrator may want to
            prioritize the External Phase.</t>

            <t>Employees who access internal systems by VPN may find that
            their ISPs provide translated IPv4, which does not support the
            required VPN protocols. In these cases, the administrator may want
            to prioritize the External Phase, and any other
            remotely-accessible internal systems.</t>

            <t>Internet-facing servers cannot be managed over IPv6 unless the
            management systems are IPv6-capable. These might be Network
            Management Systems (NMS), monitoring systems, or just remote
            management desktops. Thus in some cases, the Internet-facing
            systems are dependent on IPv6-capable internal networks. However,
            dual-stack Internet-facing systems can still be managed over
            IPv4.</t>

            <t>IPv6 is enabled by default on all modern operating systems, so
            it may be more urgent to manage the internal traffic.</t>

            <t>In many cases, the corporate accounting, payroll, human
            resource, and other internal systems may only need to be reachable
            from the internal network, so they may be a lower priority.</t>
          </list>These considerations are in conflict; each administrator must
        prioritize according to their local conditions.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Preparation and Assessment Phase" toc="default">
      <t></t>

      <section title="Inventory Phase">
        <t>
	To comprehend the inventory phase spectrum we recommended dividing 
	the problem space in two: network infrastructure readiness and 
	applications readiness.
	</t>

<section title="Network infrastructure readiness assessment">

<t>
The network infrastructure readiness assessment for IPv6 as its name state 
is focused on the network.  The goal of this assessment is identify the 
level of readiness of network equipment. This is an important step as it 
will help identify the effort required to move to an infrastructure that 
supports IPv6.  
</t>

<t>
Be able to understand which network devices are already capable, which 
devices can be made IPv6 ready with a code/firmware upgrade, and which 
devices will need to be replaced. The data collection consists of a network 
discovery to gain an understanding of the topology and inventory network 
infrastructure equipment and code versions with information gathered from 
static files and IP address management, DNS and DHCP tools.  
</t>

<t>
Remember understanding the starting point and what are the technical issues 
and challenges is critical as IPv6 might already be present in the 
environment thus creating inherent security risks.  
</t>

</section>

<section title="Applications readiness assessment">

<t>
Just like network equipment, application software needs to support IPv6. 
This includes OS, firmware, middleware and applications (including internally 
developed applications). Vendors will typically handle IPv6 enablement of 
off-the-shelf products. Enterprises need to request this support from vendors. 
For internally developed applications it is the responsibility of the 
enterprise to enable them for IPv6. Analyzing how a given application communicates 
of the network will dictate the steps required to support IPv6. Applications 
should be made to use APIs which hide the specifics of a given IP address 
family. Any applications that use APIs, such as the C language, which exposes 
the IP version specificity need to be modified to also work with IPv6. 
</t>

<t>
There are two ways to IPv6-enable your applications. The first approach is 
to have separate logic for IPv4 and IPv6, thus leaving the IPv4 code path 
mainly untouched. This approach causes the least disruption to the existing 
IPv4 logic flow, but introduces more complexity, since the application now 
has to deal with two logic loops with complex race conditions and error recovery 
mechanisms between these two logic loops. The second approach is to create a 
combined IPv4/IPv6 logic, which ensures operation regardless of the IP version 
used on the network. We recommend using industry IPv6-porting tools to locate 
the code that need to be updated. 
</t>

</section>

<section title="Importance of readiness validation and testing">

<t>
Lastly IPv6 introduces a completely new way of addressing endpoints, which 
can have ramifications at the network layer all the way up to the applications. 
So to minimize disruption during the transition phase we recommend complete 
functionality, scalability and security testing to understand how IPv6 impacts 
the services and networking infrastructure will be paramount. 
</t>

</section>

      </section>

      <section title="Training">
        <t>
IPv6 planning and deployment in the enterprise is not an entirely network centric 
affair. IPv6 adoption will be a multifaceted undertaking that will touch 
everyone in the organization. While technology and process transformations are 
taking place is it critical that people training takes place as well. Training 
will ensure that people and skill gaps are assessed proactively and managed 
accordingly. We recommend that training needs be analyzed and defined in 
order to successfully inform, train, and prepare staff for the impacts of 
the system or process changes.
	</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Routing">
        <t>
When deploying IPv6, we recommend initially choosing an IGP protocol you are 
familiar with. That is to say if you are using OSPFv2 you should be using OSPFv3. 
The main advantage of this approach is that staff do not need to be trained 
and existing processes can be leveraged. 
	</t>
	<t>
Enterprises could also take the opportunity the introduction of IPv6 brings to 
analyze your current environment and to identify which features you would 
like to change and what you would like to implement. Then using the 
validation period as a way to validate your new approach and even applying 
them to your IPv4 environment. 
	</t>
	<t>
Either way IPv6 introduces the opportunity to rationalize the environment 
and to architect it for growth.
	</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Security and Routing Policy">
        <t>
It is obvious that IPv6 network should be deployed in a secure way. 
The industry has learned a lot about network security with IPv4, so, 
network operators should leverage this knowledge and expertise when 
deploying IPv6. IPv6 is not so different than IPv4: it is a 
connectionless network protocol using the same lower layer service 
and delivering the same service to the upper layer. Therefore, the 
security issues and mitigation techniques are mostly identical with 
same exceptions that are described further.
	</t>

	<section title="Demystifying some IPv6 Security Myths">

	<t>
Some people believe that IPv6 is inherently more secure than IPv4 
because it is new. Nothing can be more wrong. Indeed, being a new 
protocol means that bugs in the implementations have yet to be 
discovered and fixed and that few people have the operational security 
expertise needed to operate securely an IPv6 network. This lack of 
operational expertise is the biggest threat when deploying IPv6: 
the importance of training is to be stressed again. 
	</t>

	<t>
One security myth is that thanks to its huge address space, a network 
cannot be scanned by enumerating all IPv6 address in a /64 LAN 
hence a malevolent person cannot find a victim.
<xref target="RFC5157"></xref> describes 
some alternate techniques to find potential targets on a network, 
for example enumerating all DNS names in a zone.
	</t>

	<t>
Another security myth is that IPv6 is more secure because it mandates 
the use of IPsec everywhere. <xref target="RFC6434"></xref>
clearly states that the IPv6 support is a SHOULD only. Moreover, 
if all the intra-enterprise traffic is encrypted, then this 
renders all the network security tools (IPS, firewall, ACL, 
IPFIX, etc) blind and pretty much useless. Therefore, 
IPsec should be used in IPv6 pretty much like in IPv4 (for example 
to establish a VPN overlay over a non-trusted network or reserve 
to some specific applications).	
	</t>

	<t>
The last security myth is that amplification attacks (such as 
http://www.cert.org/advisories/CA-1998-01.html) do not 
exist in IPv6 because there is no more broadcast. Alas, this is 
not true as ICMP error (in some cases) or information messages 
can be generated by routers and hosts when forwarding or 
receiving a multicast message (section 2.4 
of <xref target="RFC4443"></xref>). Therefore, 
the generation and the forwarding rate of ICMPv6 messages 
must be rate limited as in IPv4.
	</t>

	</section>

	<section title="Similarities between IPv6 and IPv4 security">

	<t>
As mentioned earlier, IPv6 is quite similar to IPv4, therefore 
several attacks apply for both protocol family:
	</t>
	<t>
<list style="symbols">
<t>Application layer attacks: such as cross-site scripting or 
SQL injection</t>
<t>Rogue device: such as a rogue WiFi Access Point</t>
<t>Flooding and all traffic based denial of services (including the 
use of control plane policing for IPv6 traffic see 
<xref target="RFC6192"></xref>)</t>
<t>Etc</t>
	</list>
	</t>

	<t>
A specific case of congruence is the IPv6 ULA 
<xref target="RFC4193"></xref> and IPv4 private addressing 
<xref target="RFC1918"></xref> that do not provide any security 
by 'magic'. In both case, the edge router must apply strict 
data plane and routing policy to block those private addresses 
to leave and enter the network. This filtering can be done 
by the enterprise or by the ISP.
	</t>

	<t>
IPv6 addresses can be spoofed as easily as IPv4 addresses and there 
are packets with bogons IPv6 addresses 
(see http://www.team-cymru.org/Services/Bogons/). The anti-bogon 
filtering must be done in the data and routing planes. It 
can be done by the enterprise or by the ISP.
	</t>

	</section>


	<section title="Specific Security Issues for IPv6">

	<t>
Even if IPv6 is similar to IPv4, there are some differences that 
create some IPv6-only vulnerabilities or issues.
	</t>

	<t>
Privacy extension addresses <xref target="RFC4941"></xref> 
are usually to protect individual privacy by changing periodically 
the interface identifier part of the IPv6 address to avoid 
tracking a host by its always identical and unique EUI-64. 
While this presents a real advantage on the Internet, it 
complicates the task of audit trail when a security officer or 
network operator wants to trace back a log entry to a host in 
their network because when the tracing is done the searched IPv6 
address could have disappeared from the network. A good way to 
prevent the use of privacy extension addresses without host 
configuration is to send the Router Advertisement with the 
M-bit set (to force the use of DHCPv6 to get an address) and 
with all advertized prefixes without the A-bit set (to 
prevent the use of stateless auto-configuration).
	</t>

	<t>
Extension headers complicate the task of stateless packet 
filters such as ACL. If ACL are used to enforce a security policy, 
then the enterprise must verify whether its ACL (but also stateful 
firewalls) are able to process extension headers (this means 
understand them enough to parse them to find the upper layers 
payloads) and to block unwanted extension headers (e.g. to 
implement <xref target="RFC5095"></xref>).
	</t>

	<t>
Fragmentation is different in IPv6 because it is done only by 
source host and never during a forwarding operation. This means 
that ICMPv6 packet-too-big must be allowed 
<xref target="RFC4890"></xref> through all filters. Fragments 
can also be used to evade some security mechanisms such as 
RA-guard <xref target="RFC6105"></xref>, see also 
<xref target="RFC5722"></xref>which appears to be widely 
implemented in 2012.
	</t>

	<t>
But, the biggest difference is the replacement of ARP (RFC 826) 
by Neighbor Discovery Protocol <xref target="RFC4861"></xref>. 
NDP runs over ICMPv6 (this means that security policies MUST 
allow some ICMPv6 messages see RFC 4890) but has the same lack 
of security as ARP (SeND <xref target="RFC3971"></xref>
and CGA <xref target="RFC3972"></xref> are not widely implemented). 
ARP can be made secure with the help of techniques known as 
DHCPv4 snooping and dynamic ARP inspection by access switches. 
Therefore, enterprises using those techniques for IPv4 should 
use the equivalent techniques for IPv6: this is RA-guard 
(RFC 6105) and all work in progress from the SAVI WG 
(<xref target="I-D.ietf-savi-threat-scope"></xref> and
others). Another DoS vulnerabilities are related to NDP 
cache exhaustion 
(<xref target="I-D.gashinsky-v6ops-v6nd-problems"></xref>)
and they can be mitigated by careful tuning of the NDP cache. 
In 2012, there are already several vendors offering those 
features on their switches.
	</t>

	<t>
Running a dual-stack network doubles the attack exposure as a 
malevolent person has now two attack vectors: IPv4 and IPv6. 
This simply means that all routers and hosts operating in a 
dual-stack environment with both protocol families enabled 
(even if by default) must have a congruent security policy for 
both protocol version. For example, permit TCP ports 80 
and 443 to all web servers and deny all other ports to the 
same servers must be implemented both for IPv4 and IPv6.
	</t>


	</section>


      </section>

      <section title="Address Plan">
        <t>
The most common problem encountered in IPv6 networking is in applying the 
same principles of conservation that are so important in IPv4. IPv6 
addresses do not need to be assigned conservatively. In fact, a single 
larger allocation is considered more conservative than multiple 
discountiguous small blocks, because a single block occupies only a 
single entry in a routing table.  The advice in 
<xref target="RFC5375"></xref> is still 
sound, and is recommended to the reader.  If considering ULAs, give 
careful consideration to how well it is supported, especially in multiple 
address and multicast scenarios, and assess the strength of the 
requirement for ULA.
	</t>
	<t>
The enterprise administrator will want to evaluate whether the enterprise 
will request address space from its ISP (or Local Internet Registry (LIR)), 
or whether to request address space from the local Internet Registry 
(whether a Regional Internet Registry such as AfriNIC, APNIC, ARIN, 
LACNIC, or RIPE-NCC, or a National Internet Registry, operated in some 
countries).  There may be a registration fee for requesting 
provider-independent (PI) space from and NIR/RIR, but the enterprise 
will avoid some complexity if renumbering is required after changing 
ISPs (it should be noted that renumbering caused by outgrowing the space, 
merger, or other internal reason might not be avoided with PI space).
	</t>
	<t>
Each location, no matter how small, should get at least a /48.  In 
addition to allowing for simple planning, this can allow a site to use 
its prefix for local connectivity, should the need arise, and if the 
local ISP supports it.  Generally, workstations managed by the enterprise 
will use stateful DHCPv6 for addressing on corporate LAN segments.  
DHCPv6 allows for the additional configuration options often employed 
by enterprise administrators, and by using stateful DHCPv6, 
administrators correlating system logs know which system had which 
address at any given time.
	</t>
	<t>
In the data center or server room, assume a /64 per VLAN.  This applies 
even if each individual system is on a separate VLAN; in a /48 
assignment, typical for a site, there are 65,535 /64 blocks.  Addresses 
are either configured manually on the server, or reserved on a DHCPv6 
server, which may also synchronize forward and reverse DNS.
	</t>
	<t>
Plan to aggregate at every layer of network hierarchy.  Where multiple 
VLANs or other layer two domains converge, allow some room for expansion.  
Renumbering due to outgrowing the network plan is a nuisance, so allow 
room within it.  Generally, grow to about twice the current size can be 
accomodated; where rapid growth is planned, allow for twice that growth.  
Also, for any part of the network where DNS (or reverse DNS) zones may 
be delegated, it is important to delegate addresses on nibble boundaries, 
to ensure propose name delegation.
	</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Program Planning">
        <t>
As with any project, an IPv6 deployment project will have its own phases.  
Generally, one person is identified as the project sponsor or champion, who 
will make sure time and talent resources are prioritized appropriately for 
the project.  Because enabling IPv6 can be a project with many interrelated 
tasks, identifying a project manager is also recommended.  The project 
manager and sponsor can initiate the project, determining the scope of work 
and identifying whose input is required, and who will be affected by work.  
The scope will generally include the Preparation Phase, and may include the 
Internal Phase, the External Phase, or both, and may include any or all of 
the Other Phases identified.
	</t>
	<t>
The project manager will need to spend some time planning.  It is often 
useful for the sponsor to communicate with stakeholders at this time, to 
explain why IPv6 is important to the enterprise.  Then, as the project manager 
is assessing what systems and elements will be affected, the stakeholders will 
understand why it is important for them to support the effort.  Well-informed 
project participants can help significantly by explaining the relationships 
between components.  For a large enterprise, it may take several iterations 
to really understand the level of effort required; some systems will 
require additional development, some might require software updates, and 
others might need new versions or alternate vendors.  Once the projects are 
understood, the project manager can develop a schedule and a budget, and 
work with the project sponsor to determine what constraints can be 
adjusted, if necessary.
	</t>
	<t>
It is tempting to roll IPv6 projects into other architectural upgrades - this 
can be an excellent way to improve the network and reduce costs.  Project 
participants are advised that by increasing the scope of projects, the 
schedule is often affected.  For instance, a major systems upgrade may take 
a year to complete, where just patching existing systems may take only a 
few months.  Understanding and evaluating these trade-offs are why a 
project manager is important.
	</t>
	<t>
It is very common for assessments to continue in some areas even as 
execution of the project begins in other areas.  This is fine, as long 
as recommendations in other parts of this document are considered, 
especially regarding security (for instance, one should not deploy IPv6 on 
a system before security has been evaluated).  The project manager will 
need to continue monitoring the progress of discrete projects and tasks, 
to be aware of changes in schedule, budget, or scope. "Feature creep"
is common, where engineers or management wish to add other features while 
IPv6 development or deployment is ongoing; each feature will need to 
be individually evaluated for its effect on the schedule and budget, 
and whether expanding the scope increases risk to any other part 
of the project.
	</t>
	<t>
As projects are completed, the project manager will confirm that work 
has been completed, often by means of seeing a completed test plan, 
and will report back to the project sponsor on completed parts of the 
project.  A good project manager will remember to thank the people who 
executed the project.
	</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Tools Assessment">
        <t>
Enterprises will often have a number of operational tools and support 
systems which are used to provision, monitor, manage and diagnose the 
network and systems within their environment.  These tools and systems 
will need to be assessed for compatibility with IPv6 operation.  The 
compatibility may be related to actual addressing and connectivity of 
various devices as well as IPv6 awareness in many of tools and 
processing logic. 
	</t>
	<t>
The tools within the organization fall into two general categories, 
those which focus on managing the network, and those which are focused 
on managing systems and applications on the network.  In either 
instance, the tools will run on platforms which may or may not be 
capable of operating in an IPv6 network.  This lack in functionality 
may be related to Operating system version, or based on some hardware 
constraint.  Those systems which are found to be incapable of utilizing 
a IPv6 connection may need to be replaced or upgraded.
	</t>
	<t>
In addition to devices working on an IPv6 network natively, or via 
a tunnel,  many tools and support systems may require additional updates 
to be IPv6 aware.  This awareness may include the ability to manage 
IPv6  elements and/or applications in addition to the ability to 
store and utilize IPv6 addresses.
	</t>
	<t>
Considerations when assessing the tools and support systems may include 
the fact that IPv6 addresses are significantly larger then IPv4 
requiring datastores to support the increased size.  
Such issues are among those discussed in <xref target="RFC5952"></xref>.
Many organizations 
may also run dual stack networks, therefore the tools need not only 
support IPv6 operation, but may also need to support the monitoring, 
management and intersection with both IPv6 and IPv4 simultaneously.  
It is important to note that  managing IPv6 is not just constrained to 
using large IPv6 addresses, but also that IPv6 interfaces and nodes 
may use two or more addresses as part of normal operation.  Updating  
management systems to deal with these additional nuances will 
likely time time and considerable effort.
	</t>
	<t>
For networking focus systems, like node management systems, it is 
not always necessary to support local IPv6 addressing and connectivity.  
Operation, such as SNMP MIB polling can occur over IPv4 transport 
while seeking responses related to IPv6 information.  Where this may 
seem advantageous to some, it should be noted that without local 
IPv6 connectivity, the management system may not be able to perform 
all expected functions - such as reachability and service checks.
	</t>
	<t>
Organizations should be aware of changes to older IPv4-Only SNMP 
MIB specifications have been made by the IETF related to legacy 
operation in <xref target="RFC2096"></xref> and 
<xref target="RFC2011"></xref>.  Updated 
specifications are now available in 
<xref target="RFC4296"></xref> and <xref target="RFC4293"></xref>
which 
modified the older MIB framework to be IP protocol agnostic supporting 
IPv4 and IPv6.  Polling systems will need to be upgraded to support 
these updates as well as the end stations which are polled.
	</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="External Phase">
      <t>
The external phase for Enterprise IPv6 adoption covers topics which 
deal with how an organization connects their infrastructure to the 
external world.  These external connections may be toward the 
Internet at larges, or other networks.  The external phase covers 
connectivity, security, monitoring of various elements and outward 
facing or accessible services.
	</t>
	<t>
How an organization connects to the outside worlds is very important 
as it is often a critical part of how a business functions, 
therefore must be dealt accordingly.
	</t>

      <section title="Connectivity">
        <t>
The Enterprise will need to work with one or more Service Providers to 
gain connectivity to the Internet or transport service infrastructure 
such as a BGP/MPLS IP VPN as described in 
<xref target="RFC4364"></xref> and <xref target="RFC4659"></xref>.  
On significant factor guiding how an organization may need to communist 
with the outside world will involve the use of PI (Provider Independent) 
and/or PA (Provider Aggregatable) IPv6 space.
	</t>
	<t>
In the case of PI, the organization will need to support BGP based 
connectivity for the most part since the address space is assigned 
direction from the Regional Registry to the local network.  In this 
case, the local network would act as an Autonomous System on the 
Internet and must advertise routes accordingly.   PA space is 
delegated form the upstream service provider and can then be assigned 
to the local network.   If PA space is used, other forms of route 
exchange may be possible such as RIPng, OSPFv3 and static.  PA 
assigned space would normally be routed to the general Internet via 
the upstream providers infrastructure lightening the burden on the 
local network administrations.
	</t>
	<t>
PI and PA space have additional contrasting behaviours when use 
such as how dual homing may work.  Should an operator choose to 
dual home, PI space would be routed to both upstream providers and 
then passed on to other networks.  Utilizing more then one upstream 
Service Provider may introduce challenges since traffic utilizing a 
given PA assign block would be expected to flow tears the assigning 
provider for entry to the Internet.  Should traffic flow using 
sources addresses which are not delegated form a given provider, 
reverse path forwarding rules on the operator side may reject some 
traffic.  These considerations are quite different then those of 
IPv4 which relied on NAT in most cases.
	</t>
	<t>
When seeking IPv6 connectivity to a Service Provider, the Enterprise 
will want to attempt to use Native IPv6 connectivity.  Native IPv6 
connectivity is preferred since it provides the most rebuts form 
of connectivity.  If Native IPv6 connectivity is not possible due to 
technical or business limitations, the Enterprise may utilize readily 
available tunnelled IPv6 connectivity.  There are IPv6 transit 
providers which provide tunnelled IPv6 connectivity which can operate 
over IPv4 networks.  A Enterprise need not need to wait for their 
local Service Provider to support IPv6, as tunnelled connectivity 
can be used.
	</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Security">
	<t>
The most important part of security for external IPv6 deployment is 
filtering. Filtering can be done by stateless ACL or stateful firewall. 
As described in section 2.4.3, the security policies must be congruent 
for IPv4 and IPv6 except that ICMPv6 messages must be allowed through 
and to the filtering device (see <xref target="RFC4890"></xref>):
	</t>
	<t>
<list style="symbols">
<t>unreachable packet-too-big</t>
<t>unreachable parameter-problem</t>
<t>neighbor solicitation </t>
<t>neighbor advertisement</t>
</list>
	</t>
	<t>
** Add some comment about setting MTU to 1280 to avoid tunnel pMTUd
black holes? **
	</t>
	<t>
It could also be safer to block all fragments where the transport layer
header is not in the first fragment to avoid attack as described in 
<xref target="RFC5722"></xref>. 
Some filtering devices allow this filtering. To be fully compliant with 
<xref target="RFC5095"></xref>, it 
can be useful to drop all packet containing the routing extension header 
type 0.
	</t>
	<t>
If Intrusion Prevention Systems (IPS) are used for IPv4 traffic, then 
the same IPS should also be used for IPv6 traffic. This is just a 
generalization of the dual-stack deployment: do for IPv6 what you do 
for IPv4. This also include all email content protection (anti-spam, 
content filtering, data leakage prevention, etc).
	</t>
	<t>
The peering router must also implement anti-spoofing technique based on 
<xref target="RFC2827"></xref>.
	</t>
	<t>
In order to protect the networking device, it is advised to implement 
control plane policing as per <xref target="RFC6192"></xref>.
	</t>
	<t>
The NDP cache exhaustion (see 
<xref target="I-D.gashinsky-v6ops-v6nd-problems"></xref>)
attack can be mitigated by two techniques:
	</t>
<t>
<list style="symbols">
<t> good NDP implementation with memory utilization limits as well 
as rate-limiters and prioritization of requests.</t>
<t> else, as the external deployment usually involves just a 
couple of exposed IPv6 statically configured addresses (virtual address 
of web, email servers, DNS server), then it is straightforward to 
build an ingress ACL allowing traffic for those addresses and denying 
traffic to any other addresses. This actually prevents the attack as 
packet for random destination will be dropped and will never trigger 
a neighbor resolution.</t>
	</list>
</t>

      </section>

      <section title="Monitoring">
        <t>
Monitoring the use of the Internet connectivity should be done for 
IPv6 if it is done for IPv4. This includes the use of IP flow export 
<xref target="RFC5102"></xref> to detect 
abnormal traffic pattern (such as port scanning, SYN-flooding) and 
SNMP MIB <xref target="RFC4293"></xref> 
(another way to detect abnormal bandwidth utilization).
	</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Servers and Applications">
        <t></t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Internal Phase">

        <t>
This phase deals with the delivery of IPv6 to the internal user facing
side of the IT infrastructure, which comprises of various components such
as network devices (routers, switches, etc.), end user devices and
peripherals (workstations, printers, etc.), and internal corporate systems.
        </t>
        <t>
An important design paradigm to consider during this phase is "Dual Stack
when you can, tunnel when you must". Dual stacking allows you to build
a more robust IPv6 network that is of production quality as opposed to
tunnels that are harder to troubleshoot and support. Tunnels however do
provide operators with a quick and easy way to play with IPv6 and gain
some operational experience with the protocol.
<xref target="RFC4213"></xref> describes various
transition mechanisms in more detail.
        </t>

      <section title="Network Infrastructure">

        <t>
The typical enterprise network infrastructure comprises of a combination
of the following network elements - wired access switches, wireless access
points, and routers. Although, it is fairly common to find hardware that
collapses switching and routing functionality into a single device. Basic
wired access switches and access points that operate only at the physical
and link layer, don't really have any special IPv6 considerations other
than being able to support IPv6 addresses themselves for management
purposes, if the same exists for IPv4. In many instances, these devices
possess a lot more intelligence than simply switching packets. For example,
some of these devices help assist with link layer security by incorporating
features such as ARP inspection and DHCP Snooping.
        </t>
        <t>
An important design choice to be made is what IGP to use inside the network.
A variety of IGPs (IS-IS, OSPFv3 and RIPng) support IPv6 today and picking
one over the other is purely a design choice that will be dictated mostly
by existing operational policies in an enterprise network. As mentioned
earlier, it would be beneficial to maintain operational parity between IPv4
and IPv6 and therefore it might make sense to continue using the same
protocol family that is being used for IPv4. For example, if you use OSPFv2
for IPv4, it might make sense to use OSPFv3 now.
        </t>
        <t>
Another important consideration in enterprise networks is first hop
router redundancy. This directly ties into network reachability from
an end host's point of view. IPv6 Neighbor Discovery (ND),
<xref target="RFC4861"></xref>, provides a node with the capability to
maintain a list of available routers on the link, in order to be
able to switch to a backup path should the primary be unreachable.
By default, ND will detect a router failure in 38 seconds and cycle onto
the next default router listed in its cache. While this feature does provide
with a basic level of first hop router redundancy, most enterprise IPv4
networks are designed to fail over much faster. Although this delay can
be improved by adjusting the default timers, care must be taken to
protect against transient failures and to account for increased traffic
on the link. Another option to provide robust first hop redundancy is to
use the Virtual Router Redundancy Protocol for IPv6 (VRRPv3),
<xref target="RFC5798"></xref>. This protocol provides a much faster
switchover to an alternate default router than default ND parameters.
Using VRRP, a backup router can take over for a failed default router
in around three seconds (using VRRP default parameters). This is done
without any interaction with the hosts and a minimum amount of
VRRP traffic.
        </t>
        <t>
Last but not the least, one of the most important design choices
to make while deploying IPv6 on the internal network is whether to use
Stateless Automatic Address Configuration (SLAAC),
<xref target="RFC4862"></xref>, or Dynamic Host Configuration Protocol
for IPv6 (DHCPv6), <xref target="RFC3315"></xref>, or a combination
thereof (possible when using a /64 subnet). Each option has its
own unique set of pros and cons and the choice will ultimately depend
on the operational policies that guide each enterprise's network
design. For example, if an enterprise is looking for ease of use, rapid
deployments, and less administrative overhead, then SLAAC makes more
sense. However, if the operational policies call for precise control
over IP address assignment for auditing then DHCPv6 would be the way
to go. DHCPv6 also allows you tie into DNS systems for host entry
updates and gives you the ability to send other options information to
clients. In the long term, DHCPv6 makes most sense for use in a
managed environment.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section title="End user devices">

        <t>
Most operating systems (OS) that are loaded on workstations and
laptops in a typical enterprise support IPv6 today. However, there
are various out-of-the-box nuances that one should be mindful about.
For example, the default behavior of OSes vary, some may have IPv6
turned off entirely by default, some may only have certain features
such as privacy addresses turned off while others have IPv6 fully
enabled. It is important to note that most operating systems will, by
default, prefer to use native IPv6 over IPv4 when enabled. Therefore,
it is advised that enterprises investigate the default behavior of
their installed OS base and account for it during the implementation
of IPv6. Furthermore, some OSes may have tunneling mechanisms turned on
by default and in such cases, it is recommended to administratively
shut down such interfaces unless required. It is recommended that IPv6
be deployed at the network infrastructure level before it is rolled
out to end user devices.
        </t>
        <t>
Smartphones and tablets are poised to become one of the major consumers
of IP addresses and enterprises should be ready to deploy and support
IPv6 on various networks that serve such devices. In general, support
for IPv6 in these devices, albeit in its infancy, has been steadily
rising. Most of the leading smartphone OSes have some level of support
for IPv6. However, the level of configurable options are mostly at
a minimum and are not consistent across all platforms. Also, it is
fairly common to find IPv6 support on the wifi connection alone and
not on the radio interface in these devices. This is sometimes due to
the radio network not being ready or device related. An IPv6 enabled
enterprise wifi network will allow the majority of these devices to
connect via IPv6. Much work is still being done to bring the full IPv6
feature set across all interfaces (802.11, 3G, LTE, etc.) and platforms.
        </t>
        <t>
IPv6 support in peripheral equipment such as printers, IP Cameras,
etc. has been steadily rising as well, although at a much slower pace
than traditional OSes and Smartphones. Most newer devices are coming
out with IPv6 support but there is still a large installed base of
legacy peripheral devices that might need IPv4 for sometime to come.
The audit phase mentioned earlier will make it easier for enterprises
to plan for equipment upgrades, in line with their corporate equipment
refresh cycle.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section title="Corporate Systems">
        <t>
No IPv6 deployment will be successful without ensuring that all the
corporate systems that enterprise uses as part of their IT
infrastructure, support IPv6. Examples of such systems include, but
are not limited to, Email, Video Conferencing, Telephony (VoIP), DNS,
Radius, etc. All these systems must have their own detailed IPv6
rollout plan in conjunction with the network IPv6 rollout. It is
important to note that DNS is one of the main anchors in an enterprise
deployment, since most end hosts decide whether or not use IPv6 based
on the presence of AAAA records in a reply to a DNS query. It is
recommended that system administrators selectively turn on AAAA records
for various systems as and when they are IPv6 enabled. Additionally,
all monitoring and reporting tools across the enterprise would need
to be modified to support IPv6.
        </t>
      </section>

<section title="Security">
        <t>
IPv6 must be deployed in a secure way. This means that all existing
IPv4 security policies must be extended to support IPv6; IPv6 security
policies will be the IPv6 equivalent of the existing IPv4 ones (taking
into account the difference for <xref target="RFC4890">ICMPv6</xref>).
As in IPv4, security policies for IPv6 will be enforced by firewalls,
ACL, IPS, VPN, ...
	</t>
	<t>
<xref target="RFC4941">Privacy extension addresses</xref> pose a
real challenge for audit trail. Therefore, it is recommended not to
use them within the enterprise network by using the configuration
described previously.
	</t>
	<t>
But, the biggest problem is probably linked to all threats against
Neighbor Discovery. This means that the internal network at the access
layer (i.e. where hosts connect to the network over wired or wireless)
must implement <xref target="RFC6105">RA-guard</xref> and the
techniques being specified by <xref
target="I-D.ietf-savi-threat-scope">SAVI WG</xref>.</t>

      </section>


    </section>

    <section title="Other Phases">
      <t>
	To be added.
	</t>

      <section title="Guest network">
        <t>
	To be added.
	</t>
      </section>

      <section title="IPv6-only">

        <t>
Although IPv4 and IPv6 networks will coexist for a long time to
come, the long term enterprise network roadmap should include steps
on gradually deprecating IPv4 from the dual-stack network. In
some extreme cases, deploying dual-stack networks may not even be
a viable option for very large enterprises due to lack of
availability of RFC 1918 addresses. In such cases, deploying
IPv6-only networks might be the only choice available to sustain
network growth.
        </t>
        <t>
If nodes in the network don't need to talk to an IPv4-only node,
then deploying IPv6-only networks should fe fairly trivial.
However, in the current environment, given that IPv4 is the
dominant protocol on the Internet, an IPv6-only node most likely
needs to talk to an IPv4-only node on the Internet. It is
therefore important to provide such nodes with a translation
mechanism to ensure communication between nodes configured with
different address families. As <xref target="RFC6144"></xref>
points out, it is important to look at address translation as a
transition strategy that will get you to an IPv6-only network.
        </t>
        <t>
There are various stateless and stateful IPv4/IPv6 translation
methods available today that help IPv4 to IPv6 communication.
RFC 6144 provides a framework for IPv4/IPv6 translation and
describes in detail various scenarios in which such translation
mechanisms could be used. <xref target="RFC6145"></xref>
describes stateless address translation. In this mode, a specific
IPv6 address range will represent IPv4 systems (IPv4-converted
addresses), and the IPv6 systems have addresses (IPv4-translateable
addresses) that can be algorithmically mapped to a subset of the
service provider's IPv4 addresses. <xref target="RFC6146"></xref>,
NAT64, describes stateful address translation. As the name
suggests, the translation state is maintained between IPv4
address/port pairs and IPv6 address/port pairs, enabling IPv6
systems to open sessions with IPv4 systems.
<xref target="RFC6147"></xref>, DNS64, describes a mechanism for
synthesizing AAAA resource records (RRs) from A RRs. Together,
RFCs 6146 and RFC 6147 provide a viable method for an IPv6-only
client to initiate communications to an IPv4-only server.
        </t>
        <t>
The address translation mechanisms for the stateless and stateful
translations are defined in <xref target="RFC6052"></xref>. It is
important to note that both of these mechanisms have limitations
as to which protocols they support. For example, RFC 6146 only
defines how stateful NAT64 translates unicast packets carrying TCP,
UDP, and ICMP traffic only. The ultimate choice of which translation
mechanism to chose will be dictated mostly by existing operational
policies pertaining to application support, logging requirements, etc.
        </t>
        <t>
There is additional work being done in the area of address
translation to enhance and/or optimize current mechanisms. For
example, <xref target="I-D.xli-behave-divi"></xref>
describes limitations with the current
stateless translation, such as IPv4 address sharing and application
layer gateway (ALG) problems, and presents the concept and
implementation of dual-stateless IPv4/IPv6 translation (dIVI)
to address those issues.
        </t>

      </section>


    </section>

    <section title="Considerations For Specific Enterprises">
      <t></t>

      <section title="Content Delivery Networks">
        <t>
	To be added.
	</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Data Centre Virtualisation">
        <t>
	To be added.
	</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Campus Networks">
        <t>
	A number of campus networks have made some initial IPv6 deployment.
	There are generally three areas in which such deployments may
	be made, which correspond to the Internal Phase, External Phase
	and Other Phase (Guest Network) descrobed above.
	</t>
	<t>
	In particular the areas commonly approached are:
	</t>
        <t><list style="symbols">
	<t>External-facing services. Typically the campus web presence
	and commonly also external-facing DNS and MX services.</t>
	<t>Computer science department. This is where IPv6-related
	research and/or teaching is most likely to occur, so enabling
	some or all of the campus compauter science department network
	is a sensible first step.</t>
	<t>The eduroam wireless network. Eduroam is the defacto
	wireless roaming system for academic networks, and uses 802.1X
	based authentication, which is agnotic to the IP version used
	(unlike web-redirection gateway systems).  </t>
	</list>
	</t>
      </section>

    </section>

    <section title="Security Considerations">
      <t></t>
    </section>

    <section title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>There are no IANA considerations or implications that arise from this
      document.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <!--  *****BACK MATTER ***** -->

  <back>
    <references title="Informative References">


	&rfc1918;
	&rfc2011;
	&rfc2096;
	&rfc2827;
        &rfc3315;
        &rfc3971;
        &rfc3972;
        &rfc4057;
        &rfc4193;
        &rfc4213;
	&rfc4293;
	&rfc4296;
	&rfc4364;
	&rfc4443;
	&rfc4659;
        &rfc4861;
        &rfc4862;
	&rfc4890;
	&rfc4941;
	&rfc5095;
	&rfc5102;
	&rfc5157;
        &rfc5211;
        &rfc5375;
	&rfc5722;
        &rfc5798;
	&rfc5952;
        &rfc6052;
	&rfc6104;
	&rfc6105;
        &rfc6144;
        &rfc6145;
        &rfc6146;
        &rfc6147;
	&rfc6192;
        &rfc6302;
        &rfc6434;

        &I-D.xli-behave-divi;
        &I-D.gashinsky-v6ops-v6nd-problems;
	&I-D.ietf-savi-threat-scope;

    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
