<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<rfc category="std" docName="draft-ietf-mpls-gach-adv-08" ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="MPLS G-ACh Advertisement Protocol">MPLS Generic Associated
    Channel (G-ACh) Advertisement Protocol</title>

    <author fullname="Dan Frost" initials="D" surname="Frost">
      <organization>Cisco Systems</organization>

      <address>
        <email>danfrost@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Stewart Bryant" initials="S" surname="Bryant">
      <organization>Cisco Systems</organization>

      <address>
        <email>stbryant@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Matthew Bocci" initials="M" surname="Bocci">
      <organization>Alcatel-Lucent</organization>

      <address>
        <email>matthew.bocci@alcatel-lucent.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date year="2013" />

    <area>Routing</area>

    <workgroup>MPLS</workgroup>

    <keyword>MPLS</keyword>

    <keyword>Internet-Draft</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>The MPLS Generic Associated Channel (G-ACh) provides an auxiliary
      logical data channel associated with a Label Switched Path (LSP), a
      pseudowire, or a section (link) over which a variety of protocols may
      flow. These protocols are commonly used to provide Operations,
      Administration, and Maintenance (OAM) mechanisms associated with the
      primary data channel. This document specifies simple procedures by which
      an endpoint of an LSP, pseudowire, or section may inform the other
      endpoints of its capabilities and configuration parameters, or other
      application-specific information. This information may then be used by
      the receiver to validate or adjust its local configuration, and by the
      network operator for diagnostic purposes.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>The MPLS Generic Associated Channel (G-ACh) is defined and described
      in <xref target="RFC5586"></xref>. It provides an auxiliary logical data
      channel over which a variety of protocols may flow. Each such data
      channel is associated with an MPLS Label Switched Path (LSP), a
      pseudowire, or a section (link). An important use of the G-ACh and the
      protocols it supports is to provide Operations, Administration, and
      Maintenance (OAM) <xref target="RFC6291"></xref> capabilities for the
      associated LSP, pseudowire, or section. Examples of such capabilities
      include Pseudowire Virtual Circuit Connectivity Verification (VCCV)
      <xref target="RFC5085"></xref>, Bidirectional Forwarding Detection (BFD)
      for MPLS <xref target="RFC5884"></xref>, and MPLS packet loss, delay,
      and throughput measurement <xref target="RFC6374"></xref>, as well as
      OAM functions developed for the MPLS Transport Profile (MPLS-TP) <xref
      target="RFC5921"></xref>.</t>

      <t>This document specifies procedures for an MPLS Label Switching Router
      (LSR) to advertise its capabilities and configuration parameters, or
      other application-specific information, to its peers over LSPs,
      pseudowires, and sections. Receivers can then make use of this
      information to validate or adjust their own configurations, and network
      operators can make use of it to diagnose faults and configuration
      inconsistencies between endpoints. Note in this document, an
      "application" refers an application of G-ACh, and should not be confused
      with an end-user application.</t>

      <t>The main principle guiding the design of the MPLS G-ACh Advertisement
      Protocol (GAP) is simplicity. The protocol provides a one-way method of
      distributing information about the sender. How this information is used
      by a given receiver is a local matter. The data elements distributed by
      the GAP are application-specific and, except for those associated with
      the GAP itself, are outside the scope of this document. An IANA registry
      is created to allow GAP applications to be defined as needed.</t>

      <t>Note that assigning application identifiers and associated parameters
      for protocols other than the GAP itself is out of scope for this
      document, and will need to be done in subsequent documents, using the
      IANA considerations specified here.</t>

      <section title="Motivation">
        <t>It is frequently useful in a network for a node to have general
        information about its adjacent nodes, i.e., those nodes to which it
        has links. At a minimum this allows a human operator or management
        application with access to the node to determine which adjacent nodes
        this node can see, which is helpful when troubleshooting connectivity
        problems. A typical example of an "adjacency awareness protocol" is
        the Link Layer Discovery Protocol <xref target="LLDP"></xref>, which
        can provide various pieces of information about adjacent nodes in
        Ethernet networks, such as system name, basic functional capabilities,
        link speed/duplex settings, and maximum supported frame size. Such
        data is useful both for human diagnostics and for automated detection
        of configuration inconsistencies.</t>

        <t>In MPLS networks, the G-ACh provides a convenient
        link-layer-agnostic means for communication between LSRs that are
        adjacent at the link layer. The G-ACh advertisement protocol presented
        in this document thus allows LSRs to exchange information of a similar
        sort to that supported by LLDP for Ethernet links. The GAP, however,
        does not depend on the specific link-layer protocol in use, and can be
        used to advertise information on behalf of any MPLS application.</t>

        <t>In networks based on the MPLS Transport Profile (MPLS-TP) <xref
        target="RFC5921"></xref> that do not also support IP, the normal
        protocols used to determine the Ethernet address of an adjacent MPLS
        node, such as the Address Resolution Protocol <xref
        target="RFC0826"></xref> and IP version 6 Neighbor Discovery <xref
        target="RFC4861"></xref>, are not available. One possible use of the
        G-ACh advertisement protocol is to discover the Ethernet media access
        control addresses of MPLS-TP nodes lacking IP capability <xref
        target="I-D.ietf-mpls-tp-ethernet-addressing"></xref>. However, where
        it is anticipated that the only data that needs to be exchanged
        between LSRs over an Ethernet link are their Ethernet addresses, then
        the operator may instead choose to use LLDP for that purpose.</t>

        <t>The applicability of the G-ACh advertisement protocol is not
        limited to link-layer adjacency, either in terms of message
        distribution or message content. The G-ACh exists for any MPLS LSP or
        pseudowire, so GAP messages can be exchanged with remote LSP or
        pseudowire endpoints. The content of GAP messages is extensible in a
        simple manner, and can include any kind of information that might be
        useful to MPLS LSRs connected by links, LSPs, or pseudowires. For
        example, in networks that rely on the G-ACh for OAM functions, GAP
        messages might be used to inform adjacent LSRs of a node's OAM
        capabilities and configuration parameters.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Terminology">
        <texttable align="left" style="headers">
          <ttcol>Term</ttcol>

          <ttcol>Definition</ttcol>

          <c>G-ACh</c>

          <c>Generic Associated Channel</c>

          <c>GAL</c>

          <c>G-ACh Label</c>

          <c>GAP</c>

          <c>G-ACh Advertisement Protocol</c>

          <c>LSP</c>

          <c>Label Switched Path</c>

          <c>OAM</c>

          <c>Operations, Administration, and Maintenance</c>
        </texttable>
      </section>

      <section title="Requirements Language">
        <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
        "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
        document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
        target="RFC2119"></xref>.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Overview">
      <t>The G-ACh Advertisement Protocol has a simple one-way mode of
      operation: a device configured to send information for a particular data
      channel (MPLS LSP, pseudowire, or section) transmits GAP messages over
      the G-ACh associated with the data channel. The payload of a GAP message
      is a collection of Type-Length-Value (TLV) objects, organized on a
      per-application basis. An IANA registry is created to identify specific
      applications. Application TLV objects primarily contain static data that
      the receiver is meant to retain for a period of time, but may also
      represent metadata or special processing instructions.</t>

      <t>Each GAP message can contain data for several applications. A sender
      may transmit a targeted update that refreshes the data for a subset of
      applications without affecting the data of other applications sent on a
      previous message. GAP messages are processed in the order in which they
      are received.</t>

      <t>For example, a GAP message might be sent containing the following
      data: <list style="empty">
          <t>Application A: A-TLV4, A-TLV15, A-TLV9</t>

          <t>Application B: B-TLV1, B-TLV3</t>

          <t>Application C: C-TLV6,</t>
        </list> where the TLVx refers to an example GAP TLV.</t>

      <t>A second message might then be sent containing: <list style="empty">
          <t>Application B: B-TLV7, B-TLV3</t>
        </list>Upon receiving the second message, the receiver retains B-TLV1
      from the first message and adds B-TLV7 to its B-database. How it handles
      the new B-TLV3 depends on the rules B has specified for this object
      type; this object could replace the old one or be combined with it in
      some way. The second message has no effect on the databases maintained
      by the receiver for Applications A and C.</t>

      <t>The rate at which GAP messages are transmitted is at the discretion
      of the sender, and may fluctuate over time as well as differ per
      application. Each message contains, for each application it describes, a
      lifetime that informs the receiver how long to wait before discarding
      the data for that application.</t>

      <t>The GAP itself provides no fragmentation and reassembly mechanisms.
      In the event that an application wishes to send larger chunks of data
      via GAP messages than fall within the limits of packet size, it is the
      responsibility of the application to fragment its data accordingly. It
      is the responsibility of the application and the network operator to
      ensure that the use of the GAP protocol does not congest the link to the
      peer.</t>

      <t>The GAP is designed to run over a unidirectional channel. However,
      where the channel is bidirectional, communication may be optimized
      through the use of a number of messages defined for transmission from
      the receiver back to the sender. These are optimizations and are not
      required for protocol operation.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Secmf" title="Message Format">
      <t>An Associated Channel Header (ACH) Channel Type has been allocated
      for the GAP as follows:</t>

      <texttable align="left" style="headers">
        <ttcol width="50%">Protocol</ttcol>

        <ttcol>Channel Type</ttcol>

        <c>G-ACh Advertisement Protocol</c>

        <c>0xXXXX (TBD by IANA)</c>
      </texttable>

      <t>For this Channel Type, as noted in <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-mpls-retire-ach-tlv"></xref> the ACH SHALL NOT be
      followed by the ACH TLV Header defined in<xref
      target="RFC5586"></xref>.</t>

      <t>Fields in this document shown as Reserved or Resv are reserved for
      future specification and MUST be set to zero. All integer values for
      fields defined in this document SHALL be encoded in network byte
      order.</t>

      <t>A GAP message consists of a fixed header followed by a GAP payload.
      The payload of a GAP message is an Application Data Block (ADB)
      consisting of one or more block elements. Each block element contains an
      application identifier, a lifetime, and a series of zero or more TLV
      objects for the application it describes.</t>

      <t>Malformed GAP messages MUST be discarded by the receiver, although an
      error MAY be logged. If the error is logged remotely, a suitable form of
      rate limiting SHOULD be used to prevent excessive logging messages being
      transmitted over the network.</t>

      <t>Implementations of this protocol version MUST set reserved fields in
      the message formats that follow, to all zero bits when sending and
      ignore any value when receiving messages.</t>

      <section title="GAP Message Format">
        <t>The following figure shows the format of a G-ACh Advertisement
        Protocol message, which follows the Associated Channel Header
        (ACH):</t>

        <figure anchor="Fig1" title="GAP Message Format">
          <artwork><![CDATA[
     0                   1                   2                   3
     0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
    |Version|       Reserved        |        Message Length         |
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
    |                        Message Identifier                     |
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
    |                           Timestamp                           |
    |                                                               |
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
    ~                    Application Data Block (ADB)               ~
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
          ]]></artwork>
        </figure>

        <t>The meanings of the fields are: <list style="empty">
            <t>Version (4 bits): Protocol version. This is set to zero.</t>

            <t>Reserved (12 bits): MUST be sent as zero.</t>

            <t>Message Length (16 bits): Size in octets of this message, i.e.
            of the portion of the packet following the Associated Channel
            Header</t>

            <t>Message Identifier (MI) (32 bits): Unique identifier of this
            message. For disambiguation, a sender MUST NOT re-use an MI over a
            given channel until it is confident that all ADBs associated with
            have been expired by the receiver. The sole purpose of this field
            is duplicate detection in the event of a message burst (<xref
            target="Txop"></xref>).</t>

            <t>Timestamp: 64-bit Network Time Protocol (NTP) transmit
            timestamp, as specified in Section 6 of <xref
            target="RFC5905"></xref>.</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>

      <section title="Applications Data Block">
        <t>An ADB consists of one or more elements of the following
        format:</t>

        <figure anchor="Fig2" title="Application Data Block Element">
          <artwork><![CDATA[





     0                   1                   2                   3
     0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
    |        Application ID         |        Element Length         |
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
    |            Lifetime           |           Reserved            |
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
    ~                          TLV Object                           ~
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
    ~                          TLV Object                           ~
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
    .                                                               .
    .                                                               .
    .                                                               .
          ]]></artwork>
        </figure>

        <t><list style="empty">
            <t>Application ID (16 bits) : Identifies the application this
            element describes; an IANA registry has been created to track the
            values for this field. More than one block element with the same
            Application ID may be present in the same ADB, and block elements
            with different Application IDs may also be present in the same
            ADB. The protocol rules for the mechanism, including what ADB
            elements are present and which TLVs are contained in an ADB
            element, are to be defined in the document that specifies the
            application-specific usage.</t>

            <t>Element Length (16 bits): Specifies the total length in octets
            of this block element (including the Application ID and Element
            Length fields).</t>

            <t>Lifetime field (16 bits): Specifies how long, in seconds, the
            receiver should retain the data in this message (i.e. it specifies
            the lifetime of the static data carried in the TLV set of this
            ADB). For TLVs not carrying static data, the Lifetime is no
            significance. The sender of a GAP message indicates this by
            setting the Lifetime field to zero. If the Lifetime is zero, TLVs
            in this ADB are processed by the receiver and the data associated
            with these TLV types is immediately marked as expired. If the ADB
            contains no TLVs, the receiver expires all data associated TLVs
            previously sent to this application. </t>
          </list></t>

        <t>The remainder of the Application Data Block element consists of a
        sequence of zero or more TLV objects which use the format defined in
        <xref target="TLVOF"></xref>.</t>

        <t>The scope of an ADB is an application instance attached to a
        specific channel between a specific source-destination pair, and the
        lifetime field specifies the lifetime of the associated ADB in that
        specific context.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="TLVOF" title="TLV Object Format">
        <t>GAP TLV objects use the following format:</t>

        <figure anchor="Fig3" title="TLV Object Format">
          <artwork><![CDATA[
     0                   1                   2                   3
     0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
    |      Type     |    Reserved   |            Length             |
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
    ~                             Value                             ~
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
          ]]></artwork>
        </figure>

        <t><list style="empty">
            <t>Type (8 bits): Identifies the TLV Object and is scoped to a
            specific application; each application creates an IANA registry to
            track its Type values.</t>

            <t>Reserved (8 bits): MUST be sent as zero.</t>

            <t>Length (16 bits): The length in octets of the value field. The
            value field need not be padded to provide alignment.</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>GAP messages do not contain a checksum. If validation of message
        integrity is desired, the authentication procedures in <xref
        target="auth"></xref> should be used.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="G-ACh Advertisement Protocol TLVs">
      <t>The GAP supports several TLV objects related to its own operation via
      the Application ID 0x0000. These objects represent metadata and
      processing instructions rather than static data that is meant to be
      retained. When an ADB element for the GAP is present in a GAP message,
      it MUST precede other elements. This is particularly important in the
      case for the correct operation of the flush message.</t>

      <t>Any application using the GAP inherits the ability to use facilities
      provide by Application 0x0000.</t>

      <t>Application 0x0000 GAP messages MUST be processed in the order in
      which they are received. </t>

      <section anchor="sa-tlv" title="Source Address TLV">
        <t>The Source Address object identifies the sending device and
        possibly the transmitting interface and the channel; it has the
        following format:</t>

        <figure anchor="Fig4" title="Source Address TLV Format">
          <artwork><![CDATA[





     0                   1                   2                   3
     0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
    |     Type=0    |    Reserved   |            Length             |
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
    |      Reserved (16 bits)       |    Address Family (16 bits)   |
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
    ~                            Address                            ~
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
          ]]></artwork>
        </figure>

        <t>The Address Family field indicates the type of the address; it
        SHALL be set to one of the assigned values in the IANA "Address Family
        Numbers" registry.</t>

        <t>In IP networks a Source Address SHOULD be included in GAP messages
        and set to an IP address of the sending device; when the channel is a
        link, this address SHOULD be an address of the transmitting
        interface.</t>

        <t>In non-IP MPLS-TP networks a Source Address SHOULD be included in
        GAP messages and set to the endpoint identifier of the channel. The
        formats of these channel identifiers SHALL be as given in Sections
        3.5.1, 3.5.2, and 3.5.3 of <xref target="RFC6428"></xref> (excluding
        the initial Type and Length fields shown in those sections). IANA has
        allocated Address Family Numbers for these identifiers; see <xref
        target="id-afn"></xref>.</t>

        <t>On multipoint channels a Source Address TLV is REQUIRED.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="GAP Request TLV">
        <t>This object is a request by the sender for the receiver to transmit
        an immediate unicast GAP update to the sender. If the Length field is
        zero, this signifies that an update for all applications is requested.
        Otherwise, the value field specifies the applications for which an
        update is requested, in the form of a sequence of Application IDs:</t>

        <figure anchor="Fig5" title="GAP Request TLV Format">
          <artwork><![CDATA[









     0                   1                   2                   3
     0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
    |     Type=1    |    Reserved   |            Length             |
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
    |        Application ID 1       |        Application ID 2       |
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
    .                                                               .
    .                                                               .
    .                                                               .
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
    |        Application ID N-1     |        Application ID N       |
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
          ]]></artwork>
        </figure>

        <t></t>

        <t>The intent of this TLV is to request the immediate transmission of
        data following a local event such as a restart rather than waiting for
        a periodic update. Applications need to determine what information is
        meaningful to send in response to such a request. The inclusion of an
        Application IDs in a Request TLV does not guarantee that the response
        will provide information for that application. The responder may also
        include information for applications not included in the request. A
        receiver SHOULD discard GAP Request messages that arrive at a rate in
        excess of that which is considered reasonable for the application.</t>

        <t>For an application 0x0000 GAP Request it is meaningful to respond
        with the Source Address.</t>

        <t>This TLV is considered to be part of the GAP protocol and thus does
        not need to be retained. The reception of the TLV may however be
        recorded for management purposes.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="GAP Flush TLV">
        <t>This object is an instruction to the receiver to flush the GAP data
        for all applications associated with this (sender, channel) pair. It
        is a null object, i.e. its Length is set to zero.</t>

        <t>The GAP Flush instruction does not apply to data contained in the
        message carrying the GAP Flush TLV object itself. Any application data
        contained in the same message SHALL be processed and retained by the
        receiver as usual.</t>

        <t>The flush TLV type is 2.</t>

        <t>This TLV is considered to be part of the GAP protocol and thus does
        not need to be retained. The reception of the TLV may however be
        recorded for management purposes.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="GAP Suppress TLV">
        <t>This object is a request to the receiver to cease sending GAP
        updates to the transmitter over the current channel for the specified
        duration. Duration is a 16 bit positive integer in units of seconds.
        The receiver MAY accept and act on the request, MAY ignore the
        request, or MAY resume transmissions at any time according to
        implementation or configuration choices, and depending on local
        pragmatics. The format of this object is as follows: <figure
            anchor="Fig6" title="GAP Suppress TLV Format">
            <artwork><![CDATA[
     0                   1                   2                   3
     0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
    |     Type=3    |    Reserved   |            Length             |
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
    |           Duration            |        Application ID 1       |
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
    .                                                               .
    .                                                               .
    .                                                               .
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
    |        Application ID N-1     |        Application ID N       |
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
          ]]></artwork>
          </figure> If the Length is set to 2, i.e. if the list of Application
        IDs is empty, then suppression of all GAP messages is requested;
        otherwise suppression of only those updates pertaining to the listed
        applications is requested. A duration of zero cancels any existing
        suppress requests for the listed applications.</t>

        <t>This object makes sense only for point-to-point channels or when
        the sender is receiving unicast GAP updates.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="GAP Authentication TLV">
        <t>This object is used to provide authentication and integrity
        validation for a GAP message. It has the following format:</t>

        <figure anchor="Fig7" title="GAP Authentication TLV Format">
          <artwork><![CDATA[
     0                   1                   2                   3
     0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
    |     Type=4    |    Reserved   |            Length             |
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
    |          Reserved             |            Key ID             |
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
    ~                    Authentication Data                        ~
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
          ]]></artwork>
        </figure>

        <t>The data and procedures associated with this object are explained
        in <xref target="auth"></xref>.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Operation">
      <section anchor="Txop" title="Message Transmission">
        <t>G-ACh Advertisement Protocol message transmission SHALL operate on
        a per-data-channel basis and be configurable by the operator
        accordingly.</t>

        <t>Because GAP message transmission may be active for many logical
        channels on the same physical interface, message transmission timers
        SHOULD be randomized across the channels supported by a given
        interface so as to reduce the likelihood of large synchronized message
        bursts.</t>

        <t>The Message Identifier (MI) uniquely identifies this message and
        its value is set at the sender's discretion. It MUST NOT be assumed to
        be a sequence number. The scope of an MI is a channel between a
        specific source-destination pair.</t>

        <t>The Timestamp field SHALL be set to the time at which this message
        is transmitted.</t>

        <t>The Lifetime field of each Application Data Block element SHALL be
        set to the number of seconds the receiver is advised to retain the
        data associated with this message and application.</t>

        <t>When the transmitter wishes the data previously sent in an ADB
        element to persist then it must refresh the ADB element by sending
        another update. Refresh times SHOULD be set in such a way that at
        least three updates will be sent prior to Lifetime expiration. For
        example, if the Lifetime is set to 210 seconds, then updates should be
        sent at least once every 60 seconds.</t>

        <t>A sender may signal that previously sent data SHOULD be marked as
        expired by setting the ADB element lifetime to zero as previously
        described in <xref target="Secmf"></xref> .</t>

        <t>In some cases an application may desire additional reliability for
        the delivery of some of its data. When this is the case, the
        transmitter MAY send several (for example three) instances of the
        message in succession, separated by a delay appropriate to, or
        specified by, the application. For example this procedure might be
        invoked when sending a flush instruction following device reset. The
        expectation is that the receiver will detect duplicate messages using
        the MI.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="Secmr" title="Message Reception">
        <t>G-ACh Advertisement Protocol message reception SHALL operate on a
        per-data-channel basis and be configurable by the operator
        accordingly.</t>

        <t>Upon receiving a G-ACh Advertisement Protocol message that contains
        data for some application X, the receiver determines whether it can
        interpret X-data. If it cannot, then the receiver MAY retain this data
        for the number of seconds specified by the Lifetime field; although it
        cannot parse this data, it may still be of use to the operator.</t>

        <t>If the receiver can interpret X-data, then it processes the data
        objects accordingly, retaining the data associated with those that
        represent static data for the number of seconds specified by the
        Lifetime field. If the lifetime is zero, such data is immediately
        marked as expired, and if no TLVs are specified all data associated
        with previously received TLVs is marked as expired <xref
        target="Secmf"></xref>. If one of the received TLV objects has the
        same Type as a previously received TLV then the data from the new
        object SHALL replace the data associated with that Type unless the X
        specification dictates a different behavior.</t>

        <t>The received data is made available to local applications that
        required it and are locally authorized to view it. The method for
        doing this is local to the receiver and outside the scope of this
        document.</t>

        <t>The receiver MAY make use of the application data contained in a
        GAP message to perform some level of auto-configuration, for example
        if the application is an OAM protocol. The application SHOULD,
        however, take care to prevent cases of oscillation resulting from each
        endpoint attempting to adjust its configuration to match the other.
        Any such auto-configuration based on GAP information MUST be disabled
        by default.</t>

        <t>The MI may be used to detect and discard duplicate messages.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="auth" title="Message Authentication">
      <t>The GAP provides a means of authenticating messages and ensuring
      their integrity. This is accomplished by attaching a GAP Authentication
      TLV and including, in the Authentication Data field, the output of a
      cryptographic hash function (known as a Message Authentication Code
      (MAC)), the input to which is the message together with a secret key
      known only to the sender and receiver. Upon receipt of the message, the
      receiver computes the same MAC and compares the result with the MAC in
      the message; if the MACs are not equal, the message is discarded. Use of
      GAP message authentication is RECOMMENDED.</t>

      <t>The remainder of this section gives the details of this procedure,
      which is based on the procedures for generic cryptographic
      authentication for the Intermediate System to Intermediate System
      (IS-IS) routing protocol as described in <xref
      target="RFC5310"></xref>.</t>

      <section title="Authentication Key Identifiers">
        <t>An Authentication Key Identifier (Key ID) is a 16-bit tag shared by
        the sender and receiver that identifies a set of authentication
        parameters. These parameters are not sent over the wire; they are
        assumed to be associated, on each node, with the Key ID by external
        means, such as via explicit operator configuration or a separate
        key-exchange protocol. Multiple Key IDs may be active on the sending
        and receiving nodes simultaneously, in which case the sender locally
        selects a Key ID from this set to use in an outbound message. This
        capability facilitates key migration in the network.</t>

        <t>The parameters associated with a Key ID are: <list style="symbols">
            <t>Authentication Algorithm: This signifies the authentication
            algorithm to use to generate or interpret authentication data. At
            present, the following values MAY supported: HMAC-SHA-1,
            HMAC-SHA-256. HMAC-SHA-1 MUST be supported.</t>

            <t>Authentication Keystring: A secret octet string that forms the
            basis for the cryptographic key used by the Authentication
            Algorithm. It SHOULD NOT be a human memorable string.
            Implementations MUST be able to use random binary values of the
            appropriate length as a keystring.</t>
          </list>Implementors SHOULD consider the use of <xref
        target="I-D.ietf-karp-crypto-key-table"></xref> for key management. If
        used, authenticated information sent over the gap MUST only considered
        valid if it was sent during the KARP interval between
        SendLifetimeStart and SendLifeTimeEnd. However, if the GAP TLV used to
        send it expires before the KARP SendLifetimeStart, then information is
        never used, and if it expires before KARP SendNotAfter, the key
        becomes invalid on expiry of the GAP TLV.</t>

        <t>At the time of this writing, mechanisms for dynamic key management
        in the absence of IP are not available. Key management in such
        environments therefore needs to take place via the equipment
        management system or some other out of band service. The MPLS layer in
        a network is normally isolated from direct access by users and thus is
        a relatively protected environment. Thus key turnover is a relatively
        infrequent event.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Authentication Process">
        <t>The authentication process for GAP messages is straightforward.
        First, a Key ID is associated on both the sending and receiving nodes
        with a set of authentication parameters. Following this, when the
        sender generates a GAP message, it sets the Key ID field of the GAP
        Authentication TLV accordingly. (The length of the Authentication Data
        field is also known at this point, because it is a function of the
        Authentication Algorithm.) The sender then computes a MAC for the
        message as described in <xref target="hash"></xref>, and fills the
        Authentication Data field of the GAP Authentication TLV with the MAC
        overrighting the zeros used in computation. The message is then
        sent.</t>

        <t>When the message is received, the receiver computes a MAC for it as
        described below, again setting the Authentication Data field of the
        GAP Authentication TLV to all zeros before computing the MAC. The
        receiver compares its computed MAC to the MAC received in the
        Authentication Data field. If the two MACs are equal, authentication
        of the message is considered to have succeeded; otherwise it is
        considered to have failed.</t>

        <t>This process suffices to ensure the authenticity and integrity of
        messages, but is still vulnerable to a replay attack, in which a third
        party captures a message and sends it on to the receiver at some later
        time. The GAP message header contains a Timestamp field which can be
        used to protect against replay attacks. To achieve this protection,
        the receiver checks that the time recorded in the timestamp field of a
        received and authenticated GAP message corresponds to the current
        time, within a reasonable tolerance that allows for message
        propagation delay, and accepts or rejects the message accordingly.
        Clock corrections SHOULD be monotonic to avoid replay attack unless
        operator intervention overrides this to achieve a faster convergence
        with current time.</t>

        <t>If the clocks of the sender and receiver are not synchronized with
        one another, then the receiver must perform the replay check against
        its best estimate of the current time according to the sender's clock.
        The timestamps that appear in GAP messages can be used to infer the
        approximate clock offsets of senders and, while this does not yield
        high-precision clock synchronization, it suffices for purposes of the
        replay check with an appropriately chosen tolerance.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="hash" title="MAC Computation">
        <t>The HMAC procedure described in <xref target="RFC2104"></xref> is
        used to compute the MAC.</t>

        <t>The Authentication Data field of the GAP Authentication TLV is set
        to all zeros. The MAC is then computed over the entire GAP message as
        shown in <xref target="Fig1"></xref>.</t>

        <t>Where there is less data than is needed for the MAC computation, a
        value of zero MUST be used.</t>

        <t>The length of the Authentication Data field is always less than or
        equal to the message digest size of the specific hash function that is
        being used, however the implementer needs to consider that although
        this decreases the size of the message, it results in a corresponding
        reduction in the strength of the assurance provided.</t>

        <t>MAC truncation is NOT RECOMMENDED.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Link-Layer Considerations">
      <t>When the GAP is used to support device discovery on a data link, GAP
      messages must be sent in such a way that they can be received by other
      listeners on the link without the sender first knowing the link-layer
      addresses of the listeners. In short, they must be multicast.
      Considerations for multicast MPLS encapsulation are discussed in <xref
      target="RFC5332"></xref>. For example, Section 8 of <xref
      target="RFC5332"></xref> describes how destination Ethernet MAC
      addresses are selected for multicast MPLS packets. Since a GAP packet
      transmitted over a data link contains just one label, the G-ACh Label
      (GAL) with label value 13, the correct destination Ethernet address for
      frames carrying GAP packets intended for device discovery, according to
      these selection procedures, is 01-00-5e-80-00-0d.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Managability Considerations">
      <t>The data sent and received by this protocol MUST be made accessible
      for inspection by network operators, and where local configuration is
      updated by the received information, it MUST be clear why the configured
      value has been changed. This allows the operator to determine the
      operational parameters currently in use and to understand when local
      configuration has been superseded by inbound parameters received from
      its peer. The persistence of data advertised by this protocol is
      applications specific, but in general SHOULD be persistent across
      restarts. To prevent stale information or information from a former peer
      causing incorrect operation, received advertisements MUST be discarded
      across restarts. If the received values change, the new values MUST be
      used and the change made visible to the network operators.</t>

      <t>All applications MUST be disabled by default and need be enabled by
      the operator if required.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Security Considerations">
      <t>G-ACh Advertisement Protocol messages contain information about the
      sending device and its configuration, which is sent in cleartext over
      the wire. If an unauthorized third party gains access to the MPLS data
      plane or the lower network layers between the sender and receiver, it
      can observe this information. In general, however, the information
      contained in GAP messages is no more sensitive than that contained in
      other protocol messages, such as routing updates, which are commonly
      sent in cleartext. No attempt is therefore made to guarantee
      confidentiality of GAP messages. Therefore the GAP MUST NOT be used to
      send TLVs in cleartext where the value concerned requires
      confidentiality, for example, GAP or application TLVs containing 'bare'
      cryptographic keying material. Applications which require
      confidentiality will need to implement a suitable confidentiality
      method.</t>

      <t>A more significant potential threat is the transmission of GAP
      messages by unauthorized sources, or the unauthorized manipulation of
      messages in transit; this can disrupt the information receivers hold
      about legitimate senders. To protect against this threat, message
      authentication procedures are specified in <xref target="auth"></xref>
      of this document that enable receivers to ensure the authenticity and
      integrity of GAP messages. These procedures include the means to protect
      against replay attacks, in which a third party captures a legitimate
      message and "replays" it to a receiver at some later time.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="IANA Considerations">
      <section title="Associated Channel Type Allocation">
        <t>This document requests that IANA allocate an entry in the
        "Pseudowire Associated Channel Types" registry <xref
        target="RFC5586"></xref> (currently located within the "Pseudowire
        Name Spaces (PWE3)" registry) for the "G-ACh Advertisement Protocol",
        as follows:</t>

        <texttable align="left" style="headers">
          <ttcol>Value</ttcol>

          <ttcol>Description</ttcol>

          <ttcol>TLV Follows</ttcol>

          <ttcol>Reference</ttcol>

          <c>XXXX(TBD)</c>

          <c>G-ACh Advertisement Protocol</c>

          <c>No</c>

          <c>(this draft)</c>
        </texttable>

        <t>The reader should note that the "TLV Follows" column in the
        registry is in the process of being deleted <xref
        target="I-D.ietf-mpls-retire-ach-tlv"></xref>.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="id-afn" title="Allocation of Address Family Numbers">
        <t>IANA is requested to allocate three entries from the Standards
        Track range in the "Address Family Numbers" registry for MPLS-TP
        Section, LSP, and Pseudowire endpoint identifiers, per <xref
        target="sa-tlv"></xref>. The allocations are:</t>

        <texttable align="left" style="headers">
          <ttcol>Number</ttcol>

          <ttcol>Description</ttcol>

          <ttcol>Reference</ttcol>

          <c>(TBD)</c>

          <c>MPLS-TP Section Endpoint Identifier</c>

          <c>(this draft)</c>

          <c>(TBD)</c>

          <c>MPLS-TP LSP Endpoint Identifier</c>

          <c>(this draft)</c>

          <c>(TBD)</c>

          <c>MPLS-TP Pseudowire Endpoint Identifier</c>

          <c>(this draft)</c>
        </texttable>
      </section>

      <section title="Creation of G-ACh Advertisement Protocol Application Registry">
        <t>This document requests that IANA create a new registry, "G-ACh
        Advertisement Protocol Applications" in the "Pseudowire Name Spaces
        (PWE3)" registry, with fields and initial allocations as follows:</t>

        <texttable align="left" style="headers">
          <ttcol>Application ID</ttcol>

          <ttcol>Description</ttcol>

          <ttcol>Reference</ttcol>

          <c>0x0000</c>

          <c>G-ACh Advertisement Protocol</c>

          <c>(this draft)</c>
        </texttable>

        <t>The range of the Application ID field is 0x0000 - 0xFFFF.</t>

        <t>The allocation policy for this registry is IETF Review.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Creation of G-ACh Advertisement Protocol TLV Registry">
        <t>This document requests that IANA create a new registry, "G-ACh
        Advertisement Protocol: GAP TLV Objects (Application ID 0)" in the
        "Pseudowire Name Spaces (PWE3)" registry, with fields and initial
        allocations as follows:</t>

        <texttable align="left" style="headers">
          <ttcol>Type Name</ttcol>

          <ttcol>Type ID</ttcol>

          <ttcol>Reference</ttcol>

          <c>Source Address</c>

          <c>0</c>

          <c>(this draft)</c>

          <c>GAP Request</c>

          <c>1</c>

          <c>(this draft)</c>

          <c>GAP Flush</c>

          <c>2</c>

          <c>(this draft)</c>

          <c>GAP Suppress</c>

          <c>3</c>

          <c>(this draft)</c>

          <c>GAP Authentication</c>

          <c>4</c>

          <c>(this draft)</c>
        </texttable>

        <t>The range of the Type ID field is 0 - 255.</t>

        <t>The allocation policy for this registry is IETF Review.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>We thank Adrian Farrel for his valuable review comments on this
      document.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.2119'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.5332'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.5586'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.5905'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6428'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.2104'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-karp-crypto-key-table'?>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-mpls-tp-ethernet-addressing'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.0826'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.4861'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.5085'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.5310'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.5884'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.5921'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6374'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-mpls-retire-ach-tlv'?>

      <reference anchor="LLDP">
        <front>
          <title>Station and Media Access Control Connectivity Discovery
          (802.1AB)</title>

          <author surname="IEEE">
            <organization abbrev="IEEE">IEEE</organization>
          </author>

          <date month="September" year="2009" />
        </front>
      </reference>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6291'?>
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
