<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!-- xml2rfc is available at http://xml.resource.org. -->
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [

  <!ENTITY RFC2119 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
  <!ENTITY RFC2475 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2475.xml">
  <!ENTITY RFC4201 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4201.xml">
  <!ENTITY RFC4206 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4206.xml">
  <!ENTITY RFC5286 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5286.xml">
  <!ENTITY RFC5462 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5462.xml">
  <!ENTITY RFC3209 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3209.xml">
  <!ENTITY RFC5654 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5654.xml">
  <!ENTITY RFC5714 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5714.xml">
  <!ENTITY RFC5920 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5920.xml">
  <!ENTITY RFC5960 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5960.xml">
  <!ENTITY RFC6371 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6371.xml">
  <!ENTITY RFC6374 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6374.xml">
  <!ENTITY RFC6790 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6790.xml">
  <!ENTITY RFC6941 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6941.xml">

  ]>

<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes" ?>

<rfc category="info" ipr="trust200902"
     docName="draft-ietf-mpls-multipath-use-01">

  <front>
    <title abbrev="MPLS-TP and MPLS Multipath">
      Use of Multipath with MPLS-TP and MPLS</title>

    <author role="editor"
	    fullname="Curtis Villamizar" initials="C." surname="Villamizar">
      <organization>Outer Cape Cod Network Consulting</organization>
      <address>
	<email>curtis@occnc.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date year="2013" />

    <area>Routing</area>
    <workgroup>MPLS</workgroup>

    <keyword>MPLS</keyword>
    <keyword>composite link</keyword>
    <keyword>link aggregation</keyword>
    <keyword>ECMP</keyword>
    <keyword>link bundling</keyword>
    <keyword>multipath</keyword>
    <keyword>MPLS-TP</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>
	Many MPLS implementations have supported multipath techniques
	and many MPLS deployments have used multipath techniques,
	particularly in very high bandwidth applications, such as
	provider IP/MPLS core networks.  MPLS-TP has strongly
	discouraged the use of multipath techniques.  Some degradation
	of MPLS-TP OAM performance cannot be avoided when operating
	over many types of multipath implementations.
      </t>
      <t>
	Using MPLS Entropy label, MPLS LSPs can be carried over
	multipath links while also providing a fully MPLS-TP compliant
	server layer for MPLS-TP LSPs.  This document describes the
	means of supporting MPLS as a server layer for MPLS-TP.  The
	use of MPLS-TP LSPs as a server layer for MPLS LSPs is also
	discussed.
      </t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>

    <section title="Introduction">

      <t>
	Today the requirement to handle large aggregations of traffic,
	can be handled by a number of techniques which we will
	collectively call multipath.  Multipath applied to parallel
	links between the same set of nodes includes Ethernet Link
	Aggregation <xref target="IEEE-802.1AX" />,
	<xref target="RFC4201">link bundling</xref>, or other
	aggregation techniques some of which may be vendor specific.
	Multipath applied to diverse paths rather than parallel links
	includes Equal Cost MultiPath (ECMP) as applied to OSPF, ISIS,
	or BGP, and equal cost LSPs.  Some vendors support load split
	across equal cost MPLS LSPs where the load is split
	proportionally to the reserved bandwidth of the set of LSPs.
      </t>
      <t>
	RFC 5654 requirement 33 requires the capability to carry a
	client MPLS-TP or MPLS layer over a server MPLS-TP or MPLS
	layer <xref target="RFC5654" />.  This is possible in all
	cases with one exception.  When an MPLS LSP exceeds the
	capacity of any single component link it may be carried by a
	network using multipath techniques, but may not be carried by
	a single MPLS-TP LSP due to the inherent MPLS-TP capacity
	limitation imposed by MPLS-TP OAM fate sharing constraints and
	MPLS-TP LM OAM packet ordering constraints (see
	<xref target="sect.tp-requirements" />).
      </t>
      <t>
	The term composite link is more general than terms such as
	link aggregation (which is specific to Ethernet) or ECMP
	(which implies equal cost paths within a routing protocol).
	The use of the term composite link here is consistent with the
	broad definition in <xref target="ITU-T.G.800" />.  Multipath
	is very similar to composite link as defined by ITU, but
	specifically excludes inverse multiplexing.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="sect.def" title="Definitions">

      <t><list style="hanging" hangIndent="4">
	  <t hangText="Multipath"><vspace blankLines="0" />
	    The term multipath includes all techniques in which
	    <list style="numbers">
	      <t>
		Traffic can take more than one path from one node to a
		destination.
	      </t>
	      <t>
		Individual packets take one path only.  Packets are
		not subdivided and reassembled at the receiving end.
	      </t>
	      <t>
		Packets are not resequenced at the receiving end.
	      </t>
	      <t>
		The paths may be:
		<list style="letters">
		  <t>
		    parallel links between two nodes, or
		  </t>
		  <t>
		    may be specific paths across a network to a
		    destination node, or
		  </t>
		  <t>
		    may be links or paths to an intermediate node used
		    to reach a common destination.
		  </t>
		</list>
	      </t>
	    </list>
	  </t>
	  <t hangText="Link Bundle"><vspace blankLines="0" />
	    Link bundling is a multipath technique specific to MPLS
	    <xref target="RFC4201" />.  Link bundling supports two
	    modes of operations.  Either an LSP can be placed on one
	    component link of a link bundle, or an LSP can be load
	    split across all members of the bundle.  There is no
	    signaling defined which allows a per LSP preference
	    regarding load split, therefore whether to load split is
	    generally configured per bundle and applied to all LSPs
	    across the bundle.
	  </t>
	  <t hangText="Link Aggregation"><vspace blankLines="0" />
	    The term "link aggregation" generally refers
	    to <xref target="IEEE-802.1AX">Ethernet Link
	    Aggregation</xref> as defined by the IEEE.  Ethernet Link
	    Aggregation defines a Link Aggregation Control Protocol
	    (LACP) which coordinates inclusion of LAG members in the
	    LAG.
	  </t>
	  <t hangText="Link Aggregation Group (LAG)">
	    <vspace blankLines="0" /> A group of physical Ethernet
	    interfaces that are treated as a logical link when using
	    Ethernet Link Aggregation is referred to as a Link
	    Aggregation Group (LAG).
	  </t>
	  <t hangText="Equal Cost Multipath (ECMP)">
	    <vspace blankLines="0" /> Equal Cost Multipath (ECMP) is a
	    specific form of multipath in which the costs of the links
	    or paths must be equal in a given routing protocol.  The
	    load may be split equally across all available links (or
	    available paths), or the load may be split proportionally
	    to the capacity of each link (or path).
	  </t>
	  <t hangText="Loop Free Alternate Paths">
	    <vspace blankLines="0" /> "Loop-free alternate paths"
	    (LFA) are defined in <xref target="RFC5714">RFC 5714,
	    Section 5.2</xref> as follows.  "Such a path exists when a
	    direct neighbor of the router adjacent to the failure has
	    a path to the destination that can be guaranteed not to
	    traverse the failure."  Further detail can be found in
	    <xref target="RFC5286" />.  LFA as defined for IPFRR can
	    be used to load balance by relaxing the equal cost
	    criteria of ECMP, though IPFRR defined LFA for use in
	    selecting protection paths.  When used with IP,
	    proportional split is generally not used.  LFA use in load
	    balancing is implemented by some vendors though it may
	    be rare or non-existent in deployments.
	  </t>
	  <t hangText="Composite Link"><vspace blankLines="0" />
	    The term Composite Link had been a registered trademark of
	    Avici Systems, but was abandoned in 2007.  The term
	    composite link is now defined by the ITU in
	    <xref target="ITU-T.G.800" />.  The ITU definition
	    includes multipath as defined here, plus inverse
	    multiplexing which is explicitly excluded from the
	    definition of multipath.
	  </t>
	  <t hangText="Inverse Multiplexing"><vspace blankLines="0" />
	    Inverse multiplexing either transmits whole packets and
	    resequences the packets at the receiving end or subdivides
	    packets and reassembles the packets at the receiving end.
	    Inverse multiplexing requires that all packets be handled
	    by a common egress packet processing element and is
	    therefore not useful for very high bandwidth applications.
	  </t>
	  <t hangText="Component Link"><vspace blankLines="0" />
	    The ITU definition of composite link in
	    <xref target="ITU-T.G.800" /> and the IETF definition of
	    link bundling in <xref target="RFC4201" /> both refer to
	    an individual link in the composite link or link bundle as
	    a component link.  The term component link is applicable
	    to all multipath.
	  </t>
	  <t hangText="LAG Member"><vspace blankLines="0" />
	    Ethernet Link Aggregation as defined in <xref
	    target="IEEE-802.1AX" /> refers to an individual link in a
	    LAG as a LAG member.  A LAG member is a component link.
	    An Ethernet LAG is a composite link.  IEEE does not use
	    the terms composite link or component link.
	  </t>
	  <t hangText="load split"><vspace blankLines="0" />
	    Load split, load balance, or load distribution refers to
	    subdividing traffic over a set of component links such
	    that load is fairly evenly distributed over the set of
	    component links and certain packet ordering requirements
	    are met.  Some existing techniques better acheive these
	    objectives than others.
	  </t>
	</list></t>
      <t>
	A small set of requirements are discussed.  These requirements
	make use of keywords such as MUST and SHOULD as described in
	<xref target="RFC2119" />.
      </t>

    </section>

    <section anchor="sect.mpls-server-layer"
	     title="MPLS as a Server Layer for MPLS-TP">

      <t>
	An MPLS LSP may be used as a server layer for MPLS-TP LSPs as
	long as all MPLS-TP requirements are met.
	<xref target="sect.tp-requirements" />
	reviews the basis for requirements of a server layer that
	supports MPLS-TP as a client layer.  Key requirements include
	OAM "fate-sharing" the the requirement that packets within an
	MPLS-TP LSP are not reordered, including both payload and OAM
	packets.
	<xref target="sect.tp-over-mpls-soln" />
	discusses implied requirements where MPLS is the server layer
	for MPLS-TP client LSPs, and describes a set of solutions using
	existing MPLS mechanisms.
      </t>

      <section anchor="sect.tp-requirements"
	       title="MPLS-TP Forwarding and Server Layer Requirements">

	<t>
	  <!-- ref to RFC5960 suggested by Carlos -->
	  <xref target="RFC5960" />
	  defines the date plane requirements for MPLS-TP.  Two very
	  relevant paragraphs in "Section 3.1.1 LSP Packet Encapsulation
	  and Forwarding" are the following.
	  <list style="hanging" hangIndent="4">
	    <t hangText="RFC5960, Section 3.1.1, Paragraph 3">
	      <vspace blankLines="0" />
	      Except for transient packet reordering that may occur, for
	      example, during fault conditions, packets are delivered in
	      order on L-LSPs, and on E-LSPs within a specific ordered
	      aggregate.
	    </t>
	    <t hangText="RFC5960, Section 3.1.1, Paragraph 6">
	      <vspace blankLines="0" />
	      Equal-Cost Multi-Path (ECMP) load-balancing MUST NOT be
	      performed on an MPLS-TP LSP.  MPLS-TP LSPs as defined in
	      this document MAY operate over a server layer that
	      supports load-balancing, but this load-balancing MUST
	      operate in such a manner that it is transparent to
	      MPLS-TP.  This does not preclude the future definition of
	      new MPLS-TP LSP types that have different requirements
	      regarding the use of ECMP in the server layer.
	    </t>
	  </list>
	</t>
	<t>
	  <xref target="RFC5960" />
          paragraph 3 requires that packets within a specific ordered
	  aggregate be delivered in order.  This same requirement
	  is already specified by Differentiated Services
	  <xref target="RFC2475" />.
	  <xref target="RFC5960" />
	  paragraph 6 explicitly allows a server layer to use ECMP
	  provided that it is transparent to the MPLS-TP client layer.
	</t>
	<t>
	  <!-- ref to RFC6371 inspired by conversation with Dave Allan -->
	  <xref target="RFC6371" />
	  adds a requirement for data traffic and OAM traffic
	  "fate-sharing".  The following paragraph in "Section 1
	  Introduction" summarizes this requirement.
	  <list style="hanging" hangIndent="4">
	    <t hangText="RFC6371, Section 1, Paragraph 7">
	      <vspace blankLines="0" />
	      OAM packets that instrument a particular direction of a
	      transport path are subject to the same forwarding
	      treatment (i.e., fate-share) as the user data packets and
	      in some cases, where Explicitly TC-encoded-PSC LSPs
	      (E-LSPs) are employed, may be required to have common
	      per-hop behavior (PHB) Scheduling Class (PSC) End-to-End
	      (E2E) with the class of traffic monitored.  In case of
	      Label-Only-Inferred-PSC LSP (L-LSP), only one class of
	      traffic needs to be monitored, and therefore the OAM
	      packets have common PSC with the monitored traffic class.
	    </t>
	  </list>
	</t>
	<t>
	  <xref target="RFC6371" />
	  does not prohibit multilink techniques in "Section 4.6
	  Fate-Sharing Considerations for Multilink", where multilink is
	  defined as Ethernet Link Aggregation and the use of Link
	  Bundling for MPLS, but does declare that such a network would
	  be only partially MPLS-TP compliant.  The characteristic that
	  is to be avoided is contained in the following sentence in
	  this section.
	  <list style="hanging" hangIndent="4">
	    <t hangText="RFC6371, Section 4.6, Paragraph 1, last sentence">
	      <vspace blankLines="0" />
	      These techniques frequently share the characteristic that
	      an LSP may be spread over a set of component links and
	      therefore be reordered, but no flow within the LSP is
	      reordered (except when very infrequent and minimally
	      disruptive load rebalancing occurs).
	    </t>
	  </list>
	  A declaration that implies that Link Bundling for MPLS yields
	  a partially MPLS-TP compliant network, is perhaps overstated
	  since only the Link Bundling all-ones component link has this
	  characteristic.
	</t>
	<t>
	  <!-- ref to RFC6374 from conversation with Dave Allan -->
	  <xref target="RFC6374" />
	  defines a direct Loss Measurement (LM) where LM OAM packets
	  cannot be reordered with respect to payload packets.  This
	  will require that payload packets themselves not be reordered.
	  The following paragraph in "Section 2.9.4 Equal Cost
	  Multipath" gives the reason for this restriction.
	  <list style="hanging" hangIndent="4">
	    <t hangText="RFC6374, Section 2.9.4, Paragraph 2">
	      <vspace blankLines="0" />
	      The effects of ECMP on loss measurement will depend on the
	      LM mode.  In the case of direct LM, the measurement will
	      account for any packets lost between the sender and the
	      receiver, regardless of how many paths exist between them.
	      However, the presence of ECMP increases the likelihood of
	      misordering both of LM messages relative to data packets
	      and of the LM messages themselves.  Such misorderings tend
	      to create unmeasurable intervals and thus degrade the
	      accuracy of loss measurement.  The effects of ECMP are
	      similar for inferred LM, with the additional caveat that,
	      unless the test packets are specially constructed so as to
	      probe all available paths, the loss characteristics of one
	      or more of the alternate paths cannot be accounted for.
	    </t>
	  </list>
	</t>

      </section>

      <section anchor="sect.tp-over-mpls-soln"
	       title="Methods of Supporting MPLS-TP client LSPs over MPLS">

	<t>
	  Supporting MPLS-TP LSPs over a fully MPLS-TP conformant MPLS
	  LSP server layer where the MPLS LSPs are making use of
	  multipath, requires special treatment of the MPLS-TP LSPs
	  such that those LSPs meet MPLS-TP forwarding requirements
	  (see <xref target="sect.tp-requirements" />).  This implies
	  the following brief set of requirements.
	  <list counter="mp" hangIndent="4" style="format MP#%d">
	    <t>
	      It MUST be possible for a midpoint MPLS-TP LSR which is
	      serving as ingress to a server layer MPLS LSP to
	      identify MPLS-TP LSPs, so that MPLS-TP forwarding
	      requirements can be applied, or to otherwise accommodate
	      the MPLS-TP forwarding requirements.
	    </t>
	    <t>
	      It SHOULD be possible to completely exclude MPLS-TP LSPs
	      from the multipath hash and load split.  If the selected
	      component link no longer meets requirements, an LSP is
	      considered down which may trigger protection and/or may
	      require that the ingress LSR select a new path and
	      signal a new LSP.
	    </t>
	    <t>
	      It SHOULD be possible to insure that MPLS-TP LSPs will
	      not be moved to another component link as a result of a
	      composite link load rebalancing operation.  If the
	      selected component link no longer meets requirements,
	      another component link may be selected, however a change
	      in path should not occur solely for load balancing.
	    </t>
	    <t>
	      Where an RSVP-TE control plane is used, it MUST be
	      possible for an ingress LSR which is setting up an
	      MPLS-TP or an MPLS LSP to determine at path selection
	      time whether a link or Forwarding Adjacency (FA, see
	      <xref target="RFC4206" />) within the topology can
	      support the MPLS-TP requirements of the LSP.
	    </t>
	  </list>
	</t>
	<t>
	  <!-- inspired by requests to make #1 more clear -->
	  The reason for requirement MP#1 may not be obvious.  A
	  MPLS-TP LSP may be aggregated along with other client LSP by
	  a midpoint LSR into a very large MPLS server layer LSP, as
	  would be the case in a core node to core node MPLS LSP
	  between major cities.  In this case the ingress of the MPLS
	  LSP cannot through any existing signaling mechanism
	  determine which client LSP contained within it as MPLS-TP or
	  not MPLS-TP.  
	  <!-- new sentence added for clarity at Dave's suggestion -->
	  Multipath load splitting can be avoided for MPLS-TP LSP if
	  at the MPLS server layer LSP ingress LSR an Entropy Label
	  Indicator (ELI) and Entropy Label (EL) are added to the
	  label stack <xref target="RFC6790" />.
	  For those client LSP that are MPLS-TP LSP, a
	  single EL value must be chosen.  For those client LSP that
	  are MPLS LSP, per packet entropy below the top label must,
	  for practical reasons, be used to determine the entropy
	  label value.  Requirement MP#1 simply states that there must
	  be a means to make this decision.
	</t>
	<t>
	  There is currently no signaling mechanism defined to support
	  requirement MP#1, though that does not preclude a new
	  extension being defined later.  In the absense of a
	  signaling extension, MPLS-TP can be identified through some
	  form of configuration, such as configuration which provides
	  an MPLS-TP compatible server layer to all LSP arriving on a
	  specific interface or originating from a specific set of
	  ingress LSR.
	</t>
	<t>
	  <!-- separate paragraph inspired by comment from Mach -->
	  Alternately, the need for requirement MP#1 can be eliminated
	  if evey MPLS-TP LSP can be created by the MPLS-TP ingress
	  makes use of an Entropy Label Indicator (ELI) and Entropy
	  Label (EL) below the MPLS-TP label
	  <xref target="RFC6790" />.
	  This would require that all MPLS-TP LSR in a deployment
	  support Entropy Label, which may render it impractical in
	  many deployments.
	</t>
	<!--
	    The text below was edited to make it more clear.
	    In some cases some just plain wrong statements about
	    satisfying MP#2 and MP#3 had to be corrected.
	-->
	<t>
	  Some hardware which exists today can support requirement
	  MP#2.  Signaling in the absense of MPLS Entropy Label can
	  make use of link bundling with the path pinned to a specific
	  component for MPLS-TP LSP and link bundling using the
	  all-ones component for MPLS LSP.  This prevents MPLS-TP LSP
	  from being carried within MPLS LSP but does allow the
	  co-existance of MPLS-TP and very large MPLS LSP.
	</t>
	<t>
	  MPLS-TP LSPs can be carried as client LSPs within an MPLS
	  server LSP if an Entropy Label Indicator (ELI) and Entropy
	  Label (EL) is added after the server layer LSP label(s) in
	  the label stack, just above the MPLS-TP LSP label entry
	  <xref target="RFC6790" />.  The value of EL can be randomly
	  selected at the client MPLS-TP LSP setup time and the same
	  EL value used for all packets of that MPLS-TP LSP.  This
	  allows MPLS-TP LSP to be carried as client LSP within MPLS
	  LSP and satisfies MPLS-TP forwarding requirements but
	  requires that MPLS LSR be able to identify MPLS-TP LSP
	  (requirement MP#1).
	</t>
	<t>
	  MPLS-TP traffic can be protected from an degraded performance
	  due to an imperfect load split if the MPLS-TP traffic is given
	  queuing priority (using strict priority and policing or
	  shaping at ingress or locally or weighted queuing locally).
	  This can be accomplished using the Traffic Class field and
	  Diffserv treatment of traffic
	  <xref target="RFC5462" /><xref target="RFC2475" />.  In the
	  event of congestion due to load imbalance, other traffic will
	  suffer as long as there is a minority of MPLS-TP traffic.
	</t>
	<t>
	  <!-- This paragraph was just plain wrong - fixed it -->
	  If MPLS-TP LSP are carried within MPLS LSP and ELI and EL
	  are used, requirement MP#3 is satisfied only for uncongested
	  links where load balancing is not required, or if MPLS-TP
	  LSP use TC and Diffserv and the load rebalancing
	  implementation rebalances only the less preferred traffic.
	  Load rebalance is generally needed only when congestion
	  occurs, therefore restricting MPLS-TP to be carried only
	  over MPLS LSP that are known to traverse only links which
	  are expected to be uncongested can satisfy requirement MP#3.
	</t>
	<t>
	  <!-- summary paragraph, hopefully improves clarity -->
	  An MPLS-TP LSP can be pinned to a Link Bundle component link
	  if the behavior of requirement MP#2 is preferred.  An
	  MPLS-TP LSP can be assigned to a Link Bundle but not pinned
	  if the behavior of requirement MP#3 is preferred.  In both
	  of these cases, the MPLS-TP LSP must be the top level LSP,
	  except as noted above.
	</t>
	<t>
	  If MPLS-TP LSP can be moved among component links, then the
	  Link Bundle all-ones component link can be used or server
	  layer MPLS LSPs can be used with no restrictions on the
	  server layer MPLS use of multipath except that Entropy Label
	  must be supported along the entire path.  An Entropy Label
	  must be used to insure that all of the MPLS-TP payload and
	  OAM traffic are carried on the same component, except during
	  very infrequent transitions due to load balancing.
	  <!-- clarification requested in IETF-86 by George Swallow -->
	  Since the Entropy Label Indicator and Entropy Label are
	  always placed above the GAL in the stack, the presense of
	  GAL will not affect the selection of a component link as
	  long as the LSR does not hash on the label stack entries
	  below the Entropy Label.
	</t>
	<t>
	  <!-- multiple requests to be more explicit about this -->
	  An MPLS-TP LSP may not traverse multipath links on the path
	  where MPLS-TP forwarding requirements cannot be met.  Such
	  links include any using pre-RFC6790 Ethernet Link
	  Aggregation, pre-RFC6790 Link Bundling using the all-ones
	  component link, or other form of multipath not supporting
	  termination of the entropy search at the EL label as called
	  for in <xref target="RFC6790" />.  An MPLS-TP LSP must not
	  traverse a server layer MPLS LSP which traverses any form of
	  multipath not supporting termination of the entropy search
	  at the EL label.  For this to occur, the MPLS-TP ingress LSR
	  must be aware of these links.  This is the reason for
	  requirement MP#4.
	</t>
	<t>
	  Requirement MP#4 can be supported using administrative
	  attributes.  Administrative attributes are defined in
	  <xref target="RFC3209" />.  Some configuration is required to
	  support this.
	</t>

      </section>

    </section>

    <section anchor="sect.tp-server-layer"
	     title="MPLS-TP as a Server Layer for MPLS">

      <t>
	Carrying MPLS LSP which are larger than a component link over
	a MPLS-TP server layer requires that the large MPLS client
	layer LSP be accommodated by multiple MPLS-TP server layer
	LSPs.  MPLS multipath can be used in the client layer MPLS.
      </t>
      <t>
	Creating multiple MPLS-TP server layer LSP places a greater
	Incoming Label Map (ILM) scaling burden on the LSR.  High
	bandwidth MPLS cores with
	a smaller amount of nodes have the greatest tendency to
	require LSP in excess of component links, therefore the
	reduction in number of nodes offsets the impact of increasing
	the number of server layer LSP in parallel.  Today, only in
	cases where deployed LSR ILM are small would this be an issue.
      </t>
      <t>
	The most significant disadvantage of MPLS-TP as a Server Layer
	for MPLS is that the use MPLS-TP server layer LSP reduces the
	efficiency of carrying the MPLS client layer.  The service
	which provides by far the largest offered load in provider
	networks is Internet, for which the LSP capacity reservations
	are predictions of expected load.  Many of these MPLS LSP may
	be smaller than component link capacity.  Using MPLS-TP as a
	server layer results in bin packing problems for these smaller
	LSP.  For those LSP that are larger than component link
	capacity, their capacity are not increments of convenient
	capacity increments such as 10Gb/s.  Using MPLS-TP as an
	underlying server layer greatly reduces the ability of the
	client layer MPLS LSP to share capacity.  For example, when
	one MPLS LSP is underutilizing its predicted capacity, the
	fixed allocation of MPLS-TP to component links may not allow
	another LSP to exceed its predicted capacity.  Using MPLS-TP
	as a server layer may result in less efficient use of
	resources and may result in a less cost effective network.
      </t>
      <t>
	No additional requirements beyond MPLS-TP as it is now
	currently defined are required to support MPLS-TP as a Server
	Layer for MPLS.  It is therefore viable but has some
	undesirable characteristics discussed above.
      </t>

    </section>

    <!-- Possibly an Acknowledgements or a 'Contributors' section ... -->

    <section title="Acknowledgements">

      <t>
	Carlos Pignataro, Dave Allan, and Mach Chen provided valuable
	comments and suggestions.  Carlos suggested that MPLS-TP
	requirements in RFC 5960 be explicitly referenced or quoted.
	An email conversation with Dave led to the inclusion of
	references and quotes from RFC 6371 and RFC 6374.  Mach made
	suggestions to improve clarity of the document.
      </t>

    </section>

    <section title="Implementation Status">

      <t>
	Note: this section is temporary and supports the experiment
	called for in draft-sheffer-running-code.
      </t>
      <t>
	This is an informational document which describes usage of
	MPLS and MPLS-TP.  No new protocol extensions or forwarding
	behavior are specified.  Ethernet Link Aggregation and MPLS
	Link Bundling are widely implemented and deployed.
      </t>
      <t>
	Entropy Label is not yet widely implemented and deployed, but
	both implementation and deployment are expected soon.  At
	least a few existing high end commodity packet processing
	chips are capable of supporting Entropy Label.  It would be
	helpful if a few LSR suppliers would state their intentions to
	support RFC 6790 on the mpls mailing list.
      </t>
      <t>
	Dynamic multipath (multipath load split adjustment in response
	to observed load) is referred to but not a requirement of the
	usage recommendations made in this document.  Dynamic
	multipath has been implemented and deployed, however (afaik)
	the only core LSR vendor supporting dynamic multipath is no
	longer in the router business (Avici Systems).  At least a few
	existing high end commodity packet processing chips are
	capable of supporting dynamic multipath.
      </t>

    </section>

    <section anchor="sect.iana" title="IANA Considerations">

      <t>This memo includes no request to IANA.</t>

    </section>

    <section anchor="sect.security" title="Security Considerations">

      <t>
	This document specifies requirements with discussion of
	framework for solutions using existing MPLS and MPLS-TP
	mechanisms.  The requirements and framework are related to the
	coexistence of MPLS/GMPLS (without MPLS-TP) when used over a
	packet network, MPLS-TP, and multipath.  The combination of
	MPLS, MPLS-TP, and multipath does not introduce any new
	security threats.  The security considerations for MPLS/GMPLS
	and for MPLS-TP are documented in <xref target="RFC5920" />
	and <xref target="RFC6941" />.
      </t>

    </section>

  </middle>

  <back>

    <references title="Normative References">

      &RFC2119;
      &RFC5654;
      &RFC5960;
      &RFC6371;
      &RFC6374;
      &RFC6790;

    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">

      &RFC2475;
      &RFC3209;
      &RFC4201;
      &RFC4206;
      &RFC5286;
      &RFC5462;
      &RFC5714;
      &RFC5920;
      &RFC6941;

      <reference anchor="IEEE-802.1AX"
                 target="http://standards.ieee.org/getieee802/download/802.1AX-2008.pdf">
        <front>
          <title>IEEE Std 802.1AX-2008 IEEE Standard for
	    Local and Metropolitan Area Networks - Link Aggregation</title>

          <author>
            <organization>IEEE Standards Association</organization>
          </author>

          <date year="2006" />
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="ITU-T.G.800"
                 target="http://www.itu.int/rec/T-REC-G/recommendation.asp?parent=T-REC-G.800">
        <front>
          <title>Unified functional architecture of transport
          networks</title>

          <author>
            <organization>ITU-T</organization>
          </author>

          <date year="2007" />
        </front>
      </reference>

    </references>

  </back>
</rfc>
