<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc toc="no"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<rfc category="std" docName="draft-ietf-mpls-tp-ethernet-addressing-06"
     ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="MPLS-TP Ethernet Addressing">MPLS-TP Next-Hop Ethernet
    Addressing</title>

    <author fullname="Dan Frost" initials="D" surname="Frost">
      <organization>Cisco Systems</organization>

      <address>
        <email>danfrost@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Stewart Bryant" initials="S" surname="Bryant">
      <organization>Cisco Systems</organization>

      <address>
        <email>stbryant@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Matthew Bocci" initials="M" surname="Bocci">
      <organization>Alcatel-Lucent</organization>

      <address>
        <email>matthew.bocci@alcatel-lucent.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date year="2013" />

    <area>Routing</area>

    <workgroup>MPLS</workgroup>

    <keyword>MPLS</keyword>

    <keyword>Internet-Draft</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>The Multiprotocol Label Switching (MPLS) Transport Profile (MPLS-TP)
      is the set of MPLS protocol functions applicable to the construction and
      operation of packet-switched transport networks. This document presents
      considerations for link-layer addressing of Ethernet frames carrying
      MPLS-TP packets.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>The MPLS Transport Profile (MPLS-TP) <xref target="RFC5921"></xref>
      is the set of protocol functions that meet the requirements <xref
      target="RFC5654"></xref> for the application of MPLS to the construction
      and operation of packet-switched transport networks. The MPLS-TP data
      plane consists of those MPLS-TP functions concerned with the
      encapsulation and forwarding of MPLS-TP packets and is described in
      <xref target="RFC5960"></xref>.</t>

      <t>This document presents considerations for link-layer addressing of
      Ethernet frames carrying MPLS-TP packets. Since MPLS-TP packets are MPLS
      packets, existing procedures (<xref target="RFC3032"></xref>, <xref
      target="RFC5332"></xref>) for the encapsulation of MPLS packets over
      Ethernet apply. Because IP functionality is only optional in an MPLS-TP
      network, IP-based protocols for Media Access Control (MAC) address
      learning, such as the Address Resolution Protocol (ARP) <xref
      target="RFC0826"></xref> and IP version 6 Neighbor Discovery <xref
      target="RFC4861"></xref>, may not be available. This document specifies
      the options for the determination and selection of the next-hop Ethernet
      MAC address when MPLS-TP is used between nodes that do not have an IP
      dataplane.</t>

      <section title="Terminology">
        <texttable align="left" style="headers">
          <ttcol>Term</ttcol>

          <ttcol>Definition</ttcol>

          <c>ARP</c>

          <c>Address Resolution Protocol</c>

          <c>G-ACh</c>

          <c>Generic Associated Channel</c>

          <c>LSP</c>

          <c>Label Switched Path</c>

          <c>LSR</c>

          <c>Label Switching Router</c>

          <c>MAC</c>

          <c>Media Access Control</c>

          <c>MPLS-TP</c>

          <c>MPLS Transport Profile</c>
        </texttable>

        <t>Additional definitions and terminology can be found in <xref
        target="RFC5960"></xref> and <xref target="RFC5654"></xref>.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Requirements Language">
        <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
        "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
        document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
        target="RFC2119"></xref>.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="eth-p2p" title="Point-to-Point Link Addressing">
      <t>When two MPLS-TP nodes are connected by a point-to-point Ethernet
      link, the question arises as to what destination Ethernet Media Access
      Control (MAC) address should be specified in Ethernet frames transmitted
      to the peer node over the link. The problem of determining this address
      does not arise in IP/MPLS networks because of the presence of the
      Ethernet Address Resolution Protocol (ARP) <xref
      target="RFC0826"></xref> or IP version 6 Neighbor Discovery protocol
      <xref target="RFC4861"></xref>, which allow the unicast MAC address of
      the peer device to be learned dynamically.</t>

      <t>If existing mechanisms are available in an MPLS-TP network to
      determine the destination unicast MAC addresses of peer nodes -- for
      example, if the network also happens to be an IP/MPLS network, or if
      Link Layer Discovery Protocol (LLDP) <xref target="LLDP"></xref> is in
      use, or if it implements the procedures in <xref target="gap"></xref> of
      this document -- such mechanisms SHOULD be used. The remainder of this
      section discusses the available options when this is not the case.</t>

      <t>Each node MAY be statically configured with the MAC address of its
      peer. Note however that static MAC address configuration can present an
      administrative burden and lead to operational problems. For example,
      replacement of an Ethernet interface to resolve a hardware fault when
      this approach is used requires that the peer node be manually
      reconfigured with the new MAC address. This is especially problematic if
      the peer is operated by another provider.</t>

      <t>Another approach which may be considered is to use the Ethernet
      broadcast address FF-FF-FF-FF-FF-FF as the destination MAC address in
      frames carrying MPLS-TP packets over a link that is known to be
      point-to-point. This may, however, lead to excessive frame distribution
      and processing at the Ethernet layer. Broadcast traffic may also be
      treated specially by some devices and this may not be desirable for
      MPLS-TP data frames.</t>

      <t>In view of the above considerations, the approach which SHOULD be
      used, is therefore to configure both nodes to use the method described
      in this document which uses, as a destination MAC address, an Ethernet
      multicast address reserved for MPLS-TP for use over point-to-point
      links. The address allocated for this purpose by the Internet Assigned
      Numbers Authority (IANA) is 01-00-5E-90-00-00. An MPLS-TP implementation
      MUST process Ethernet frames received over a point-to-point link with
      this destination MAC address by default.</t>

      <t>The use of broadcast or multicast addressing for the purpose
      described in this section, i.e. as a placeholder for the unknown unicast
      MAC address of the destination, is applicable only when the attached
      Ethernet link is known to be point-to-point. If a link is not known to
      be point-to-point, these forms of broadcast or multicast addressing MUST
      NOT be used. Thus the implementation MUST provide a means for the
      operator to declare that a link is point-to-point if it supports these
      addressing modes. Moreover, the operator is cautioned that it is not
      always clear whether a given link is, or will remain, strictly
      point-to-point, particularly when the link is supplied by an external
      provider; point-to-point declarations must therefore be used with care.
      Because of these caveats it is RECOMMENDED that implementations support
      the procedures in <xref target="gap"></xref> so that unicast addressing
      can be used.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Multipoint Link Addressing">
      <t>When a multipoint Ethernet link serves as a section <xref
      target="RFC5960"></xref> for a point-to-multipoint MPLS-TP LSP, and
      multicast destination MAC addressing at the Ethernet layer is used for
      the LSP, the addressing and encapsulation procedures specified in <xref
      target="RFC5332"></xref> SHALL be used.</t>

      <t>When a multipoint Ethernet link -- that is, a link which is not known
      to be point-to-point -- serves as a section for a point-to-point MPLS-TP
      LSP, unicast destination MAC addresses MUST be used for Ethernet frames
      carrying packets of the LSP. According to the discussion in the previous
      section, this implies the use of either static MAC address configuration
      or a protocol that enables peer MAC address discovery.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="gap"
             title="MAC Address Discovery via the G-ACh Advertisement Protocol">
      <t>The G-ACh Advertisement Protocol (GAP) <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-mpls-gach-adv"></xref> provides a simple means of
      informing listeners on a link of the sender's capabilities and
      configuration. When used for this purpose on an Ethernet link, GAP
      messages are multicast to the address 01-00-5e-80-00-0d (see <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-mpls-gach-adv"></xref> Section 7). If these messages
      contain the unicast MAC address of the sender, then listeners can learn
      this address and use it in the future when transmitting frames
      containing MPLS-TP packets. Since the GAP does not rely on IP, this
      provides a means of unicast MAC discovery for MPLS-TP nodes without IP
      support.</t>

      <t>This document defines a new GAP application "Ethernet Interface
      Parameters" (TBD1), to support the advertisement of Ethernet-specific
      parameters associated with the sending interface. The following
      Type-Length-Value (TLV) objects are defined for this application; the
      TLV format is as defined in <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-mpls-gach-adv"></xref>:<list style="empty">
          <t>Source MAC Address (type = 0, length = 8): The Value of this
          object is an EUI-64 <xref target="EUI-64"></xref> unicast MAC
          address assigned to one of the interfaces of the sender that is
          connected to this data link. The IEEE-defined mapping from 48-bit
          MAC addresses to EUI-64 form is used.</t>

          <t>MTU (type = 1, length = 4): The Value of this object is a 32-bit
          unsigned integer encoded in network byte order that specifies the
          maximum transmission unit size in octets of an MPLS label stack plus
          payload that can be sent over the sending interface. Where MAC
          address learning occurs by some other means, this TLV group MAY be
          used to advertise only the MTU. If multiple advertisements are made
          for the same parameter, use of these advertisements is
          undefined.</t>
        </list></t>

      <figure>
        <artwork><![CDATA[    0                   1                   2                   3
    0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |     Type=0    |    Reserved   |           Length=8            |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |                MAC Address in EUI-64 Format                   |
   |                                                               |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+

                    Figure 1: Source MAC Address Object Format]]></artwork>
      </figure>

      <t></t>

      <figure>
        <artwork><![CDATA[   0                   1                   2                   3
   0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
  +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
  |      Type=1    |    Reserved   |          Length=4            |
  +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
  |                             MTU                               |
  +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+

                        Figure 2: TLV Object Format]]></artwork>
      </figure>

      <t></t>

      <t>Per <xref target="I-D.ietf-mpls-gach-adv"></xref>, MAC Address
      Discovery information needs to be periodically retransmitted and is to
      be retained by a receiver based on the period of time indicated by the
      associated Lifetime field. To expedite the initialization of a link it
      is RECOMMENDED that a node that has been reconfigured, rebooted or is
      aware that it have been disconnected from its peer send a GAP Ethernet
      Interface Parameter message, and that it issues a GAP request message
      for the Ethernet parameters at the earliest opportunity.</t>

      <t>When the MAC address in the received Source MAC Address TLV changes
      the new MAC address MUST be used (see Section 5.2 of <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-mpls-gach-adv"></xref>).</t>

      <t>If a minimum MTU is configured for a link and the MTU advertised by
      the peer is lower than that minimum, the operator MUST be notified of
      the MTU mismatch. Under these circumstances the operator may choose to
      configure the LSR to shut the link, thereby triggering a fault, and
      hence causing the end-to-end path to be repaired. Alternatively the
      operator may choose to configure the LSR to leave the link up so that an
      OAM message can be used to verify the actual MTU.</t>

      <t>In the event a GAP message is not received within the previously
      received associated Lifetime, the receiving node MUST assume that it is
      now connected to a node that does not support these advertisements and
      must behave as configured for this eventuality.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Manageability Considerations">
      <t>The values sent and received by this protocol MUST be made accessible
      for inspection by network operators, and where local configuration is
      updated by the received information, it MUST be clear why the configured
      value has been changed. The advertised information SHOULD be persistent
      across restarts. Received advertisements MUST be discarded across
      restarts. If the received values change, the new values MUST be used and
      the change made visible to the network operators.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Security Considerations">
      <t>The use of broadcast or multicast Ethernet destination MAC addresses
      for frames carrying MPLS-TP data packets can potentially result in such
      frames being distributed to devices other than the intended destination
      node or nodes when the Ethernet link is not point-to-point. The operator
      SHOULD take care to ensure that MPLS-TP nodes are aware of the Ethernet
      link type (point-to-point or multipoint). In the case of multipoint
      links, the operator SHOULD either ensure that no devices are attached to
      the link that are not authorized to receive the frames, or take steps to
      mitigate the possibility of excessive frame distribution, for example by
      configuring the Ethernet switch to appropriately restrict the delivery
      of multicast frames to authorized ports.</t>

      <t>An attacker could disrupt communications by modifying the Source MAC
      Address or the MTU values, however this is mitigated by the use of
      cryptographic authentication as described in <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-mpls-gach-adv"></xref> which also describes other
      considerations applicable to the GAP protocol. Visibility into the
      contents of either of the TLVs could provide information that is useful
      for an attacker. This is best addressed by physical security of the
      links.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="IANA Considerations">
      <section title="Ethernet Multicast Address Allocation">
        <t>IANA has allocated an Ethernet multicast address from the "IANA
        Multicast 48-bit MAC Addresses" address block in the "Ethernet
        Numbers" registry for use by MPLS-TP LSRs over point-to-point links as
        described in <xref target="eth-p2p"></xref>. The allocated address is
        01-00-5E-90-00-00. IANA is requested to update the reference to point
        to the RFC number assigned to this document.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="G-ACh Advertisement Protocol Allocation">
        <t>IANA is requested to allocate a new Application ID in the "G-ACh
        Advertisement Protocol Applications" registry <xref
        target="I-D.ietf-mpls-gach-adv"></xref> (currently located in the
        "Pseudowire Name Spaces (PWE3)"), as follows:</t>

        <texttable align="left" style="headers">
          <ttcol>Application ID</ttcol>

          <ttcol>Description</ttcol>

          <ttcol>Reference</ttcol>

          <c>TBD1 to be assigned by IANA</c>

          <c>Ethernet Interface Parameters</c>

          <c>(this draft)</c>
        </texttable>
      </section>

      <section title="Creation of Ethernet Interface Parameters Registry">
        <t>IANA is requested to create a new registry, "G-ACh Advertisement
        Protocol: Ethernet Interface Parameters" within the "Pseudowire Name
        Spaces (PWE3)" with fields and initial allocations as follows:</t>

        <texttable align="left" style="headers">
          <ttcol>Type Name</ttcol>

          <ttcol>Type ID</ttcol>

          <ttcol>Reference</ttcol>

          <c>Source MAC Address</c>

          <c>0</c>

          <c>(this draft)</c>

          <c>MTU</c>

          <c>1</c>

          <c>(this draft)</c>
        </texttable>

        <t>The range of the Type ID field is 0 - 255.</t>

        <t>The allocation policy for this registry is IETF Review.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>We thank Adrian Farrel for his valuable review comments on this
      document.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-mpls-gach-adv'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.2119'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.3032'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.5654'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.5332'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.5960'?>

      <reference anchor="EUI-64">
        <front>
          <title>[EUI64] IEEE, "Guidelines for 64-bit Global Identifier
          (EUI-64) Registration Authority",
          http://standards.ieee.org/regauth/oui/tutorials/EUI64.html, March
          1997.</title>

          <author>
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date />
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="LLDP">
        <front>
          <title>IEEE, "Station and Media Access Control Connectivity
          Discovery (802.1AB)", September 2009.</title>

          <author>
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date />
        </front>
      </reference>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.0826'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.4861'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.5921'?>
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
