<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc rfcedstyle="yes"?>
<rfc category="info" docName="draft-ietf-mpls-tp-p2mp-framework-02"
     ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="MPLS Transport Profile P2MP Framework">A Framework for
    Point-to-Multipoint MPLS in Transport Networks</title>

    <author fullname="Dan Frost" initials="D" role="editor" surname="Frost">
      <organization>Cisco Systems</organization>

      <address>
        <email>danfrost@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Stewart Bryant" initials="S" role="editor"
            surname="Bryant">
      <organization>Cisco Systems</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>

          <city></city>

          <region></region>

          <code></code>

          <country></country>
        </postal>

        <phone></phone>

        <facsimile></facsimile>

        <email>stbryant@cisco.com</email>

        <uri></uri>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Matthew Bocci" initials="M" role="editor"
            surname="Bocci">
      <organization>Alcatel-Lucent</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Voyager Place, Shoppenhangers Road</street>

          <city>Maidenhead</city>

          <region>Berks</region>

          <code>SL6 2PJ</code>

          <country>United Kingdom</country>
        </postal>

        <email>matthew.bocci@alcatel-lucent.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Lou Berger" initials="L" role="editor" surname="Berger">
      <organization>LabN Consulting</organization>

      <address>
        <phone>+1-301-468-9228</phone>

        <email>lberger@labn.net</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date year="2013" />

    <area>Routing</area>

    <workgroup>MPLS Working Group</workgroup>

    <keyword>mpls-tp</keyword>

    <keyword>MPLS</keyword>

    <keyword>Internet-Draft</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>The Multiprotocol Label Switching (MPLS) Transport Profile (MPLS-TP)
      is the common set of MPLS protocol functions defined to enable the
      construction and operation of packet transport networks. The MPLS-TP
      supports both point-to-point and point-to-multipoint transport paths.
      This document defines the elements and functions of the MPLS-TP
      architecture applicable specifically to supporting point-to-multipoint
      transport paths.</t>

      <t>This document is a product of a joint Internet Engineering Task Force
      (IETF) / International Telecommunication Union Telecommunication
      Standardization Sector (ITU-T) effort to include an MPLS Transport
      Profile within the IETF MPLS and PWE3 architectures to support the
      capabilities and functions of a packet transport network.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>The Multiprotocol Label Switching (MPLS) Transport Profile (MPLS-TP)
      is the common set of MPLS protocol functions defined to meet the
      requirements specified in <xref target="RFC5654"></xref>. The MPLS-TP
      Framework <xref target="RFC5921"></xref> provides an overall
      introduction to the MPLS-TP and defines the general architecture of the
      Transport Profile, as well as those aspects specific to point-to-point
      transport paths. The purpose of this document is to define the elements
      and functions of the MPLS-TP architecture applicable specifically to
      supporting point-to-multipoint transport paths.</t>

      <t>This document is a product of a joint Internet Engineering Task Force
      (IETF) / International Telecommunication Union Telecommunication
      Standardization Sector (ITU-T) effort to include an MPLS Transport
      Profile within the IETF MPLS and PWE3 architectures to support the
      capabilities and functions of a packet transport network.</t>

      <section title="Scope">
        <t>This document defines the elements and functions of the MPLS-TP
        architecture related to supporting point-to-multipoint transport
        paths. The reader is referred to <xref target="RFC5921"></xref> for
        those aspects of the MPLS-TP architecture that are generic, or
        concerned specifically with point-to-point transport paths.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Terminology">
        <texttable align="left" style="headers">
          <ttcol>Term</ttcol>

          <ttcol>Definition</ttcol>

          <c>LSP</c>

          <c>Label Switched Path</c>

          <c>MPLS-TP</c>

          <c>MPLS Transport Profile</c>

          <c>SDH</c>

          <c>Synchronous Digital Hierarchy</c>

          <c>ATM</c>

          <c>Asynchronous Transfer Mode</c>

          <c>OTN</c>

          <c>Optical Transport Network</c>

          <c>OAM</c>

          <c>Operations, Administration and Maintenance</c>

          <c>G-ACh</c>

          <c>Generic Associated Channel</c>

          <c>GAL</c>

          <c>G-ACh Label</c>

          <c>MEP</c>

          <c>Maintenance End Point</c>

          <c>MIP</c>

          <c>Maintenance Intermediate Point</c>

          <c>APS</c>

          <c>Automatic Protection Switching</c>

          <c>SCC</c>

          <c>Signaling Communication Channel</c>

          <c>MCC</c>

          <c>Management Communication Channel</c>

          <c>EMF</c>

          <c>Equipment Management Function</c>

          <c>FM</c>

          <c>Fault Management</c>

          <c>CM</c>

          <c>Configuration Management</c>

          <c>PM</c>

          <c>Performance Monitoring</c>

          <c>LSR</c>

          <c>Label Switching Router</c>

          <c>MPLS-TE</c>

          <c>MPLS Traffic Engineering</c>

          <c>P2MP</c>

          <c>Point-to-multipoint</c>

          <c>PW</c>

          <c>Pseudowire</c>
        </texttable>

        <section title="Additional Definitions and Terminology">
          <t>Detailed definitions and additional terminology may be found in
          <xref target="RFC5921"></xref> and <xref
          target="RFC5654"></xref>.</t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section title="Applicability">
        <t>The point-to-multipoint connectivity provided by an MPLS-TP network
        is based on the point-to-multipoint connectivity provided by MPLS
        networks. P2MP MPLS TE-LSP support is discussed in <xref
        target="RFC4875"></xref> and <xref target="RFC5332"></xref>, and P2MP
        PW support is being developed based on <xref
        target="I-D.ietf-pwe3-p2mp-pw-requirements"></xref> and <xref
        target="I-D.ietf-l2vpn-vpms-frmwk-requirements"></xref>. MPLS-TP
        point-to-multipoint connectivity is analogous to that provided by
        traditional transport technologies such as Optical Transport Network
        (OTN) point-to-multipoint [G.798] and drop-and-continue [G.780], and
        thus supports the same class of traditional applications, e.g., video
        distribution.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="MPLS Transport Profile Point-to-Multipoint Requirements">
      <t>The requirements for MPLS-TP are specified in <xref
      target="RFC5654"></xref>, <xref target="RFC5860"></xref>, and <xref
      target="RFC5951"></xref>. This section provides a brief summary of
      point-to-multipoint transport requirements as set out in those
      documents; the reader is referred to the documents themselves for the
      definitive and complete list of requirements.</t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>MPLS-TP must support unidirectional point-to-multipoint (P2MP)
          transport paths.</t>

          <t>MPLS-TP must support traffic-engineered point-to-multipoint
          transport paths.</t>

          <t>MPLS-TP must be capable of using P2MP server (sub)layer
          capabilities as well as P2P server (sub)layer capabilities when
          supporting P2MP MPLS-TP transport paths.</t>

          <t>The MPLS-TP control plane must support establishing all the
          connectivity patterns defined for the MPLS-TP data plane (i.e.,
          unidirectional P2P, associated bidirectional P2P, co-routed
          bidirectional P2P, unidirectional P2MP) including configuration of
          protection functions and any associated maintenance functions.</t>

          <t>Recovery techniques used for P2P and P2MP should be identical to
          simplify implementation and operation.</t>

          <t>Unidirectional 1+1 and 1:n protection for P2MP connectivity must
          be supported.</t>

          <t>MPLS-TP recovery in a ring must protect unidirectional P2MP
          transport paths.</t>
        </list></t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="arch" title="Architecture">
      <t>The overall architecture of the MPLS Transport Profile is defined in
      <xref target="RFC5921"></xref>. The architecture for point-to-multipoint
      MPLS-TP comprises the following additional elements and functions: <list
          style="symbols">
          <t>Unidirectional point-to-multipoint Label Switched Paths
          (LSPs)</t>

          <t>Unidirectional point-to-multipoint pseudowires (PWs)</t>

          <t>Optional point-to-multipoint LSP and PW control planes</t>

          <t>Survivability, network management, and Operations, Administration
          and Maintenance (OAM) functions for point-to-multipoint PWs and
          LSPs</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>The following subsections summarise the encapsulation and forwarding
      of point-to-multipoint traffic within an MPLS-TP network, and the
      encapsulation options for delivery of traffic to and from MPLS-TP
      Customer Edge devices when the network is providing a packet transport
      service.</t>

      <section title="MPLS-TP Encapsulation and Forwarding">
        <t>Packet encapsulation and forwarding for MPLS-TP point-to-multipoint
        LSPs is identical to that for MPLS-TE point-to-multipoint LSPs.
        MPLS-TE point-to-multipoint LSPs were introduced in <xref
        target="RFC4875"></xref> and the related data-plane behaviour was
        further clarified in <xref target="RFC5332"></xref>. MPLS-TP allows
        for both upstream-assigned and downstream-assigned labels for use with
        point-to-multipoint LSPs.</t>

        <t>Packet encapsulation and forwarding for point-to-multipoint PWs is
        currently being defined by the PWE3 Working Group <xref
        target="I-D.raggarwa-pwe3-p2mp-pw-encaps"></xref>.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="oam"
             title="Operations, Administration and Maintenance (OAM)">
      <t>The overall OAM architecture for MPLS-TP is defined in <xref
      target="RFC6371"></xref>, and P2MP OAM design considerations are
      described in Section 3.7 of that RFC.</t>

      <t>All the traffic sent over a P2MP transport path, including OAM
      packets generated by a MEP, is sent (multicast) from the root to all the
      leaves, thus every OAM packet is sent to all leaves, and thus can
      simultaneously instrument all the MEs in a P2MP MEG. If an OAM packet is
      to be processed by only one leaf, it requires information to indicate to
      all other leaves that the packet must be discarded. To address a packet
      to an intermediate node in the tree, TTL based addressing is used to set
      the radius and addressing information in the OAM payload is used to
      identify the specific destination node.</t>

      <t>P2MP paths are unidirectional; therefore, any return path to an
      originating MEP for on-demand transactions will be out-of-band. Out of
      band return paths are discussed in Section 3.8 of <xref
      target="RFC5921"></xref>.</t>

      <t>Packet Loss and Delay Measurement for MPLS Networks <xref
      target="RFC6374"></xref> already considers the P2MP case and it is not
      thought that any change is needed to the MPLS-TP profile of <xref
      target="RFC6374"></xref> <xref target="RFC6375"></xref>.</t>

      <t>[Editor's note: Additional information / text has been published in
      <xref target="I-D.hmk-mpls-tp-p2mp-oam-framework"></xref>. The Editors
      will coordinate with the draft authors to identify which text should be
      folded into this document and which should remain in a standalone
      document.]</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="cp" title="Control Plane">
      <t>The framework for the MPLS-TP control plane is provided in <xref
      target="RFC6373"></xref>. This document reviews MPLS-TP control plane
      requirements as well as provides details on how the MPLS-TP control
      plane satisfies these requirements. Most of the requirements identified
      in <xref target="RFC6373"> </xref> apply equally to P2P and P2MP
      transport paths. The key P2MP specific control plane requirements are
      identified in requirement 6 (P2MP transport paths), 34 (use P2P
      sub-layers), 49 (common recovery solutions for P2P and P2MP), 59 (1+1
      protection), 62 (1:n protection), and 65 (1:n shared mesh recovery).</t>

      <t><xref target="RFC6373"></xref> defines the control plane approach
      used to support MPLS-TP transport paths. It identifies Generalized MPLS
      (GMPLS) as the control plane for MPLS-TP Label Switched Paths (LSPs) and
      Targeted LDP (T-LDP) as the control plane for pseudowires (PWs). MPLS-TP
      allows that either, or both, LSPs and PWs to be provisioned statically
      or via a control plane. As noted in <xref target="RFC6373"></xref>:</t>

      <t>The PW and LSP control planes, collectively, must satisfy the MPLS-TP
      control-plane requirements. As with P2P services, when P2MP client
      services are provided directly via LSPs, all requirements must be
      satisfied by the LSP control plane. When client services are provided
      via PWs, the PW and LSP control planes can operate in combination, and
      some functions may be satisfied via the PW control plane while others
      are provided to PWs by the LSP control plane. This is particularly
      noteworthy for P2MP recovery.</t>

      <section title="Point-to-Multipoint LSP Control Plane">
        <t>The MPLS-TP control plane for point-to-multipoint LSPs uses GMPLS
        and is based on Resource Reservation Protocol - Traffic Engineering
        (RSVP-TE) for point-to-multipoint LSPs as defined in <xref
        target="RFC4875"></xref>. A detailed listing of how GMPLS satisfies
        MPLS-TP control plane requirements is provided in <xref
        target="RFC6373"></xref>.</t>

        <t>Per <xref target="RFC6373"></xref>, the definitions of P2MP, <xref
        target="RFC4875"></xref>, and GMPLS recovery, <xref
        target="RFC4872"></xref> and <xref target="RFC4873"></xref>, do not
        explicitly cover their interactions. MPLS-TP requires a formal
        definition of recovery techniques for P2MP LSPs. Such a formal
        definition will be based on existing RFCs and may not require any new
        protocol mechanisms but, nonetheless, should be documented. Protection
        of P2MP LSPs is also discussed in <xref target="RFC6372"></xref>
        Section 4.7.3.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Point-to-Multipoint PW Control Plane">
        <t>The MPLS-TP control plane for point-to-multipoint PWs uses the LDP
        P2MP signaling extensions for PWs defined in <xref
        target="I-D.ietf-pwe3-p2mp-pw"></xref>. This definition is limited to
        single segment PWs and is based on LDP <xref target="RFC5036"></xref>
        with upstream-assigned labels <xref target="RFC5331"></xref>. The
        document does not address recovery of P2MP PWs. Such recovery can be
        provided via P2MP LSP recovery as generally discussed in <xref
        target="RFC6372"></xref>. Alternatively, PW recovery <xref
        target="RFC6718"></xref> can be extended to explicitly support
        recovery of P2MP PWs.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="survive" title="Survivability">
      <t>The overall survivability architecture for MPLS-TP is defined in
      <xref target="RFC6372"></xref>, and section 4.7.3 in particular
      describes the application of linear protection to unidirectional P2MP
      entities using 1+1 and 1:1 protection architecture. For 1+1, the
      approach is for the root of the P2MP tree to bridge the user traffic to
      both the working and protection entities. Each sink/leaf MPLS-TP node
      selects the traffic from one entity according to some predetermined
      criteria. For 1:1, the source/root MPLS-TP node needs to identify the
      existence of a fault condition on any of the branches of the network.
      Fault notification happens from the node identifying the fault to the
      root node and from the leaves to the root via an out of band path. In
      either case the root then selects the protection transport path for
      traffic transfer. More sophisticated survivability approaches such as
      partial tree protection and 1:n protection are for further study.</t>

      <t>The IETF has no experience with P2MP PW survivability as yet, and
      therefore it is proposed that the P2MP PW survivability will initially
      rely on the LSP survivability. Further work is needed on this subject,
      particularly if a requirement emerges to provide survivability for P2MP
      PWs in an MPLS-TP context.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="nm" title="Network Management">
      <t>The network management architecture and requirements for MPLS-TP are
      specified in <xref target="RFC5951"></xref>. They derive from the
      generic specifications described in ITU-T G.7710/Y.1701 <xref
      target="G.7710"></xref> for transport technologies. They also
      incorporate the OAM requirements for MPLS Networks <xref
      target="RFC4377"></xref> and MPLS-TP Networks <xref
      target="RFC5860"></xref> and expand on those requirements to cover the
      modifications necessary for fault, configuration, performance, and
      security in a transport network.</t>

      <t>[Editor's note: Decide what if anything needs to be said about
      P2MP-specific network management considerations.]</t>

      <t>Section 3.14 of " Framework for MPLS in Transport Networks" <xref
      target="RFC5921"></xref> describe the aspects of network management in
      the P2P MPLS-TP case. This apply to the P2MP case.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Security Considerations">
      <t>General security considerations for MPLS-TP are covered in <xref
      target="RFC5921"></xref>. Additional security considerations for
      point-to-multipoint LSPs are provided in <xref target="RFC4875"></xref>.
      This document introduces no new security considerations beyond those
      covered in those documents.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>IANA considerations resulting from specific elements of MPLS-TP
      functionality are detailed in the documents specifying that
      functionality. This document introduces no additional IANA
      considerations in itself.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.5654'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.5921'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.4875'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.4873'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.4872'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.5332'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.5036'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.5331'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6374'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6375'?>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.5860'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6371'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6373'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.5951'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6372'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-pwe3-p2mp-pw'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-l2vpn-vpms-frmwk-requirements'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-pwe3-p2mp-pw-requirements'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.raggarwa-pwe3-p2mp-pw-encaps'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6718'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.4377'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.hmk-mpls-tp-p2mp-oam-framework'?>

      <reference anchor="G.7710">
        <front>
          <title>Common equipment management function requirements</title>

          <author>
            <organization>ITU-T Recommendation G.7710/Y.1701
            (07/2007)</organization>
          </author>

          <date year="2007" />
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="G.780">
        <front>
          <title>Terms and definitions for synchronous digital hierarchy (SDH)
          networks</title>

          <author>
            <organization>ITU-T Recommendation G.780//Y.1351
            (07/2010)</organization>
          </author>

          <date year="2010" />
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="G.798">
        <front>
          <title>Characteristics of optical transport network hierarchy
          equipment functional blocks</title>

          <author>
            <organization>ITU-T Recommendation G.798 (10/2010)</organization>
          </author>

          <date year="2010" />
        </front>
      </reference>
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
