<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<rfc category="exp" docName=" draft-ietf-nvo3-security-requirements-01"
     ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="NVO3 security">Security Requirements of NVO3</title>

    <author fullname="Sam Hartman" initials="S." surname="Hartman">
      <organization>Painless Security</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>356 Abbott Street</street>

          <city>North Andover</city>

          <region>MA</region>

          <code>01845</code>

          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>

        <email>hartmans@painless-security.com</email>

        <uri>http://www.painless-security.com</uri>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Dacheng Zhang" initials="D." surname="Zhang">
      <organization>Huawei</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street/>

          <city>Beijing</city>

          <region/>

          <code/>

          <country>China</country>
        </postal>

        <phone/>

        <facsimile/>

        <email>zhangdacheng@huawei.com</email>

        <uri/>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Margaret Wasserman" initials="M." surname="Wasserman">
      <organization>Painless Security</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>356 Abbott Street</street>

          <city>North Andover</city>

          <region>MA</region>

          <code>01845</code>

          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>

        <phone>+1 781 405 7464</phone>

        <email>mrw@painless-security.com</email>

        <uri>http://www.painless-security.com</uri>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date day="21" month="October" year="2013"/>

    <abstract>
      <t>The draft provides a list of security requirements to benefit the
      design of NOV3 security mechanisms. In addition, this draft introduces
      the candidate techniques which could be used to fulfill such security
      requirements.</t>

      <t/>
    </abstract>

    <note title="Requirements Language">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
      document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
      target="RFC2119">RFC 2119</xref>.</t>
    </note>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>Security is a key issue which needs to be considered in the design of
      a data center network. This document discusses the security risks that a
      NVO3 network may encounter and the security requirements that a NVO3
      network needs to fulfill. In addition, this draft attempts to discuss
      the security techniques which could be applied to fulfill such
      requirements.</t>

      <t>The remainder of this document is organized as follows. Section 2
      introduces the terms used in this memo. Section 3 gives a briefly
      introduction of the NVO3 network architecture. Section 4 discusses the
      attack model of this work. <xref target="Requirements"/> describes the
      essential security requirements which should be fulfilled in the
      generation of a NVO3 network. </t>

      <t/>
    </section>

    <section title="Terminology">
      <t>This document uses the same terminology as found in the NVO3
      Framework document <xref target="I-D.ietf-nvo3-framework"/> and <xref
      target="I-D.kreeger-nvo3-hypervisor-nve-cp"/>. Some of the terms defined
      in the framework document have been repeated in this section for the
      convenience of the reader, along with additional terminology that is
      used by this document.</t>

      <t>Tenant System (TS): A physical or virtual system that can play the
      role of a host, or a forwarding element such as a router, switch,
      firewall, etc. It belongs to a single tenant and connects to one or more
      VNs of that tenant.</t>

      <t>End System (ES): An end system of a tenant, which can be, e.g., a
      virtual machine(VM), a non-virtualized server, or a physical appliance.
      A TS is attached to a Network Virtualization Edge(NVE) node.</t>

      <t>Network Virtualization Edge (NVE): An NVE implements network
      virtualization functions that allow for L2/L3 tenant separation and
      tenant-related control plane activity. An NVE contains one or more
      tenant service instances whereby a TS interfaces with its associated
      instance. The NVE also provides tunneling overlay functions.</t>

      <t>Virtual Network (VN): This is a virtual L2 or L3 domain that belongs
      to a tenant.</t>

      <t>Network Virtualization Authority (NVA). A back-end system that is
      responsible for distributing and maintaining the mapping information for
      the entire overlay system. Note that the WG never reached consensus on
      what to call this architectural entity within the overlay system, so
      this term is subject to change. </t>

      <t>NVO3 device: In this memo, the devices (e.g., NVE and NVA) work
      cooperatively to provide NVO3 overlay functionalities are called as NOV3
      devices. </t>
    </section>

    <section title="NVO3 Overlay Architecture">
      <t/>

      <t><figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[

                   ..................................
                   .                                .
                   .                                .
                   .                                .
                 +-+--+                          +--+-++--------+
 +--------+      | NV |                          | NV || Tenant |
 | Tenant +------+Edge|       L3 Overlay         |Edge|| System |
 | System |      +-+--+        Network           +--+-++--------+
 +--------+        .                                .
                   .                                .
                   .                                .
                   ..................................

]]></artwork>
        </figure>This figure illustrates a simple nov3 overlay example where
      NVEs provide a logical L2/L3 interconnect for the TSes that belong to a
      specific tenant network over L3 networks. A packet from a tenant system
      is encapsulated when they reach the egress NVE. Then encapsulated packet
      is then sent to the remote NVE through a proper tunnel. When reaching
      the ingress NVE, the packet is decapsulated and forwarded to the target
      tenant system. The address advertisements and tunnel mappings are
      distributed among the NVEs through either distributed control protocols
      or by certain centralized servers (called NVAs).</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="ThreatModel" title="Threat Model">
      <t>To benefit the discussion, in this analysis work, attacks are
      classified into two categories: inside attacks and outside attacks. An
      attack is considered as an inside attack if the adversary performing the
      attack (inside attacker or insider) has got certain privileges in
      changing the configuration or software of a NVO3 device and initiates
      the attack within the overlay security perimeter. In contrast, an attack
      is referred to as an outside attack if the adversary performing the
      attack (outside attacker or outsider) has no such privilege and can only
      initiate the attacks from compromised TSes (or the network devices of
      the underlying network which the overlay is located upon). Note that in
      a complex attack inside and outside attacking operations may be
      performed in a well organized way to expand the damages caused by the
      attack.</t>

      <section title="Outsider Capabilities">
        <t>The following capabilities of outside attackers MUST be considered
        in the design of a NOV3 security mechanism:</t>

        <t><list style="numbers">
            <t>Eavesdropping on the packets,</t>

            <t>Replaying the intercepted packets, and</t>

            <t>Generating illegal packets and injecting them into the
            network.</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>With a successful outside attack, an attacker may be able to:<list
            style="numbers">
            <t>Analyze the traffic pattern within the network,</t>

            <t>Disrupt the network connectivity or degrade the network service
            quality, or</t>

            <t>Access the contents of the data/control packets if they are not
            properly encrypted.</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>

      <section title="Insider Capabilities">
        <t>It is assumed that an inside attacker can perform any types of
        outside attacks from the inside or outside of the overlay perimeter.
        In addition, in an inside attack, an attacker may use already obtained
        privilege to, for instance,</t>

        <t><list style="numbers">
            <t>Interfere with the normal operations of the overlay as a legal
            entity, by sending packets containing invalid information or with
            improper frequencies,</t>

            <t>Perform spoofing attacks and impersonate another legal device
            to communicate with victims using the cryptographic information it
            obtained, and</t>

            <t>Access the contents of the data/control packets if they are
            encrypted with the keys held by the attacker.</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>

      <section title="Security Issues In Scope and Out of Scope">
        <t>During the specification of security requirements, the following
        security issues needs to be considered:</t>

        <t><list style="numbers">
            <t>Insecure underlying network. It is normally assumed that a
            underlying network connecting NOV3 devices (NVEs and NVAs) is
            secure if it is located within a data center and cannot be
            directly accessed by tenants. However, in a virtual data center
            scenario, a NVO3 overlay scatters across different sites which are
            connected through the public network. Outside attacks may be
            raised from the underlying network.</t>

            <t>Insider attacker. During the design of a security solution for
            a NVO3 network, the inside attacks raised from compromised NVO3
            devices (NVEs and NVAs) needs to be considered.</t>

            <t>Insecure tenant network. It is reasonable to consider the
            conditions where the network connecting TSes and NVEs is
            accessible to outside attackers.</t>
          </list>The following issues are out of scope of cosideration in this
        document:</t>

        <t><list style="numbers">
            <t>In this memo it is assumed that security protocols, algorithms,
            and implementations provide the security properties for which they
            are designed; attacks depending on a failure of this assumption
            are out of scope. As an example, an attack caused by a weakness in
            a cryptographic algorithm is out of scope, while an attack caused
            by failure to use confidentiality when confidentiality is a
            security requirement is in scope.</t>

            <t>In practice an attacker controlling an underlying network
            device may break the communication of the overlays by discarding
            or delaying the delivery of the packets passing through it.
            However, this type of attack is out of scope.</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Requirements"
             title="Security Requirements and Candidate Approaches">
      <t>This section introduces the security requirements and candidate
      solutions.</t>

      <section title="Control/Data Traffic within Overlay">
        <t>This section analyzes the security issues in the control and data
        plans of a NVO3 overlay.</t>

        <section title="Control Plane Security">
          <t><list style="hanging">
              <t hangText="REQ1:">A NVO3 security solution MUST enable two
              NOV3 devices (NVE or NVA) to perform mutual authentication
              before exchanging control packets.</t>

              <t hangText="">This requirement is used to prevent an attacker
              from impersonating a legal NVO3 device and sending out bogus
              control packets without being detected.</t>

              <t hangText="">The authentication between devices can be
              performed as a part of automated key management protocols (e.g.,
              IKEv2<xref target="RFC5996"/>, EAP<xref target="RFC4137"/>,
              etc.). After such an authentication procedure, an device can
              find out whether its peer holds valid security credentials and
              is the one who it has claimed. Additionally, the keys shared
              between the devices can be also used for the authentication
              purpose. For instance, assumed a NVE and a NVA have shared a
              secret key without known by any other third parties. The NVE can
              ensure that a device that it is communicating with is the NVA if
              the device can prove that it possesses the shared key. </t>

              <t hangText="">a: The identity of the network devices SHOULD be
              verified during authentication. </t>

              <t hangText="">In some authentication mechanisms, instead of
              verifying the peers' identities, the authentication result can
              only prove that a device joining the authentication is a legal
              member of a group. However, for a better damage confining
              capability to insider attacker, it is recommended to verify the
              devices' identities during authentication. Therefore, an insider
              attacker cannot impersonate others, even when it holds legal
              credentials or keys.</t>
            </list></t>

          <t><list style="hanging">
              <t hangText="REQ2:">Before accepting a control packet, the
              device receiving the packet MUST verify whether the packet comes
              from one which has the privilege to send that packet.</t>

              <t hangText="">This is an authorization requirement. A device
              needs to clarify the roles (e.g., a NVE or a NVA) that its
              authentication peer acts as in the overlay. Therefore, if a
              compromised NVE uses it credentials to impersonate a NVA to
              communicate with other NVEs, it will be detected. In addition,
              authorization is important for enforcing the VN isolation, a
              device only can distribute control packets within the VNs it is
              involved within. If a control packet about a VN is sent from a
              NVE which is not authorized to support the VN, the packet will
              not be accepted</t>

              <t hangText="">Normally, it is assumed that the access control
              operations are based on the authentication results. The simple
              authorization mechanisms (such as ACLs which filters packets
              based on the packet addresses) can be used as auxiliary
              approaches since they are relatively easy to bypass if attackers
              can access to the network and modify packets. </t>
            </list></t>

          <t><list style="hanging">
              <t hangText="REQ3:">Integrity, confidentiality, and origin
              Authentication protection for Control traffics</t>

              <t>It is the responsibility of a NVO3 overlay to protect the
              control packets transported over the overlay against the attacks
              raised from the underlying network. </t>

              <t>a: The integrity and origin authentication of the packets
              MUST be guaranteed. </t>

              <t>With this requirement, the receiver can ensure that the
              packets are from the legitimate sender, not replayed, and not
              modified during the transportation. </t>

              <t>b: The signaling packets SHOULD be encrypted.</t>

              <t>On many occasions, the signaling packets can be transported
              in plaintext. However, In the cases where the information
              contained within the signaling packets are sensitive or valuable
              to attackers , the signaling packets related with that tenant
              need be encrypted. </t>

              <t>To achieve such objectives, when the network devices exchange
              control plane packets, integrated security mechanisms or
              underlying security protocols need to provided. In addition,
              cryptographic keys need to be deployed manually in advance or
              dynamically generated by using certain automatic key management
              protocols (e.g., TLS <xref target="RFC5246"/>). The keys are
              used to generate digests for or encrypt control packets.</t>
            </list></t>

          <t><list style="hanging">
              <t hangText="REQ4:">The toleration of DOS attacks</t>

              <t>a: Frequency in distributing control packets within in the
              overlay MUST be limited.</t>

              <t>The issues within DOS attacks also need to be considered in
              designing the overlay control plane. For instance, in the VXLAN
              solution<xref target="I-D.mahalingam-dutt-dcops-vxlan"/>, an
              attacker attached to a NVE can try to manipulate the NVE to keep
              multicasting control packets by sending a large amount of ARP
              packets to query the inexistent VMs. In order to mitigate this
              type of attack, the NVEs SHOULD be only allowed to send
              signaling packet in the overlay with a limited frequency. When
              there are centralized servers (e.g., the backend oracles
              providing mapping information for NVEs<xref
              target="I-D.ietf-nvo3-overlay-problem-statement"/>, or the SDN
              controllers) are located within the overlay, the potential
              security risks caused by DDOS attack on such servers can be more
              serious.</t>

              <t>b: Mitigation of amplification attacks SHOULD be
              provided.</t>

              <t>During the design of the control plane, it is important to
              consider the amplification effects. For instance, if NVEs may
              generate a large response to a short request, an attacker may
              send spoofed requests to the NVEs with the source address of a
              victim. Then the NVEs will send the response to the victim and
              result in DDOS attacks.</t>

              <t>If the amplification effect cannot be avoided in the control
              protocol, the requirements 1,2,3, and 4a can all be used to
              benefit the mitigation of this type of attacks.</t>
            </list><list style="hanging">
              <t hangText="REQ5:">The key management solution MUST be able to
              confine the scope of key distribution and provide different keys
              to isolate the control traffic according to different security
              requirements.</t>

              <t hangText="">a: It SHOULD be guaranteed that different keys
              are used to secure the control packets exchanged within
              different tenant networks.</t>

              <t hangText="">This requirement can be used to provide a basic
              attack confinement capability. The compromise of a NVE working
              within a tenant will not result in the key leakage of other
              tenant networks.</t>

              <t hangText="">b: It SHOULD be guaranteed that different keys
              are used to secure the control packets exchanges with different
              VNs.</t>

              <t hangText="">This requirement can be used to provide a better
              attack confinement capability for the control plane. The
              compromise of a NVE working within a VN will not result in the
              key leakage of other VNs. However, since there is only a single
              key used for securing the data traffic within a VN, an attacker
              which has compromised a NVE within the VN may be able to
              impersonate any other NVEs within the VN to send out bogus
              control packets. In addition, the key management overheads
              introduced by key revocation also need to be considered<xref
              target="RFC4046"/>. When a NVE stops severing a VN, the key used
              for the VN needs to be revoked, and a new key needs to be
              distributed for the NVO3 devices still within the VN.</t>

              <t hangText="">If we expect to provide a even stronger
              confinement capability and prevent a compromised NVE from
              impersonating other NVEs even when they are in the same VN,
              different NVEs working inside a VN need to secure their
              signaling packets with different keys. </t>

              <t hangText="">If there is automated key management deployed,
              the authentication and authorization can be used to largely
              mitigate the isolation issues. When a NVE attempts to join a VN,
              the NVE needs to be authenticated and prove that it have
              sufficient privileges. Then, a new key (or a set of keys) will
              be generated to secure its control packet exchanged with this
              VN. </t>
            </list></t>

          <t/>
        </section>

        <section title="Data Plane">
          <t><xref target="I-D.ietf-nvo3-framework"/> specifies a NVO3 overlay
          needs to generate tunnels between NVEs for data transportation. When
          a data packet reaches the boundary of a overlay, it will be
          encapsulated and forwarded to the destination NVE through a proper
          tunnel.</t>

          <t><list style="hanging">
              <t hangText="REQ6:">Integrity, confidentiality, and origin
              authentication protection for data traffics</t>

              <t>a: The integrity and origin authentication of data traffics
              MUST be guaranteed when the underlying network is not
              secure.</t>

              <t>During the transportation of data packets, it is the
              responsibility of the NVO3 overlay to deal with the attacks from
              the underlying network. For instance, an inside attacker
              compromising a underlying network device may intercept an
              encapsulated data packet transported within a tunnel, modify the
              contents in the encapsulating tunnel packet and, transfer it
              into another tunnel without being detected. When the modified
              packet reaches a NVE, the NVE may decapsulated the data packet
              and forward it into a VN according to the information within the
              encapsulating header generated by the attacker. Similarly, a
              compromised NVE may try to redirect the data packets within a VN
              into another VN by adding improper encapsulating tunnel headers
              to the data packets. </t>

              <t>Under such circumstances, in order to enforce the VN
              isolation property, underlying security protocols need to
              provided. Signatures or digests need to be generated for both
              data packets and the encapsulating tunnel headers in order to
              provide data origin authentication and integrity protection.</t>

              <t>b: The confidentiality protection of data traffics SHOULD be
              provided, when the underlying network is not secure.</t>

              <t>If the data traffics from the TSes is sensitive, they needs
              to be encrypted during the tunnels. However, if the data
              traffics is not valuable and sensitive, the encryption is not
              necessary.</t>
            </list><list style="hanging">
              <t hangText="REQ7:">Different tunnels SHOULD be secured with
              different keys</t>

              <t>This requirement can be used to provide a basic attack
              confinement capability. When different tunnels secured with
              different keys, the compromise of a key in a tunnel will not
              affect the security of others. </t>
            </list></t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section title="Control/Data Traffic between NVEs and Hypervisors">
        <t>Assume there is a VNE providing a logical L2/L3 interconnect for a
        set of TSes. Apart from data traffics, the NVE and certain TSes (i.e.,
        Hypervisors) also need to exchange signaling packets in order to
        facilitate, e.g., VM online detection, VM migration detection, or
        auto-provisioning/service discovery <xref
        target="I-D.ietf-nvo3-framework"/>.</t>

        <t>The NVE and its associated TSes can be deployed in a distributed
        way (e.g., a NVE is implemented in an individual device, and VMs are
        located on servers) or in a co-located way (e.g., a NVE and the TSes
        it serves are located on the same server).</t>

        <section title="Distributed Deployment of NVE and Hypervisor">
          <t>In this case, the data and control traffic between the NVE and
          the TSes are exchanged over network.</t>

          <section title="Control Plane">
            <t><list style="hanging">
                <t hangText="REQ8:">Mutual authentication MUST be performed
                between a NVE and a TS at the beginning of their
                communication, if the network connecting them is not secure.
                </t>

                <t hangText="">Mutual authentication is used to guarantee that
                an attacker cannot impersonate a legal NVE or a hypervisor
                without being detected.</t>

                <t hangText="">There are various ways to perform mutual
                authentication. If there are auto key management mechanism
                (e.g., IKEv2, EAP), the NVE and the TS can use their
                credential to perform authentication. If there a key
                pre-distributed between a NVE and a TS, an entity can also use
                the key verify the identity of is remote peer. </t>

                <t hangText="">If practice, a NVE and a TS may simply use IP
                or MAC addresses to identify each other. This type of
                technique can be used as a complementary approach although it
                may becomes vulnerable if attackers can inject bogus control
                packets the network and modify the packets transported between
                the NVE and TS. </t>
              </list><list style="hanging">
                <t hangText="REQ9:">Before accepting a control packet, the
                receiver device MUST verify whether the packet comes from one
                which has the privilege to send that packet.</t>

                <t hangText="">This is an authorization requirement. A device
                needs to clarify the roles (e.g., a TS or a NVE) of the device
                that it is communicating with. Therefore, if a compromised TS
                attempts to use it credentials to impersonate a NVE to
                communicate with other TSes, it will be detected.</t>

                <t hangText="">Authorization is very important to guarantee
                the isolation property. For instance, if a compromised
                hypervisor tries to elevate its privilege and interfere the
                VNs that it is not supposed to be involved within, its attempt
                will be detected and rejected. </t>

                <t hangText="">Normally, it is assumed that the access control
                operations are based on the authentication results. The simple
                authorization mechanisms (such as ACLs which filters packets
                based on the packet addresses) can be used as complementary
                solutions. </t>
              </list></t>

            <t><list style="hanging">
                <t hangText="REQ10:">Integrity, Confidentiality, and Origin
                Authentication for Control Packets</t>

                <t hangText="">a:The security solution of a NVE network MUST
                be able to provide integrity protection and origin
                authentication for the control packets exchanged between a NVE
                and a TS if they have to use an insecure network to transport
                their packet. </t>

                <t hangText="">This requirement can prevent an attacker from
                illegally interfere with the normal operations of NVEs and
                TSes by injecting bogus control packets into the network.</t>

                <t hangText="">b:The confidentiality protection for the
                control packet exchange SHOULD be provided.</t>

                <t hangText="">When the contents of the control packets (e.g.,
                the location of a ES, when a VM migration happens) are
                sensitive to a tenant, the control packet needs to be
                encrypted. </t>

                <t hangText="">There are various security protocols (such as
                IPsec, SSL, and TCP-AO) can be used for transport control
                packets. In addition, it is possible to define integrated
                security solutions for the control packets.</t>

                <t hangText="">In order to secure the control traffic,
                cryptographic keys need to be distributed to generate digests
                or signatures for the control packets. Such cryptographic keys
                can be manually deployed in advance or dynamically generated
                with certain automatic key management protocols (e.g., TLS
                <xref target="RFC5246"/>). </t>
              </list><list style="hanging">
                <t hangText="REQ11:">The key management solution MUST be able
                to confine the scope of key distribution and provide different
                keys to isolate the control traffic according to different
                security requirements. </t>

                <t>a: If assuming TSes (hypervisors) will not be compromised,
                the TSes belonging to different Tenants MUST use different
                keys to secure the control packet exchanges with their NVE.
                </t>

                <t>This requirement is used to enforce the security boundaries
                of different tenant networks. Since different tenants belong
                to different security domains and may be competitive to each
                other, the control plane traffics need to be carefully
                isolated so that an attacker from a tenant cannot affect the
                operations of another tenant network.</t>

                <t>b: If assuming the hypervisors can be compromised, the TSes
                belonging to different VNs MUST use different keys to secure
                the control packets exchanges with their NVE. </t>

                <t>Therefore, if a key used for a VN is compromised, other VNs
                will not be affected. This requirement is used to ensure the
                VN isolation property. </t>
              </list></t>
          </section>

          <section title="Data Plane">
            <t><list style="hanging">
                <t hangText="REQ12:">The data traffic isolation of different
                VNs MUST be guaranteed.</t>

                <t>In <xref
                target="I-D.ietf-nvo3-overlay-problem-statement"/>, the data
                plane isolation requirement amongst different VNs has been
                discussed. The traffic within a virtual network can only be
                transited into another one in a controlled fashion (e.g., via
                a configured router and/or a security gateway). Therefore, if
                the NVE supports multiple VNs concurrently, the data traffic
                in different VNs MUST be isolated.</t>

                <t>a:The security solution of a NVE network MUST be able to
                provide integrity protection and origin authentication for the
                data packets exchanged between a NVE and a TS if they have to
                use an insecure network to transport their data packet.</t>

                <t>In practice, the data traffics in different VNs can be
                isolated physically or by using VPN technologies. If the
                network connecting the NVE and the TSes is potentially
                accessible to attackers, security solutions need to be
                considered to prevent an attacker locating in the middle
                between the NVE and TS from modifying the VN identification
                information in the packet headers so as to manipulate the NVE
                to transport the data packets within a VN to another. The
                security protocols such as IPsec and TCP-AO, can be used to
                enforce the isolation property if necessary. </t>
              </list></t>

            <t>The key management requirement R11 can be applied here for data
            traffic</t>
          </section>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section title="Key Management ">
        <t><list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="REQ13:">A security solution for NVO3 SHOULD provide
            automated key management mechanisms.</t>

            <t hangText="">In the cases where there are a large amount of NVEs
            working within a NVO3 overlay, manual key management may become
            infeasible. First, it could be burdensome to deploy pre-shared
            keys for thousands of NVEs, not to mention that multiple keys may
            need to be deployed on a single device for different purposes. Key
            derivation can be used to mitigate this problem. Using key
            derivation functions, multiple keys for different usages can be
            derived from a pre-shared master key. However, key derivation
            cannot protect against the situation where a system was
            incorrectly trusted to have the key used to perform the
            derivation. If the master key were somehow compromised, all the
            resulting keys would need to be changed <xref target="RFC4301"/>.
            In addition, VM migration will introduce challenges to manual key
            management. The migration of a VM in a VN may cause the change of
            the NVEs which are involved within the NV. When a NVE is newly
            involved within a VN, it needs to get the key to join the
            operations within the VN. If a NVE stops supporting a VN, it
            should not keep the keys associated with that VN. All those key
            updates need to be performed at run time, and difficult to be
            handled by human beings. As a result, it is reasonable to
            introduce automated key management solutions such as EAP <xref
            target="RFC4137"/> for NVO3 overlays.</t>

            <t hangText="">Without the support automated key management
            mechanisms, some security functions of certain security protocols
            cannot work properly. For instance, the anti-replay mechanism of
            IPsec is turned off without the support of automated key
            management mechanisms. Therefore, if IPsec is selected to protect
            the control packets. In this case, the system may suffer from the
            replay attacks. </t>
          </list></t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>This document makes no request of IANA.</t>

      <t>Note to RFC Editor: this section may be removed on publication as an
      RFC.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>TBD</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>Thanks a lot for the comments from Melinda Shore, and Zu Qiang.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.2119'?>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-nvo3-overlay-problem-statement'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-ipsecme-ad-vpn-problem'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.mahalingam-dutt-dcops-vxlan'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-nvo3-framework'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.kreeger-nvo3-hypervisor-nve-cp'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.4137'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.4301'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.4046'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.5996'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.5246'?>
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
