<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc toccompact="no" ?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes" ?>
<?rfc tocappendix="yes" ?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="no" ?>
<?rfc strict="no" ?>
<?rfc rfcedstyle="yes" ?>
<rfc category="info" docName="draft-montenegro-hybi-upgrade-hello-handshake-00" ipr="trust200902">

<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="rfc2629.xslt" ?>

<front>
    <title abbrev="WebSocket Upgrade+Hello Handshake">
	WebSocket Upgrade+Hello Handshake
    </title>

    <author initials="G." surname="Wilkins" fullname="Greg Wilkins" role="">
      <organization>WebTide</organization>
      <address>
        <email>gregw@webtide.com</email>
      </address>
      </author>

      <author initials="G." surname="Montenegro" fullname="Gabriel Montenegro" role="">
      <organization>Microsoft Corporation</organization>
      <address>
        <email>gabriel.montenegro@microsoft.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>





        <date year="2010"/>
        <area>APP</area>
        <workgroup>HYBI Working Group</workgroup>
        <keyword>HTTP</keyword>
        <keyword>WebSocket</keyword>

	<abstract>
	<t>
	This document defines the 'Upgrade+Hello' handshake for the Websocket protocol. 

	</t>
        </abstract>

    <note title="Requirements Language">
        <t>The key words &quot;MUST&quot;, &quot;MUST NOT&quot;,
        &quot;REQUIRED&quot;, &quot;SHALL&quot;, &quot;SHALL NOT&quot;,
        &quot;SHOULD&quot;, &quot;SHOULD NOT&quot;, &quot;RECOMMENDED&quot;,
        &quot;MAY&quot;, and &quot;OPTIONAL&quot; in this document are to be
        interpreted as described in <xref target="RFC2119">RFC 2119</xref>.
        </t>
</note>
</front>


<middle>

<section title="Introduction"> 
	<t>

		As of version 3 of the websocket (WS) protocol 
		<xref target="I-D.ietf-hybi-thewebsocketprotocol"/>, the handshake used to 
	transition from HTTP to Websocket protocol is deficient with respect to
	HTTP compatibility and security. Accordingly, much discussion has ensued
	to try to define the replacement handshake for adoption by the WG.  
	</t>

	<t>
	The handshake defined in this document maintains compatibility with HTTP 
	in accordance with <xref target="I-D.ietf-hybi-websocket-requirements"/>
	while protecting against currently known vulnerabilities. It leverages the 
	'GET+Upgrade' approach in the current handshake, in addition to several 
	other mechanisms, as detailed below.
	</t>

	<t>
	An initial version of this handshake has been previously shared with the working group (http://www.ietf.org/mail-archive/web/hybi/current/msg04534.html).
	</t>

</section>

<section title="Terminology">

<t>
	This document uses HyBi-related terms as defined in
	<xref target="I-D.ietf-hybi-websocket-requirements"/>.</t>
</section>


<section title="Upgrade+Hello Handshake"> 
	<t>
		The Upgrade+Hello handshake implements the following mechanisms:
	</t>


<t>
<list style="letters">
		<t>
Use Websocket Hello from the server and a Websocket Hello from the client, 
using Websocket frames to transport hashed nonces (rather than unframed bytes). 
This fixes the issue with intermediaries not forwarding the unframed bytes
on the wire and makes the handshake comply with the requirement to be
HTTP/1.1 compliant up through the 101 response from the server.
		</t>
		<t>
Include a server nonce in the server-sent Hello, that the client
must hash and return in its Hello.
		</t>
		<t>
Use a Hello frame type instead of ping/pong.
This does not require an extra round trip.
It just ensures that the first frame in each direction is something that is
entirely not HTTP and uses the Websocket binary framing instead.
		</t>
		<t>
Replace the char/space encoding of the client nonce with simple hex encoding.
		</t>
		<t>
Define tight restrictions on the punctuation that can be sent in ws
URLs and subprotocols (e.g., prohibit use of ':' ) so that they cannot be
used to inject HTTP headers.  While not as robust as encrypting the
handshakes, these restrictions will provide substantial protection
against user provided data being used as part of an attack.
		</t>
		<t>
Invert the framing MORE bit to be a FIN bit, so that WS control
frames will start with a non-ascii character. This mitigates the
attack vector affecting some intermediaries (transparent proxies, load balancers, etc)
that have been known to continue parsing the traffic (incorrectly assuming it is
still HTTP) even after the handshake.
		</t>
		<t>
TODO: Change use of MD5 to SHA1. Note the use in a "Challenge-Response" manner is not 
considered susceptible to recent attacks against these hash families per RFC4270, but 
still makes sense to migrate away from MD5 if nothing else for easier deployment.
		</t>
</list>
</t>

<t>
	The above summarizes the changes. The following sections show the text changes that implement the above
	mechanisms, in traditional "OLD" and "NEW" IETF notation. 
</t>
 

</section>





<section title="Changes to 1.2.  Protocol overview">
<t>
OLD:
</t>
<figure><artwork>
        GET /demo HTTP/1.1
        Host: example.com
        Connection: Upgrade
        Sec-WebSocket-Key2: 12998 5 Y3 1  .P00
        Sec-WebSocket-Protocol: sample
        Upgrade: WebSocket
        Sec-WebSocket-Key1: 4 @1  46546xW%0l 1 5
        Origin: http://example.com

        ^n:ds[4U

   The handshake from the server looks as follows:


        HTTP/1.1 101 WebSocket Protocol Handshake
        Upgrade: WebSocket
        Connection: Upgrade
        Sec-WebSocket-Origin: http://example.com
        Sec-WebSocket-Location: ws://example.com/demo
        Sec-WebSocket-Protocol: sample

        8jKS'y:G*Co,Wxa-
</artwork></figure>
<t>
NEW:
</t>
<figure><artwork>
        GET /demo HTTP/1.1
        Host: example.com
        Connection: Upgrade
        Sec-WebSocket-Nonce: A23F2BCA452DDE01
        Sec-WebSocket-Protocol: sample
        Upgrade: WebSocket
        Origin: http://example.com
	Sec-WebSocket-Draft: 3


   The handshake from the server looks as follows:


        HTTP/1.1 101 Switching Protocols
        Upgrade: WebSocket
        Connection: Upgrade
        Sec-WebSocket-Origin: http://example.com
        Sec-WebSocket-Location: ws://example.com/demo
        Sec-WebSocket-Protocol: sample
</artwork></figure>

<t>
</t>

<t>
OLD:
</t>
<figure><artwork>
   Finally, after the last field, the client sends 10 bytes starting
   with 0x0D 0x0A and followed by 8 random bytes, part of a challenge,
   and the server sends 18 bytes starting with 0x0D 0x0A and followed by
   16 bytes consisting of a challenge response.  The details of this
   challenge and other parts of the handshake are described in the next
   section.

   Once the client and server have both sent their handshakes, and if
   the handshake was successful, then the data transfer part starts.
   This is a two-way communication channel where each side can,
   independently from the other, send data at will.
</artwork></figure>
<t>
NEW:
</t>
<figure><artwork>
   Once the client and server have both sent their handshakes, and if
   the handshake was successful, then the data transfer part starts.
   This is a two-way communication channel where each side can,
   independently from the other, send data at will.

   The first frame sent in both directions must be a Hello frame 
   containing digests to prove the handshakes have been processed. 
</artwork></figure>
</section>

<section title="Changes to 1.3.  Opening handshake">
<t>
OLD:
</t>

<figure><artwork>
   The opening handshake is intended to be compatible with HTTP-based
   server-side software, so that a single port can be used by both HTTP
   clients talking to that server and WebSocket clients talking to that
   server.  To this end, the WebSocket client's handshake appears to
   HTTP servers to be a regular GET request with an Upgrade offer:


        GET / HTTP/1.1
        Upgrade: WebSocket
        Connection: Upgrade

   Fields in the handshake are sent by the client in a random order; the
   order is not meaningful.
</artwork></figure>

<t>
NEW:
</t>

<t>
   The opening handshake is intended to be compatible with HTTP-based
   server-side software, so that a single port can be used by both HTTP
   clients talking to that server and WebSocket clients talking to that
   server.  To this end, the WebSocket client's handshake appears to
   HTTP servers to be a regular HTTP request with an Upgrade offer:
</t>
<figure><artwork>


        GET / HTTP/1.1
        Upgrade: WebSocket
        Connection: Upgrade

</artwork></figure>
<t>
   Any valid URI may be passed, except that the client must not send a
   handshake with a URI path that contain the character ':' or any
   control or whitspace characters in explicit or encoded form. This limits
   the possibility of using a websocket client to attack a vulnerable
   non WebSocket servers.
</t>

<t>
   Fields in the handshake are sent by the client in an unspecified order; the
   order is not meaningful.
</t>


<t>
</t>

<t>
OLD:
</t>

<figure><artwork><![CDATA[
   To prove that the handshake was received, the server has to take
   three pieces of information and combine them to form a response.  The
   first two pieces of information come from the |Sec-WebSocket-Key1|
   and |Sec-WebSocket-Key2| fields in the client handshake:


        Sec-WebSocket-Key1: 18x 6]8vM;54 *(5:  {   U1]8  z [  8
        Sec-WebSocket-Key2: 1_ tx7X d  <  nw  334J702) 7]o}` 0

   For each of these fields, the server has to take the digits from the
   value to obtain a number (in this case 1868545188 and 1733470270
   respectively), then divide that number by the number of spaces
   characters in the value (in this case 12 and 10) to obtain a 32-bit
   number (155712099 and 173347027).  These two resulting numbers are
   then used in the server handshake, as described below.

   The counting of spaces is intended to make it impossible to smuggle
   this field into the resource name; making this even harder is the
   presence of _two_ such fields, and the use of a newline as the only
   reliable indicator that the end of the key has been reached.  The use
   of random characters interspersed with the spaces and the numbers
   ensures that the implementor actually looks for spaces and newlines,
   instead of being treating any character like a space, which would
   make it again easy to smuggle the fields into the path and trick the
   server.  Finally, _dividing_ by this number of spaces is intended to
   make sure that even the most naive of implementations will check for
   spaces, since if ther server does not verify that there are some
   spaces, the server will try to divide by zero, which is usually fatal
   (a correct handshake will always have at least one space).

   The third piece of information is given after the fields, in the last
   eight bytes of the handshake, expressed here as they would be seen if
   interpreted as UTF-8:

        Tm[K T2u

   The concatenation of the number obtained from processing the |Sec-
   WebSocket-Key1| field, expressed as a big-endian 32 bit number, the
   number obtained from processing the |Sec-WebSocket-Key2| field, again
   expressed as a big-endian 32 bit number, and finally the eight bytes
   at the end of the handshake, form a 128 bit string whose MD5 sum is
   then used by the server to prove that it read the handshake.
]]></artwork></figure>

<t>
NEW:
</t>

<t>
   To prove that the handshake was received, the server has to initiate
   websocket communication with a Hello frame containing the MD5 hash of
   a random 64 bit client nonce generated by the client and sent as a
   hex encoded string in the Sec-WebSocket-Nonce field of the client
   handshake:
</t>
<figure><artwork><![CDATA[

        Sec-WebSocket-Nonce: A23F2BCA452DDE01

]]></artwork></figure>
<t>
   The server has to take 8 octets of the client nonce, append the octets
   of the ASCII string "WebSocket" and then append 8 octets of a randomly
   generated server nonce (eg 15F0D2278BCD457F).  The server nonce and the
   16 octet MD5 hash (eg Ee7eBe0c369cBf255a4451Fc58D7Cc4f) of the combined
   octets must be sent in a Hello frame as the first websocket frame from
   the server to the client:
</t>
<figure><artwork><![CDATA[
   
      8F18 15F0D2278BCD457F Ee7eBe0c369cBf255a4451Fc58D7Cc4f
]]></artwork></figure>

<t>
</t>

<t>
OLD:
</t>

<figure><artwork><![CDATA[
   After the fields, the server sends the aforementioned MD5 sum, a 16
   byte (128 bit) value, shown here as if interpreted as UTF-8:

        fQJ,fN/4F4!~K~MH

   This value depends on what the client sends, as described above.  If
   it doesn't match what the client is expecting, the client would
   disconnect.

   Having part of the handshake appear after the fields ensures that
   both the server and the client verify that the connection is not
   being interrupted by an HTTP intermediary such as a man-in-the-middle
   cache or proxy.
]]></artwork></figure>

<t>
NEW:
</t>

<t>
   After the fields, the server sends the aforementioned Hello frame 
   containing the 8 octets of the server nonce followed by the 16 
   octets of the MD5 digest.
</t>

<t>
   After receiving the server handshake, the client must wait for the
   following Hello frame and verify that the contents. The digest value 
   depends on both the client and server nonces, as described above.
   If it doesn't match what the client is expecting, the client must 
   disconnect.   Only after verifying the contents of the Hello frame
   may the client application be notified of an open connection. 
</t>

<t>
   The first websocket frame sent by the client to the server must be
   a Hello frame containing the 128 bit MD5 digest of the 8 octets of the
   server nonce followed by the octets of the ASCII string "WebSocket" 
   followed by the 8 octets of the client nonce: 
</t>
<figure><artwork><![CDATA[
   
        8F10 33122035D11258Fd7c764314580e539c
]]></artwork></figure>

</section>

<section title="Changes to 1.9  Subprotocols using the WebSocket protocol">

<t>
OLD:
</t>

<figure><artwork><![CDATA[
   The client can request that the server use a specific subprotocol by
   including the |Sec-Websocket-Protocol| field in its handshake.  If it
   is specified, the server needs to include the same field and one of
   the selected subprotocol values in its response for the connection to
   be established.

   These subprotocol names do not need to be registered, but if a
]]></artwork></figure>

<t>
NEW:
</t>

<figure><artwork><![CDATA[
   The client can request that the server use a specific subprotocol by
   including the |Sec-Websocket-Protocol| field in its handshake.  If it
   is specified, the server needs to include the same field and one of
   the selected subprotocol values in its response for the connection to
   be established.

   Subprotocol names are restricted to use the ASCII characters A-Z, 
   a-z, 0-9, '/', '_' and '-'.

   These subprotocol names do not need to be registered, but if a
]]></artwork></figure>

</section>

<section title="Changes to 3.1.  Parsing WebSocket URLs">
<t>
OLD:
</t>
<figure><artwork><![CDATA[
   11.  If /url/ has a <query> component, then append a single U+003F
        QUESTION MARK character (?) to /resource name/, followed by the
        value of the <query> component.

   12.  Return /host/, /port/, /resource name/, and /secure/.
]]></artwork></figure>

<t>
NEW:
</t>
<figure><artwork><![CDATA[
   11.  If /resource name/ contains the character ':' or any white 
        space sharacters or any characters with codes <= U+0020, 
        then the URL is invalid.

   12.  If /url/ has a <query> component, then append a single U+003F
        QUESTION MARK character (?) to /resource name/, followed by the
        value of the <query> component.

   13.  Return /host/, /port/, /resource name/, and /secure/.
]]></artwork></figure>

</section>

<section title="Changes to 4.2.  Base Framing Protocol">
<t>
OLD:
</t>
<figure><artwork><![CDATA[
      0                   1                   2                   3
      0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
     +-+-+-+-+-------+-+-------------+-------------------------------+
     |M|R|R|R| opcode|R| Payload len |    Extended payload length    |
     |O|S|S|S|  (4)  |S|     (7)     |             (16/63)           |
     |R|V|V|V|       |V|             |   (if payload len==126/127)   |
     |E|1|2|3|       |4|             |                               |
     +-+-+-+-+-------+-+-------------+ - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - +
     |     Extended payload length continued, if payload len == 127  |
     + - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - +-------------------------------+
     |                               |         Extension data        |
     +-------------------------------+ - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - +
     :                                                               :
     +---------------------------------------------------------------+
     :                       Application data                        :
     +---------------------------------------------------------------+

   MORE:  1 bit

      Indicates more fragments follow in the current message
]]></artwork></figure>

<t>
NEW:
</t>
<figure><artwork><![CDATA[
      0                   1                   2                   3
      0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
     +-+-+-+-+-------+-+-------------+-------------------------------+
     |F|R|R|R| opcode|R| Payload len |    Extended payload length    |
     |I|S|S|S|  (4)  |S|     (7)     |             (16/63)           |
     |N|V|V|V|       |V|             |   (if payload len==126/127)   |
     | |1|2|3|       |4|             |                               |
     +-+-+-+-+-------+-+-------------+ - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - +
     |     Extended payload length continued, if payload len == 127  |
     + - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - +-------------------------------+
     |                               |         Extension data        |
     +-------------------------------+ - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - +
     :                                                               :
     +---------------------------------------------------------------+
     :                       Application data                        :
     +---------------------------------------------------------------+

   FIN:  1 bit

      Indicates no more fragments follow in the current message
]]></artwork></figure>

<t></t>

<t>
OLD:
</t>
<figure><artwork><![CDATA[
      ws-frame               = frame-more
                               frame-rsv1
                               frame-rsv2
                               frame-rsv3
                               frame-opcode
                               frame-rsv4
                               frame-length
                               frame-extension
                               application-data;

      frame-more             = %x0 ; final frame of message
                             / %x1 ; more frames of this message follow

      frame-rsv1             = %x0 ; 1 bit, must be 0

      frame-rsv2             = %x0 ; 1 bit, must be 0

      frame-rsv3             = %x0 ; 1 bit, must be 0

      frame-opcode           = %x0 ; continuation frame
                             / %x1 ; connection close
                             / %x2 ; ping
                             / %x3 ; pong
                             / %x4 ; text frame
                             / %x5 ; binary frame
                             / %x6-F ; reserved
]]></artwork></figure>

<t>
NEW:
</t>
<figure><artwork><![CDATA[
      ws-frame               = frame-fin
                               frame-rsv1
                               frame-rsv2
                               frame-rsv3
                               frame-opcode
                               frame-rsv4
                               frame-length
                               frame-extension
                               application-data;

      frame-fin              = %x1 ; final frame of message
                             / %x0 ; more frames of this message follow

      frame-rsv1             = %x0 ; 1 bit, must be 0

      frame-rsv2             = %x0 ; 1 bit, must be 0

      frame-rsv3             = %x0 ; 1 bit, must be 0

      frame-opcode           = %x0 ; continuation frame
                             / %x1 ; connection close
                             / %x2 ; ping
                             / %x3 ; pong
                             / %x4 ; text frame
                             / %x5 ; binary frame
                             / %x6-E ; reserved
                             / %xF ; Hello frame
]]></artwork></figure>

</section>

<section title="Changes to 4.3.  Fragmentation">
<t>
OLD:
</t>
<figure><artwork><![CDATA[
   o  An unfragmented message consists of a single frame with the MORE
      bit clear and an opcode other than 0.

   o  A fragmented message consists of a single frame with the MORE bit
      set and an opcode other than 0, followed by zero or more frames
      with the MORE bit set and the opcode set to 0, and terminated by a
      single frame with the MORE bit clear and an opcode of 0.  Its
      content is the concatenation of the application data from each of
      those frames in order.
]]></artwork></figure>

<t>
NEW:
</t>
<figure><artwork><![CDATA[
   o  An unfragmented message consists of a single frame with the FIN
      bit set and an opcode other than 0.

   o  A fragmented message consists of a single frame with the FIN bit
      clear and an opcode other than 0, followed by zero or more frames
      with the FIN bit clear and the opcode set to 0, and terminated
      by asingle frame with the FIN bit set and an opcode of 0.  Its
      content is the concatenation of the application data from each of
      those frames in order.
]]></artwork></figure>

</section>


<section title="Changes to 4.4.  Control Frames">
<t>
OLD:
</t>
<figure><artwork><![CDATA[
   Control frames have opcodes of 0x01 (Close), 0x02 (Ping), or 0x03
   (Pong).  Control frames are used to communicate state about the
   websocket.
]]></artwork></figure>

<t>
NEW:
</t>
<figure><artwork><![CDATA[
   Control frames have opcodes of 0x01 (Close), 0x02 (Ping), 0x03
   (Pong) or 0x0f (Hello).  Control frames are used to communicate 
   state about the websocket.
]]></artwork></figure>

<t></t>
<t>
Add a NEW section 4.4.4. after 4.4.3 for the new "Hello" command:
</t>
<figure><artwork><![CDATA[
4.4.4.  Hello

   The Hello message contains an opcode of 0x0F and must be the first
   frame sent on any WebSocket connection.

   A Hello message sent from the server to the client must contain 24 
   octets of data, comprising of the 8 octets of the server nonce and 
   the 16 octets of the MD5 digest of the 41 octets of the client 
   nonce, plus the ASCII string "WebSocket", plus the server nonce.

   A Hello message sent from the client to the server must contain 16
   octets of data, comprising the MD5 digest of the 41 octets of the
   server nonce, plus the ASCII string "WebSocket", plus the client 
   nonce.
]]></artwork></figure>

</section>

<section title="Changes to 4.6.  Examples">

<t>
OLD:
</t>
<figure><artwork><![CDATA[
   o  A single-frame text message

      *  0x04 0x05 "Hello"

   o  A fragmented text message

      *  0x84 0x03 "Hel"

      *  0x00 0x02 "lo"

   o  Ping request and response

      *  0x02 0x05 "Hello"

      *  0x03 0x05 "Hello"

   o  256 bytes binary message in a single frame

      *  0x05 0x7E 0x0100 [256 bytes of binary data]

   o  64KiB binary message in a single frame

      *  0x05 0x7F 0x0000000000010000 [65536 bytes of binary data]
]]></artwork></figure>

<t>
NEW:
</t>
<figure><artwork><![CDATA[
   o  A single-frame text message

      *  0x84 0x05 "Hello"

   o  A fragmented text message

      *  0x04 0x03 "Hel"

      *  0x80 0x02 "lo"

   o  Ping request and response

      *  0x82 0x05 "Hello"

      *  0x83 0x05 "Hello"

   o  256 bytes binary message in a single frame

      *  0x85 0x7E 0x0100 [256 bytes of binary data]

   o  64KiB binary message in a single frame

      *  0x85 0x7F 0x0000000000010000 [65536 bytes of binary data]
]]></artwork></figure>

</section>

<section title="Changes to 5.1.  Client Requirements">
<t>
OLD:
</t>
<figure><artwork><![CDATA[
   15.  Add the string "Sec-WebSocket-Draft: 2" to /fields/.
]]></artwork></figure>

<t>
NEW:
</t>
<figure><artwork><![CDATA[
   15.  Add the string "Sec-WebSocket-Draft: 3" to /fields/.
]]></artwork></figure>


<t>Note: In the following changes, renumbering is not shown. That should be taken care of by the diff patch to the 
specification source file.</t>

<t>
OLD:
</t>
<figure><artwork><![CDATA[
   19.  Let /spaces_1/ be a random integer from 1 to 12 inclusive.

        Let /spaces_2/ be a random integer from 1 to 12 inclusive.

        EXAMPLE: For example, 5 and 9.

   20.  Let /max_1/ be the largest integer not greater than
        4,294,967,295 divided by /spaces_1/.

        Let /max_2/ be the largest integer not greater than
        4,294,967,295 divided by /spaces_2/.

        EXAMPLE: Continuing the example, 858,993,459 and 477,218,588.

   21.  Let /number_1/ be a random integer from 0 to /max_1/ inclusive.

        Let /number_2/ be a random integer from 0 to /max_2/ inclusive.

        EXAMPLE: For example, 777,007,543 and 114,997,259.

   22.  Let /product_1/ be the result of multiplying /number_1/ and
        /spaces_1/ together.

        Let /product_2/ be the result of multiplying /number_2/ and
        /spaces_2/ together.

        EXAMPLE: Continuing the example, 3,885,037,715 and
        1,034,975,331.

   23.  Let /key_1/ be a string consisting of /product_1/, expressed in
        base ten using the numerals in the range U+0030 DIGIT ZERO (0)
        to U+0039 DIGIT NINE (9).

        Let /key_2/ be a string consisting of /product_2/, expressed in
        base ten using the numerals in the range U+0030 DIGIT ZERO (0)
        to U+0039 DIGIT NINE (9).

        EXAMPLE: Continuing the example, "3885037715" and "1034975331".

   24.  Insert between one and twelve random characters from the ranges
        U+0021 to U+002F and U+003A to U+007E into /key_1/ at random
        positions.

        Insert between one and twelve random characters from the ranges
        U+0021 to U+002F and U+003A to U+007E into /key_2/ at random
        positions.

        NOTE: This corresponds to random printable ASCII characters
        other than the digits and the U+0020 SPACE character.

        EXAMPLE: Continuing the example, this could lead to "P388O503D&
        ul7{K%gX(%715" and "1N?|kUT0or3o4I97N5-S3O31".

   25.  Insert /spaces_1/ U+0020 SPACE characters into /key_1/ at random
        positions other than the start or end of the string.

        Insert /spaces_2/ U+0020 SPACE characters into /key_2/ at random
        positions other than the start or end of the string.

        EXAMPLE: Continuing the example, this could lead to "P388 O503D&
        ul7 {K%gX( %7  15" and "1 N ?|k UT0or 3o  4 I97N 5-S3O 31".

   26.  Add the string consisting of the concatenation of the string
        "Sec-WebSocket-Key1:", a U+0020 SPACE character, and the /key_1/
        value, to /fields/.

        Add the string consisting of the concatenation of the string
        "Sec-WebSocket-Key2:", a U+0020 SPACE character, and the /key_2/
        value, to /fields/.
]]></artwork></figure>

<t>
NEW:
</t>
<figure><artwork><![CDATA[
   19.  Let /client nonce/ be a random 64 bit integer.

        EXAMPLE expressed as a hexadecimal number :

           A23F2BCA452DDE01

   26.  Add the string consisting of the concatenation of the string
        "Sec-WebSocket-Nonce:", a U+0020 SPACE character, and the
	/client nonce/ value expressed as a base 16 using numerals
        in the range U+0030 DIGIT ZERO (0) to U+0039 DIGIT  NINE (9)
        and letters in the range U+0041 LATIN CAPITAL LETTER A to
        U+0046 LATIN CAPITAL LETTER F, to /fields/.
]]></artwork></figure>

<t>
Delete these OLD items:
</t>
<figure><artwork><![CDATA[
   29.  Let /key_3/ be a string consisting of eight random bytes (or
        equivalently, a random 64 bit unsigned integer encoded in big-
        endian order).

        EXAMPLE: For example, 0x47 0x30 0x22 0x2D 0x5A 0x3F 0x47 0x58.

   30.  Send /key_3/ to the server.
]]></artwork></figure>

<t></t>

<t>
OLD:
</t>
<figure><artwork><![CDATA[
   45.  Let /challenge/ be the concatenation of /number_1/, expressed as
        a big-endian 32 bit integer, /number_2/, expressed as a big-
        endian 32 bit integer, and the eight bytes of /key_3/ in the
        order they were sent on the wire.

        EXAMPLE: Using the examples given earlier, this leads to the 16
        bytes 0x2E 0x50 0x31 0xB7 0x06 0xDA 0xB8 0x0B 0x47 0x30 0x22
        0x2D 0x5A 0x3F 0x47 0x58.

   46.  Let /expected/ be the MD5 fingerprint of /challenge/ as a big-
        endian 128 bit string.  [RFC1321]

        EXAMPLE: Using the examples given earlier, this leads to the 16
        bytes 0x30 0x73 0x74 0x33 0x52 0x6C 0x26 0x71 0x2D 0x32 0x5A
        0x55 0x5E 0x77 0x65 0x75.  In UTF-8, these bytes correspond to
        the string "0st3Rl&q-2ZU^weu".

   47.  Read sixteen bytes from the server.  Let /reply/ be those bytes.

        If the connection closes before these bytes are received, then
        fail the WebSocket connection and abort these steps.

   48.  If /reply/ does not exactly equal /expected/, then fail the
        WebSocket connection and abort these steps.
]]></artwork></figure>

<t>
NEW:
</t>
<figure><artwork><![CDATA[
   47.  Read twenty six bytes from the server.  Let /server hello/ be those bytes.

        If the connection closes before these bytes are received, then
        fail the WebSocket connection and abort these steps.

   48.  If the first octet of /server hello/ is not 0x8f then fail the WebSocket
        connection and abort these steps.
        
        If the second octet of /server hello/ is not 0x18 then fail the WebSocket
        connection and abort these steps.

   49.  Let /server nonce/ be the 8 octets starting from the third octet of 
        /server hello/

        EXAMPLE expressed as a hexadecimal number:

            15F0D2278BCD457F

        Let /server digest/ be the 16 octets starting from the eleventh
        octet of /server hello/

   50.  Let /server expected/ be the 16 octets of MD5 digest of the 
        concatenation of /client nonce/, the ASCII string "WebSocket" and
        /server nonce/

        EXAMPLE expressed as a hexadecimal number:

            Ee7eBe0c369cBf255a4451Fc58D7Cc4f

   51.  If /server digest/ does not equal /server expected/ then fail
        the WebSocket connection and abort these steps.

   52.  Let /client digest/ be the 16 octets of MD5 digest of the 
        concatenation of /server nonce/, the ASCII string "WebSocket" and
        /client nonce/.

   53.  Send the octets 0x8f, 0x10 and /client digest/
]]></artwork></figure>

</section>

<section title="Changes to 5.2.1.  Reading the client's opening handshake">
<t>
OLD:
</t>
<figure><artwork><![CDATA[
   1.  The three-character UTF-8 string "GET".

   2.  A UTF-8-encoded U+0020 SPACE character (0x20 byte).

   3.  A string consisting of all the bytes up to the next UTF-8-encoded
       U+0020 SPACE character (0x20 byte).  The result of decoding this
       string as a UTF-8 string is the name of the resource requested by
       the server.  If the server only supports one resource, then this
       can safely be ignored; the client verifies that the right
]]></artwork></figure>

<t>
NEW:
</t>
<figure><artwork><![CDATA[
   1.  The three-character UTF-8 string "GET".

   2.  A UTF-8-encoded U+0020 SPACE character (0x20 byte).

   3.  A string consisting of all the bytes up to the next UTF-8-encoded
       U+0020 SPACE character (0x20 byte).  The result of decoding this
       string as a UTF-8 string is the name of the resource requested by
       the server and must be a valid resource name according to Section 3.3.

       If the server only supports one resource, then this
       can safely be ignored; the client verifies that the right
]]></artwork></figure>


<t></t>

<t>
OLD:
</t>
<figure><artwork><![CDATA[
   |Sec-WebSocket-Key1|

   |Sec-WebSocket-Key2|
]]></artwork></figure>

<t>
NEW:
</t>
<figure><artwork><![CDATA[
   |Sec-WebSocket-Nonce|
]]></artwork></figure>

<t></t>

<t>
OLD:
</t>
<figure><artwork><![CDATA[
        /key_1/
           The value of the "Sec-WebSocket-Key1" field in the client's
           handshake.





Fette                    Expires April 20, 2011                [Page 40]

Internet-Draft           The WebSocket protocol             October 2010


        /key_2/
           The value of the "Sec-WebSocket-Key2" field in the client's
           handshake.

        /key_3/
           The eight random bytes sent after the first 0x0D 0x0A 0x0D
           0x0A sequence in the client's handshake.

   3.   Let /location/ be the string that results from constructing a
        WebSocket URL from /host/, /port/, /resource name/, and /secure
        flag/.

   4.   Let /key-number_1/ be the digits (characters in the range U+0030
        DIGIT ZERO (0) to U+0039 DIGIT NINE (9)) in /key_1/, interpreted
        as a base ten integer, ignoring all other characters in /key_1/.

        Let /key-number_2/ be the digits (characters in the range U+0030
        DIGIT ZERO (0) to U+0039 DIGIT NINE (9)) in /key_2/, interpreted
        as a base ten integer, ignoring all other characters in /key_2/.

           EXAMPLE: For example, assume that the client handshake was:


              GET / HTTP/1.1
              Connection: Upgrade
              Host: example.com
              Upgrade: WebSocket
              Sec-WebSocket-Key1: 3e6b263  4 17 80
              Origin: http://example.com
              Sec-WebSocket-Key2: 17  9 G`ZD9   2 2b 7X 3 /r90

              WjN}|M(6

           The /key-number_1/ would be the number 3,626,341,780, and the
           /key-number_2/ would be the number 1,799,227,390.

           In this example, incidentally, /key_3/ is "WjN}|M(6", or 0x57
           0x6A 0x4E 0x7D 0x7C 0x4D 0x28 0x36.

   5.   Let /spaces_1/ be the number of U+0020 SPACE characters in
        /key_1/.

        Let /spaces_2/ be the number of U+0020 SPACE characters in
        /key_2/.

        If either /spaces_1/ or /spaces_2/ is zero, then abort the
        WebSocket connection.  This is a symptom of a cross-protocol
        attack.

        EXAMPLE: In the example above, /spaces_1/ would be 4 and
        /spaces_2/ would be 10.

   6.   If /key-number_1/ is not an integral multiple of /spaces_1/,
        then abort the WebSocket connection.

        If /key-number_2/ is not an integral multiple of /spaces_2/,
        then abort the WebSocket connection.

        NOTE: This can only happen if the client is not a conforming
        WebSocket client.

   7.   Let /part_1/ be /key-number_1/ divided by /spaces_1/.

        Let /part_2/ be /key-number_2/ divided by /spaces_2/.

        EXAMPLE: In the example above, /part_1/ would be 906,585,445 and
        /part_2/ would be 179,922,739.

   8.   Let /challenge/ be the concatenation of /part_1/, expressed as a
        big-endian 32 bit integer, /part_2/, expressed as a big-endian
        32 bit integer, and the eight bytes of /key_3/ in the order they
        were sent on the wire.

        EXAMPLE: In the example above, this would be the 16 bytes 0x36
        0x09 0x65 0x65 0x0A 0xB9 0x67 0x33 0x57 0x6A 0x4E 0x7D 0x7C 0x4D
        0x28 0x36.

   9.   Let /response/ be the MD5 fingerprint of /challenge/ as a big-
        endian 128 bit string.  [RFC1321]

        EXAMPLE: In the example above, this would be the 16 bytes 0x6E
        0x60 0x39 0x65 0x42 0x6B 0x39 0x7A 0x24 0x52 0x38 0x70 0x4F 0x74
        0x56 0x62, or "n`9eBk9z$R8pOtVb" in UTF-8.
]]></artwork></figure>

<t>
NEW:
</t>
<figure><artwork><![CDATA[
        /client nonce/
           The value of the "Sec-WebSocket-Nonce" field in the client's
           handshake.

        /server nonce/
           An 64 bit random integer generated by the server.

           EXAMPLE expressed in hexadecimal:

               15F0D2278BCD457F

   3.   Let /location/ be the string that results from constructing a
        WebSocket URL from /host/, /port/, /resource name/, and /secure
        flag/.

   4.   Let /server digest/ be the 16 octets of MD5 digest of the 
        concatenation of /client nonce/, the ASCII string "WebSocket" and
        /server nonce/

        EXAMPLE expressed in hexadecimal:

            Ee7eBe0c369cBf255a4451Fc58D7Cc4f
]]></artwork></figure>

<t></t>

<t>
OLD:
</t>
<figure><artwork><![CDATA[
   13.  Send /response/.
]]></artwork></figure>

<t>
NEW:
</t>
<figure><artwork><![CDATA[
   13.  Send the octets 0x8F, 0x18, /server nonce/ and /server digest/.

   14.  The *WebSocket connection is accepted*.  Now the server may 
        send messages to the connection as described in the next section.

   15.  Read eighteen octets from the server.  Let /client hello/ be those bytes.

        If the connection closes before these bytes are received, then
        fail the WebSocket connection and abort these steps.

   48.  If the first octet of /client hello/ is not 0x8f then fail the WebSocket
        connection and abort these steps.
        
        If the second octet of /client hello/ is not 0x10 then fail the WebSocket
        connection and abort these steps.

   50.  Let /client expected/ be the 16 octets of MD5 digest of the 
        concatenation of /server nonce/, the ASCII string "WebSocket" and
        /client nonce/

        EXAMPLE expressed as a hexadecimal number:

            33122035D11258Fd7c764314580e539c

        Let /client digest/ be the 16 octets starting from the third
        octet of /client hello/

   51.  If /client digest/ does not equal /client expected/ then fail
        the WebSocket connection and abort these steps.

   52.  The *WebSocket connection is established*.  Now the server
        may send and receive to and from the connection as described in
        the next section.
]]></artwork></figure>

</section>

<section title="Security Considerations">
<t>
</t>
</section>

<section title="IANA Considerations">
	<t>This requirements document does not mandate any IANA actions.  </t>
</section>


<section title="Acknowledgments">
<t>
Thanks to Scott Ferguson, Willy Tarreau, Dave Cridland, among others.
</t>
</section>



</middle>


<back>

	<references title="Normative References">


		<?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119"?>
		<?rfc include="reference.RFC.2616"?>
                <?rfc include="reference.I-D.ietf-hybi-websocket-requirements"?>
                <?rfc include="reference.I-D.ietf-hybi-thewebsocketprotocol"?>

	</references>


	<references title="Informative References">


                <?rfc include="reference.I-D.ietf-hybi-design-space"?>

	</references>
</back>

</rfc>
