<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='http://xml.resource.org/authoring/rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<!-- Default toc="no" No Table of Contents -->
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
<!-- Default symrefs="no" Don't use anchors, but use numbers for refs -->
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<!-- Default sortrefs="no" Don't sort references into order -->
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<!-- Default compact="no" Start sections on new pages -->
<?rfc strict="no" ?>
<!-- Default strict="no" Don't check I-D nits -->
<?rfc rfcedstyle="yes" ?>
<!-- Default rfcedstyle="yes" attempt to closely follow finer details from the latest observable RFC-Editor style -->
<?rfc linkmailto="yes" ?>
<!-- Default linkmailto="yes" generate mailto: URL, as appropriate -->
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<rfc category="info" docName="draft-ietf-conex-concepts-uses-02"
     ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="ConEx Concepts &amp; Use Cases">ConEx Concepts and Use
    Cases</title>

    <!--
    <author fullname="Toby Moncaster" initials="T." surname="Moncaster">
      <organization>Moncaster Internet Consulting</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Dukes</street>

          <street>Layer Marney</street>

          <city>Colchester</city>

          <code>CO5 9UZ</code>

          <country>UK</country>
        </postal>

        <email>toby@moncaster.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="John Leslie" initials="J." surname="Leslie">
      <organization>JLC.net</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>10 Souhegan Street</street>

          <city>Milford</city>

          <code>03055</code>

          <region>NH</region>

          <country>US</country>
        </postal>

        <email>john@jlc.net</email>
      </address>
    </author>
-->

    <author fullname="Bob Briscoe" initials="B." role="editor"
            surname="Briscoe">
      <organization>BT</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>B54/77, Adastral Park</street>

          <street>Martlesham Heath</street>

          <city>Ipswich</city>

          <code>IP5 3RE</code>

          <country>UK</country>
        </postal>

        <phone>+44 1473 645196</phone>

        <email>bob.briscoe@bt.com</email>

        <uri>http://bobbriscoe.net/</uri>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Richard Woundy" initials="R." role="editor"
            surname="Woundy">
      <organization>Comcast</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Comcast Cable Communications</street>

          <street>27 Industrial Avenue</street>

          <city>Chelmsford</city>

          <code>01824</code>

          <region>MA</region>

          <country>US</country>
        </postal>

        <email>richard_woundy@cable.comcast.com</email>

        <uri>http://www.comcast.com</uri>
      </address>
    </author>

    <!--
    <author fullname="Dave McDysan" initials="D." surname="McDysan">
      <organization>Verizon</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>22001 Loudon County Pkwy</street>

          <city>Ashburn</city>

          <code>20147</code>

          <region>VA</region>

          <country>US</country>
        </postal>

        <email>dave.mcdysan@verizon.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
-->

    <date day="11" month="July" year="2011" />

    <area>Transport Area</area>

    <workgroup>ConEx</workgroup>

    <keyword>Internet-Draft</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>This document provides the entry point to the set of documentation on
      a new Congestion Exposure (ConEx) protocol. It motivates a new ConEx
      field at the IP layer, focusing on the 'why' rather than the 'how'. In
      the absence of such a protocol, traffic is subjected to numerous traffic
      management checks and limits as it crosses the Internet. The purpose of
      this protocol is to expose congestion to network operators, so that they
      have no need to intervene at all when there is no congestion, and so
      they have exactly the right information when there is congestion. Then
      it will at least be possible for traffic management to be
      application-neutral, openly transparent and free of unnecessary
      restraints. Although traffic management is the focus of this document,
      it also briefly introduces a number of other important potential uses
      for ConEx, demonstrating its role as a generative technology and
      justifying its placement in the IP layer.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <!-- ====================================================================== -->

    <section anchor="conex-uses-intro" title="Introduction">
      <t>The power of Internet technology comes from multiplexing shared
      capacity with packets rather than circuits. Network operators usually
      provide sufficient shared capacity, but whenever too much packet load
      meets too little shared capacity, congestion results. Congestion appears
      as either increased delay, missing packets or packets explicitly marked
      with ECN&nbsp;<xref target="RFC3168"></xref>. Referring to <xref
      target="conex-uses_Fig_ConEx_Placement"></xref>, congestion control
      currently relies on the transport receiver detecting these 'Congestion
      Signals' and informing the transport sender in 'Congestion Feedback
      Signals'. The sender is then meant to reduce its rate in response.</t>

      <t>This document provides the entry point to the set of documentation on
      Congestion Exposure (ConEx). It motivates a new ConEx field at the IP
      layer, focusing on the 'why' rather than the 'how'. A companion document
      about the ConEx protocol mechanism gives the 'how' <xref
      target="ConEx-Abstract-Mech"></xref>. Briefly, the idea is for the
      sender to continually signal expected congestion in the headers of any
      data it sends. To a first approximation the sender does this by relaying
      the 'Congestion Feedback Signals' back into the IP layer. They then
      travel unchanged across the network to the receiver (shown as
      'IP-Layer-ConEx-Signals' in <xref
      target="conex-uses_Fig_ConEx_Placement"></xref>). Certain IP layer
      devices can then use this new information, for example as input to
      traffic management.</t>

      <figure anchor="conex-uses_Fig_ConEx_Placement"
              title="Where the ConEx Protocol Fits in the Internet Architecture">
        <!--0        1         2         3         4         5         6         7
123456789012345678901234567890123456789012345678901234567890123456789012 -->

        <artwork><![CDATA[
,---------.                                               ,---------.
|Transport|                                               |Transport|
| Sender  |   .                                           |Receiver |
|         |  /|___________________________________________|         |
|     ,-<---------------Congestion-Feedback-Signals--<--------.     |
|     |   |/                                              |   |     |
|     |   |\           Transport Layer Feedback Flow      |   |     |
|     |   | \  ___________________________________________|   |     |
|     |   |  \|                                           |   |     |
|     |   |   '         ,-----------.               .     |   |     |
|     |   |_____________|           |_______________|\    |   |     |
|     |   |    IP Layer |           |  Data Flow      \   |   |     |
|     |   |             |(Congested)|                  \  |   |     |
|     |   |             |  Network  |--Congestion-Signals--->-'     |
|     |   |             |  Device   |                    \|         |
|     |   |             |           |                    /|         |
|     `----------->--(new)-IP-Layer-ConEx-Signals-------->|         |
|         |             |           |                  /  |         |
|         |_____________|           |_______________  /   |         |
|         |             |           |               |/    |         |
`---------'             `-----------'               '     `---------'
]]></artwork>
      </figure>

      <t>Current traffic management solutions limit traffic based on either
      bit-rate or volume. For instance, weighted fair queuing (based on <xref
      target="RFC0970"></xref>) shares out bit-rate when a link is congested.
      However it fails to consider how much of the time a consumer keeps the
      link busy, which is the main factor that determines everyone else's
      bit-rate. To try to address this issue, many network operators have
      introduced volume limits. However, these tend to be either not strict
      enough during congested periods, or unnecessarily strict when traffic is
      light.</t>

      <t>Because each solution only partially addresses the problem, operators
      keep adding more solutions. So a data path across the Internet often
      encounters numerous blockages and throttles in each network it crosses.
      This clutter is actually a symptom of a deeper underlying problem:
      neither bit-rate nor volume is the right metric.</t>

      <t>Traffic management would be so much better (and simpler) if
      congestion were visible in packets. Then, whenever congestion was not
      present, all restraints could be removed, leaving the full capacity
      available to everyone. But if some excessive users were causing a lot of
      congestion, the traffic management function would know and be able to
      directly limit their traffic, in order to protect the service of other
      users sharing the same capacity.</t>

      <t>ConEx exposes exactly the right information for this, in the IP
      layer. It reveals a consumer's overall contribution to congestion, which
      is a direct measure of how much one user affects others. ConEx makes
      this easy to measure&mdash;as easy as counting straight volume, except
      you only count the volume of packets with ConEx markings. With the right
      metric visible, traffic management would only have to be done once on a
      path because it would be done well.</t>

      <t>In the absence of the right metric, some operators have deployed deep
      packet inspection (DPI) equipment; not just in the public Internet but
      also in enterprise and campus networks. Their main aim has been to
      identify and limit specific types of application that they associate
      with heavy usage.<!--Quite apart from the architectural and neutrality issues raised by such technology, 
its applicability is declining anyway. 
In recent years, video traffic has overtaken peer-to-peer filesharing as the predominant type of traffic. 
But even those operators who have been limiting peer-to-peer have no wish to limit certain types of video application.--></t>

      <t>With ConEx, a network operator can manage traffic without dipping
      into the higher layers, because ConEx makes the relevant bulk congestion
      information accessible at the IP layer. This solves two problems that
      have made DPI controversial: traffic management can be
      application-neutral and compatible with IPsec encryption.</t>

      <t>Also, because ConEx information is added explicitly at the IP layer,
      it is visible to provider and consumer alike. Therefore traffic
      contracts or acceptable use policies can be based on a quantifiable
      metric that is open and transparent to both parties, so that it will be
      sufficient to manage traffic without extra non-transparent wriggle-room
      and caveats.</t>

      <t>To summarise so far, ConEx is designed to make it simple to do
      traffic management that is transparent, neutral and free of unnecessary
      restraints. Although it is not our place to make a network provider meet
      these requirements, ConEx is designed to make this the simplest service
      to provide.</t>

      <t>{ToDo: review this para when done and shorten} This introduction has
      focused on traffic management as the main use for ConEx. However, ConEx
      is intended as a generative technology, with a wider range of potential
      uses. The document structure reflects this. <xref
      target="conex-uses-traffic-mgmt"></xref> overviews existing approaches
      to traffic management and <xref
      target="conex-uses-exposing_congestion"></xref> explains why exposing
      congestion would address their limitations. <xref
      target="conex-uses-cases"></xref> introduces the main use-cases for
      ConEx: traffic management, incentivising scavenger transports and
      intra-class quality of service as well as briefly mentioning others.
      Then <xref target="conex-uses-deployments"></xref> presents how how the
      above use-cases might drive deployment of ConEx. Finally, <xref
      target="conex-uses-issues"></xref> discusses a number of potential
      issues (and non-issues) that are often raised about ConEx, before the
      usual tailpiece sections in conclusion.</t>

      <t>But before all this, <xref target="conex-uses-defs"></xref>
      introduces the basic concepts necessary to understand ConEx, as well as
      dispelling a number of common misconceptions.</t>
    </section>

    <!-- ====================================================================== -->

    <section anchor="conex-uses-defs" title="Concepts">
      <t>Despite its central role in network control and management,
      congestion is a remarkably hard concept to define. <xref
      target="Bauer09"></xref> provides a good academic background. For the
      purposes of ConEx, the definition below focuses on how congestion would
      be measured, rather than precisely what it is. Our definition of
      congestion is then equivalent to the loss probability (or the marking
      probability if ECN is used).</t>

      <t>ConEx is essentially about accountability for congestion (or blame in
      crude language). The blame for congestion lies equally between too
      little capacity and too much traffic. On the capacity side, congestion
      itself measures how badly the network provider is to blame. On the
      traffic side, in a shared network, the blame is split among all the
      users. Congestion-volume measures how much of each user's traffic is to
      blame for the congestion. Note that congestion-volume is a property of
      traffic, whereas congestion is a property of a link or a path.</t>

      <t>Congestion-volume is a relatively newly defined metric that is
      central to ConEx. To grasp an intuitive feel for what congestion-volume
      measures, some network operators give you an allowance and only count
      data volume during the peak period against it. This is equivalent to
      counting your congestion-volume by assuming that congestion is 100%
      during the peak period and 0% otherwise.</t>

      <t>The congestion-volume metric is more refined but broadly equivalent
      to the above time-of-day volume example and still as simple to measure.
      Imagine Alice sends 1GB while the loss-probability is a constant 0.2%.
      Then her contribution to congestion (or congestion-volume) is 1GB x 0.2%
      = 2MB. If she then sends 3GB while congestion is 0.1%, this adds 3MB to
      her congestion-volume. Her total contribution to congestion is then
      2MB+3MB = 5MB.</t>

      <t>To measure Alice's congestion-volume no-one has to do all these
      multiplications and additions. It is simply a matter of counting the
      total volume of Alice's traffic that was discarded (a queue with a
      percentage loss involves multiplication inherently).</t>

      <t>Finally, there is yet another way to cut the blame for congestion.
      Recall that the level of congestion itself measures the provider's
      blame. However, in an internetwork there are multiple providers. If a
      data centre network with zero congestion is connected to an access
      network and sends traffic over a link with 0.4% loss probability, then
      clearly all the blame for congestion lies with the access network.
      However, at another time, there might be 0.1% congestion across the data
      centre and 0.7% across the access, making 0.8% end-to-end congestion
      across the path.</t>

      <t>In order to apportion blame accordingly, ConEx information is placed
      in the IP layer so that a simple border meter can see how much of the
      congestion is on one side or other, termed upstream and downstream
      congestion.</t>

      <t>If A and B are connected within a chain of more than two networks, A
      attributes all congestion beyond B to B, and vice versa. As far as A is
      concerned, B chooses who to route to, so B takes responsibility for its
      choices.</t>

      <section title="Definitions">
        <t><list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="Congestion:">Congestion occurs when any user's
            traffic suffers increased delay, loss or ECN marking as a result
            of one or more network resources becoming overloaded. For the
            purposes of ConEx, the focus is on concrete signals of congestion
            (ECN and loss), therefore delay is set to one side. Congestion is
            measured as the probability of loss or the probability of ECN
            marking, usually expressed as dimensionless percentages.</t>

            <t hangText="Congestion-volume:">For any granularity of traffic
            (packet, flow, aggregate, link, etc.), the volume of bytes dropped
            or marked in a given period of time. Conceptually, data volume
            multiplied by the instantaneous congestion each packet of the
            volume experienced. Usually expressed in bytes (or MB, GB, of
            course).</t>

            <t hangText="Congestion-rate:">For any granularity of traffic
            (packet, flow, aggregate, link, etc.), the instantaneous rate of
            traffic discarded or marked due to congestion. Conceptually, the
            instantaneous bit-rate of the traffic weighted by the
            instantaneous congestion it experiences. Usually expressed in
            b/s.</t>

            <t hangText="Upstream Congestion:">The accumulated level of
            congestion experienced by a traffic flow thus far, relative to a
            point along its path. In other words, at any point the Upstream
            Congestion is the accmulated level of congestion the traffic flow
            has experienced as it travels from the sender to that point. At
            the receiver this is equivalent to the end-to-end congestion level
            that (usually) is reported back to the sender.</t>

            <t hangText="Downstream Congestion:">The level of congestion a
            flow of traffic is expected to experience on the remainder of its
            path. In other words, at any point the Downstream Congestion is
            the level of congestion the traffic flow is yet to experience as
            it travels from that point to the receiver. Aka. Rest-of-Path
            Congestion.</t>

            <t hangText="Network provider:">(also 'operator'): the term is not
            confined to Internet service providers (ISPs) who run commercial
            public networks but is also intended to generalise to operators of
            enterprise, campus and other networks.</t>

            <t hangText="Consumer:">A general term representing the
            contractual entity such as a user or business or institution that
            uses the service of a network provider. There is no implication
            that the contract has to be commercial; for instance the consumers
            of a University or enterprise network service would be students or
            employees and they might well be required to comply with some form
            of contract or acceptable use policy. There is also no implication
            that the consumer is necessarily an end-consumer. Where two
            networks form a customer-provider relationship, the term consumer
            is also intended to cover the customer network.</t>
          </list></t>

        <t><xref target="ConEx-Abstract-Mech"></xref> gives further
        definitions for aspects of ConEx to do with protocol mechanisms.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Non-Goals of ConEx and Common Misconceptions">
        <t>Congestion exposure is about the transport sender exposing
        congestion to the network, not the other way round. That would not
        make sense given by design the transport endpoints handle congestion
        in the TCP/IP protocol suite.</t>

        <t>Nonetheless, it is a non-goal for IP layer devices to use this
        ConEx information to do fine-grained congestion control. That is still
        best done at the transport sender. There is also no expectation that
        the information will be used by every IP router and forwarding device.
        More likely, specific ConEx-based functions like traffic management
        will be added to edge routers. This in turn should incentivize
        end-system transports to be more careful about congesting others.</t>

        <t>Note that good behaviour at individual flow granularity is the
        intended outcome, not the forcing function&mdash;it is the end, not
        the means. Enforcing per-flow compliance to the TCP congestion
        response (or any per-flow rate enforcement) is a non-goal:<list
            style="symbols">
            <t>It used to be commonly believed that TCP-friendliness was
            critical to fairness on the Internet. However, no congestion
            control algorithm can determine how much data an application
            transfers, or how many flows it opens, or which congestion control
            algorithm an application uses, or how many applications the user
            runs, or how many users are active at once. These factors all have
            a stronger impact on how great a share of a link is available for
            any particular data transfer. To achieve fairness at this broader
            granularity (between users, homes, sites or whole networks)
            requires that individual flows in the same bottleneck will
            sometimes be very unequal.</t>

            <t>If the network forced everything to be TCP-friendly, some
            important applications would not work. Worse still, this would
            prevent deployment of higher performance replacements to TCP. It
            is important to allow give and take between one user's flows: some
            can be more aggressive than TCP and others less, e.g. long
            transfers, following the example of LEDBAT <xref
            target="LEDBAT"></xref> (see <xref
            target="conex-uses-scavenge"></xref>).</t>
          </list>Therefore, network enforcement of per-flow fairness is not
        only a non-goal, it would be a harmful goal in many respects.</t>

        <t>Capacity provisioning is another area of confusion in relation to
        ConEx. Congestion-based traffic management is not an alternative to
        good capacity provisioning. Either or both can be good practice
        depending on the situation, and ConEx can provide a useful metric for
        both (see <xref target="conex-uses-other"></xref>).</t>

        <t>Any network that is persistently highly congested is inefficient.
        However, the total absence of congestion from <spanx style="emph">all</spanx>
        parts of a network is equally inefficient. If an end-to-end transport
        protocol cannot go fast enough to find a bottleneck somewhere along
        the path&mdash;typically in an access network&mdash;it is probably
        broken. The long-standing aim of congestion control has been to find
        the healthy point of balance with a low level of congestion <spanx
        style="emph">somewhere </spanx>on the path. Just to be clear though,
        zero congestion somewhere else (e.g. the core) is also perfectly
        healthy.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <!-- ====================================================================== -->

    <section anchor="conex-uses-traffic-mgmt" title="Traffic Management">
      <t>Since 1988 congestion management has been the responsibility of the
      end-systems in the Internet architecture. The network signals congestion
      to the receiver, the receiver feeds this back to the sender and the
      sender is expected to reduce the traffic it sends.</t>

      <t>Nonetheless, since at least when Nagle proposed fair queuing in 1985
      <xref target="RFC0970"></xref>, it has been recognised that end-systems
      alone cannot be entrusted with sharing out capacity between
      themselves.</t>

      <t>Since then capacity has been shared by a mix of traffic management
      approaches, partly network-based (weighted round-robin scheduling,
      weighted fair queuing, etc) and partly host-based (TCP). However, in
      recent years, network operators became concerned that a relatively small
      number of end-machines were consuming a disproportionately high share of
      network resources. This is actually because both TCP and all the
      traditional network-based approaches only share out a bottleneck at each
      instant. They fail to take account of how much of the time a consumer is
      keeping the link busy, which is the main factor that determines everyone
      else's bit-rate.</t>

      <t>As a result, some network operators introduced additional limits
      based on data volume transferred over time. These also were generally
      too blunt an instrument, because they counted volume whether or not it
      was sent at a congested time that would limit other users. Some
      operators have therefore tried to address this perceived problem by
      introducing further traffic management boxes that artificially starve
      certain types of traffic that they associate with heavy usage.</t>

      <section anchor="conex-uses-Existing"
               title="Existing Approaches to Traffic Management">
        <t>Beyond this brief history, the authors have chosen not to
        exhaustively list current approaches to traffic management. Broadly
        they can be divided into those that happen at Layer 3 of the OSI model
        and those that use information gathered from higher layers. In general
        these approaches attempt to find a "proxy" measure for congestion.
        Layer 3 approaches include: <list style="symbols">
            <t>Rate-based &mdash; the traffic rate per user or per network is
            constrained. The absolute rate a given consumer sends at may be
            limited, perhaps more at peak hours, or relative rates per
            consumer are equalised at a known bottleneck. The average rate or
            more typically the 95th percentile taken over periods of a few
            minutes is also commonly used as the basis for inter-network
            billing.</t>

            <t>Volume accounting &mdash; the overall volume of traffic a given
            consumer sends (and/or receives) is measured. Consumers may be
            subject to an absolute volume cap (e.g. 10Gbytes per month) or the
            "heaviest" users may be sanctioned in some other manner.</t>
          </list> Higher layer approaches include: <list style="symbols">
            <t>Bottleneck per-flow rate policing &mdash; bottleneck flow rate
            policers (e.g. approximate fair dropping or AFD) aim to share the
            available capacity at a given bottleneck between all concurrent
            flows.</t>

            <t>DPI and application rate policing &mdash; in some regions of
            the world and particularly in mobile networks, deep packet
            inspection and other techniques are used to determine what
            application a given traffic flow is associated with <xref
            target="Fair-use"></xref>. Operators may then use this information
            to rate-limit or otherwise sanction certain applications,
            typically at peak hours.</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>All of these current approaches suffer from some general
        limitations. First, they introduce performance uncertainty. Flat-rate
        pricing plans are popular because users appreciate the certainty of
        having their monthly bill amount remain the same for each billing
        period, allowing them to plan their costs accordingly. But while
        flat-rate pricing avoids billing uncertainty, it creates performance
        uncertainty: users cannot know whether the performance of their
        connection is being altered or degraded based on how the network
        operator is attempting to manage congestion.</t>

        <t>Second, none of the approaches is able to make use of what may be
        the most important factor in managing congestion: the amount that a
        given endpoint contributes to congestion on the network. This
        information simply is not available to network nodes, and neither
        volume nor rate nor application usage is an adequate proxy for
        congestion-volume, because none of these metrics measures a consumer's
        or network's actual contribution to congestion on the network.</t>

        <t>Finally, none of these solutions accounts for inter-network
        congestion. Mechanisms may exist that allow an operator to identify
        and mitigate congestion in their own network, but the design of the
        Internet means that only the end-hosts have full visibility of
        congestion information along the whole path. ConEx allows this
        information to be visible to everyone on the path and thus allows
        operators to make better-informed decisions about controlling
        traffic.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <!-- ====================================================================== -->

    <section anchor="conex-uses-exposing_congestion"
             title="Exposing Congestion">
      <t>We argue that current traffic-control mechanisms seek to control the
      wrong quantity. What matters in the network is neither the volume of
      traffic nor the rate of traffic: it is the contribution to congestion
      over time&nbsp;&mdash; congestion means that your traffic impacts other
      users, and conversely that their traffic impacts you. So if there is no
      congestion there need not be any restriction on the amount a user can
      send; restrictions only need to apply when others are sending traffic
      such that there is congestion.</t>

      <t>For example, an application intending to transfer large amounts of
      data could use a congestion control mechanism like <xref
      target="LEDBAT"></xref> (Low Extra Delay BAckground Transport) to reduce
      its transmission rate before any competing TCP flows do, by detecting an
      increase in end-to-end delay (as a measure of impending congestion).
      Currently, such techniques rely on voluntary, altruistic action by end
      users and their application providers. Operators cannot encourage their
      use, and worse, they penalize such applications for the large amount of
      volume they send rather than rewarding them for carefully avoiding
      congestion while sending it.</t>

      <t>The Internet was designed so that end-hosts detect and control
      congestion. We argue that congestion needs to be visible to network
      nodes as well, not just to the end hosts. More specifically, a network
      needs to be able to measure how much congestion any particular traffic
      expects to cause between the monitoring point in the network and the
      destination ("rest-of-path congestion"). This would be a new capability.
      Today a network can use Explicit Congestion Notification (ECN) <xref
      target="RFC3168"></xref> to detect how much congestion the traffic has
      suffered between the source and a monitoring point ("upstream
      congestion"), but not beyond. This new capability would enable an ISP to
      give incentives for the use of LEDBAT-like applications that seek to
      minimise congestion in the network whilst also being able to determine
      if excessive use of traditional UDP or even TCP applications was
      contributing excessively to congestion.</t>

      <t>So we propose a new approach which we call Congestion Exposure. We
      propose that congestion information should be made visible at the IP
      layer, so that any network node can measure the contribution to
      congestion of an aggregate of traffic as easily as straight volume can
      be measured today. Once the information is exposed in this way, it is
      then possible to use it to measure the true impact of any traffic on the
      network.</t>

      <t>In general, congestion exposure gives operators a principled way to
      hold their customers accountable for the impact on others of their
      network usage and reward them for choosing congestion-sensitive
      applications.</t>

      <!-- = = = = = = = = = = = = = = = = = = = = = = = = = = = = = = = = = = -->

      <section title="ECN - a Step in the Right Direction">
        <t>Explicit Congestion Notification <xref target="RFC3168"></xref>
        allows routers to explicitly tell end-hosts that they are approaching
        the point of congestion. ECN builds on Active Queue Mechanisms such as
        random early detection (RED) <xref target="RFC2309"></xref> by
        allowing the router to mark a packet with a Congestion Experienced
        (CE) codepoint, rather than dropping it. The probability of a packet
        being marked increases with the length of the queue and thus the rate
        of CE marks is a guide to the level of congestion at that queue. This
        CE codepoint travels forward through the network to the receiver which
        then informs the sender that it has seen congestion. The sender is
        then required to respond as if it had experienced a packet loss.
        Because the CE codepoint is visible in the IP layer, this approach
        reveals the upstream congestion level for a packet.</t>

        <t>Alas, this is not enough - ECN gives a network node an idea of the
        congestion experienced on the path up to that node. If this network
        node were near a receiver, it could help hold that receiver
        accountable for the congestion caused by incoming traffic. But a
        receiver can only indirectly influence incoming congestion, by
        politely asking the sender to control it. A receiver cannot make a
        sender install an adaptive codec, or install LEDBAT instead of TCP
        congestion-control. And a receiver cannot cause an attacker to stop
        flooding it with traffic.</t>

        <t>What is needed is knowledge of the downstream congestion level
        relative to the node in the network that is measuring it. That is, the
        congestion expected from that point along the rest of the path to the
        receiver. This requires additional information that is still concealed
        from the network, but which ConEx is designed to reveal.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <!-- ====================================================================== -->

    <section anchor="conex-uses-cases" title="ConEx Use Cases">
      <t>This section sets out some of the potentially most important use
      cases for ConEx. These use cases rely on some of the components
      described in <xref target="ConEx-Abstract-Mech"></xref>. The authors
      don't claim this is an exhaustive list of use cases, nor that they have
      equal merit. But these use cases represent a consensus among people that
      have been working on this approach for some years.</t>

      <!-- = = = = = = = = = = = = = = = = = = = = = = = = = = = = = = = = = = -->

      <section anchor="conex-uses-traff-man"
               title="Inform the Operator's Traffic Management">
        <t>Currently many operators impose some form of traffic management.
        They consider this as an economic necessity&nbsp;particularly at peak
        hours&mdash; the only reason their networks work as a commercial
        concern is that they can rely on statistical multiplexing to share
        their expensive network between large numbers of customers. In order
        to ensure all customers get decent performance from the network, they
        subject the "heaviest" customers to some form of traffic management
        (see <xref format="title" target="conex-uses-Existing"></xref> in
        <xref target="conex-uses-Existing"></xref>). Often multiple approaches
        are added on top of each other, including resorting to expensive flow
        aware devices such as DPI boxes or flow-aware routers. This is
        probably a sign that none of the approaches are really addressing the
        problem properly.</t>

        <t>ConEx offers a better approach that will actually target the
        traffic from consumers that contribute most to any congestion, and
        otherwise stand aside without intervening. By using Ingress or Egress
        Policers, an operator can identify which consumers are causing the
        greatest congestion-volume throughout the network. This can then be
        used as the basis for traffic management decisions. The Ingress
        Policer described in <xref target="Policing-freedom"></xref> is one
        interesting approach that gives the consumer a congestion-volume
        allowance as the fill-rate of a token-bucket, but where the tokens
        give the right to cause bits of congestion-volume, rather than to send
        bits of data-volume. So long as consumers stay within their limit,
        then their traffic is unaffected. Once they exceed that limit then
        their traffic will be slowed temporarily.</t>
      </section>

      <!-- = = = = = = = = = = = = = = = = = = = = = = = = = = = = = = = = = = -->

      <section anchor="conex-uses-scavenge"
               title="Consequence: Incentivise Scavenger Transports">
        <t>Recent work proposes a new approach for QoS where traffic is
        provided with a less than best effort or "scavenger" quality of
        service. The idea is that low priority but high volume traffic such as
        OS updates, P2P file transfers and view-later TV programs should be
        allowed to use any spare network capacity, but should rapidly get out
        of the way if a higher priority or interactive application starts up.
        To a degree, this facility can be provided in the network. Low Extra
        Delay BAckground Transport <xref target="LEDBAT"></xref> is an example
        of a new type of solution being actively explored which proposes that
        hosts can provide this scavenger service for themselves using a new
        congestion control algorithm. LEDBAT yields when seeking out bandwidth
        if it detects that delay is rising, and other similar protocols share
        capacity less aggressively when competing with protocols like TCP.</t>

        <t>At present most operators assume a strong correlation between the
        volume of a flow and the impact that flow causes in the network. This
        assumption can fail badly for protocols like LEDBAT that transfer
        large volumes of data but yield if congestion approaches. At the other
        extreme, this assumption is eroded by unresponsive interactive
        streaming which is unresponsive to congestion (inelastic) and hence
        can cause high congestion at relatively low data volumes. LEDBAT-like
        transports can transfer large volumes of data and may reach high
        transfer speeds if the network is uncongested. Therefore network
        operators who use volume or bit-rate to judge the impact of traffic on
        their network give these protocols no encouragement, when they ought
        to welcome them. Consequently the only current incentive for LEDBAT is
        that it can reduce self-congestion effects (see <xref
        target="conex-uses-self-congestion"></xref>).</t>

        <t>If the network operator has deployed a ConEx-aware Ingress Policer
        then they are able to incentivise the use of LEDBAT because a user
        will be policed according to the overall congestion-volume their
        traffic generates, not the rate or data volume. If all background file
        transfers are only generating a low level of congestion, then the
        sender has more "congestion budget" to "spend" on their interactive
        applications. It can be shown <xref target="Kelly"></xref> that this
        approach improves social welfare&mdash;in other words if you limit the
        congestion that all users can generate then everyone benefits from a
        better service.</t>
      </section>

      <!-- = = = = = = = = = = = = = = = = = = = = = = = = = = = = = = = = = = -->

      <section anchor="conex-uses-qos"
               title="Consequence: User-Controlled Intra-Class Quality of Service (QoS)">
        <t>Most QoS approaches require the active participation of routers to
        control the delay and loss characteristics for the traffic. For
        real-time interactive traffic it is clear that low delay (and
        predictable jitter) are critical, and thus these probably always need
        different treatment at a router. However if low loss is the issue then
        ConEx offers an alternative approach.</t>

        <t>Assuming the ingress ISP has deployed a ConEx Ingress Policer, then
        the only control on a user's traffic is dependent on the congestion
        that user has caused. Likewise, if they are receiving traffic through
        a ConEx Egress Policer then their ISP will impose traffic controls
        (prioritisation, rate limiting, etc) based on the congestion they have
        caused. If an end-user (be they the receiver or sender) wants to
        prioritise some traffic over other traffic then they can allow that
        traffic to generate or cause more congestion. The price they will pay
        will be to reduce the congestion that their other traffic causes.</t>

        <t>Streaming video content-delivery is a good candidate for such
        ConEx-mediated QoS. Such traffic can tolerate moderately high delays,
        but there are strong economic pressures to maintain a high enough data
        rate (as that will directly influence the Quality of Experience the
        end-user receives. This approach removes the need for bandwidth
        brokers to establish QoS sessions, by removing the need to coordinate
        requests from multiple sources to pre-allocate bandwidth, as well as
        to coordinate which allocations to revoke when bandwidth predictions
        turn out to be wrong. There is also no need to "rate-police" at the
        boundaries on a per-flow basis, removing the need to keep per-flow
        state (which in turn makes this approach more scalable).</t>
      </section>

      <!-- = = = = = = = = = = = = = = = = = = = = = = = = = = = = = = = = = = -->

      <section anchor="conex-uses-other" title="Other Use-Cases">
        <t><list style="hanging">
            <t
            hangText="Another Consequence: Preventing Congestion Collapse:">The
            Internet is no less vulnerable to congestion collapses now than it
            was in the 1980s <xref target="RFC3714"></xref>. Under extreme
            congestion, ConEx-based traffic management would automatically
            override host congestion control and prevent congestion collapse.
            Without visibility of congestion, other traffic management
            approaches do not have this property.</t>

            <t hangText="Inform Inter-Operator Contracts:">Just as ConEx can
            inform a bulk traffic policer of the congestion-volume a
            particular end-consumer causes, it can also inform a border meter
            of the total congestion-volume one network sends into the next. If
            ConEx made such information available, it is likely that operators
            would build it into the traffic contracts in their interconnection
            arrangements.</t>

            <t hangText="Inform Capacity Provisioning:">{ToDo:}</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <!-- ====================================================================== -->

    <section anchor="conex-uses-deployments" title="Deployment Arrangements">
      <t>This document is about concepts and use-cases, not mechanism.
      However, in order to describe how the above use-cases would be deployed,
      a high-level understanding of ConEx mechanism is first given below.</t>

      <section title="Incremental Deployment Features of the Protocol Mechanism">
        <t>The ConEx mechanism document <xref
        target="ConEx-Abstract-Mech"></xref> goes to great lengths to design
        for incremental deployment in all the respects below. It should be
        referred to for precise details on each of these points:<list
            style="symbols">
            <t>The ConEx mechanism is essentially a change to the source, in
            order to re-insert congestion feedback into the network (<xref
            target="conex-uses_Fig_ConEx_Placement"></xref>).</t>

            <t>Source-host-only deployment is possible without any negotiation
            required, and individual transport protocol implementations within
            a source host can be updated separately.</t>

            <t>Receiver modification may optionally improve ConEx for some
            transport protocols with feedback limitations (TCP being the main
            example), but it is not a necessity</t>

            <t>Proxies for the source and/or receiver are feasible (though not
            necessarily straightforward)</t>

            <t>Queues and network forwarding do not require any modification
            for ConEx.</t>

            <t>ECN is not required in the network for ConEx. If some network
            nodes support ECN, it can be used by ConEx.</t>

            <t>ECN is not required at the receiver for ConEx. The sender
            should nonetheless attempt to negotiate ECN-usage with the
            receiver, given some aspects of ConEx work better the more ECN is
            deployed, particularly auditing and border measurement.</t>

            <t>Given ConEx exposes information for IP-layer policy devices to
            use, the design does not preclude possible innovative uses of
            ConEx information by other IP-layer devices, e.g. forwarding
            itself</t>

            <t>Packets indicate whether or not they support ConEx.</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="conex-uses-deploy-concepts"
               title="Per-Network Deployment Concepts">
        <t>Network deployment-related definitions:<list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="Internet Ingress:">The first IP node a packet
            traverses that is outside the source's own network. In a domestic
            network that will be the first node downstream from the home
            access equipment. In an enterprise network this is the provider
            edge router.</t>

            <t hangText="Internet Egress:">The last IP node a packet traverses
            before reaching the receiver's network.</t>

            <t hangText="ConEx-Enabled Network:">A network whose edge nodes
            implement ConEx policy functions.</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>Each network can unilaterally choose to use any ConEx information
        given by those sources using ConEx, independently of whether other
        networks use it.</t>

        <t>Typically, a network will use ConEx information by deploying a
        policy function at the ingress edge of its network to monitor arriving
        traffic and to act in some way on the congestion information in those
        packets that are ConEx-enabled. Actions might include policing,
        altering the class of service, or re-routing. Alternatively, less
        direct actions via a management system might include triggering
        capacity upgrades, triggering penalty clauses in contracts or levying
        charges between networks based on ConEx measurements.</t>

        <t>{ToDO: I need to sleep, so I'll resort to bullets for the
        rest...}</t>

        <t>Audit: what it is (checks ConEx info is never less than actual
        congestion so far on the path). If ConEx protocol is adhered to, there
        should be no place in a network where this is not true, so audit can
        be placed wherever most convenient. But most useful placement is after
        the likely congestion locations, ideally as close to the egress as
        possible.</t>

        <t>Typically, a network using ConEx info will deploy a ConEx policy
        function near the ingress edge and a ConEx audit function near the
        egress edge. The segment of the path between a ConEx policy function
        and a ConEx audit function can be considered to be a ConEx-protected
        segment of the path. And assuming a network covers all its ingresses
        and egresses with policy functions and audit functions respectively,
        the network within this ring will be a ConEx-protected network.</t>

        <t>Of course, because each edge device usually serves as both an
        ingress and an egress, the two functions are both likely to be present
        in each edge device.</t>

        <t>[Plan view diagram of a ConEx-protected segment and ConEx-protected
        network here?]</t>

        <t>[We might have to explain the concept of non-negativity of
        congestion earlier in the doc, so we can use it here. Could also
        require one of those staircase diags I used in re-ECN, but that assume
        ECN and ConEx - I'd rather focus on drop-only cases.]</t>

        <t>Sources can choose not to send ConEx-enabled packets. Networks are
        expected to make it in senders' interests to expose congestion
        information in packets by treating ConEx-enabled packets better (in
        some sense) than non-ConEx packets.</t>

        <t>Prior to ConEx, networks have generally place constraints on
        incoming traffic to reduce the chances of it causing congestion. For
        ConEx-enabled traffic, networks can remove these pessimistic
        constraints and solely apply constraints when the ConEx information
        indicates traffic is contributing to congestion.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="conex-uses-single-net-scenario"
               title="Single Receiving Network Scenario">
        <t>Charter scenario [Description, picture and some deployment
        incentive text]</t>

        <t>Focusing on first step: why OS developers of senders would
        implement and why users would send ConEx. Then, once info is there,
        why network would use it.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="conex-uses-other-deployments"
               title="Other Initial Deployment Scenarios">
        <t><list style="symbols">
            <t>Mobile: <xref target="conex-mobile"></xref> Couple of sentence
            description (characterised by terminals and network standards all
            co-ordinated.)</t>

            <t>Data Centre: Brief description. (Happens because under one
            authority)</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <!-- ====================================================================== -->

    <section anchor="conex-uses-issues" title="Potential Issues or Non-Issues">
      <!-- = = = = = = = = = = = = = = = = = = = = = = = = = = = = = = = = = = -->

      <section anchor="conex-uses-secret"
               title="Congestion as a Commercial Secret">
        <t>Network operators have long viewed the congestion levels in their
        network as a business secret. In some ways this harks back to the days
        of fixed-line telecommunications where congestion manifested as failed
        connections or dropped calls. But even in modern data-centric packet
        networks congestion is viewed as a secret not to be shared with
        competitors. It can be debated whether this view is sensible, but it
        may make operators uneasy about deploying ConEx. The following two
        examples highlight some of the arguments used: <list style="symbols">
            <t>An ISP buys backhaul capacity from an operator. Most operators
            want their customers to get a decent service and so they want the
            backhaul to be relatively uncongested. If there is competition,
            operators will seek to reassure their customers (the operators)
            that their network is not congested in order to attract their
            custom. Some operators may see ConEx as a threat since it will
            enable those operators to see the actual congestion in their
            network. On the other hand, operators with low congestion could
            use ConEx to show how well their network performs, and so might
            have an incentive to enable it.</t>

            <t>ISPs would like to be part of the lucrative content provision
            market. Currently the ISP can gain a competitive edge as it can
            put its own content in a higher QoS class, whereas traffic from
            content providers has to use the Best Effort class. The ISP may
            take the view that if they can conceal the congestion level in
            their Best Effort class this will make it harder for the content
            provider to maintain a good level of QoS. But in reality the
            Content Provider will just use the feedback mechanisms in
            streaming protocols such as Adobe Flash to monitor the
            congestion.</t>
          </list> Of course some might say that the idea of keeping congestion
        secret is silly. After all, end-hosts already have knowledge of the
        congestion throughout the network, albeit only along specific paths,
        and operators can work out that there is persistent congestion as
        their customers will be suffering degraded network performance.</t>
      </section>

      <!-- = = = = = = = = = = = = = = = = = = = = = = = = = = = = = = = = = = -->

      <section anchor="conex-uses-self-congestion" title="Self Congestion">
        <t>{ToDo: The following para has been moved here from the
        Introduction. Re-phrase as an issue}</t>

        <t>Congestion takes two distinct forms. The first results from the
        interaction of traffic from one set of users with traffic from other
        users, causing in a reduction in service (a cost) for all of them. the
        second, often referred to as "self-congestion", occurs when an
        increase in traffic from a single user causes that user to suffer a
        worse service (for instance because their traffic is being "shaped" by
        their ISP, or because they have an excessively large buffer in their
        home router). ConEx is principally interested in the first form of
        congestion since it involves informing those other users of the impact
        you expect to have on them.</t>

        <t></t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <!-- ====================================================================== -->

    <section title="Security Considerations">
      <t>This document proposes a mechanism tagging onto Explicit Congestion
      Notification <xref target="RFC3168"></xref>, and inherits the security
      issues listed therein. The additional issues from ConEx markings relate
      to the degree of trust each forwarding point places in the ConEx
      markings it receives, which is a business decision mostly orthogonal to
      the markings themselves.</t>

      <t>One expected use of exposed congestion information is to hold the
      end-to-end transport and the network accountable to each other. The
      network cannot be relied on to report information to the receiver
      against its interest, and the same applies for the information the
      receiver feeds back to the sender, and that the sender reports back to
      the network. Looking at each in turn: <list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="The Network">In general it is not in any network's
          interest to under-declare congestion since this will have
          potentially negative consequences for all users of that network. It
          may be in its interest to over-declare congestion if, for instance,
          it wishes to force traffic to move away to a different network or
          simply to reduce the amount of traffic it is carrying. Congestion
          Exposure itself won't significantly alter the incentives for and
          against honest declaration of congestion by a network, but we can
          imagine applications of Congestion Exposure that will change these
          incentives. There is a perception among network operators that their
          level of congestion is a business secret. Today, congestion is one
          of the worst-kept secrets a network has, because end-hosts can see
          congestion better than network operators can. Congestion Exposure
          will enable network operators to pinpoint whether congestion is on
          one side or the other of any border. It is conceivable that
          forwarders with underprovisioned networks may try to obstruct
          deployment of Congestion Exposure.</t>

          <t hangText="The Receiver">Receivers generally have an incentive to
          under-declare congestion since they generally wish to receive the
          data from the sender as rapidly as possible. <xref
          target="Savage"></xref> explains how a receiver can significantly
          improve their throughput by failing to declare congestion. This is a
          problem with or without Congestion Exposure. <xref
          target="KGao"></xref> explains one possible technique to encourage
          receiver's to be honest in their declaration of congestion.</t>

          <t hangText="The Sender">One proposed mechanism for Congestion
          Exposure deployment adds a requirement for a sender to advise the
          network how much congestion it has suffered or caused. Although most
          senders currently respond to congestion they are informed of, one
          use of exposed congestion information might be to encourage sources
          of persistent congestion to back off more aggressively. Then clearly
          there may be an incentive for the sender to under-declare
          congestion. This will be a particular problem with sources of
          flooding attacks. "Policing" mechanisms have been proposed to deal
          with this.</t>
        </list> In addition there are potential problems from source spoofing.
      A malicious sender can pretend to be another user by spoofing the source
      address. Congestion Exposure allows for "Policers" and "Traffic Shapers"
      so as to be robust against injection of false congestion information
      into the forward path.</t>

      <section title="Information Security">
        <t>make a source believe it has seen more congestion than it has</t>

        <t>hijack a user's identity and make it appear they are dishonest at
        an egress policer</t>

        <t>clear or otherwise tamper with the ConEx markings</t>

        <t>...</t>

        <t>{ToDo} Write these up properly...</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <!-- ====================================================================== -->

    <section title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>This document does not require actions by IANA.</t>
    </section>

    <!-- ====================================================================== -->

    <section title="Conclusions">
      <t>{ToDo}</t>

      <t></t>
    </section>

    <!-- ====================================================================== -->

    <section title="Acknowledgments">
      <t>Bob Briscoe is partly funded by Trilogy, a research project
      (ICT-216372) supported by the European Community under its Seventh
      Framework Programme. The views expressed here are those of the author
      only.</t>

      <t>The authors would like to thank the many people that have commented
      on this document. Bernard Aboba, Mikael Abrahamsson, Jo&atilde;o Taveira
      Ara&uacute;jo, Marcelo Bagnulo Braun, Steve Bauer, Caitlin Bestler,
      Steven Blake, Louise Burness, Ken Carlberg, Alissa Cooper, Nandita
      Dukkipati, Philip Eardley, Wes Eddy, Matthew Ford, Ingemar Johansson,
      Georgios Karagiannis, Mirja Kuehlewind, Dirk Kutscher, Zhu Lei, Kevin
      Mason, Matt Mathis, David McDysan, Michael Menth, Chris Morrow, Tim
      Shepard, Hannes Tschofenig and Stuart Venters. Please accept our
      apologies if your name has been missed off this list.</t>

      <section title="Contributors">
        <t>The following co-edited this document through most of its life:</t>

        <figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[
   Toby Moncaster
   Moncaster Internet Consulting
   Dukes
   Layer Marney
   Colchester  CO5 9UZ
   UK
   EMail: toby@moncaster.com

   John Leslie
   JLC.net
   10 Souhegan Street
   Milford, NH  03055
   US
   EMail: john@jlc.net
]]></artwork>
        </figure>
      </section>
    </section>

    <!-- ====================================================================== -->
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Informative References">
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.0970'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.2309'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.3168'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.3714'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6077'?>

      <!-- <reference anchor="Re-Feedback"
                 target="http://www.acm.org/sigs/sigcomm/sigcomm2005/techprog.html#session8">
        <front>
          <title>Policing Congestion Response in an Internetwork Using
          Re-Feedback</title>

          <author fullname="Bob Briscoe" initials="B" surname="Briscoe">
            <organization>BT &amp; UCL</organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="Arnaud Jacquet" initials="A" surname="Jacquet">
            <organization>BT</organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="Carla Di Cairano-Gilfedder" initials="C"
                  surname="Di Cairano-Gilfedder">
            <organization>BT</organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="Alessandro Salvatori" initials="A"
                  surname="Salvatori">
            <organization>Eur&eacute;com &amp; BT</organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="Andrea Soppera" initials="A" surname="Soppera">
            <organization>BT</organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="Martin Koyabe" initials="M" surname="Koyabe">
            <organization>BT</organization>
          </author>

          <date month="August" year="2005" />
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="ACM SIGCOMM CCR" value="35(4)277&mdash;288" />

        <format target="http://www.cs.ucl.ac.uk/staff/B.Briscoe/projects/2020comms/refb/refb_sigcomm05.pdf"
                type="PDF" />
      </reference>
 -->

      <reference anchor="LEDBAT">
        <front>
          <title>Low Extra Delay Background Transport (LEDBAT)</title>

          <author fullname="Stanislav Shalunov" initials="S"
                  surname="Shalunov">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="Greg Hazel" initials="G" surname="Hazel">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="Janardhan Iyengar" initials="J" surname="Iyengar">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="Mirja Kuehlewind" initials="M"
                  surname="Kuehlewind">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date day="31" month="May" year="2011" />

          <abstract>
            <t>LEDBAT is an experimental delay-based congestion control
            algorithm that attempts to utilize the available bandwidth on an
            end-to-end path while limiting the consequent increase in queueing
            delay on the path. LEDBAT uses changes in one-way delay
            measurements to limit congestion that the flow itself induces in
            the network. LEDBAT is designed for use by background
            bulk-transfer applications; it is designed to be no more
            aggressive than TCP congestion control and to yield in the
            presence of any competing TCP flows, thus limiting interference
            with the network performance of the competing flows.</t>
          </abstract>
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft"
                    value="draft-ietf-ledbat-congestion-06" />

        <format target="http://www.ietf.org/internet-drafts/draft-ietf-ledbat-congestion-06.txt"
                type="TXT" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="Savage">
        <front>
          <title>TCP Congestion Control with a Misbehaving Receiver</title>

          <author fullname="S. Savage" initials="S." surname="Savage">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="D. Wetherall" initials="D." surname="Wetherall">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="T. Anderson" initials="T." surname="Anderson">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date year="1999" />
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="ACM SIGCOMM Computer Communication Review" value="" />

        <format target="http://www.cs.ucsd.edu/~savage/papers/CCR99.pdf"
                type="PDF" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="KGao">
        <front>
          <title>Incrementally Deployable Prevention to TCP Attack with
          Misbehaving Receivers</title>

          <author fullname="Kun Gar" initials="K." surname="Gao">
            <organization>Computer Science Department, Carnegie Mellon
            University</organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="Chengwen Chris Wang" initials="C. C."
                  surname="Wang">
            <organization>Computer Science Department, Carnegie Mellon
            University</organization>
          </author>

          <date day="14" month="December" year="2004" />
        </front>

        <format target="http://www.cs.cmu.edu/~kgao/course/15744/network.pdf"
                type="PDF" />
      </reference>

      <!--
      <reference anchor="BB-incentive">
        <front>
          <title>The Broadband Incentive Problem</title>

          <author>
            <organization>MIT Communications Futures Program
            (CFP)</organization>
          </author>

          <author>
            <organization>Cambridge University Communications Research
            Network</organization>
          </author>

          <date month="September" year="2005" />
        </front>

        <format target="http://cfp.mit.edu/docs/incentive-wp-sept2005.pdf"
                type="PDF" />
      </reference>
-->

      <reference anchor="Fair-use">
        <front>
          <title>Truth about 'fair usage' broadband</title>

          <author>
            <organization>Broadband Choices</organization>
          </author>

          <date year="2009" />
        </front>

        <format target="http://www.broadbandchoices.co.uk/fair-usage-broadband.html"
                type="HTML" />
      </reference>

      <!-- <reference anchor="Fairer-faster">
        <front>
          <title>A Fairer Faster Internet Protocol</title>

          <author fullname="Bob Briscoe" initials="B" surname="Briscoe">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date month="December" year="2008" />
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="IEEE Spectrum" value="Dec 2008 pp38-43" />

        <format target="http://spectrum.ieee.org/telecom/standards/a-fairer-faster-internet-protocol"
                type="HTML" />
      </reference>
 -->

      <reference anchor="Policing-freedom">
        <front>
          <title>Policing Freedom to Use the Internet Resource Pool</title>

          <author fullname="Bob Briscoe" initials="B" surname="Briscoe">
            <organization>BT &amp; UCL</organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="Arnaud Jacquet" initials="A" surname="Jacquet">
            <organization>BT</organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="Toby Moncaster" initials="T" surname="Moncaster">
            <organization>BT</organization>
          </author>

          <date day="4" month="December" year="2008" />
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="RE-Arch 2008 hosted at the 2008 CoNEXT conference"
                    value="" />

        <format target="http://portal.acm.org/ft_gateway.cfm?id=1544083&amp;type=pdf&amp;coll=GUIDE&amp;dl=GUIDE&amp;CFID=94433196&amp;CFTOKEN=11585540"
                type="PDF" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="Kelly"
                 target="http://www.statslab.cam.ac.uk/~frank/rate.html">
        <front>
          <title>Rate control for communication networks: shadow prices,
          proportional fairness and stability</title>

          <author fullname="Frank P. Kelly" initials="F.P" surname="Kelly">
            <organization>Cam Uni</organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="Aman K. Maulloo" initials="A.K" surname="Maulloo">
            <organization>Cam Uni</organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="David K. H. Tan" initials="D.K.H" surname="Tan">
            <organization>Cam Uni</organization>
          </author>

          <date month="" year="1998" />
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="Journal of the Operational Research Society"
                    value="49(3) 237--252" />

        <format target="http://www.statslab.cam.ac.uk/~frank/rate.html"
                type="PDF" />
      </reference>

      <!-- <reference anchor="Malice"
                 target="http://wesii.econinfosec.org/draft.php?paper_id=19">
        <front>
          <title>Using Self Interest to Prevent Malice; Fixing the Denial of
          Service Flaw of the Internet</title>

          <author fullname="Bob Briscoe" initials="B" surname="Briscoe">
            <organization>BT &amp; UCL</organization>
          </author>

          <date year="2006" />
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="WESII - Workshop on the Economics of Securing the Information Infrastructure"
                    value="2006" />

        <format target="http://wesii.econinfosec.org/draft.php?paper_id=19"
                type="PDF" />
      </reference>
 -->

      <!-- <reference anchor="Design-Philosophy">
        <front>
          <title>The Design Philosophy of the DARPA Internet Protocols</title>

          <author fullname="David D. Clark" initials="D.D." surname="Clark">
            <organization>MIT</organization>
          </author>

          <date year="1988" />
        </front>

        <format target="http://groups.csail.mit.edu/ana/Publications/PubPDFs/The%20design%20philosophy%20of%20the%20DARPA%20internet%20protocols.pdf"
                type="PDF" />
      </reference>
 -->

      <!-- <reference anchor="QoS-Models">
        <front>
          <title>Commercial Models for IP Quality of Service
          Interconnect</title>

          <author fullname="Bob Briscoe" initials="B" surname="Briscoe">
            <organization>BT &amp; UCL</organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="Steve Rudkin" initials="S" surname="Rudkin">
            <organization>BT</organization>
          </author>

          <date month="April" year="2005" />
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="BTTJ Special Edition on IP Quality of Service"
                    value="vol 23 (2)" />

        <format target="http://bobbriscoe.net/projects/ipe2eqos/gqs/papers/ixqos_bttj05.pdf"
                type="PDF" />
      </reference>
 -->

      <!-- <reference anchor="re-ecn-motive">
        <front>
          <title>Re-ECN: A Framework for adding Congestion Accountability to
          TCP/IP</title>

          <author fullname="Bob Briscoe" initials="B" surname="Briscoe">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="Arnaud Jacquet" initials="A" surname="Jacquet">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="Toby Moncaster" initials="T" surname="Moncaster">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="Alan Smith" initials="A" surname="Smith">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date month="October" year="2010" />
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft"
                    value="draft-briscoe-tsvwg-re-ecn-tcp-motivation-02" />

        <format target="http://www.ietf.org/internet-drafts/draft-briscoe-tsvwg-re-ecn-tcp-motivation-02.txt"
                type="TXT" />
      </reference>
 -->

      <!-- <reference anchor="Padhye">
        <front>
          <title>Modeling TCP Throughput: A Simple Model and its Empirical
          Validation</title>

          <author fullname="Jitendra Padhye" initials="J" surname="Padhye">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="Vicotor Firoiu" initials="V" surname="Firoiu">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="Don Towsley" initials="D" surname="Towsley">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="Jim Kurose" initials="J" surname="Kurose">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date day="30" month="May" year="1998" />
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="ACM SIGCOMM Computer Communications Review"
                    value="Vol 28(4), pages 303-314" />

        <format target="http://citeseerx.ist.psu.edu/viewdoc/download?doi=10.1.1.143.9137&amp;rep=rep1&amp;type=pdf"
                type="PDF" />
      </reference>
 -->

      <reference anchor="ConEx-Abstract-Mech">
        <front>
          <title>Congestion Exposure (ConEx) Concepts and Abstract
          Mechanism</title>

          <author fullname="Matt Mathis" initials="M" surname="Mathis">
            <organization>Google</organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="Bob Briscoe" initials="B" surname="Briscoe">
            <organization>BT</organization>
          </author>

          <date day="11" month="July" year="2011" />
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft"
                    value="draft-ietf-conex-abstract-mech-02" />

        <format target="http://www.ietf.org/internet-drafts/draft-ietf-conex-abstract-mech-00.txt"
                type="TXT" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="conex-mobile">
        <front>
          <title>Mobile Communication Congestion Exposure Scenario</title>

          <author fullname="Dirk Kutscher" initials="D" surname="Kutscher">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="Faisal Mir" initials="F" surname="Mir">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="Rolf Winter" initials="R" surname="Winter">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="Suresh Krishnan" initials="S" surname="Krishnan">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="Ying Zhang" initials="Y" surname="Zhang">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date day="7" month="March" year="2011" />

          <abstract>
            <t>This memo describes a mobile communications use case for
            congestion exposure (CONEX) with a particular focus on mobile
            communication networks such as 3GPP LTE. The draft describes the
            architecture of these networks (access and core networks), current
            QoS mechanisms and then discusses how congestion exposure concepts
            could be applied. Based on this, this memo suggests a set of
            requirements for CONEX mechanisms that particularly apply to
            mobile networks.</t>
          </abstract>
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft"
                    value="draft-kutscher-conex-mobile-00" />

        <format target="http://www.ietf.org/internet-drafts/draft-kutscher-conex-mobile-00.txt"
                type="TXT" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="Bauer09">
        <front>
          <title>The Evolution of Internet Congestion</title>

          <author fullname="Steven Bauer" initials="S" surname="Bauer">
            <organization>MIT</organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="David Clark" initials="D" surname="Clark">
            <organization>MIT</organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="William Lehr" initials="W" surname="Lehr">
            <organization>MIT</organization>
          </author>

          <date year="2009" />
        </front>

        <format target="http://mitas.csail.mit.edu/papers/Bauer_Clark_Lehr_2009.pdf"
                type="PDF" />
      </reference>

      <!-- <reference anchor="Varian">
        <front>
          <title>Congestion pricing principles</title>

          <author fullname="Hal Varian" initials="H" surname="Varian">
            <organization>Google</organization>
          </author>

          <date day="29" month="July" year="2010" />
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="Technical Plenary" value="78th IETF Meeting" />
      </reference>
 -->
    </references>

    <!-- ====================================================================== -->

    <section title="Changes from previous drafts (to be removed by the RFC Editor)">
      <t><list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="From draft-ietf-conex-concepts-uses-01 to -02:">New
          Abstract &amp; Introduction. Concepts and Misconceptions sections
          added around defintions. Minor clarifications to Existing Traffic
          Management and Use-Cases sections, with Other use Cases Added.
          Deployment Arrangements Section added.</t>

          <t hangText="From draft-ietf-conex-concepts-uses-00 to -01:"></t>

          <t>Added section on timescales: Section 6</t>

          <t>Revised introduction to clarify congestion definitions</t>

          <t>Changed source for congestion definition in <xref
          target="conex-uses-defs"></xref></t>

          <t>Other minor changes</t>

          <t
          hangText="From draft-moncaster-conex-concepts-uses-02 to draft-ietf-conex-concepts-uses-00 (per decisions of working group):"></t>

          <t>Removed section on DDoS mitigation use case.</t>

          <t>Removed appendix on ConEx Architectural Elements. PLEASE NOTE:
          Alignment of terminology with the Abstract Mechanism draft has been
          deferred to the next version.</t>

          <t
          hangText="From draft-moncaster-conex-concepts-uses-01 to draft-moncaster-conex-concepts-uses-02:"></t>

          <t>Updated document to take account of the new Abstract Mechanism
          draft <xref target="ConEx-Abstract-Mech"></xref>.</t>

          <t>Updated the definitions section.</t>

          <t>Removed sections on Requirements and Mechanism.</t>

          <t>Moved section on ConEx Architectural Elements to appendix.</t>

          <t>Minor changes throughout.</t>

          <t
          hangText="From draft-moncaster-conex-concepts-uses-00 to draft-moncaster-conex-concepts-uses-01:"></t>

          <t>Changed end of Abstract to better reflect new title</t>

          <t>Created new section describing the architectural elements of
          ConEx. Added Edge Monitors and Border Monitors (other elements are
          Ingress, Egress and Border Policers).</t>

          <t>Extensive re-write of <xref target="conex-uses-cases"></xref>
          partly in response to suggestions from Dirk Kutscher</t>

          <t>Improved layout of <xref target="conex-uses-defs"></xref> and
          added definitions of Whole Path Congestion, ConEx-Enabled and
          ECN-Enabled. Re-wrote definition of Congestion Volume. Renamed
          Ingress and Egress Router to Ingress and Egress Node as these nodes
          may not actually be routers.</t>

          <t>Improved document structure. Merged sections on Exposing
          Congestion and ECN.</t>

          <t>Added new section on ConEx requirements with a ConEx Issues
          subsection. Text for these came from the start of the old ConEx Use
          Cases section</t>

          <t>Added a sub-section on Partial vs Full Deployment (Section
          5.5)</t>

          <t>Added a discussion on ConEx as a Business Secret <xref
          target="conex-uses-secret"></xref></t>

          <t
          hangText="From draft-conex-mechanism-00 to draft-moncaster-conex-concepts-uses-00:"></t>

          <t>Changed filename to draft-moncaster-conex-concepts-uses.</t>

          <t>Changed title to ConEx Concepts and Use Cases.</t>

          <t>Chose uniform capitalisation of ConEx.</t>

          <t>Moved definition of Congestion Volume to list of definitions.</t>

          <t>Clarified mechanism section. Changed section title.</t>

          <t>Modified text relating to conex-aware policing and policers
          (which are NOT defined terms).</t>

          <t>Re-worded bullet on distinguishing ConEx and non-ConEx traffic in
          <xref target="conex-uses-cases"></xref>.</t>
        </list></t>
    </section>
  </back>
</rfc>
