<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!-- This template is for creating an Internet Draft using xml2rfc,
    which is available here: http://xml.resource.org. -->
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!-- One method to get references from the online citation libraries.
    There has to be one entity for each item to be referenced. 
    An alternate method (rfc include) is described in the references. -->

<!ENTITY RFC0793 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.0793.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC1191 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1191.xml">
<!-- update to latest TCP congestion control RFC -->
<!ENTITY RFC4821 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4821.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC1981 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1981.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC2581 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2581.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5681 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5681.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC2675 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2675.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC1122 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1122.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC2883 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2883.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4015 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4015.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4963 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4963.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC1072 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1072.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC1185 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1185.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC1323 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1323.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC2018 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2018.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC1110 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1110.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC0896 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.0896.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC2119 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3522 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3522.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6298 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6298.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6528 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6528.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6675 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6675.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6691 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6691.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6817 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6817.xml">


]>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<!-- used by XSLT processors -->
<!-- For a complete list and description of processing instructions (PIs), 
    please see http://xml.resource.org/authoring/README.html. -->
<!-- Below are generally applicable Processing Instructions (PIs) that most I-Ds might want to use.
    (Here they are set differently than their defaults in xml2rfc v1.32) -->
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<!-- give errors regarding ID-nits and DTD validation -->
<!-- control the table of contents (ToC) -->
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<!-- generate a ToC -->
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<!-- the number of levels of subsections in ToC. default: 3 -->
<!-- control references -->
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<!-- use symbolic references tags, i.e, [RFC2119] instead of [1] -->
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<!-- sort the reference entries alphabetically -->
<!-- control vertical white space 
    (using these PIs as follows is recommended by the RFC Editor) -->
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<!-- do not start each main section on a new page -->
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<!-- keep one blank line between list items -->
<!-- end of list of popular I-D processing instructions -->
<rfc category="std" 
     docName="draft-ietf-tcpm-1323bis-17" 
     ipr="trust200902">
<!-- category values: std, bcp, info, exp, and historic
     ipr values: trust200902, noModificationTrust200902, noDerivativesTrust200902,
       or pre5378Trust200902
     you can add the attributes updates="NNNN" and obsoletes="NNNN" 
     they will automatically be output with "(if approved)" -->

<!-- ***** FRONT MATTER ***** -->
<front>
  <!-- The abbreviated title is used in the page header - it is only necessary if the 
       full title is longer than 39 characters -->

  <title>TCP Extensions for High Performance</title> 
  <!-- <title>TCP options for Window Scaling and Timestamps</title> -->
   
  <!-- add 'role="editor"' below for the editors if appropriate -->

  <!-- Another author who claims to be an editor -->

  <author fullname="David Borman" 
          initials="D." 
          surname="Borman">
    <organization>Quantum Corporation</organization>
    <address>
      <postal>
        <street></street>
        <city>Mendota Heights</city>
        <code>MN 55120</code>
        <country>USA</country>
      </postal>
      <email>david.borman@quantum.com</email>
    </address>
  </author>
    
  <author fullname="Bob Braden" 
          initials="B." 
          surname="Braden">
    <organization>University of Southern California</organization>
    <address>
      <postal>
        <street>4676 Admiralty Way</street>
        <city>Marina del Rey</city>
        <code>CA 90292</code>
        <country>USA</country>
      </postal>
      <email>braden@isi.edu</email>
    </address>
  </author>
    
  <author fullname="Van Jacobson" 
          initials="V." 
          surname="Jacobson">
    <organization>Google, Inc.</organization>
    <address>
      <postal>
        <street>1600 Amphitheatre Parkway</street>
        <city>Mountain View</city>
        <code>CA 94043</code>
        <country>USA</country>
      </postal>
      <email>vanj@google.com</email>
    </address>
  </author>
    
    
    
  <author fullname="Richard Scheffenegger" 
          initials="R."
          surname="Scheffenegger" 
          role="editor">
    <organization>NetApp, Inc.</organization>
    <address>
      <postal>
        <street>Am Euro Platz 2</street>
        <code>1120</code>
        <city>Vienna</city>
        <region></region>
        <country>Austria</country>
      </postal>
      <email>rs@netapp.com</email>
    </address>
  </author>

  <date year="2013" />


  <area>Transport</area>

  <workgroup>TCP Maintenance (TCPM)</workgroup>

  <keyword>Internet-Draft</keyword>
  <keyword>I-D</keyword>
  
  <abstract>
    
    <t>This document specifies a set of TCP extensions to improve 
    performance over paths with a large bandwidth * delay product and to 
    provide reliable operation over very high-speed paths.  It defines 
    the TCP Window Scale (WS) option and the TCP Timestamps (TS) option 
    and their semantics. The Window Scale option is used to support 
    larger receive windows, while the Timestamps option can be used for 
    at least two distinct mechanisms, PAWS (Protection Against Wrapped 
    Sequences) and RTTM (Round Trip Time Measurement), that are also 
    described herein. </t>
    
    <t>This document obsoletes RFC1323 and describes changes from it.
    </t>
  </abstract>
</front>

<middle>
  <section anchor="sec1" title="Introduction">
    <t>The TCP protocol <xref target="RFC0793"/> was designed to operate 
      reliably over almost any transmission medium regardless of transmission 
      rate, delay, corruption, duplication, or reordering of segments. Over the 
      years, advances in networking technology have resulted in ever-higher 
      transmission speeds, and the fastest paths are well beyond the domain for 
      which TCP was originally engineered.
    </t>
    <t>This document defines a set of modest extensions to TCP to extend the 
      domain of its application to match the increasing network capability.  It 
      is an update to and obsoletes <xref target="RFC1323"/>, which in turn is 
      based upon and obsoletes <xref target="RFC1072"/> and <xref 
      target="RFC1185"/>.
    </t>
    <t>Changes between <xref target="RFC1323"/> and this document are detailed 
      in <xref target="AppC"/>. These changes are partly due to errata in 
      <xref target="RFC1323"/>, and partly due to the improved understanding 
      of how the involved components interact.</t>
    <t>For brevity, the full discussions of the merits and history behind the 
      TCP options defined within this document have been omitted. <xref 
      target="RFC1323"/> should be consulted for reference. It is recommended 
      that a modern TCP stack implements and make use of the extensions 
      described in this document.
    </t>
    <section anchor="sec11" title="TCP Performance">
      <t>TCP performance problems arise when the bandwidth * delay product is 
        large. A network having such paths is referred to as "long, fat network" 
        (LFN).  
      </t>
      <t>There are two fundamental performance problems with basic TCP over LFN 
        paths:
        <list style="format (%d)">
          <t>Window Size Limit
            <vspace blankLines="1"/>
            The TCP header uses a 16 bit field to report the receive window size 
            to the sender.  Therefore, the largest window that can be used is 
            2^16 = 64 KiB. For LFN paths where the bandwidth * delay product 
            exceeds 64 KiB, the receive window limits the maximum throughput of 
            the TCP connection over the path, i.e., the amount of unacknowledged 
            data that TCP can send in order to keep the pipeline full.
            <vspace blankLines="1"/>
            To circumvent this problem, Section 2 of this memo defines a TCP 
            option, "Window Scale", to allow windows larger than 2^16.  This 
            option defines an implicit scale factor, which is used to multiply 
            the window size value found in a TCP header to obtain the true 
            window size.
            <vspace blankLines="1"/>
            It must be noted, that the use of large receive windows increases 
            the chance of too quickly wrapping sequence numbers, as described 
            below in <xref target="sec12"/>, (1). 
          </t>
          <t>Recovery from Losses
            <vspace blankLines="1"/> 
            Packet losses in an LFN can have a catastrophic effect on 
            throughput.  
            <vspace blankLines="1"/> 
            To generalize the Fast Retransmit / Fast Recovery mechanism to handle 
            multiple packets dropped per window, Selective Acknowledgments are 
            required.  Unlike the normal cumulative acknowledgments of TCP, 
            Selective Acknowledgments give the sender a complete picture of 
            which segments are queued at the receiver and which have not yet 
            arrived. 
            <vspace blankLines="1"/> 
            Selective acknowledgements and their use are specified in separate 
            documents, "TCP Selective Acknowledgment options" <xref 
            target="RFC2018"/>, "An Extension to the Selective Acknowledgement 
            (SACK) option for TCP" <xref target="RFC2883"/>, and "A Conservative 
            Selective Acknowledgment (SACK)-based Loss Recovery Algorithm for 
            TCP" <xref target="RFC6675"/>, and not further discussed in this 
            document.
          </t>
        </list>
      </t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="sec12" title="TCP Reliability">
      
      <t>An especially serious kind of error may result from an accidental reuse 
        of TCP sequence numbers in data segments.  TCP reliability depends upon 
        the existence of a bound on the lifetime of a segment: the "Maximum 
        Segment Lifetime" or MSL.  
      </t>
      <t>Duplication of sequence numbers might happen in either of two  ways:
        <list style="format (%d)">
          <t>Sequence number wrap-around on the current connection
            <vspace blankLines="1"/>
            A TCP sequence number contains 32 bits.  At a high enough transfer 
            rate of large volumes of data (at least 4 GiB in the same session), 
            the 32-bit sequence space may be "wrapped" (cycled) within the 
            time that a segment is delayed in queues. 
          </t>
          <t>Earlier incarnation of the connection
            <vspace blankLines="1"/>
            Suppose that a connection terminates, either by a proper close 
            sequence or due to a host crash, and the same connection (i.e., 
            using the same pair of port numbers) is immediately reopened.  A 
            delayed segment from the terminated connection could fall within the 
            current window for the new incarnation and be accepted as valid.
          </t>
        </list>
      </t>  
      <t>Duplicates from earlier incarnations, case (2), are avoided by 
        enforcing the current fixed MSL of the TCP specification, as explained 
        in <xref target="sec43"/> and <xref target="AppB"/>. In addition, the 
        randmizing of ephemeral ports can also help to probabilistically reduce 
        the chances of duplicates from earlier connections. However, case 
        (1), avoiding the reuse of sequence numbers within the same connection, 
        requires an upper bound on MSL that depends upon the transfer rate, and 
        at high enough rates, a dedicated mechanism is required.
      </t>
      <t>A possible fix for the problem of cycling the sequence space would be 
        to increase the size of the TCP sequence number field.  For example, the 
        sequence number field (and also the acknowledgment field) could be 
        expanded to 64 bits.  This could be done either by changing the TCP 
        header or by means of an additional option. 
      </t>
      <t><xref target="sec4"/> presents a different mechanism, which we call 
        PAWS (Protection Against Wrapped Sequence numbers), to extend TCP 
        reliability to transfer rates well beyond the foreseeable upper limit of 
        network bandwidths.  PAWS uses the TCP Timestamps option defined in 
        <xref target="sec32"/> to protect against old duplicates from the same 
        connection.
      </t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="sec13" title="Using TCP options">
      <t>The extensions defined in this document all use TCP options. 
      </t>
      <t>When <xref target="RFC1323"/> was published, there was concern that 
        some buggy TCP implementation might crash on the first appearance 
        of an option on a non-&lt;SYN&gt; segment. However, bugs like that can 
        lead to DOS attacks against a TCP. Research has shown that most TCP 
        implementations will properly handle unknown options on non-&lt;SYN&gt; 
        segments (<xref target="Medina04"/>, <xref target="Medina05"/>). But it 
        is still prudent to be conservative in what you send, and avoiding buggy 
        TCP implementation is not the only reason for negotiating TCP options on 
        &lt;SYN&gt; segments.
      </t>
      <t>The window scale option negotiates fundamental parameters of the TCP 
        session. Therefore, it is only sent during the initial handshake. 
        Furthermore, the window scale option will be sent in a &lt;SYN,ACK&gt; 
        segment only if the corresponding option was received in the initial 
        &lt;SYN&gt; segment.
      </t>
      <t> The Timestamps option may appear in any data or &lt;ACK&gt; segment, 
        adding 10 bytes (up to 12 bytes including padding) to the 20-byte TCP 
        header. It is required that this TCP 
        option will be sent on all non-&lt;SYN&gt; segments after an exchange of 
        options on the &lt;SYN&gt; segments has indicated that both sides 
        understand this extension. 
      </t>
      <t>Research has shown that the use of the Timestamps option to take 
        additional RTT samples within each RTT has little 
        effect on the ultimate retransmission timeout value <xref 
        target="Allman99"/>. However, there are other uses of the Timestamps 
        option, such as the Eifel mechanism <xref target="RFC3522"/>, <xref 
        target="RFC4015"/>, and PAWS (see <xref target="sec4"/>) which improve 
        overall TCP security and performance. The extra header bandwidth used by 
        this option should be evaluated for the gains in performance and 
        security in an actual deployment. 
      </t>
      <t><xref target="AppA"/> contains a recommended layout of the options in 
        TCP headers to achieve reasonable data field alignment.  
      </t>
      <t>Finally, we observe that most of the mechanisms defined in this 
        document are important for LFN's and/or very high-speed networks.  For 
        low-speed networks, it might be a performance optimization to NOT use 
        these mechanisms.  A TCP vendor concerned about optimal performance over 
        low-speed paths might consider turning these extensions off for low-
        speed paths, or allow a user or installation manager to disable them.
      </t>
    </section>
    <section title="Terminology" anchor="secTerm">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT", 
        "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this 
        document are to be interpreted as described in <xref target="RFC2119"/>.
      </t>
      <t>In this document, these words will appear with that interpretation only 
        when in UPPER CASE. Lower case uses of these words are not to be 
        interpreted as carrying <xref target="RFC2119"/> significance.
        <vspace blankLines="30"/>
      </t>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section anchor="sec2" title="TCP Window Scale option">
    <section anchor="sec21" title="Introduction">
      <t>The window scale extension expands the definition of the TCP
        window to 30 bits and then uses an implicit scale factor to 
        carry this 30-bit value in the 16-bit Window field of the TCP 
        header (SEG.WND in <xref target="RFC0793"/>).  The exponent of 
        the scale factor is carried in a TCP option, Window Scale.  
        This option is sent only in a &lt;SYN&gt; segment (a segment 
        with the SYN bit on), hence the window scale is fixed in
        each direction when a connection is opened.  
      </t>
      <t>The maximum receive window, and therefore the scale factor, is
        determined by the maximum receive buffer space.  In a typical
        modern implementation, this maximum buffer space is set by default
        but can be overridden by a user program before a TCP connection is
        opened.  This determines the scale factor, and therefore no new
        user interface is needed for window scaling.
      </t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="sec22" title="Window Scale option">
      <t>The three-byte Window Scale option MAY be sent in a &lt;SYN&gt; 
        segment by a TCP.  It has two purposes: (1) indicate that the 
        TCP is prepared to both send and receive window scaling, and 
        (2) communicate the exponent of a scale factor to be applied to 
        its receive window.  Thus, a TCP that is prepared to scale 
        windows SHOULD send the option, even if its own scale factor 
        is 1 and the exponent 0.  The scale factor is limited to a power
        of two and encoded logarithmically, so it may be implemented by
        binary shift operations. The maximum scale exponent is limited 
        to 14 for a maximum permissible receive window size of 1 GiB 
        (2^(14+16)).
      </t>
      <t>
      <figure align="left">
        <preamble>TCP Window Scale option (WSopt):</preamble>
        <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[
Kind: 3

Length: 3 bytes

       +---------+---------+---------+
       | Kind=3  |Length=3 |shift.cnt|
       +---------+---------+---------+
            1         1         1
        ]]></artwork>
      </figure>
      </t>
      <t>This option is an offer, not a promise; both sides MUST send Window 
        Scale options in their &lt;SYN&gt; segments to enable window scaling in 
        either direction.  If window scaling is enabled, then the TCP that sent 
        this option will right-shift its true receive-window values by 
        'shift.cnt' bits for transmission in SEG.WND.  The value 'shift.cnt' MAY 
        be zero (offering to scale, while applying a scale factor of 1 to the 
        receive window).
      </t>
      <t>This option MAY be sent in an initial &lt;SYN&gt; segment (i.e., a 
        segment with the SYN bit on and the ACK bit off).  It MAY also be sent 
        in a &lt;SYN,ACK&gt; segment, but only if a Window Scale option was 
        received in the initial &lt;SYN&gt; segment.  A Window Scale option in a 
        segment without a SYN bit MUST be ignored.
      </t>
      <t>The window field in a segment where the SYN bit is set (i.e., a 
        &lt;SYN&gt; or &lt;SYN,ACK&gt;) MUST NOT be scaled.
      </t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="sec23" title="Using the Window Scale option">
      <t>A model implementation of window scaling is as follows, using the 
        notation of <xref target="RFC0793"/>:
        <list style="symbols">
          <!--
          <t>All windows MUST be treated as 32-bit quantities for storage in the 
            connection control block and for local calculations. This includes 
            the send-window (SND.WND) and the receive-window (RCV.WND) values, 
            as well as the congestion window.
          </t>-->
          <t>The connection state is augmented by two window shift counters, 
            Snd.Wind.Shift and Rcv.Wind.Shift, to be applied to the incoming and 
            outgoing window fields, respectively.
          </t>
          <t>If a TCP receives a &lt;SYN&gt; segment containing a Window Scale 
            option, it SHOULD send its own Window Scale option in the &lt;SYN,ACK&gt; 
            segment.
          </t>
          <t>The Window Scale option MUST be sent with shift.cnt = R, where R is the 
            value that the TCP would like to use for its receive window.
          </t>
          <t>Upon receiving a &lt;SYN&gt; segment with a Window Scale option 
            containing shift.cnt = S, a TCP MUST set Snd.Wind.Shift to S and MUST set 
            Rcv.Wind.Shift to R; otherwise, it MUST set both Snd.Wind.Shift and 
            Rcv.Wind.Shift to zero.
          </t>
          <t>The window field (SEG.WND) in the header of every incoming segment, 
            with the exception of &lt;SYN&gt; segments, MUST be left-shifted by 
            Snd.Wind.Shift bits before updating SND.WND:
            <figure align="center">
              <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
SND.WND = SEG.WND << Snd.Wind.Shift              
              ]]></artwork>
            </figure>
            (assuming the other conditions of <xref target="RFC0793"/> are met, 
            and using the "C" notation "&lt;&lt;" for left-shift).
          </t>
          <t>The window field (SEG.WND) of every outgoing segment, with the 
            exception of &lt;SYN&gt; segments, MUST be right-shifted by 
            Rcv.Wind.Shift bits:
            <figure align="center">
              <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
SEG.WND = RCV.WND >> Rcv.Wind.Shift              
              ]]></artwork>
            </figure>
          </t>
        </list>
      </t>
      <t>TCP determines if a data segment is "old" or "new" by testing whether 
        its sequence number is within 2^31 bytes of the left edge of the window, 
        and if it is not, discarding the data as "old".  To insure that new data 
        is never mistakenly considered old and vice versa, the left edge of the 
        sender's window has to be at most 2^31 away from the right edge of the 
        receiver's window. Similarly with the sender's right edge and receiver's 
        left edge. Since the right and left edges of either the sender's or 
        receiver's window differ by the window size, and since the sender and 
        receiver windows can be out of phase by at most the window size, the 
        above constraints imply that two times the maximum window size must be 
        less than 2^31, or
        <figure align="center">
          <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
max window < 2^30
          ]]></artwork>
        </figure>
      </t>
      <t>Since the max window is 2^S (where S is the scaling shift count) times 
        at most 2^16 - 1 (the maximum unscaled window), the maximum window is 
        guaranteed to be &lt; 2^30 if S &lt;= 14.  Thus, the shift count MUST be 
        limited to 14 (which allows windows of 2^30 = 1 GiB).  If a Window Scale 
        option is received with a shift.cnt value larger than 14, the TCP SHOULD 
        log the error but MUST use 14 instead of the specified value. This is 
        safe as a sender can always choose to only partially use any signaled 
        receive window. If the receiver is scaling by a factor larger than 14 and
        the sender is only scaling by 14 then the receive window used by the 
        sender will appear smaller than it is in reality.
      </t>
      <t>The scale factor applies only to the Window field as transmitted in the 
        TCP header; each TCP using extended windows will maintain the window 
        values locally as 32-bit numbers.  For example, the "congestion window" 
        computed by Slow Start and Congestion Avoidance (see <xref 
        target="RFC5681"/>) is not affected by the scale factor, so window 
        scaling will not introduce quantization into the congestion window.
      </t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="sec24" title="Addressing Window Retraction">
      <t>When a non-zero scale factor is in use, there are instances when a 
        retracted window can be offered - see <xref target="AppH"/> for a 
        detailed example. The end of the window will be on a boundary based on 
        the granularity of the scale factor being used.  If the sequence number 
        is then updated by a number of bytes smaller than that granularity, the 
        TCP will have to either advertise a new window that is beyond what it 
        previously advertised (and perhaps beyond the buffer), or will have to 
        advertise a smaller window, which will cause the TCP window to shrink. 
        Implementations MUST ensure that they handle a shrinking window, as 
        specified in section 4.2.2.16 of <xref target="RFC1122"/>.
      </t>
      <t>For the receiver, this implies that:
        <list style="format %d)" counter="WinRetract">
          <t>The receiver MUST honor, as in-window, any segment that would have 
            been in-window for any &lt;ACK&gt; sent by the receiver.
          </t>
          <t>When window scaling is in effect, the receiver SHOULD track the 
            actual maximum window sequence number (which is likely to be greater 
            than the window announced by the most recent &lt;ACK&gt;, if more 
            than one segment has arrived since the application consumed any data 
            in the receive buffer).
          </t>
        </list>
        On the sender side:
        <list style="format %d)" counter="WinRetract">
          <t>The initial transmission MUST be within the window announced by the 
            most recent &lt;ACK&gt;.
          </t>
          <t>On first retransmission, or if the sequence number is out-of-window 
            by less than 2^Rcv.Wind.Shift then do normal retransmission(s) 
            without regard to receiver window as long as the original segment 
            was in window when it was sent.
          </t>
          <t>Subsequent retransmissions MAY only be sent, if they are within the 
            window announced by the most recent &lt;ACK&gt;.
          </t>
        </list>
        <vspace blankLines="30"/>
      </t>
    </section>
  </section>
  
  <section anchor="sec3" title="TCP Timestamps option">
    
    <section anchor="sec31" title="Introduction">
      <t>The Timestamps option is introduced to address some of the issues 
        mentioned in <xref target="sec11"/> and <xref target="sec12"/>. 
        The Timestamps option is specified in a symmetrical manner, so that 
        TSval timestamps 
        are carried in both data and &lt;ACK&gt; segments and are echoed in 
        TSecr fields carried in returning &lt;ACK&gt; or data segments.
        Originally used primarily for timestamping individual segments, the 
        properties of the Timestamps option allow not only the use for taking time 
        measurements (<xref target="sec33"/>), but additional 
        uses as well (<xref target="sec4"/>).
      </t>
      <t>It is necessary to remember that there is a distinction between the 
        Timestamps option conveying timestamp information, and the use of that 
        information. In particular, the Round Trip Time Measurement (RTTM) 
        mechanism must be viewed independently from updating the Retransmission 
        Timeout (RTO) (see <xref target="sec331"/>). In this case, the sample 
        granularity also needs to be taken into account. Other mechanisms, such 
        as PAWS, or Eifel, are not built upon the timestamp information itself, 
        but are based on the intrinsic property of monotonically non-decreasing values.
      </t>
      <t>The Timestamps option is important when large receive windows are used, 
        to allow the use of the PAWS mechanism (see <xref target="sec4"/>). 
        Furthermore, the option may be useful for all TCP's, since it simplifies the 
        sender and allows the use of additional optimizations such as Eifel 
        (<xref target="RFC3522"/>, <xref target="RFC4015"/>) and others 
        (<xref target="RFC6817"/>, <xref target="Kuzmanovic03"/>, <xref target="Kuehlewind10"/>. 
      </t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="sec32" title="Timestamps option">
      <t>TCP is a symmetric protocol, allowing data to be sent at any time in 
        either direction, and therefore timestamp echoing may occur in either 
        direction.  For simplicity and symmetry, we specify that timestamps 
        always be sent and echoed in both directions.  For efficiency, we 
        combine the timestamp and timestamp reply fields into a single TCP 
        Timestamps option.
      </t>
      <t>
        <figure align="left">
          <preamble>TCP Timestamps option (TSopt):</preamble>
          <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[
Kind: 8

Length: 10 bytes

       +-------+-------+---------------------+---------------------+
       |Kind=8 |  10   |   TS Value (TSval)  |TS Echo Reply (TSecr)|
       +-------+-------+---------------------+---------------------+
           1       1              4                     4
          ]]></artwork>
        </figure>
      </t>  
      <t>The Timestamps option carries two four-byte timestamp fields. 
      The Timestamp Value field (TSval) contains the current value of 
      the timestamp clock of the TCP sending the option.
      </t>
      
      <t>The Timestamp Echo Reply (TSecr) field is valid if the ACK bit 
      is set in the TCP header. If the ACK bit is not set in the 
      outgoing TCP header, the sender of that segment SHOULD set the 
      TSecr field to zero.  When the ACK bit is set in an outgoing 
      segment, the sender MUST echo a recently received Timestamp Value (TSval) sent 
      by the remote TCP in the TSval field of a Timestamps option. The 
      exact rules on which TSval MUST be echoed are given in  <xref 
      target="sec34"/>. When the ACK bit is not set, the receiver MUST 
      ignore the value of the TSecr field.
      
      <!--
      valid, it echoes a timestamp 
      value that was sent by the remote TCP in the TSval field of a 
      Timestamps option.  When TSecr is not valid, its value MUST be 
      zero. However, a value of zero does not imply TSecr being invalid. 
      The TSecr value will generally be from the most recent Timestamps 
      option that was received; however, there are exceptions that are 
      explained below.-->
      </t>
      <t>A TCP MAY send the Timestamps option (TSopt) in an initial 
      &lt;SYN&gt; segment (i.e., segment containing a SYN bit and no ACK 
      bit), and MAY send a TSopt in &lt;SYN,ACK&gt; only if it received a 
      TSopt in the initial &lt;SYN&gt; segment for the connection.
      </t>
      <t>Once TSopt has been successfully negotiated, that is both 
        &lt;SYN&gt;, and &lt;SYN,ACK&gt; contain TSopt, the TSopt MUST be 
      sent in every non-&lt;RST&gt; segment for the duration of the 
      connection, and SHOULD be sent in an &lt;RST&gt; segment (see 
      <xref target="sec42"/> for details). The TCP SHOULD remember this 
      state by setting a flag, referred to as Snd.TS.OK, to one. If a non-&lt;RST&gt; segment 
      is received without a TSopt, a TCP SHOULD silently drop the 
      segment. A TCP MUST NOT abort a TCP connection because any segment 
      lacks an expected TSopt.
      </t>
      <t>Implementations are strongly encouraged to follow the above 
      rules for handling a missing Timestamps option, and the order of 
      precedence mentioned in <xref target="sec421"/> when deciding on 
      the acceptance of a segment.
      </t>
      <t>If a receiver chooses to accept a segment without an expected 
      Timestamps option, it must be clear that undetectable data 
      corruption may occur. 
      </t>
      <t>Such a TCP receiver may experience undetectable wrapped-
      sequence effects, such as data (payload) corruption or session 
      stalls. In order to maintain the integrity of the payload data, in 
      particular on high speed networks, it is paramount to follow the 
      described processing rules.
      </t>
      <t>However, it has been mentioned that under some circumstances, 
      the above guidelines are too strict, and some paths sporadically 
      suppress the Timestamps option, while maintaining payload 
      integrity. A path behaving in this manner should be deemed 
      unacceptable, but it has been noted that some implementations 
      relax the acceptance rules as a workaround, and allow TCP to run 
      across such paths <xref target="Oppermann13"/> 
      </t>
      <t>If a TSopt is received on a connection where TSopt was not 
      negotiated in the initial three-way handshake, the TSopt MUST be 
      ignored and the packet processed normally. 
      </t>
      <t>In the case of crossing &lt;SYN&gt; segments where one &lt;SYN&gt; 
        contains a TSopt and the other doesn't, both sides MAY send a TSopt in 
        the &lt;SYN,ACK&gt; segment.
      </t>
      <t>TSopt is required for the two mechanisms described in sections <xref 
        target="sec33" format="counter"/> and <xref target="sec4" 
        format="counter"/>. There are also other mechanisms that rely on the 
        presence of the TSopt, e.g. <xref target="RFC3522"/>. If a TCP stopped 
        sending TSopt at any time during an established session, it interferes 
        with these mechanisms.  This update to <xref target="RFC1323"/> 
        describes explicitly the previous assumption (see <xref 
        target="sec42"/>), that each TCP segment must have TSopt, once 
        negotiated.
        <vspace blankLines="30"/>

      </t> 
    </section>
  </section>
    <section anchor="sec33" title="The RTTM Mechanism">
      <section anchor="sec330" title="Introduction">
      <t>One use of the Timestamps option is to measure the round trip time of 
        virtually every packet acknowledged. The Round Trip Time Measurement 
        (RTTM) mechansim requires a Timestamps option in every measured segment, with a TSval that is 
        obtained from a (virtual) "timestamp clock".  Values of this clock MUST 
        be at least approximately proportional to real time, in order to measure 
        actual RTT. 
      </t>
      <t>TCP measures the round trip time (RTT), primarily for the purpose of 
        arriving at a reasonable value for the Retransmission Timeout (RTO) 
        timer interval. Accurate and current RTT estimates are necessary to 
        adapt to changing traffic conditions, while a conservative estimate of 
        the RTO interval is necessary to minimize spurious RTOs.
      </t>
      <t>These TSval values are echoed in TSecr values in the reverse direction. 
        The difference between a received TSecr value and the current timestamp 
        clock value provides an RTT measurement.
      </t>
      <t>When timestamps are used, every segment that is received will contain a 
        TSecr value. However, these values cannot all be used to update the 
        measured RTT.  The following example illustrates why. It shows a one-way 
        data flow with segments arriving in sequence without loss.  Here A, B, 
        C... represent data blocks occupying successive blocks of sequence 
        numbers, and ACK(A),...  represent the corresponding cumulative 
        acknowledgments.  The two timestamp fields of the Timestamps option are 
        shown symbolically as &lt;TSval=x,TSecr=y&gt;.  Each TSecr field 
        contains the value most recently received in a TSval field.
      </t>
        <figure align="center">
          <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
TCP  A                                     TCP B

                <A,TSval=1,TSecr=120> ----->

     <---- <ACK(A),TSval=127,TSecr=1>

                <B,TSval=5,TSecr=127> ----->

     <---- <ACK(B),TSval=131,TSecr=5>

  . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .

                <C,TSval=65,TSecr=131> ---->

     <---- <ACK(C),TSval=191,TSecr=65>

                    (etc.)
          ]]></artwork>
        </figure>
      <t>The dotted line marks a pause (60 time units long) in which A had 
        nothing to send.  Note that this pause inflates the RTT which B could 
        infer from receiving TSecr=131 in data segment C.  Thus, in one-way data 
        flows, RTTM in the reverse direction measures a value that is inflated 
        by gaps in sending data.  However, the following rule prevents a 
        resulting inflation of the measured RTT: 
        <list style="hanging" hangIndent="11">
          <t hangText="RTTM Rule:"> A TSecr value received in a segment MAY be 
            used to update the averaged RTT measurement only if the segment 
            advances the left edge of the send window, i.e. SND.UNA is 
            increased.   
          </t>      
        </list>
      </t>
      <t>Since TCP B is not sending data, the data segment C does not 
        acknowledge any new data when it arrives at B.  Thus, the inflated RTTM 
        measurement is not used to update B's RTTM measurement.
      </t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="sec331" title="Updating the RTO value">
      <t>When <xref target="RFC1323"/> was originally written, it was perceived 
        that taking RTT measurements for each segment, and also during 
        retransmissions, would contribute to reduce spurious RTOs, while 
        maintaining the timeliness of necessary RTOs. At the time, RTO was also 
        the only mechanism to make use of the measured RTT. It has been shown, 
        that taking more RTT samples has only a very limited effect to optimize 
        RTOs <xref target="Allman99"/>. 
      </t>
      <t>Implementers should note that with timestamps multiple RTTMs can be 
        taken per RTT.  The <xref target="RFC6298"/> RTO estimator has weighting 
        factors, alpha and beta,  based on an implicit assumption that at most 
        one RTTM will be sampled per RTT.  When multiple RTTMs per RTT are 
        available to update the RTO estimator, an implementation SHOULD try to 
        adhere to the spirit of the history specified in <xref target="RFC6298"/>.  
        An implementation suggestion is detailed in <xref target="AppI"/>. 
      </t>
      <t><xref target="Ludwig00"/> and <xref target="Floyd05"/> have highlighted 
        the problem that an unmodified RTO calculation, which is updated with 
        per-packet RTT samples, will truncate the path history too soon. This 
        can lead to an increase in spurious retransmissions, when the path 
        properties vary in the order of a few RTTs, but a high number of RTT 
        samples are taken on a much shorter timescale.
      </t>        
    </section>
    <section anchor="sec34" title="Which Timestamp to Echo">
      <t>If more than one Timestamps option is received before a reply segment 
        is sent, the TCP must choose only one of the TSvals to echo, ignoring 
        the others.  To minimize the state kept in the receiver (i.e., the 
        number of unprocessed TSvals), the receiver should be required to retain 
        at most one timestamp in the connection control block.
      </t>
      <t>There are three situations to consider:
        <list style="format (%C)">
          <t>Delayed ACKs.
            <vspace blankLines="1"/>
            Many TCP's acknowledge only every second segment out of a group of 
            segments arriving within a short time interval; this policy is known 
            generally as "delayed ACKs".  The data-sender TCP must measure the 
            effective RTT, including the additional time due to delayed ACKs, or 
            else it will retransmit unnecessarily.  Thus, when delayed ACKs are 
            in use, the receiver SHOULD reply with the TSval field from the 
            earliest unacknowledged segment.
          </t>
          <t>A hole in the sequence space (segment(s) have been lost).
            <vspace blankLines="1"/>
            The sender will continue sending until the window is filled, and the 
            receiver may be generating &lt;ACK&gt;s as these out-of-order 
            segments arrive (e.g., to aid "fast retransmit"). 
            <vspace blankLines="1"/> 
            The lost segment is probably a sign of congestion, and in that 
            situation the sender should be conservative about retransmission. 
            Furthermore, it is better to overestimate than underestimate the 
            RTT.  An &lt;ACK&gt; for an out-of-order segment SHOULD therefore 
            contain the timestamp from the most recent segment that advanced 
            RCV.NXT. 
            <vspace blankLines="1"/> 
            The same situation occurs if segments are re-ordered by the network.
          </t>
          <t>A filled hole in the sequence space.
            <vspace blankLines="1"/>
            The segment that fills the hole and advances the window represents 
            the most recent measurement of the network characteristics.  An RTT 
            computed from an earlier segment would probably include the sender's 
            retransmit time-out, badly biasing the sender's average RTT 
            estimate.  Thus, the timestamp from the latest segment (which filled 
            the hole) MUST be echoed.
          </t>
        </list>
      </t>
      <t>An algorithm that covers all three cases is described in the following 
        rules for Timestamps option processing on a synchronized connection:
        <list style="format (%d)">
          <t>The connection state is augmented with two 32-bit slots:
            <vspace blankLines="1"/>
            TS.Recent holds a timestamp to be echoed in TSecr whenever a segment 
            is sent, and Last.ACK.sent holds the ACK field from the last segment 
            sent.  Last.ACK.sent will equal RCV.NXT except when &lt;ACK&gt;s 
            have been delayed. 
          </t>
          <t>If:
            <figure align="center">
              <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
SEG.TSval >= TS.recent and SEG.SEQ <= Last.ACK.sent
              ]]></artwork>
            </figure>
            then SEG.TSval is copied to TS.Recent; otherwise, it is ignored.
          </t>
          <t>When a TSopt is sent, its TSecr field is set to the current 
            TS.Recent value.
          </t>
        </list>
      </t>
      <t>The following examples illustrate these rules.  Here A, B, C... 
        represent data segments occupying successive blocks of sequence numbers, 
        and ACK(A),...  represent the corresponding acknowledgment segments. 
        Note that ACK(A) has the same sequence number as B.  We show only one 
        direction of timestamp echoing, for clarity.
        <list style="symbols">
          <t>Segments arrive in sequence, and some of the &lt;ACK&gt;s are 
            delayed.
            <vspace blankLines="1"/>
            By case (A), the timestamp from the oldest unacknowledged segment is 
            echoed.
            <figure align="center">
              <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
                                  TS.Recent
<A, TSval=1> ------------------->
                                      1
<B, TSval=2> ------------------->
                                      1
<C, TSval=3> ------------------->
                                      1
         <---- <ACK(C), TSecr=1>
(etc)
              ]]></artwork>
            </figure>
          </t>
          <t>Segments arrive out of order, and every segment is acknowledged. 
            <vspace blankLines="1"/> 
            By case (B), the timestamp from the last segment that advanced the 
            left window edge is echoed, until the missing segment arrives; it is 
            echoed according to Case (C).  The same sequence would occur if 
            segments B and D were lost and retransmitted.
            <figure align="center">
              <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
                                  TS.Recent
<A, TSval=1> ------------------->
                                      1
         <---- <ACK(A), TSecr=1>
                                      1
<C, TSval=3> ------------------->
                                      1
         <---- <ACK(A), TSecr=1>
                                      1
<B, TSval=2> ------------------->
                                      2
         <---- <ACK(C), TSecr=2>
                                      2
<E, TSval=5> ------------------->
                                      2
         <---- <ACK(C), TSecr=2>
                                      2
<D, TSval=4> ------------------->
                                      4
         <---- <ACK(E), TSecr=4>
(etc)
              ]]></artwork>
            </figure>
          </t>
        </list>
        <vspace blankLines="30"/>
      </t>
    </section>
  </section>
  
  <section anchor="sec4" title="PAWS - Protection Against Wrapped Sequence Numbers">
    <section anchor="sec41" title="Introduction">
      <t>Another use for the Timestamps options is the mechanism to Protect Against
        Wrapped Sequence numbers (PAWS). <xref target="sec42"/> describes a 
        simple mechanism to reject old 
        duplicate segments that might corrupt an open TCP connection. PAWS 
        operates within a single TCP connection, using state that is saved in 
        the connection control block.  <xref target="sec43"/> and <xref 
        target="AppC"/> discuss the implications of the PAWS mechanism for 
        avoiding old duplicates from previous incarnations of the same 
        connection.
      </t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="sec42" title="The PAWS Mechanism">
      <t>PAWS uses the TCP Timestamps option  
        described earlier, and assumes that every received TCP segment 
        (including data and &lt;ACK&gt; segments) contains a timestamp SEG.TSval 
        whose values are monotonically non-decreasing in time.  The basic idea 
        is that a segment can be discarded as an old duplicate if it is received 
        with a timestamp SEG.TSval less than some timestamp recently received on 
        this connection.
      </t>
      <t>In the PAWS mechanism, the "timestamps" are 32-bit 
        unsigned integers in a modular 32-bit space.  Thus, "less than" is 
        defined the same way it is for TCP sequence numbers, and the same 
        implementation techniques apply.  If s and t are timestamp values, 
        <figure align="center">
          <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
s < t  if 0 < (t - s) < 2^31, 
          ]]></artwork>
        </figure>
        computed in unsigned 32-bit arithmetic.
      </t>
      <t>The choice of incoming timestamps to be saved for this comparison MUST 
        guarantee a value that is monotonically non-decreasing.  For example, an implementation 
        might save the timestamp from the segment that last advanced the left 
        edge of the receive window, i.e., the most recent in-sequence segment. 
        For simplicity, the value TS.Recent introduced in <xref 
        target="sec34"/> is used instead, as using a common value for 
        both PAWS and RTTM simplifies the implementation.  As <xref 
        target="sec34"/> explained, TS.Recent differs from the timestamp from 
        the last in-sequence segment only in the case of delayed &lt;ACK&gt;s, 
        and therefore by less than one window.  Either choice will therefore 
        protect against sequence number wrap-around.
      </t>
      <t> PAWS 
        submits all incoming segments to the same test, and therefore protects 
        against duplicate &lt;ACK&gt; segments as well as data segments. (An 
        alternative non-symmetric algorithm would protect against old duplicate 
        &lt;ACK&gt;s: the sender of data would reject incoming &lt;ACK&gt; 
        segments whose TSecr values were less than the TSecr saved from the last 
        segment whose ACK field advanced the left edge of the send window.  This 
        algorithm was deemed to lack economy of mechanism and symmetry.)
      </t>
      <t>TSval timestamps sent on &lt;SYN&gt; and &lt;SYN,ACK&gt; segments are 
        used to initialize PAWS.  PAWS protects against old duplicate non-
        &lt;SYN&gt; segments, and duplicate &lt;SYN&gt; segments received while 
        there is a synchronized connection.  Duplicate &lt;SYN&gt; and 
        &lt;SYN,ACK&gt; segments received when there is no connection will be 
        discarded by the normal 3-way handshake and sequence number checks of 
        TCP.
      </t>
      <t><xref target="RFC1323"/> recommended that &lt;RST&gt; segments NOT 
        carry timestamps, and that they be acceptable regardless of their 
        timestamp.  At that time, the thinking was that old duplicate 
        &lt;RST&gt; segments should be exceedingly unlikely, and their cleanup 
        function should take precedence over timestamps.  More recently, 
        discussions about various blind attacks on TCP connections have raised 
        the suggestion that if the Timestamps option is present, SEG.TSecr could 
        be used to provide stricter acceptance tests for &lt;RST&gt; segments. 
      </t>
      <t>
        While still under discussion, to enable research into this area it is 
        now RECOMMENDED that when generating an &lt;RST&gt;, that if the segment 
        causing the &lt;RST&gt; to be generated contained a Timestamps option, 
        that the &lt;RST&gt; also contain a Timestamps option. In the 
        &lt;RST&gt; segment, SEG.TSecr SHOULD be set to SEG.TSval from the 
        incoming segment and SEG.TSval SHOULD be set to zero.  If an &lt;RST&gt; 
        is being generated because of a user abort, and Snd.TS.OK is set, then a 
        Timestamps option SHOULD be included in the &lt;RST&gt;.  When an 
        &lt;RST&gt; segment is received, it MUST NOT be subjected to the PAWS 
        check by verifying an acceptable value in SEG.TSval, and information from 
        the Timestamps option MUST NOT be used to 
        update connection state information.  SEG.TSecr MAY be used to provide 
        stricter &lt;RST&gt; acceptance checks.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="sec421" title="Basic PAWS Algorithm">
      <t>If the PAWS algorithm is used, the following processing MUST be 
        performed on all incoming segments for a synchronized connection. Also, 
        PAWS processing MUST take precedence over the regular TCP acceptablitiy 
        check (Section 3.3 in <xref target="RFC0793"/>), which is performed 
        after verification of the received Timestamps option:
        <list style="format R%d)">
          <t>If there is a Timestamps option in the arriving segment, SEG.TSval 
            &lt; TS.Recent, TS.Recent is valid (see later discussion) and the 
            RST bit is not set, then treat the arriving segment as not 
            acceptable:
            <list style="empty">
              <t>Send an acknowledgement in reply as specified in <xref 
                target="RFC0793"/> page 69 and drop the segment. 
              </t>
              <t>Note: it is necessary to send an &lt;ACK&gt; segment in order 
                to retain TCP's mechanisms for detecting and recovering from 
                half- open connections.  For example, see Figure 10 of <xref 
                target="RFC0793"/>.
              </t>
            </list>
          </t>
          <t>If the segment is outside the window, reject it (normal TCP 
            processing)
          </t>
          <t>If an arriving segment satisfies: SEG.SEQ &lt;= Last.ACK.sent (see 
            <xref target="sec34"/>), then record its timestamp in TS.Recent. 
          </t>
          <t>If an arriving segment is in-sequence (i.e., at the left window 
            edge), then accept it normally.
          </t>
          <t>Otherwise, treat the segment as a normal in-window, out-of-sequence 
            TCP segment (e.g., queue it for later delivery to the user).
          </t>
        </list>
      </t>
      <t>Steps R2, R4, and R5 are the normal TCP processing steps specified by 
        <xref target="RFC0793"/>.
      </t>
      <t>It is important to note that the timestamp MUST be checked only when a 
        segment first arrives at the receiver, regardless of whether it is in-
        sequence or it must be queued for later delivery. 
      </t>
      <t>Consider the following example.
        <list style="empty">
          <t>Suppose the segment sequence: A.1, B.1, C.1, ..., Z.1 has been 
            sent, where the letter indicates the sequence number and the digit 
            represents the timestamp.  Suppose also that segment B.1 has been 
            lost.  The timestamp in TS.Recent is 1 (from A.1), so C.1, ..., Z.1 
            are considered acceptable and are queued.  When B is retransmitted 
            as segment B.2 (using the latest timestamp), it fills the hole and 
            causes all the segments through Z to be acknowledged and passed to 
            the user.  The timestamps of the queued segments are *not* inspected 
            again at this time, since they have already been accepted.  When B.2 
            is accepted, TS.Recent is set to 2.
          </t>
        </list>
      </t>
      <t>This rule allows reasonable performance under loss.  A full window of 
        data is in transit at all times, and after a loss a full window less one 
        segment will show up out-of-sequence to be queued at the receiver (e.g., 
        up to ~2^30 bytes of data); the Timestamps option must not result in 
        discarding this data.
      </t>
      <t>In certain unlikely circumstances, the algorithm of rules R1-R5 could 
        lead to discarding some segments unnecessarily, as shown in the 
        following example:
        <list style="empty">
          <t>Suppose again that segments: A.1, B.1, C.1, ..., Z.1 have been sent 
            in sequence and that segment B.1 has been lost. Furthermore, suppose 
            delivery of some of C.1, ... Z.1 is delayed until *after* the 
            retransmission B.2 arrives at the receiver.  These delayed segments 
            will be discarded unnecessarily when they do arrive, since their 
            timestamps are now out of date.
          </t>
        </list>
      </t>
      <t>This case is very unlikely to occur.  If the retransmission was 
        triggered by a timeout, some of the segments C.1, ... Z.1 must have been 
        delayed longer than the RTO time.  This is presumably an unlikely event, 
        or there would be many spurious timeouts and retransmissions.  If B's 
        retransmission was triggered by the "fast retransmit" algorithm, i.e., 
        by duplicate &lt;ACK&gt;s, then the queued segments that caused these 
        &lt;ACK&gt;s must have been received already.
      </t>
      <t>Even if a segment were delayed past the RTO, the Fast Retransmit 
        mechanism <xref target="Jacobson90c"/> will cause the delayed segments 
        to be retransmitted at the same time as B.2, avoiding an extra RTT and 
        therefore causing a very small performance penalty.
      </t>
      <t>We know of no case with a significant probability of occurrence in 
        which timestamps will cause performance degradation by unnecessarily 
        discarding segments.
      </t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="sec422" title="Timestamp Clock">
      <t>It is important to understand that the PAWS algorithm does not
         require clock synchronization between sender and receiver.  The
         sender's timestamp clock is used as a source of monotonic 
         non-decreasing values to stamp the segments.  The receiver 
         treats the timestamp value as simply a monotonically
         non-decreasing serial number, without any connection to
         time.  From the receiver's viewpoint, the timestamp is
         acting as a logical extension of the high-order bits of the
         sequence number.
        </t>
        <t>The receiver algorithm does place some requirements on the
         frequency of the timestamp clock.
          <list style="format (%c)">
            <t>The timestamp clock must not be "too slow".
              <vspace blankLines="1"/>
              It MUST tick at least once for each 2^31 bytes sent.  In
              fact, in order to be useful to the sender for round trip
              timing, the clock SHOULD tick at least once per window's
              worth of data, and even with the window extension defined
              in <xref target="sec22"/>, 2^31 bytes must be at least two 
              windows.
              <vspace blankLines="1"/>
              To make this more quantitative, any clock faster than 1
              tick/sec will reject old duplicate segments for link
              speeds of ~8 Gbps.  A 1 ms timestamp clock will work at
              link speeds up to 8 Tbps (8*10^12) bps!
            </t>
            <t>The timestamp clock must not be "too fast".
              <vspace blankLines="1"/>
              The  recycling time of the timestamp clock MUST be greater than MSL seconds.
              Since the clock (timestamp) is 32 bits and the worst-case
              MSL is 255 seconds, the maximum acceptable clock frequency
              is one tick every 59 ns.
              <vspace blankLines="1"/>
              However, it is desirable to establish a much longer
              recycle period, in order to handle outdated timestamps on
              idle connections (see <xref target="sec423"/>), and to 
              relax the MSL
              requirement for preventing sequence number wrap-around.
              With a 1 ms timestamp clock, the 32-bit timestamp will
              wrap its sign bit in 24.8 days.  Thus, it will reject old
              duplicates on the same connection if MSL is 24.8 days or
              less.  This appears to be a very safe figure; an MSL of
              24.8 days or longer can probably be assumed in the Internet
              without requiring precise MSL enforcement.
            </t>
          </list>
        </t>
        <t>Based upon these considerations, we choose a timestamp clock
         frequency in the range 1 ms to 1 sec per tick.  This range also
         matches the requirements of the RTTM mechanism, which does not
         need much more resolution than the granularity of the
         retransmit timer, e.g., tens or hundreds of milliseconds.
        </t>
        <t>The PAWS mechanism also puts a strong monotonicity requirement
         on the sender's timestamp clock.  The method of implementation
         of the timestamp clock to meet this requirement depends upon
         the system hardware and software.
          <list style="symbols">
            <t>Some hosts have a hardware clock that is guaranteed to be
              monotonic between hardware resets.
            </t>
            <t>A clock interrupt may be used to simply increment a binary
              integer by 1 periodically.
            </t>
            <t>The timestamp clock may be derived from a system clock
              that is subject to being abruptly changed, by adding a
              variable offset value.  This offset is initialized to
              zero.  When a new timestamp clock value is needed, the
              offset can be adjusted as necessary to make the new value
              equal to or larger than the previous value (which was
              saved for this purpose).
            </t>
            <t>A random offset may be added to the timestamp clock on a
              per connection basis.  See <xref target="RFC6528"/>, 
              section 3, on randomizing the initial sequence number 
              (ISN).  The same function with a different
              secret key can be use to generate the per connection
              timestamp offset.
            </t>
          </list>
        </t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="sec423" title="Outdated Timestamps">
        <t>If a connection remains idle long enough for the timestamp
         clock of the other TCP to wrap its sign bit, then the value
         saved in TS.Recent will become too old; as a result, the PAWS
         mechanism will cause all subsequent segments to be rejected,
         freezing the connection (until the timestamp clock wraps its
         sign bit again).
        </t>
        <t>With the chosen range of timestamp clock frequencies (1 sec to
         1 ms), the time to wrap the sign bit will be between 24.8 days
         and 24800 days.  A TCP connection that is idle for more than 24
         days and then comes to life is exceedingly unusual.  However,
         it is undesirable in principle to place any limitation on TCP
         connection lifetimes.
        </t>
        <t>We therefore require that an implementation of PAWS include a
         mechanism to "invalidate" the TS.Recent value when a connection
         is idle for more than 24 days.  (An alternative solution to the
         problem of outdated timestamps would be to send keep-alive
         segments at a very low rate, but still more often than the
         wrap-around time for timestamps, e.g., once a day.  This would
         impose negligible overhead.  However, the TCP specification has
         never included keep-alives, so the solution based upon
         invalidation was chosen.)
        </t>
        <t>Note that a TCP does not know the frequency, and therefore, the
         wraparound time, of the other TCP, so it must assume the worst.
         The validity of TS.Recent needs to be checked only if the basic
         PAWS timestamp check fails, i.e., only if SEG.TSval &lt;
         TS.Recent.  If TS.Recent is found to be invalid, then the
         segment is accepted, regardless of the failure of the timestamp
         check, and rule R3 updates TS.Recent with the TSval from the
         new segment.
        </t>
        <t>To detect how long the connection has been idle, the TCP MAY
         update a clock or timestamp value associated with the
         connection whenever TS.Recent is updated, for example.  The
         details will be implementation-dependent.
        </t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="sec424" title="Header Prediction">
        <t>"Header prediction" <xref target="Jacobson90a"/> is 
        a high-performance
         transport protocol implementation technique that is most
         important for high-speed links.  This technique optimizes the
         code for the most common case, receiving a segment correctly
         and in order.  Using header prediction, the receiver asks the
         question, "Is this segment the next in sequence?"  This
         question can be answered in fewer machine instructions than the
         question, "Is this segment within the window?"
        </t>
        <t>Adding header prediction to our timestamp procedure leads to
         the following recommended sequence for processing an arriving
         TCP segment:
          <list style="format H%d)">
            <t>Check timestamp (same as step R1 above)
            </t>
            <t>Do header prediction: if segment is next in sequence and
              if there are no special conditions requiring additional
              processing, accept the segment, record its timestamp, and
              skip H3.
            </t>
            <t>Process the segment normally, as specified in RFC 793.
              This includes dropping segments that are outside the
              window and possibly sending acknowledgments, and queuing
              in-window, out-of-sequence segments.
            </t>
          </list>
        </t>
        <t>Another possibility would be to interchange steps H1 and H2,
         i.e., to perform the header prediction step H2 *first*, and
         perform H1 and H3 only when header prediction fails.  This
         could be a performance improvement, since the timestamp check
         in step H1 is very unlikely to fail, and it requires unsigned
         modulo arithmetic.  To
         perform this check on every single segment is contrary to the
         philosophy of header prediction.  We believe that this change
         might produce a measurable reduction in CPU time for TCP
         protocol processing on high-speed networks.
        </t>
        <t>However, putting H2 first would create a hazard: a segment from
         2^32 bytes in the past might arrive at exactly the wrong time
         and be accepted mistakenly by the header-prediction step.  The
         following reasoning has been introduced in <xref target="RFC1185"/>
         <!--xref target="Jacobson90b"/--> to show
         that the probability of this failure is negligible.
         <list style="empty">
            <t>If all segments are equally likely to show up as old
              duplicates, then the probability of an old duplicate
              exactly matching the left window edge is the maximum
              segment size (MSS) divided by the size of the sequence
              space.  This ratio must be less than 2^-16, since MSS
              must be &lt; 2^16; for example, it will be (2^12)/(2^32) =
              2^-20 for a 100 Mbit/s link.  However, the older a segment is,
              the less likely it is to be retained in the Internet, and
              under any reasonable model of segment lifetime the
              probability of an old duplicate exactly at the left window
              edge must be much smaller than 2^-16.
           </t>
           <t>The 16 bit TCP checksum also allows a basic unreliability
              of one part in 2^16.  A protocol mechanism whose
              reliability exceeds the reliability of the TCP checksum
              should be considered "good enough", i.e., it won't
              contribute significantly to the overall error rate.  We
              therefore believe we can ignore the problem of an old
              duplicate being accepted by doing header prediction before
              checking the timestamp.
           </t>
         </list>
       </t>
       <t>However, this probabilistic argument is not universally
         accepted, and the consensus at present is that the performance
         gain does not justify the hazard in the general case.  It is
         therefore recommended that H2 follow H1.
       </t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="sec425" title="IP Fragmentation">
        <t>At high data rates, the protection against old segments provided
         by PAWS can be circumvented by errors in IP fragment reassembly
         (see <xref target="RFC4963"/><!--xref target="Heffner07"/-->).  
         The only way to protect against incorrect IP
         fragment reassembly is to not allow the segments to be
         fragmented.  This is done by setting the Don't Fragment (DF)
         bit in the IP header.  Setting the DF bit implies the use of
         Path MTU Discovery as described in 
         <xref target="RFC1191"/>, <xref target="RFC1981"/>, and <xref target="RFC4821"/>, thus any
         TCP implementation that implements PAWS MUST also implement
         Path MTU Discovery.
        </t>

      </section>
    <section anchor="sec43" title="Duplicates from Earlier Incarnations of Connection">
      <t>The PAWS mechanism protects against errors due to sequence number
      wrap-around on high-speed connections.  Segments from an earlier
      incarnation of the same connection are also a potential cause of
      old duplicate errors.  In both cases, the TCP mechanisms to
      prevent such errors depend upon the enforcement of a maximum
      segment lifetime (MSL) by the Internet (IP) layer (see Appendix of
      RFC 1185 for a detailed discussion).  Unlike the case of sequence
      space wrap-around, the MSL required to prevent old duplicate
      errors from earlier incarnations does not depend upon the transfer
      rate.  If the IP layer enforces the recommended 2 minute MSL of
      TCP, and if the TCP rules are followed, TCP connections will be
      safe from earlier incarnations, no matter how high the network
      speed.  Thus, the PAWS mechanism is not required for this case.
      </t>
      <t>We may still ask whether the PAWS mechanism can provide additional
      security against old duplicates from earlier connections, allowing
      us to relax the enforcement of MSL by the IP layer.  <xref target="AppB"/>
      explores this question, showing that further assumptions and/or
      mechanisms are required, beyond those of PAWS.  This is not part
      of the current extension.
      </t>
    </section>
  </section>
  
  <section anchor="sec5" title="Conclusions and Acknowledgements">
    <t>This memo presented a set of extensions to TCP to provide efficient
   operation over large bandwidth * delay product paths and reliable
   operation over very high-speed paths.  These extensions are designed
   to provide compatible interworking with TCP stacks that do not implement
   the extensions.
   </t>
   <t>These mechanisms are implemented using TCP options for scaled
   windows and timestamps.  The timestamps are used for two distinct
   mechanisms: RTTM (Round Trip Time Measurement) and PAWS (Protection
   Against Wrapped Sequences).
   </t>
   <t>The Window Scale option was originally suggested by Mike St. Johns of
   USAF/DCA.  The present form of the option was suggested by Mike
   Karels of UC Berkeley in response to a more cumbersome scheme defined
   by Van Jacobson.  Lixia Zhang helped formulate the PAWS mechanism
   description in <xref target="RFC1185"/>.
   </t>
   <t>Finally, much of this work originated as the result of discussions
   within the End-to-End Task Force on the theoretical limitations of
   transport protocols in general and TCP in particular.  Task force
   members and other on the end2end-interest list have made valuable
   contributions by pointing out flaws in the algorithms and the
   documentation.  Continued discussion and development since the
   publication of <xref target="RFC1323"/> originally occurred in the IETF TCP Large
   Windows Working Group, later on in the End-to-End Task Force, and
   most recently in the IETF TCP Maintenance Working Group.  The authors
   are grateful for all these contributions.
   </t>

  </section>
  
  <section anchor="sec6" title="Security Considerations">
    <t>The TCP sequence space is a fixed size, and as the window becomes
   larger it becomes easier for an attacker to generate forged packets
   that can fall within the TCP window, and be accepted as valid
   segments.  While use of timestamps and PAWS can help to mitigate this,
   when using PAWS, if an attacker is able to forge a packet that is
   acceptable to the TCP connection, a timestamp that is in the future
   would cause valid segments to be dropped due to PAWS checks.  Hence,
   implementers should take care to not open the TCP window drastically
   beyond the requirements of the connection.
   </t>
   <t>A naive implementation that derives the timestamp clock value 
    directly from a system uptime clock may unintentionally leak this 
    information to an attacker. This does not directly compromise any 
    of the mechanisms described in this document. However, this may 
    be valuable information to a potential attacker. An implementer 
    should evaluate the potential impact and mitigate this accordingly 
    (i.e. by using a random offset for the timestamp clock on each 
    connection, or using an external, real-time derived timestamp clock source).
   </t>
   <t>Expanding the TCP window beyond 64 KiB for IPv6 allows Jumbograms
    <xref target="RFC2675"/> to be used when the local network supports 
    packets larger than 64 KiB.  When larger TCP segments are used, the 
    TCP checksum becomes weaker.
   </t>
   <t>Mechanisms to protect the TCP header from modification should also
    protect the TCP options.
   </t>
   <t>Middleboxes and TCP options: 
     <list>
       <t>Some middleboxes have been known to remove the TCP options
         described in this document from TCP segments <xref target="Honda11"/>.  
         Middleboxes that remove TCP options described in this document
         from the &lt;SYN&gt; segment interfere with the selection of 
         parameters appropriate for the session. Removing any of these 
         options in a &lt;SYN,ACK&gt; segment will leave the end hosts in
         a state that destroys the proper operation of the protocol.
         <list style="symbols">
           <t>If a Window Scale option is removed from a 
             &lt;SYN,ACK&gt; segment, the end hosts will not 
             negotiate the window scaling factor correctly.     
             Middleboxes must not remove or modify the Window Scale 
             option from &lt;SYN,ACK&gt; segments.
           </t>
           <t>If a stateful firewall uses the window field to 
             detect whether a received segment is inside the 
             current window, and does not support the Window 
             Scale option, it will not be able to correctly 
             determine whether or not a packet is in the 
             window.  These middle boxes must also support 
             the Window Scale option and apply the scale factor 
             when processing segments. If the window scale factor
             cannot be determined, it must not do window 
             based processing.
           </t>
           <t>If the Timestamps option is removed from the 
             &lt;SYN&gt; or &lt;SYN,ACK&gt; segment, high 
             speed connections that need PAWS would not 
             have that protection. Successful negotiation of 
             Timestamps option enforces a stricter verification 
             of incoming segments at the receiver. If the 
             Timestamps option was removed from a subsequent 
             data segment after a successful negotiation (e.g. 
             as part of re-segmentation), the segment is 
             discarded by the receiver without further 
             processing. Middleboxes should not remove the 
             Timestamps option. 
           </t>
           <t>It must be noted that <xref target="RFC1323"/> doesn't 
            address the case of the Timestamps option being dropped or 
            selectively omitted after being negotiated, and that the 
            update in this document may cause some broken middlebox 
            behavior to be detected (potentially unresponsive TCP 
            sessions).
           </t>
         </list>
       </t>
     </list>
   </t>
   <t>Implementations that depend on PAWS could provide a mechanism for the 
     application to determine whether or not PAWS is in use on the connection, 
     and chose to terminate the connection if that protection doesn't exist. 
     This is not just to protect the connection against middleboxes that might 
     remove the Timestamps option, but also against remote hosts that do not 
     have Timestamp support.
    </t>
    <section anchor="sec61" title="Privacy Considerations">
      <t>The TCP options described in this document do not expose individual 
        users data. However, a naive implementation simply using the system 
        clock as source for the Timestamps option will reveal characteristics 
        of the TCP potentially allowing more targeted attacks. It is therefore 
        RECOMMENDED to generate a random, per-connection offset to be used 
        with the clock source when generating the Timestamps option value 
        (see <xref target="sec422"/>).
      </t>
      <t>Furthermore, the combination, relative ordering and padding of the 
        TCP options described in <xref target="sec22"/> and 
        <xref target="sec32"/> will reveal additional clues to allow the 
        fingerprinting of the system.
      </t>
    </section>
  </section>
  
  <section anchor="sec7" title="IANA Considerations">
    <t>This document has no actions for IANA.  The described TCP options are
      well known from the superceded <xref target="RFC1323"/>.
      <vspace blankLines="5"/>
    </t>
  </section>
  
 </middle>
 
 <back>
   <references title="Normative References">
     &RFC0793;
     &RFC1191;
     &RFC2119;
   </references>
   
   <references title="Informative References">
     &RFC0896;
     &RFC1072;
     &RFC1110;
     &RFC1122;
     &RFC1185;
     &RFC1323;
     &RFC1981;
     &RFC2018;
     &RFC2581;
     &RFC2675;
     &RFC2883;
     &RFC3522;
     &RFC4015;
     &RFC4821;
     &RFC4963;
     &RFC5681;
     &RFC6298;
     &RFC6528;
     &RFC6675;
     &RFC6691;
     &RFC6817;

     
     <reference anchor="Garlick77" target="http://www.rfc-editor.org/ien/ien12.txt">
        <front>
            <title>Issues in Reliable Host-to-Host Protocols</title>
            <author initials="L." surname="Garlick"/>
            <author initials="R." surname="Rom"/>
            <author initials="J." surname="Postel"/>  
            <date month="May" year="1977" />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="Proc." value="Second Berkeley Workshop
      on Distributed Data Management and Computer Networks"/>
    </reference>
    
    <reference anchor="Hamming77" target="">
      <front>
        <title>Digital Filters</title>
        <author initials="R." surname="Hamming"/>
        <date year="1977"/>
      </front>
      <seriesInfo name="Prentice Hall, Englewood Cliffs, N.J." 
        value="ISBN 0-13-212571-4"/>
    </reference>
    
    <reference anchor="Jacobson88a" target="http://ee.lbl.gov/papers/congavoid.pdf">
      <front>
        <title>Congestion Avoidance and Control</title>
        <author initials="V." surname="Jacobson"/>
        <date month="August" year="1988"/>
      </front>
      <seriesInfo name="SIGCOMM '88, Stanford," value=" CA."/>
    </reference>
    
    <reference anchor="Jacobson90a" target="">
      <front>
        <title>4BSD Header Prediction</title>
        <author initials="V." surname="Jacobson"/>
        <date month="April" year="1990"/>
      </front>
      <seriesInfo name="ACM" value="Computer Communication Review"/>
    </reference>
    
    <reference anchor="Jacobson90c" target="ftp://ftp.isi.edu/end2end/end2end-interest-1990.mail">
      <front>
        <title>Modified TCP congestion avoidance algorithm</title>
        <author initials="V." surname="Jacobson"/>
        <date month="April" year="1990" day="30"/>
      </front>
      <seriesInfo name="Message to the" value="end2end-interest mailing list"/>
    </reference>
    
    <reference anchor="Allman99" target="http://aciri.org/mallman/papers/estimation-la.pdf">
      <front>
        <title>On Estimating End-to-End Network Path Properties</title>
        <author initials="M." surname="Allman"/>
        <author initials="V." surname="Paxson"/>
        <date month="September" year="1999"/>
      </front>
      <seriesInfo name="Proc." value="ACM SIGCOMM Technical Symposium, Cambridge, MA"/>
    </reference>
    
    <reference anchor="Jain86" target="http://arxiv.org/ftp/cs/papers/9809/9809097.pdf">
      <front>
        <title>Divergence of Timeout Algorithms for Packet
      Retransmissions</title>
        <author initials="R." surname="Jain"/>
        <date month="March" year="1986"/>
      </front>
      <seriesInfo name="Proc." value="Fifth Phoenix Conf. on Comp. and Comm.,
      Scottsdale, Arizona"/>
    </reference>
    
    
    <reference anchor="Karn87" target="">
      <front>
        <title>Estimating Round-Trip Times
      in Reliable Transport Protocols</title>
        <author initials="P." surname="Karn"/>
        <author initials="C." surname="Partridge"/>
        <date month="August" year="1987"/>
      </front>
      <seriesInfo name="Proc." value="SIGCOMM '87"/>
    </reference>
    
    <reference anchor="Martin03" target="http://www.ietf.org/mail-archive/web/tsvwg/current/msg04435.html">
      <front>
        <title>[Tsvwg] RFC 1323.bis</title>
        <author initials="D." surname="Martin"/>
        <date month="September" year="2003" day="30"/>
      </front>
      <seriesInfo name="Message to the" value="tsvwg mailing list"/>
    </reference>
    
    <reference anchor="Medina04" target="http://www.icir.net/tbit/tbit-Aug2004.pdf">
      <front>
        <title>Measuring Interactions Between Transport Protocols and Middleboxes</title>
        <author initials="A." surname="Medina"/>
        <author initials="M." surname="Allman"/>
        <author initials="S." surname="Floyd"/>
        <date month="August" year="2004"/>
      </front>
      <seriesInfo name="Proc." value="ACM SIGCOMM/USENIX Internet Measurement Conference.  October 2004"/>
    </reference>
    
    <reference anchor="Medina05" target="http://icir.net/floyd/papers/TCPevolution-Mar2005.pdf">
      <front>
        <title>Measuring the Evolution of Transport Protocols in the Internet</title>
        <author initials="A." surname="Medina"/>
        <author initials="M." surname="Allman"/>
        <author initials="S." surname="Floyd"/>
        <date month="April" year="2005"/>
      </front>
      <seriesInfo name="ACM Computer Communication Review" value="35(2)"/>
    </reference>
    
    <reference anchor="Ludwig00" target="http://ccr.sigcomm.org/archive/2000/july00/LudwigFinal.pdf">
      <front>
        <title>The Eifel Retransmission Timer</title>
        <author initials="R." surname="Ludwig"/>
        <author initials="K." surname="Sklower"/>
        <date month="July" year="2000"/>
      </front>
      <seriesInfo name="ACM SIGCOMM Computer Communication Review" value="Volume 30 Issue 3"/>
    </reference>
    
    <reference anchor="Ekstroem04" target="http://citeseerx.ist.psu.edu/viewdoc/download?doi=10.1.1.76.2748&amp;rep=rep1&amp;type=pdf">
      <front>
        <title>The Peak-Hopper: A New End-to-End Retransmission Timer for Reliable Unicast Transport</title>
        <author initials="H." surname="Ekstroem"/>
        <author initials="R." surname="Ludwig"/>
        <date month="March" year="2004"/>
      </front>
      <seriesInfo name="INFOCOM 2004" value="IEEE"/>
    </reference>
    
    <reference anchor="Oppermann13" target="http://www.ietf.org/mail-archive/web/tcpm/current/msg08001.html">
      <front>
        <title>[tcpm] Explanation to the relaxation of TSopt acceptance rules</title>
        <author initials="A." surname="Oppermann"/>
        <date month="Jun" year="2013" day="1"/>
      </front>
      <seriesInfo name="Message to the" value="tcpm mailing list"/>
    </reference>
    
    <reference anchor="Mathis08" target="http://www.ietf.org/mail-archive/web/tcpm/current/msg03564.html">
      <front>
        <title>[tcpm] Example of 1323 window retraction
      problem</title>
        <author initials="M." surname="Mathis"/>
        <date month="March" year="2008" day="11"/>
      </front>
      <seriesInfo name="Message to the" value="tcpm mailing list"/>
    </reference>
    
    
    <reference anchor="Floyd05" target="http://www.ietf.org/mail-archive/web/tcpm/current/msg02508.html">
      <front>
        <title>[tcpm] How the RTO should be estimated with timestamps</title>
        <author initials="S." surname="Floyd"/>
        <date month="August" year="2005" day="09"/>
      </front>
      <seriesInfo name="Message from 26.Jan.2007 to the" value="tcpm mailing list"/>
    </reference>
    
    <reference anchor="Honda11" target="">
      <front>
        <title>Is it still possible to extend TCP?</title>
        <author initials="M." surname="Honda"/>
        <author initials="Y." surname="Nishida"/>
        <author initials="C." surname="Raiciu"/>
        <author initials="A." surname="Greenhalgh"/>
        <author initials="M." surname="Handley"/>
        <author initials="H." surname="Tokuda"/>
        <date month="November" year="2011"/>
      </front>
      <seriesInfo name="Proc. of ACM Internet Measurement Conference" value="(IMC) '11"/>
    </reference>
    
    <reference anchor="Kuzmanovic03" target="www.cs.northwestern.edu/~akuzma/doc/TCP-LP-ToN.pdf">
      <front>
        <title>TCP-LP: Low-Priority Service via End-Point Congestion Control</title>
        <author initials="A." surname="Kuzmanovic"/>
        <author initials="E." surname="Knightly"/>
        <date year="2003"/>
      </front>
   </reference>
    
    <reference anchor="Kuehlewind10" target="bobbriscoe.net/projects/netsvc_i-f/chirp_pfldnet10.pdf">
      <front>
        <title>Chirping for Congestion Control -
Implementation Feasibility</title>
        <author initials="M." surname="Kuehlewind"/>
        <author initials="B." surname="Briscoe"/>
        <date month="November" year="2010"/>
      </front>
   </reference>
        
    
    <reference anchor="Watson81" target="">
      <front>
        <title>Timer-based Mechanisms in Reliable
      Transport Protocol Connection Management</title>
        <author initials="R." surname="Watson"/>
        <date year="1981"/>
      </front>
      <seriesInfo name="Computer Networks," value="Vol. 5"/>
    </reference>
    
    <reference anchor="Zhang86" target="">
      <front>
        <title>Why TCP Timers Don't Work Well</title>
        <author initials="L." surname="Zhang"/>
        <date month="August" year="1986"/>
      </front>
      <seriesInfo name="Proc." value="SIGCOMM '86, Stowe, VT"/>
    </reference>

   </references>
   
   <section anchor="AppA" title="Implementation Suggestions">
     <t>TCP Option Layout
       <list>
         <t>The following layout is recommended for sending options on
        non-&lt;SYN&gt; segments, to achieve maximum feasible alignment of
        32-bit and 64-bit machines.
           <figure align="center">
            <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
+--------+--------+--------+--------+
|   NOP  |  NOP   |  TSopt |   10   |
+--------+--------+--------+--------+
|          TSval timestamp          |
+--------+--------+--------+--------+
|          TSecr timestamp          |
+--------+--------+--------+--------+
           ]]></artwork>
          </figure>
        </t>
      </list>
     </t>
     <t>Interaction with the TCP Urgent Pointer
       <list>
         <t>The TCP Urgent pointer, like the TCP window, is a 16 bit value.
        Some of the original discussion for the TCP Window Scale option
        included proposals to increase the Urgent pointer to 32 bits.
        As it turns out, this is unnecessary.  There are two
        observations that should be made:
        <list style="format (%d)">
          <t>With IP Version 4, the largest amount of TCP data that can
             be sent in a single packet is 65495 bytes (64 KiB - 1 -- size
             of fixed IP and TCP headers).
          </t>
          <t>Updates to the urgent pointer while the user is in "urgent
             mode" are invisible to the user.
          </t>
        </list>
      </t>
      <t>This means that if the Urgent Pointer points beyond the end of
        the TCP data in the current segment, then the user will remain in
        urgent mode until the next TCP segment arrives.  That segment will
        update the urgent pointer to a new offset, and the user will
        never have left urgent mode.
      </t>
      <t>Thus, to properly implement the Urgent Pointer, the sending TCP
        only has to check for overflow of the 16 bit Urgent Pointer
        field before filling it in.  If it does overflow, than a value
        of 65535 should be inserted into the Urgent Pointer.
      </t>
      <t>The same technique applies to IP Version 6, except in the case
        of IPv6 Jumbograms.  When IPv6 Jumbograms are supported, 
        <xref target="RFC2675"/><!--xref target"Borman99"/--> requires 
        additional steps for dealing with the
        Urgent Pointer, these are described in section 5.2 of 
        <xref target="RFC2675"/>.
      </t>
      </list>
     </t>
  </section>
  <section anchor="AppB" title="Duplicates from Earlier Connection Incarnations">
    <t>There are two cases to be considered:  (1) a system crashing (and
   losing connection state) and restarting, and (2) the same connection
   being closed and reopened without a loss of host state.  These will
   be described in the following two sections.
    </t>
    <section anchor="AppB1" title="System Crash with Loss of State">
      <t>TCP's quiet time of one MSL upon system startup handles the loss
      of connection state in a system crash/restart.  For an
      explanation, see for example "When to Keep Quiet" in the TCP
      protocol specification <xref target="RFC0793"/><!--xref target="Postel81"/-->.  The MSL that is required here
      does not depend upon the transfer speed.  The current TCP MSL of 2
      minutes seemed acceptable as an operational compromise, when many
      host systems used to take this long to boot after a crash. Current
      host systems can boot considerably faster.
      </t>
      <t>The Timestamps option may be used to ease the MSL
      requirements (or to provide additional security against data
      corruption).  If timestamps are being used and if the timestamp
      clock can be guaranteed to be monotonic over a system
      crash/restart, i.e., if the first value of the sender's timestamp
      clock after a crash/restart can be guaranteed to be greater than
      the last value before the restart, then a quiet time is
      unnecessary.
      </t>
      <t>To dispense totally with the quiet time would require that the
      host clock be synchronized to a time source that is stable over
      the crash/restart period, with an accuracy of one timestamp clock
      tick or better.  We can back off from this strict requirement to
      take advantage of approximate clock synchronization.  Suppose that
      the clock is always re-synchronized to within N timestamp clock
      ticks and that booting (extended with a quiet time, if necessary)
      takes more than N ticks.  This will guarantee monotonicity of the
      timestamps, which can then be used to reject old duplicates even
      without an enforced MSL.
      </t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="AppB2" title="Closing and Reopening a Connection">
      <t>When a TCP connection is closed, a delay of 2*MSL in TIME-WAIT
      state ties up the socket pair for 4 minutes (see Section 3.5 of
      <xref target="RFC0793"/><!--xref target="Postel81"/-->.  Applications built upon TCP that close one connection
      and open a new one (e.g., an FTP data transfer connection using
      Stream mode) must choose a new socket pair each time.  The 
      TIME-WAIT delay serves two different purposes:
        <list style="format (%c)">
          <t>Implement the full-duplex reliable close handshake of TCP.
          <vspace blankLines="1"/>
           The proper time to delay the final close step is not really
           related to the MSL; it depends instead upon the RTO for the
           FIN segments and therefore upon the RTT of the path.  (It
           could be argued that the side that is sending a FIN knows
           what degree of reliability it needs, and therefore it should
           be able to determine the length of the TIME-WAIT delay for
           the FIN's recipient.  This could be accomplished with an
           appropriate TCP option in FIN segments.)
           <vspace blankLines="1"/>
           Although there is no formal upper-bound on RTT, common
           network engineering practice makes an RTT greater than 1
           minute very unlikely.  Thus, the 4 minute delay in TIME-WAIT
           state works satisfactorily to provide a reliable full-duplex
           TCP close.  Note again that this is independent of MSL
           enforcement and network speed.
          <vspace blankLines="1"/>
           The TIME-WAIT state could cause an indirect performance
           problem if an application needed to repeatedly close one
           connection and open another at a very high frequency, since
           the number of available TCP ports on a host is less than
           2^16.  However, high network speeds are not the major
           contributor to this problem; the RTT is the limiting factor
           in how quickly connections can be opened and closed.
           Therefore, this problem will be no worse at high transfer
           speeds.
          </t>
          <t>Allow old duplicate segments to expire.
          <vspace blankLines="1"/>
           To replace this function of TIME-WAIT state, a mechanism
           would have to operate across connections.  PAWS is defined
           strictly within a single connection; the last timestamp
           (TS.Recent) is kept in the connection control block, and
           discarded when a connection is closed.
          <vspace blankLines="1"/>
           An additional mechanism could be added to the TCP, a per-host
           cache of the last timestamp received from any connection.
           This value could then be used in the PAWS mechanism to reject
           old duplicate segments from earlier incarnations of the
           connection, if the timestamp clock can be guaranteed to have
           ticked at least once since the old connection was open.  This
           would require that the TIME-WAIT delay plus the RTT together
           must be at least one tick of the sender's timestamp clock.
           Such an extension is not part of the proposal of this RFC.
          <vspace blankLines="1"/>
           Note that this is a variant on the mechanism proposed by
           Garlick, Rom, and Postel <xref target="Garlick77"/>, 
           which required each
           host to maintain connection records containing the highest
           sequence numbers on every connection.  Using timestamps
           instead, it is only necessary to keep one quantity per remote
           host, regardless of the number of simultaneous connections to
           that host.          
          </t>
        </list>
      </t>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section anchor="AppD" title="Summary of Notation">
<?rfc subcompact="yes" ?>
    <t>The following notation has been used in this document.
    </t>
    <t>Options
      <list><t>
      <list hangIndent="18" style="hanging">
        <t hangText="WSopt:">TCP Window Scale option</t>
        <t hangText="TSopt:">TCP Timestamps option</t>
      </list></t>
      </list>
    </t>
    <t>Option Fields
      <list><t>
      <list hangIndent="18" style="hanging">
        <t hangText="shift.cnt:">Window scale byte in WSopt</t>
        <t hangText="TSval:">32-bit Timestamp Value field in TSopt</t>
        <t hangText="TSecr:">32-bit Timestamp Reply field in TSopt</t>
      </list></t>
      </list>
    </t>
    <t>Option Fields in Current Segment
      <list><t>
      <list hangIndent="18" style="hanging">
        <t hangText="SEG.TSval:">TSval field from TSopt in current segment</t>
        <t hangText="SEG.TSecr:">TSecr field from TSopt in current segment</t>
        <t hangText="SEG.WSopt:">8-bit value in WSopt</t>
      </list></t>
      </list>
    </t>
    <t>Clock Values
      <list><t>
      <list hangIndent="18" style="hanging">
        <t hangText="my.TSclock:">System wide source of 32-bit timestamp values</t>
        <t hangText="my.TSclock.rate:">Period of my.TSclock (1 ms to 1 sec)</t>
        <t hangText="Snd.TSoffset:">A offset for randomizing Snd.TSclock</t>
        <t hangText="Snd.TSclock:">my.TSclock + Snd.TSoffset</t>
      </list></t>
      </list>
    </t>  
    <t>Per-Connection State Variables
      <list><t>
      <list hangIndent="18" style="hanging">
        <t hangText="TS.Recent:">Latest received Timestamp</t>
        <t hangText="Last.ACK.sent:">Last ACK field sent</t>
        <t hangText="Snd.TS.OK:">1-bit flag</t>
        <t hangText="Snd.WS.OK:">1-bit flag</t>
        <t hangText="Rcv.Wind.Shift:">Receive window scale exponent</t>
        <t hangText="Snd.Wind.Shift:">Send window scale exponent</t>
        <t hangText="Start.Time:">Snd.TSclock value when segment being
          timed was sent (used by pre-1323 code).</t>
      </list></t>
      </list>
    </t>
    <t>Procedure
      <list><t>
      <list hangIndent="18" style="hanging">
        <t hangText="Update_SRTT(m)">Procedure to update the smoothed RTT
          and RTT variance estimates, using the rules of
          <xref target="Jacobson88a"/>, given m, a new RTT measurement</t>
      </list></t>
      </list>
    </t>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
  </section>
  <!--
  <section anchor="AppE" title="Pseudo-code Summary">
    <t>
      <figure align="left">
         <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[
   Create new TCB => {
      Rcv.wind.scale =
         MIN(14, MAX(0, floor(log2(receive buffer space)) - 15));
      Snd.wind.scale = 0;
      Last.ACK.sent = 0;
      Snd.TS.OK = Snd.WS.OK = FALSE;
      Snd.TSoffset = random 32 bit value
   }

   Send initial <SYN> segment => {
      SEG.WND = MIN( RCV.WND, 65535 );
      Include in segment: TSopt(TSval=Snd.TSclock, TSecr=0);
      Include in segment: WSopt = Rcv.wind.scale;
   }

   Send <SYN,ACK> segment => {
      SEG.ACK = Last.ACK.sent = RCV.NXT;
      SEG.WND = MIN( RCV.WND, 65535 );
      if (Snd.TS.OK) then
         Include in segment:
            TSopt(TSval=Snd.TSclock, TSecr=TS.Recent);
      if (Snd.WS.OK) then
         Include in segment: 
            WSopt = Rcv.wind.scale;
   }

   Receive <SYN> or <SYN,ACK> segment => {
      if (Segment contains TSopt) then {
         TS.Recent = SEG.TSval;
         Snd.TS.OK = TRUE;
         if (is <SYN,ACK> segment) then
            Update_SRTT(
               (Snd.TSclock - SEG.TSecr)/my.TSclock.rate);
      }
      if (Segment contains WSopt) then {
         Snd.wind.scale = SEG.WSopt;
         Snd.WS.OK = TRUE;
         if (the ACK bit is not set, and Rcv.wind.scale has not 
               been initialized by the user) then
            Rcv.wind.scale = Snd.wind.scale;
      }
      else
         Rcv.wind.scale = Snd.wind.scale = 0;
   }

   Send non-SYN segment => {
      SEG.ACK = Last.ACK.sent = RCV.NXT;
      SEG.WND = MIN( RCV.WND >> Rcv.wind.scale, 65535 );
      if (Snd.TS.OK) then
         Include in segment:
            TSopt(TSval=Snd.TSclock, TSecr=TS.Recent);
   }

   Receive non-SYN segment in (state >= ESTABLISHED) => {
      Window = (SEG.WND << Snd.wind.scale);
         /* Use 32-bit 'Window' instead of 16-bit 'SEG.WND'
          * in rest of processing.
          */
      if (Segment contains TSopt) then {
         if (SEG.TSval < TS.Recent && 
               Idle less than 24 days) then {
            if (Send.TS.OK AND (NOT RST) ) then {
               /* Timestamp too old =>
                *    segment is unacceptable.
                */
               Send ACK segment;
               Discard segment and return;
            }
         }
         else {
            if (SEG.SEQ <= Last.ACK.sent) then
               TS.Recent = SEG.TSval;
         }
      }
      if (SEG.ACK > SND.UNA) then {
         /* (At least part of) first segment in
          * retransmission queue has been ACKed
          */
         if (Segment contains TSopt) then
            Update_SRTT(
               (Snd.TSclock - SEG.TSecr)/my.TSclock.rate);
         else
            Update_SRTT( /* for compatibility */
               (Snd.TSclock - Start.Time)/my.TSclock.rate);
      }
   }
        ]]></artwork>
      </figure>
    </t>
  </section>
  -->
  <section anchor="AppF" title="Event Processing Summary">
    <t>OPEN Call
      <list>
        <t>...
        </t>
        <t>An initial send sequence number (ISS) is selected.  
          Send a &lt;SYN&gt; segment of the form:
          <figure align="center">
             <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
<SEQ=ISS><CTL=SYN><TSval=Snd.TSclock><WSopt=Rcv.Wind.Shift>
            ]]></artwork>
          </figure>
        </t>
        <t>...
        </t>
      </list>
    </t>
    <t>SEND Call
      <list>
        <t>CLOSED STATE (i.e., TCB does not exist)
          <list>
            <t>...
            </t>
          </list>
        </t>
        <t>LISTEN STATE
          <list>
            <t>If the foreign socket is specified, then change 
              the connection from passive to active, select an ISS.  
              Send a &lt;SYN&gt; segment containing the options: 
              &lt;TSval=Snd.TSclock&gt; and &lt;WSopt=Rcv.Wind.Shift&gt;.  
              Set SND.UNA to ISS, SND.NXT to ISS+1. Enter SYN-SENT state. 
              ...
            </t>
          </list>
        </t>
        <t>SYN-SENT STATE<vspace blankLines="0"/>
          SYN-RECEIVED STATE
          <list>
            <t>...
            </t>
          </list>
        </t>
        <t>ESTABLISHED STATE<vspace blankLines="0"/>
          CLOSE-WAIT STATE
          <list>
            <t>Segmentize the buffer and send it with a piggybacked
              acknowledgment (acknowledgment value = RCV.NXT).  ...
            </t>
            <t>If the urgent flag is set ...
            </t>
            <t>If the Snd.TS.OK flag is set, then include the TCP 
              Timestamps option 
              &lt;TSval=Snd.TSclock,TSecr=TS.Recent&gt; in each 
              data segment.
            </t>
            <t>Scale the receive window for transmission in the 
              segment header:
              <figure align="center">
                <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
SEG.WND = (RCV.WND >> Rcv.Wind.Shift).
                ]]></artwork>
              </figure>
            </t>
          </list>
        </t>
      </list>
    </t>
    <t>SEGMENT ARRIVES
      <list>
        <t>...
        </t>
        <t>If the state is LISTEN then
          <list>
            <t>first check for an RST
              <list>
                <t>...
                </t>
              </list>
            </t>
            <t>second check for an ACK
              <list>
                <t>...
                </t>
              </list>
            </t>
            <t>third check for a SYN
              <list>
                <t>if the SYN bit is set, check the security.  If the ...
                  <list>
                    <t>...
                    </t>
                  </list>
                </t>
                <t>if the SEG.PRC is less than the TCB.PRC then continue.
                </t>
                <t>Check for a Window Scale option (WSopt); if one is 
                  found, save SEG.WSopt in Snd.Wind.Shift and set 
                  Snd.WS.OK flag on. Otherwise, set both Snd.Wind.Shift 
                  and Rcv.Wind.Shift to zero and clear Snd.WS.OK flag.
                </t>
                <t>Check for a TSopt option; if one is found, save 
                  SEG.TSval in the variable TS.Recent and turn on the 
                  Snd.TS.OK bit.
                </t>
                <t>Set RCV.NXT to SEG.SEQ+1, IRS is set to SEG.SEQ and 
                  any other control or text should be queued for 
                  processing later.  ISS should be selected and a &lt;SYN&gt; 
                  segment sent of the form:
                  <figure align="center">
                    <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
<SEQ=ISS><ACK=RCV.NXT><CTL=SYN,ACK>
                    ]]></artwork>
                  </figure>
                </t>
                <t>If the Snd.WS.OK bit is on, include a WSopt option
                  &lt;WSopt=Rcv.Wind.Shift&gt; in this segment.  If the 
                  Snd.TS.OK bit is on, include a TSopt 
                  &lt;TSval=Snd.TSclock, TSecr=TS.Recent&gt; in this 
                  segment.  Last.ACK.sent is set to RCV.NXT.
                </t>
                <t>SND.NXT is set to ISS+1 and SND.UNA to ISS.  The 
                  connection state should be changed to SYN-RECEIVED.  
                  Note that any other incoming control or data (combined 
                  with SYN) will be processed in the SYN-RECEIVED state, 
                  but processing of SYN and ACK should not be repeated.  
                  If the listen was not fully specified (i.e., the foreign 
                  socket was not fully specified), then the unspecified 
                  fields should be filled in now.
                </t>
              </list>
            </t>
            <t>fourth other text or control
              <list>
                <t>...
                </t>
              </list>
            </t>
          </list>
        </t>
        <t>If the state is SYN-SENT then
          <list>
            <t>first check the ACK bit
              <list>
                <t>...
                </t>
              </list>
            </t>
            <t>...
            </t>
            <t>fourth check the SYN bit
              <list>
                <t>...
                </t>
                <t>If the SYN bit is on and the security/compartment and 
                  precedence are acceptable then, RCV.NXT is set to 
                  SEG.SEQ+1, IRS is set to SEG.SEQ, and any 
                  acknowledgements on the retransmission queue which 
                  are thereby acknowledged should be removed.
                </t>
                <t>Check for a Window Scale option (WSopt); if it<!--[###]--> 
                  is found, save SEG.WSopt in Snd.Wind.Shift; otherwise, 
                  set both Snd.Wind.Shift and Rcv.Wind.Shift to zero.
                </t>
                <t>Check for a TSopt option; if one is found, save 
                  SEG.TSval in variable TS.Recent and turn on the 
                  Snd.TS.OK bit in the connection control block.  If 
                  the ACK bit is set, use Snd.TSclock - SEG.TSecr as 
                  the initial RTT estimate.
                </t>
                <t>If SND.UNA > ISS (our &lt;SYN&gt; has been ACKed), change the 
                  connection state to ESTABLISHED, form an &lt;ACK&gt; segment:
                  <figure align="center">
                    <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
<SEQ=SND.NXT><ACK=RCV.NXT><CTL=ACK>
                    ]]></artwork>
                  </figure>
                  and send it.  If the Snd.Echo.OK bit is on, include 
                  a TSopt option &lt;TSval=Snd.TSclock,TSecr=TS.Recent&gt;
                  in this &lt;ACK&gt; segment. Last.ACK.sent is set to RCV.NXT.
                </t>
                <t>Data or controls which were queued for transmission 
                  may be included.  If there are other controls or text 
                  in the segment then continue processing at the sixth 
                  step below where the URG bit is checked, otherwise 
                  return.
                </t>
                <t>Otherwise enter SYN-RECEIVED, form a &lt;SYN,ACK&gt; segment:
                  <figure align="center">
                    <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
<SEQ=ISS><ACK=RCV.NXT><CTL=SYN,ACK>
                    ]]></artwork>
                  </figure>  
                  and send it.  If the Snd.Echo.OK bit is on, include 
                  a TSopt option &lt;TSval=Snd.TSclock,TSecr=TS.Recent&gt; 
                  in this segment.  If the Snd.WS.OK bit is on, include 
                  a WSopt option &lt;WSopt=Rcv.Wind.Shift&gt; in this 
                  segment.  Last.ACK.sent is set to RCV.NXT.
                </t>
                <t>If there are other controls or text in the segment, 
                  queue them for processing after the ESTABLISHED state 
                  has been reached, return.
                </t>
              </list>
            </t>
            <t>fifth, if neither of the SYN or RST bits is set then 
              drop the segment and return.
            </t>
          </list>
        </t>
        <t>Otherwise,
        </t>
        <t>First, check sequence number
          <list>
            <t>SYN-RECEIVED STATE<vspace blankLines="0"/>
              ESTABLISHED STATE<vspace blankLines="0"/>
              FIN-WAIT-1 STATE<vspace blankLines="0"/>
              FIN-WAIT-2 STATE<vspace blankLines="0"/>
              CLOSE-WAIT STATE<vspace blankLines="0"/>
              CLOSING STATE<vspace blankLines="0"/>
              LAST-ACK STATE<vspace blankLines="0"/>
              TIME-WAIT STATE
              <list>
                <t>Segments are processed in sequence.  Initial tests 
                  on arrival are used to discard old duplicates, but 
                  further processing is done in SEG.SEQ order.  If a 
                  segment's contents straddle the boundary between old 
                  and new, only the new parts should be processed.
                </t>
                <t>Rescale the received window field:
                  <figure align="center">
                    <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
TrueWindow = SEG.WND << Snd.Wind.Shift,
                    ]]></artwork>
                  </figure>
                  and use "TrueWindow" in place of SEG.WND in the 
                  following steps.
                </t>
                <t>Check whether the segment contains a Timestamps
                  option and bit Snd.TS.OK is on.  If so:
                  <list>
                    <t>If SEG.TSval &lt; TS.Recent and the RST bit 
                      is off, then test whether connection has been 
                      idle less than 24 days; if all are true, then 
                      the segment is not acceptable; follow steps 
                      below for an unacceptable segment.
                    </t>
                    <t>If SEG.SEQ is less than or equal to Last.ACK.sent, then 
                      save SEG.TSval in variable TS.Recent.
                    </t>
                  </list>
                </t>
                <t>There are four cases for the acceptability test 
                  for an incoming segment:
                  <list>
                    <t>...
                    </t>
                  </list>
                </t>
                <t>If an incoming segment is not acceptable, an 
                  acknowledgment should be sent in reply (unless 
                  the RST bit is set, if so drop the segment and 
                  return):
                  <figure align="center">
                    <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
<SEQ=SND.NXT><ACK=RCV.NXT><CTL=ACK>
                    ]]></artwork>
                  </figure>
                </t>
                <t>Last.ACK.sent is set to SEG.ACK of the 
                  acknowledgment.  If the Snd.Echo.OK bit is on, 
                  include the Timestamps option 
                  &lt;TSval=Snd.TSclock,TSecr=TS.Recent&gt; in this 
                  &lt;ACK&gt; segment.  Set Last.ACK.sent to SEG.ACK and send 
                  the &lt;ACK&gt; segment.  After sending the acknowledgment, 
                  drop the unacceptable segment and return.
                </t>
              </list>
            </t>
          </list>
        </t>
        <t>...
        </t>
        <t>fifth check the ACK field.
          <list>
            <t>if the ACK bit is off drop the segment and return.
            </t>
            <t>if the ACK bit is on
              <list>
                <t>...
                </t>
                <t>ESTABLISHED STATE
                  <list>
                    <t>If SND.UNA &lt; SEG.ACK &lt;= SND.NXT then, set 
                      SND.UNA &lt;-<!--[###]--> SEG.ACK. Also compute a new estimate 
                      of round-trip time.  If Snd.TS.OK bit is on, use 
                      Snd.TSclock - SEG.TSecr; otherwise use the
                      elapsed time since the first segment in the 
                      retransmission queue was sent.  Any segments on 
                      the retransmission queue which are thereby entirely 
                      acknowledged...
                    </t>
                  </list>
                </t>
              </list>
            </t>
          </list>
        </t>
        <t>...
        </t>
        <t>Seventh, process the segment text.
          <list>
            <t>ESTABLISHED STATE<vspace blankLines="0"/>
              FIN-WAIT-1 STATE<vspace blankLines="0"/>
              FIN-WAIT-2 STATE
              <list>
                <t>...
                </t>
                <t>Send an acknowledgment of the form:
                  <figure align="center">
                    <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
<SEQ=SND.NXT><ACK=RCV.NXT><CTL=ACK>
                      ]]></artwork>
                  </figure>
                </t>
                <t>If the Snd.TS.OK bit is on, include Timestamps
                  option &lt;TSval=Snd.TSclock,TSecr=TS.Recent&gt; 
                  in this &lt;ACK&gt; segment. Set Last.ACK.sent to SEG.ACK 
                  of the acknowledgment, and send it. This 
                  acknowledgment should be piggy-backed on a segment 
                  being transmitted if possible without incurring 
                  undue delay.
                </t>
                <t>...
                </t>
              </list>
            </t>
          </list>
        </t>
      </list>
    </t>
  </section>
  <section anchor="AppG" title="Timestamps Edge Cases">
    <t>While the rules laid out for when to calculate RTTM produce the
   correct results most of the time, there are some edge cases where an
   incorrect RTTM can be calculated.  All of these situations involve
   the loss of segments.  It is felt that these scenarios are rare, and
   that if they should happen, they will cause a single RTTM measurement
   to be inflated, which mitigates its effects on RTO calculations.
    </t>
    <t><xref target="Martin03"/> cites two similar cases when the 
      returning &lt;ACK&gt; is lost,
   and before the retransmission timer fires, another returning &lt;ACK&gt; segment
   arrives, which aknowledges the data.  In this case, the RTTM calculated will
   be inflated:
      <figure align="center">
         <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
clock
  tc=1   <A, TSval=1> ------------------->

  tc=2   (lost) <---- <ACK(A), TSecr=1, win=n>
      (RTTM would have been 1)

         (receive window opens, window update is sent)
  tc=5        <---- <ACK(A), TSecr=1, win=m>
         (RTTM is calculated at 4)
        ]]></artwork>
      </figure>
    </t>
    <t>One thing to note about this situation is that it is somewhat bounded
   by RTO + RTT, limiting how far off the RTTM calculation will be.
   While more complex scenarios can be constructed that produce larger
   inflations (e.g., retransmissions are lost), those scenarios involve
   multiple segment losses, and the connection will have other more
   serious operational problems than using an inflated RTTM in the RTO
   calculation.
    </t>
  </section>
  <section anchor="AppH" title="Window Retraction Example">
    <t>Consider an established TCP connection using a scale factor 
      of 128, Snd.Wind.Shift=7 and Rcv.Wind.Shift=7, that is running 
      with a very small window because the receiver 
      is bottlenecked and both ends are doing small reads and writes.
    </t>
    <t>Consider the ACKs coming back:
      <figure align="center">
         <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[
SEG.ACK  SEG.WIN computed SND.WIN   receiver's actual window
1000     2       1256               1300
        ]]></artwork>
      </figure>
    </t>
    <t>The sender writes 40 bytes and receiver ACKs:
      <figure align="center">
         <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[
1040     2       1296               1300
        ]]></artwork>
      </figure>
    </t>
    <t>The sender writes 5 additional bytes and the receiver has a problem.  
      Two choices:
      <figure align="center">
         <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[
1045     2       1301               1300   - BEYOND BUFFER

1045     1       1173               1300   - RETRACTED WINDOW
        ]]></artwork>
      </figure>
    </t>
    <t>This is a general problem and can  happen 
      any time the sender does a write which is smaller
      than the window scale factor.
    </t>
    <t>In most stacks it is at least partially obscured when the window 
      size is larger than some small number of segments because the stacks 
      prefer to announce windows that are an integral number of segments, 
      rounded up to the next scale factor.  This plus silly window 
      suppression tends to cause less frequent, larger window updates.  
      If the window was rounded down to a segment size there is more 
      opportunity to advance the window, the BEYOND BUFFER case above,
      rather than retracting it.
    </t>
  </section>
  
  <section anchor="AppI" title="RTO calculation modification">
    <t> 
        Taking multiple RTT samples per window would shorten the history 
        calculated by the RTO mechanism in <xref target="RFC6298"/>, and 
        the below algorithm aims to maintain a similar history as originally 
        intended by <xref target="RFC6298"/>.
      </t>
      <t>
        
        It is roughly known how many samples  
        a congestion window worth of data will yield, not accounting 
        for ACK compression, and ACK losses. Such events will result in
        more history of the path being reflected in the final value
        for RTO, and are uncritical. This modification will ensure 
        that a similar amount of time is taken into account for the 
        RTO estimation, regardless of how many samples are taken per 
        window:
        <list>
          <t>ExpectedSamples = ceiling(FlightSize / (SMSS * 2))
          </t>
          <t>alpha' = alpha / ExpectedSamples
          </t>
          <t>beta' = beta / ExpectedSamples
          </t>
        </list>
        Note that the factor 2 in ExpectedSamples is due to "Delayed ACKs".
      </t>
      <t>Instead of using alpha and beta in the algorithm of 
        <xref target="RFC6298"/>, use alpha' and beta' instead:
        <list>
          <t>RTTVAR &lt;- (1 - beta') * RTTVAR + beta' * |SRTT - R'|
          </t>
          <t>SRTT &lt;- (1 - alpha') * SRTT + alpha' * R'
          </t>
          <t>(for each sample R')
          </t>
        </list>
      </t>
<!--
      <t>        
        Alternatively, an implementation could choose to just use one sample 
        per RTT to update the RTO estimator. By using the statistical 
        properties of the additional samples, , e.g. use the maximum devation 
        in that window to update RTTVAR, and the last RTT sample to update 
        SRTT . In the second approach, the expected number of samples can be
        estimated by FlightSize / (SMSS * 2), accounting for delayed ACKs.
      </t>
-->
  </section>
    
  <!--
  <section anchor="AppC" title="Changes from RFC 1072, RFC 1185, and RFC 1323">
  -->
  <section anchor="AppC" title="Changes from RFC 1323">
    <!--
    <t>The protocol extensions defined in RFC 1323 document differ in
   several important ways from those defined in RFC 1072 and RFC 1185.
      <list style="format (%c)">
        <t>SACK has been split off into a separate document, 
          <xref target="RFC2018"/><!-xref target="Mathis96"/->.
        </t>
        <t>The detailed rules for sending timestamp replies (see 
          <xref target="sec34"/>) differ in important ways.  The earlier 
          rules could result in an under-estimate of the RTT in certain 
          cases (packets dropped or out of order).
        </t>
        <t>The same value TS.Recent is now shared by the two distinct
        mechanisms RTTM and PAWS.  This simplification became possible
        because of change (b).
        </t>
        <t>An ambiguity in RFC 1185 was resolved in favor of putting
        timestamps on ACK as well as data segments.  This supports the
        symmetry of the underlying TCP protocol.
        </t>
        <t>The echo and echo reply options of RFC 1072 were combined into a
        single Timestamps option, to reflect the symmetry and to
        simplify processing.
        </t>
        <t>The problem of outdated timestamps on long-idle connections,
        discussed in <xref target="sec422"/>, was realized and resolved.
        </t>
        <t>RFC 1185 recommended that header prediction take precedence over
        the timestamp check.  Based upon some skepticism about the
        probabilistic arguments given in <xref target="sec424"/>, 
        it was decided
        to recommend that the timestamp check be performed first.
        </t>
        <t>The spec was modified so that the extended options will be sent
        on &lt;SYN,ACK&gt; segments only when they are received in the
        corresponding &lt;SYN&gt; segments.  This provides the most
        conservative possible conditions for interoperation with
        implementations without the extensions.
        </t>
      </list>
    </t>
    <t>In addition to these substantive changes, the present RFC 
      attempts to specify the algorithms unambiguously by presenting 
      modifications to the Event Processing rules of RFC 793; 
      see <xref target="AppF"/>.
    </t>
    <t>There are additional changes in this document from RFC 1323.  These
   changes are:-->
    <t>Several important updates and clarifications to the specification 
      in RFC 1323 are made in these document. The technical changes are 
      summarized below:
      <list style="format (%c)">
        <t><!-- -13:2.3 -->A wrong reference to SND.WND was corrected 
          to SEG.WND in <xref target="sec23"/>
        </t>
        <t><!-- -08:2.4 --><xref target="sec24"/> was added describing 
          the unavoidable window retraction issue, and explicitly 
          describing the mitigation steps necessary.
        </t>
        <t><!-- -08:3.2 -->In <xref target="sec32"/> the wording how 
          the Timestamps option negotiation is to be performed was 
          updated with RFC2119 wording. Further, a number of paragraphs 
          were added to clarify the expected behavior with a compliant 
          implementation using TSopt, as RFC1323 left room for 
          interpretation - e.g. potential late enablement of TSopt.
        </t>
        <t><!-- -08:3.3 -->The description of which TSecr values can be 
          used to update the measured RTT has been clarified.  
          Specifically, with timestamps, the Karn algorithm 
          <xref target="Karn87"/> is disabled. The Karn algorithm 
          disables all RTT measurements during retransmission, since it 
          is ambiguous whether the &lt;ACK&gt; is for the original 
          segment, or the retransmitted segment.  With timestamps, 
          that ambiguity is removed since the TSecr in the &lt;ACK&gt; 
          will contain the TSval from whichever data segment made it 
          to the destination.
        </t>
        <t><!-- -08:3.3 -->RTTM update processing explicitly excludes 
          segments not updating SND.UNA. The original text could be 
          interpreted to allow taking RTT samples when SACK acknowledges
          some new, non-continuous data.
        </t>
        <t><!-- -08:3.4 -->In RFC1323, section 3.4, step (2) of the 
          algorithm to control which timestamp is echoed was incorrect 
          in two regards:
          <list style="format (%d)">
            <t>It failed to update TS.recent for a retransmitted segment
             that resulted from a lost &lt;ACK&gt;.
            </t>
            <t>It failed if SEG.LEN = 0.
            </t>
          </list>
          In the new algorithm, the case of SEG.TSval &gt;= TS.recent is
          included for consistency with the PAWS test.
        </t>
        <t><!-- -08:4.2 -->It is now recommended that the Timestamps 
          option is included in &lt;RST&gt; segments if the incoming 
          segment contained a Timestamps option.
        </t>
        <t><!-- -08:4.2,4.3 -->&lt;RST&gt; segments are explicitly 
          excluded from PAWS processing.
        </t>
        <t><!-- -08:4.3 -->Added text to clarify the precedence between 
          regular TCP <xref target="RFC0793"/> and this document
          Timestamps option / PAWS processing. Discussion about combined 
          acceptability checks are ongoing.
        </t>
        <t><!-- -08:4.4,6,AppC -->Snd.TSoffset and Snd.TSclock variables 
          have been added. Snd.TSclock is the sum of my.TSclock and 
          Snd.TSoffset.  This allows the starting points for timestamp 
          values to be randomized on a per-connection basis.  Setting 
          Snd.TSoffset to zero yields the same results as 
          <xref target="RFC1323"/>. Text was added to guide implementors 
          to the proper selection of these offsets, as entirly random 
          offsets for each new connection will conflict with PAWS.
        </t>
        <t><!-- -8:AppA --><xref target="AppA"/> has been expanded with 
          information about the TCP Urgent Pointer. An earlier revision 
          contained text around the TCP MSS option, which was split off 
          into <xref target="RFC6691"/>.
        </t>
        <t><!-- -08:AppD -->One correction was made to the Event 
          Processing Summary in <xref target="AppF"/>.  In SEND 
          CALL/ESTABLISHED STATE, RCV.WND is used to fill in the SEG.WND 
          value, not SND.WND.
        </t>
        <t><xref target="AppI"/> was added to exemplify how an RTO
          calculation might be updated to properly take the much higher
          RTT sampling frequency enabled by the Timestamps option
          into account.
        </t>
          
      </list>
    </t>
    <t>Editorial changes of the document, that don't impact the 
      implementation or function of the mechanisms described in this 
      document include:
      <list style="format (%c)">
        <t><!-- -08:1.1,1.2,1.3 -->Removed much of the discussion in 
          <xref target="sec1"/> to streamline the document. However, 
          detailed examples and discussions in <xref target="sec2"/>, 
          <xref target="sec3"/> and <xref target="sec4"/> are kept as 
          guideline for implementers.
        </t>
        <t>Added short text that the use of WS increases the chances of sequence number wrap, thus the PAWS mechanism is required in certain environments.</t>
        <t><!-- -08:1.3 -->Removed references to "new" options, as 
          the options were introduced in <xref target="RFC1323"/> 
          already. Changed the text in <xref target="sec13"/> to 
          specifically address TS and WS options.
        </t>
        <t><!-- -08:1.4 --><xref target="secTerm"/> was added for 
          <xref target="RFC2119"/> wording. Normative text was updated with the 
          appropriate phrases.
        </t>
        <t><!-- docwide -->Added &lt; &gt; brackets to mark specific 
          types of segments, and replaced most occurances of "packet" 
          with "segment", where TCP segments are referred to. 
        </t>
        <t><!-- -12:3 -->Updated the text in <xref target="sec3"/> 
          to take into account what has been learned since 
          <xref target="RFC1323"/>.
        </t>
        <t><!-- AppC -->Removed the list of changes between 
          <xref target="RFC1323"/> and prior versions. These changes 
          are mentioned in Appendix C of <xref target="RFC1323"/>.
        </t>
        <t><!-- -08:AppG -->Moved Appendix 
          <xref target="AppC" format="title"/> to the end of the 
          appendices for easier lookup. In addition, the entries were 
          split into a technical and an editorial part, and sorted to 
          roughly correspond with the sections in the text where they 
          apply.
        </t>
      </list>
    </t>
  </section>
  
   
 </back>
</rfc>