<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!-- $Id: draft-roca-rmt-newfcast-04.xml,v 1.2 2009-03-06 11:02:20 roca Exp $ -->
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<!--<rfc category="exp" docName="draft-roca-rmt-newfcast-03" ipr="full3978">-->
<rfc category="exp"  docName="draft-ietf-rmt-fcast-00" ipr="pre5378Trust200902">
  <!--
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
-->

  <?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl'
                href='http://xml.resource.org/authoring/rfc2629.xslt' ?>

  <?rfc toc="yes"?>

  <?rfc tocompact="yes"?>

  <?rfc tocdepth="3"?>

  <?rfc tocindent="yes"?>

  <?rfc symrefs="yes"?>

  <?rfc sortrefs="no"?>

  <?rfc comments="yes"?>

  <?rfc inline="yes"?>

  <?rfc compact="yes"?>

  <?rfc subcompact="no"?>

  <?rfc iprnotified="no" ?>

  <?rfc strict="yes" ?>

  <front>
    <title abbrev="FCAST: Scalable Object Delivery">FCAST: Scalable Object
    Delivery for the ALC and NORM Protocols</title>

    <author fullname="Vincent Roca" initials="V." surname="Roca">
      <organization>INRIA</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>655, av. de l'Europe</street>

          <street>Inovallee; Montbonnot</street>

          <city>ST ISMIER cedex</city>

          <code>38334</code>

          <country>France</country>
        </postal>

        <email>vincent.roca@inria.fr</email>

        <uri>http://planete.inrialpes.fr/people/roca/</uri>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Brian Adamson" initials="B." surname="Adamson">
      <organization>Naval Research Laboratory</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>

          <city>Washington, DC</city>

          <code>20375</code>

          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>

        <email>adamson@itd.nrl.navy.mil</email>

        <uri>http://cs.itd.nrl.navy.mil</uri>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date month="December" year="2009" />

    <area>Transport</area>

    <workgroup>RMT</workgroup>

    <keyword>ALC, NORM</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>This document introduces the FCAST object (e.g., file) delivery
      application on top of the ALC and NORM reliable multicast protocols.
      FCAST is a highly scalable application that provides a reliable object
      delivery service.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>

<!--
<t>
<list style="empty">
<t>  *** Editor's note:
XXX  </t>
</list>
</t>
-->

    <section anchor="intro" title="Introduction">
      <t>This document introduces the FCAST reliable and scalable object
      (e.g., file) delivery application. Two versions of FCAST exist: <list
          style="symbols">
          <t>FCAST/ALC that relies on the Asynchronous Layer Coding (ALC)
          <xref target="RMT-PI-ALC"></xref> and the Layered Coding Transport
          (LCT) <xref target="RFC5651"></xref> reliable multicast transport
          protocol, and</t>

          <t>FCAST/NORM that relies on the NACK-Oriented Reliable Multicast
          (NORM) <xref target="RFC5740"></xref> reliable multicast
          transport protocol.</t>
        </list> Hereafter, the term FCAST denotes either FCAST/ALC or
      FCAST/NORM.</t>

      <t>Depending on the target use case, the delivery service provided by
      FCAST is more or less reliable. For instance, with FCAST/ALC used in
      ON-DEMAND mode over a time period that largely exceeds the typical
      download time, the service can be considered as fully reliable.
      Similarly, when FCAST is used along with a session control application
      that collects reception information and takes appropriate corrective
      measures (e.g., a direct point-to-point retransmission of missing
      packets, or a new multicast recovery session), then the service can be
      considered as fully reliable. On the opposite, if FCAST operates in PUSH
      mode, then the service is usually only partially reliable, and a
      receiver that is disconnected during a sufficient time will perhaps not
      have the possibility to download the object.</t>

      <t>Depending on the target use case, the FCAST scalability is more or
      less important. For instance, if FCAST/ALC is used on top of purely
      unidirectional transport channels, with no feedback information at all,
      which is the default mode of operation, then the scalability is maximum
      since neither FCAST, nor ALC, UDP or IP generates any feedback message.
      On the opposite, the FCAST/NORM scalability is typically limited by NORM
      scalability itself. Similarly, if FCAST is used along with a session
      control application that collects reception information from the
      receivers, then this session control application may limit the
      scalability of the global object delivery system. This situation can of
      course be mitigated by using a hierarchy of feedback message aggregators
      or servers. The details of this are out of the scope of the present
      document.</t>

      <t>A design goal behind FCAST is to define a streamlined solution, in
      order to enable lightweight implementations of the protocol stack, and
      limit the operational processing and storage requirements. A consequence
      of this choice is that FCAST cannot be considered as a versatile
      application, capable of addressing all the possible use-cases. On the
      opposite, FCAST has some intrinsic limitations. From this point of view
      it differs from FLUTE <xref target="RMT-FLUTE"></xref> which favors
      flexibility at the expense of some additional complexity.</t>

      <t>A good example of the design choices meant to favor the simplicity is
      the way FCAST manages the object meta-data: by default, the meta-data
      and the object content are sent together, in a compound object. This
      solution has many advantages in terms of simplicity as will be described
      later on. However, as such, it also has an intrinsic limitation since it
      does not enable a receiver to decide in advance, before beginning the
      reception of the compound object, whether the object is of interest or
      not, based on the information that may be provided in the meta-data.
      Therefore this document defines additional techniques that may be used
      to mitigate this limitation. It is also possible that some use-cases
      require that each receiver download the whole set of objects sent in the
      session (e.g., with mirroring tools). When this is the case, the above
      limitation is no longer be a problem.</t>

      <section anchor="applicability" title="Applicability">
        <!-- ==================================== -->

        <t>FCAST is compatible with any congestion control protocol designed
        for ALC/LCT or NORM. However, depending on the use-case, the data flow
        generated by the FCAST application might not be constant, but instead
        be bursty in nature. Similarly, depending on the use-case, an FCAST
        session might be very short. Whether and how this will impact the
        congestion control protocol is out of the scope of the present
        document.</t>

        <t>FCAST is compatible with any security mechanism designed for
        ALC/LCT or NORM. The use of a security scheme is strongly RECOMMENDED
        (see <xref target="security"></xref>).</t>

        <t>FCAST is compatible with any FEC scheme designed for ALC/LCT or
        NORM. Whether FEC is used or not, and the kind of FEC scheme used, is
        to some extent transparent to FCAST.</t>

        <t>FCAST is compatible with both IPv4 and IPv6. Nothing in the FCAST
        specification has any implication on the source or destination IP
        address.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Requirements notation">
      <!-- ==================================== -->

      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
      document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
      target="RFC2119"></xref>.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Definitions, Notations and Abbreviations">
      <!-- ================================================= -->

      <section title="Definitions">
        <!-- ==================== -->

        <t>This document uses the following definitions: <list hangIndent="7"
            style="hanging">
            <t hangText="FCAST/ALC:">denotes the FCAST application running on
            top of the ALC/LCT reliable transport protocol;</t>

            <t hangText="FCAST/NORM:">denotes the FCAST application running on
            top of the NORM reliable transport protocol;</t>

            <t hangText="FCAST:">denotes either FCAST/ALC or FCAST/NORM;</t>

            <t hangText="Compound Object:">denotes an ALC or NORM transport
            object composed of the Compound Object Header (<xref
            target="header_format"></xref>), including any meta-data, and the
            content of the original application object (e.g., a file);</t>

            <t hangText="Carousel:">denotes the Compound Object transmission
            system of an FCAST sender;</t>

            <t hangText="Carousel Instance:">denotes a fixed set of registered
            Compound Objects that are sent by the carousel during a certain
            number of cycles. Whenever Compound Objects need to be added or
            removed, a new Carousel Instance is defined;</t>

            <t hangText="Carousel Instance Object (CIO):">denotes a specific
            object that lists the Compound Objects that comprise a given
            Carousel Instance;</t>

            <t hangText="Carousel Cycle:">denotes a transmission round within
            which all the Compound Objects registered in the Carousel Instance
            are transmitted a certain number of times. By default, Compound
            Objects are transmitted once per cycle, but higher values are
            possible, that might differ on a per-object basis;</t>

            <t hangText="Transmission Object Identifier (TOI):">denotes the
            numeric identifier associated to a specific object by the
            underlying transport layer. In the case of ALC, this corresponds
            to the TOI described in that specification while for the NORM
            specification this corresponds to the NormTransportId described
            there.</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>

      <section title="Abbreviations">
        <!-- ====================== -->

        <t>This document uses the following abbreviations: <list
            hangIndent="7" style="hanging">
            <t hangText="CIO:">Carousel Instance Object</t>

            <t hangText="CIID:">Carousel Instance IDentifier</t>

            <t hangText="FEC OTI:">FEC Object Transmission Information</t>

            <t hangText="TOI:">Transmission Object Identifier</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="fcast_principles" title="FCAST Principles">
      <!-- ==================================== -->

      <section anchor="fcast_service" title="FCAST Content Delivery Service">
        <!-- ==================================== -->

        <t>The basic goal of FCAST is to transmit objects to a group of
        receivers in a reliable way. The receiver set MAY be restricted to a
        single receiver or MAY include possibly a very large number of
        receivers. FCAST is specified to support two forms of operation:<list
            style="numbers">
            <t>FCAST/ALC: where the FCAST application is meant to run on top
            of the ALC/LCT reliable multicast transport protocol, and</t>

            <t>FCAST/NORM: where the FCAST application is meant to run on top
            of the NORM reliable multicast transport protocol.</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>This specification is designed such that both forms of operation
        share as much commonality as possible.</t>

        <t>While the choice of the underlying transport protocol (i.e., ALC or
        NORM) and its parameters may limit the practical receiver group size,
        nothing in FCAST itself limits it. The transmission might be fully
        reliable, or only partially reliable depending upon the way ALC or
        NORM is used (e.g., whether FEC encoding and/or NACK-based repair
        requests are used or not), the way the FCAST carousel is used (e.g.,
        whether the objects are made available for a long time span or not),
        and the way in which FCAST itself is employed (e.g., whether there is
        a session control application that might automatically extend an
        existing FCAST session until all receivers have received the
        transmitted content).</t>

        <t>FCAST is designed to be as self-sufficient as possible, in
        particular in the way object meta-data is attached to object data
        content. However, for some uses, meta-data MAY also be communicated by
        an out-of-band mechanism that is out of the scope of the present
        document.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="meta-data_tx" title="Meta-Data Transmission">
        <!-- ==================================== -->

        <t>FCAST usually carries meta-data elements by prepending them to the
        object it refers to. As a result, a Compound Object is created that is
        composed of a header followed by the original object data. This
        header is itself composed of the meta-data as well as several fields,
        for instance to indicate the boundaries between the various parts of
        this Compound Object (<xref target="fig_compound_obj"></xref>).</t>

        <figure anchor="fig_compound_obj" title="Compound Object composition.">
          <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
<------------------------ Compound Object ----------------------->
+-------------------------+--------------------------------------+
|  Compound Object Header |              Object Data             |
| (can include meta-data) |       (can be encoded by FCAST)      |
+-------------------------+--------------------------------------+
]]></artwork>
        </figure>

        <t>Attaching the meta-data to the object is an efficient solution,
        since it guaranties that meta-data be received along with the
        associated object, and it allows the transport of the meta-data to
        benefit from any transport-layer erasure protection of the Compound
        Object (e.g., using FEC encoding and/or NACK-based repair). However a
        limit of this scheme, as such, is that a client does not know the
        meta-data of an object before beginning its reception, and in case of
        erasures affecting the meta-data, not until the object decoding is
        completed. The details of course depend upon the transport protocol
        and the FEC code used.</t>

        <t>In certain use-cases, FCAST can also be associated to another
        in-band (e.g., via NORM INFO messages, <xref
        target="norm_specifics"></xref>) or out-of-band signaling mechanism.
        In that case, this mechanism can be used in order to carry the whole
        meta-data (or a subset of it), possibly ahead of time.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="meta-data_content" title="Meta-Data Content">
        <!-- ==================================== -->

        <t>The meta-data associated to an object can be composed of, but are
        not limited to: <list style="symbols">
            <t>Content-Location: the URI of the object, which gives the name
            and location of the object;</t>

            <t>Content-Type: the MIME type of the object;</t>

            <t>Content-Length: the size of the initial object, before any
            content encoding (if any). Note that this content length does not
            include the meta-data nor the fixed size Compound Object
            header;</t>

            <t>Content-Encoding: the optional encoding of the object performed
            by FCAST. If there is no Content-Encoding entry, the receiver MUST
            assume that the object is not encoded (default). The support of
            gzip encoding, or any other solution, remains optional.</t>

            <t>Content-MD5: the MD5 message digest of the object in order to
            check its integrity. Note that this digest is meant to protect
            from transmission and processing errors, not from deliberate
            attacks by an intelligent attacker. Note also that this digest
            only protects the object, not the header, and therefore not the
            meta-data. A separate checksum is provided to that purpose (<xref
            target="header_format"></xref>);</t>

            <t>a digital signature for this object;</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>This list is not limited and new meta-data information can be
        added. For instance, when dealing with very large objects (e.g., that
        largely exceed the working memory of a receiver), it can be
        interesting to split this object into several sub-objects (or slices).
        When this happens, the meta-data associated to each sub-object MUST
        include the following entries: <list style="symbols">
            <t>Fcast-Obj-Slice-Nb: the total number of slices. A value
            strictly greater than 1 indicates that this object is the result
            of a split of the original object;</t>

            <t>Fcast-Obj-Slice-Idx: the slice index (in the {0 .. SliceNb - 1}
            interval);</t>

            <t>Fcast-Obj-Slice-Offset: the offset at which this slice starts
            within the original object;</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>When meta-data elements are communicated out-of-band, in advance of
        data transmission, the following pieces of information MAY also be
        useful: <list style="symbols">
            <t>TOI: the Transmission Object Identifier (TOI) of the object
            (<xref target="object_id"></xref>), in order to enable a receiver
            to easily associate the meta-data to the object;</t>

            <t>FEC Object Transmission Information (FEC OTI). In this case the
            FCAST sender does not need to use the optional EXT_FTI mechanism
            of the ALC or NORM protocols.</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="carousel" title="Carousel Transmission">
        <!-- ==================================== -->

        <t>A set of FCAST Compound Objects scheduled for transmission are
        considered a logical "Carousel". A given "Carousel Instance" is
        comprised of a fixed set of Compound Objects. Whenever the FCAST
        application needs to add new Compound Objects to, or remove old
        Compound Objects from the transmission set, a new Carousel Instance is
        defined since the set of Compound Objects changes.</t>

        <t>For a given Carousel Instance, one or more transmission cycles are
        possible. During each cycle, all of the Compound Objects comprising
        the Carousel are sent. By default, each object is transmitted once per
        cycle. However, in order to allow different levels of priority, some
        objects MAY be transmitted more often that others during a cycle,
        and/or benefit from higher FEC protection than others. This can be the
        case for instance of the CIO objects (<xref target="cio"></xref>). For
        some FCAST usage (e.g., a unidirectional "push" mode), a Carousel
        Instance may be associated to a single transmission cycle. In other
        cases it may be associated to a large number of transmission cycles
        (e.g., in "on-demand" mode, where objects are made available for
        download during a long period of time).</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="cio" title="Carousel Instance Object">
        <!-- ==================================== -->

        <t>The FCAST sender CAN transmit an OPTIONAL Carousel Instance Object
        (CIO). The CIO carries the list of the Compound Objects that are part
        of a given Carousel Instance, by specifying their respective
        Transmission Object Identifiers (TOI). However the CIO does not
        describe the objects themselves (i.e., there is no meta-data).
        Additionally, the CIO MAY include a "Complete" flag that is used to
        indicate that no further modification to the enclosed list will be
        done in the future. Finally, the CIO MAY include a Carousel Instance
        ID that identifies the Carousel Instance it pertains to. These aspects
        are discussed in <xref target="carousel_instance_object"></xref>.</t>

        <t>There is no reserved TOI value for the CIO itself, since this
        object is regarded by ALC/LCT or NORM as a standard object. On the
        opposite, the nature of this object (CIO) is indicated by means of a
        specific Compound Object header field (the "I" flag) so that it can be
        recognized and processed by the FCAST application as needed. A direct
        consequence is the following: since a receiver does not know in
        advance which TOI will be used for the following CIO (in case of a
        dynamic session), he MUST NOT filter out packets that are not in the
        current CIO's TOI list. Said differently, the goal of CIO is not to
        setup ALC or NORM packet filters (this mechanism would not be secure
        in any case).</t>

        <t>The use of a CIO remains optional. If it is not used, then the
        clients progressively learn what files are part of the carousel
        instance by receiving ALC or NORM packets with new TOIs. However using
        a CIO has several benefits: <list style="symbols">
            <t>When the "Complete" flag is set (if ever), the receivers know
            when they can leave the session, i.e., when they have received all
            the objects that are part of the last carousel instance of this
            delivery session;</t>

            <t>In case of a session with a dynamic set of objects, the sender
            can reliably inform the receivers that some objects have been
            removed from the carousel with the CIO. This solution is more
            robust than the "Close Object flag (B)" of ALC/LCT since a client
            with an intermittent connectivity might loose all the packets
            containing this B flag. And while NORM provides a robust object
            cancellation mechanism in the form of its NORM_CMD(SQUELCH)
            message in response to receiver NACK repair requests, the use of
            the CIO provides an additional means for receivers to learn of
            objects for which it is futile to request repair;</t>

            <t>The TOI equivalence (<xref target="object_id"></xref>) can be
            signaled with the CIO. This is often preferable to the alternative
            solution where the equivalence is identified by examining the
            object meta-data, especially in case of erasures.</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>During idle periods, when the carousel instance does not contain
        any object, a CIO with an empty TOI list MAY be transmitted. In that
        case, a new carousel instance ID MUST be used to differentiate this
        (empty) carousel instance from the other ones. This mechanism can be
        useful to inform the receivers that: <list style="symbols">
            <t>all the previously sent objects have been removed from the
            carousel. It therefore improves the FCAST robustness even during
            "idle" period;</t>

            <t>the session is still active even if there is currently no
            content being sent. Said differently, it can be used as a
            heartbeat mechanism. If the "Complete" flag has not been set, it
            implicitly informs the receivers that new objects MAY be sent in
            the future;</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>The decisions of whether a CIO should be used or not, how often and
        when a CIO should be sent, are left to the sender and depend on many
        parameters, including the target use case and the session dynamics.
        For instance it may be appropriate to send a CIO at the beginning of
        each new carousel instance, and then periodically. These operational
        aspects are out of the scope of the present document.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="object_id" title="Compound Object Identification">
        <!-- ==================================== -->

        <t>The FCAST Compound Objects are directly associated with the
        object-based transport service that the ALC and NORM protocols
        provide. In each of these protocols, the messages containing transport
        object content are labeled with a numeric transport object identifier
        (i.e., the ALC TOI and the NORM NormTransportId). For the purposes of
        this document, this identifier in either case (ALC or NORM) is
        referred to as the TOI.<!--
        The FCAST Compound Object Header
        meta-data can include an attribute that identifies the given object's
        TOI. Additionally, the CIO lists objects for the applicable Carousel
        Instance by using the TOI.
        --></t>

        <t>There are several differences between ALC and NORM: <list
            style="symbols">
            <t>the ALC use of TOI is rather flexible, since several TOI field
            sizes are possible (from 16 to 112 bits), since this size can be
            changed at any time, on a per-packet basis, and since the TOI
            management is totally free as long as each object is associated to
            a unique TOI (if no wraparound happened);</t>

            <t>the NORM use of TOI is more directive, since the TOI field is
            16 bit long and since TOIs MUST be managed sequentially;</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>In both NORM and ALC, it is possible that the transport
        identification space may eventually wrap for long-lived sessions
        (especially with NORM where this phenomenon is expected to happen more
        frequently). This can possibly introduce some ambiguity in FCAST
        object identification if a sender retains some older objects in newer
        Carousel Instances with updated object sets. Thus, when an updated
        object set, for a new Carousel Instance, would transport identifiers
        that exceed one-half of the TOI sequence space (or otherwise exceed
        the sender repair window capability in the case of NORM), it MAY be
        necessary to re-enqueue old objects within the Carousel with new TOI
        to stay within transport identifier limits. In case of NORM, this
        constraint limits to 32768 the maximum number of objects that can be
        part of any carousel instance. In order to allow receivers to properly
        combine the transport packets with a newly-assigned TOI to those of
        associated to the previously-assigned TOI, a mechanism is required to
        equate the objects with the new and the old TOIs.</t>

        <t>The preferred mechanism consists in signaling, within the CIO, that
        the newly assigned TOI, for the current Carousel Instance, is
        equivalent to the TOI used within a previous Carousel Instance. By
        convention, the reference tuple for any object is the {TOI; CI ID}
        tuple used for its first transmission within a Carousel Instance. This
        tuple MUST be used whenever a TOI equivalence is provided.</t>

        <t>An alternative solution, when meta-data can be processed rapidly
        (e.g., by using NORM-INFO messages), consists for the receiver in
        identifying that both objects are the same, after examining the
        meta-data. The receiver can then take appropriate measures.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="alc_specifics"
               title="FCAST/ALC Additional Specificities">
        <!-- ==================================== -->

        <t>There are no additional detail or option for FCAST/ALC
        operation.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="norm_specifics"
               title="FCAST/NORM Additional Specificities">
        <!-- ==================================== -->

        <t>The NORM Protocol provides a few additional capabilities that can
        be used to specifically support FCAST operation:</t>

        <t><list style="numbers">
            <t>The NORM_INFO message can convey "out-of-band" content with
            respect to a given transport object. With FCAST, it MAY be used to
            provide to the receivers a new, associated, Compound Object which
            contains the main Compound Object meta-data, or a subset of it.
            In that case the NORM_INFO Compound Object MUST NOT contain any
            Object Data field (i.e., it is only
            composed of the header), it MUST feature a non global checksum, and
            it MUST NOT include any padding field. The main Compound
            Object MUST in any case contain the whole meta-data (e.g., because
            a receiver MAY not support the NORM_INFO facility). Additionally, the
            meta-data entries contained in the NORM_INFO MUST be identical to
            the same entries in the main Compound Object. Finally, note that
            the availability of NORM_INFO for a given object is signaled
            through the use of a dedicated flag in the NORM_DATA message
            header. Along with NORM's NACK-based repair request signaling, it
            allows a receiver to quickly (and independently) request an
            object's NORM_INFO content. However, a limitation here is that the
            NORM_INFO Compound Object header MUST fit within the byte size
            limit defined by the NORM sender's configured "segment size"
            (typically a little less than the network MTU);</t>

            <t>The NORM_CMD(SQUELCH) messages are used by the NORM protocol
            sender to inform receivers of objects that have been canceled when
            receivers make repair requests for such invalid objects. Along
            with the CIO mechanism, a receiver has two efficient and reliable
            ways to discover old objects that have been removed from the
            carousel instance;</t>

            <t>NORM also supports an optional positive acknowledgment
            mechanism that can be used for small-scale multicast receiver
            group sizes. Also, it may be possible in some cases for the sender
            to infer, after some period without receiving NACKs at the end of
            its transmission that the receiver set has fully received the
            transmitted content. In particular, if the sender completes its
            end-of-transmission series of NORM_CMD(FLUSH) messages without
            receiving repair requests from the group, it may have some
            assurance that the receiver set has received the content prior to
            that point. These mechanisms are likely to help FCAST in achieving
            fully reliable transmissions;</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>It should be noted that the NORM_INFO message header may carry
        the EXT_FTI extension. The reliable delivery of the NORM_INFO content
        allows the individual objects' FEC Transmission Information to be
        provided to the receivers without burdening every packet (i.e.
        NORM_DATA messages) with this additional, but important, content.
        Examples are provided in <xref target="fcast_exple"></xref>.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="sender_behavior" title="FCAST Sender Behavior">
        <!-- ==================================== -->

        <t>The following operations MAY take place at a sender: <list
            style="numbers">
            <t>The user (or another application) selects a set of objects
            (e.g., files) to deliver and submits them, along with their
            meta-data, to the FCAST application;</t>

            <t>For each object, FCAST creates the Compound Object and
            registers this latter in the carousel instance;</t>

            <t>The user then informs FCAST that all the objects of the set
            have been submitted. If the user knows that no new object will be
            submitted in the future (i.e., if the session's content is now
            complete), the user informs FCAST. Finally, the user specifies how
            many transmission cycles are desired (this number may be
            infinite);</t>

            <t>At this point, the FCAST application knows the full list of
            Compound Objects that are part of the Carousel Instance and can
            create a CIO if desired, possibly with the complete flag set;</t>

            <t>The FCAST application can now define a transmission schedule of
            these Compound Objects, including the optional CIO. This schedule
            defines in which order the packets of the various Compound Objects
            should be sent. This document does not specify any scheme. This is
            left to the developer within the provisions of the underlying ALC
            or NORM protocol used and the knowledge of the target
            use-case.</t>

            <t>The FCAST application then starts the carousel transmission,
            for the number of cycles specified. Transmissions take place
            until: <list style="symbols">
                <t>the desired number of transmission cycles has been reached,
                or</t>

                <t>the user wants to prematurely stop the transmissions,
                or</t>

                <t>the user wants to add one or several new objects to the
                carousel, or on the opposite wants to remove old objects from
                the carousel. In that case a new carousel instance must be
                created.</t>
              </list></t>

            <t>If the session is not finished, then continue as Set 1
            above;</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="receiver_behavior" title="FCAST Receiver Behavior">
        <!-- ==================================== -->

        <t>The following operations MAY take place at a receiver: <list
            style="numbers">
            <t>The receiver joins the session and collects incoming
            packets;</t>

            <t>If the header portion of a Compound Object is entirely received
            (which may happen before receiving the entire object with some
            ALC/NORM configurations), or if the meta-data is sent by means of
            another mechanism prior to the object, the receiver processes the
            meta-data and chooses to continue to receive the object content or
            not;</t>

            <t>When a Compound Object has been entirely received, the receiver
            processes the header, retrieves the object meta-data, perhaps
            decodes the meta-data, and processes the object accordingly;</t>

            <t>When a CIO is received, which is indicated by the 'I' flag set
            in the Compound Object header, the receiver decodes the CIO, and
            retrieves the list of objects that are part of the current
            carousel instance. This list CAN be used to remove objects sent in
            a previous carousel instance that might not have been totally
            decoded and that are no longer part of the current carousel
            instance;</t>

            <t>When a CIO is received, the receiver also retrieves the list of
            TOI equivalences, if any, and takes appropriate measures, for
            instance by informing the transport layer;</t>

            <t>When a receiver has received a CIO with the "Complete" flag
            set, and has successfully received all the objects of the current
            carousel instance, it can safely exit from the current FCAST
            session;</t>

            <t>Otherwise continue at Step 2 above.</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="fcast_specifications" title="FCAST Specifications">
      <!-- ==================================== -->

      <t>This section details the technical aspects of FCAST.</t>

      <section anchor="header_format" title="Compound Object Header Format">
        <!-- ==================================== -->

        <t>In an FCAST session, Compound Objects are constructed by prepending
        the Compound Object Header (which may include meta-data) before the
        original object data content (<xref
        target="header_with_md_format"></xref>).</t>

        <figure anchor="header_with_md_format"
                title="Compound Object Header with Meta-Data.">
          <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+  ^
|rsv|G|C|MDF|MDE|                 Header Length                 |  |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+  |
|            Checksum           |                               |  h
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+                               |  d
|         Object Meta-Data (optional, variable length)          |  r
|                               +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+  |
|                               |      Padding (optional)       |  |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+  v
|                                                               |
.          Object Data (optional, variable length)              .
.                                                               .
.                                                               .]]></artwork>
        </figure>

        <t>The Compound Object Header fields are:</t>

        <texttable>
          <ttcol align="right" width="15%">Field</ttcol>

          <ttcol align="left">Description</ttcol>

          <c>Reserved</c>

          <c>2-bit field set to 0 in this specification and reserved for
          future use.</c>

          <c>G</c>

          <c>1-bit field that, when set to 1, indicates that the checksum
          encompasses the whole Compound Object (Global checksum). When set to
          0, this field indicates that the checksum encompasses only the
          Compound Object header.</c>

          <c>C</c>

          <c>1-bit field that, when set to 1, indicates the object is a
          Carousel Instance Object (CIO). When set to 0, this field indicates
          that the transported object is a standard object.</c>

          <c>Meta-Data Format (MDFmt)</c>

          <c>2-bit field that defines the format of the object meta-data (see
          <xref target="iana"></xref>). An HTTP/1.1 metainformation format
          <xref target="RFC2068"></xref> MUST be supported and is associated
          to value 0. Other formats (e.g., XML) MAY be defined in the
          future.</c>

          <c>Meta-Data Encoding (MDEnc)</c>

          <c>2-bit field that defines the optional encoding of the Object
          Meta-Data field (see <xref target="iana"></xref>). By default, a
          plain text encoding is used and is associated to value 0. Gzip
          encoding MUST also be supported and is associated to value 1. Other
          encodings MAY be defined in the future.</c>

          <c>Header Length</c>

          <c>24-bit field indicating total length (in bytes) of all fields of
          the Compound Object Header, except the optional padding. A header
          length field set to value 6 means that there is no meta-data
          included. When this size is not multiple to 32-bits words and when
          the Compound Object Header is followed by a non null Compound Object Data,
          padding MUST be added. It should be noted that the meta-data field maximum
          size is equal to 2^24 - 6 bytes.</c>

          <c>Checksum</c>

          <c>16-bit field that contains the checksum computed over either the
          whole Compound Object (when G is set to 1), or over the Compound
          Object header (when G is set to 0), using the algorithm specified
          for TCP in RFC793. More precisely, the checksum field is the 16-bit
          one's complement of the one's complement sum of all 16-bit words to
          be considered. If a segment contains an odd number of octets to be
          checksummed, the last octet is padded on the right with zeros to
          form a 16-bit word for checksum purposes (this pad is not
          transmitted). While computing the checksum, the checksum field
          itself is set to zero.</c>

          <c>Object Meta-Data</c>

          <c>Optional, variable length field that contains the meta-data
          associated to the object, either in plain text or encoded, as
          specified by the MDEnc field. The Meta-Data is NULL-terminated plain
          text that follows the "TYPE" ":" "VALUE" "&lt;CR-LF&gt;" format used
          in HTTP/1.1 for metainformation <xref target="RFC2068"></xref>. The
          various meta-data items can appear in any order. The associated
          string, when non empty, MUST be NULL-terminated. When no meta-data
          is communicated, this field MUST be empty and the Header Length MUST
          be equal to 6.</c>

          <c>Padding</c>

          <c>Optional, variable length field of zero-value bytes to align the
          start of the Object Data to 32-bit boundary. Padding is only
          used when the header length value, in bytes, is not multiple of
          4 and when the Compound Object Header is followed by a non null
          Compound Object Data.</c>
        </texttable>

        <t>The Compound Object Header is then followed by the Object Data,
        i.e., the original object possibly encoded by FCAST. Note that the
        length of this content is the transported object length (e.g., as
        specified by the FEC OTI) minus the Header Length and optional padding
        if any.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="carousel_instance_object"
               title="Carousel Instance Object Format">
        <!-- ==================================== -->

        <t>The format of the CIO, which is a particular Compound Object, is
        given in <xref target="cio_format"></xref>.</t>

        <figure anchor="cio_format" title="Carousel Instance Object Format.">
          <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+  ^
|rsv|G|1|MDF|MDE|                 Header Length                 |  |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+  |
|            Checksum           |                               |  h
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+                               |  d
|         Object Meta-Data (optional, variable length)          |  r
|                               +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+  |
|                               |      Padding (optional)       |  |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+  v
.                                                               .  ^
.                Object List (variable length)                  .  |
.                                                               .  o
.                                               +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+  b
.                                               |                  j
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+                  v ]]></artwork>
        </figure>

        <t>Because the CIO is transmitted as a special Compound Object, the
        following CIO-specific meta-data entries are defined: <list
            style="symbols">
            <t>Fcast-CIO-Complete: when set to 1, it indicates that no new
            objects in addition to the ones whose TOI are specified in this
            CIO, or the ones that have been specified in the previous CIO(s),
            will be sent in the future. Otherwise it MUST be set to 0. This
            entry is optional. If absent, a receiver MUST conclude that the
            session is complete.</t>

            <t>Fcast-CIO-ID: this value identifies the carousel instance. It
            starts from 0 and is incremented by 1 for each new carousel
            instance. This entry is optional if the FCAST session consists of
            a single, complete, carousel instance. In all other cases, this
            entry MUST be defined. In particular, the CIID is used by the TOI
            equivalence mechanism thanks to which any object is uniquely
            identified, even if the TOI is updated (e.g., after re-enqueuing
            the object with NORM). The Fcast-CIO-ID value can also be useful
            to detect possible gaps in the Carousel Instances, for instance
            caused by long disconnection periods. Finally, it can also be
            useful to avoid problems when TOI wrapping to 0 takes place to
            differentiate the various incarnations of the TOIs if need be.</t>
          </list> The motivation for making the Fcast-CIO-Complete and
        Fcast-CIO-Complete entries optional is to simplify the simple case of
        a session consisting of a single, complete, carousel instance. Indeed,
        the CIO does not need to contain any meta-data entry then.</t>

        <t>Additionally, the following standard meta-data entries are often
        used (<xref target="meta-data_content"></xref>): <list style="symbols">
            <t>Content-Length: it specifies the size of the object list,
            before any content encoding (if any).</t>

            <t>Content-Encoding: it specifies the optional encoding of the
            object list, performed by FCAST. For instance: <figure>
                <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[        Content-Encoding: gzip  ]]></artwork>
              </figure> indicates that the Object List field has been encoded
            with gzip <xref target="RFC1952"></xref>. If there is no
            Content-Encoding entry, the receiver MUST assume that the Object
            List field is plain text (default). The support of gzip encoding,
            or any other solution, remains optional.</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>An empty Object List is valid and indicates that the current
        carousel instance does not include any object (<xref
        target="cio"></xref>). This can be specified by using the following
        meta-data entry: <figure>
            <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[        Content-Length: 0  ]]></artwork>
          </figure> or simply by leaving the Object List empty. In both
        cases, padding MUST NOT be used and consequently the transported object
        length (e.g., as specified by the FEC OTI) minus the Header Length equals
        zero.</t>

        <t>The non-encoded (i.e., plain text) Object List, when non empty, is
        a NULL-terminated ASCII string. It can contain two things: <list
            style="symbols">
            <t>a list of TOI values, and</t>

            <t>a list of TOI equivalences;</t>
          </list> First of all, this string can contain the list of TOIs
        included in the current carousel instance, specified either as the
        individual TOIs of each object, or as TOI intervals, or any
        combination. The format of the ASCII string is a comma-separated list
        of individual "TOI" values or "TOI_a-TOI_b" elements. This latter case
        means that all values between TOI_a and TOI_b, inclusive, are part of
        the list. In that case TOI_a MUST be strictly inferior to TOI_b. If a
        TOI wrapping to 0 occurs in an interval, then two TOI intervals MUST
        be specified, TOI_a-MAX_TOI and 0-TOI_b.</t>

        <t>This string can also contain the TOI equivalences, if any. The
        format is a comma-separated list of "(" newTOI "=" 1stTOI "/" 1stCIID
        ")" elements. Each element says that the new TOI, for the current
        Carousel Instance, is equivalent to (i.e., refers to the same object
        as) the provided identifier, 1stTOI, for the Carousel Instance of ID
        1stCIID.</t>

        <t>The ABNF specification is the following:</t>

        <figure>
          <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[cio-list   =  *(list-elem *( "," list-elem))
list-elem    =  toi-elem / toieq-elem
toi-elem     =  toi-value / toi-interval
toi-value    =  1*DIGIT
toi-interval =  toi-value "-" toi-value
                ; additionally, the first toi-value MUST be
                ; strictly inferior to the second toi-value
toieq-elem   =  "(" toi-value "=" toi-value "/" ciid-value ")"
ciid-value   = 1*DIGIT
DIGIT        =  %x30-39
                ; a digit between O and 9, inclusive]]></artwork>
        </figure>

        <t>For readability purposes, it is RECOMMENDED that all the TOI values
        in the list be given in increasing order. However a receiver MUST be
        able to handle non-monotonically increasing values. It is also
        RECOMMENDED to group the TOI equivalence elements together, at the end
        of the list, in increasing newTOI order. However a receiver MUST be
        able to handle lists of mixed TOI and TOI equivalence elements.
        Specifying a TOI equivalence for a given newTOI relieves the sender
        from specifying newTOI explicitly in the TOI list. However a receiver
        MUST be able to handle situations where the same TOI appears both in
        the TOI value and TOI equivalence lists. Finally, a given TOI value or
        TOI equivalence item MUST NOT be included multiple times in either
        list.</t>

        <t>For instance, the following object list specifies that the current
        Carousel Instance is composed of 8 objects, and that TOIs 100 to 104
        are equivalent to the TOIs 10 to 14 of Carousel Instance ID 2 and
        refer to the same objects:</t>

        <figure>
          <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[
97,98,99,(100=10/2),(101=11/2),(102=12/2),(103=13/2),(104=14/2)
  ]]></artwork>
        </figure>

        <t>or equivalently:</t>

        <figure>
          <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[
97-104,(100=10/2),(101=11/2),(102=12/2),(103=13/2),(104=14/2)
  ]]></artwork>
        </figure>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="security" title="Security Considerations">
      <!-- ==================================== -->

      <!-- XXX: this section is taken from FLUTE. It is therefore very ALC centric... -->

      <section anchor="pb_statement" title="Problem Statement">
        <!-- ==================================== -->

        <t>A content delivery system is potentially subject to attacks.
        Attacks may target: <list style="symbols">
            <t>the network (to compromise the routing infrastructure, e.g., by
            creating congestion),</t>

            <t>the Content Delivery Protocol (CDP) (e.g., to compromise the
            normal behavior of FCAST), or</t>

            <t>the content itself (e.g., to corrupt the objects being
            transmitted).</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>These attacks can be launched either: <list style="symbols">
            <t>against the data flow itself (e.g., by sending forged
            packets),</t>

            <t>against the session control parameters (e.g., by corrupting the
            session description, the CIO, the object meta-data, or the ALC/LCT
            control parameters), that are sent either in-band or out-of-band,
            or</t>

            <t>against some associated building blocks (e.g., the congestion
            control component).</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>In the following sections we provide more details on these possible
        attacks and sketch some possible counter-measures.
        We finally provide recommendations in <xref target="min-sec-recommendations"/>.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="attacks_against_data"
               title="Attacks Against the Data Flow">
        <!-- ==================================== -->

        <t>Let us consider attacks against the data flow first. At least, the
        following types of attacks exist: <list style="symbols">
            <t>attacks that are meant to give access to a confidential object
            (e.g., in case of a non-free content) and</t>

            <t>attacks that try to corrupt the object being transmitted (e.g.,
            to inject malicious code within an object, or to prevent a
            receiver from using an object, which is a kind of Denial of
            Service (DoS)).</t>
          </list></t>

        <section anchor="access_to_confidential_obj"
                 title="Access to Confidential Objects">
          <!-- ==================================== -->

          <t>Access control to the object being transmitted is typically
          provided by means of encryption. This encryption can be done over
          the whole object (e.g., by the content provider, before submitting
          the object to FCAST), or be done on a packet per packet basis (e.g.,
          when IPSec/ESP is used <xref target="RFC4303"></xref>, see
          <xref target="min-sec-recommendations"/>).
          If confidentiality is a concern, it is RECOMMENDED that one of these
          solutions be used.</t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="obj_corruption" title="Object Corruption">
          <!-- ==================================== -->

          <t>Protection against corruptions (e.g., if an attacker sends forged
          packets) is achieved by means of a content integrity verification/sender
          authentication scheme. This service can be provided at the object
          level, but in that case a receiver has no way to identify which
          symbol(s) is(are) corrupted if the object is detected as corrupted.
          This service can also be provided at the packet level. In this case,
          after removing all corrupted packets, the file may be in some cases
          recovered. Several techniques can provide this content
          integrity/sender authentication service: <list style="symbols">
              <t>at the object level, the object can be digitally signed,
              for instance by using RSASSA-PKCS1-v1_5 <xref target="RFC3447"></xref>.
              This signature enables a receiver to check the object integrity, once this
              latter has been fully decoded. Even if digital signatures are
              computationally expensive, this calculation occurs only once per
              object, which is usually acceptable;</t>

              <t>at the packet level, each packet can be digitally signed <xref target="RMT-SIMPLE-AUTH"/>.
              A major limitation is the high computational and transmission
              overheads that this solution requires. To avoid this
              problem, the signature may span a set of packets (instead of a
              single one) in order to amortize the signature calculation. But
              if a single packets is missing, the integrity of the whole set
              cannot be checked;</t>

              <t>at the packet level, a Group Message Authentication Code
              (MAC) <xref target="RFC2104"></xref><xref target="RMT-SIMPLE-AUTH"/>
              scheme can be used, for
              instance by using HMAC-SHA-256 with a secret key shared by all the
              group members, senders and receivers. This technique creates a
              cryptographically secured digest of a packet that is sent along
              with the packet. The Group MAC scheme does not create
              prohibitive processing load nor transmission overhead, but it
              has a major limitation: it only provides a group
              authentication/integrity service since all group members share
              the same secret group key, which means that each member can send
              a forged packet. It is therefore restricted to situations where
              group members are fully trusted (or in association with another
              technique as a pre-check);</t>

              <t>at the packet level, Timed Efficient Stream Loss-Tolerant
              Authentication (TESLA) <xref target="RFC4082"/><xref target="MSEC-TESLA"/>
              is an attractive solution that is robust to losses, provides a true
              authentication/integrity service, and does not create any
              prohibitive processing load or transmission overhead. Yet
              checking a packet requires a small delay (a second or more)
              after its reception;</t>

              <t> at the packet level, IPsec/ESP <xref target="RFC4303"/>
              can be used to check the integrity and authenticate the sender
              of all the packets being exchanged in a session
              (see <xref target="min-sec-recommendations"/>).</t> 
            </list></t>

          <t>Techniques relying on public key cryptography (digital signatures
          and TESLA during the bootstrap process, when used) require that
          public keys be securely associated to the entities. This can be
          achieved by a Public Key Infrastructure (PKI), or by a PGP Web of
          Trust, or by pre-distributing securely the public keys of each group
          member.</t>

          <t>Techniques relying on symmetric key cryptography (Group MAC)
          require that a secret key be shared by all group members. This can
          be achieved by means of a group key management protocol, or simply
          by pre-distributing securely the secret key (but this manual
          solution has many limitations).</t>

          <t>It is up to the developer and deployer, who know the security
          requirements and features of the target application area, to define
          which solution is the most appropriate. In any case, whenever there
          is any concern of the threat of file corruption, it is RECOMMENDED
          that at least one of these techniques be used.</t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section anchor="attack_against_ctrl_param"
               title="Attacks Against the Session Control Parameters and Associated Building Blocks">
        <!-- ==================================== -->

        <t>Let us now consider attacks against the session control parameters
        and the associated building blocks. The attacker has at least the
        following opportunities to launch an attack: <list style="symbols">
            <t>the attack can target the session description,</t>

            <t>the attack can target the FCAST CIO,</t>

            <t>the attack can target the meta-data of an object,</t>

            <t>the attack can target the ALC/LCT parameters, carried within
            the LCT header or</t>

            <t>the attack can target the FCAST associated building blocks,
            for instance the multiple rate congestion control protocol.</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>The consequences of these attacks are potentially serious, since
        they can compromise the behavior of content delivery system or even
        compromise the network itself.</t>

        <section anchor="attack_against_sdp"
                 title="Attacks Against the Session Description">
          <!-- ==================================== -->

          <t>An FCAST receiver may potentially obtain an incorrect Session
          Description for the session. The consequence of this is that
          legitimate receivers with the wrong Session Description are unable
          to correctly receive the session content, or that receivers
          inadvertently try to receive at a much higher rate than they are
          capable of, thereby possibly disrupting other traffic in the
          network.</t>

          <t>To avoid these problems, it is RECOMMENDED that measures be taken
          to prevent receivers from accepting incorrect Session Descriptions.
          One such measure is the sender authentication to ensure that
          receivers only accept legitimate Session Descriptions from
          authorized senders. How these measures are achieved is outside the
          scope of this document since this session description is usually
          carried out-of-band.</t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="attack_against_cio"
                 title="Attacks Against the FCAST CIO">
          <!-- ==================================== -->

          <t>Corrupting the FCAST CIO is one way to create a Denial of Service
          attack. For example, the attacker can set the "Complete" flag to
          make the receivers believe that no further modification will be
          done.</t>

          <t>It is therefore RECOMMENDED that measures be taken to guarantee
          the integrity and to check the sender's identity of the CIO. To that
          purpose, one of the counter-measures mentioned above (<xref
          target="obj_corruption"></xref>) SHOULD be used. These measures will
          either be applied on a packet level, or globally over the whole CIO
          object. When there is no packet level integrity verification scheme,
          it is RECOMMENDED to digitally sign the CIO.</t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="attack_against_meta_data"
                 title="Attacks Against the Object Meta-Data">
          <!-- ==================================== -->

          <t>Corrupting the object meta-data is another way to create a Denial
          of Service attack. For example, the attacker changes the MD5 sum
          associated to a file. This possibly leads a receiver to reject the
          files received, no matter whether the files have been correctly
          received or not. When the meta-data are appended to the object,
          corrupting the meta-data means that the Compound Object will be
          corrupted.</t>

          <t>It is therefore RECOMMENDED that measures be taken to guarantee
          the integrity and to check the sender's identity of the Compound
          Object. To that purpose, one of the counter-measures mentioned above
          (<xref target="obj_corruption"></xref>) SHOULD be used. These
          measures will either be applied on a packet level, or globally over
          the whole Compound Object. When there is no packet level integrity
          verification scheme, it is RECOMMENDED to digitally sign the
          Compound Object.</t>

          <!-- XXX: how can we digitally sign a compound object? -->
        </section>

        <section anchor="attack_against_alc"
                 title="Attacks Against the ALC/LCT and NORM Parameters">
          <!-- ==================================== -->

          <t>By corrupting the ALC/LCT header (or header extensions) one can
          execute attacks on the underlying ALC/LCT implementation. For
          example, sending forged ALC packets with the Close Session flag (A)
          set to one can lead the receiver to prematurely close the session.
          Similarly, sending forged ALC packets with the Close Object flag (B)
          set to one can lead the receiver to prematurely give up the reception
          of an object. The same comments can be made for NORM.</t>

          <t>It is therefore RECOMMENDED that measures be taken to guarantee
          the integrity and to check the sender's identity of each ALC or NORM
          packet received. To that purpose, one of the counter-measures
          mentioned above (<xref target="obj_corruption"></xref>) SHOULD be
          used.</t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="attack_against_bb"
                 title="Attacks Against the Associated Building Blocks">
          <!-- ==================================== -->

          <t>Let us first focus on the congestion control building block that
          may be used in an ALC or NORM session. A receiver with an incorrect
          or corrupted implementation of the multiple rate congestion control
          building block may affect the health of the network in the path
          between the sender and the receiver. That may also affect the
          reception rates of other receivers who joined the session.</t>

          <t>When congestion control is applied with FCAST, it is therefore
          RECOMMENDED that receivers be required to identify themselves as
          legitimate before they receive the Session Description needed to
          join the session. If authenticating a receiver does not prevent this
          latter to launch an attack, it will enable the network operator to
          identify him and to take counter-measures. This authentication can
          be made either toward the network operator or the session sender (or
          a representative of the sender) in case of NORM. The details of how
          it is done are outside the scope of this document.</t>

          <t>When congestion control is applied with FCAST, it is also
          RECOMMENDED that a packet level authentication scheme be used, as
          explained in <xref target="obj_corruption"></xref>. Some of them,
          like TESLA, only provide a delayed authentication service, whereas
          congestion control requires a rapid reaction. It is therefore
          RECOMMENDED <xref target="RMT-PI-ALC"></xref> that a receiver using
          TESLA quickly reduces its subscription level when the receiver
          believes that a congestion did occur, even if the packet has not yet
          been authenticated. Therefore TESLA will not prevent DoS attacks
          where an attacker makes the receiver believe that a congestion
          occurred. This is an issue for the receiver, but this will not
          compromise the network.
          Other authentication methods that do not feature this delayed
          authentication could be preferred, or a group MAC scheme could be
          used in parallel to TESLA to prevent attacks launched from outside
          of the group.</t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section title="Other Security Considerations">
        <!-- ==================================== -->

        <t>Lastly, we note that the security considerations that apply to, and
        are described in, ALC <xref target="RMT-PI-ALC"></xref>, LCT <xref
        target="RFC5651"></xref>, NORM <xref target="RFC5740"></xref>
        and FEC <xref target="RFC5052"></xref> also apply to FCAST as FCAST
        builds on those specifications. In addition, any security
        considerations that apply to any congestion control building block
        used in conjunction with FCAST also applies to FCAST. Finally, the
        security discussion of <xref target="RMT-SEC"></xref> also applies
        here.</t>
      </section>


      <section anchor='min-sec-recommendations' title='Minimum Security Recommendations'>
        <!-- ==================================== -->

	  <t>
	  We now introduce a mandatory to implement but not necessarily to use security configuration,
	  in the sense of <xref target="RFC3365"/>.
	  Since FCAST relies on ALC/LCT, it inherits the "baseline secure ALC operation" of <xref target="RMT-PI-ALC"/>.
	  More precisely, security is achieved by means of IPsec/ESP in transport mode.
	  <xref target='RFC4303'/> explains that ESP can be used to potentially provide confidentiality, data origin
	  authentication, content integrity, anti-replay and (limited) traffic flow confidentiality.
	  <xref target="RMT-PI-ALC"/> specifies that the data origin authentication, content integrity and
	  anti-replay services SHALL be used, and that the confidentiality service is RECOMMENDED.
	  If a short lived session MAY rely on manual keying, it is also RECOMMENDED that an automated key management
	  scheme be used, especially in case of long lived sessions.
	  </t>

	  <t>
	  Therefore, the RECOMMENDED solution for FCAST provides per-packet security, with data origin
	  authentication, integrity verification and anti-replay.
	  This is sufficient to prevent most of the in-band attacks listed above.
	  If confidentiality is required, a per-packet encryption SHOULD also be used.
	  </t>
      </section>

    </section>

    <section anchor="iana" title="IANA Considerations">
      <!-- ==================================== -->

      <t>This document requires a IANA registration for the following
      attributes:</t>

      <t>Object meta-data format (MDFmt): All implementations MUST support
      format 0 (default).</t>

      <texttable>
        <preamble></preamble>

        <ttcol align="center">format name</ttcol>

        <ttcol align="center">Value</ttcol>

        <c>as per HTTP/1.1 metainformation format</c>

        <c>0 (default)</c>
      </texttable>

      <t>Object Meta-Data Encoding (MDENC): All implementations MUST support
      value 0 (plain-text, default) and value 1 (gzip).</t>

      <texttable>
        <preamble></preamble>

        <ttcol align="center">Name</ttcol>

        <ttcol align="center">Value</ttcol>

        <c>plain text</c>

        <c>0 (default)</c>

        <c>gzip</c>

        <c>1</c>
      </texttable>
    </section>

    <section title="Acknowledgments">
      <!-- ==================================== -->

      <t>The authors are grateful to the authors of <xref
      target="ALC-00"></xref> for specifying the first version of FCAST/ALC.
      The authors are also grateful to Gorry Fairhurst for his valuable
      comments.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <!-- ==================================== -->

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.2119'?>
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.5651'?>
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.5740'?>

      <reference anchor="RMT-PI-ALC">
        <front>
          <title>Asynchronous Layered Coding (ALC) Protocol
          Instantiation</title>

          <author initials="M." surname="Luby">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author initials="M." surname="Watson">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author initials="L." surname="Vicisano">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date month="November" year="2009" />
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="Work in" value="Progress" />
      </reference>

    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <!-- ==================================== -->

      <reference anchor="ALC-00">
        <front>
          <title>Asynchronous Layered Coding: a Scalable Reliable Multicast
          Protocol</title>

          <author initials="M." surname="Luby">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author initials="G." surname="Gemmell">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author initials="L." surname="Vicisano">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author initials="J." surname="Crowcroft">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author initials="B." surname="Lueckenhoff">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date month="March" year="2000" />
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RMT-FLUTE">
        <front>
          <title>FLUTE - File Delivery over Unidirectional Transport</title>

          <author initials="T." surname="Paila">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author initials="R." surname="Walsh">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author initials="M." surname="Luby">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author initials="V." surname="Roca">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author initials="R." surname="Lehtonen">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date month="December" year="2009" />
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="Work in" value="Progress" />
      </reference>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.3365'?>

      <reference anchor="RMT-SEC">
        <front>
          <title>Security and Reliable Multicast Transport Protocols:
          Discussions and Guidelines</title>

          <author initials="V." surname="Roca">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author initials="B." surname="Adamson">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author initials="H." surname="Asaeda">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date month="July" year="2009" />
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="Work in progress, "
                    value="draft-ietf-rmt-sec-discussion-04.txt" />
      </reference>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.1952'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.2068'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.2104'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.3447'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.4082'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.4303'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.5052'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.5510'?>


      <reference anchor="MSEC-TESLA">
	<front>
		<title>Use of TESLA in the ALC and NORM Protocols</title>
		<author initials="V." surname="Roca" fullname="V. Roca">
			<organization/></author>
		<author initials="A." surname="Francillon" fullname="A. Francillon">
			<organization/></author>
		<author initials="S." surname="Faurite" fullname="S. Faurite">
			<organization/></author>
		<date year="2009" month="October"/>
	</front>
	<seriesInfo name="" value="draft-ietf-msec-tesla-for-alc-norm-10.txt (work in progress)"/>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RMT-SIMPLE-AUTH">
        <front>
          <title>Simple Authentication Schemes for the ALC and NORM Protocols</title>
          <author initials='V.' surname='Roca'> <organization /></author>
          <date month="October" year="2009"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="" value="draft-ietf-rmt-simple-auth-for-alc-norm-02.txt (work in progress)"/>
      </reference>

    </references>

    <section anchor="fcast_exple" title="FCAST Examples">
      <!-- ==================================== -->

      <section title="Basic Examples">
        <!-- ==================================== -->

        <figure anchor="expl_object" title="Compound Object Example.">
          <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[ 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
| 0 |1|0| 0 | 0 |                   39                          |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|            Checksum           |                               |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+                               |
.                                                               .
.       meta-data ASCII null terminated string (33 bytes)       .
.                                                               .
+                                               +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                                               |    Padding    |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
.                                                               .
.                         Object data                           .
.                                                               .
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+]]></artwork>
        </figure>

        <t><xref target="expl_object"></xref> shows a regular Compound Object
        where the meta-data ASCII string, in HTTP/1.1 meta-information format
        (MDFmt=0) contains:</t>

        <figure>
          <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[
Content-Location: example.txt <CR-LF>
  ]]></artwork>
        </figure>

        <t>This string is 33 bytes long, including the NULL-termination
        character. There is no gzip encoding of the meta-data (MDEnc=0) and
        there is no Content-Length information either since this length can
        easily be calculated by the receiver as the FEC OTI transfer length
        minus the header length. Finally, the checksum encompasses the whole
        Compound Object (G=1).</t>

        <figure anchor="expl_no_meta-data"
                title="Compound Object Example with no Meta-Data.">
          <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[ 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
| 0 |1|0| 0 | 0 |                    6                          |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|            Checksum           |            Padding            |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
.                                                               .
.                         Object data                           .
.                                                               .
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+]]></artwork>
        </figure>

        <t><xref target="expl_no_meta-data"></xref> shows a Compound Object
        without any meta-data. The fact there is no meta-data is indicated by
        the value 6 of the Header Length field.</t>

        <t><xref target="expl_cio"></xref> shows an example CIO object, in the
        case of a static FCAST session, i.e., a session where the set of
        objects is set once and for all.</t>

        <figure align="center" anchor="expl_cio"
                title="Example of CIO, in case of a static session.">
          <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[ 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|  0  |1| 0 | 0 |                4                              |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
.                                                               .
.                Object List string                             .
.                                                               .
.                                               +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
.                                               |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+]]></artwork>
        </figure>

        <t>The object list contains the following string:</t>

        <figure>
          <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[
1,2,3,100-104,200-203,299
  ]]></artwork>
        </figure>

        <t>There are therefore a total of 3+5+4+1 = 13 objects in the carousel
        instance, and therefore in the FCAST session. There is no meta-data
        associated to this CIO. The session being static and composed of a
        single Carousel Instance, the sender did not feel the necessity to
        carry a Carousel Instance ID meta-data.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="FCAST/NORM with NORM_INFO Examples">
        <!-- ==================================== -->

        <t>In case of FCAST/NORM, the FCAST Compound Object meta-data
        (or a subset of it) can be carried as part of a NORM_INFO message,
        as a new Compound Object that does not contain any Compound Object
        Data. In the following example we assume that the whole meta-data
        is carried in such a message for a certain Compound Object. <xref
        target="expl_norm_info"></xref> shows an example NORM_INFO message
        that contains the FCAST Compound Object Header and meta-data as its
        payload. In this example, the first 16 bytes are the NORM_INFO base
        header, the next 12 bytes are a NORM EXT_FTI header extension
        containing the FEC Object Transport Information for the associated
        object, and the remaining bytes are the FCAST Compound Object Header
        and meta-data. Note that "padding" MUST NOT be used and that the
        FCAST checksum only encompasses the Compound Object Header (G=0).</t>

        <figure align="center" anchor="expl_norm_info"
                title="NORM_INFO containing FCAST Compound Object Header">
          <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[0                   1                   2                   3
0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+   
|version| type=1|  hdr_len = 7  |          sequence             |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                           source_id                           |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|          instance_id          |     grtt      |backoff| gsize |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|     flags     |  fec_id = 5   |     object_transport_id       |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|   HET = 64    |    HEL = 3    |                               |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+                               +
|                      Transfer Length (L)                      |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|   Encoding Symbol Length (E)  | MaxBlkLen (B) |     max_n     |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
| 0 |0|0| 0 | 0 |                   39                          |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|            Checksum           |                               |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+                               +
.                                                               .
.       meta-data ASCII null terminated string (33 bytes)       .
.                                                               .
+                                               +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                                               |  
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+]]></artwork>
        </figure>

        <t>The NORM_INFO message shown in <xref
        target="expl_norm_info"></xref> contains the EXT_FTI header extension
        to carry the FEC OTI. In this example, the FEC OTI format is that of
        the Reed-Solomon FEC coding scheme for fec_id = 5 as described in
        <xref target="RFC5510"></xref>. Other alternatives for providing the
        FEC OTI would have been to either include it directly in the meta-data
        of the FCAST Compound Header, or to include an EXT_FTI header extension to
        all NORM_DATA packets (or a subset of them). Note that the NORM
        "Transfer_Length" is the total length of the associated FCAST Compound
        Object.
        <!-- VR: my problem is that we need to say CO header length of the
        regular Compound Object, not the NORM-INFO header length. We also
        need to substract the padding (if any) of the regular Compound Object.
        This holds even if in this particular case it turns out that the
        whole meta-data is copied in the NORM-INFO, so current wording remains
        okay. However this is misleading.
        Makes everything very complex to explain... => remove; it's clear the
        receiver must first recover the Compound Object, then remove the header.

        The actual length of the Compound Object Data is the FEC OTI
        "Transfer_Length" minus the Compound Object Header Length (39 bytes in
        this example).
        -->
        </t>

        <t>The FCAST Compound Object in this example does contain the same
        meta-data and is formatted as in the example of <xref
        target="expl_object"></xref>. With the combination of the FEC_OTI and
        the FCAST meta-data, the NORM protocol and FCAST application have all
        of the information needed to reliably receive and process the
        associated object. Indeed, the NORM protocol provides rapid (NORM_INFO has
        precedence over the associated object content), reliable delivery of
        the NORM_INFO message and its payload, the FCAST Compound Object
        Header.</t>
      </section>
    </section>
  </back>
</rfc>
