<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<rfc category="info" docName="draft-ietf-rmt-sec-discussion-05"
     ipr="pre5378Trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="Security and RMT Protocols">Security and Reliable Multicast
    Transport Protocols: Discussions and Guidelines</title>

    <author fullname="Brian Adamson" initials="B." surname="Adamson">
      <organization>Naval Research Laboratory</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>

          <city>Washington, DC</city>

          <code>20375</code>

          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>

        <email>adamson@itd.nrl.navy.mil</email>

        <uri>http://cs.itd.nrl.navy.mil</uri>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Vincent Roca" initials="V." surname="Roca">
      <organization>INRIA</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>

          <city>Montbonnot</city>

          <code>38334</code>

          <country>France</country>
        </postal>

        <email>vincent.roca@inria.fr</email>

        <uri>http://planete.inrialpes.fr/~roca/</uri>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Hitoshi Asaeda" initials="H" surname="Asaeda">
      <organization>Keio University</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <!--	  <street>Graduate School of Media and Governance</street>-->

          <street>5322 Endo</street>

          <city>Fujisawa</city>

          <region>Kanagawa</region>

          <code>252-8520</code>

          <country>Japan</country>
        </postal>

        <email>asaeda@wide.ad.jp</email>

        <uri>http://www.sfc.wide.ad.jp/~asaeda/</uri>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date day="10" month="May" year="2010" />

    <area>Transport</area>

    <workgroup>RMT</workgroup>

    <keyword>security analysis</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>This document describes general security considerations for the
      Reliable Multicast Transport (RMT) Working Group set of building blocks
      and protocols. An emphasis is placed on risks that might be resolved in
      the scope of transport protocol design. However, relevant security
      issues related to IP Multicast control-plane and other concerns not
      strictly within the scope of reliable transport protocol design are also
      discussed. The document also begins an exploration of approaches that
      could be embraced to mitigate these risks. The purpose of this document
      is to provide a consolidated security discussion and provide a basis for
      further discussions and potential resolution of any significant security
      issues that may exist in the current set of RMT standards.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section anchor="intro" title="Introduction">
      <t>The Reliable Multicast Transport (RMT) Working Group has produced a
      set of building block (BB) and protocol instantiation (PI)
      specifications for reliable multicast data transport. Some present PIs
      defined within the scope of RMT include <xref
      target="RFC5775">Asynchronous Layered Coding (ALC)</xref>, <xref
      target="RFC5740">NACK-Oriented Reliable Multicast (NORM)</xref>, and the
      <xref target="I-D.ietf-rmt-flute-revised">File Delivery over
      Unidirectional Transport (FLUTE)</xref> application that is built on top
      of ALC. These can be considered "Content Delivery Protocols" (CDP) as
      described in <xref target="Neumann05"></xref>. In this document, the
      term CDP will refer indifferently to either ALC or NORM, with their
      associated BBs.</t>

      <t>The use of these BBs and PIs raises some new security risks. For
      instance, these protocols share a novel set of Forward Error Correction
      (FEC) and congestion control building blocks that present some new
      capabilities for Internet transport, but may also pose some new security
      risks. Yet some security risks are not related to the particular BBs
      used by the PIs, but are more general. Reliable multicast transport
      sessions are expected to involve at least one sender and multiple
      receivers. Thus, the risk of and avenues to attack are implicitly
      greater than that of point-to-point (unicast) transport sessions. Also
      the nature of IP multicast can expose other coexistent network flows and
      services to risk if malicious users exploit it. The classic <xref
      target="RFC1112">Any-Source Multicast (ASM)</xref> model of multicast
      routing allows any host to join an IP multicast group and send traffic
      to that group. This poses many potential security challenges. And, while
      the emerging <xref target="RFC3569">Source-Specific Multicast
      (SSM)</xref>, <xref target="RFC4607"></xref> model that enables users to
      receive multicast data sent only from specified sender(s) simplifies
      some challenges, there are still specific issues. For instance, possible
      areas of attack include those against the control plane where malicious
      hosts join IP multicast groups to cause multicast traffic to be directed
      to parts of the network where it is not needed or desired. This may
      indirectly cause denial-of-service (DoS) to other network flows. Also,
      attackers may transmit erroneous or corrupt messages to the group or
      employ strategies such as replay attack within the "data plane" of
      protocol operation.</t>

      <t>The goals of this document are therefore to: <list style="numbers">
          <t>Define the possible general security goals: protecting the
          network infrastructure, and/or the protocol, and/or the content,
          and/or the user (e.g., its privacy);</t>

          <t>List the possible elementary security services that will make it
          possible to fulfill the general security goals. Some of these
          services are generic (e.g., object and/or packet integrity), while
          others are specific to RMT protocols (e.g., congestion control
          specific security schemes);</t>

          <t>List some technological building blocks and solutions that can
          provide the desired security services;</t>

          <t>Highlight the CDP and the use-case specificities that will impact
          security. Indeed, the set of solutions proposed to fulfill the
          security goals will greatly be impacted by these considerations;</t>
        </list> In some cases, the existing RMT documents already discuss the
      risks and outline approaches to solve them, at least partially. The
      purpose of this document is to consolidate this content and provide a
      basis for further discussion and potential resolution of any significant
      security issues that may exist.</t>

      <section title="Conventions Used in this Document">
        <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
        "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
        document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
        target="RFC2119"></xref>.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Quick Introduction to RMT Protocols and their Use">
      <section title="The Two Families of CDP">
        <t>The ALC and NORM classes of CDP are designed to reliably deliver
        content to a group of multicast receivers. However, ALC and NORM have
        a different set of features and limitations. ALC supports a
        unidirectional delivery model where there is no feedback from the
        receivers to senders. Reliability is achieved by the joint use of
        carousel-based transmission techniques associated to FEC encoding to
        recover from missing (erased) packets.</t>

        <!--
        The transmission stream can
        deliver data at different rates to different receivers, thus offering
        the potential for multirate congestion control. This allows
        scalability for delivery of bulk content to potentially very large
        group sizes.
-->

        <t>On the opposite, NORM achieves reliability by means of FEC encoding
        (as with ALC) and feedback from the receivers. More specifically, NORM
        leverages Negative Acknowledgement techniques to control the senders'
        transmission of content. The advantage is that the sender need not
        transmit any more information than necessary to satisfy the receivers'
        need for fully reliable transfers. However, while NORM specifies
        feedback control techniques to allow it to scale to large group sizes,
        it is not as massively scalable as ALC. Additionally, the NORM
        feedback control mechanisms add some header content and protocol
        implementation complexity.</t>

        <t>The appropriate choice of a CDP depends upon application needs,
        deployment constraints, and network connectivity considerations. And
        while there are many common security considerations for these two
        classes of CDP, there are also some unique considerations for
        each.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="protocolCharacteristics"
               title="RMT Protocol Characteristics">
        <t>This section focuses on the RMT protocol characteristics that
        impact the choice of the technological building blocks, and the way
        they can be applied. Both ALC and NORM have been designed with
        receiver group size scalability. While ALC targets massively scalable
        sessions (e.g., millions of receivers), NORM is less ambitious,
        essentially because of the use of feedback messages.<!--Ideally, the use of security mechanisms should not break these scalability features.--></t>

        <t>The ALC and NORM protocols also differ in the communication paths:
        <list style="symbols">
            <t>sender to receivers: ALC and NORM, for bulk data transfer and
            signaling messages;</t>

            <t>receivers to sender: NORM only, for feedback messages;</t>

            <t>receivers to receivers: NORM only for control messages;</t>
          </list> Note that the fact ALC is capable of working on top of
        purely unidirectional networks does not mean that no back-channel is
        available (<xref target="useCaseCharacteristics"></xref>).</t>

        <t>The NORM and ALC protocols support a variety of content delivery
        models where transport may be carefully coordinated among the sender
        and receivers or with looser coordination and interaction. This leads
        to a number of different use cases for these protocols.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="useCaseCharacteristics"
               title="Target Use Case Characteristics">
        <t>This section focuses on the target use cases and their special
        characteristics. These details will impact both the choice of the
        technological building blocks and the way they can be applied. One can
        distinguish the following use case features: <list style="symbols">
            <t>Purely unidirectional transport versus symmetric bidirectional
            transport versus asymmetric bidirectional transport. Most of the
            time, the amount of traffic flowing to the source is limited, and
            one can overlook whether the transport channel is symmetric or
            not. The nature of the underlying transport channel is of
            paramount importance, since many security building blocks will
            require a bidirectional communication;</t>

            <t>Massively scalable versus moderately scalable session. Here we
            do not define precisely what the terms "massively scalable" and
            "moderately scalable" mean.</t>

            <t>Known set of receivers versus unknown set of receivers: I.e.,
            does the source know at any point of time the set of receivers or
            not? Of course, knowing the set of receivers is usually not
            compatible with massively scalable sessions;</t>

            <t>Dynamic set of receivers versus fixed set of receivers: I.e.,
            does the source know at some point of time the maximum set of
            receivers or will it evolve dynamically?</t>

            <t>High rate data flow versus small rate data flow: Some security
            building blocks are CPU-intensive and are therefore incompatible
            with high data rate sessions (e.g., solutions that digitally sign
            all packets sent).</t>

            <t>Protocol stack available at both ends: A solution that requires
            some unusual features within the protocol stack will not always be
            usable. Some target environments (e.g., embedded systems) provide
            a minimum set of features and extending them (e.g., to add IPsec)
            is not necessarily realistic;</t>

            <t>Multicast routing and other layer-3 protocols in use: E.g., SSM
            routing is often seen as one of the key service to improve the
            security within multicast sessions, and some security building
            blocks require specialized versions of layer-3 protocols (e.g.,
            IGMP/MLD with security extensions). In some cases these
            assumptions might not be realistic.</t>
          </list>Depending on the target goal and the associated security
        building block used, other features might be of importance. For
        instance TESLA requires a loose time synchronization between the
        source and the receivers. Several possible techniques are available to
        provide this, but some of them may be feasible only if the target use
        case has the appropriate characteristics.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Some Security Threats">
      <t>The IP architecture provides common access to notional control and
      data planes to both end and intermediate systems. For the purposes of
      discussion here, the "control plane" mechanisms are considered those
      with message exchanges between end systems (typically computers) and
      intermediate systems (typically routers) (or among intermediate systems)
      while the "data plane" encompasses messages exchanged among end systems,
      usually pertaining to the transfer of application data. The security
      threats described here are introduced within the taxonomy of control
      plane and data plane IP mechanisms.</t>

      <section title="Control-Plane Attacks">
        <t>In this discussion, "control-plane" in the context of Internet
        Protocol systems refers to signaling among end systems and
        intermediate systems to facilitate routing and forwarding of packets.
        For IP multicast, this notably includes Internet Group Management
        Protocol (IGMP), Multicast Listener Discovery protocol (MLD), and
        multicast routing protocol messaging. While control-plane attacks may
        be considered outside of the scope of the transport protocol
        specifications discussed here, it is important to understand the
        potential impact of such attacks with respect to the deployment and
        operation of these protocols. For example, awareness of possible IP
        Multicast control-plane manipulation that can lead to unauthorized (or
        unexpected) monitoring of data plane traffic by malicious users may
        lead a transport application or protocol implementation to support
        encryption to ensure data confidentiality and/or privacy. Also, these
        types of attack also have bearing on assessing the real risks of
        potentially more complex attacks against the transport mechanisms
        themselves. In some cases, the solutions to these control-plane risk
        areas may reduce the impact or possibility of some data-plane attacks
        that are discussed in this document.</t>

        <t>The presence of these types of attack may necessitate that
        policy-based controls be embedded in routers to limit the distribution
        (including transmission and reception) of multicast traffic (on a
        group-wise and/or traffic volume basis) to different parts of the
        network. Such policy-based controls are beyond the scope of the RMT
        protocol specifications. However, such network protection mechanisms
        may reduce the opportunities for or effectiveness of some of the
        data-plane attacks discussed later. For example, reverse-path checks
        can significantly limit opportunities for attackers to conduct replay
        attacks when hosts actually do use IPsec. Also, future IP Multicast
        control protocols may wish to consider providing security mechanism to
        prevent unauthorized monitoring or manipulation of messages related to
        group membership, routing, and activity. The sections below describe
        some variants of control-plane attacks.</t>

        <section title="Control Plane Monitoring">
          <t>While this may not be a direct attack on the transport system, it
          may be possible for an attacker to gain useful information in
          advancing attack goals by monitoring IP Multicast control plane
          traffic including group membership and multicast routing
          information. Identification of hosts and/or routers participating in
          specific multicast groups may readily identify systems vulnerable to
          protocol-specific exploitation. And, with regards to user privacy
          concerns, such "side information" may be relevant to this emerging
          aspect of network security as described in <xref
          target="sec.privacy"></xref>.</t>

          <!-- [HA] Pointed a privacy section -->
        </section>

        <section anchor="sec.unauthorized_group_membership"
                 title="Unauthorized (or Malicious) Group Membership">
          <t>One of the simplest attacks is that where a malicious host joins
          an IP multicast group so that potentially unwanted traffic is routed
          to the host's network interface. This type of attack can turn a
          legitimate source of IP traffic into a "attacker" without requiring
          any access privileges to the source host or routers involved. This
          type of attack can be used for denial-of-service purposes or for the
          real attacker (the malicious joiner) to gain access to the
          information content being sent. Similarly, some routing protocols
          may permit any sender (whether joined to the specific group or not)
          to transmit messages to a multicast group.</t>

          <t>It is possible that malicious hosts could also spoof IGMP/MLD
          messages, joining groups posing as legitimate hosts (or spoof source
          traffic from legitimate hosts). This may be done at intermediate
          locations in the network or by hosts co-resident with the authorized
          hosts on local area networks. Such spoofing could be done by raw
          packet generation or with replay of previously-recorded control
          messages.</t>

          <t>For the sake of completeness, it should be noted that multicast
          routing protocol control messaging may be subject to similar threats
          if sufficient protocol security mechanisms are not enabled in the
          routing infrastructure. <xref target="RFC4609"></xref> describes
          security threats to the PIM-SM multicast routing
          infrastructures.</t>

          <!-- [HA] Added text and pointed mroutesec RFC -->
        </section>
      </section>

      <section title="Data-Plane Attacks">
        <t>This section discusses some types of active attacks that might be
        conducted "in-band" with respect to the reliable multicast transport
        protocol operating within the data plane of network data transfer.
        I.e., the "data-plane" here refers to IP packets containing end-to-end
        transport content to support the reliable multicast transfer. The
        passive attack of unauthorized data-plan monitoring is discussed above
        since such activity might be made possible by the vulnerabilities of
        the IP Multicast control plane. To cover the two classes of RMT
        protocols, the active data-plane attacks are categorized as 1) those
        where the attacker generates messages posing as a data sender, and 2)
        those where the attacker generates messages posing as a receiver
        providing feedback to the sender(s) or group. Additionally, a common
        threat to protocol operation is that of brute-force, rogue packet
        generation. This is discussed briefly below, but the more subtle
        attacks that might be conducted are given more attention as those fall
        within the scope of the RMT transport protocol design. Additionally,
        special consideration is given to that of the "replay attack" [see
        <xref target="ReplayAttacks"></xref>], as it can be applied across
        these different categories.</t>

        <section title="Rogue Traffic Generation">
          <t>If an attacker is able to successfully inject packets into the
          multicast distribution tree, one obvious denial-of-service attack is
          for the attacker to generate a large volume of apparently
          authenticate traffic (and if authentication mechanisms are used, a
          "replay" attack strategy might be used). The impact of this type of
          attack can be significant since the potential for routers to relay
          the traffic to multiple portions of a networks (as compared to a
          single unicast routing path). However, other than the amplified
          negative impact to the network, this type of attack is no different
          than what is possible with rogue unicast packet generation and
          similar measures used to protect the network from such attacks could
          be used to contain this type of brute-force attack. Of course, the
          pragmatic question of whether current implementations of such
          protection mechanisms support IP Multicast SHOULD be considered.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Sender Message Spoofing">
          <t>Sender message spoofing attacks are applicable to both CDP: ALC
          (sender-only transmission) and NORM (sender-receiver exchanges).
          Without an authentication mechanism, an attacker can easily generate
          sender messages that could disrupt a reliable multicast transfer
          session. And with FEC-based transport mechanisms, a single packet
          with an apparently-correct FEC payload identifier<xref
          target="RFC5052"></xref> but a corrupted FEC payload could
          potentially render an entire block of transported data invalid.
          Thus, a modest injection rate of corrupt traffic could cause severe
          impairment of data transport. Additionally, such invalid sender
          packets could convey out-of-bound indices (e.g., bad symbol or block
          identifiers) that can lead to buffer overflow exploits or similar
          issues in implementations that insufficiently check for invalid
          data.</t>

          <t>An indirect use of sender message spoofing would be to generate
          messages that would cause receivers to take inappropriate
          congestion-control action. In the case of the layered congestion
          control mechanisms proposed for ALC use, this could lead to the
          receivers erroneously leaving groups associated with higher
          bandwidth transport layers and suffering unnecessarily low transport
          rates. Similarly, receivers may be misled to join inappropriate
          groups directing unwanted traffic to their part of the network.
          Attacks with similar effect could be conducted against the <xref
          target="RFC4654">TCP-Friendly Multicast Congestion Control
          (TFMCC)</xref> approach proposed for NORM operation with spoofing of
          sender messages carrying congestion control state to receivers.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Receiver Message Spoofing">
          <t>These attacks are limited to CDP that use feedback from receivers
          in the group to influence sender and other receiver operation. In
          the NORM protocol, this includes negative-acknowledgement (NACK)
          messages fed back to the sender to achieve reliable transfer,
          congestion control feedback content, and the optional positive
          acknowledgement features of the specification. It is also important
          to note that for ASM operation, NORM receivers pay attention to the
          messages of other receivers for the purpose of suppression to avoid
          feedback implosion as group size grows large.</t>

          <t>An attacker that can generate false feedback can manipulate the
          NORM sender to unnecessarily transmit repair information and reduce
          the goodput of the reliable transfer regardless of the sender's
          transmit rate. Contrived congestion control feedback could also
          cause the sender to transmit at an unfairly low rate.</t>

          <t>As mentioned, spoofed receiver messaging may not be directed only
          at senders, but also at receivers participating in the session. For
          example, an attacker may direct phony receiver feedback messages to
          selected receivers in the group causing those receivers to suppress
          feedback that might have otherwise been transmitted. This attack
          could compromise the ability of those receivers to achieve reliable
          transfer. Also, suppressed congestion control feedback could cause
          the sender to transmit at a rate unfair to those attacked receivers
          if their fair congestion control rate were lower.</t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="ReplayAttacks" title="Replay Attacks">
          <t>The infamous "replay attack" (injection of a previously
          transmitted packet to one or more participants) is given special
          attention here because of the special consequences it can have on
          RMT protocol operation. Without specific protection mechanisms
          against replay (e.g., duplicate message detection), it is possible
          for these attacks to be successful even when security mechanisms
          such as packet authentication and/or encryption are employed.</t>

          <section title="Replay of Sender Messages">
            <t>Generally, replay of recent protocol messages from the sender
            will not harm transport, and could potentially assist it, unless
            it is of sufficient volume to result in the same type of impact as
            the "rogue traffic generation" described above. However, it is
            possible that replay of sufficiently old messages may cause
            receivers to think they are "out of sync" with the sender and
            reset state, compromising the transfer. Also, if sender transport
            data identifiers are reused (object identifiers, FEC payload
            identifiers, etc), it is possible that replay of old messages
            could corrupt data of a current transfer.</t>
          </section>

          <section title="Replay of Receiver Messages">
            <t>Replay of receiver messages are problematic for the NORM
            protocol, because replay of NACK messages could cause the sender
            to unnecessarily transmit repair information for an FEC coding
            block. Similarly, the sender transmission rate might be
            manipulated by replay of congestion control feedback messages from
            receivers in the group. And the way that NORM senders estimate
            group round-trip timing (GRTT) could allow a replay attack to
            manipulate the senders' GRTT estimate to an unnecessarily large
            value, adding latency to the reliable transport process.</t>
          </section>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="generalGoals" title="General Security Goals">
      <t>The term "security" is extremely vast and encompasses many different
      meanings. The goal of this section is to clarify what "security" means
      when considering the CDP defined in the IETF RMT working group. However,
      the scope can also encompass additional applications, like streaming
      applications. This section only focuses on the desired general goals.
      The following sections will then discuss the possible elementary
      services that will be required to fulfill these general goals, as well
      as the underlying technological building blocks.</t>

      <t>The possible final goals include, in decreasing order of importance:
      <list style="symbols">
          <t>network protection: the goal is to protect the network from
          attacks, no matter whether these attacks are voluntary (i.e.,
          launched by one or several attackers) or non voluntary (i.e., caused
          by a misbehaving system, where "system" can designate a building
          block, a protocol, an application, or a user);</t>

          <t>protocol protection: the goal is to protect the RMT protocol
          itself, e.g., to avoid that a misbehaving receiver prevents other
          receivers to get the content, no matter whether this is done
          intentionally or not;</t>

          <t>content protection: to goal is to protect the content itself, for
          instance to guaranty the integrity of the content, or to make sure
          that only authorized clients can access the content;</t>

          <t>and user protection: the goal is often to protect the user
          privacy.</t>
        </list></t>

      <section title="Network Protection">
        <t>Protecting the network is of course of primary importance. An
        attacker should not be able to damage the whole infrastructure by
        exploiting some features of the RMT protocol. Unfortunately, recent
        past has shown that the multicast routing infrastructure is relatively
        fragile, as well as the applications built on top of it. Since the RMT
        protocols may use congestion control mechanisms to regulate sender
        transmission rate, the protocol security features should ensure that
        the sender may not be manipulated to transmit at incorrect rates (most
        importantly not at an excessive rate) to any parts of the receiver
        group. In the case of NORM, the security mechanisms should ensure that
        the feedback suppression mechanisms are protected to prevent
        badly-behaving network nodes from purposefully causing feedback
        implosion. In the case of ALC, where layered congestion control may be
        used via dynamic grou/layer membership, this extends to considerations
        of excessive manipulation of the multicast router control plane.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Protocol Protection">
        <t>Protecting the protocols is also of importance, since the higher
        the number of clients, the more serious the consequences of an attack.
        This is all the more true as scalability is often one of the desired
        goals of CDP. Ideally, receivers should be sufficiently isolated from
        one another, so that a single misbehaving receiver does not affect
        others. Similarly, an external attacker should not be able to break
        the system, i.e., resulting in unreliable operation or delivery of
        incorrect content.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Content Protection">
        <t>The content itself should be protected when meaningful. This level
        of security is often the concern of the content provider (and its
        responsibility). For instance, in case of confidential (or non-free)
        content, the typical solution consists in encrypting the content. It
        can be done within the upper application, i.e., above the RMT
        protocol, or within the transport system.</t>

        <t>But other requirements may exist, like verifying the integrity of a
        received object, or authenticating the sender of the received packets.
        To that goal, one can rely on the use of building blocks integrated
        within, or above, or beneath the RMT protocol.</t>

        <t>One may also consider that offering the packet sender
        authentication and content integrity services are basic requirements
        that should fulfill any RMT system that operates within an open
        network, where any attacker can easily inject spurious traffic in an
        ongoing NORM or ALC session. In that case this goal is not the
        responsibility of the content provider but the responsibility of the
        administrator who deploys the RMT system itself.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="sec.privacy" title="Privacy">
        <t>Finally the user should be protected, and more specifically its
        privacy. In general, there is no privacy issue for data sender: the
        data sender's address is announced to all prospective receivers prior
        to their joins. Moreover receivers need to specify the source
        address(es) as well as the IP multicast address in SSM communication
        upon their subscription. The situation is different if we consider
        receivers since their address should not be disclosed publicly.</t>

        <t>Data receivers use IGMP or MLD protocols to notify their upstream
        routers to join or leave IP multicast session. The recent IGMPv3 <xref
        target="RFC3376"></xref> and MLDv2 <xref target="RFC3810"></xref> do
        not adopt the "report suppression mechanism". Report suppression makes
        the receiver host withdraw its own report when the host hears a report
        scheduled to be sent from other host joining the same group.
        Eliminating the report suppression mechanism does not contribute to
        minimizing the number of responses, but enables the router to keep
        track of host membership status on a link. Due to this specification,
        operators who maintain upstream routers that attach multicast data
        receiver can recognize data receivers' addresses by tracing IGMP/MLD
        report messages. Although such traced data may be useful for capacity
        planning or accounting from operator's perspective, the detail
        information including receivers' IP addresses should be carefully
        treated.</t>

        <t>As described in <xref
        target="sec.unauthorized_group_membership"></xref>, unauthorized users
        may spoof IGMP/MLD query messages and trace receivers' addresses on
        the same LAN. Currently, IGMP/MLD protocols do not protect this
        attack. It is desired for these protocols to ignore invalid query
        messages and provide receiver's privacy by some means.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Elementary Security Techniques">
      <t>The goals defined in <xref target="generalGoals"></xref> will be
      fulfilled by means of underlying security techniques, provided by one or
      several technological building blocks. This section only focuses on
      these elementary security techniques. Some general techniques
      traditionally available are:</t>

      <texttable title="General Security Techniques">
        <ttcol width="20%">Technique</ttcol>

        <ttcol>Goal</ttcol>

        <c>packet integrity</c>

        <c>Enable session participants to verify that a packet has not been
        inappropriately modified in transit.</c>

        <c>packet source authentication</c>

        <c>Enable a receiver to verify the source of a packet.</c>

        <c>packet group authentication</c>

        <c>Enable a receiver to verify that a packet originated or was
        modified only within the group and has not been modified by nonmembers
        in transit; Additionally, if attribution of any modifications by the
        group is required, certain group authentication mechanisms may provide
        this capability.</c>

        <c>packet non-repudiation</c>

        <c>Enable any third party to verify the source of a packet such that
        the source cannot repudiate having sent the packet.</c>

        <c>packet anti-replay</c>

        <c>Enable a receiver to detect that a packet is the same as a
        previously-received packet</c>

        <c>object integrity</c>

        <c>Enable a receiver to verify the integrity of a whole object. Such
        object integrity verification should be possible for any singular
        object or any composition of sub-objects which together constitute a
        larger object structure.</c>

        <c>object source authentication</c>

        <c>Enable a receiver to verify the source of an object.</c>

        <c>object confidentiality</c>

        <c>Enable a source to guarantee that only authorized receivers can
        access the object data.</c>
      </texttable>

      <t>Some additional techniques are specific to the RMT protocols:</t>

      <texttable title="RMT-Specific Security Techniques">
        <ttcol width="20%">Technique</ttcol>

        <ttcol>Goal</ttcol>

        <c>congestion control security</c>

        <c>Prevent an attacker from modifying the congestion control protocol
        normal behavior (e.g., by reducing the transmission (NORM) or
        reception (ALC) rate, or on the opposite increasing this rate up to a
        point where congestion occurs)</c>

        <c>group management</c>

        <c>Ensure that only authorized receivers (as defined by a certain
        group management policy) join the RMT session and possibly inform the
        source</c>

        <c>backward group secrecy</c>

        <c>Prevent a new group member to access the information in clear sent
        to the group before he joined the group</c>

        <c>forward group secrecy</c>

        <c>Prevent a former group member to access the information in clear
        sent to the group after he left the group</c>
      </texttable>

      <t>These techniques are usually achieved by means of one or several
      technological building blocks. The target use case where the RMT system
      will be deployed will greatly impact the choice of the technological
      building block(s) used to provide these services, as explained in <xref
      target="useCaseCharacteristics"></xref>.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Technological Building Blocks">
      <t>Here is a list of techniques and building blocks that are likely to
      fulfill one or several of the goals listed above: <list style="symbols">
          <t>IPsec;</t>

          <t>Group MAC;</t>

          <t>Digital signatures;</t>

          <t>TESLA;</t>

          <t>SSM communication model;</t>

          <!-- [HA] wording -->
        </list> Each of them is now quickly discussed. In particular we
      identify what service it can offer, its limitations, and its field of
      application (adequacy with respect to the CDP and the target use
      case).</t>

      <section title="IPsec">
        <section title="Benefits">
          <t>One direct approach using existing standards is to apply IPsec
          <xref target="RFC4301"></xref> to achieve the following properties:
          <list style="symbols">
              <t>source authentication and packet integrity (IPsec AH or
              ESP)</t>

              <t>confidentiality by means of encryption (IPsec ESP)</t>
            </list></t>
        </section>

        <section title="Requirements">
          <t>It is expected that the approach to apply IPsec for reliable
          multicast transport sessions is similar to that described for OSPFv3
          security<xref target="RFC4552"></xref>. The following list proposes
          the IPsec capabilities needed to support a similar approach to RMT
          protocol security: <list style="symbols">
              <t>Mode - Transport mode IPsec security is required;</t>

              <t>Selectors - source and destination addresses and ports,
              protocol.</t>

              <t>For some uses, preplaced, manual key support may be required
              to support application deployment and operation. For automated
              key management for group communication the Group Secure
              Association Key Management Protocol (GSAKMP) described in <xref
              target="RFC4535"></xref> may be used to emplace the keys for
              IPsec operation.</t>
            </list> Note that a periodic rekeying procedure similar to that
          described in RFC 4552 can also be applied with the additional
          benefit that the reliable transport aspects of the CDP provide
          robustness to any message loss that might occur due to ANY timing
          discrepancies among the participants in the reliable multicast
          session.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Limitations">
          <t>It should be noted that current IPsec implementations may not
          provide the capability for anti-replay protection for multicast
          operation. In the case of the NORM protocol, a sequence number is
          provided for packet loss measurement to support congestion control
          operation. This sequence number can also be used within a NORM
          implementation for detecting duplicate (replayed) messages from
          sources (senders or receivers) within the transport session group.
          In this way, protection against replay attack can be achieved in
          conjunction with the authentication and possibly confidentiality
          properties provided by an IPsec encapsulation of NORM messages. NORM
          receivers generate a very low volume of feedback traffic and it is
          expected that the 16-bit sequence space provided by NORM will be
          sufficient for replay attack protection. When a NORM session is
          long-lived, the limits of the sender repair window are expected to
          provide protection from replayed NACKs as they would typically be
          outside of the sender's current repair window. It is suggested that
          IPsec implementations that can provide anti-replay protection for IP
          Multicast traffic, even when there are multiple senders within a
          group, be adopted. The GSAKMP document has some discussion in this
          area.</t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section title="Group MAC">
        <section title="Benefits">
          <t>The use of Group MAC (Message Authentication Codes) within the
          CDP <xref target="SimpleAuth"></xref> is a simple solution to
          provide a loss tolerant group authentication/integrity service for
          all the packets exchanged within a session (i.e., the packets
          generated by the session's sender and the session's receivers). This
          scheme is easy to deploy since it only requires that all the group
          members share a common secret key. Because Group MAC heavily relies
          on fast symmetric cryptographic building blocks, CPU processing
          remains limited both at the sender and receiver sides, which makes
          it suitable for high data rate transmissions, and/or lightweight
          terminals. Finally, the transmission overhead remains limited.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Requirements">
          <t>This scheme only requires that all the group members share a
          common secret key, possibly associated to a re-keying mechanism
          (e.g., each time the group membership changes, or on a periodic
          basis).</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Limitations">
          <t>This scheme cannot protect against attacks coming from inside the
          group, where a group member impersonates the sender and sends forged
          messages to other receivers. It only provides a group-level
          authentication/integrity service, unlike the TESLA and Digital
          Signature schemes. Note that the Group MAC and Digital Signature
          schemes can be advantageously used together, as explained in <xref
          target="SimpleAuth"></xref>.</t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section title="Digital Signatures">
        <section title="Benefits">
          <t>The use of Digital Signatures within the CDP <xref
          target="SimpleAuth"></xref> is a simple solution to provide a
          loss-tolerant authentication/integrity service for all the packets
          exchanged within a session (i.e., the packets generated by the
          session's sender and the session's receivers). This scheme is easy
          to deploy since it only requires that the participants know the
          packet sender's public key, which can be achieved with either Public
          Key Infrastructure (PKI) or by preplacement of these keys.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Requirements">
          <t>This scheme is easy to deploy since it requires only that the
          participants know the packet sender's public key, which can be
          achieved with either PKI or by preplacement of these keys.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Limitations">
          <t>When RSA <xref target="RsaPaper"></xref> asymmetric cryptography
          is used, the digital signatures approach has two major shortcomings:
          <list style="symbols">
              <t>it is limited by high computational costs, especially at the
              sender, and</t>

              <t>it is limited by high transmission overheads.</t>
            </list>This scheme is well suited to low data rate flows, when
          transmission overheads are not a major issue. For instance it can be
          used as a complement to TESLA for the feedback traffic coming from
          the session's receivers. The use of ECC ("Elliptic Curve
          Cryptography") significantly relaxes these constraints, especially
          when seeking for higher security levels. For instance, the following
          key size provide equivalent security:</t>

          <texttable>
            <ttcol align="center">Symmetric Key Size</ttcol>

            <ttcol align="center">RSA Key Size</ttcol>

            <ttcol align="center">ECC Key Size</ttcol>

            <c>80 bits</c>

            <c>1024 bits</c>

            <c>160 bits</c>

            <c>112 bits</c>

            <c>2048 bits</c>

            <c>224 bits</c>
          </texttable>

          <t>However in some cases, the Intellectual Property Rights (IPR)
          considerations for ECC may limit its use, so the other techniques
          are presented here as well. Note that the Group MAC and Digital
          Signature schemes can be advantageously used together, as explained
          in <xref target="SimpleAuth"></xref>.</t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section title="TESLA">
        <section title="Benefits">
          <t>The use of <xref target="RFC5776">TESLA</xref> within the CDP
          offers a loss tolerant, lightweight, authentication/integrity
          service for the packets generated by the session's sender. Depending
          on the time synchronization and bootstrap methods used, TESLA can be
          compatible with massively scalable sessions. Because TESLA heavily
          relies on fast symmetric cryptographic building blocks, CPU
          processing remains limited both at the sender and receiver sides,
          which makes it suitable for high data rate transmissions, and/or
          lightweight terminals. Finally, the transmission overhead remains
          limited.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Requirements">
          <t>The security offered by TESLA relies heavily on time. Therefore
          the session's sender and each receiver need to be loosely
          synchronized in a secure way. To that purpose, several methods
          exist, depending on the use case: direct time synchronization (which
          requires a bidirectional transport channel), using a secure <xref
          target="RFC1305">Network Time Protocol (NTP)</xref> infrastructure
          (which also requires a bidirectional transport channel), or a Global
          Positioning System (GPS) device, or a clock with a time-drift that
          is negligible in front of the TESLA time accuracy requirements.</t>

          <t>The various bootstrap parameters must also be communicated to the
          receivers, using either an in-band or out-of-band mechanism,
          sometimes requiring bidirectional communications. So, depending on
          the time synchronization scheme and the bootstrap mechanism method,
          TESLA can be used with either bidirectional or unidirectional
          transport channels.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Limitations">
          <t>One limitation is that TESLA does not protect the packets that
          are generated by receivers, for instance the feedback packets of
          NORM. These packets must be protected by other means.</t>

          <t>Another limitation is that TESLA requires some buffering
          capabilities at the receivers in order to enable the delayed
          authentication feature. This is not considered though as a major
          issue in the general case (e.g., FEC decoding of objects within an
          ALC session already requires some buffering capabilities, that often
          exceed that of TESLA), but it might be one in case of embedded
          environments.</t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section title="Source-Specific Multicast">
        <!-- [HA] Changed -->

        <t><xref target="RFC3569">Source-Specific Multicast (SSM)</xref>,
        <xref target="RFC4607"></xref> amends the classical Any-Source
        Multicast (ASM) model by creating logical IP multicast "channels" that
        are defined by the multicast destination address <spanx style="emph">and</spanx>
        the specific source address(es). Thus for a given "channel", only the
        specific source(s) can inject packets that are distributed to the
        receivers. This form of multicast has group management benefits since
        a source can independently control the "channels" it creates.</t>

        <section title="Requirements">
          <t>Use of SSM requires that the network intermediate systems
          explicitly support it. Additionally, hosts operating systems are
          required to support the IGMPv3/MLDv2 extensions for SSM, and the CDP
          implementations need to support the IGMPv3/MLDv2 API, including
          management of the &lt;srcAddr; dstMcastAddr&gt; "channel"
          identifiers.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Limitations">
          <t>CDP such as NORM that use signaling from receivers to multicast
          senders will need to use unicast addressing for feedback messages.
          In the case of NORM, its timer-based feedback suppression requires
          support of the sender NORM_CMD(REPAIR_ADV) message to control
          receiver feedback. In some topologies, use of unicast feedback may
          require some additional latency (increased backoff factor) for safe
          operation. The security of the unicast feedback from the receivers
          to sender will need to be addressed separately since the IP
          multicast model, including SSM, does not provide the sender
          knowledge of authorized group members.</t>
        </section>

        <!-- [HA] Modified with source-based and receiver-based attacks, and merged "Benefits" section -->

        <section title="Source-Based and Receiver-Based Attacks">
          <t>The security threats are categorized into "source-based" and
          "receiver-based" attacks <xref target="RFC4609"></xref>. In short,
          the former is a DoS attack against the multicast networks, in which
          data is sent to numerous and random group addresses, and the latter
          is a DoS attack against multicast routers, in which innumerable
          IGMP/MLD joins are sent from a client.</t>

          <t>Regarding source-based attack, there are some security benefits
          in SSM. Since data-plane traffic for an SSM "channel" is limited to
          that of a single, specific source address, it is possible that
          network intermediate systems may impose mechanism that prevent
          injection of traffic to the group from inappropriate (perhaps
          malicious) nodes. This can reduce the risk for denial-of-service and
          some of the other attacks described in this document. While SSM
          alone is not a complete security solution, it can simplify secure
          RMT operation.</t>

          <t>On the contrary, SSM is not robust against receiver-based attack.
          An SSM capable router constructs a Shortest-Path Tree (SPT) with no
          shared tree coordination. Therefore, even if a host triggers invalid
          or unavailable channel subscriptions, the upstream router starts
          establishing all SPTs with no intellectual decision. What is worse
          is that these multicast routers cannot recognize the original router
          that is attacked and cannot stop the attack itself.</t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section title="Summary">
        <t>The following table summarizes the pros/cons of each
        authentication/integrity scheme used at application/transport level
        (where "-" means bad, "0" means neutral, and "+" means good):</t>

        <texttable>
          <ttcol align="left"></ttcol>

          <ttcol align="center">RSA Digital Signature</ttcol>

          <ttcol align="center">ECC Digital Signature</ttcol>

          <ttcol align="center">Group MAC</ttcol>

          <ttcol align="center">TESLA</ttcol>

          <c>True authentication and integrity</c>

          <c>Yes</c>

          <c>Yes</c>

          <c>No (group security)</c>

          <c>Yes</c>

          <c>Immediate authentication</c>

          <c>Yes</c>

          <c>Yes</c>

          <c>Yes</c>

          <c>No</c>

          <c>Processing load</c>

          <c>-</c>

          <c>0</c>

          <c>+</c>

          <c>+</c>

          <c>Transmission overhead</c>

          <c>-</c>

          <c>0</c>

          <c>+</c>

          <c>+</c>

          <c>Complexity</c>

          <c>+</c>

          <c>+</c>

          <c>+</c>

          <c>-</c>
        </texttable>

        <!--
        <t>The following table summarizes the pros/cons of each
        authentication/integrity scheme used at application/transport
        level:</t>

        <texttable>
          <ttcol align="left"></ttcol>

          <ttcol align="center">RSA Digital Signature</ttcol>

          <ttcol align="center">ECC Digital Signature</ttcol>

          <ttcol align="center">Group MAC</ttcol>

          <ttcol align="center">TESLA</ttcol>

          <c>True auth and integrity</c>

          <c>Yes</c>

          <c>Yes</c>

          <c>No (group security)</c>

          <c>Yes</c>

          <c>Immediate auth</c>

          <c>Yes</c>

          <c>Yes</c>

          <c>Yes</c>

          <c>No</c>

          <c>Processing load</c>

          <c>- -</c>

          <c>+</c>

          <c>++</c>

          <c>+</c>

          <c>Transmission overhead</c>

          <c>- -</c>

          <c>+</c>

          <c>++</c>

          <c>+</c>

          <c>Complexity</c>

          <c>++</c>

          <c>++</c>

          <c>++</c>

          <c>- -</c>
        </texttable>
-->
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Security Infrastructure">
      <t>Deploying the elementary technological building blocks often requires
      that a security infrastructure exists. Such security infrastructure can
      provide: <list style="symbols">
          <t>Public Key Infrastructure (PKI) for trusted third party vetting
          of, and vouching for, user identities. PKI also allows the binding
          of public keys to users, usually by means of certificates.</t>

          <t>Group Key Management with rekeying schemes that are either
          periodic or triggered by some higher level event. It is required in
          particular when the group is dynamic and forward/backward secrecy
          are important. This is also required to improve the scalability of
          the CDP (since key management is done automatically, using a key
          server topology), or the security provided by the CDP (since the
          underlying cryptographic keys will be changed frequently)</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>It is expected that some CDP deployments may use existing
      client-server security infrastructure models so that receivers may
      acquire any necessary security material and be authenticated or
      validated as needed for group participation. Then, the reliable delivery
      of session data content will be provided via the applicable RMT
      protocols. Note that in this case the security infrastructure itself may
      limit the scalability of the group size or other aspects of reliable
      multicast transfer. The IETF Multicast Security (MSEC) Working Group has
      developed some protocols that can be applied to achieve more scalable
      and effective group communication security infrastructure<xref
      target="RFC4046"></xref>. It is encouraged that these mechanisms be
      considered in the development of security for CDP.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="New Threats Introduced by the Security Scheme Itself">
      <t>Introducing a security scheme, as a side effect, can sometimes
      introduce new security threats. For instance, signing all packets with
      asymmetric cryptographic schemes (to provide a source
      authentication/content integrity/anti-replay service) opens the door to
      DoS attacks. Indeed, verifying asymmetric-based cryptographic signatures
      is a CPU intensive task. Therefore an attacker can easily overload a
      receiver (or a sender in case of NORM) by injecting a significant number
      of faked packets.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Consequences for the RMT and MSEC Working Group">
      <t>To meet the goals outlined in this document, it is expected that the
      RMT and MSEC Working Groups may need to develop some supporting protocol
      security mechanisms. It is also possible to cooperate with the Multicast
      Backbone (MBONE) Deployment (MBONED) Working Group for defining
      operational considerations.</t>

      <!-- [HA] Added MBONED WG statement -->

      <section title="RMT Transport Message Security Encapsulation Header">
        <t>An alternative approach to using IPsec to provide the necessary
        properties to protect RMT protocol operation from the application
        attacks described earlier, is to extend the RMT protocol message set
        to include a message encapsulation option. This encapsulation header
        could be used to provide authentication, confidentiality, and
        anti-replay protection as needed. Since this would be independent of
        the IP layer, the header might need to provide a source identifier to
        be used as a "selector" for recalling security state (including
        authentication certificate(s), sequence state, etc) for a given
        message. In the case of the NORM protocol, a <spanx style="verb">NormNodeId</spanx>
        field exists that could be used for this purpose. In the case of ALC,
        the security encapsulation mechanism would need to add this function.
        The security encapsulation mechanism, although resident "above" the IP
        layer, could use <xref target="RFC4535">GSAKMP</xref> or a similar
        approach for automated key management.</t>
      </section>

      <!--
FROM THE JULY 2006 RMT MINUTES:

2- RMT BBs to Standard Track and Security

(point raised by Magnus Westerlund on the ML)

Magnus explains that having specifications (BBs, PIs) on the STD track
without any detailed guidelines on how to implement security services is
not reasonable. Hence this discussion...
Lorenzo answers there are many possible goals which makes this discussion
(and recommendations) difficult. The highest security goal is probably
to protect the network, a lower goal is to protect the protocol itself,
and an even lower goal is to protect the objects being transported.
Magnus agrees that there is a hierarchy of possible goals, but it does
not mean that we can ignore them altogether.
Lorenzo reminds that one initial RMT's goal was scalability, and therefore
it was decided that the source should not know the identity of the
receivers. As a consequence, it makes some security requirements more
complex to achieve.
George Gross: Scalability was one of the goals also for MSEC too
(e.g., for key management). Many BBs developed in MSEC will come for free.
Lorenzo: Do we need any modification to the protocols defined in MSEC
to use them in RMT?
George reminds the group that IPsec has been redesigned recently in order
to support multicast.
Lorenzo: We are not standardizing the application, but the transport.
As RMT is providing transport solutions, is there any need to bother
with application topics?
George: IPsec is one solution, but the question is whether we want to
use it (there are limitations) or want provide security in the
application layer?
Magnus: If we want to do that on a lower layer (i.e., with IPsec) we
need to  specify a profile for it here.

The discussion now focuses on the above three goals (content, network
and protocol protection):

1) Content protection:
Magnus: The provider of the content has its own opinion on how to protect
the content.
Lorenzo: It's not the problem of RMT to provide content protection.
We can say we need a WG in the application level to address this problem.
Magnus agrees with Lorenzo.
Mark: Yet but we must keep in mind that there's an urgent need to make
progress. Many people are using FLUTE/ALC now...
Magnus: Confidentiality issue is the last problem to solve. There are
more important problems to solve first.

2) Network protection:
Lorenzo: Network protection in our case means protecting the network
from congestion. What is the situation ?
Brian: There is a potential attack to TFMCC (used by NORM). The sender
can slow down because of a malicious receivers who says to be a bad
node.
George explains that against this kind of receiver feedback attack, the
only solution is to provide group key management and to use digital
signatures. This technique can enable the sender to decide whether
a receiver who sends feedback is an authorized member of the group or
not. But a requirement is to use a key management infrastructure...

3) Protocol protection:
One possible goal is to protect the transport protocol against nodes
that want to stop the protocol.
Lorenzo: Can we mandate the use of SSM to protect NORM?
Magnus answers that an attacker having control over the network can
easily spoof the source, so using SSM does not really solve the problem.
George: Using public keys, a certificate authority and digital signature
can help... The new version of IPsec, that features multicast extensions,
is another  way to achieve that goal.
Lorenzo suggests to ask the MSEC WG to have it a WG item. He also
suggests to add in the security requirement of NORM a note explaining
that this scheme can be used.

Gorry: Why do we go to SSM?
Lorenzo explains there's a potential solution for TFMCC if we mandate the
use of SSM. It seems a realistic assumption.
Brian explains that with SSM, a receiver can still slow down the sender
but cannot break the network. 
Lorenzo: A possible solution, for TFMCC, is to say that if the sender
receives contradicting feedback, then he should trust the worst one.

Gorry explains that in case of the ALC layer congestion control
scheme, there's an incentive to receive at a higher rate even if it
breaks the network (i.e., by not being fair with other TCP flows).
Lorenzo: Is there any work in unicast to address the problem?
What about a TCP receiver that acknowledges each packet even if
he didn't receive them? It can happen in NORM and ALC but also in TCP.
It seems to be a very tough problem since it needs to involve the routers.
Somebody explains that the problem is that we trust the host to do
the congestion control. In TCP, if a receiver misbehaves, he will
probably be the only one to be hurt.
Lorenzo: So we have a very big problem here... But we are only
opening issues, we are not solving them!

-->
    </section>

    <section title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>This document has no actions for IANA.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Security Considerations">
      <t>This document is a general discussion of security for the RMT
      protocol family. But specific security considerations are not applicable
      as this document does not introduce any new techniques.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Acknowledgments">
      <t>The authors would like acknowledge Magnus Westerlund for stimulating
      the working group activity in this area. Additionally George Gross and
      Ran Atkinson contributed many ideas to the discussion here.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.2119'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.4301'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.5052'?>

      <?rfc include="reference.I-D.ietf-rmt-flute-revised"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5740"?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.4535'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.4552'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.4046'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.4609'?>

      <!-- [HA] RFC4609: mroutesec -->

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5775"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5776"?>

      <reference anchor="SimpleAuth">
        <front>
          <title>Simple Authentication Schemes for the ALC and NORM
          Protocols</title>

          <author fullname="Vincent Roca" initials="V." surname="Roca">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date day="" month="October" year="2009" />
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="Internet Draft"
                    value="draft-ietf-rmt-simple_auth-for-alc-norm-02.txt (work in progress)" />
      </reference>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.3376'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.3810'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.1112'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.3569'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.4607'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.4654'?>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <reference anchor="Neumann05">
        <front>
          <title>Large Scale Content Distribution Protocols</title>

          <author fullname="Christoph Neumann" initials="C." surname="Neumann">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="Vincent Roca" initials="V." surname="Roca">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="Rod Walsh" initials="R." surname="Walsh">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date month="October" year="2005" />

          <abstract>
            <t></t>
          </abstract>
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="ACM Computer Communications Review (CCR)"
                    value="Vol. 35 No. 5" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RsaPaper">
        <front>
          <title>A Method for Obtaining Digital Signatures and Public-Key
          Cryptosystems</title>

          <author fullname="R.L. Rivest" initials="R.L." surname="Rivest">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="A. Shamir" initials="A." surname="Shamir">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="L. Adleman" initials="L." surname="Adleman">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date year="1978" />
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="Communications of the ACM 21," value="pp. 120-126" />

        <format target="http://people.csail.mit.edu/rivest/Rsapaper.pdf"
                type="HTML" />
      </reference>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.1305'?>
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
