<?xml version="1.0" encoding="us-ascii"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc PUBLIC '' "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/rfc2629.dtd"[
  <!ENTITY RFC2119 PUBLIC '' "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
  <!ENTITY RFC2629 PUBLIC '' "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2629.xml">
  <!ENTITY RFC3552 PUBLIC '' "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3552.xml">
  <!ENTITY RFC3640 PUBLIC '' "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3640.xml">
]>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' 

href="http://greenbytes.de/tech/webdav/rfc2629xslt/rfc2629.xslt" ?>
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<!-- generate a ToC -->
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<!-- the number of levels of subsections in ToC. default: 3 -->
<!-- control references -->
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<!-- use symbolic references tags, i.e, [RFC2119] instead of [1] -->
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<!-- sort the reference entries alphabetically -->
<!-- control vertical white space 
     (using these PIs as follows is recommended by the RFC Editor) -->
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<!-- do not start each main section on a new page -->
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<!-- keep one blank line between list items -->
<!-- end of list of popular I-D processing instructions -->
<rfc category="info"
     docName="draft-jasinska-ix-bgp-route-server-00"
     ipr="trust200902"
     obsoletes=""
     updates=""
     submissionType="IETF"
     xml:lang="en">
  <!-- category values: std, bcp, info, exp, and historic
     ipr values: full3667, noModification3667, noDerivatives3667
     you can add the attributes updates="NNNN" and obsoletes="NNNN" 
     they will automatically be output with "(if approved)" -->
  <!-- ***** FRONT MATTER ***** -->

  <front>

    <title abbrev="IX BGP Route Server">
      Internet Exchange Route Server
    </title>

    <author initials="E" surname="Jasinska" fullname="Elisa Jasinska">
      <organization>AMS-IX B.V.</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Westeinde 12</street>
          <city>Amsterdam</city> 
          <region>NH</region>
          <code>1017 ZN</code>
          <country>NL</country>
        </postal>
        <email>elisa.jasinska@ams-ix.net</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author initials="N" surname="Hilliard" fullname="Nick Hilliard">
      <organization>INEX</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>4027 Kingswood Road</street>
          <city>Dublin</city> 
          <code>24</code>
          <country>IE</country>
        </postal>
        <email>nick@inex.ie</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author initials="R" surname="Raszuk" fullname="Robert Raszuk">
      <organization>Cisco Systems</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>170 West Tasman Drive</street>
          <city>San Jose</city> 
          <region>CA</region>
          <code>95134</code>
          <country>US</country>
        </postal>
        <email>raszuk@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>


    <date month="July" year="2010" />
    <area>Routing</area>
    <workgroup>GROW Working Group</workgroup>
    <keyword>I-D</keyword>
    <keyword>Internet-Draft</keyword>
    <keyword>GROW</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>
        The growing popularity of Internet exchange points (IXPs) brings a new
        set of requirements to interconnect participating networks. While
        bilateral exterior BGP sessions between exchange participants were
        previously the most common means of exchanging reachability
        information, the overhead associated with dense interconnection has
        caused substantial operational scaling problems for IXP participants.
      </t>
      <t>
        This document outlines a specification for multilateral
        interconnections at IXPs. Multilateral interconnection describes a
        method of exchanging routing information between three or more BGP
        speakers using a single intermediate broker system, referred to as a
        route server. Route servers are typically used on shared access media
        networks such as Internet Exchanges (IXPs), to facilitate simplified
        interconnection between multiple Internet routers on such a network.
      </t> 
    </abstract>

  </front>

  <middle>

     <section title="Introduction to Multilateral Interconnection">
      <t>
        Internet Exchange Points (IXPs) provide IP data interconnection
        facilities for their participants, typically using shared Layer-2
        networking media such as Ethernet. The Border Gateway Protocol (BGP)
        <xref target="RFC4271" />, an inter-Autonomous System routing
        protocol, is commonly used to facilitate exchange of network
        reachability information over such media.
      </t>
      <t>
        In the case of bilateral interconnection between two exchange
        participant routers, each router must be configured with a BGP session
        to the other. At IXPs with many participants who wish to implement
        dense interconnection, this requirement can lead both to large router
        configurations and high administrative overhead. Given the growth in
        the number of participants at many IXPs, it has become operationally
        troublesome to implement densely meshed interconnections at these
        IXPs.
      </t>
      <t>
        Multilateral interconnection describes a method of interconnecting BGP
        speaking routers using a third party brokering system, commonly
        referred to as a route server and typically managed by the exchange
        fabric operator. Each of the multilateral interconnection participants
        (usually referred to as route server clients) announces network
        reachability information to the route server using exterior BGP, and
        the route server in turn forwards this information to each other route
        server client connected to it, according to its configuration.
        Although a route server uses BGP to exchange reachability information
        with each of its clients, it does not forward traffic itself and is
        therefore not a router.
      </t> 
      
      <t>
        A route server can be viewed as similar in function to an <xref
        target="RFC4456" /> route reflector, except that it operates using
        EBGP instead of iBGP.
      </t>

      <section title="Specification of Requirements">
        <t>
          The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
          "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and
          "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in
          <xref target="RFC2119" />.
        </t>
      </section>

    </section>

    <section title="Bilateral Interconnection">
      <t>
        Bilateral interconnection describes a method of interconnecting
        routers using individual BGP sessions between each participant router
        on an IXP in order to exchange reachability information. While
        interconnection policies vary from participant to participant, most
        IXPs have significant numbers of participants who see value in
        interconnecting with as many other exchange participants as possible.
        In order for an IXP participant to implement a dense interconnection
        policy, it is necessary for the participant to liaise with each of
        their intended interconnection partners and if this partner agrees to
        interconnect, then both participants' routers much be configured with
        a BGP session to exchange network reachability information. If each
        exchange participant interconnects with each other participant, a full
        mesh of BGP sessions is needed, as detailed in <xref
        target="ixp_interconnection" />.
      </t>
      <figure title='Full-Mesh Interconnection at an IXP' anchor="ixp_interconnection">
        <preamble></preamble>
        <artwork align='center'>
     AS1      AS2
     ***      ***
IXP *   *    *   *
+---*   *----*   *---+
|   *   *____*   *   |
|    ***\    /***    |
|     |  \  /  |     |
|     |   \/   |     |
|     |   /\   |     |
|     |  /  \  |     |
|    ***/____\***    |
|   *   *    *   *   |
+---*   *----*   *---+
    *   *    *   *
     ***      ***
     AS3      AS4
        </artwork>
        <postamble></postamble>
      </figure>
      <t>
        <xref target="ixp_interconnection" /> depicts an IXP platform with
        four connected routers, administered by four separate exchange
        participants, each with a locally unique autonomous system number:
        AS1, AS2, AS3 and AS4. Each of these four participants wishes to
        exchange traffic with all other participants; this is accomplished by
        configuring a full mesh of BGP sessions on each router connected to
        the exchange, resulting in 6 BGP sessions across the IXP fabric.
      </t>
      <t>
        It can be calculated that the number of BGP sessions at an exchange
        has an upper bound of n*(n-1)/2, where n is the number of routers at
        the exchange. As many exchanges have relatively large numbers of
        participating networks, the super-linear scaling requirements of dense
        interconnection tend to cause operational and administrative overhead
        at large IXPs. In particular, new participants to an IXP require
        significant initial resourcing in order to gain value from their IXP
        connection.
      </t>
    </section>


    <section title="Multilateral Interconnection">
      <t>
        Multilateral interconnection is implemented using a route server
        configured to use BGP to exchange reachability information between
        each client router. The route server preserves the BGP NEXT_HOP
        attribute from all received NLRI UPDATE messages, and passes these
        messages with unchanged NEXT_HOP to its route server clients,
        according to its configured routing policy. Using this method of
        exchanging NLRIs, an IXP participant router can receive an aggregated
        list of prefixes from all other route server clients using a single
        BGP session to the route server instead of depending on multiple BGP
        sessions with each other participant router. This reduces the overall
        number of BGP sessions over an Internet exchange from n*(n-1)/2 to n,
        where n is the number of routers at the exchange.
      </t>
      <t>
        In practical terms, this allows dense interconnection between IXP
        participants with low administrative overhead and significantly
        simpler and smaller router configurations. In particular, new IXP
        participants benefit from immediate and extensive interconnection,
        while existing route server participants receive reachability
        information from these new participants without necessarily having to
        adapt their configurations.
       </t>

      <figure title='IXP-based Interconnection with Route Server' anchor="rs_interconnection">
        <preamble></preamble>
        <artwork align='center'>
     AS1      AS2
     ***      ***
IXP *   *    *   *
+---*   *----*   *---+
|   *   *    *   *   |
|    ***\    /***    |
|        \  /        |
|         **         |
|        *  *        |
|     RS *  *        |
|        *  *        |
|         **         |
|        /  \        |
|    ***/    \***    |
|   *   *    *   *   |
+---*   *----*   *---+
    *   *    *   *
     ***      ***
     AS3      AS4
        </artwork>
        <postamble></postamble>
      </figure>
      <t>
        As illustrated in <xref target="rs_interconnection" />, each router on
        the IXP fabric requires only a single BGP session to the route server,
        from which it can receive reachability information for all other
        routers on the IXP which also connect to the route server.
      </t>
    </section>


    <section title="Technical Considerations for Route Server Implementations">

      <section title="Client UPDATE Messages">
        <t>
          A route server MUST accept all UPDATE messages transmitted to it
          from each of its clients for inclusion in its Adj-RIB-In. These
          UPDATE messages may subsequently not be included in the route
          server's Loc-RIB or Loc-RIBs, due to filters configured for the
          purposes of implementing policy routing. The route server SHOULD
          perform one or more BGP Decision Processes to select routes for
          subsequent advertisement to its clients, taking into account
          possible configuration to provide multiple NLRI paths to a
          particular client as described in <xref target="phm_multiple_paths"
          /> or multiple Loc-RIBs as described in <xref
          target="phm_multiple_ribs" />. The route server SHOULD forward
          UPDATE messages where appropriate from its Loc-RIB or Loc-RIBs to
          its clients.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section title="Attribute Transparency">
        <t>
          As a route server primarily performs a brokering service,
          modification of attributes could cause route server clients to alter
          their BGP best-path selection process for received prefix
          reachability information, thereby changing the intended routing
          policies of exchange participants. Therefore, contrary to what is
          specified in section 5.1 of <xref target="RFC4271" />, route servers
          should not generally modify BGP attributes received from route
          server clients before distributing them to their other route server
          clients.
        </t>

        <section title="NEXT_HOP Attribute">
          <t>
            The BGP NEXT_HOP attribute defines the IP address of the router
            used as the next hop to the destinations listed in the Network
            Layer Reachability Information field of the UPDATE message. As the
            route server does not participate in the actual routing of
            traffic, the NEXT_HOP attribute MUST be passed unmodified to the
            route server clients, similar to the "third party" next hop
            feature described in <xref target="RFC2283" />.
          </t>
        </section>

        <section title="AS_PATH Attribute">
          <t>
            AS_PATH is a mandatory transitive attribute which identifies the
            autonomous systems through which routing information carried in
            the UPDATE message has passed.
          </t>
          <t>
            As a route server does not participate in the process of
            forwarding data between client routers, and because modification
            of the AS_PATH attribute could affect route server client
            best-path calculations, the route server SHOULD NOT either prepend
            its own AS number to the AS_PATH segment or modify the AS_PATH
            segment in any other way.
          </t>
        </section>
 
        <section title="MULTI_EXIT_DISC Attribute">
           <t>
            The multi-exit discriminator is an optional non-transitive
            attribute intended to be used on external (inter-AS) links to
            discriminate among multiple exit or entry points to the same
            neighboring AS. If applied to an NLRI UPDATE sent to a route
            server, the attribute SHOULD be treated as a transitive attribute
            (contrary to section 5.1.4 of <xref target="RFC4271" />) and the
            route server SHOULD NOT modify the value of this attribute.
          </t>
        </section>
  
        <section title="BGP Community Attributes">
           <t>
            The BGP COMMUNITIES and Extended Communities attributes are
            optional transitive attributes intended for labeling information
            carried in BGP UPDATE messages. If applied to an NLRI UPDATE sent
            to a route server, these attributes SHOULD NOT not generally be
            modified or removed, except in the case where the attributes are
            intended for processing by the route server itself.
           </t>
        </section>

       </section>

      <section title="Per-Client Prefix Filtering" anchor="prefix_filtering"> 
        <section title="Prefix Hiding on a Route Server" anchor="prefix_hiding"> 
          <t>
            While IXP participants often use route servers with the intention
            of interconnecting with as many other route server participants as
            possible, there are several circumstances where control of prefix
            distribution on a per-client basis is important for ensuring that
            the desired interconnection policy is met.
          </t>
          <figure title='Filtered Interconnection at an IXP' anchor="ixp_filtered_interconnection">
            <preamble></preamble>
            <artwork align='center'>
     AS1      AS2
     ***      ***
IXP *   *    *   *
+---*   *----*   *---+
|   *   *    *   *   |
|    ***\    /***    |
|        \  /  |     |
|         \/   |     |
|         /\   |     |
|        /  \  |     |
|    ***/____\***    |
|   *   *    *   *   |
+---*   *----*   *---+
    *   *    *   *
     ***      ***
     AS3      AS4
            </artwork>
            <postamble></postamble>
          </figure>
          <t>
            Using the example in <xref target="ixp_filtered_interconnection"
            />, AS1 does not directly exchange prefix information with either
            AS2 or AS3 at the IXP, but only interconnects with AS4.
          </t>
          <t> 
            In the traditional bilateral interconnection model, prefix
            filtering to a third party exchange participant is accomplished
            either by not engaging in a bilateral interconnection with that
            participant or else by implementing outbound prefix filtering on
            the BGP session towards that participant. However, in a
            multilateral interconnection environment, only the route server
            can perform outbound prefix filtering in the direction of the
            route server client; other route server clients do not have direct
            control over what prefix filters the route server employs towards
            any particular client.
          </t>
          <t>
            If the same prefix is sent to a route server from multiple route
            server clients with different BGP attributes, and traditional
            best-path route selection is performed on that list of prefixes,
            then the route server will select a single best-path prefix for
            propagation to all connected clients. If, however, the route
            server has been configured to filter the calculated best-path
            prefix from reaching a particular route server client, then that
            client will receive no reachability information for that prefix
            from the route server, despite the fact that the route server has
            received alternative reachability information for that prefix from
            other route server clients. This phenomenon is referred to as
            "prefix hiding".
          </t>
          <t>
            For example, in <xref target="ixp_filtered_interconnection" />, if
            the same prefix were sent to the route server via AS2 and AS4, and
            the route via AS2 was preferred according to BGP's traditional
            best-path selection, but AS2 was filtered by AS1, then AS1 would
            never receive this prefix, even though the route server had
            previously received a valid alternative path via AS4. This happens
            because the best-path selection is performed only once on the
            route server for all clients.
          </t>
          <t>
            It is noted that prefix hiding will only occur on route servers
            which employ per-client prefix filtering; if an IXP operator
            deploys a route server without prefix filtering, then prefix
            hiding does not occur, as all paths are considered equally valid
            from the point of view of the route server.
          </t>
          <t>
            There are several techniques which may be employed to prevent the
            prefix hiding problem from occurring. Route server implementations
            SHOULD implement at least one one method to prevent prefix hiding.
          </t>
        </section>

         <section title="Mitigation Techniques" anchor="prefix_hiding_mitigation"> 
          <section title="Multiple Route Server RIBs" anchor="phm_multiple_ribs">
            <t>
              The most portable means of preventing the route server prefix
              hiding problem is by using a route server BGP implementation
              which performs the per-client best-path calculation for each set
              of prefixes which results after the route server's client
              filtering policies have been taken into consideration. This can
              be implemented by using per-client Loc-RIBs, with prefix
              filtering implemented between the Adj-RIB-In and the per-client
              Loc-RIB. Live implementations will usually optimise this by
              maintaining prefixes not subject to filtering policies in a
              global Loc-RIB, with per-client Loc-RIBs stored as deltas.
            </t>
            <t>
              This problem mitigation technique is highly portable, as it
              makes no assumptions about the feature capabilities of the route
              server clients.
            </t>
          </section>

          <section title="Advertising Multiple Paths" anchor="phm_multiple_paths"> 
            <t>
              The prefix distribution model described above assumes standard
              BGP session encoding where the route server sends a single path
              to its client for any given prefix. This path is selected using
              the BGP path selection decision process described in <xref
              target="RFC4271" />. If, however, it were possible for the route
              server to send more than a single path to a route server client,
              then this would alleviate the requirement for route server
              clients to depend on receiving a single best path to a
              particular prefix; consequently the prefix hiding problem
              described in <xref target="prefix_hiding" /> would disappear.
            </t>
            <t>
              This document discusses two methods which describe how such
              increased path diversity could be implemented.
            </t>

            <section title="Diverse BGP Path Approach" anchor="phm_diverse_bgp"> 
              <t>
                The Diverse BGP Path proposal as defined in <xref
                target="I-D.ietf-grow-diverse-bgp-path-dist"></xref> is a
                simple way to distribute multiple prefix paths from a route
                server to a route server client by using a separate BGP
                session between the route server and the route server client
                for each different path.
              </t>
              <t>
                The number of paths which may be distributed to a client is
                constrained by the number of BGP sessions which the route
                server and the route server client are willing to establish
                with each other. The distributed paths may be established both
                from the global BGP Loc-RIB on the route server in addition to
                any per-client Loc-RIB. As there may be more potential paths
                to a given prefix than configured BGP sessions, this method is
                not guaranteed to eliminate the prefix hiding problem in all
                situations.
              </t>
            </section>

            <section title="Add-Paths Approach"> 
              <t>
                The <xref target="I-D.ietf-idr-add-paths"></xref> Internet
                draft proposes a different approach to multiple path
                propagation, by allowing a BGP speaker to forward multiple
                paths for the same prefix on a single BGP session. As <xref
                target="RFC4271" /> specifies that a BGP listener must
                implement an implicit withdraw when it receives an UPDATE
                message for a prefix which already exists in its Adj-RIB-In,
                this approach requires explicit support for the feature both
                on the route server and on its clients. Furthermore, if the
                add-paths capability is negotiated bidirectionally between the
                route server and a route server client, and the route server
                client propagates multiple paths for the same prefix to the
                route server, then this could potentially cause the
                propagation of inactive, invalid or suboptimal paths to the
                route server, thereby causing loss of reachability to other
                route server clients.
              </t>
            </section>
          </section>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Operational Considerations for Route Server Installations" anchor="ops_considerations"> 
      <section title="Route Server Scaling" anchor="ops_scaling"> 
        <t>
          While deployment of multiple Loc-RIBs on the route server presents a
          simple way of avoid the prefix hiding problem noted in <xref
          target="prefix_hiding" />, this approach requires significantly more
          computing resources on the route server than where a single Loc-RIB
          is deployed for all clients. As the <xref target="RFC4271" />
          Decision Process must be applied to all Loc-RIBs deployed on the
          route server, both CPU and memory requirements on the host computer
          scale approximately according to O(P * N), where P is the total
          number of unique prefixes received by the route server and N is the
          number of route server clients which require a unique Loc-RIB. As
          this is a super-linear scaling relationship, large route server
          deployments may derive benefit from only deploying per-client
          Loc-RIBs where they are required.
        </t>
        <t>
          Regardless of any Loc-RIB optimization implemented, the route
          server's network bandwidth requirements will continue to bounded
          above by a relationship of order O(P * N), where P is the total
          number of unique prefixes received by the route server and N is the
          total number of route server clients. In the case where P_avg, the
          mean number of unique prefixes received per route server client,
          remains roughly constant according as the number of connected
          clients, this relationship can be rewritten as O((P_avg * N) * N) or
          O(N^2). This polynomial upper bound on the network traffic
          requirements indicates that the route server model will not
          functionally scale to arbitrarily large sizes.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section title="NLRI Leakage Mitigation" anchor="ops_leakage_mitigation"> 
        <t>
          NLRI leakage occurs when a BGP client unintentionally distributes
          NLRI UPDATE messages to one or more neighboring BGP routers. NLRI
          leakage of this form to a route server can cause connectivity
          problems at an IXP if each route server client is configured to
          accept all prefix UPDATE messages from the route server. It is
          therefore RECOMMENDED when deploying route servers that, due to the
          potential for collateral damage caused by NLRI leakage, route server
          operators deploy NLRI leakage mitigation measures in order to
          prevent unintentional prefix announcements or else limit the scale
          of any such leak. Although not foolproof, per-client inbound prefix
          limits can restrict the damage caused by prefix leakage in many
          cases. Per-client inbound prefix filtering on the route server is a
          more deterministic and usually more reliable means of preventing
          prefix leakage, but requires more administrative resources to
          maintain properly.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section title="Route Server Redundancy" anchor="ops_use_two_of_em"> 
        <t>
          As the purpose of an IXP route server implementation is to provide a
          reliable reachability brokerage service, it is RECOMMENDED that
          exchange operators who implement route server systems provision
          multiple route servers on each shared Layer-2 domain. There is no
          requirement to use the same BGP implementation for each route server
          on the IXP fabric; however, it is RECOMMENDED that where an
          operators provisions more than a single server on the same shared
          Layer-2 domain, each route server implementation be configured
          equivalently and in such a manner that the path reachability
          information from each system is identical.
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Security Considerations">
      <t>
        On route server installations which do not employ prefix-hiding
        mitigation techniques, the prefix hiding problem outlined in section
        <xref target="prefix_hiding" /> can be used in certain circumstances
        to proactively block third party prefix announcements from other route
        server clients.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>
        The new set of mechanism for route servers does not require any new
        allocations from IANA.
      </t>
    </section>


    <section title="Acknowledgments">
      <t>
        The authors would like to thank Niels Bakker and Ryan Bickhart for
        their valuable input.
      </t>
      <t>
        In addition, the authors would like to acknowledge the developers of
        BIRD, OpenBGPD and Quagga, whose open source BGP implementations
        include route server capabilities which are compliant with this
        document.
      </t>
    </section>

  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2283"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4271"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4456"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.I-D.ietf-idr-add-paths"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.I-D.ietf-grow-diverse-bgp-path-dist"?>
    </references>
    <references title="Informative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5226"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4760"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5065"?>
    </references>
  </back>

</rfc>
