<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="rfc2629.xslt" ?>
<?rfc toc="no"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc iprnotified="yes" ?>
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="no" ?>
<?rfc colonspace="yes" ?>
<?rfc rfcedstyle="no" ?>
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<rfc category="std" docName="draft-jennings-energy-pricing-01"
     ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="Energy Pricing">Communication of Energy Price
    Information</title>

    <author fullname="Cullen Jennings" initials="C." surname="Jennings">
      <organization>Cisco</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>170 West Tasman Drive</street>

          <city>San Jose</city>

          <region>CA</region>

          <code>95134</code>

          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>

        <phone>+1 408 421-9990</phone>

        <email>fluffy@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Bruce Nordman" initials="B." surname="Nordman">
      <organization>Lawrence Berkeley National Laboratory</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>1 Cyclotron Road</street>

          <city>Berkeley</city>

          <region>CA</region>

          <code>94720</code>

          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>

        <email>BNordman@LBL.gov</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date day="10" month="July" year="2011" />

    <abstract>
      <t>This specification defines media types for representing the future
      price of energy in JSON. It also defines a way for a client device, such
      as a car, refrigerator, air conditioner, water heater, or
      display to discover a web server that can provide the future price for
      local electrical energy. This will allow the client device to make
      intelligent decisions about when to use energy, and enable price
      distribution when the building is off-grid. It enables obtaining price
      from a local or non-local price server.</t>

      <t>This draft is an early skeleton of a draft to start discussion around
      this idea.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Overview">
      <t>Many uses of energy can be shifted in time, or changed in quantity,
      based on price. Consider charging an electric car. For users that plug
      in cars at 9pm, they may not care when it actually charges, as long as
      it is ready at 8am when they need to go to work. This is a classic real
      time problem and can be optimized as long as the charger for the car has
      relevant information about how long it will take to charge and the cost
      of electricity between the current time and the time when the task needs
      to be complete.</t>

      <t>Other devices such as refrigerators, air conditioners, and washers
      can similarly shift load. For their primary temperature regulation
      function, they can lower their setpoint (for cooling devices) when costs
      are low, and increase it when costs are high. The amount of deviation
      from the base target is keyed to the value of the price, operational
      considerations (e.g. not letting food freeze or spoil), or other
      non-price information available (e.g. occupancy). Devices such as
      displays (TV or computer) or lights can dim in some proportion to the
      electricity price, to balance cost and functionality. Devices with
      user-oriented time-outs (e.g. when an occupancy sensor's lack of seeing
      anyone in a space leads to a light going off) can adjust the length of
      such time-outs in proportion to price. Periodic functions (e.g. a
      refrigerator defrost cycle) can be shifted to the lowest cost time in
      the relevant time horizon. In general, the end-use device itself usually
      has the most knowledge about how best to act, and the the best access to 
      internal actuators to accomplish the change.</t>

      <t>Development around &ldquo;Demand Response (DR)&rdquo; has been
      advancing since around 2000. Most work in that area involves sending
      signals from the grid (DR-service provider) to a large building
      (commercial/industrial) or large device within it, to request load
      shedding or load shifting. There are then financial arrangements to pay
      the building owner for the service. More recently, the DR community and
      regulators have turned to enabling dynamic pricing so that the price
      customers actually pay at the meter more closely corresponds to the
      actual costs that the utility faces. Prices can be sent from the grid to
      an end use device, or from the grid to a gateway device (could be the
      meter) that then sends the prices to end use devices.</t>

      <t>This specification defines a simple JSON<xref
      target="RFC4627"></xref>media type to provide the cost of energy at
      future points of time. It is an array of objects in which each object
      contains the time a new price will come into effect and the price at
      that time. JSON also defines a well known URL on a web server so that an
      HTTP client can retrieve this data. Finally as a way to automatically
      discover the web server, this specification defines a DHCP option to
      provide the host name of the web server.</t>

      <t>At this time, only electricity is contemplated, but other resources
      do plausibly have time-varying prices, such as centrally provided steam
      or hot/cold water. Any resource (e.g. water) could use this mechanism to
      have a local price to distribute. Resources with a local supply constraint
      will then have a local price to ensure a balance with demand.</t>

      <t>The base usage case for this specification is a time-varying
      electricity price with the current price and a set of future prices
      (confirmed or estimates), usually for a 24 hour period. This price comes
      from the electric utility. The price can be fetched directly from the
      utility. However, many alternate cases are also expected and supported.
      The building may have one entity (likely a piece of network equipment
      since it is always on already) that gets prices from the grid and all
      others get it from this building-local 'price server'. Both transactions
      use this mechanism.</t>

      <t>The operator of the building may choose to present a higher price to
      devices in the building to take into account carbon emissions or other
      pollution from generating electricity. The building may also have local
      generation and/or storage, whose state and operation may indicate
      changes in price. For example, a building with an excess of solar power
      on-site may sell marginal electricity back to the grid at a low price.
      This would suggest lowering the price until supply and demand in the
      building were approximately in balance.</t>

      <t>Some buildings operate off-grid, either all the time or
      intermittently. A building is a structure that uses resources and
      provides services. Common examples are homes, office, retail, and
      institutional buildings. Other building types include vehicles such as
      cars, ships, and airplanes. All these building types have electricity
      systems that would benefit from a price mechanism.</t>

      <t>There are other protocols designed to get prices from the grid to a
      building, particularly to a building control system. One example of
      these is OpenADR. This mechanism complements rather than replaces these
      other mechanisms.</t>

      <t>Electricity pricing has other aspects that complicate pricing. For
      example, in many places electricity use over a monthly billing period is
      sold in blocks, with the price increasing or decreasing with larger
      blocks depending on what the utility is trying to accomplish with the
      price. For example, the first five hundred kWh could be $0.10/kWh, the
      second 500 kWh $0.15, and so on. Thus, the monthly marginal price (what
      is paid if the consumption goes up or down modestly) is the last block
      used. This could be substantially different from an average price. There
      are many options for how utilities could combine blocks with dynamic
      prices. This specification is not attempting to provide a set of prices
      that are legally binding. Rather, it is intended to provide a simple and
      reasonably reliable set of prices that devices can use (when the
      alternative may be in fact no information at all).</t>

      <t>Consider a typical residence with broadband Internet and a
      residential gateway that gets its IP address via DHCP from the service
      provider. The service provider would provide the domain of the local
      power provider via DHCP. The residential gateway would get this and
      provide it in DHCP requests sent to the residential gateway. The
      residential gateway would also be able to override this, so if the
      consumer had arranged power from an alternative power provider, the name
      of that provider could be configured in the device.</t>

      <t>A device on the residential network, such as a dishwasher, could find
      the energy provider name via DHCP. The dishwasher would then make an
      HTTP GET request to the well known URI defined in this specification. In
      other words, it would do an HTTP GET to the
      /.well_known/electricity-price.json and would receive back an
      energyprice+json media type. For example</t>

      <figure>
        <artwork><![CDATA[
{
"currency" : "USD",
"prices":[
    { "time": "2011-04-12T23:20:00.00Z", "price": "0.028" },
    { "time": "2011-04-12T23:21:00.00Z", "price": "0.025" },
    { "time": "2011-04-12T23:22:00.00Z", "price": "0.021" }
]}]]></artwork>
      </figure>

      <t>The above example shows a case where at 21:00 UTC, the price falls
      from 2.8 cents per KWh to 2.5 cents per kWh. Using kWh is fixed.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Terminology">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
      document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
      target="RFC2119">RFC 2119</xref>.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Semantics">
      <t>Each media type carries a single JSON object that represents a set of
      prices and times. This object contains optional attributes described
      below and a mandatory array of one or more measurements.</t>

      <t><list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="validTill:">Time at which this data series will become
          invalid. UTC time in RFC 3339 format.</t>

          <t hangText="currency:">Optional. Specify currency in ISO 4217 [REF]
          currency code.</t>

          <t hangText="prices:">Array of price objects. Mandatory and there
          must be at least one object in the array. Objects MUST be ordered in
          this array by time.</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>Each price time object contains several attributes, some of which are
      optional and some of which are mandatory.</t>

      <t><list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="time:">Time this price becomes effective. UTC time in
          RFC 3339 format.</t>

          <t hangText="price:">Price per kWh. The cost of energy changes to
          this price at the time in this object and remains at this price
          until the time of the next object in the prices array.</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>Open Issue: What is the best representation for time?</t>

      <t>Open Issue: Is it OK that currency is optional?</t>

      <t>Open Issue: How many entries can the array have? It would be nice to
      have some maximum size.</t>

      <t>The price in the last entry in the series is ignored. That is, the
      purpose of the last entry is to close the time of the last period. While
      24 hours will be a typical time horizon, it could be shorter or
      longer.</t>

      <t>Question: Can the request have a start time (zero for the present),
      so that if there is a limit on array size, one can get the rest?</t>

      <t>Open Issue: should we be able to represent both buy and sell
      prices?</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Well Known URL ">
      <t>A client that implements this specification uses the path
      "//.well-known/electricity-price.json" for the resource name unless the
      client has been configured with an alternative path.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="DHCP">
      <t>Open Issues: Is DHCP the best approach to discovery or would
      something else be better?</t>
    </section>

    <section title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>Note to RFC Editor: Please replace all occurrences of "RFC-AAAA" with
      the RFC number of this specification.</t>

      <section title="Well-Known URI Registration">
        <t>IANA will make the following "Well Known URI" registration as
        described in RFC 5785:</t>

        <texttable>
          <ttcol></ttcol>

          <ttcol></ttcol>

          <c>URI suffix:</c>

          <c>electricity-price.json</c>

          <c>Change controller:</c>

          <c>IETF &lt;iesg@ietf.org&gt;</c>

          <c>Specification document(s):</c>

          <c>[RFC-AAAA]</c>

          <c>Related information:</c>

          <c>None</c>
        </texttable>
      </section>

      <section anchor="sec-dhcp" title="DHCP Options">
        <t>TBD</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="sec-iana-media" title="Media Type Registration">
        <t>The following registrations are done following the procedure
        specified in <xref target="RFC4288"></xref> and <xref
        target="RFC3023"></xref>.</t>

        <t>Note to RFC Editor: Please replace all occurrences of "RFC-AAAA"
        with the RFC number of this specification.</t>

        <section title="energyprice+json Media Type Registration">
          <t>TBD</t>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Mapping to OpenADR">
      <t>Lawrence Berkeley National Laboratory led the development of OpenADR
      initially (OpenADR v1.0), and it is now being formalized as an open
      standard through OASIS and national Smart Grid activity (OpenADR v2.0).
      At present, there are two relevant OASIS technical committees (TCs) that
      are relevant to the dynamic pricing (includes real-time prices)
      discussion: the Energy Interoperation TC (EI) and the Energy Market
      Information Exchange TC (EMIX). Each committee has a draft standard of
      the same name as the technical committee.</t>

      <t>The OpenADR v2.0 standard will become a subset of what EI produces.
      EMIX is charged with defining a standard abstract form of price
      signaling. The details of how to represent a price product is defined in
      EMIX<xref target="EMIX"></xref> (then EI<xref target="EI"></xref> would
      reference and build implementation models, for e.g., XML schemas).</t>

      <t>Both committees cover much more than just price (and price forecast)
      information. The discussion below focuses only on features relevant to
      this IETF specification. The OpenADR model uses XML as the data
      description language. OpenADR v1.0 and v2.0 can specify prices in
      different terms - absolute, multiple, or in relative terms to a base
      price (either additive or multiplicative).</t>

      <t>Pricing can be a very complicated topic, but for the discussion here,
      we limit it to what this specification does- a schedule of time periods
      and a price for each period.</t>

      <t>To represent time, EI and EMIX use WS-Calendar (also an OASIS
      standard), which provides for complex scheduling; simple price sequences
      use only a small part of this. Sequences are represented as a start time
      and a sequence of interval durations. As WS-Calendar builds on iCalendar
      (see RFC 5545) it uses the same date/time format as this draft.</t>

      <t>A related issue is how to specify the current time to assure that the
      price source and user of the price have consistent time (or know how to
      adjust the schedule for a difference in time). This discussion does not
      consider this topic. So long as prices do not vary significantly from
      one time period to the next, and the time differences are not large, this
      issue is not of great concern.</t>

      <t>EMIX can encode prices in several ways, including relative prices.
      For absolute prices, the price is simply a numeric value in cents/kWh
      for the U.S. Other additional attributes relevant to price
      representations are under consideration (e.g., currency). The following
      is a sample excerpt of an OpenADR v1.0 price schedule:</t>

      <figure>
        <artwork><![CDATA[
<p:drEventData>
  <p:notificationTime>2009-06-02T17:15:00.0</p:notificationTime>
  <p:startTime>2009-06-03T00:00:00.0</p:startTime>
  <p:endTime>2009-06-03T23:59:00.0</p:endTime>
  <p:eventInfoInstances>
     <p:eventInfoTypeID>PRICE_ABSOLUTE</p:eventInfoTypeID>
     <p:eventInfoName>Price</p:eventInfoName>
     <p:eventInfoValues>
        <p:value>0.0</p:value>
        <p:timeOffset>0</p:timeOffset>
     </p:eventInfoValues>
     <p:eventInfoValues>
        <p:value>0.0</p:value>
        <p:timeOffset>3600</p:timeOffset>
     </p:eventInfoValues>
     ...
     <p:eventInfoValues>
        <p:value>0.0</p:value>
        <p:timeOffset>82800</p:timeOffset>
     </p:eventInfoValues>
  </p:eventInfoInstances>
</p:drEventData>
]]></artwork>
      </figure>

      <t></t>

      <t>TBD - define a simple mapping to and from OpenADR.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Security Considerations">
      <t>TBD</t>

      <t>Further discussion of security proprieties for media types can be
      found in <xref target="sec-iana-media"></xref>.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Privacy Considerations">
      <t>TBD</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Acknowledgement">
      <t>We would like to thank Girish Ghatikar at LBNL for information and
      text about OpenADR. Thanks for helpful comments from many people
      including Scott Brim, &lt;get your name here&gt;. </t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <reference anchor="RFC4627">
        <front>
          <title>The application/json Media Type for JavaScript Object
          Notation (JSON)</title>

          <author fullname="D. Crockford" initials="D." surname="Crockford">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date month="July" year="2006" />

          <abstract>
            <t>JavaScript Object Notation (JSON) is a lightweight, text-based,
            language-independent data interchange format. It was derived from
            the ECMAScript Programming Language Standard. JSON defines a small
            set of formatting rules for the portable representation of
            structured data. This memo provides information for the Internet
            community.</t>
          </abstract>
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="4627" />

        <format octets="16319"
                target="http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc4627.txt" type="TXT" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RFC3023">
        <front>
          <title>XML Media Types</title>

          <author fullname="M. Murata" initials="M." surname="Murata">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="S. St. Laurent" initials="S."
                  surname="St. Laurent">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="D. Kohn" initials="D." surname="Kohn">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date month="January" year="2001" />

          <abstract>
            <t>This document standardizes five new media types -- text/xml,
            application/xml, text/xml-external-parsed-entity, application/xml-
            external-parsed-entity, and application/xml-dtd -- for use in
            exchanging network entities that are related to the Extensible
            Markup Language (XML). This document also standardizes a
            convention (using the suffix '+xml') for naming media types
            outside of these five types when those media types represent XML
            MIME (Multipurpose Internet Mail Extensions) entities. [STANDARDS
            TRACK]</t>
          </abstract>
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="3023" />

        <format octets="86011"
                target="http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc3023.txt" type="TXT" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RFC4288">
        <front>
          <title>Media Type Specifications and Registration Procedures</title>

          <author fullname="N. Freed" initials="N." surname="Freed">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="J. Klensin" initials="J." surname="Klensin">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date month="December" year="2005" />

          <abstract>
            <t>This document defines procedures for the specification and
            registration of media types for use in MIME and other Internet
            protocols. This document specifies an Internet Best Current
            Practices for the Internet Community, and requests discussion and
            suggestions for improvements.</t>
          </abstract>
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="BCP" value="13" />

        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="4288" />

        <format octets="52667"
                target="http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc4288.txt" type="TXT" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RFC2119">
        <front>
          <title abbrev="RFC Key Words">Key words for use in RFCs to Indicate
          Requirement Levels</title>

          <author fullname="Scott Bradner" initials="S." surname="Bradner">
            <organization>Harvard University</organization>

            <address>
              <postal>
                <street>1350 Mass. Ave.</street>

                <street>Cambridge</street>

                <street>MA 02138</street>
              </postal>

              <phone>- +1 617 495 3864</phone>

              <email>sob@harvard.edu</email>
            </address>
          </author>

          <date month="March" year="1997" />

          <area>General</area>

          <keyword>keyword</keyword>

          <abstract>
            <t>In many standards track documents several words are used to
            signify the requirements in the specification. These words are
            often capitalized. This document defines these words as they
            should be interpreted in IETF documents. Authors who follow these
            guidelines should incorporate this phrase near the beginning of
            their document: <list style="empty">
                <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL",
                "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and
                "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described
                in RFC 2119.</t>
              </list></t>

            <t>Note that the force of these words is modified by the
            requirement level of the document in which they are used.</t>
          </abstract>
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="BCP" value="14" />

        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="2119" />

        <format octets="4723"
                target="http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc2119.txt" type="TXT" />

        <format octets="17491"
                target="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/html/rfc2119.html"
                type="HTML" />

        <format octets="5777"
                target="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/xml/rfc2119.xml"
                type="XML" />
      </reference>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <reference anchor="EMIX"
                 target="http://www.oasis-open.org/committees/tc_home.php?wg_abbrev=emix">
        <front>
          <title>Energy Market Information Exchange (EMIX) Version 1.0,
          Committee Specification Draft 02 / Public Review Draft</title>

          <author>
            <organization>OASIS</organization>

            <address></address>
          </author>

          <date day="28" month="April" year="2011" />
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="EI"
                 target="http://www.oasis-open.org/committees/tc_home.php?wg_abbrev=energyinterop">
        <front>
          <title>Energy Interoperation Version 1.0, Committee Specification
          Draft 01</title>

          <author>
            <organization>OASIS</organization>

            <address></address>
          </author>

          <date day="26" month="November" year="2010" />
        </front>
      </reference>

      <!--
      
      <reference anchor="OpenADR" target="http://drrc.lbl.gov/publications/open-automated-demand-response-dynamic-pricing-technologies-and-demonstration">
        <front>
         <title>
          Ghatikar, Girish; Mathieu, Johanna; Piette, Mary Ann; Koch, Ed; Hennage, Dan;  'Open Automated Demand Response Dynamic Pricing Technologies and Demonstration', LBNL-3921E
         </title>
         <author >
          
           <address>            </address>
         </author>
         <date  year="2010"  />
        </front>
      </reference>
      
-->
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
