<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="rfc2629.xslt" ?>
<?rfc toc="no" ?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc iprnotified="no" ?>
<?rfc strict="no" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="no" ?>
<?rfc colonspace="yes" ?>
<?rfc rfcedstyle="yes"?>
<rfc category="bcp" docName="draft-jennings-errata-01" ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="Errata">IESG Errata Processing</title>

    <author fullname="Cullen Jennings" initials="C." surname="Jennings">
      <organization>Cisco</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>170 West Tasman Drive</street>

          <street>MS: SJC-21/2</street>

          <city>San Jose</city>

          <region>CA</region>

          <code>95134</code>

          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>

        <phone>+1 408 421-9990</phone>

        <email>fluffy@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date day="9" month="November" year="2009" />

    <area>GEN</area>

    <abstract>
      <t>This brief note discusses plans the IESG is considering on errata
      processing. It is not intended to become an RFC but is only a draft for
      the IESG to solicit input from the community on how the IESG to should
      handle errata.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>The RFC editor has instigated a new errata process and as part of
      this the IESG will need to decide how to approve errata. The IESG is
      considering the following guidelines to be used for approving errata on
      documents in the IETF stream.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Proposed IESG Statement">
      <t>These are strong guidelines and not immutable rules. Common sense and
      good judgment should be used by the IESG to decide what is the right
      thing to do. Errata are meant to fix "bugs" in the specification and
      should not be used to change what the community meant when it approved
      the RFC. These guidelines only apply to errata on RFCs in the IETF
      stream. They apply to new errata and not errata that have already been
      approved.</t>

      <t>After an erratum is reported, a report will be sent to the authors,
      chairs, and Area Directors (ADs) of the WG in which it originated. If
      the WG has closed or the document was not associated with a WG, then the
      report will be sent to the ADs for the Area most closely associated to
      the subject matter. The ADs are responsible for ensuring review; they
      may delegate the review or perform it personally. The reviewer will
      classify the erratum as falling under one of the following states: <list
          style="symbols">
          <t>Approved - The erratum is appropriate under the criteria below
          and should be available to implementors or people deploying the
          RFC.</t>

          <t>Rejected - The erratum is in error, or proposes a change to the
          RFC that should be done my publishing a new RFC that replaces the
          current RFC. In the latter case, if the change is to be considered
          for future updates of the document, it should be proposed using
          channels other than the errata process, such as a WG mailing
          list.</t>

          <t>Hold for Document Update - The erratum is not a necessary update
          to the RFC. However, any future update of the document might
          consider this erratum, and determine whether it is correct and
          merits including in the update.</t>
        </list> Guidelines for review are: <list style="numbers">
          <t>Only errors that could cause implementation or deployment
          problems or significant confusion should be Approved.</t>

          <t>Things that are clearly wrong but could not cause an
          implementation or deployment problem should be Hold for Document
          Update.</t>

          <t>Errata on obsolete RFCs should be treated the same as errata on
          RFCs that are not obsolete where there is strong evidence that some
          people are still making use of the related technology.</t>

          <t>Trivial grammar corrections should be Hold for Document
          Update.</t>

          <t>Typographical errors which would not cause any confusions to
          implementation or deployments should be Hold for Document
          Update.</t>

          <t>Changes which are simply stylistic issues or simply make things
          read better should be Hold for Document Update.</t>

          <t>Changes that modify the working of a protocol to something that
          might be different from the intended consensus when the document was
          approved should be either Hold for Document Update or Rejected.
          Deciding between these two depends on judgment. Changes that are
          clearly modifications to the intended consensus, or involve large
          textual changes, should be Rejected. In unclear situations, small
          changes can be Hold for Document Update.</t>

          <t>Changes that modify the working of a process, such as changing an
          IANA registration procedure, to something that might be different
          from the intended consensus when the document was approved should be
          Rejected.</t>
        </list></t>
    </section>

    <section title="Suggested Tool Changes">
      <t>Future RFC&rsquo;s from IETF track should include a line that tell
      people reading the RFC were they might find errata. When the RFC was
      first published it would include text along the lines of:</t>

      <t><list style="empty">
          <t>There may be errata and other information for this RFC which can
          be found at http://www.rfc-editor.org/errata/rfcXXXX</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>This errata list should show just Approved errata on the first page -
      perhaps with links to pages with other types such as Rejected or Hold
      for Document Update.</t>

      <t>When searching for all errata it would be nice to be able to filter
      by area and by working group name. It would also be nice to be able to
      filter on Type and Status. Ideally the results of a search could be
      sorted by Date-Reported, RFC number, or by errata submitter name.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>This draft has no IANA considerations.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Acknowledgements and Thanks">
      <t>Several members of IESG sent comments but special thanks to Sandy
      Ginoza who found and fixed many mistakes in this text.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Security Considerations">
      <t>Too many to discuss.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back></back>
</rfc>
