<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="rfc2629.xslt" ?>
<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc iprnotified="yes" ?>
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="no" ?>
<?rfc colonspace="yes" ?>
<?rfc rfcedstyle="no" ?>
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<rfc category="std" docName="draft-jennings-mmusic-adjacent-grouping-00"
     ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="SDP Adjacent Grouping">Grouping of Adjacent Media in
    SDP</title>

    <author fullname="Cullen Jennings" initials="C." surname="Jennings">
      <organization>Cisco</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>170 West Tasman Drive</street>

          <city>San Jose</city>

          <region>CA</region>

          <code>95134</code>

          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>

        <phone>+1 408 421-9990</phone>

        <email>fluffy@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date day="21" month="September" year="2010" />

    <area>RAI</area>

    <abstract>
      <t>Applications, such as multiple screen teleconference systems, often
      have multiple video streams that are organized to be displayed side by
      side. This specification defines uses the RFC 5888 grouping semantics to
      define a new group type that indicates that multiple audio or video
      streams may be rendered side by side and also indicates the relative
      ordering of streams.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>There are many situations where applications create media streams
      that are meant do be displayed adjacent to each other. A common example
      is a multi screen teleconference system. Another examples are several
      video monitors placed side by side to display signs, and audio streams
      from a linear array of microphones. SDP <xref target="RFC4566"></xref>
      allows negotiation of multiple media streams but does not have a way to
      carry the ordering information to indicate which media stream are
      adjacent to each other.</t>

      <t>This specification defines a new group, using the SDP grouping
      framework defined in <xref target="RFC5888"></xref> that indicates media
      streams are adjacent, and the adjacency order is defined by the order of
      the entires in the group.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Terminology">
      <t>This specification uses all the terms defined in <xref
      target="RFC5888"></xref> and will not make sense unless you have read
      RFC 5888. The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", and
      "MAY" in this specification are to be interpreted as described in <xref
      target="RFC2119"></xref>.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Semantics">
      <t>This specification defines a new SDP group attribute of "ADJ" that
      indicates the media stream in this group are meant to be displayed
      adjacently. Furthermore, the order of media streams in the group
      indicates the display order. The first stream in the group MUST be the
      left most media stream then working to the right or clockwise from point
      of view of person viewing the media.</t>

      <section title="Use in Offer/Answer systems">
        <t>The offer MUST contains the senders desired layout. If the system
        sending the Answer supports this specification, then the Answer SHOULD
        indicate the actual layout selected.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Examples">
      <t>A telepresence system with three screen and six audio channels, sends
      an SIP Offer to a two video conferencing system that with two screens
      that support stereo audio. The following figure shows a top down view of
      the room with the telepresence system that is sending the Offer. Screen
      A is the left most screen for the user in this room but should be
      displayed as the rightmost screen for user at the far end. The M1 to M6
      indicate the placement of the audio microphones for the six streams of
      audio.</t>

      <figure>
        <artwork><![CDATA[
  Screen A      Screen B     Screen C 
[----------][------------][------------] 
 M1      M2  M3        M4  M5        M6 


                 User

]]></artwork>
      </figure>

      <t>Assume the SDP mid values for the screens are sa, sb, and sc, for
      screens a to c respectively and the audio streams have mid values m1 to
      m6. The offer would contain the following in the SDP:</t>

      <figure>
        <artwork><![CDATA[    
    a=group:ADJ sc sb sa  
    a=group:ADJ m6 m5 m4 m3 m2 m1 
]]></artwork>
      </figure>

      <t>There might be other media streams, such as presentation video, that
      are not part of any adjacency group. If the far end decided to only
      accept the video from screen A and scene B and takes the audio from M1
      and m6. The answer would contain the following in the SDP:</t>

      <figure>
        <artwork><![CDATA[   
    a=group:ADJ sb sa 
    a=group:ADJ m6 m1 
]]></artwork>
      </figure>

      <t>As a note to implementors, consider the case where each screen had
      two media flows that were in the same FID group. In this case all the
      media streams are still listed in the ADJ group and the order of two
      streams in the same FID group can be arbitrarily picked as they will be
      displayed on the same device.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>This specification, following the Standards Action policy from <xref
      target="RFC5226"></xref>, adds the following entry to the "Semantics for
      the group SDP Attribute" registry defined by <xref
      target="RFC5888"></xref>. [Note to RFC Editor: Please replace RFC-AAAA
      with the RFC number for this specification.]</t>

      <t></t>

      <figure>
        <artwork><![CDATA[
Semantics                         Token Reference 
--------------------------------- ----- ----------- 
Adjacent Media                    ADJ   RFC-AAAA
]]></artwork>
      </figure>

      <t></t>
    </section>

    <section title="Security Considerations">
      <t>Like all SDP, integrity of this information is important. When caring
      SDP in SIP, mechanisms such as TLS can provide hop by confidentiality
      and integrity. End to end integrity can be provided by <xref
      target="RFC4474"></xref>.</t>

      <t>Further discussion of security proprieties can be found in <xref
      target="RFC4566"></xref>.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>I would like to thank Flemming Andreasen, Allyn Romanow, and &lt;get
      your name here&gt; for their review comments.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <reference anchor="RFC5888">
        <front>
          <title>The Session Description Protocol (SDP) Grouping
          Framework</title>

          <author fullname="G. Camarillo" initials="G." surname="Camarillo">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="H. Schulzrinne" initials="H."
                  surname="Schulzrinne">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date month="June" year="2010" />

          <abstract>
            <t>In this specification, we define a framework to group "m" lines
            in the Session Description Protocol (SDP) for different purposes.
            This framework uses the "group" and "mid" SDP attributes, both of
            which are defined in this specification. Additionally, we specify
            how to use the framework for two different purposes: for lip
            synchronization and for receiving a media flow consisting of
            several media streams on different transport addresses. This
            document obsoletes RFC 3388. [STANDARDS TRACK]</t>
          </abstract>
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="5888" />

        <format octets="43924"
                target="http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc5888.txt" type="TXT" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RFC4566">
        <front>
          <title>SDP: Session Description Protocol</title>

          <author fullname="M. Handley" initials="M." surname="Handley">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="V. Jacobson" initials="V." surname="Jacobson">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="C. Perkins" initials="C." surname="Perkins">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date month="July" year="2006" />

          <abstract>
            <t>This memo defines the Session Description Protocol (SDP). SDP
            is intended for describing multimedia sessions for the purposes of
            session announcement, session invitation, and other forms of
            multimedia session initiation. [STANDARDS TRACK]</t>
          </abstract>
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="4566" />

        <format octets="108820"
                target="http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc4566.txt" type="TXT" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RFC2119">
        <front>
          <title abbrev="RFC Key Words">Key words for use in RFCs to Indicate
          Requirement Levels</title>

          <author fullname="Scott Bradner" initials="S." surname="Bradner">
            <organization>Harvard University</organization>

            <address>
              <postal>
                <street>1350 Mass. Ave.</street>

                <street>Cambridge</street>

                <street>MA 02138</street>
              </postal>

              <phone>- +1 617 495 3864</phone>

              <email>sob@harvard.edu</email>
            </address>
          </author>

          <date month="March" year="1997" />

          <area>General</area>

          <keyword>keyword</keyword>

          <abstract>
            <t>In many standards track documents several words are used to
            signify the requirements in the specification. These words are
            often capitalized. This document defines these words as they
            should be interpreted in IETF documents. Authors who follow these
            guidelines should incorporate this phrase near the beginning of
            their document: <list style="empty">
                <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL",
                "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and
                "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described
                in RFC 2119.</t>
              </list></t>

            <t>Note that the force of these words is modified by the
            requirement level of the document in which they are used.</t>
          </abstract>
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="BCP" value="14" />

        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="2119" />

        <format octets="4723"
                target="http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc2119.txt" type="TXT" />

        <format octets="17491"
                target="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/html/rfc2119.html"
                type="HTML" />

        <format octets="5777"
                target="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/xml/rfc2119.xml"
                type="XML" />
      </reference>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <reference anchor="RFC4474">
        <front>
          <title>Enhancements for Authenticated Identity Management in the
          Session Initiation Protocol (SIP)</title>

          <author fullname="J. Peterson" initials="J." surname="Peterson">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="C. Jennings" initials="C." surname="Jennings">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date month="August" year="2006" />

          <abstract>
            <t>The existing security mechanisms in the Session Initiation
            Protocol (SIP) are inadequate for cryptographically assuring the
            identity of the end users that originate SIP requests, especially
            in an interdomain context. This document defines a mechanism for
            securely identifying originators of SIP messages. It does so by
            defining two new SIP header fields, Identity, for conveying a
            signature used for validating the identity, and Identity-Info, for
            conveying a reference to the certificate of the signer. [STANDARDS
            TRACK]</t>
          </abstract>
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="4474" />

        <format octets="104952"
                target="http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc4474.txt" type="TXT" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RFC5226">
        <front>
          <title>Guidelines for Writing an IANA Considerations Section in
          RFCs</title>

          <author fullname="T. Narten" initials="T." surname="Narten">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="H. Alvestrand" initials="H." surname="Alvestrand">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date month="May" year="2008" />

          <abstract>
            <t>Many protocols make use of identifiers consisting of constants
            and other well-known values. Even after a protocol has been
            defined and deployment has begun, new values may need to be
            assigned (e.g., for a new option type in DHCP, or a new encryption
            or authentication transform for IPsec). To ensure that such
            quantities have consistent values and interpretations across all
            implementations, their assignment must be administered by a
            central authority. For IETF protocols, that role is provided by
            the Internet Assigned Numbers Authority (IANA).&lt;/t&gt;&lt;t&gt;
            In order for IANA to manage a given namespace prudently, it needs
            guidelines describing the conditions under which new values can be
            assigned or when modifications to existing values can be made. If
            IANA is expected to play a role in the management of a namespace,
            IANA must be given clear and concise instructions describing that
            role. This document discusses issues that should be considered in
            formulating a policy for assigning values to a namespace and
            provides guidelines for authors on the specific text that must be
            included in documents that place demands on
            IANA.&lt;/t&gt;&lt;t&gt; This document obsoletes RFC 2434. This
            document specifies an Internet Best Current Practices for the
            Internet Community, and requests discussion and suggestions for
            improvements.</t>
          </abstract>
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="BCP" value="26" />

        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="5226" />

        <format octets="66160"
                target="http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc5226.txt" type="TXT" />
      </reference>
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
