<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='http://xml.resource.org/authoring/rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<!-- Alterations to I-D/RFC boilerplate -->
<?rfc private="" ?>
<!-- Default private="" Produce an internal memo 2.5pp shorter than an I-D or RFC -->
<?rfc rfcprocack="yes" ?>
<!-- Default rfcprocack="no" add a short sentence acknowledging xml2rfc -->
<?rfc strict="no" ?>
<!-- Default strict="no" Don't check I-D nits -->
<?rfc rfcedstyle="yes" ?>
<!-- Default rfcedstyle="yes" attempt to closely follow finer details from the latest observable RFC-Editor style -->
<!-- IETF process -->
<?rfc iprnotified="no" ?>
<!-- Default iprnotified="no" I haven't disclosed existence of IPR to IETF -->
<!-- ToC format -->
<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<!-- Default toc="no" No Table of Contents -->
<!-- Cross referencing, footnotes, comments -->
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<!-- Default symrefs="no" Don't use anchors, but use numbers for refs -->
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<!-- Default sortrefs="no" Don't sort references into order -->
<?rfc comments="yes" ?>
<!-- Default comments="no" Don't render comments -->
<?rfc inline="no" ?>
<!-- Default inline="no" if comments is "yes", then render comments inline; otherwise render them in an `Editorial Comments' section -->
<!-- Pagination control -->
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<!-- Default compact="no" Start sections on new pages -->
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<!-- Default subcompact="(as compact setting)" yes/no is not quite as compact as yes/yes -->
<!-- HTML formatting control -->
<?rfc emoticonic="yes" ?>
<!-- Default emoticonic="no" Doesn't prettify HTML format -->
<rfc category="bcp" docName="draft-briscoe-tsvwg-ecn-encap-guidelines-03"
     ipr="trust200902" updates="3819">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="ECN Encapsulation Guidelines">Guidelines for Adding
    Congestion Notification to Protocols that Encapsulate IP</title>

    <author fullname="Bob Briscoe" initials="B." surname="Briscoe">
      <organization>BT</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>B54/77, Adastral Park</street>

          <street>Martlesham Heath</street>

          <city>Ipswich</city>

          <code>IP5 3RE</code>

          <country>UK</country>
        </postal>

        <phone>+44 1473 645196</phone>

        <email>bob.briscoe@bt.com</email>

        <uri>http://bobbriscoe.net/</uri>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="John Kaippallimalil" initials="J."
            surname="Kaippallimalil">
      <organization>Huawei</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>5340 Legacy Drive, Suite 175</street>

          <city>Plano</city>

          <region>Texas</region>

          <code>75024</code>

          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>

        <email>john.kaippallimalil@huawei.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Pat Thaler" initials="P." surname="Thaler">
      <organization>Broadcom Corporation</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>5025 Keane Drive</street>

          <city>Carmichael</city>

          <region>CA</region>

          <code>95608</code>

          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>

        <email>pthaler@broadcom.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date day="17" month="September" year="2013"/>

    <area>Transport</area>

    <workgroup>Transport Area Working Group</workgroup>

    <keyword>Congestion Control and Management</keyword>

    <keyword>Congestion Notification</keyword>

    <keyword>Information Security</keyword>

    <keyword>Tunnelling</keyword>

    <keyword>Encapsulation &amp; Decapsulation</keyword>

    <keyword>Protocol</keyword>

    <keyword>ECN</keyword>

    <keyword>Layering</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>The purpose of this document is to guide the design of congestion
      notification in any lower layer or tunnelling protocol that encapsulates
      IP. The aim is for explicit congestion signals to propagate consistently
      from lower layer protocols into IP. Then the IP internetwork layer can
      act as a portability layer to carry congestion notification from
      non-IP-aware congested nodes up to the transport layer (L4). Following
      these guidelines should assure interworking between new lower layer
      congestion notification mechanisms, whether specified by the IETF or
      other standards bodies.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <!-- ================================================================ -->

  <middle>
    <!-- ================================================================ -->

    <section anchor="ecnencap_Introduction" title="Introduction">
      <t>Explicit Congestion Notification (ECN <xref target="RFC3168"/>) is
      defined in the IP header (v4 &amp; v6) to allow a resource to notify the
      onset of queue build-up without having to drop packets, by explicitly
      marking a proportion of packets with the congestion experienced (CE)
      codepoint.<!--In the layered model of communication, each layer accepts requests to forward PDUs and eventually returns 
a status code to the higher layer. Without ECN, each layer returns either a 'delivered' status code or an 
implicit 'not delivered'. Explicit notification of congestion adds a useful 'delivered but congestion 
experienced' status code to each layer interface.--></t>

      <t>ECN removes nearly all congestion loss and it cuts delays for two
      main reasons: i) it avoids the delay when recovering from congestion
      losses, which particularly benefits small flows, making their completion
      time predictably short <xref target="RFC2884"/>; and ii) as ECN is used
      more widely by end-systems, it will gradually remove the need to
      configure a degree of delay into buffers before they start to notify
      congestion (the cause of bufferbloat). The latter delay is because drop
      involves a trade-off between sending a timely signal and trying to avoid
      impairment, whereas ECN is solely a signal not an impairment, so there
      is no harm triggering it earlier.</t>

      <t>Some lower layer technologies (e.g. MPLS, Ethernet) are used to form
      large subnetworks with IP-aware nodes only at the edges. These networks
      are often designed so that it is rare for interior queues to overflow.
      However, this has often only been possible because the original design
      of TCP did not scale, and fixes (e.g. <xref target="RFC1323"/>) proved
      hard to deploy. Now that modern operating systems are finally capable of
      saturating inerior links, even the buffers of well-provisioned interior
      switches will need to signal episodes of queuing. However, the above
      benefits of ECN can only be fully realised if support for ECN is added
      to the relevant subnetwork technology, as well as IP. When a lower layer
      queue drops a packet it does not just drop at that layer; the packet
      disappears from all layers. In contrast, when a lower layer marks a
      packet with ECN, the marking needs to be explicitly propagated up the
      layers.</t>

      <t>Propagation of ECN is defined for MPLS <xref target="RFC5129"/>, and
      is being defined for TRILL <xref target="trill-rbridge-options"/>, but
      it remains to be defined for a number of other subnetwork
      technologies.</t>

      <t>Similarly, ECN propagation is yet to be defined for many tunnelling
      protocols. <xref target="RFC6040"/> defines how ECN should be propagated
      for IP-in-IP <xref target="RFC2003"/> and IPsec <xref target="RFC4301"/>
      tunnels. However, as Section 9.3 of RFC3168 pointed out, ECN support
      will need to be defined for other tunnelling protocols, e.g. L2TP <xref
      target="RFC2661"/>, GRE [<xref format="counter" target="RFC1701"/>,
      <xref format="counter" target="RFC2784"/>], PPTP <xref
      target="RFC2637"/> and GTP [<xref format="counter" target="GTPv1"/>,
      <xref format="counter" target="GTPv1-U"/>, <xref format="counter"
      target="GTPv2-C"/>].<!--Add PMIP (Proxy Mobile IPv6) [RFC5213]?--></t>

      <t>The purpose of this document is to guide the addition of congestion
      notification to any subnet technology or tunnelling protocol, so that
      lower layer equipment can signal congestion explicitly and it will
      propagate consistently into encapsulated (higher layer) headers,
      otherwise the signals will not reach their ultimate destination.</t>

      <t>Incremental deployment is the most tricky aspect when adding support
      for ECN. The original ECN protocol in IP <xref target="RFC3168"/> was
      carefully designed so that a congested buffer would not mark a packet
      (rather than drop it) unless both source and destination hosts were
      ECN-capable. Otherwise its congestion markings would never be detected
      and congestion would just deteriorate further. However, to support
      congestion marking below the IP layer, it is not sufficient to only
      check that the two end-points support ECN; correct operation also
      depends on the decapsulator at each subnet egress faithfully propagating
      congestion notifications to the higher layer. Otherwise, a legacy
      decapsulator might silently fail to propagate any ECN signals from the
      outer to the forwarded header. Then the lost signals would never be
      detected and again congestion would deteriorate further. The guidelines
      given later require protocol designers to carefully consider incremental
      deployment, and suggest various safe approaches for different
      circumstances.</t>

      <t>Of course, the IETF does not have standards authority over every link
      layer protocol. So this document gives guidelines for designing
      propagation of congestion notification across the interface between IP
      and protocols that may encapsulate IP (i.e. that can be layered beneath
      IP). Each lower layer technology will exhibit different issues and
      compromises, so the IETF or the relevant standards body must be free to
      define the specifics of each lower layer congestion notification scheme.
      Nonetheless, if the guidelines are followed, congestion notification
      should interwork between different technologies, using IP in its role as
      a 'portability layer'.</t>

      <t>Therefore, the capitalised term 'SHOULD' or 'SHOULD NOT' are often
      used in preference to 'MUST' or 'MUST NOT', because it is difficult to
      know the compromises that will be necessary in each protocol design. If
      a particular protocol design chooses to contradict a 'SHOULD (NOT)'
      given in the advice below, it MUST include a sound justification.</t>

      <t>It has not been possible to give common guidelines for all lower
      layer technologies, because they do not all fit a common pattern.
      Instead they have been divided into a few distinct modes of operation:
      feed-forward-and-upward; feed-upward-and-forward; feed-backward; and
      null mode. These modes are described in <xref target="ecnencap_Modes"/>,
      then in the following sections separate guidelines are given for each
      mode.</t>

      <t>This document updates the advice to subnetwork designers about ECN in
      Section 13 of <xref target="RFC3819"/>.</t>

      <section anchor="ecnencap_Scope" title="Scope">
        <t>This document only concerns wire protocol processing of explicit
        notification of congestion and makes no changes or recommendations
        concerning algorithms for congestion marking or for congestion
        response (algorithm issues should be independent of the layer the
        algorithm operates in).</t>

        <t>The question of congestion notification signals with different
        semantics to those of ECN in IP is touched on in a couple of specific
        cases (e.g. QCN <xref target="IEEE802.1Qau"/>) and with schemes with
        multiple severity levels such as PCN <xref target="RFC6660"/>).
        However, no attempt is made to give guidelines about schemes with
        different semantics that are yet to be invented.</t>

        <t>The semantics of congestion signals can be relative to the traffic
        class. Therefore correct propagation of congestion signals could
        depend on correct propagation of any traffic class field between the
        layers. In this document, correct propagation of traffic class
        information is assumed, while what 'correct' means and how it is
        achieved is covered elsewhere (e.g. <xref target="RFC2983"/>) and is
        outside the scope of the present document.</t>

        <t>Note that these guidelines do not require the subnet wire protocol
        to be changed to accommodate congestion notification. Another way to
        add congestion notification without consuming header space in the
        subnet protocol might be to use a parallel control plane protocol.</t>

        <t>This document focuses on the congestion notification interface
        between IP and lower layer protocols that can encapsulate IP, where
        the term 'IP' includes v4 or v6, unicast, multicast or anycast.
        However, it is likely that the guidelines will also be useful when a
        lower layer protocol or tunnel encapsulates itself (e.g. Ethernet MAC
        in MAC <xref target="IEEE802.1Qah"/>) or when it encapsulates other
        protocols. In the feed-backward mode, propagation of congestion
        signals for multicast and anycast packets is out-of-scope (because it
        would be so complicated that it is hoped no-one would attempt such an
        abomination).</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <!-- ================================================================ -->

    <section anchor="ecnencap_Reqs_Language" title="Terminology">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
      document are to be interpreted as described in RFC 2119 <xref
      target="RFC2119"/>.</t>

      <t>Further terminology used within this document:<list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="Protocol data unit (PDU):">Information that is
          delivered as a unit among peer entities of a layered network
          consisting of protocol control information (typically a header) and
          possibly user data (payload) of that layer. The scope of this
          document includes layer 2 and layer 3 networks, where the PDU is
          respectively termed a frame or a packet (or a cell in ATM). PDU is a
          general term for any of these. This definition also includes a
          payload with a shim header lying somewhere between layer 2 &amp;
          3.</t>

          <t hangText="Transport:">The end-to-end transmission control
          function, conventionally considered at layer-4 in the OSI reference
          model. Given the audience for this document will often use the word
          transport to mean low level bit carriage, whenever the term is used
          it will be qualified, e.g. 'L4 transport'.</t>

          <t hangText="Encapsulator:">The link or tunnel endpoint function
          that adds an outer header to a PDU (also termed the 'link ingress',
          the 'subnet ingress', the 'ingress tunnel endpoint' or just the
          'ingress' where the context is clear).</t>

          <t hangText="Decapsulator:">The link or tunnel endpoint function
          that removes an outer header from a PDU (also termed the 'link
          egress', the 'subnet egress', the 'egress tunnel endpoint' or just
          the 'egress' where the context is clear).</t>

          <t hangText="Incoming header:">The header of an arriving PDU before
          encapsulation.</t>

          <t hangText="Outer header:">The header added to encapsulate a
          PDU.</t>

          <t hangText="Inner header:">The header encapsulated by the outer
          header.</t>

          <t hangText="Outgoing header:">The header forwarded by the
          decapsulator.</t>

          <t hangText="CE:">Congestion Experienced <xref
          target="RFC3168"/></t>

          <t hangText="ECT:">ECN-Capable Transport <xref
          target="RFC3168"/></t>

          <t hangText="Not-ECT:">Not ECN-Capable Transport <xref
          target="RFC3168"/></t>

          <t hangText="ECN-PDU:">A PDU that is part of a feedback loop within
          which all the nodes that need to propagate explicit congestion
          notifications back to the Load Regulator are ECN-capable. An IP
          packet with a non-zero ECN field implies that the endpoints are
          ECN-capable, so this would be an ECN-PDU. However, ECN-PDU is
          intended to be a general term for a PDU at any layer, not just
          IP.</t>

          <t hangText="Not-ECN-PDU:">A PDU that is part of a feedback-loop
          within which some nodes necessary to propagate explicit congestion
          notifications back to the load regulator are not ECN-capable.</t>

          <t hangText="Load Regulator:">For each flow of PDUs, the transport
          function that is capable of controlling the data rate. Typically
          located at the data source, but in-path nodes can regulate load in
          some congestion control arrangements (e.g. admission control or
          policing nodes). Note the term "a function capable of controlling
          the load" deliberately includes a transport that doesn't actually
          control the load but ideally it ought to (e.g. a sending application
          without congestion control that uses UDP).</t>

          <t hangText="Congestion Baseline:">The location of the function on
          the path that initialised the values of all congestion notification
          fields in a sequence of packets, before any are set to the
          congestion experienced (CE) codepoint if they experience congestion
          further downstream. Typically the original data source at
          layer-4.</t>
        </list></t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="ecnencap_Modes" title="Modes of Operation">
      <t>This section sets down the different modes by which congestion
      information is passed between the lower layer and the higher one. It
      acts as a reference framework for the following sections, which give
      normative guidelines for designers of explicit congestion notification
      protocols, taking each mode in turn:<list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="Feed-Forward-and-Up:">Nodes feed forward congestion
          notification towards the egress within the lower layer then up and
          along the layers towards the end-to-end destination at the transport
          layer. The following local optimisation is possible:<list
              style="hanging">
              <t hangText="Feed-Up-and-Forward:">A lower layer switch feeds-up
              congestion notification directly into the ECN field in the
              higher layer (e.g. IP) header, irrespective of whether the node
              is at the egress of a subnet.</t>
            </list></t>

          <t hangText="Feed-Backward:">Nodes feed back congestion signals
          towards the ingress of the lower layer and (optionally) attempt to
          control congestion within their own layer.</t>

          <t hangText="Null:">Nodes cannot experience congestion at the lower
          layer except at ingress nodes (which are IP-aware or equivalently
          higher-layer-aware).</t>
        </list></t>

      <section anchor="ecnencap_Forward" title="Feed-Forward-and-Up Mode">
        <t>Like IP and MPLS, many subnet technologies are based on
        self-contained protocol data units (PDUs) or frames sent unreliably.
        They provide no feedback channel at the subnetwork layer, instead
        relying on higher layers (e.g. TCP) to feed back loss signals.</t>

        <t>In these cases, ECN may best be supported by standardising explicit
        notification of congestion into the lower layer protocol that carries
        the data forwards. It will then also be necessary to define how the
        egress of the lower layer subnet propagates this explicit signal into
        the forwarded upper layer (IP) header. It can then continue forwards
        until it finally reaches the destination transport (at L4). Then
        typically the destination will feed this congestion notification back
        to the source transport using an end-to-end protocol (e.g. TCP). This
        is the arrangement that has already been used to add ECN to IP-in-IP
        tunnels <xref target="RFC6040"/>, IP-in-MPLS and MPLS-in-MPLS <xref
        target="RFC5129"/>.</t>

        <t>This mode is illustrated in <xref
        target="ecnencap_Fig_Feed-Forward-and-Up"/>. Along the middle of the
        figure, layers 2, 3 &amp; 4 of the protocol stack are shown, and one
        packet is shown along the bottom as it progresses across the network
        from source to destination, crossing two subnets connected by a
        router, and crossing two switches on the path across each subnet.
        Congestion at the output of the first switch (shown as *) leads to a
        congestion marking in the L2 header (shown as C in the illustration of
        the packet). The chevrons show the progress of the resulting
        congestion indication. It is propagated from link to link across the
        subnet in the L2 header, then when the router removes the marked L2
        header, it propagates the marking up into the L3 (IP) header. The
        router forwards the marked L3 header into subnet 2, and when it adds a
        new L2 header it copies the L3 marking into the L2 header as well, as
        shown by the 'C's in both layers (assuming the technology of subnet 2
        also supports explicit congestion marking).</t>

        <t>Note that there is no implication that each 'C' marking is encoded
        the same; a different encoding might be used for the 'C' marking in
        each protocol.</t>

        <t>Finally, for completeness, we show the L3 marking arriving at the
        destination, where the host transport protocol (e.g. TCP) feeds it
        back to the source in the L4 acknowledgement (the 'C' at L4 in the
        packet at the top of the diagram).</t>

        <figure align="center" anchor="ecnencap_Fig_Feed-Forward-and-Up"
                title="Feed-Forward-and-Up Mode">
          <artwork><![CDATA[                     _ _ _ 
          /_______  | | |C|  ACK Packet (V)
          \         |_|_|_|
 +---+        layer: 2 3 4 header                            +---+
 |  <|<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<< Packet V <<<<<<<<<<<<<|<< |L4
 |   |                         +---+                         | ^ |
 |   | . . . . . . Packet U. . | >>|>>> Packet U >>>>>>>>>>>>|>^ |L3
 |   |     +---+     +---+     | ^ |     +---+     +---+     |   |
 |   |     |  *|>>>>>|>>>|>>>>>|>^ |     |   |     |   |     |   |L2
 |___|_____|___|_____|___|_____|___|_____|___|_____|___|_____|___|
 source          subnet A      router       subnet B         dest
     __ _ _ _    __ _ _ _    __ _ _        __ _ _ _
    |  | | | |  |  | | |C|  |  | |C|      |  | |C|C|  Data________\
    |__|_|_|_|  |__|_|_|_|  |__|_|_|      |__|_|_|_|  Packet (U)  /
 layer: 4 3 2A      4 3 2A      4 3           4 3 2B
 header]]></artwork>
        </figure>

        <t>Of course, modern networks are rarely as simple as this text-book
        example, often involving multiple nested layers. For example, a 3GPP
        mobile network may have two IP-in-IP (GTP) tunnels in series and an
        MPLS backhaul between the base station and the first router.
        Nonetheless, the example illustrates the general idea of feeding
        congestion notification forward then upward whenever a header is
        removed at the egress of a subnet.</t>

        <t>Note that the FECN (forward ECN) bit in Frame Relay and the
        explicit forward congestion indication (EFCI <xref
        target="ITU-T.I.371"/>) bit in ATM user data cells follow a
        feed-forward pattern. However, in ATM, this is only as part of a
        feed-forward-and-backward pattern at the lower layer, not
        feed-forward-and-up out of the lower layer&mdash;the intention was
        never to interface to IP ECN at the subnet egress. To our knowledge,
        Frame Relay FECN is solely used to detect where more capacity should
        be provisioned <xref target="Buck00"/>.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="ecnencap_Up" title="Feed-Up-and-Forward Mode">
        <t>Ethernet is particularly difficult to extend incrementally to
        support explicit congestion notification. One way to support ECN in
        such cases has been to use so called 'layer-3 switches'. These are
        Ethernet switches that bury into the Ethernet payload to find an IP
        header and manipulate or act on certain IP fields (specifically
        Diffserv &amp; ECN). For instance, in Data Center TCP <xref
        target="DCTCP"/>, layer-3 switches are configured to mark the ECN
        field of the IP header within the Ethernet payload when their output
        buffer becomes congested. With respect to switching, a layer-3 switch
        acts solely on the addresses in the Ethernet header; it doesn't use IP
        addresses, and it doesn't decrement the TTL field in the IP
        header.</t>

        <figure align="center" anchor="ecnencap_Fig_Feed-Up"
                title="Feed-Up-and-Forward Mode">
          <artwork><![CDATA[                     _ _ _ 
          /_______  | | |C|  ACK packet (V)
          \         |_|_|_|
 +---+        layer: 2 3 4 header                            +---+
 |  <|<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<< Packet V <<<<<<<<<<<<<|<< |L4
 |   |                         +---+                         | ^ |
 |   | . . .  >>>> Packet U >>>|>>>|>>> Packet U >>>>>>>>>>>>|>^ |L3
 |   |     +--^+     +---+     |   |     +---+     +---+     |   |
 |   |     |  *|     |   |     |   |     |   |     |   |     |   |L2
 |___|_____|___|_____|___|_____|___|_____|___|_____|___|_____|___|
 source          subnet E      router       subnet F         dest
     __ _ _ _    __ _ _ _    __ _ _        __ _ _ _
    |  | | | |  |  | |C| |  |  | |C|      |  | |C|C|  data________\
    |__|_|_|_|  |__|_|_|_|  |__|_|_|      |__|_|_|_|  packet (U)  /
 layer: 4 3 2       4 3 2       4 3           4 3 2
 header]]></artwork>
        </figure>

        <t>By comparing <xref target="ecnencap_Fig_Feed-Up"/> with <xref
        target="ecnencap_Fig_Feed-Forward-and-Up"/>, it can be seen that
        subnet E (perhaps a subnet of layer-3 Ethernet switches) works in
        feed-up-and-forward mode by notifying congestion directly into L3 at
        the point of congestion, even though the congested switch does not
        otherwise act at L3. In this example, the technology in subnet F (e.g.
        MPLS) does support ECN natively, so when the router adds the layer-2
        header it copies the ECN marking from L3 to L2 as well.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="ecnencap_Backward" title="Feed-Backward Mode">
        <t>In some layer 2 technologies, explicit congestion notification has
        been defined for use internally within the subnet with its own
        feedback and load regulation, but typically the interface with IP for
        ECN has not been defined.</t>

        <t>For instance, for the available bit-rate (ABR) service in ATM, the
        relative rate mechanism was one of the more popular mechanisms for
        managing traffic, tending to supersede earlier designs. In this
        approach ATM switches send special resource management (RM) cells in
        both the forward and backward directions to control the ingress rate
        of user data into a virtual circuit. If a switch buffer is approaching
        congestion or congested it sends an RM cell back towards the ingress
        with respectively the No Increase (NI) or Congestion Indication (CI)
        bit set in its message type field <xref target="ATM-TM-ABR"/>. The
        ingress then holds or decreases its sending bit-rate accordingly.</t>

        <figure align="center" anchor="ecnencap_Fig_Feed-Backward"
                title="Feed-Backward Mode">
          <artwork><![CDATA[                     _ _ _ 
          /_______  | | |C|  ACK packet (X)
          \         |_|_|_|
 +---+        layer: 2 3 4 header                            +---+
 |  <|<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<<< Packet X <<<<<<<<<<<<<|<< |L4
 |   |                         +---+                         | ^ |
 |   |                         |  *|>>> Packet W >>>>>>>>>>>>|>^ |L3
 |   |     +---+     +---+     |   |     +---+     +---+     |   |
 |   |     |   |     |   |     |  <|<<<<<|<<<|<(V)<|<<<|     |   |L2
 |   | . . | . |Packet U | . . | . | . . | . | . . | .*| . . |   |L2
 |___|_____|___|_____|___|_____|___|_____|___|_____|___|_____|___|
 source          subnet G      router       subnet H         dest
     __ _ _ _    __ _ _ _    __ _ _        __ _ _ _   later
    |  | | | |  |  | | | |  |  | | |      |  | |C| |  data________\
    |__|_|_|_|  |__|_|_|_|  |__|_|_|      |__|_|_|_|  packet (W)  /
        4 3 2       4 3 2       4 3           4 3 2
                                        _        
                                  /__  |C|  Feedback control
                                  \    |_|  cell/frame (V)
                                        2    
     __ _ _ _    __ _ _ _    __ _ _        __ _ _ _   earlier
    |  | | | |  |  | | | |  |  | | |      |  | | | |  data________\
    |__|_|_|_|  |__|_|_|_|  |__|_|_|      |__|_|_|_|  packet (U)  /
layer:  4 3 2       4 3 2       4 3           4 3 2
header
]]></artwork>
        </figure>

        <t>ATM's feed-backward approach doesn't fit well when layered beneath
        IP's feed-forward approach&mdash;unless the initial data source is the
        same node as the ATM ingress. <!--(which would be the case if ATM had achieved its aspiration of becoming the global internetwork standard, 
rather than just a subnetwork technology)--><xref
        target="ecnencap_Fig_Feed-Backward"/> shows the feed-backward approach
        being used in subnet H. If the final switch on the path is congested
        (*), it doesn't feed-forward any congestion indications on packet (U).
        Instead it sends a control cell (V) back to the router at the ATM
        ingress.</t>

        <t>However, the backward feedback doesn't reach the original data
        source directly because IP doesn't support backward feedback (and
        subnet G is independent of subnet H). Instead, the router in the
        middle throttles down its sending rate but the original data sources
        don't reduce their rates. The resulting rate mismatch causes the
        middle router's buffer at layer 3 to back up until it becomes
        congested, which it signals forwards on later data packets at layer 3
        (e.g. packet W). Note that the forward signal from the middle router
        is not triggered directly by the backward signal. Rather, it is
        triggered by congestion resulting from the middle router's mismatched
        rate response to the backward signal.</t>

        <t>In response to this later forward signalling, end-to-end feedback
        at layer-4 finally completes the tortuous path of congestion
        indications back to the origin data source, as before.</t>

        <!--To summarise so far, feeding congestion notification backwards can reach the source faster, but only 
if the congested subnet is directly connected to the original data source. In a more general case, 
feedback takes a tortuous path part-way backwards, which can lead to queuing at the higher layer in 
the middle of the network, which can in turn trigger a much-delayed feed-forward signal, which then 
has to be fed back from destination to source.-->
      </section>

      <section title="Null Mode">
        <t>Often link and physical layer resources are 'non-blocking' by
        design. In these cases congestion notification may be implemented but
        it does not need to be deployed at the lower layer; ECN in IP would be
        sufficient.</t>

        <t>A degenerate example is a point-to-point Ethernet link. Excess
        loading of the link merely causes the queue from the higher layer to
        back up, while the lower layer remains immune to congestion. Even a
        whole meshed subnetwork can be made immune to interior congestion by
        limiting ingress capacity and careful sizing of links, particularly if
        multi-path routing is used to ensure even worst-case patterns of load
        cannot congest any link.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="ecnencap_Guidelines_Forward"
             title="Feed-Forward-and-Up Mode: Guidelines for Adding Congestion Notification">
      <t>Feed-forward-and-up is the mode already used for signalling ECN up
      the layers through MPLS into IP <xref target="RFC5129"/> and through
      IP-in-IP tunnels <xref target="RFC6040"/>. These RFCs take a consistent
      approach and the following guidelines are designed to ensure this
      consistency continues as ECN support is added to other protocols that
      encapsulate IP. The guidelines are also designed to ensure compliance
      with the more general best current practice for the design of alternate
      ECN schemes given in <xref target="RFC4774"/>.</t>

      <t>The rest of this section is structured as follows:<list
          style="symbols">
          <t><xref target="ecnencap_IP-IP_Coupled_Shim_Tunnels"/> addresses
          the most straightforward cases, where <xref target="RFC6040"/> can
          be applied directly to add ECN to tunnels that are effectively the
          same as IP-in-IP tunnels.</t>

          <t>The subsequent sections give guidelines for adding ECN to a
          subnet technology that uses feed-forward-and-up mode like IP, but it
          is not so similar to IP that <xref target="RFC6040"/> rules can be
          applied directly. Specifically:<list style="symbols">
              <t>Sections <xref format="counter"
              target="ecnencap_WireProtocolECNSupport"/>, <xref
              format="counter" target="ecnencap_EncapGuidelines"/> and <xref
              format="counter" target="ecnencap_DecapGuidelines"/>
              respectively address how to add ECN support to the wire protocol
              and to the encapsulators and decapsulators at the ingress and
              egress of the subnet.</t>

              <t><xref target="ecnencap_Sequences"/> deals with the special,
              but common, case of sequences of tunnels or subnets that all use
              the same technology</t>

              <t><xref target="ecnencap_Reframing"/> deals with the question
              of reframing when IP packets do not map 1:1 into lower layer
              frames.</t>
            </list></t>
        </list></t>

      <section anchor="ecnencap_IP-IP_Coupled_Shim_Tunnels"
               title="IP-in-IP Tunnels with Tightly Coupled Shim Headers">
        <t>A common pattern for many tunnelling protocols is to encapsulate an
        inner IP header with shim header(s) then an outer IP header. In many
        cases the shim header(s) always have to be tightly coupled to the
        outer IP header because they are not sufficient as outer headers in
        their own right. In such cases the shim header(s) and the outer IP
        header are always added (or removed) in the same operation. Therefore,
        in all such tightly coupled IP-in-IP tunnelling protocols, the rules
        in <xref target="RFC6040"/> for propagating the ECN field between the
        two IP headers SHOULD be applied directly.</t>

        <t>Examples of tightly coupled IP-in-IP tunnelling protocols where
        <xref target="RFC6040"/> can be applied directly are: <list
            style="symbols">
            <t>L2TP <xref target="RFC2661"/></t>

            <t>GRE [<xref format="counter" target="RFC1701"/>, <xref
            format="counter" target="RFC2784"/>]</t>

            <t>PPTP <xref target="RFC2637"/></t>

            <t>GTP [<xref format="counter" target="GTPv1"/>, <xref
            format="counter" target="GTPv1-U"/>, <xref format="counter"
            target="GTPv2-C"/>]</t>

            <t>VXLAN <xref target="vxlan"/>.</t>

            <!--{ToDo: Check that all the above are always tightly coupled to the IP outer.}
{ToDo: More examples?, e.g. PMIP (Proxy Mobile IPv6) [RFC5213]?}-->
          </list></t>

        <t/>
      </section>

      <section anchor="ecnencap_WireProtocolECNSupport"
               title="Wire Protocol Design: Indication of ECN Support">
        <t>This section is intended to guide the redesign of any lower layer
        protocol that encapsulate IP to add native ECN support at the lower
        layer. It reflects the approaches used in <xref target="RFC6040"/> and
        in <xref target="RFC5129"/>. Therefore IP-in-IP tunnels or IP-in-MPLS
        or MPLS-in-MPLS encapsulations that already comply with <xref
        target="RFC6040"/> or <xref target="RFC5129"/> will already satisfy
        this guidance.</t>

        <t>A lower layer (or subnet) congestion notification system:<list
            style="numbers">
            <t>SHOULD NOT apply explicit congestion notifications to PDUs that
            are destined for legacy layer-4 transport implementations that
            will not understand ECN, and</t>

            <t anchor="ecnencap_Egress_Check">SHOULD NOT apply explicit
            congestion notifications to PDUs if the egress of the subnet might
            not propagate congestion notifications onward into the higher
            layer.<vspace blankLines="1"/>We use the term ECN-PDUs for a PDU
            on a feedback loop that will propagate congestion notification
            properly because it meets both the above criteria. And a
            Not-ECN-PDU is a PDU on a feedback loop that does not meet both
            criteria, and will therefore not propagate congestion notification
            properly. A corollary of the above is that a lower layer
            congestion notification protocol:</t>

            <t>SHOULD be able to distinguish ECN-PDUs from Not-ECN-PDUs.</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>Note that there is no need for all interior nodes within a subnet
        to be able to mark congestion explicitly. A mix of ECN and drop
        signals from different nodes is fine. However, if <spanx style="emph">any</spanx>
        interior nodes might generate ECN markings, guideline <xref
        format="counter" target="ecnencap_Egress_Check"/> above says that all
        relevant egress node(s) SHOULD be able to propagate those markings up
        to the higher layer.</t>

        <t>In IP, if the ECN field in each PDU is cleared to the Not-ECT (not
        ECN-capable transport) codepoint, it indicates that the L4 transport
        will not understand congestion markings. A congested buffer must not
        mark these Not-ECT PDUs, and therefore drops them instead.</t>

        <t>The mechanism a lower layer uses to distinguish the ECN-capability
        of PDUs need not mimic that of IP. All the above guidelines say is
        that the lower layer system, as a whole, should achieve the same
        outcome. For instance, ECN-capable feedback loops might use PDUs that
        are identified by a particular set of labels or tags. Alternatively,
        logical link protocols that use flow state might determine whether a
        PDU can be congestion marked by checking for ECN-support in the flow
        state. Other protocols might depend on out-of-band control
        signals.</t>

        <t>The per-domain checking of ECN support in MPLS <xref
        target="RFC5129"/> is a good example of a way to avoid sending
        congestion markings to transports that will not understand them,
        without using any header space in the subnet protocol.</t>

        <t>In MPLS, header space is extremely limited, therefore RFC5129 does
        not provide a field in the MPLS header to indicate whether the PDU is
        an ECN-PDU or a Not-ECN-PDU. Instead, interior nodes in a domain are
        allowed to set explicit congestion indications without checking
        whether the PDU is destined for a transport that will understand them.
        Nonetheless, this is made safe by requiring that the network operator
        upgrades all decapsulating edges of a whole domain at once, as soon as
        even one switch within the domain is configured to mark rather than
        drop during congestion. Therefore, any edge node that might
        decapsulate a packet will be capable of checking whether the higher
        layer transport is ECN-capable. When decapsulating a CE-marked packet,
        if the decapsulator discovers that the higher layer (inner header)
        indicates the transport is not ECN-capable, it drops the
        packet&mdash;effectively on behalf of the earlier congested node (see
        Decapsulation Guideline <xref format="counter"
        target="ecnencap_dropNot-ECTinnerCEouter"/> in <xref
        target="ecnencap_DecapGuidelines"/>).</t>

        <t>It was only appropriate to define such an incremental deployment
        strategy because MPLS is targeted solely at professional operators,
        who can be expected to ensure that a whole subnetwork is consistently
        configured. This strategy might not be appropriate for other link
        technologies targeted at zero-configuration deployment or deployment
        by the general public (e.g. Ethernet). For such 'plug-and-play'
        environments it will be necessary to invent a failsafe approach that
        ensures congestion markings will never fall into black holes, no
        matter how inconsistently a system is put together. Alternatively,
        congestion notification relying on correct system configuration could
        be confined to flavours of Ethernet intended only for professional
        network operators, such as IEEE 802.1ah Provider Backbone Bridges
        (PBB).</t>

        <t>QCN <xref target="IEEE802.1Qau"/> provides another example of how
        to indicate to lower layer devices that the end-points will not
        understand ECN. An operator can define certain 802.1p classes of
        service to indicate non-QCN frames and an ingress bridge is required
        to map arriving not-QCN-capable IP packets to one of these non-QCN
        802.1p classes.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="ecnencap_EncapGuidelines"
               title="Encapsulation Guidelines">
        <t>This section is intended to guide the redesign of any node that
        encapsulates IP with a lower layer header when adding native ECN
        support to the lower layer protocol. It reflects the approaches used
        in <xref target="RFC6040"/> and in <xref target="RFC5129"/>. Therefore
        IP-in-IP tunnels or IP-in-MPLS or MPLS-in-MPLS encapsulations that
        already comply with <xref target="RFC6040"/> or <xref
        target="RFC5129"/> will already satisfy this guidance.<list
            style="numbers">
            <t>Egress Capability Check: A subnet ingress needs to be sure that
            the corresponding egress of a subnet will propagate any congestion
            notification added to the outer header across the subnet. This is
            necessary in addition to checking that an incoming PDU indicates
            an ECN-capable (L4) transport. Examples of how this guarantee
            might be provided include:<list style="symbols">
                <t>by configuration (e.g. if any label switches in a domain
                support ECN marking, <xref target="RFC5129"/> requires all
                egress nodes to have been configured to propagate ECN)</t>

                <t>by the ingress explicitly checking that the egress
                propagates ECN (e.g. TRILL uses IS-IS to check path
                capabilities before using critical options <xref
                target="trill-rbridge-options"/>)</t>

                <t>by inherent design of the protocol (e.g. by encoding ECN
                marking on the outer header in such a way that a legacy egress
                that does not understand ECN will consider the PDU corrupt and
                discard it, thus at least propagating a form of congestion
                signal).</t>
              </list></t>

            <t>Egress Fails Capability Check: If the ingress cannot guarantee
            that the egress will propagate congestion notification, the
            ingress SHOULD disable ECN when it forwards the PDU at the lower
            layer. An example of how the ingress might disable ECN at the
            lower layer would be by setting the outer header of the PDU to
            identify it as a Not-ECN-PDU, assuming the subnet technology
            supports such a concept.</t>

            <t anchor="ecnencap_Encap_Copy">Standard Congestion Monitoring
            Baseline: Once the ingress to a subnet has established that the
            egress will correctly propagate ECN, on encapsulation it SHOULD
            encode the same level of congestion in outer headers as is
            arriving in incoming headers. For example it might copy any
            incoming congestion notification into the outer header of the
            lower layer protocol.<vspace blankLines="1"/>This ensures that all
            outer headers reflect congestion accumulated along the whole
            upstream path since the Load Regulator, not just since the ingress
            of the subnet. A node that is not the Load Regulator SHOULD NOT
            re-initialise the level of CE markings in the outer to zero.
            <vspace blankLines="1"/>This guideline is intended to ensure that
            any bulk congestion monitoring of outer headers (e.g. by a network
            management node monitoring ECN in passing frames) is most
            meaningful. For instance, if an operator measures CE in 0.4% of
            passing outer headers, this information is only useful if the
            operator knows where the proportion of CE markings was last
            initialised to 0% (the Congestion Baseline). Such monitoring
            information will not be useful if some subnet ingress nodes reset
            all outer CE markings while others copy incoming CE markings into
            the outer.<vspace blankLines="1"/>Most information can be
            extracted if the Congestion Baseline is standardised at the node
            that is regulating the load (the Load Regulator&mdash;typically
            the data source). Then the operator can measure both congestion
            since the Load Regulator, and congestion since the subnet ingress.
            The latter might be measurable by subtracting the level of CE
            markings on inner headers from that on outer headers (see Appendix
            C of <xref target="RFC6040"/>).<!--{If required, an example can be given of where it would be appropriate to contradict this SHOULD.
It may be safe to assume a subnetwork technology will not span a trust boundary. 
Especially if copy on encap is not desirable, e.g. if using Floyd's 1-bit MPLS scheme.}

--></t>
          </list></t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="ecnencap_DecapGuidelines"
               title="Decapsulation Guidelines">
        <t>This section is intended to guide the redesign of any node that
        decapsulates IP from within a lower layer header when adding native
        ECN support to the lower layer protocol. It reflects the approaches
        used in <xref target="RFC6040"/> and in <xref target="RFC5129"/>.
        Therefore IP-in-IP tunnels or IP-in-MPLS or MPLS-in-MPLS
        encapsulations that already comply with <xref target="RFC6040"/> or
        <xref target="RFC5129"/> will already satisfy this guidance.</t>

        <t>A subnet egress SHOULD NOT simply copy congestion notification from
        outer headers to the forwarded header. It SHOULD calculate the
        outgoing congestion notification field from the inner and outer
        headers using the following guidelines. If there is any conflict,
        rules earlier in the list take precedence over rules later in the
        list:<list style="numbers">
            <t anchor="ecnencap_dropNot-ECTinnerCEouter">If the arriving inner
            header is a Not-ECN-PDU it implies the L4 transport will not
            understand explicit congestion markings. Then:<list
                style="symbols">
                <t>If the outer header carries an explicit congestion marking,
                the packet SHOULD be dropped&mdash;the only indication of
                congestion that the L4 transport will understand.</t>

                <!--{ToDo: RFC6040 allows forwarding if it is not the most severe marking.}-->

                <t>If the outer is an ECN-PDU that carries no indication of
                congestion or a Not-ECN-PDU the PDU SHOULD be forwarded, but
                still as a Not-ECN-PDU.</t>
              </list></t>

            <t>If the outer header does not support explicit congestion
            notification (a Not-ECN-PDU), but the inner header does (an
            ECN-PDU), the inner header SHOULD be forwarded unchanged.</t>

            <t>In some lower layer protocols congestion may be signalled as a
            numerical level, such as in the control frames of quantised
            congestion notification <xref target="IEEE802.1Qau"/>. If such a
            multi-bit encoding encapsulates an ECN-capable IP data packet, a
            function will be needed to convert the quantised congestion level
            into the frequency of congestion markings in outgoing IP
            packets.</t>

            <t>Congestion indications may be encoded by a severity level. For
            instance increasing levels of congestion might be encoded by
            numerically increasing indications, e.g. pre-congestion
            notification (PCN) can be encoded in each PDU at three severity
            levels in IP or MPLS <xref target="RFC6660"/>.<vspace
            blankLines="1"/>If the arriving inner header is an ECN-PDU, where
            the inner and outer headers carry indications of congestion of
            different severity, the more severe indication SHOULD be forwarded
            in preference to the less severe.</t>

            <t>The inner and outer headers might carry a combination of
            congestion notification fields that should not be possible given
            any currently used protocol transitions. For instance, if
            Encapsulation Guideline <xref format="counter"
            target="ecnencap_Encap_Copy"/> in <xref
            target="ecnencap_EncapGuidelines"/> had been followed, it should
            not be possible to have a less severe indication of congestion in
            the outer than in the inner. It MAY be appropriate to log
            unexpected combinations of headers and possibly raise an alarm.
            <vspace blankLines="1"/>If a safe outgoing codepoint can be
            defined for such a PDU, the PDU SHOULD be forwarded rather than
            dropped. Some implementers discard PDUs with currently unused
            combinations of headers just in case they represent an attack.
            However, an approach using alarms and policy-mediated drop is
            preferable to hard-coded drop, so that operators can keep track of
            possible attacks but currently unused combinations are not
            precluded from future use through new standards actions.</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="ecnencap_Sequences"
               title="Sequences of Similar Tunnels or Subnets">
        <t>In some deployments, particularly in 3GPP networks, an IP packet
        may traverse two or more IP-in-IP tunnels in sequence that all use
        identical technology (e.g. GTP).</t>

        <t>In such cases, it would be sufficient for every encapsulation and
        decapsulation in the chain to comply with RFC 6040. Alternatively, as
        an optimisation, a node that decapsulates a packet and immediately
        re-encapsulates it for the next tunnel MAY copy the incoming outer ECN
        field directly to the outgoing outer and the incoming inner ECN field
        directly to the outgoing inner. Then the overall behavior across the
        sequence of tunnel segments would still be consistent with RFC
        6040.</t>

        <t>Appendix C of RFC6040 describes how a tunnel egress can monitor how
        much congestion has been introduced within a tunnel. A network
        operator might want to monitor how much congestion had been introduced
        within a whole sequence of tunnels. Using the technique in Appendix C
        of RFC6040 at the final egress, the operator could monitor the whole
        sequence of tunnels, but only if the above optimisation were used
        consistently along the sequence of tunnels, in order to make it appear
        as a single tunnel. Therefore, tunnel endpoint implementations SHOULD
        allow the operator to configure whether this optimisation is
        enabled.</t>

        <t>When ECN support is added to a subnet technology, consideration
        SHOULD be given to a similar optimisation between subnets in sequence
        if they all use the same technology.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="ecnencap_Reframing"
               title="Reframing and Congestion Markings">
        <t>The guidance in this section is worded in terms of framing
        boundaries, but it applies equally whether the protocol data units are
        frames, cells or packets.</t>

        <t>Where framing boundaries are different between two layers,
        congestion indications SHOULD be propagated on the basis that a
        congestion indication on a PDU applies to all the octets in the PDU.
        On average, an encapsulator or decapsulator SHOULD approximately
        preserve the number of marked octets arriving and leaving (counting
        the size of inner headers, but not added encapsulating headers).</t>

        <t>The next departing frame SHOULD be immediately marked even if only
        enough incoming marked octets have arrived for part of the departing
        frame. This ensures that any outstanding congestion marked octets are
        propagated immediately, rather than held back waiting for a frame no
        bigger than the outstanding marked octets&mdash;which might involve a
        long wait.</t>

        <t>For instance, an algorithm for marking departing frames could
        maintain a counter representing the balance of arriving marked octets
        minus departing marked octets. It adds the size of every marked frame
        that arrives and if the counter is positive it marks the next frame to
        depart and subtracts its size from the counter. This will often leave
        a negative remainder in the counter, which is deliberate.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="ecnencap_Guidelines_Up"
             title="Feed-Up-and-Forward Mode: Guidelines for Adding Congestion Notification">
      <t>The guidance in this section is primarily applicable to encapsulation
      of IP packets in Ethernet headers. However, it generalises to
      encapsulation by other subnet technologies with no native support for
      explicit congestion notification. It is unlikely to be applicable or
      necessary for IP-in-IP encapsulation, where feed-forward-and-up mode
      based on <xref target="RFC6040"/> would be more appropriate.</t>

      <t>Marking the IP header while switching at layer-2 (by using a layer-3
      switch) seems to represent a layering violation. However, it can be
      considered as a benign optimisation if the guidelines below are
      followed. Feed-up-and-forward is certainly not a general alternative to
      implementing feed-forward congestion notification in the lower layer,
      because:<list style="symbols">
          <t>IPv4 and IPv6 are not the only layer-3 protocols that might be
          encapsulated by lower layer protocols</t>

          <t>Link-layer encryption might be in use, making the layer-2 payload
          inaccessible</t>

          <t>Many Ethernet switches do not have 'layer-3 switch' capabilities
          so they cannot read or modify an IP payload</t>

          <t>It might be costly to find an IP header (v4 or v6) when it may be
          encapsulated by more than one Ethernet header (e.g. MAC in MAC <xref
          target="IEEE802.1Qah"/>).</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>Nonetheless, configuring a layer-3 switch to look for an ECN field in
      an encapsulated IP header is a useful optimisation. If the
      implementation follows the guidelines below, this optimisation does not
      have to be confined to a controlled environment such as within a data
      centre; it could usefully be applied on any network&mdash;even if the
      operator is not sure whether the above issues will never apply:<list
          style="numbers">
          <t>If a native lower-layer congestion notification mechanism exists
          for a subnet technology, it is safe to mix feed-up-and-forward with
          feed-forward-and-up on other switches in the same subnet. However,
          it will generally be more efficient to use the native mechanism.</t>

          <t>The depth of the search for an IP header SHOULD be limited. If an
          IP header is not found soon enough, or an unrecognised or unreadable
          header is encountered, the switch SHOULD resort to an alternative
          means of signalling congestion (e.g. drop, or the native lower layer
          mechanism if available).</t>

          <t>It is sufficient to use the first IP header found in the stack;
          the egress of the relevant tunnel can propagate congestion
          notification upwards to any more deeply encapsulated IP headers
          later.</t>
        </list></t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="ecnencap_Guidelines_Backward"
             title="Feed-Backward Mode: Guidelines for Adding Congestion Notification">
      <t>It can be seen from <xref target="ecnencap_Backward"/> that
      congestion notification in a subnet using feed-backward mode has
      generally not been designed to be directly coupled with IP layer
      congestion notification. The subnet attempts to minimise congestion
      internally, and if the incoming load at the ingress exceeds the capacity
      somewhere through the subnet, the layer 3 buffer into the ingress backs
      up. Thus, a feed-backward mode subnet is in some sense similar to a null
      mode subnet, in that there is no need for any direct interaction between
      the subnet and higher layer congestion notification. Therefore no
      detailed protocol design guidelines are appropriate. Nonetheless, a more
      general guideline is appropriate: <list style="numbers">
          <t>A subnetwork technology intended to eventually interface to IP
          SHOULD NOT be designed using only the feed-backward mode, which is
          certainly best for a stand-alone subnet, but would need to be
          modified to work efficiently as part of the wider Internet, because
          IP uses feed-forward-and-up mode.</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>The feed-backward approach at least works beneath IP, where the term
      'works' is used only in a narrow functional sense because feed-backward
      can result in very inefficient and sluggish congestion
      control&mdash;except if it is confined to the subnet directly connected
      to the original data source, when it is faster than feed-forward. It
      would be valid to design a protocol that could work in feed-backward
      mode for paths that only cross one subnet, and in feed-forward-and-up
      mode for paths that cross subnets.</t>

      <t>In the early days of TCP/IP, a similar feed-backward approach was
      tried for explicit congestion signalling, using source-quench (SQ) ICMP
      control packets. However, SQ fell out of favour and is now formally
      deprecated <xref target="RFC6633"/>. The main problem was that it is
      hard for a data source to tell the difference between a spoofed SQ
      message and a quench request from a genuine buffer on the path. It is
      also hard for a lower layer buffer to address an SQ message to the
      original source port number, which may be buried within many layers of
      headers, and possibly encrypted.</t>

      <t>Quantised congestion notification (QCN&mdash;also known as backward
      congestion notification or BCN) <xref target="IEEE802.1Qau"/> uses a
      feed-backward mode structurally similar to ATM's relative rate
      mechanism. However, QCN confines its applicability to scenarios such as
      some data centres where all endpoints are directly attached by the same
      Ethernet technology. If a QCN subnet were later connected into a wider
      IP-based internetwork (e.g. when attempting to interconnect multiple
      data centres) it would suffer the inefficiency shown <xref
      target="ecnencap_Fig_Feed-Backward"/>.</t>

      <!--{ToDo - either make this a separate case, move it to modes, or delete it} 
In some circumstances (e.g. pseudowire emulations with link-local flow control), the whole 
path is divided into segments, each with its own congestion notification and feedback loop. 
In these cases, the function that regulates load at the start of each segment will need to 
reset congestion notification (i.e. clear any accumulated congestion notifications) at the 
start of its segment.-->
    </section>

    <!-- ================================================================ -->

    <section anchor="ecnencap_IANA_Considerations"
             title="IANA Considerations (to be removed by RFC Editor)">
      <t>This memo includes no request to IANA.</t>
    </section>

    <!-- ================================================================ -->

    <section anchor="ecnencap_Security_Considerations"
             title="Security Considerations">
      <t>If a lower layer wire protocol is redesigned to include explicit
      congestion signalling in-band in the protocol header, care SHOULD be
      take to ensure that the field used is specified as mutable during
      transit. Otherwise interior nodes signalling congestion would invalidate
      any authentication protocol applied to the lower layer header&mdash;by
      altering a header field that had been assumed as immutable.</t>

      <t>The redesign of protocols that encapsulate IP in order to propagate
      congestion signals between layers raises potential signal integrity
      concerns. Experimental or proposed approaches exist for assuring the
      end-to-end integrity of in-band congestion signals, e.g.:<list
          style="symbols">
          <t>Congestion exposure (ConEx ) for networks to audit that their
          congestion signals are not being suppressed by other networks or by
          receivers, and for networks to police that senders are responding
          sufficiently to the signals, irrespective of the transport protocol
          used <xref target="I-D.ietf-conex-abstract-mech"/>.</t>

          <t>The ECN nonce <xref target="RFC3540"/> for a TCP sender to detect
          whether a network or the receiver is suppressing congestion
          signals.</t>

          <t>A test with the same goals as the ECN nonce, but without the need
          for the receiver to co-operate with the protocol <xref
          target="I-D.moncaster-tcpm-rcv-cheat"/>.</t>
        </list>Given these end-to-end approaches are already being specified,
      it would make little sense to attempt to design hop-by-hop congestion
      signal integrity into a new lower layer protocol, because end-to-end
      integrity inherently achieves hop-by-hop integrity.</t>
    </section>

    <!-- ================================================================ -->

    <section anchor="ecnencap_Conclusions" title="Conclusions">
      <t>Following the guidance in the document enables ECN support to be
      extended to numerous protocols that encapsulate IP (v4 &amp; v6) in a
      consistent way, so that IP continues to fulfil its role as an end-to-end
      interoperability layer. This includes:<list style="symbols">
          <t>A wide range of tunnelling protocols with various forms of shim
          header between two IP headers;</t>

          <t>A wide range of subnet technologies, particularly those that work
          in the same 'feed-forward-and-up' mode that is used to support ECN
          in IP and MPLS.</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>Guidelines have been defined for supporting propagation of ECN
      between Ethernet and IP on so-called Layer-3 Ethernet switches, using a
      'feed-up-an-forward' mode. This approach could enable other subnet
      technologies to pass ECN signals into the IP layer, even if they do not
      support ECN natively.</t>

      <t>Finally, attempting to add ECN to a subnet technology in
      feed-backward mode is deprecated except in special cases, due to its
      likely sluggish response to congestion.</t>
    </section>

    <!-- ================================================================ -->

    <section anchor="ecnencap_Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>Thanks to Gorry Fairhurst for extensive initial reviews. Michael
      Welzl pointed out that lower layer congestion notification signals may
      have different semantics to those in IP.</t>

      <t>Bob Briscoe was part-funded by the European Community under its
      Seventh Framework Programme through the Trilogy project (ICT-216372) for
      initial drafts and through the Reducing Internet Transport Latency
      (RITE) project (ICT-317700) subsequently. The views expressed here are
      solely those of the authors.</t>
    </section>

    <!-- ================================================================ -->

    <section anchor="ecnencap_Comments_Solicited" title="Comments Solicited">
      <t>Comments and questions are encouraged and very welcome. They can be
      addressed to the IETF Transport Area working group mailing list
      &lt;tsvwg@ietf.org&gt;, and/or to the authors.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <!-- ================================================================ -->

    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119" ?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.3168'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.3819'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.4774'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.5129'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6040'?>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.1323'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.1701'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.2003'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.2637'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.2661'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.2784'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.2884'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.2983'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.3540'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.4301'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6633'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6660'?>

      <reference anchor="trill-rbridge-options">
        <front>
          <title>RBridges: Further TRILL Header Extensions</title>

          <author fullname="Donald Eastlake" initials="D" surname="Eastlake">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <author fullname="Anoop Ghanwani" initials="A" surname="Ghanwani">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <author fullname="Vishwas Manral" initials="V" surname="Manral">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <author fullname="Caitlin Bestler" initials="C" surname="Bestler">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <date day="6" month="June" year="2012"/>

          <abstract>
            <t>The TRILL base protocol standard specifies minimal hooks to
            safely support TRILL Header extensions. Initial extensions have
            been specified in RFC [ExtendHeader]. This document specifies the
            format for further such extensions and specifies some further
            specific extensions.</t>
          </abstract>
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft"
                    value="draft-ietf-trill-rbridge-options-07"/>

        <format target="http://www.ietf.org/internet-drafts/draft-ietf-trill-rbridge-options-07.txt"
                type="TXT"/>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="vxlan">
        <front>
          <title>VXLAN: A Framework for Overlaying Virtualized Layer 2
          Networks over Layer 3 Networks</title>

          <author fullname="Mallik Mahalingam" initials="M"
                  surname="Mahalingam">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <author fullname="Dinesh Dutt" initials="D" surname="Dutt">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <author fullname="Kenneth Duda" initials="K" surname="Duda">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <author fullname="Puneet Agarwal" initials="P" surname="Agarwal">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <author fullname="Lawrence Kreeger" initials="L" surname="Kreeger">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <author fullname="T. Sridhar" initials="T" surname="Sridhar">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <author fullname="Mike Bursell" initials="M" surname="Bursell">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <author fullname="Chris Wright" initials="C" surname="Wright">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <date day="08" month="May" year="2013"/>

          <abstract>
            <t>This document describes Virtual eXtensible Local Area Network
            (VXLAN), which is used to address the need for overlay networks
            within virtualized data centers accommodating multiple tenants.
            The scheme and the related protocols can be used in cloud service
            provider and enterprise data center networks.</t>
          </abstract>
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft"
                    value="draft-mahalingam-dutt-dcops-vxlan-04"/>

        <format target="http://www.ietf.org/internet-drafts/draft-mahalingam-dutt-dcops-vxlan-04.txt"
                type="TXT"/>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="I-D.ietf-conex-abstract-mech">
        <front>
          <title>Congestion Exposure (ConEx) Concepts and Abstract
          Mechanism</title>

          <author fullname="Matt Mathis" initials="M" surname="Mathis">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <author fullname="Bob Briscoe" initials="B" surname="Briscoe">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <date day="15" month="July" year="2013"/>

          <abstract>
            <t>This document describes an abstract mechanism by which senders
            inform the network about the congestion encountered by packets
            earlier in the same flow. Today, network elements at any layer may
            signal congestion to the receiver by dropping packets or by ECN
            markings, and the receiver passes this information back to the
            sender in transport-layer feedback. The mechanism described here
            enables the sender to also relay this congestion information back
            into the network in-band at the IP layer, such that the total
            amount of congestion from all elements on the path is revealed to
            all IP elements along the path, where it could, for example, be
            used to provide input to traffic management. This mechanism is
            called congestion exposure or ConEx. The companion document "ConEx
            Concepts and Use Cases" provides the entry-point to the set of
            ConEx documentation.</t>
          </abstract>
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft"
                    value="draft-ietf-conex-abstract-mech-07"/>

        <format target="http://www.ietf.org/internet-drafts/draft-ietf-conex-abstract-mech-07.txt"
                type="TXT"/>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="I-D.moncaster-tcpm-rcv-cheat">
        <front>
          <title>A TCP Test to Allow Senders to Identify Receiver
          Non-Compliance</title>

          <author fullname="T  Moncaster" initials="T" surname="Moncaster">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <date day="7" month="June" year="2007"/>

          <abstract>
            <t>The TCP protocol relies on receivers sending accurate and
            timely feedback to the sender. Currently the sender has no means
            to verify that a receiver is correctly sending this feedback
            according to the protocol. A receiver that is non-compliant has
            the potential to disrupt a sender's resource allocation,
            increasing its transmission rate on that connection which in turn
            could adversely affect the network itself. This document presents
            a two stage test process that can be used to identify whether a
            receiver is non-compliant. The tests enshrine the principle that
            one shouldn't attribute to malice that which may be accidental.
            The first stage test causes minimum impact to the receiver but
            raises a suspicion of non-compliance. The second stage test can
            then be used to verify that the receiver is non-compliant. This
            specification does not modify the core TCP protocol - the tests
            can either be implemented as a test suite or as a stand-alone test
            through a simple modification to the sender implementation.</t>
          </abstract>
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft"
                    value="draft-moncaster-tcpm-rcv-cheat-01"/>

        <format target="http://www.ietf.org/internet-drafts/draft-moncaster-tcpm-rcv-cheat-01.txt"
                type="TXT"/>
      </reference>

      <?rfc include='localref.IEEE802.1Qah.MACinMAC'?>

      <?rfc include='localref.IEEE802.1QauCongNotif'?>

      <?rfc include='localref.ITU-T.I.371_ATMTrafficMgmt'?>

      <?rfc include='localref.Alizadeh10.DCTCP'?>

      <?rfc include='localref.Buckwalter00.FrameRelay'?>

      <reference anchor="GTPv1">
        <front>
          <title>GPRS Tunnelling Protocol (GTP) across the Gn and Gp
          interface</title>

          <author>
            <organization>3GPP</organization>
          </author>

          <date/>
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="Technical Specification" value="TS 29.060"/>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="GTPv1-U">
        <front>
          <title>General Packet Radio System (GPRS) Tunnelling Protocol User
          Plane (GTPv1-U)</title>

          <author>
            <organization>3GPP</organization>
          </author>

          <date/>
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="Technical Specification" value="TS 29.281"/>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="GTPv2-C">
        <front>
          <title>Evolved General Packet Radio Service (GPRS) Tunnelling
          Protocol for Control plane (GTPv2-C)</title>

          <author>
            <organization>3GPP</organization>
          </author>

          <date year=""/>
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="Technical Specification" value="TS 29.274"/>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="ATM-TM-ABR">
        <front>
          <title>Understanding the Available Bit Rate (ABR) Service Category
          for ATM VCs</title>

          <author>
            <organization>Cisco</organization>
          </author>

          <date day="5" month="June" year="2005"/>
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="Design Technote" value="10415"/>

        <format target="http://www.cisco.com/en/US/tech/tk39/tk51/technologies_tech_note09186a00800fbc76.shtml"
                type="HTML"/>
      </reference>
    </references>

    <section title="Outstanding Document Issues">
      <t><list style="numbers">
          <t>[GF] Concern that certain guidelines warrant a MUST (NOT) rather
          than a SHOULD (NOT). Given the guidelines say that if any SHOULD
          (NOT)s are not followed, a strong justification will be needed, they
          have been left as SHOULD (NOT) pending further list discussion. In
          particular:<list style="symbols">
              <t>If inner is a Not-ECN-PDU and Outer is CE (or highest
              severity congestion level), MUST (not SHOULD) drop?</t>
            </list></t>

          <t>Consider whether an IETF Standard Track doc will be needed to
          Update the IP-in-IP protocols listed in <xref
          target="ecnencap_IP-IP_Coupled_Shim_Tunnels"/>&mdash;at least those
          that the IETF controls&mdash;and which Area it should sit under.</t>
        </list></t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="ecnencap_Doc_Changes"
             title="Changes in This Version (to be removed by RFC Editor)  ">
      <t><list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="From briscoe-02 to 03:"><list style="symbols">
              <t>Scope section:<list style="symbols">
                  <t>Added dependence on correct propagation of traffic class
                  information</t>

                  <t>For the feed-backward mode, deemed multicast and anycast
                  out of scope</t>
                </list></t>

              <t>Ensured all guidelines referring to subnet technologies also
              refer to tunnels and vice versa by adding applicability
              sentences at the start of sections 4.1, 4.2, 4.3, 4.4, 4.6 and
              5.</t>

              <t>Added Security Considerations on ensuring congestion signal
              fields are classed as immutable and on using end-to-end
              congestion signal integrity technologies rather than
              hop-by-hop.</t>
            </list></t>

          <t hangText="From briscoe-01 to 02:"><list style="symbols">
              <t>Added authors: JK &amp; PT</t>

              <t>Added <list style="symbols">
                  <t>Section 4.1 "IP-in-IP Tunnels with Tightly Coupled Shim
                  Headers"</t>

                  <t>Section 4.5 "Sequences of Similar Tunnels or Subnets"</t>

                  <t>roadmap at the start of Section 4, given the subsections
                  have become quite fragmented.</t>

                  <t>Section 9 "Conclusions"</t>
                </list></t>

              <t>Clarified why transports are starting to be able to saturate
              interior links</t>

              <t>Under Section 1.1, addressed the question of alternative
              signal semantics and included multicast &amp; anycast.</t>

              <t>Under Section 3.1, included a 3GPP example.</t>

              <t>Section 4.2. "Wire Protocol Design":<list style="symbols">
                  <t>Altered guideline 2. to make it clear that it only
                  applies to the immediate subnet egress, not later ones</t>

                  <t>Added a reminder that it is only necessary to check that
                  ECN propagates at the egress, not whether interior nodes
                  mark ECN</t>

                  <t>Added example of how QCN uses 802.1p to indicate support
                  for QCN.</t>
                </list></t>

              <t>Added references to Appendix C of RFC6040, about monitoring
              the amount of congestion signals introduced within a tunnel</t>

              <t>Appendix A: Added more issues to be addressed, including plan
              to produce a standards track update to IP-in-IP tunnel
              protocols.</t>

              <t>Updated acks and references</t>
            </list></t>

          <t hangText="From briscoe-00 to 01:"><list style="symbols">
              <t>Intended status: BCP (was Informational) &amp; updates 3819
              added.</t>

              <t>Briefer Introduction: Introductory para justifying benefits
              of ECN. Moved all but a brief enumeration of modes of operation
              to their own new section (from both Intro &amp; Scope).
              Introduced incr. deployment as most tricky part.</t>

              <t>Tightened &amp; added to terminology section</t>

              <t>Structured with Modes of Operation, then Guidelines section
              for each mode.</t>

              <t>Tightened up guideline text to remove vagueness / passive
              voice / ambiguity and highlight main guidelines as numbered
              items.</t>

              <t>Added Outstanding Document Issues Appendix</t>

              <t>Updated references</t>
            </list></t>
        </list></t>
    </section>
  </back>
</rfc>
