<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="rfc2629.xslt"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM 'rfc2629.dtd'
[
  <!ENTITY rfc2119 PUBLIC '' 'bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml'>
  <!ENTITY rfc3986 PUBLIC '' 'bibxml/reference.RFC.3986.xml'>
  <!ENTITY rfc4627 PUBLIC '' 'bibxml/reference.RFC.4627.xml'>
  <!ENTITY rfc4648 PUBLIC '' 'bibxml/reference.RFC.4648.xml'>
  <!ENTITY rfc5234 PUBLIC '' 'bibxml/reference.RFC.5234.xml'>
  <!ENTITY rfc5545 PUBLIC '' 'bibxml/reference.RFC.5545.xml'>
  <!ENTITY rfc6321 PUBLIC '' 'bibxml/reference.RFC.6321.xml'>
  <!ENTITY I-D.sheffer-running-code PUBLIC '' 'bibxml3/reference.I-D.sheffer-running-code.xml'>
  <!ENTITY I-D.ietf-jcardcal-jcard PUBLIC '' 'bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-jcardcal-jcard.xml'>
  <!ENTITY thisrfc "RFCTODO">
]>
<?rfc rfcedstyle="yes" ?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<!-- default = 3 -->
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<?rfc strict="yes"?>
<!--<?rfc comments="yes"?> -->
<!--<?rfc inline="yes"?> -->
<rfc category='std' ipr='trust200902' docName='draft-ietf-jcardcal-jcal-02'>
  <front>
    <title abbrev="jCal">jCal: The JSON format for iCalendar</title>
    <author initials="P." surname="Kewisch" fullname="Philipp Kewisch">
      <organization abbrev="Mozilla">Mozilla Corporation</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>650 Castro Street, Suite 300</street>
          <city>Mountain View</city>
          <region>CA</region>
          <code>94041</code>
          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>
        <email>mozilla@kewis.ch</email>
        <uri>http://www.mozilla.org/</uri>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author initials="C." surname="Daboo" fullname="Cyrus Daboo">
      <organization abbrev="Apple, Inc.">Apple Inc.</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>1 Infinite Loop</street>
          <city>Cupertino</city>
          <region>CA</region>
          <code>95014</code>
          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>
        <email>cyrus@daboo.name</email>
        <uri>http://www.apple.com/</uri>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author initials="M." surname="Douglass" fullname="Mike Douglass">
      <organization abbrev="RPI">Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>110 8th Street</street>
          <city>Troy</city>
          <region>NY</region>
          <code>12180</code>
          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>
        <email>douglm@rpi.edu</email>
        <uri>http://www.rpi.edu/</uri>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date />
    <area>Applications</area>
    <workgroup>JSON data formats for vCard and iCalendar</workgroup>
    <abstract>
      <t>This specification defines "jCal", a JSON format for iCalendar data.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>
  <middle>

    <section title='Introduction'>

      <t>
        The iCalendar data format <xref target='RFC5545'/> is a widely deployed 
        interchange format for calendaring and scheduling data. While many 
        applications and services consume and generate calendar data, iCalendar
        is a specialized format that requires its own parser/generator. In contrast, 
        JSON-based formats as defined in <xref target='RFC4627' /> are the native 
        format for JavaScript widgets and libraries and it is appropriate to
        have a standard form of calendar data that is easier to work with than
        iCalendar.
      </t>

      <t>
        The purpose of this specification is to define "jCal", a JSON format 
        for iCalendar data. jCal is defined as a straightforward mapping into 
        JSON from iCalendar, so that iCalendar data can be converted to JSON, 
        and then back to iCalendar, without losing any semantic meaning in the 
        data. Anyone creating jCal calendar data according to this specification 
        will know that their data can be converted to a valid iCalendar 
        representation as well.
      </t>

      <t>
        The key design considerations are essentially the same as those for 
        <xref target='RFC6321' />, that is:
        <list>
          <t>
            Round-tripping (converting an iCalendar instance to jCal and back)
            will give the same semantic result as the starting point. For
            example, all components, properties and property parameters are
            guaranteed to be preserved.
          </t>
          <t>
            Ordering of elements will not necessarily be preserved. 
          </t>
          <t>
            Preserve the semantics of the iCalendar data. While a simple consumer 
            can easily browse the calendar data in jCal, a full understanding of 
            iCalendar is still required in order to modify and/or fully 
            comprehend the calendar data.
          </t>
          <t>
            Ability to handle many extensions to the underlying iCalendar 
            specification without requiring an update to this document.
          </t>
        </list>
      </t>

    </section>

    <section title='Conventions Used in This Document'>

      <t>
        The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT", 
        "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this 
        document are to be interpreted as described in 
        <xref target='RFC2119' />.
      </t>

      <t>
        The underlying format used for jCal is JSON. Consequently, the terms
        "object" and "array" as well as the four primitive types are to be
        interpreted as described in Section 1 of <xref target="RFC4627"/>.
      </t>

      <t>
        Some examples in this document contain "partial" JSON documents used 
        for illustrative purposes. In these examples, three periods "..." are 
        used to indicate a portion of the document that has been removed for 
        compactness.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section title='Converting from iCalendar to jCal'>
      <t>
        This section describes how iCalendar data is converted to jCal using a 
        simple mapping between the iCalendar data model and JSON elements.
      </t>

      <section title="Pre-processing">
        <t>
          iCalendar uses a line folding mechanism to limit lines of data to a 
          maximum line length (typically 72 characters) to ensure maximum 
          likelihood of preserving data integrity as it is transported via 
          various means (e.g., email) - see Section 3.1 of <xref target='RFC5545'/>. 
          Prior to converting iCalendar data into jCal all folded lines MUST be 
          unfolded.
        </t>

        <t>
          iCalendar data uses an "escape" character sequence for text values and 
          property parameter values. When such text elements are converted into 
          jCal the escaping MUST be removed. The only escaping that may be
          applied is any escaping mandated by JSON.

        </t>

        <t>
          iCalendar uses a base64 encoding for binary data. However, it does not 
          restrict the encoding from being applied to non-binary value types. 
          So the following rules MUST be applied when processing a property with 
          the "ENCODING" property parameter set to "BASE64":
          <list style="symbols">
            <t>
              If the property value type is "BINARY", the base64 encoding MUST 
              be preserved.
            </t>
            <t>
              If the value type is not "BINARY", the "ENCODING" property
               parameter MUST be removed, and the value MUST be base64 decoded.
             </t>
          </list>
        </t>
        
        <t>
          When base64 encoding and decoding is used, it MUST conform to Section 
          4 of <xref target='RFC4648'/>, which is the base64 method used in 
          <xref target='RFC5545'/>.
        </t>
        
        <t>
          One key difference in the formatting of values used in iCalendar and 
          jCal is that in jCal the specification uses date/time and utc-offset
          values aligned with the complete representation, extended format of
          <xref target="ISO.8601.2004"/>.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section title="iCalendar stream (RFC5545 section 3.4)">
        <t>
          At the top level of the iCalendar object model is an "iCalendar
          stream".  This stream encompasses multiple "iCalendar objects". In
          jCal, the entire stream is represented by an array, where the first
          element is the string "icalendar" and subsequent elements are
          iCalendar objects represented as described in this document.
        </t>

        <t>
          In the typical case where there is only one iCalendar object,
          encapsulation inside an "icalendar" array MAY be omitted.
        </t>

        <t>
          An iCalendar stream can contain one or more iCalendar objects. Each
          iCalendar object, delimited by "BEGIN:VCALENDAR" and "END:VCALENDAR",
          is represented by a fixed length array with three elements:
          <list style="numbers">
            <t>The string "vcalendar"</t>
            <t>An array of jCal properties</t>
            <t>An array of jCal components</t>
          </list>
        </t>

        <t>
          The representation of an iCalendar object in JSON will be named
          "vcalendar component" throughout this document.
        </t>

        <t>
          <figure>
            <preamble>Example:</preamble>
            <artwork><![CDATA[
["icalendar",
  ["vcalendar",
    [ /* properties */ ],
    [ /* components */ ]
  ],
  ["vcalendar",
    [ /* properties */ ],
    [ /* components */ ]
  ],
  ...
]
]]></artwork></figure>
        </t>

        <t>
          iCalendar objects are comprised of a set of "components", "properties", 
          "parameters" and "values". A "component" can contain other "components" 
          or "properties". A "property" has a "value" and a set of zero or more 
          "parameters".
        </t>
        
        <t>
          An iCalendar object may contain a mix of iCalendar component types, 
          for example vevent objects delimited by "BEGIN:VEVENT" and "END:VEVENT",
          task objects delimited by "BEGIN:VTODO" and "END:VTODO".
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="components" title="Components (RFC5545 section 3.6)">
        <t>
          Each calendar component in the "VCALENDAR" object, delimited by
          "BEGIN" and "END", will be converted to a fixed length array with
          three fields that have a specific structure:
          <list style="numbers">
            <t>
              A string with the name of the iCalendar component, but in
              lowercase.
            </t>
            <t>
              An array of jCal properties as described in
              <xref target="properties"/>.
            </t>
            <t>
              An array of jCal components, representing the sub-components of
              the component in question.
            </t>
          </list>
        </t>

        <t>
          While the grouping of properties and sub-components does not retain
          the original order specified in the iCalendar stream, the semantics
          of a component are preserved.
        </t>
        
        <t>
          The iCalendar to jCal component mapping is valid for both current
          iCalendar components and any new iCalendar components added in the
          future. Conversion is to be done in the same way.
        </t>

        <t>
          <figure>
            <preamble>Example:</preamble>
            <artwork><![CDATA[
["vevent",
  [ /* Array of jCal properties */ ],
  [ /* Array of jCal sub-components */ ]
]
]]></artwork></figure>    
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="properties" title="Properties (RFC5545 section 3.7 and 3.8)">
        <t>
          iCalendar properties, whether they apply to the "VCALENDAR" object 
          or to a component, are handled in a consistent way in the jCal format.
        </t>

        <t>
          Each individual iCalendar property is represented in jCal by an array
          with three fixed elements, followed by at one or more additional
          elements, depending on if the property is a multi-value property as
          described in Section 3.1.2 of <xref target="RFC5545"/>.
        </t>

        <t>
          The array consists of the following fixed elements:
          <list style="numbers">
            <t>The name of the property as a string, but in lowercase.</t>
            <t>
              An object containing the parameters as described in
              <xref target="parameters"/>.
            </t>
            <t>The type identifier string of the value, in lowercase.</t>
          </list>
          The remaining elements of the array are used for the value of the
          property. For single-value properties, the array MUST have exactly
          four elements, for multi-valued properties as described in
          <xref target="multivalue"/> there can be any number of additional
          elements.
        </t>

        <t>
          The array describing the property can then be inserted into the array
          designated for properties in any component, including the "vcalendar"
          component described in <xref target="components"/>. 
        </t>

        <t>
          <figure>
            <preamble>Example:</preamble>
            <artwork><![CDATA[
["vevent",
  [
    ["summary", {}, "text", "Meeting with Fred"],
    ["categories", {}, "text", "Meetings", "Work"]
    ...
  ],
  [ /* sub-components */ ]
]
]]></artwork></figure>
        </t>

        <t>
          The property parameters in the second element of the property array
          associate a set of parameter names with their respective value.
          Parameters are further described in <xref target="parameters"/>.
        </t>

        <t>
          To allow for a cleaner implementation, the parameter object MUST be
          present even if there are no parameters. In this case, an empty
          object MUST be used.
        </t>

        <section title="Special Cases for Properties">
          <t>
            This section describes some properties that have special handling 
            when converting to jCal.
          </t>

          <section anchor="multivalue" title="Multi-valued Properties (RFC5545 Section 3.1.2)">
            <t>
              Various iCalendar properties defined in <xref target="RFC5545"/>,
              for example the "CATEGORIES" property, are defined as multi-valued
              properties. In jCal these properties are added as further members
              of the array describing the property.
            </t>

            <t>
              Note that additional multi-valued properties may be added in
              extensions to the iCalendar format.
            </t>
          </section>
          
          <section title="GEO Property (RFC5545 Section 3.8.1.6)">
            <t>
              In iCalendar, the "GEO" property value is defined as a semi-colon 
              separated list of two "FLOAT" values, the first representing 
              latitude and the second longitude.
            </t>
            
            <t>
              In jCal, the value for the "geo" property value is represented as
              an array of two values. The first value of the property
              represents the latitude, the second value represents the
              longitude.
            </t>

            <t>
              When converting from jCal to iCalendar, the two values MUST be
              converted using a semi-colon as the separator character.
            </t>

            <t>
              This kind of special casing can be seen as a "structured value",
              as described in <xref target="I-D.ietf-jcardcal-jcard"/>, Section
              3.3.1.3. Implementors may want to keep this in mind in case they
              aim to support both jCard and jCal in their product. For example,
              checking the data type of all property values instead of assuming
              an array for just GEO is RECOMMENDED.
              <cref>Make sure section is still valid when publishing final rfc</cref>
            </t>

			<t>
			  <figure>
              <preamble>Example</preamble>
              <artwork><![CDATA[
["vevent", 
  [
    ["geo", {}, "float", [ 37.386013, -122.082932 ] ]
    ...
  ],
  ...
]
]]></artwork></figure>
	        </t>
          </section>
          
          <section title="REQUEST-STATUS Property (RFC5545 Section 3.8.8.3)">
            <t>
              In iCalendar, the "REQUEST-STATUS" property value is defined as a 
              semi-colon separated list of two or three "TEXT" values. The first 
              represents a code, the second a description, and the third any 
              additional data.
            </t>
            
            <t>
              In jCal, the value for the "request-status" property value is
              represented as an array with two or three values. The first array
              element corresponds to the code, the second element  corresponds
              to the description and the third element corresponds to the
              additional data. Each value is represented using a string value.
              If there is no additional data in the iCalendar value, the last
              element of the array SHOULD NOT be present.
            </t>

            <t>
              This kind of special casing can be seen as a "structured value",
              as described in <xref target="I-D.ietf-jcardcal-jcard"/>, Section
              3.3.1.3. Implementors may want to keep this in mind in case they
              aim to support both jCard and jCal in their product. For example,
              checking the data type of all property values instead of assuming
              an array for just REQUEST-STATUS is RECOMMENDED.
              <cref>Make sure section is still valid when publishing final rfc</cref>
            </t>

            <t>
              When converting from jCal to iCalendar, the two or three values
              MUST be converted using a semi-colon as the separator character.
            </t>
            
			<t>
			  <figure>
                <preamble>Example:</preamble>
                <artwork><![CDATA[
["vevent":
  [
    ["request-status", {}, "text", "2.0", "Success" ],
    ["request-status", {}, "text",
       [
        "3.7",
        "Invalid Calendar User",
        "ATTENDEE:mailto:jsmith@example.org"
       ]
    ],
    ...
  ],
  ...
]
]]></artwork></figure>
	        </t>
          </section>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section anchor="parameters" title="Parameters (RFC5545 section 3.2)">
        <t>
          Property parameters are represented as a JSON object where each
          key-value pair represents the iCalendar parameter name and its value.
          The name of the parameter MUST be in lowercase, the original case of
          the parameter value MUST be preserved.
        </t>

        <t>
          Each individual iCalendar property parameter is represented in jCal
          by a key-value pair in the parameters object. The key uses the
          same name as the iCalendar property parameter, but in lowercase. For
          example, the "PARTSTAT" property parameter is represented in jCal by
          the "partstat" key. The case of the parameter value MUST be
          preserved.
        </t>

        <t>
          <figure>
            <preamble>Example:</preamble>
          <artwork><![CDATA[
["vevent":
  [
    ["attendee",
     { 
       "partstat": "ACCEPTED",
       "rsvp": "TRUE",
       "role": "REQ-PARTICIPANT"
     },
     "cal-address",
     "mailto:jsmith@example.org"
    ],
    ["summary", {}, "text", "Meeting"],
    ...
  ],
  ...
]
]]></artwork></figure>
        </t>

        <section title="VALUE parameter">
          <t>
            iCalendar defines a "VALUE" property parameter (Section 3.2.20 of
            <xref target='RFC5545'/>). This property parameter MUST NOT be
            added to the parameters object. Instead, the value type is always
            explicitly mentioned in the third element of the array describing
            the property. Thus, when converting from iCalendar to jCal, any
            "VALUE" property parameters are skipped. When converting from
            jCal into iCalendar, the appropriate "VALUE" property parameter MUST
            be included in the iCalendar property if the value type is not
            "unknown" or the default value type for that property. See
            <xref target="unrecognized"/> for information on handling unknown
            value types.
          </t>
        </section>

        <section title="Multi-value Parameters">
          <t>
            In <xref target='RFC5545'/>, some parameters allow using a
            COMMA-separated list of values. To ease processing in jCal, the
            value of a parameter with multiple values MUST be represented
            in an array containing the separated values. The array elements
            MUST be string values. Single-value parameters SHOULD be
            represented using a single string value, but an array with one
            element MAY also be used. An example for a such parameter is the
            iCalendar "DELEGATED-FROM" and "DELEGATED-TO" parameter, more such
            parameters may be added in extensions.
          </t>

          <t>
            DQUOTE characters used to encapsulate the separated values MUST NOT
            be added to the jCal parameter value.
          </t>
          <t>
            <figure>
              <preamble>Example 1:</preamble>
              <artwork><![CDATA[
...
["attendee",
 { 
   "delegated-to": ["mailto:jdoe@example.org",
                    "mailto:jqpublic@example.org"]
 },
 "cal-address",
 "mailto:jsmith@example.org"
],
...
]]></artwork></figure>
          </t>
          <t>
            <figure>
              <preamble>Example 2:</preamble>
              <artwork><![CDATA[
...
["attendee",
 { 
   "delegated-to": "mailto:jdoe@example.org"
 },
 "cal-address",
 "mailto:jsmith@example.org"
],
...
]]></artwork></figure>
          </t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section anchor="values" title="Values (RFC5545 section 3.3)">
        <t>
          The type of an iCalendar value is explicitly mentioned in the third
          element of the array describing a jCal property. The actual values of
          the property can be found in the fourth and following elements of the
          array.
        </t>

        <section title="Binary (RFC5545 section 3.3.1)">
        <t><list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="Description:">
              iCalendar "BINARY" properties are represented by a property with
              type identifier "binary". The value is base64 encoded data,
              conforming to Section 4 of <xref target='RFC4648'/>, which is the
              base64 method used in <xref target='RFC5545'/>.
            </t>

			<t hangText="Example:"><figure><artwork><![CDATA[
...
["attach", {}, "binary", "SGVsbG8gV29ybGQh"],
...
]]></artwork></figure></t>
          </list></t>
        </section>
        <section title="Boolean  (RFC5545 section 3.3.2)">
          <t><list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="Description:">
              iCalendar "BOOLEAN" properties are represented by a property with
              the type identifier "boolean". The value is a boolean JSON value.
            </t>

			<t hangText="Example:"><figure><artwork><![CDATA[
...
["x-non-smoking", {}, "boolean", true],
...
]]></artwork></figure></t>
          </list></t>
        </section>
        <section title="Calendar User Address (RFC5545 section 3.3.3)">
          <t><list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="Description:">
              iCalendar "CAL-ADDRESS" properties are represented by a property
              with the type identifier "cal-address". The value is a string
              with the URI as described in <xref target="RFC3986"/>.
            </t>

			<t hangText="Example:"><figure><artwork><![CDATA[
...
["attendee", {}, "cal-address", "mailto:kewisch@example.com"],
...
]]></artwork></figure></t>
          </list></t>
        </section>
        <section title="Date (RFC5545 section 3.3.4)">
          <t><list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="Description:">
              iCalendar "DATE" properties are represented by a property with
              the type identifier "date". The value is the same date value
              specified by <xref target="RFC5545"/>, but formatted using the
              <xref target="ISO.8601.2004"/> complete representation, extended
              format. The textual format specifies a four-digit year, two-digit
              month, and two-digit day of the month, separated by the "-"
              character.
            </t>

			<t hangText="Example:"><figure><artwork><![CDATA[
...
["dtstart", {}, "date", "2011-05-17"],
...
]]></artwork></figure></t>
          </list></t>
        </section>
        <section title="Date-Time (RFC5545 section 3.3.5)">
          <t><list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="Description:">
              iCalendar "DATE-TIME" properties are represented by a property
              with the type identifier "date-time". The value is the same date
              value specified by <xref target="RFC5545"/>, but formatted using
              the <xref target="ISO.8601.2004"/> complete representation,
              extended format. The same restrictions with respect to leap
              seconds and timezone offsets as specified in <xref
              target="RFC5545"/> Section 3.3.5 apply.
            </t>

			<t hangText="Example:"><figure><artwork><![CDATA[
...
["dtstart", {}, "date-time", "2012-10-17T12:00:00"],
["dtstamp", {}, "date-time", "2012-10-17T12:00:00Z"],
["dtend",
 { "tzid": "Europe/Berlin" },
 "date-time",
 "2011-10-17T13:00:00"
],
...
]]></artwork></figure></t>
          </list></t>
        </section>
        <section title="Duration (RFC5545 section 3.3.6)">
          <t><list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="Description:">
              iCalendar "DURATION" properties are represented by a property
              with the type identifier "duration". The value is the same
              duration value specified by <xref target="RFC5545"/> as a string.
            </t>

			<t hangText="Example:"><figure><artwork><![CDATA[
...
["duration", {}, "duration", "P1D"],
...
]]></artwork></figure></t>
          </list></t>
        </section>
        <section title="Float (RFC5545 section 3.3.7)">
          <t><list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="Description:">
              iCalendar "FLOAT" properties are represented by a property with
              the type identifier "float". The value is the floating point
              number as a JSON primitive number value.
            </t>

			<t hangText="Example:"><figure><artwork><![CDATA[
...
["x-grade", {}, "float", 1.3],
...
]]></artwork></figure></t>
          </list></t>
        </section>
        <section title="Integer (RFC5545 section 3.3.8)">
          <t><list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="Description:">
              iCalendar "INTEGER" properties are represented by a property with
              the type identifier "integer". The value is the floating point
              number as a JSON primitive number value.
            </t>

			<t hangText="Examples:"><figure><artwork><![CDATA[
...
["percent-complete", {}, "integer", 42],
...
]]></artwork></figure></t>
          </list></t>
        </section>
        <section title="Period of Time (RFC5545 section 3.3.9)">
          <t><list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="Description:">
              iCalendar "PERIOD" properties are represented by a jCal property
              with the type identifier "period". The property value is an
              array, with the first element representing the start of the
              period and the second element representing the end of the period.
              As in <xref target='RFC5545'/>, the start of the period is always
              formatted as a date-time value and the end of the period MUST be
              either a date-time or duration value. Any date, date-time or
              duration values contained in the period value MUST be formatted
              in accordance to the rules for date, date-time or duration values
              specified in this document.
            </t>

			<t hangText="Example:"><figure><artwork><![CDATA[
...
["freebusy",
 { "fbtype": "FREE" },
 "period",
 ["1997-03-08T16:00:00Z", "P1D"]
],
...
]]></artwork></figure></t>
          </list></t>
        </section>
        <section title="Recurrence Rule (RFC5545 section 3.3.10)">
          <t><list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="Description:">
              iCalendar "RECUR" properties are represented by a property with
              the type identifier "recur". The value is an object describing
              the structured data as specified by <xref target='RFC5545'/>.
              Each rule part is described by the combination of key and value.
              The key specifies the name of the rule part and MUST be converted
              to lowercase. The value of the rule part MUST be mapped by the
              following rules:

              <list style="symbols">
                <t>
                  The value of the "freq" and "wskt" rule parts MUST be a
                  string as specified in <xref target='RFC5545'/>, with case
                  preserved.
                </t>
                <t>
                  The value of the "until" rule part MUST be a date or
                  date-time value formatted in accordance to the rules for date
                  or date-time specified in this document.
                </t>
                <t>
                  The "count" and "interval" rule parts MUST be specified as a
                  single number value.
                </t>
                <t>
                  The "bysecond", "byminute", "byhour", "bymonthday",
                  "byyearday", "byweekno", "bymonth" and "bysetpos" rule parts
                  MUST each be specified as an array with multiple number values.
                  Single-value rule parts SHOULD be represented using a single
                  string value, but an array with one element MAY also be used.
                </t>
                <t>
                  The "byday" rule part MUST be specified as an array with
                  multiple string values. A single-value "byday" rule part
                  SHOULD be represented using a single string value, but an
                  array with one element MAY also be used.
                </t>
              </list>
            </t>

			<t hangText="Example 1:"><figure><artwork><![CDATA[
...
["rrule",
 {},
 "recur",
 {
   "freq": "YEARLY",
   "count": 5,
   "byday": [ "-1SU", "2MO" ],
   "bymonth": 10
 }
],
...
]]></artwork></figure></t>
			<t hangText="Example 2:"><figure><artwork><![CDATA[
...
["rrule",
 {},
 "recur",
 { 
   "freq": "MONTHLY",
   "interval": 2,
   "bymonthday": [ 1, 15, -1 ],
   "until": "2013-10-01"
 }
],
...
]]></artwork></figure></t>
          </list></t>
        </section>
        <section title="Text (RFC5545 section 3.3.11)">
          <t><list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="Description:">
              iCalendar "TEXT" properties are represented by a property with
              the type identifier "text". The value is the same text value
              specified by <xref target='RFC5545'/> as a string.
            </t>

			<t hangText="Example:"><figure><artwork><![CDATA[
...
["comment", {}, "text", "hello, world"],
...
]]></artwork></figure></t>
          </list></t>
        </section>
        <section title="Time (RFC5545 section 3.3.12)">
          <t><list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="Description:">
              iCalendar "TIME" propertes are represented by a property with the
              type identifier "time". The value is the same date value
              specified by <xref target="RFC5545"/>, but formatted using the
              <xref target="ISO.8601.2004"/> complete representation, extended
              format. The same restrictions with respect to leap seconds, time
              fractions, and timezone offsets as specified in
              <xref target="RFC5545"/> Section 3.3.12 apply.
            </t>

			<t hangText="Example:"><figure><artwork><![CDATA[
...
["x-time-local", {}, "time", "12:30:00"],
["x-time-utc", {}, "time", "12:30:00Z"],
["x-time-offset", { "tzid": "Europe/Berlin" }, "time", "12:30:00"],
...
]]></artwork></figure></t>
          </list></t>
        </section>
        <section title="URI (RFC5545 section 3.3.13)">
          <t><list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="Description:">
              iCalendar "URI" properties are represented by a property with the
              type identifier "uri". The value is a string with the URI.
            </t>

			<t hangText="Example:"><figure><artwork><![CDATA[
...
["tzurl", {}, "uri", "http://example.org/tz/Europe-Berlin.ics"],
...
]]></artwork></figure></t>
          </list></t>
        </section>
        <section title="UTC Offset (RFC5545 section 3.3.14)">
          <t><list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="Description:">
              iCalendar "UTC-OFFSET" properties are represented by a property
              with the type identifier "utc-offset". The value is a string with
              the same UTC offset value specified by <xref target="RFC5545"/>,
              with the exception that the hour and minute components are
              separated by a ":" character, for consistency with the
              <xref target="ISO.8601.2004"/> timezone offset, extended format.
            </t>

			<t hangText="Example:"><figure><artwork><![CDATA[
...
["tzoffsetfrom", {}, "utc-offset", "-05:00"],
["tzoffsetto", {}, "utc-offset", "+12:45"],
..

]]></artwork></figure></t>
          </list></t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section title="Extensions">
        <t>
          iCalendar extension properties and property parameters (those with an
          "X-" prefix in their name) are handled in the same way as other
          properties and property parameters: the property is represented by an
          array, the property parameter represented by an object. The property
          or parameter name uses the same name as for the iCalendar extension,
          but in lowercase. For example, the "X-FOO" property in iCalendar
          turns into the "x-foo" jCal property. See <xref target="unrecognized"/>
          for how to deal with default values for unrecognized extension
          properties or property parameters.
        </t>
      </section>

    </section>

    <section title="Converting from jCal into iCalendar">
      <t>
        When converting component, property and property parameter values, the
        names SHOULD be converted to uppercase. Although iCalendar names are
        case insensitive, common practice is to keep them all uppercase
        following the actual definitions in <xref target="RFC5545"/>.
      </t>

      <t>
        Backslash escaping and line folding MUST be applied to the resulting
        iCalendar data as required by <xref target="RFC5545"/>.
      </t>
      
      <t>Non-binary value types MUST NOT be base64 encoded.</t>

      <t>
        jCal properties that do not specify the default type for the iCalendar
        property MUST add a VALUE parameter when converting to iCalendar. jCal
        properties that specify the default type SHOULD NOT add a VALUE
        parameter.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section title="Handling Unrecognized Properties or Parameters" anchor="unrecognized">
      <t>
        In iCalendar, properties have a default value type specified by their
        definition, e.g. "SUMMARY"'s value type is "TEXT" and "DURATION"'s is
        "DURATION". When a property uses its default value type, the "VALUE"
        property parameter does not need to be specified on the property.
      </t>
      <t>
        When new properties are defined or "X-" properties used, an iCalendar
        to jCal converter might not recognize them, and not know what the
        appropriate default value types are, yet they need to be able to
        preserve the values. A similar issue arises for unrecognized property
        parameters.
      </t>
      <t>
        In jCal, a new UNKNOWN property value type is introduced. Its purpose
        is to allow preserving unknown property values when roundtripping
        between jCal and iCalendar.

        <list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="Value name:">UNKNOWN</t>
          <t hangText="Purpose:">
            To allow preserving unknown property values during roundtripping
          </t>
          <t hangText="Format definition:">(Not applicable)</t>
          <t hangText="Description:">
            The UNKNOWN value data type is reserved for the exclusive use of
            the jCal format &thisrfc;. It MUST NOT be used in plain iCalendar
            <xref target="RFC5545"/>. Conversion rules are as follows:

            <list style="symbols">
              <t>When converting iCalendar into jCal:
                <list style="symbols">
                  <t>
                    Any property that does not include a "VALUE" property
                    parameter and whose default value type is not known, MUST
                    be converted to a primative JSON string. The content of
                    that string is the unprocessed value text. Also, value type
                    MUST be set to "unknown".
                  </t>
                  <t>
                    To correctly implement this format, it is critical that if
                    the default type is not known that the type "unknown" is
                    used. If this requirement is ignored and for example "text"
                    is used, additional escaping may occur which breaks
                    roundtripping values.
                  </t>
                  <t>
                    Any unrecognized property parameter MUST be converted to a
                    string value, with its content set to the property
                    parameter value text, treated as if it were a "TEXT" value.
                  </t>
                </list>
              </t>
              
              <t>When converting jCal into iCalendar:
                <list style="symbols">
                  <t>
                    Since jCal always explicitly specifies the value type, it
                    can always be converted to iCalendar using the VALUE
                    parameter.
                  </t>
                  <t>
                    If the value type specified in jCal matches the default
                    value type in iCalendar, the VALUE parameter SHOULD be
                    omitted.
                  </t>
                  <t>
                    If the value type specified in jCal is set to "unknown",
                    the value MUST be taken over in iCalendar without proessing. In
                    this case, the VALUE parameter MUST NOT be specified.
                  </t>
                </list>
              </t>
            </list>
          </t>
        </list>
      </t>

      <t>
        Example: The following is an example of an unrecognized iCalendar
        property (that uses a "DATE-TIME" value as its default), and the
        equivalent jCal representation of that property.
      </t>
        
      <figure><preamble>iCalendar:</preamble><artwork><![CDATA[
X-PROPERTY:20110512T120000Z
]]></artwork></figure>
        
      <figure><preamble>jCal:</preamble><artwork><![CDATA[
...
["x-property", {}, "unknown", "20110512T120000Z"],
...
]]></artwork></figure>
      <t>
        Example: The following is an example of how to cope with jCal data
        where the parser was unable to identify the type. Note how the
        "unknown" value type is not added to the iCalendar data and escaping,
        aside from standard JSON string escaping, is not processed.
      </t>
      <figure><preamble>jCal:</preamble><artwork><![CDATA[
...
["x-coffee-data", {}, "unknown", "Stenophylla;Guinea\\,Africa"],
...
]]></artwork></figure>
        <figure><preamble>iCalendar:</preamble><artwork><![CDATA[
X-COFFEE-DATA:Stenophylla;Guinea\,Africa
]]></artwork></figure>

      <t>
        Example: The following is an example of a jCal property (where the
        corresponding iCalendar property uses a "INTEGER" value as its
        default), and the equivalent iCalendar representation of that
        property.
      </t>
        
        <figure><preamble>jCal:</preamble><artwork><![CDATA[
...
["percent-complete", {}, "integer", 95],
...
]]></artwork></figure>

        <figure><preamble>iCalendar:</preamble><artwork><![CDATA[
PERCENT-COMPLETE:95
]]></artwork></figure>

      <t>
        Example: The following is an example of an unrecognized iCalendar
        property parameter (that uses a "FLOAT" value as its default) specified
        on a recognized iCalendar property, and the equivalent jCal
        representation of that property and property parameter.
      </t>
        
        <figure><preamble>iCalendar:</preamble><artwork><![CDATA[
DTSTART;X-PARAM=30.3;VALUE=DATE:20110512
]]></artwork></figure>
        
        <figure><preamble>jCal:</preamble><artwork><![CDATA[
...
["dtstart", { "x-param": "30.3" }, "date", "2011-05-12"],
...
]]></artwork></figure>
    </section>

    <section title="Implementation Status (to be removed prior to publication as an RFC)">
      <t>
        This section describes libraries known to implement this draft as per
        <xref target='I-D.sheffer-running-code'/>.
        <list style="numbers">
          <t>
            ICAL.js - Philipp Kewisch, James Lal. A JavaScript parser for iCalendar (rfc5545)
            <list style="hanging">
              <t hangText="Source:">https://github.com/mozilla-comm/ical.js/</t>
              <t hangText="Maturity:">production</t>
              <t hangText="Coverage:">All aspects of this draft, up to version 01. Includes an online validator. (as of rev 847c67c501, 2013-02-14)</t>
              <t hangText="Licensing:">MPL, Mozilla Public License 2.0</t>
            </list>
          </t>
          <t>
            Py Calendar - Cyrus Daboo. iCalendar/vCard Library
            <list style="hanging">
              <t hangText="Source:">https://svn.calendarserver.org/repository/calendarserver/PyCalendar/branches/json/</t>
              <t hangText="Maturity:">production</t>
              <t hangText="Coverage:">All aspects of this draft, up to version 01.</t>
              <t hangText="Licensing:">Apache License, Version 2.0</t>
            </list>
          </t>
        </list>
      </t>
      <t>
        Additionally, interoperability testing of this draft is an ongoing
        effort under members of calconnect, the Calendaring and Scheduling
        Consortium. CalDAV Vendors are looking into supporting this draft.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section title="Security Considerations" anchor="security">
      <t>
        For security considerations specific to calendar data, see Section 7 of
        <xref target="RFC5545"/>. Since this specification is a mapping from
        iCalendar, no new security concerns are introduced related to calendar
        data.
      </t>
 
      <t>
        The use of JSON as a format does have security risks. Section 7 of
        <xref target="RFC4627"/> discusses these risks.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>
        This document defines a MIME media type for use with iCalendar in JSON
        data. This media type SHOULD be used for the transfer of calendaring
        data in JSON.
        <list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="Type name:">application</t>
          <t hangText="Subtype name:">calendar+json</t>
          <t hangText="Required parameters:">none</t>
          <t hangText="Optional parameters:">
            method, component and optinfo as defined for the text/calendar
            media type in <xref target="RFC5545"/>.
          </t>
          <t hangText="Encoding considerations:">
            Same as encoding considerations of application/json as specified in
            <xref target="RFC4627"/>.
          </t>
          <t hangText="Security considerations:">See <xref target="security"/>.</t>
          <t hangText="Interoperability considerations:">
            This media type provides an alternative format for iCalendar data
            based on JSON.
          </t>
          <t hangText="Published specification:">This specification.</t>
          <t hangText="Applications which use this media type:">
            Applications that currently make use of the text/calendar media
            type can use this as an alternative. Similarly, Applications that
            use the application/json media type to transfer calendaring data
            can use this to further specify the content.
          </t>
          <t hangText="Person &amp; email address to contact for further information:">calsify@ietf.org</t>
          <t hangText="Intended usage:">COMMON</t>
          <t hangText="Restrictions on usage:">
            There are no restrictions on where this media type can be used.
          </t>
          <t hangText="Author:">
            See the "Author's Address" section of this document.
          </t>
          <t hangText="Change controller:">IETF</t>
        </list>
      </t>
      <section title="UNKNOWN iCalendar Value Data Type">
        <t>
          IANA has added the following entry to the iCalendar Data Types registry,
          defined in Section 8.3.4 of <xref target="RFC5545"/>.
        </t>
        <texttable>
          <ttcol>Value Data Type</ttcol>
          <ttcol>Status</ttcol>
          <ttcol>Reference</ttcol>
          <c>UNKNOWN</c>
          <c>Current</c>
          <c>
            &thisrfc;, <xref target="unrecognized"/>
          </c>
        </texttable>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Acknowledgments">
      <t>
        The authors would like to thank the following for their valuable
        contributions: William Gill, Erwin Rehme, and Dave Thewlis. This
        specification originated from the work of the XML-JSON technical
        committee of the Calendaring and Scheduling Consortium.
      </t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      &rfc2119;
      &rfc5234;
      &rfc4648;
      &rfc5545;
      &rfc6321;
      &rfc3986;
      <reference anchor="ISO.8601.2004">
        <front>
          <title>
            "Data elements and interchange formats -- Information interchange
            -- Representation of dates and times"
          </title>
          <author>
            <organization>International Organization for Standardization</organization>
          </author>
          <date year="2004" month="12"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="ISO" value="8601"/>
      </reference>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      &rfc4627;
      &I-D.sheffer-running-code;
      &I-D.ietf-jcardcal-jcard;
      <reference anchor="calconnect-artifacts"
                 target="http://www.calconnect.org/artifacts.shtml">
        <front>
          <title>Code Artifacts and Schemas</title>
          <author>
            <organization>The Calendaring and Scheduling Consortium</organization>
          </author>
          <date/>
        </front>
      </reference>
    </references>
            

    <section anchor="schema" title="ABNF Schema">
      <t>
        Below is an ABNF schema as per <xref target="RFC5234"/> for iCalendar
        in JSON. ABNF Symbols not described here are taken from
        <xref target="RFC4627"/>. The schema is non-normative and given for
        reference only.
      </t>
      
      <t>
        The numeric section numbers given in the comments refer to section in
        <xref target="RFC5545"/>. Additional semantic restrictions apply,
        especially regarding the allowed properties and sub-components per
        component. Details on these restrictions can be found in this document
        and <xref target="RFC5545"/>.
      </t>

      <t>
        Additional schemas may be available on the internet at
        <xref target="calconnect-artifacts"/>.
      </t>

      <figure><artwork><![CDATA[
; An iCalendar Stream is an array with the first element being the
; string "icalendar". All remaining elements are jcalobjects.
jcalstream = begin-array
             DQUOTE "icalendar" DQUOTE
             *(value-separator jcalobject)
             end-array

; A jCal Object is a component with the component-name "vcalendar".
; Restrictions to which properties and sub-components may be
; specified are to be taken from RFC5545.
jcalobject = component

; A jCal component consists of the name string, properties array and
; component array
component = begin-array
            DQUOTE component-name DQUOTE value-separator
            properties-array value-separator
            components-array
            end-array

components-array = begin-array
                   [ component *(value-separator component) ]
                   end-array

; A jCal property consists of the name string, parameters object,
; type string and one or more values as specified in this document.
property = begin-array
           DQUOTE property-name DQUOTE value-separator
           params-object value-separator
           DQUOTE type-name DQUOTE
           propery-value *(value-separator property-value)
           end-array
properties-array = begin-array
                   [ property *(value-separator property) ]
                   end-array

; Property values depend on the type-name. Aside from the value types
; mentioned here, extensions may make use of other JSON value types.
; The non-terminal symbol sructured-prop-value covers the special
; cases for GEO and REQUEST-STATUS
property-value = simple-prop-value / structured-prop-value
simple-prop-value = string / number / boolean
structured-prop-value = 
    begin-array
    [ structured-element *(value-separator structured-element) ]
    end-array
structured-element = simple-prop-value

; The jCal params-object is a JSON object which follows the semantic
; guidelines described in this document.
params-object = begin-object
                [ params-member *(value-separator params-member) ]
                end-object
params-member = DQUOTE param-name DQUOTE name-separator param-value
param-value = string / param-multi
param-multi = begin-array
              [ string *(value-separtor string) ]
              end-array

; The type MUST be a valid type as described by this document. New
; value types can be added by extensions.
type-name = "binary" / "boolean" / "cal-address" / "date" /
            "date-time" / "duration" / "float" / "integer" /
            "period" / "recur" / "text" / "time" / "uri" /
            "utc-offset" / x-type
           

; Component, property, parameter and type names MUST be lowercase.
; Additional semantic restrictions apply as described by this
; document and RFC5545.
component-name = lowercase-name
property-name = lowercase-name
param-name = lowercase-name
x-type = lowercase-name
lowercase-name = 1*(%x61-7A / DIGIT / "-")
]]></artwork></figure>
    </section>

    <section title="Examples">
      <t>
        This section contains two examples of iCalendar objects with their jCal
        representation.
      </t>

      <section title="Example 1">
        <section title="iCalendar Data">
          <figure><artwork><![CDATA[
BEGIN:VCALENDAR 
CALSCALE:GREGORIAN 
PRODID:-//Example Inc.//Example Calendar//EN
VERSION:2.0 
BEGIN:VEVENT 
DTSTAMP:20080205T191224Z 
DTSTART:20081006 
SUMMARY:Planning meeting 
UID:4088E990AD89CB3DBB484909 
END:VEVENT 
END:VCALENDAR 
]]></artwork></figure>
        </section>

        <section title="jCal Data">
          <figure><artwork><![CDATA[
["vcalendar",
  [
    ["calscale", {}, "text", "GREGORIAN"],
    ["prodid", {}, "text", "-//Example Inc.//Example Calendar//EN"],
    ["version", {}, "text", "2.0"]
  ],
  [
    ["vevent",
      [
        ["dtstamp", {}, "date-time", "2008-02-05T19:12:24Z"],
        ["dtstart", {}, "date", "2008-10-06"],
        ["summary", {}, "text", "Planning meeting"],
        ["uid", {}, "text", "4088E990AD89CB3DBB484909"],
      ],
      []
    ]
  ]
]
]]></artwork></figure>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section title="Example 2">

        <section title="iCalendar Data">
          <figure><artwork><![CDATA[
BEGIN:VCALENDAR
VERSION:2.0
PRODID:-//Example Corp.//Example Client//EN
BEGIN:VTIMEZONE
LAST-MODIFIED:20040110T032845Z
TZID:US/Eastern
BEGIN:DAYLIGHT
DTSTART:20000404T020000
RRULE:FREQ=YEARLY;BYDAY=1SU;BYMONTH=4
TZNAME:EDT
TZOFFSETFROM:-0500
TZOFFSETTO:-0400
END:DAYLIGHT
BEGIN:STANDARD
DTSTART:20001026T020000
RRULE:FREQ=YEARLY;BYDAY=-1SU;BYMONTH=10
TZNAME:EST
TZOFFSETFROM:-0400
TZOFFSETTO:-0500
END:STANDARD
END:VTIMEZONE
BEGIN:VEVENT
DTSTAMP:20060206T001121Z
DTSTART;TZID=US/Eastern:20060102T120000
DURATION:PT1H
RRULE:FREQ=DAILY;COUNT=5
RDATE;TZID=US/Eastern;VALUE=PERIOD:20060102T150000/PT2H
SUMMARY:Event #2
DESCRIPTION:We are having a meeting all this week at 12 pm fo
 r one hour\, with an additional meeting on the first day 2 h
 ours long.\nPlease bring your own lunch for the 12 pm meetin
 gs.
UID:00959BC664CA650E933C892C@example.com
END:VEVENT
BEGIN:VEVENT
DTSTAMP:20060206T001121Z
DTSTART;TZID=US/Eastern:20060104T140000
DURATION:PT1H
RECURRENCE-ID;TZID=US/Eastern:20060104T120000
SUMMARY:Event #2 bis
UID:00959BC664CA650E933C892C@example.com
END:VEVENT
END:VCALENDAR
]]></artwork></figure>
        </section>

        <section title="jCal Data">
          <figure><artwork><![CDATA[
["vcalendar",
  [
    ["prodid", {}, "text", "-//Example Corp.//Example Client//EN"],
    ["version", {}, "text", "2.0"],
  ],
  [
    ["vtimezone",
      [
        ["last-modified", {}, "date-time", "2004-01-10T03:28:45Z"],
        ["tzid", {}, "text", "US/Eastern"],
      ],
      [
        ["daylight",
          [
            ["dtstart", {}, "date-time", "2000-04-04T02:00:00"],
            ["rrule",
             {},
             "recur",
             "FREQ=YEARLY;BYDAY=1SU;BYMONTH=4"
            ],
            ["tzname", {}, "text", "EDT"],
            ["tzoffsetfrom", {}, "utc-offset", "-05:00"],
            ["tzoffsetto", {}, "utc-offset", "-04:00"]
          ],
          []
        ],
        ["standard",
          [
            ["dtstart", {}, "date-time", "2000-10-26T02:00:00"],
            ["rrule",
             {},
             "recur",
             "FREQ=YEARLY;BYDAY=1SU;BYMONTH=10"
            ],
            ["tzname", {}, "text", "EST"],
            ["tzoffsetfrom", {}, "utc-offset", "-04:00"],
            ["tzoffsetto", {}, "utc-offset", "-05:00"]
          ],
          []
        ]
      ]
    ],
    ["vevent",
      [
        ["dtstamp", {}, "date-time", "2006-02-06T00:11:21Z"],
        ["dtstart",
         { "tzid": "US/Eastern" },
         "date-time",
         "2006-01-02T12:00:00"
        ],
        ["duration", {}, "duration", "PT1H"],
        ["rrule", {}, "recur", "FREQ=DAILY;COUNT=5"],
        ["rdate",
         { "tzid": "US/Eastern" },
         "period",
         "2006-01-02T15:00:00/PT2H"
        ],
        ["summary", {}, "text", "Event #2"],
        ["description",
         {},
         "text",
         // Note that comments and string concatenation are not
         // allowed per JSON specification and is used here only
         // to avoid long lines.
         "We are having a meeting all this week at 12 pm for one " +
         "hour, with an additional meeting on the first day 2 " +
         "hours long.\nPlease bring your own lunch for the 12 pm " +
         "meetings."
        ],
        ["uid", {}, "text", "00959BC664CA650E933C892C@example.com"]
      ],
      []
    ],
    ["vevent",
      [
        ["dtstamp", {}, "date-time", "2006-02-06T00:11:21Z"],
        ["dtstart",
         { "tzid": "US/Eastern" },
         "date-time",
         "2006-01-02T14:00:00"
        ],
        ["duration", {}, "duration", "PT1H"],
        ["recurrence-id",
         { "tzid": "US/Eastern" },
         "date-time",
         "2006-01-04T12:00:00"
        ],
        ["summary", {}, "text", "Event #2"],
        ["uid", {}, "text", "00959BC664CA650E933C892C@example.com"]
      ],
      []
    ]
  ]
]
]]></artwork></figure>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>


    <section title='Change History (to be removed prior to publication as an RFC)'>
      <t>
        <list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="draft-kewisch-et-al-icalendar-in-json-01">
            <list style="symbols">
              <t>
                Added information on how to handle multi-value parameter. The
                decision leads to a cleaner draft for a similar proposal for
                vcard.
              </t>
              <t>
                Removed the open discussion point section regarding the mime
                media type in favor of adding one.
              </t>
              <t>
                Minor corrections in wording and typo fixes.
              </t>
            </list>
          </t>
          <t hangText="draft-kewisch-et-al-icalendar-in-json-02">
            <list style="symbols">
              <t>
                Added implementation status section.
              </t>
              <t>
                Removed various text tables that just show a conversion from
                uppercase to lowercase.
              </t>
              <t>
                Changed value format for RECUR and PERIOD types
              </t>
              <t>
                Minor corrections in wording and typo fixes.
              </t>
            </list>
          </t>
          <t hangText="draft-ietf-jcardcal-jcal-00">
            <list style="symbols">
              <t>
                Pubication as a WG draft
              </t>
            </list>
          </t>
          <t hangText="draft-ietf-jcardcal-jcal-01">
            <list style="symbols">
              <t>
                Changed handling of GEO and REQUEST-STATUS to align with jCard
              </t>
              <t>
                Corrections and additions to the ABNF Section
              </t>
              <t>
                Added a further sentence on preprocessing and escaping to clarify that JSON escaping must be used.
              </t>
            </list>
          </t>
          <t hangText="draft-ietf-jcardcal-jcal-02">
            <list style="symbols">
              <t>
                Changed handling of unknown property parameter types.
              </t>
              <t>
                Minor corrections and fixing typos.
              </t>
            </list>
          </t>
        </list>
      </t>
    </section>
  </back>
</rfc>
