<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<?rfc artworklines="1"?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc rfcedstyle="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc  PUBLIC "" "rfc2629.dtd" [
	  <!ENTITY RFC1518 SYSTEM
		   "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1518.xml"> 
	  <!ENTITY RFC1519 SYSTEM
		   "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1519.xml"> 
	  <!ENTITY RFC1887 SYSTEM
		   "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1887.xml">
	  <!ENTITY RFC2131 SYSTEM
		   "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2131.xml"> 
	  <!ENTITY RFC3221 SYSTEM
		   "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3221.xml"> 
	  <!ENTITY RFC4116 SYSTEM
		   "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4116.xml"> 
	  <!ENTITY RFC4632 SYSTEM
		   "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4632.xml"> 
	  <!ENTITY I-D.narten-radir-problem-statement SYSTEM
		   "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.narten-radir-problem-statement.xml"> 
	  ] >
<rfc ipr="trust200902" docName="draft-azinger-cidrv6-00" updates="1887"
     category="std">
  <front>
    <title abbrev='CIDR for IPv6'>
      CIDR for IPv6: Address Aggregation, Allocation, and Assignment Strategy
    </title> 

    <author initials="M." surname="Azinger" fullname="Marla Azinger">
      <organization>Frontier Communications Corporation</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <city>Vancouver</city>
          <region>WA</region>
          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>
        <email>marla.azinger@frontiercorp.com</email>
        <uri>http://www.frontiercorp.com/</uri>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Tony Li" initials="T." surname="Li">
      <organization>Cisco Systems</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>170 West Tasman Dr.</street>
          <city>San Jose</city>
          <region>CA</region>
          <code>95134</code>
          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>
        <phone>+1 408 853 9317</phone>
        <email>tony.li@tony.li</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Jason Weil" initials="J." surname="Weil">
      <organization>Cox Communications</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>1400 Lake Hearn Dr.</street>
          <city>Atlanta</city>
          <region>GA</region>
          <code>95134</code>
          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>
        <phone>+1 404 269 6809</phone>
        <email>jason.weil@cox.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date month="June" day="29" year="2010"/>

    <abstract>
      <t>
	This document discusses strategies for assigning and aggregating
	IPv6 address space.  While CIDR was created to help alleviate this
	problem in regards to IPv4 addresses with the original
	<xref target='RFC1519'/> (and updated in <xref target='RFC4632'/>)
	we are now in need of a similar document to give direction for IPv6
	addressing policies. Similarly, <xref target='RFC1518'/> discussed
	how to use CIDR to allocate address space for IPv4, and
	<xref target='RFC1887'/> discusses the subject for IPv6.  The
	objective here is to update these documents and provide the best
	current guidance on how to manage address space in conjunction with
	managing the growth of routing tables in an IPv6 world.
      </t>
    </abstract>

  </front>
  <middle>
    <section anchor="intro" title="Introduction">
      <t>
	The Internet has continued to evolve and the demands placed on its
	infrastructure continue to grow at an increasing rate. While there
	are a number of contributing factors there are a few key elements
	that have led to a concerning escalation in routing table growth
	and have made scalability an area of serious concern for network
	operators.  Effort must be put forward to minimize the impact of
	IPv6 deployment to the routing system. Two key aspects of this
	system include routing table churn composed of routing
	advertisements and withdrawals and the routing table size as
	measured by the number of entries in the DFZ, the Default-Free
	zone. While retaining current Internet practices, this document
	addresses the problem of routing table size by examining steps to
	minimize the impact of Multi-homing and Traffic Engineering, two
	widely implemented features that provide enhanced network
	resiliency and traffic path control.
      </t>
      </section>
    <section title="Contributing factors to the problem">
      <t>
	There are several factors that work against routing table
	scalability.  A full description of the contributing factors and
	views can be read in
	<xref target='I-D.narten-radir-problem-statement'/>. The exhaustion
	of the unassigned IPv4 address space is the principal motivator
	resulting in two of the key growth drivers. The first driver is the
	presence of increasingly longer prefixes in the DFZ Over the years
	the longest prefix generally accepted globally has increased from a
	relatively small number of classful prefixes to a preponderance of
	classless /24 CIDR prefixes. As IPv4 address availability
	diminishes, more Internet users are and will continue to push their
	providers to route even longer prefixes externally that in the past
	were filtered.  This is something that we must look to minimize and
	find ways to deter as much as possible.
      </t>
      <t>
	The second driver resulting from IPv4 address exhaustion is the
	rapid uptake in IPv6 deployment by providers and end users. This
	adoption, while clearly in the best interest for the long term
	viability of the Internet, contributes a unique set of challenges
	that must be addressed to promote efficient routing table
	growth. Some of these challenges visible today are the liberal
	assignment of Provider Independent (PI) space to end users,
	micro-allocations, and critical network infrastructure allocations
	by the various RIRs.
      </t>
      <t>
	These drivers have increased the need for more guidance on routing
	policy in order to limit the number of unnecessary entries in the
	global routing table. The future impact of this increased pressure
	on routing table growth is an area of immediate concern.
      </t>
    </section>
    <section title='Aggregation'>
      <t>
	The common method for reducing state on both internal and external
	routing tables is through aggregation of information.  Borrowing
	from experience gained in operating IPv4 networks, in order for
	CIDR to succeed in reducing the global routing system growth rate,
	the IPv6 address assignment process needs to make aggregation of
	routing information along topological lines.  In general, the
	topology of the network has not changed since IPv4 CIDR and even
	with IPv6 the topology of the network is still determined by the
	service providers who have built it. . Topologically significant
	address assignments are necessarily service-provider oriented.
      </t>
      <t>
	Start of Excerpt from <xref target='RFC4632'/>
	<list style='empty'>
	  <t>
	    The assignment of prefixes is intended to roughly follow the
	    underlying Internet topology so that aggregation can be used to
	    facilitate scaling of the global routing system.  One implication
	    of this strategy is that prefix assignment and aggregation is
	    generally done according to provider-subscriber relationships,
	    since that is how the Internet topology is determined.
	  </t>
	  <t>
	    Aggregation is simple for an end site that is connected to one
	    service provider: it uses address space assigned by its service
	    provider, and that address space is a small piece of a larger
	    block allocated to the service provider.  No explicit route is
	    needed for the end site; the service provider advertises a single
	    aggregate route for the larger block.  This advertisement
	    provides reachability and routeability for all the customers
	    numbered in the block.
	  </t>
	  <t>
	    There are two, more complex, situations that reduce the effectiveness
	    of aggregation:
	    <list style='symbols'>
	      <t>
		An organization that is multi-homed.  Because a multi-homed
		organization must be advertised into the system by each of
		its service providers, it is often not feasible to aggregate
		its routing information into the address space of any one of
		those providers.  Note that the organization still may
		receive its address assignment out of a service provider's
		address space (which has other advantages), but that a route
		to the organization's prefix is, in the most general case,
		explicitly advertised by all of its service providers.  For
		this reason, the global routing cost for a multi-homed
		organization is generally the same as it was prior to the
		adoption of CIDR.  A more detailed consideration of
		multi-homing practices can be found in
		<xref target='RFC4116'/>.
	      </t>
	      <t>
		An organization that changes service provider but does not
		renumber.  This has the effect of "punching a hole" in one of
		the original service provider's aggregated route
		advertisements.  CIDR handles this situation by requiring
		that the newer service provider to advertise a specific
		advertisement for the re-homed organization; this
		advertisement is preferred over provider aggregates because
		it is a longer match.  To maintain efficiency of aggregation,
		it is recommended that an organization that changes service
		providers plan eventually to migrate its network into a an
		prefix assigned from its new provider's address space.  To
		this end, it is recommended that mechanisms to facilitate
		such migration, such as dynamic host address assignment that
		uses <xref target='RFC2131'/>), be deployed wherever
		possible, and that additional protocol work be done to
		develop improved technology for renumbering.
	      </t>
	    </list>
	  </t>
	</list>
	End of Excerpt from <xref target='RFC4632'/>
      </t>
      <t>
	It is important to recognize that some efficiency can still be
	gained with multi-homed sites (and in general, for any site
	composed of multiple, logical IPv6 networks).
      </t>
      <t>
	Start of Excerpt from <xref target='RFC4632'/>
	<list style='empty'>
	  <t>
	    By allocating a contiguous power-of-two block address space to
	    the site (as opposed to multiple, independent prefixes), the
	    site's routing information may be aggregated into a single
	    prefix.  Also, since the routing cost associated with assigning
	    a multi-homed site out of a service provider's address space is
	    no greater than the old method of sequential number assignment
	    by a central authority, it makes sense to assign all end-site
	    address space out of blocks allocated to service providers.
	  </t>
	  <t>
	    It is also worthwhile to mention that since aggregation may
	    occur at multiple levels in the system, it may still be
	    possible to aggregate these anomalous routes at higher levels
	    of whatever hierarchy may be present.  For example, if a site
	    is multi-homed to two relatively small providers that both
	    obtain connectivity and address space from the same large
	    provider, then aggregation by the large provider of routes from
	    the smaller networks will include all routes to the multi-homed
	    site.  The feasibility of this sort of second-level aggregation
	    depends on whether topological hierarchy exists among a site,
	    its directly-connected providers, and other providers to which
	    they are connected; it may be practical in some regions of the
	    global Internet but not in others.
	  </t>
	</list>
	End of Excerpt from <xref target='RFC4632'/>
      </t>
    </section>

    <section title='Allocation plan'>
      <t>
	Allocations of /32 or shorter prefixes are best provided to network
	service providers from their regional registries.  RIR initial and
	subsequent allocation policy to service providers should allow for
	a minimum of 2 years worth of usage based on historical or business
	plan projections.  Organizations should be assigned appropriate
	subnets from their network service providers larger aggregate
	allocations that are in turn appropriately sized, such as /48 for
	organizations wishing to multi-home.
      </t>
      <t>
	Start of Excerpt from <xref target='RFC4632'/>
	<list style='empty'>
	  <t>
	    Hierarchical delegation of addresses in this manner implies
	    that sites with addresses assigned out of a given service
	    provider are, for routing purposes, part of that service
	    provider and will be routed via its infrastructure.  This
	    implies that routing information about multi-homed
	    organizations (i.e., organizations connected to more than one
	    network service provider) will still need to be known by higher
	    levels in the hierarchy.
	  </t>
	  <t>
	    A historical perspective on these issues is described in
	    <xref target='RFC1518'/>. Additional discussion may also be
	    found in <xref target='RFC3221'/>.
	  </t>
	</list>
	End of Excerpt from <xref target='RFC4632'/>
      </t>
      <t>
	Similarly to the days of classful routing, IPv6 is following the
	same historical path of giving PI assignments. It is in the
	interests of the network infrastructure to document a best practice
	for obtaining IPv6 addresses, and it is recommended that most, if
	not all, network numbers be distributed through service
	providers. Using the process proposed in this document will support
	this from becoming a growing problem and will also reduce the
	scalability concerns core engineers face and the workload for
	Regional Registries.
      </t>
    </section>
    <section title='Current Statistics and Projections'>
      <t>
	The good news is that IPv6 has started growing at a significant
	rate.  The bad news is that IPv6 has started growing at a
	significant rate.  Table 1 shows the observed growth for 2009.
      </t>
      <texttable>
	<ttcol></ttcol>
	<ttcol align='right'>Jan '09</ttcol>
	<ttcol align='right'>Dec '09</ttcol>
	<ttcol align='right'>Growth</ttcol>
	<c>Prefix count</c>
	<c>1,600</c>
	<c>2,460</c>
	<c>54%</c>
	<c>Roots</c>
	<c>1,310</c>
	<c>1,970</c>
	<c>50%</c>
	<c>More Specifics</c>
	<c>290</c>
	<c>490</c>
	<c>69%</c>
	<c>AS Count</c>
	<c>1,220</c>
	<c>1,830</c>
	<c>50%</c>
	<c>Transit</c>
	<c>300</c>
	<c>390</c>
	<c>30%</c>
	<c>Stub</c>
	<c>920</c>
	<c>1,440</c>
	<c>56%</c>
	<postamble>
	  Table 1: IPv6 Routing Table Statistics for
	  2009 <xref target='Huston'/>.
	</postamble>
      </texttable>
      <t>
	There are several salient points that should be extracted
	from this table.  The first, and foremost, is that the
	routing table is now growing rapidly.  At 54% growth, this is
	faster than Moore's law would accommodate.  The roots are
	prefixes that have no 'less specifics' in the routing
	table. Even at 50% growth per year, this number exceeds
	Moore's law.  More specifics are typically injected to
	support traffic engineering or multi-homing.   
      </t>
      <t>
	The AS count growth shows the number of new organizations
	participating in BGP.  Transit ASes are routing domains that
	have multiple peer ASes.  Stub ASes are routing domains that
	have only a single peer AS.
      </t>
      <section title='Analysis'>
	<t>
	  These numbers show that 610 new organizations have joined IPv6
	  routing.  Of these new organizations, 85% are stub ASes.  The new
	  organizations are injecting 860 new prefixes.  Of these, 76% are
	  root prefixes.  Since any new AS must inject at least one prefix
	  into routing to be counted, there would appear to be a very high
	  correlation between new stub ASes and new root prefixes.  From
	  this, it seems reasonable to conclude that the bulk of the new
	  root prefixes are injected by stub ASes.  Further, since it seems
	  unlikely that most of these stub ASes will turn into transit ASes
	  in the future, it also seems reasonable to conclude that these
	  organizations are actually end-user organizations who are
	  injecting routes based on their PI address assignments.
	</t>
	<t>
	  Thus, the bulk of the routing table growth appears to be due to
	  PI prefix injection.
	</t>
      </section>

      <section title='Projections'>
	<t>
	  Given the high state of flux in the deployment of IPv6, it seems
	  difficult to conclude that the statistics from 2009 will be
	  representative of future routing table growth.  Thanks to the
	  influx of new users who are being forced onto IPv6 by the
	  impending IPv4 runout, there are plausible arguments that would
	  suggest that growth could accelerate.  There are also plausible
	  arguments that suggest that as IPv6 deployment reaches ubiquity,
	  that the growth might curtail in a logistic S-curve.  Lacking
	  more data, it is difficult to clearly argue that either of these
	  results is inevitable.
	</t>
	<t>
	  It is possible, however, to look at the implications of the
	  current growth rate, if it is sustained at the 2009 rate of 54%.
	  Table 2 shows this growth rate: 
	  <texttable>
	    <ttcol>Year</ttcol>
	    <ttcol align='right'>Size</ttcol>
	    <c>2009</c>
	    <c>2,460</c>
	    <c>2010</c>
	    <c>3,788</c>
	    <c>2011</c>
	    <c>5,834</c>
	    <c>2012</c>
	    <c>8,985</c>
	    <c>2013</c>
	    <c>13,836</c>
	    <c>2014</c>
	    <c>21,308</c>
	    <c>2015</c>
	    <c>32,814</c>
	    <c>2020</c>
	    <c>284,225</c>
	    <c>2025</c>
	    <c>2,461,879</c>
	    <c>2040</c>
	    <c>1,599,843,323</c>
	    <postamble>
	      Table 2: 54% growth rate, extrapolated
	    </postamble>
	  </texttable>
	</t>
      </section>

      <section title='Impact of CIDR'>
	<t>
	  With the adoption of the plan outlined here, growth of the
	  routing table in a default-free router is greatly reduced since
	  most new address assignments will come from one of the large
	  blocks allocated to the service providers.  This plan recognizes
	  the continued need for multi-homing and the requirement to offer
	  multi-homing via IPv6.  Due to this requirement multi-homing will
	  be the main reason for the continued growth of the routing table
	  size but not because of independent subnet statements based
	  solely on the desire for independence.
	</t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section title='Protocol'>
      <t>
	This document requires that all parties implement routing protocols
	for IPv6 as previously published for IPv4 in <xref target='RFC4632'/>.
      </t>
    </section>
    <section title='Rules for Route Advertisements'>
      <t>
	This document requires that all parties follow the rules for route
	advertisements for IPv6 as previously published for IPv4 in
	<xref target='RFC4632'/>.
      </t>
    </section>
    <section title='Responsibility of configuration and aggregation'>
      <t>
	This document requires that all parties take responsibility of
	configuration or aggregation for IPv6 as previously published for
	IPv4 in <xref target='RFC4632'/>.
      </t>
    </section>
    <section title='Procedural Changes'>
      <t>
	It is possible that some organizations will need to alter their
	filters to follow the guidance of this document.  This is minimal and
	should not be considered an issue.
      </t>
    </section>
    <section title='Recommendations'>
      <t>
	Internet Registries should begin to hand out IPv6 blocks of /32 or
	shorter to network service providers in order to accommodate both
	their growth and their customers' growth. In addition Internet
	Registries should severely limit or eliminate the amount of PI
	assignments in order to help facilitate the decrease in routing
	table growth.  Service providers will allocate /48's to their
	customer organizations with multi-home requirements.
	Implementation and deployment of these modifications should occur
	immediately.
      </t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>
	The authors would like to extend their thanks to the authors of
	<xref target='RFC4632'/> (and by extension, to the authors of
	<xref target='RFC1519'/>).  Much of that work has been incorporated
	directly into this document as it is conceptually identical and
	simply translated to IPv6 herein.
      </t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      &RFC1887;
      &RFC4632;
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      &RFC1518;
      &RFC1519;
      &RFC2131;
      &RFC3221;
      &RFC4116;
      &I-D.narten-radir-problem-statement;

      <reference anchor='Huston'
		 target='http://www.potaroo.net/presentations/2010-03-04-bgp2009.pdf'> 
	<front>
	  <title>
	    BGP in 2009
	  </title>
	  <author initials='G.' surname='Huston' fullname='Geoff Huston'>
	    <organization>
	      Asia Pacific Network Information Centre
	    </organization>
	  </author>
	</front>
      </reference>

    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
