<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!-- comment -->
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd"[]>
<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="no" ?>
<rfc ipr="trust200811" category="std" docName="draft-holmberg-sipcore-proxy-feature-03.txt" obsoletes="" updates="" submissionType="IETF" xml:lang="en">
	<front>
		<title abbrev="proxy feature">
			Indication of features supported by proxy
		</title>
		<author initials="C.H." surname="Holmberg" fullname="Christer Holmberg">
			<organization>Ericsson</organization>
			<address>
				<postal>
					<street>Hirsalantie 11</street>
					<code>02420</code>
					<city>Jorvas</city>
					<country>Finland</country>
				</postal>
				<email>christer.holmberg@ericsson.com</email>
			</address>
		</author>
		<author initials="I.S." surname="Sedlacek" fullname="Ivo Sedlacek">
			<organization>Ericsson</organization>
			<address>
				<postal>
					<street>Scheelevägen 19C</street>
					<code>22363</code>
					<city>Lund</city>
					<country>Sweden</country>
				</postal>
				<email>ivo.sedlacek@ericsson.com</email>
			</address>
		</author>

		<date year="2011" />
		<area>Transport</area>
		<workgroup>SIPCORE Working Group</workgroup>
		<keyword>SIP</keyword>
		<keyword>proxy</keyword>
		<keyword>feature</keyword>
		<keyword>feature-tag</keyword>
		<keyword>capabiltiy</keyword>		
		<abstract>
			<t>
				The Session Initiation Protocol (SIP) "Caller Preferences" extension, defined in RFC 3840, provides 
				a mechanism that allows a SIP message to convey information relating to the originator's features 
				and capabilities. This document defines a new SIP header field, Feature-Caps, that can be used by 
				entities to indicate support of features and capabilities, in case they cannot use the Contact
				header field for that purpose.
			</t>
		</abstract>
	</front>
	<middle>
		<section title="Introduction" toc="default">
			<t>
				The Session Initiation Protocol (SIP) "Caller Preferences" extension, defined in RFC 3840 
				<xref target="RFC3840" pageno="false" format="default"/>, provides a mechanism that allows a 
				SIP message to convey information relating to the originator's features and capabilities.
			</t>
			<t>
				This document defines a new SIP header field, Feature-Caps, that can be used by entities
				to indicate support of features and capabilities, in case they cannot use the Contact
				header field for that purpose.
			</t>							
		</section>
		
		<section title="Conventions" toc="default">
			<t>
				The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", 
				"RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in 
				BCP 14, RFC 2119 <xref target="RFC2119" pageno="false" format="default" />.
			</t>
		</section>

		<section title="Definitions" toc="default">
			<t>
				Proxy: Within this specification, a "proxy" refers to an entity that does not indicate
				supported features using the Contact header field. Normally, however, entities
				that indicate support of features do not act as pure proxies, as defined by RFC 3261, 
				but rather contain different levels of B2BUAs functionality.
			</t>
			<t>
				Downstream SIP entity: SIP entity in the direction towards which a SIP request is sent.
			</t>
			<t>
				Upstream SIP entity: SIP entity in the direction from which a SIP request is received.
			</t>
		</section>
		
		<section title="User Agent (UA) Behavior" anchor="sec-ua" toc="default">
			<section title="General" anchor="sec-ua-gen" toc="default">			
				<t>
					A UA MUST NOT, except when it acts as a SIP registrar, insert a Feature-Caps header 
					field in a SIP request or response.
				</t>
				<t>
					NOTE: Feature-caps header field values of a request are not copied to the 
					associated responses.
				</t>
				<t>
					When a UA receives a SIP request, or response, that contains one or more Feature-Caps 
					header fields, the feature tags in the header field inform the UA is about the 
					features supported by the proxies that inserted the header fields. Procedures how 
					features are invoked are outside the scope of this specification, and MUST be described 
					by individual feature tag specifications.
				</t>
				<t>
					When the UA receives the SIP request or the response, the feature
					tags in the topmost Feature-Caps header field will represent the
					supported features "closest" to the UA.
				</t>
			</section>
			<section title="Registrar Behavior" anchor="sec-ua-reg" toc="default">			
				<t>
					If a SIP registrar wants to indicate support of features towards its upstream SIP entities,
					it can insert a Feature-Caps header field, together with feature tags associated with the
					supported features, in a REGISTER response.
				</t>
			</section>
		</section>
		
		<section title="Proxy behavior" anchor="sec-proxy" toc="default">			
			<t>
				When a proxy receives a SIP request, if the proxy wants to indicate support of features
				towards its downstream SIP entities, it adds a Feature-Caps header field to the request, 
				together with one or more feature tags associated with the supported features, before it 
				forwards the request.
			</t>
			<t>
				When a proxy adds a Feature-Caps header field to a SIP request, it MUST place the header 
				field before any existing Feature-Caps header field in the request.
			</t>
			<t>
				When a proxy receives a SIP response, if the proxy wants to indicate support of features
				towards its upstream SIP entities, it adds a Feature-Caps header field to the response, 
				together with one or more feature tags associated with the supported features, before it 
				forwards the response.
			</t>
			<t>
				When a proxy adds a Feature-Caps header field to a SIP response, it MUST place the header 
				field before any existing Feature-Caps header field in the response. 
			</t>
			<t>
				Each value of a Feature-Caps header field MUST contain a "*" value, followed
				by one or more feature tags, associated with the supported features, separated by 
				semicolon (";").
			</t>
			<t>
				A "*" value means that no information regarding which proxy, or domain, that support
				the features associated with the feature tags, is provided.
			</t>
			<t>
				NOTE: When used in a Contact header field, a "*" value has an "any URI" meaning. When used
				in a Feature-Caps header field, it simply means that no URI information is provided.
			</t>
		</section>

		<section title="Feature-Caps Header Field Definition" anchor="sec-fc" toc="default">
			<section title="General" anchor="sec-fc-sip-gen" toc="default">
				<t>
					This section describes how the Feature-Caps header field is
					used, and the associated semantics, with different SIP methods and
					response codes.
				</t>
				<t>
					NOTE: Future specification can define usage semantics of
					the Feature-Caps header fields for SIP methods, response codes and
					request types not specified in this specification.
				</t>
			</section>
			<section title="SIP Dialog" anchor="sec-fc-sip-dia" toc="default">				
				<t>
					The Feature-Caps header field can be used within an initial SIP request for a dialog, 
					and within any provisional or successful final response (18x and 2xx) associated 
					with such request.
				</t>
				<t>
					If a feature tag is inserted in a Feature-Caps header field of an initial SIP request or
					response for a dialog, the feature associated with the feature tag MUST be supported for
					the dialog, until the dialog is terminated.				
				</t>
			</section>
			<section title="SIP Registration (REGISTER)" anchor="sec-fc-sip-reg" toc="default">				
				<t>
					The Feature-Caps header field can be used within a SIP REGISTER request, and within 
					the 200 (OK) response of such request.
				</t>
				<t>
					If a feature tag is inserted in a Feature-Caps header field of a SIP REGISTER request or
					response, the feature associated with the feature tag MUST be supported for
					the registration, and all SIP transactions associated with the registration, until the 
					registration is re-freshed or terminated.
				</t>
			</section>
			<section title="SIP Stand-Alone Transactions" anchor="sec-fc-sip-sa" toc="default">
				<t>
					The Feature-Caps header field can be used within an request for standalone SIP transaction, 
					and within any provisional or successful final response (18x and 2xx) associated 
					with such request.
				</t>
				<t>
					If a feature tag is inserted in a Feature-Caps header field of an
					request or response for a standalone transaction, the feature associated
					with the feature tag MUST be supported for the standalone transaction.
				</t>
			</section>
			<section title="SIP Capability Query (OPTIONS)" anchor="sec-fc-sip-opt" toc="default">TBD</section>			
		</section>
		
		<section title="Syntax" toc="default">
			<section title="General" toc="default">TBD</section>
			<section title="ABNF" toc="default">
				<t>
					The ABNF for the Feature-Caps header fields is:
				</t>
				<figure title="ABNF" anchor="fig-abnf" suppress-title="false" align="left" alt="" width="" height="">
          			<artwork xml:space="preserve" name="" type="" align="left" alt="" width="" height=""><![CDATA[ 
					
        Feature-Caps = ("Feature-Caps" / "fc") HCOLON fc-value
                       *(COMMA fc-value)   
        fc-value     = "*" *(SEMI feature-param)
                       ;;feature-param from RFC 3840
                       
					]]></artwork>
      			</figure>
			</section>
		</section>


		<section title="Feature Tag Usage With Feature-Caps" anchor="sec-fc-use" toc="default">
			<t>
				Feature tags inserted in a Feature-Caps header field indicate that the SIP entity
				that inserted the header field support of the associated 
				features.
			</t>
			<t>	
				In order to use a feature tag in a Feature-Caps header field, 
				the feature tag specification MUST specify the semantics of the feature 
				tag when inserted in that specific header field. Unless the feature 
				specification defines such semantics, a the feature tag MUST NOT be used 
				in a Feature-Caps header field.
			</t>
			<t>
				Within a given Feature-Caps header field, features are listed in a non-priority 
				order, and for a given header field the the order of listed features have the 
				same meaning. For example, "foo;bar" and "bar;foo" have the same meaning 
				(i.e. that the entity that inserted the feature tags support the features 
				associated with the "foo" and "bar" feature tags.
			</t>						
		</section>	
	    
		<section title="IANA Considerations" toc="default">
			<t>
				This specification registers a new SIP header field, Feature-Caps, according 
				to the process of RFC 3261 <xref target="RFC3261" pageno="false" format="default"/>.
			</t>
			<t>
				The following is the registration for the Feature-Caps header field:
			</t>
			<t>
				RFC Number: RFC XXX
			</t>
			<t>
				Header Field Name: Feature-Caps
			</t>
			<t>
				Compact Form: fc
			</t>
    	</section>

    	<section title="Security Considerations" anchor="sec-security" toc="default">
			<t>				
				Feature tags can provide sensitive information about a SIP entity.
				RFC 3840 cautions against providing sensitive information to
				another party. Once this information is given out, any use may be 
				made of it.
			</t>
		</section>
		
		<section title="Acknowledgements" anchor="sec-acks" toc="default">
			<t>
				Thanks to Paul Kyzivat and Dale Worley for their comments and 
				guidance on the mailing list.
			</t>
			<t>
				The usage of a new header field, and the header field
				name, were suggested by Hadriel Kaplan.
			</t>
		</section>
		
		<section title="Change Log">
			<t>[RFC EDITOR NOTE: Please remove this section when publishing]</t>
			<t>
				Changes from draft-holmberg-sipcore-proxy-feature-02
				<list style="symbols">
					<t>
						Definition, and usage of, a new header field, instead of
						Path, Record-Route, Route and Service-Route.
					</t>					
				</list>
			</t>	
			<t>
				Changes from draft-holmberg-sipcore-proxy-feature-01
				<list style="symbols">
					<t>Requirement section added</t>					
					<t>Use-cases and examples updated based on work in 3GPP</t>					
				</list>
			</t>	
			<t>
				Changes from draft-holmberg-sipcore-proxy-feature-00
				<list style="symbols">
					<t>Additional use-cases added</t>
					<t>Direction section added</t>
				</list>
			</t>		
		</section>		
	</middle>
	
	<back>
		<references title="Normative References">
			<?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119"?>
			<?rfc include="reference.RFC.3261"?>			
			<?rfc include="reference.RFC.3840"?>
		</references>
		<references title="Informative References">	  			
			<?rfc include="reference.3GPP.23.237"?>
			<?rfc include="reference.3GPP.24.837"?>
		</references>
	</back>
</rfc>