<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!-- comment -->
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd"[]>
<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="no" ?>
<rfc ipr="trust200811" category="std" docName="draft-holmberg-sipcore-rkeep-00.txt" obsoletes="" updates="" submissionType="IETF" xml:lang="en">
	<front>
		<title abbrev="reverse keep-alive">
			Indication of support for reverse keep-alive
		</title>
		<author initials="C.H." surname="Holmberg" fullname="Christer Holmberg">
			<organization>Ericsson</organization>
			<address>
				<postal>
					<street>Hirsalantie 11</street>
					<code>02420</code>
					<city>Jorvas</city>
					<country>Finland</country>
				</postal>
				<email>christer.holmberg@ericsson.com</email>
			</address>
		</author>
		<author initials="O.G" surname="Gallego" fullname="Oscar Gallego">
			<organization>Vodafone</organization>
            <address>
				<postal>
					<street>One Kingdom Street, Paddington Central</street>
                    <code>W2 6BY</code>
                    <city>London</city>
                    <country>UK</country>
                    </postal>
                    <email>oscar.gallego@vodafone.com</email>
            </address>
		</author>
		<date year="2012" />
		<area>Transport</area>
		<workgroup>SIPCORE Working Group</workgroup>
		<keyword>SIP</keyword>
		<keyword>keepalive</keyword>
		<keyword>keep-alive</keyword>
		<keyword>STUN</keyword>
		<keyword>outbound</keyword>
		<keyword>NAT traversal</keyword>
		<abstract>
			<t>
				This specification defines a new Session Initiation Protocol (SIP) Via header field 
				parameter, "rkeep". The "rkeep" parameter allows a SIP entity to indicate willingness 
				to receive keep-alives from its adjacent downstream SIP entity, the adjacent downstream
				SIP entity to indicate willingness to send keep-alives, and for SIP entities willing 
				to send keep-alives to inform the receiver about the keep-alive frequency.
			</t>
		</abstract>
	</front>
	<middle>
		<section title="Introduction" toc="default">			
			<t>
				RFC 6263 <xref target="RFC6263" pageno="false" format="default" /> defines a mechanism, which 
				allows adjacent SIP entities to explicitly negotiate usage of the NAT keep-alive mechanisms 
				defined in SIP Outbound <xref target="RFC5626" pageno="false" format="default" />. The "keep" 
				parameter <xref target="RFC6263" pageno="false" format="default" /> allows SIP entities, when
				sending a request, to indicate willingness to send keep-alives, and it allows SIP entities, when 
				sending a response, indicate willingness to receive keep-alives.
			</t>
			<t>
				In some cases a SIP device, located behind a NAT, is not able to send keep-alives. 
				One reason can be that the scheduling policy of the operating system used by the SIP 
				device does not meet the requirement for sending keep-alives using a proper frequency, 
				meaning that NAT bindings might not be kept. In such cases, the device needs to request 
				another device to send keep-alives towards the itself. Then, the keep-alive response message
				sent from the SIP device will ensure that the NAT binding is kept open.
			</t>
			<t>
				This specification defines a new Session Initiation Protocol (SIP) Via header field 
				parameter <xref target="RFC3261" pageno="false" format="default" />, "rkeep". The 
				"rkeep" parameter allows a SIP entity to indicate willingness to receive keep-alives 
				from its adjacent downstream SIP entity, the adjacent downstream SIP entity to indicate 
				willingness to send keep-alives, and for SIP entities willing to send keep-alives to 
				inform the receiver about the keep-alive frequency.
			</t>
			<t>			
				The following sections describe use-cases where a mechanism to explicitly negotiate usage of 
				keep-alives is needed.
			</t>
			<section title="Use-case: UA not able to send keep-alives due to sleep mode" toc="default">
				<t>
				</t>
			</section>
		</section>

		<section title="Applicability" toc="default">
			<t>
				The mechanism defined in this specification MUST only be used by SIP entities that
				are not able, e.g. because the scheduling policy of the operating system used by
				the SIP device does not meet the requirement for sending keep-alives using a proper
				frequency.
			</t>
		</section>
		
		<section title="Conventions" toc="default">
			<t>
				The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", 
				"RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in 
				BCP 14, RFC 2119 <xref target="RFC2119" pageno="false" format="default" />.
			</t>
		</section>
		
		<section title="Definitions" toc="default">
			<t>
				Keep-alives: The keep-alive messages defined in RFC 5626.
			</t>
			<t>
				"rkeep" parameter: A SIP Via header field parameter that a SIP entity can 
				insert in the topmost Via header field that it adds to the request, to 
				explicitly indicate willingness to receive keep-alives from its adjacent 
				downstream SIP entity. A SIP entity can add a parameter value to the "rkeep" 
				parameter, or remove an existing parameter value, in a response to explicitly 
				indicate willingness to send keep-alives to its adjacent upstream SIP entity.
			</t>
			<t>
				SIP entity: SIP User Agent (UA), or proxy, as defined in RFC 3261.
			</t>
			<t>
				Adjacent downstream SIP entity: The adjacent SIP entity in the direction 
				towards which a SIP request is sent.
			</t>
			<t>
				Adjacent upstream SIP entity: The adjacent SIP entity in the direction 
				from which a SIP request is received.
			</t>						
		</section>

		<section title="User Agent and Proxy behavior" anchor="sec-sipent" toc="default">
			<section title="General" anchor="sec-sipent-gen" toc="default">
				<t>
					This section describes how SIP UAs and proxies negotiate usage of 
					keep-alives associated with a registration, or a dialog, which types 
					of SIP requests can be used in order to negotiate the usage, and the 
					lifetime of the negotiated keep-alives.
				</t>
				<t>
					SIP entities indicate willingness to receive keep-alives from the 
					adjacent downstream SIP entity using SIP requests. The associated 
					responses are used by SIP entities to indicate willingness to send 
					keep-alives. Both SIP entities can indicate a recommended keep-alive
					frequency.
				</t>
				<t>
					The procedures to negotiate usage of keep-alives are identical for SIP 
					UAs and proxies.
				</t>
				<t> 
					NOTE: Usage of keep-alives is negotiated per direction. If a SIP entity 
					has indicated willingness to receive keep-alives from an adjacent SIP 
					entity, sending of keep-alives towards that adjacent SIP entity needs 
					to be separately negotiated.
				</t>				
			</section>			
			<section title="Lifetime of keep-alives" anchor="sec-scope" toc="default">
				<t>
					The lifetime of negotiated keep-alives depends on whether the 
					keep-alives are associated with a registration or a dialog. 
					The rules defined in RFC 6223 <xref target="RFC6223" pageno="false" 
					format="default" /> also apply when keep-alives are negotiated 
					using the 'rkeep' Via header field parameter.						
				</t>
			</section>

			<section title="Behavior of a SIP entity willing to receive keep-alives" anchor="sec-sipent-recv" toc="default">
				<t>									
					As defined in RFC 5626, a SIP entity that supports receiving of keep-alives must act as a STUN 
					server <xref target="RFC5389" pageno="false" format="default" />. The SIP entity must support those 
					aspects of STUN that are required in order to apply the STUN keep-alive mechanism defined in 
					RFC 5626, and it must support the CRLF keep-alive mechanism defined in RFC 5626.																
				</t>	
				<t>
					When a SIP entity sends or forwards a request, if it wants to negotiate the receiving of keep-alives 
					associated with a registration, or a dialog, it MUST insert a "rkeep" parameter in the topmost 
					Via header field that it adds to the request, to indicate willingness to receive keep-alives.
					The SIP entity MAY add a parameter value to the "rkeep" parameter before sending or forwarding the 
					request. The parameter value, if present and with a value other than zero, represents a recommended
					keep-alive frequency, given in seconds.
				</t>
				<t>
					When the SIP entity receives the associated response, if the "rkeep" parameter in the topmost 
					Via header field of the response contains a "rkeep" parameter value with a non-zero value, 
					or a value which is different from the value sent in the request (counting a "rkeep" parameter without
					a value) it MUST be prepared to start receiving keep-alives from the same 
					destination from where it received the response which was used to negotiate the receiving of keep-alives. 
					If the "rkeep" parameter does not contain a value, the SIP entity MUST assume that keep-alives 
					will be sent using the recommended keep-alive frequency, if any, that the SIP entity added to 
					the associated request.
				</t>
				<t>
					If the associated response contains the same "rkeep" parameter value as the request (counting a 
					"rkeep" parameter without a value), the SIP entity MUST assume that keep-alives will not be sent.
				</t>
				<t>
					Once a SIP entity has negotiated receiving of keep-alives associated with a dialog towards an 
					adjacent SIP entity, it MUST NOT insert a "rkeep" parameter in any subsequent SIP requests, 
					associated with the dialog, towards that adjacent SIP entity. Such "rkeep" parameter MUST be 
					ignored, if received.
				</t>
				<t>
					Since an ACK request does not have an associated response, it can not be used to negotiate 
					usage of keep-alives. Therefore, a SIP entity MUST NOT insert a "rkeep" parameter in the 
					topmost Via header field of an ACK request. Such "rkeep" parameter MUST be ignored, if 
					received.
				</t>
				<t>
					A SIP entity MUST NOT indicates willingness to receive keep-alives associated with a 
					dialog, unless it has also inserted itself in the dialog route set <xref target="RFC3261" 
					pageno="false" format="default" />.				
				</t>				
				<t>
					If an INVITE request is used to indicate willingness to receive keep-alives, as long as at least 
					one response (provisional or final) to the INVITE request contains a "rkeep" parameter with 
					a parameter value which is different from the value in the request (counting a "rkeep" parameter
					without a value) it is seen as an indication that the adjacent downstream SIP entity is 
					willing to send keep-alives associated with the dialog on which the response is received.			
				</t>				
			</section>
			<section title="Behavior of a SIP entity willing to send keep-alives" anchor="sec-sipent-send-reg" toc="default">
				<t>									
					As defined in RFC 5626, a SIP entity that supports sending of keep-alives must act as a Session 
					Traversal Utilities for NAT (STUN) client <xref target="RFC5389" pageno="false" format="default" />. 
					The SIP entity must support those aspects of STUN that are required in order to apply the 
					STUN keep-alive mechanism defined in RFC 5626, and it must support the CRLF keep-alive 
					mechanism defined in RFC 5626. RFC 5626 defines when to use STUN, respectively double-CRLF, 
					for keep-alives.
				</t>
				<t>
					When a SIP entity sends or forwards a response, and the adjacent upstream SIP entity 
					indicated willingness to receive keep-alives without a recommended keep-alive frequency, 
					if the SIP entity is willing to send keep-alives associated with the registration, or 
					the dialog, to the adjacent upstream SIP entity it MUST add a parameter value to the 
					"rkeep" parameter, before sending or forwarding the response. The parameter value, represents 
					the keep-alive frequency, given in seconds, that the sender of the keep-alives will use.
				</t>
				<t>
					If the adjacent upstream SIP entity provided a recommended keep-alive frequency, and if
					the SIP entity is willing to send keep-alives using that frequency, it MUST remove the
					"rkeep" parameter value which indicates the recommended keep-alive frequency, before
					sending or forwarding the response.
				</t>
				<t>
					NOTE: The reason for removing the "rkeep" parameter value is to indicate that the SIP
					entity supports the mechanism, and simply does not forward an unknown parameter.
				</t>
				<t>
					If the adjacent upstream SIP entity provided a recommended keep-alive frequency, and if
					the SIP entity is willing to send keep-alives using a different frequency, it MUST modify 
					the "rkeep" parameter value which indicates the recommended keep-alive frequency, before
					sending or forwarding the response.
				</t>
				<t>
					There might be multiple responses to an INVITE request. When a SIP entity indicates willingness 
					to send keep-alives in a response to an INVITE request, it MUST add a parameter value to the 
					"rkeep" parameter in at least one reliable response to the request. The SIP entity MAY add 
					identical parameter values to the "rkeep" parameters in other responses to the same request.
					The SIP entity MUST NOT add different parameter value to the "rkeep" parameters in responses to 
					the same request. The SIP entity SHOULD indicate the willingness to send keep-alives as soon 
					as possible.
				</t>
				<t>
					A SIP entity MUST NOT indicates willingness to send keep-alives associated with a dialog, 
					unless it has also inserted itself in the dialog route set <xref target="RFC3261" pageno="false" 
					format="default" />.				
				</t>
				<t>
					When the SIP entity has indicated willingness to send keep-alives, it MUST start sending 
					keep-alives towards the same destination where it sent the response used to indicate 
					willingness to send keep-alives.
				</t>
			</section>	
		</section>
						
		<section title="Keep-alive frequency" anchor="sec-keepalive-freq" toc="default">
			<t>		
				If a SIP entity sends a SIP response, where the topmost Via header 
				field contains a "rkeep" parameter with a non-zero value that indicates 
				the keep-alive frequency, given in seconds, it MUST use the 
				procedures defined for the Flow-Timer header field <xref target="RFC5626" 
				pageno="false" format="default" />. According to the procedures, the SIP 
				entity must send keep-alives at least as often as the indicated keep-alive 
				frequency, and if the SIP entity uses the indicated keep-alive frequency then 
				it should send its keep-alives so that the interval between each keep-alive 
				is randomly distributed between 80% and 100% of the indicated keep-alive 
				frequency.
			</t>
			<t>
				This specification does not define any semantic for a "rkeep" Via header parameter
				value with a zero value. A SIP entity MUST NOT insert a zero value to a "rkeep" 
				parameter. A SIP entity that receives a "rkeep" parameter with a zero value SHOULD
				NOT assume that the sender of the response will send keep-alives towards the SIP
				entity.
			</t>
			<t>
				This specification does not specify actions to take if negotiated keep-alives 
				are not received. As defined in RFC 5626, the receiving SIP entity may 
				consider a connection to be dead in such situations.					
			</t>
			<t>		
				NOTE: The Flow-Timer header field <xref target="RFC5626" pageno="false" 
				format="default" /> has no impact on keep-alives negotiated using the 
				"rkeep" Via header field parameter.
			</t>
		</section>				
										
    	<section title="Examples" toc="default">
			<t>
			</t>
		</section>

		<section title="Grammar" anchor="sec-grammar" toc="default">
			<section title="General" anchor="sec-grammal-gen" toc="default">
				<t>
					This section describes the syntax extensions to the ABNF syntax defined in 
					RFC 3261, by defining a new Via header field parameter, "rkeep". The ABNF 
					defined in this specification is conformant to RFC 5234 <xref target="RFC5234" 
					pageno="false" format="default"/>.
				</t>
			</section>
			<section title="ABNF" anchor="sec-grammal-abnf" toc="default">
				<figure>
					<preamble></preamble>
					<artwork><![CDATA[
via-params =/ rkeep

rkeep      = "rkeep" [ EQUAL 1*(DIGIT) ] 

					]]></artwork>
				</figure>
			</section>
		</section>
	    
		<section title="IANA Considerations" toc="default">
			<section title="rkeep" Via header field parameter" anchor="sec-uri-param" toc="default">
				<t>
					This specification defines a new Via header field parameter
					called keep in the "Header Field Parameters and Parameter Values"
					sub-registry as per the registry created by <xref target="RFC3968" 
					pageno="false" format="default"/>. The syntax is defined in 
					<xref target="sec-grammar"/>. The required information is:
				</t>
				<figure>
					<preamble></preamble>
					<artwork><![CDATA[
                                               Predefined
Header Field            Parameter Name         Values      Reference
----------------------  ---------------------  ----------  ---------
Via                     rkeep                  No          [RFCXXXX]

					]]></artwork>
				</figure>
			</section>
    	</section>

    	<section title="Security Considerations" anchor="sec-security" toc="default">
			<t>
				The Security Considerations in RFC 6223 apply.
			</t>
		</section>
		
		<section title="Acknowledgements" anchor="sec-acks" toc="default">
			<t>
			</t>
		</section>
		
		<section title="Change Log">
			<t>[RFC EDITOR NOTE: Please remove this section when publishing]</t>
			<t>
				Changes from draft-holmberg-sipcore-rkeep-xx
				<list style="symbols">
					<t>TBA</t>
				</list>
			</t>
		</section>		
	</middle>
	
	<back>
		<references title="Normative References">
			<?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119"?>
			<?rfc include="reference.RFC.3261"?>
			<?rfc include="reference.RFC.5234"?>
			<?rfc include="reference.RFC.5389"?>		
			<?rfc include="reference.RFC.5626"?>
			<?rfc include="reference.RFC.6223"?>
			<?rfc include="reference.RFC.6263"?>
		</references>
		<references title="Informative References">	  
			<?rfc include="reference.RFC.3968"?>									
		</references>
	</back>
</rfc>