<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<rfc category="info" docName="draft-ietf-cdni-requirements-06"
     ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="CDNI Requirements">Content Distribution Network
    Interconnection (CDNI) Requirements</title>

    <author fullname="Kent Leung" initials="K." role="editor" surname="Leung">
      <organization abbrev="Cisco">Cisco Systems</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>170 West Tasman Drive</street>

          <city>San Jose</city>

          <code>95134</code>

          <region>CA</region>

          <country>U.S.A.</country>
        </postal>

        <phone>+1 408 526 5030</phone>

        <email>kleung@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Yiu Lee" initials="Y." role="editor" surname="Lee">
      <organization abbrev="Comcast">Comcast</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>One Comcast Center</street>

          <city>Philadelphia</city>

          <region>PA</region>

          <code>19103</code>

          <country>U.S.A.</country>
        </postal>

        <email>yiu_lee@cable.comcast.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date day="9" month="April" year="2013"/>

    <abstract>
      <t>Content Delivery Networks (CDNs) are frequently used for large-scale
      content delivery. As a result, existing CDN providers are scaling up
      their infrastructure and many Network Service Providers (NSPs) are
      deploying their own CDNs. There is a requirement for interconnecting
      standalone CDNs so that their collective CDN footprint can be leveraged
      for the end-to-end delivery of content from Content Service Providers
      (CSPs) to end users. The Content Distribution Network Interconnection
      (CDNI) working group has been chartered to develop an interoperable and
      scalable solution for such CDN interconnection.</t>

      <t>The goal of the present document is to outline the requirements for
      the solution and interfaces to be specified by the CDNI working group.
      This draft is a work in progress and requirements may be added,
      modified, or removed by the working group.</t>
    </abstract>

    <note title="Requirements Language">
      <t>The key words "High Priority", "Medium Priority" and "Low Priority"
      in this document are to be interpreted in the following way:</t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>"High Priority" indicates requirements that are to be supported
          by the CDNI interfaces. A requirement is stated as "High Priority"
          when it is established by the working group that it can be met
          without compromising the targeted schedule for WG deliverables, or
          when it is established that specifying a solution without meeting
          this requirement would not make sense and would justify re-adjusting
          the WG schedule, or both. This is tagged as "[HIGH]".</t>

          <t>"Medium Priority" indicates requirements that are to be supported
          by the CDNI interfaces unless the WG realizes at a later stage that
          attempting to meet this requirement would compromise the overall WG
          schedule (for example it would involve complexities that would
          result in significantly delaying the deliverables). This is tagged
          as "[MED]".</t>

          <t>"Low Priority" indicates requirements that are to be supported by
          the CDNI interfaces provided that dedicating WG resources to this
          work does not prevent addressing "High Priority" and "Medium
          Priority" requirements and that attempting to meet this requirement
          would not compromise the overall WG schedule. This is tagged as
          "[LOW]".</t>
        </list></t>

      <t/>
    </note>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>The volume of video and multimedia content delivered over the
      Internet is rapidly increasing and expected to continue doing so in the
      future. In the face of this growth, Content Delivery Networks (CDNs)
      provide numerous benefits: reduced delivery cost for cacheable content,
      improved quality of experience for end users, and increased robustness
      of delivery. For these reasons CDNs are frequently used for large-scale
      content delivery. As a result, existing CDN providers are scaling up
      their infrastructure and many Network Service Providers (NSPs) are
      deploying their own CDNs. It is generally desirable that a given content
      item can be delivered to an End User regardless of that End User's
      location or attachment network. However, the footprint of a given CDN in
      charge of delivering a given content may not expand close enough to the
      End User's current location or attachment network to realize the cost
      benefit and user experience that a more distributed CDN would provide.
      This creates a requirement for interconnecting standalone CDNs so that
      their collective CDN footprint can be leveraged for the end-to-end
      delivery of content from Content Service Providers (CSPs) to End Users.
      The Content Distribution Network Interconnection (CDNI) working group
      has been chartered to develop an interoperable and scalable solution for
      such CDN interconnection.</t>

      <t><xref target="RFC6707"/> outlines the problem area that the CDNI
      working group is chartered to address. <xref target="RFC6770"/>
      discusses the use cases for CDN Interconnection. <xref
      target="I-D.davie-cdni-framework"/> discusses the technology framework
      for the CDNI solution and interfaces.</t>

      <t>The goal of the present document is to document the requirements for
      the CDNI solution and interfaces. In order to meet the timelines defined
      in the working group charter, the present document categorizes the CDNI
      requirements as "High Priority", "Medium Priority", and "Low
      Priority".</t>

      <section anchor="terminology" title="Terminology">
        <t>This document uses the terminology defined in section 1.1 of <xref
        target="I-D.davie-cdni-framework"/>.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="cdni-interfaces" title="CDNI Model and CDNI Interfaces">
      <t>For convenience Figure 1 from <xref
      target="I-D.davie-cdni-framework"/> illustrating the CDNI problem area
      and the CDNI protocols is replicated below.</t>

      <figure anchor="fig-cdni-model" title="CDNI Model and CDNI Interfaces">
        <preamble/>

        <artwork>   -------- 
  /        \
  |   CSP  |
  \        /
   --------
       *
       *
       *                         /\
       *                        /  \
   ----------------------      |CDNI|        ----------------------
  /     Upstream CDN     \     |    |       /    Downstream CDN    \
  |      +-------------+ | Control Interface| +-------------+      |
  |*******   Control   |&lt;======|====|========&gt;|   Control   *******|
  |*     +------*----*-+ |     |    |       | +-*----*------+     *|
  |*            *    *   |     |    |       |   *    *            *|
  |*     +------*------+ | Logging Interface| +------*------+     *|
  |* *****   Logging   |&lt;======|====|========&gt;|   Logging   ***** *|
  |* *   +-*-----------+ |     |    |       | +-----------*-+   * *|
  |* *     *         *   | Request Routing  |   *         *     * *|
.....*...+-*---------*-+ |    Interface     | +-*---------*-+...*.*...
. |* * *** Req-Routing |&lt;======|====|========&gt;| Req-Routing *** * *| .
. |* * * +-------------+.|     |    |       | +-------------+ * * *| .
. |* * *                 .  CDNI Metadata   |                 * * *| .
. |* * * +-------------+ |.   Interface     | +-------------+ * * *| .
. |* * * | Distribution|&lt;==.===|====|========&gt;| Distribution| * * *| .
. |* * * |             | |  .   \  /        | |             | * * *| .
. |* * * |+---------+  | |   .   \/         | |  +---------+| * * *| .
. |* * ***| +---------+| |    ....Request......+---------+ |*** * *| .
. |* *****+-|Surrogate|************************|Surrogate|-+***** *| .
. |*******  +---------+| |   Acquisition    | |+----------+ *******| .
. |      +-------------+ |                  | +-------*-----+      | .
. \                      /                  \         *            / .
.  ----------------------                    ---------*------------  .
.                                                     *              .
.                                                     * Delivery     .
.                                                     *              .
.                                                  +--*---+          .
...............Request.............................| User |..Request..
                                                   | Agent|
                                                   +------+

&lt;==&gt;  interfaces inside the scope of CDNI

****  interfaces outside the scope of CDNI
....  interfaces outside the scope of CDNI
</artwork>

        <postamble/>
      </figure>

      <t/>

      <t/>
    </section>

    <section title="Generic CDNI Requirements">
      <t>This section identifies generic requirements independent of the
      individual CDNI interfaces. Some of those are expected to affect
      multiple or all interfaces.</t>

      <t><list counter="gen-reqs" hangIndent="4" style="format GEN-%d">
          <t>[MED] Wherever possible, the CDNI interfaces should reuse or
          leverage existing IETF protocols.</t>

          <t>[HIGH] The CDNI solution shall not require a change, or an
          upgrade, to the User Agent to benefit from content delivery through
          interconnected CDNs.</t>

          <t>[HIGH] The CDNI solution shall not require a change, or an
          upgrade, to the Content Service Provider to benefit from content
          delivery through interconnected CDNs.</t>

          <t>[HIGH] The CDNI solution shall not depend on intra-CDN
          information to be exposed to other CDNs for effective and efficient
          delivery of the content. Examples of intra-CDN information include
          surrogate topology, surrogate status, cached content, etc.</t>

          <t>[HIGH] The CDNI solution shall support delivery to the user agent
          based on HTTP <xref target="RFC2616"/>. (Note that while delivery
          and acquisition "data plane" protocols are out of the CDNI solution
          scope, the CDNI solution "control plane" protocols are expected to
          participate in enabling, selecting or facilitating operations of
          such acquisition and delivery protocols. Hence it is useful to state
          requirements on the CDNI solution in terms of which acquisition and
          delivery protocols).</t>

          <t>[HIGH] The CDNI solution shall support acquisition across CDNs
          based on HTTP <xref target="RFC2616"/>. (The note above applies to
          this requirement too)</t>

          <t>[LOW] The CDNI solution may support delivery to the user agent
          based on protocols other than HTTP.</t>

          <t>[LOW] The CDNI solution may support acquisition across CDNs based
          on protocols other than HTTP.</t>

          <t>[MED] The CDNI solution should support cascaded CDN redirection
          (CDN1 redirects to CDN2 that redirects to CDN3) to an arbitrary
          number of levels beyond the first level.</t>

          <t>[MED] The CDNI solution should support an arbitrary topology of
          interconnected CDNs (i.e. the CDN topology cannot be restricted to a
          tree, a loop-free topology, etc.).</t>

          <t>[HIGH] The CDNI solution shall prevent looping of any CDNI
          information exchange.</t>

          <t>[HIGH] When making use of third party reference, the CDNI
          solution shall consider the potential issues associated with the use
          of various format of third-party references (e.g. NAT or IPv4/IPv6
          translation potentially breaking third-party references based on an
          IP addresses such as URI containing IPv4 or IPv6 address litterals,
          split DNS situations potentially breaking third-party references
          based on DNS fully qualified domain names) and wherever possible
          avoid, minimize or mitigate the associated risks based on the
          specifics of the environments where the reference is used (e.g.
          likely or unlikely presence of NAT in the path). In particular, this
          applies to situations where the CDNI solution needs to construct and
          convey uniform resource identifiers for directing/redirecting a
          content request, as well as to situations where the CDNI solution
          needs to pass on a third party reference (e.g. to identify a User
          Agent) in order to allow another entity to make a more informed
          decision (e.g. make a more informed request routing decision by
          attempting to derive location information from the third party
          reference).</t>

          <t>[HIGH] The CDNI solution shall support HTTP Adaptive Streaming
          content.</t>
        </list></t>
    </section>

    <section title="CDNI Control Interface Requirements">
      <t>The primary purpose of the CDNI Control interface (CI) is to initiate
      the interconnection across CDNs, bootstrap the other CDNI interfaces and
      trigger actions into the Downstream CDN by the Upstream CDN (such as
      delete object from caches or trigger pre-positioned content
      acquisition). We observe that while the CDNI Control interface is
      currently discussed as a single "protocol", further analysis will
      determine whether the corresponding requirements are to be realized over
      a single interface and protocol, or over multiple interfaces and
      protocols.</t>

      <t><list counter="control-reqs" hangIndent="4" style="format CI-%d">
          <t>[HIGH] The CDNI Control interface shall allow the Upstream CDN to
          request that the Downstream CDN (and, if cascaded CDNs are supported
          by the solution, that the potential cascaded Downstream CDNs) delete
          an object or set of objects and/or its CDNI metadata from the CDN
          surrogates and any storage. Only the object(s) and CDNI metadata
          that pertain to the requesting Upstream CDN are allowed to be
          purged.</t>

          <t>[MED] The CDNI Control interface should allow for multiple
          content items identified by a Content Collection ID to be purged
          using a single Content Purge action.</t>

          <t>[MED] The CDNI Control interface should allow the Upstream CDN to
          request that the Downstream CDN (and, if cascaded CDNs are supported
          by the solution, that the potential cascaded Downstream CDNs) mark
          an object or set of objects and/or its CDNI metadata as
          &ldquo;stale&rdquo; and revalidate them before they are delivered
          again.</t>

          <t>[HIGH] The CDNI Control interface shall allow the Downstream CDN
          to report on the completion of these actions (by itself, and if
          cascaded CDNs are supported by the solution, by potential cascaded
          Downstream CDNs), in a manner appropriate for the action (e.g.
          synchronously or asynchronously). The confirmation receipt should
          include a success or failure indication. The failure indication is
          used if the Downstream CDN cannot delete the content in its
          storage.</t>

          <t>[MED] The CDNI Control interface should support initiation and
          control by the Upstream CDN of pre-positioned CDNI metadata
          acquisition by the Downstream CDN.</t>

          <t>[MED] The CDNI Control interface should support initiation and
          control by the Upstream CDN of pre-positioned content acquisition by
          the Downstream CDN.</t>

          <t>[LOW] The CDNI Control interface may allow a CDN to establish,
          update and terminate a CDN interconnection with another CDN whereby
          one CDN can act as a Downstream CDN for the other CDN (that acts as
          an Upstream CDN).</t>

          <t>[LOW] The CDNI Control interface may allow control of the CDNI
          interconnection between any two CDNs independently for each
          direction (i.e. For the direction where CDN1 is the Upstream CDN and
          CDN2 is the Downstream CDN, and for the direction where CDN2 is the
          Upstream CDN and CDN1 is the Downstream CDN).</t>

          <t>[LOW] The CDNI Control interface may allow bootstrapping of the
          Request-Routing interface. For example, this can potentially
          include:<list style="symbols">
              <t>negotiation of the Request-Routing method (e.g. DNS vs HTTP,
              if more than one method is specified)</t>

              <t>discovery of the Request-Routing protocol endpoints</t>

              <t>information necessary to establish secure communication
              between the Request-Routing protocol endpoints.</t>
            </list></t>

          <t>[LOW] The CDNI Control interface may allow bootstrapping of the
          CDNI Metadata interface. This information could, for example,
          include:<list style="symbols">
              <t>discovery of the CDNI Metadata signaling protocol
              endpoints</t>

              <t>information necessary to establish secure communication
              between the CDNI Metadata signaling protocol endpoints.</t>
            </list></t>

          <t>[LOW] The CDNI Control interface may allow bootstrapping of the
          Content Acquisition interface. This could, for example, include
          exchange and negotiation of the Content Acquisition protocols to be
          used across the CDNs (e.g. HTTP, HTTPS, FTP, ATIS C2).</t>

          <t>[LOW] The CDNI Control interface may allow bootstrapping of the
          CDNI Logging interface. This information could, for example,
          include:<list style="symbols">
              <t>discovery of the Logging protocol endpoints</t>

              <t>information necessary to establish secure communication
              between the Logging protocol endpoints</t>

              <t>negotiation/definition of the log file format and set of
              fields to be exported through the Logging protocol, with some
              granularity (e.g. On a per content type basis).</t>

              <t>negotiation/definition of parameters related to transaction
              Logs export (e.g., export protocol, file compression, export
              frequency, directory).</t>
            </list></t>
        </list></t>
    </section>

    <section title="CDNI Request Routing/Redirection Interface Requirements">
      <t/>

      <t>The main function of the CDNI request routing/ Redirection (RI)
      interface is to allow the Request-Routing systems in interconnected CDNs
      to communicate to facilitate redirection of the request across CDNs.</t>

      <t><list counter="reqrouting-ri" hangIndent="4" style="format RI-%d">
          <t>[HIGH] The CDNI request routing/Redirection interface shall
          support efficient request-routing for small objects. This may, for
          example, call for a mode of operation (e.g. DNS-based request
          routing) where freshness and accuracy of CDN/Surrogate selection can
          be traded-off against reduced request-routing load (e.g. Via
          lighter-weight queries and caching of request-routing
          decisions).</t>

          <t>[HIGH] The CDNI request routing/Redirection interface shall
          support efficient request-routing for large objects. This may, for
          example, call for a mode of operation (e.g. HTTP-based request
          routing) where freshness and accuracy of CDN/Surrogate selection
          justifies a per-request decision and a per-request CDNI
          Request-Routing protocol call.</t>

          <t>[HIGH] The CDNI request routing/Redirection interface shall
          support recursive CDNI request routing.</t>

          <t>[HIGH] The CDNI request routing/Redirection interface shall
          support iterative CDNI request routing.</t>

          <t>[MED] In case of detection of a request redirection loop, the
          CDNI request routing/Redirection interface's loop prevention
          mechanism should allow routing of the request by avoiding the loop
          (as opposed to the request loop being simply interrupted without
          routing the request).</t>

          <t>[MED] The CDNI request routing/Redirection interface should
          support a mechanism allowing enforcment of a limit on the number of
          successive CDN redirections for a given request.</t>

          <t>[LOW] The CDNI request routing/Redirection interface may support
          a mechanism allowing an Upstream CDN to avoid redirecting a request
          to a Downstream CDN if that is likely to result in the total
          redirection time exceeding some limit.</t>

          <t>[HIGH] The CDNI request routing/Redirection interface shall allow
          the Upstream CDN to include, in the query to the Downstream CDN, the
          necessary information to allow the Downstream CDN to process the
          redirection query. This could, for example, include:<list
              style="symbols">
              <t>information from which the location of the user-agent that
              originated the request can be inferred (e.g. User Agent fully
              qualified domain name in case of HTTP-based Request Routing, DNS
              Proxy fully qualified domain name in case of DNS-based Request
              Routing)</t>

              <t>requested resource information (e.g. Resource URI in case of
              HTTP-based Request Routing, Resource hostname in case of
              DNS-based Request Routing)</t>

              <t>additional available request information (e.g. request
              headers in case of HTTP-based Request Routing).</t>
            </list></t>

          <t>[LOW] The CDNI request routing/Redirection interface may also
          allow the Upstream CDN to convey information pointing to CDNI
          metadata applicable (individually or through inheritance) to the
          requested content. For illustration, the CDNI metadata pointed to
          could potentially include metadata that is applicable to any
          content, metadata that is applicable to a content collection (to
          which the requested content belongs) and/or metadata that is
          applicable individually to the requested content.</t>

          <t>[HIGH] The CDNI request routing/Redirection interface shall allow
          the Downstream CDN to include the following information in the
          response to the Upstream CDN:<list style="symbols">
              <t>status code, in particular indicating acceptance or rejection
              of request (e.g. Because the Downstream CDN is unwilling or
              unable to serve the request). In case of rejection, an error
              code is also to be provided, which allows the Upstream CDN to
              react appropriately (e.g. Select another Downstream CDN, or
              serve the request itself)</t>

              <t>redirection information (e.g. Resource URI in case of
              HTTP-based Request Routing, equivalent of a DNS record in case
              of DNS-based Request Routing).</t>
            </list></t>

          <t>[HIGH] The CDNI request routing/Redirection interface shall allow
          for per-chunk request routing of HTTP Adaptive Streaming
          content.</t>

          <t>[LOW] The CDNI request routing/Redirection interface may allow
          the Upstream CDN to use the information conveyed by the Downstream
          CDN during the Recursive Request Routing process to rewrite an HTTP
          Adaptive Streaming manifest file. </t>

          <t>[LOW] The CDNI Request-Routing interface may allow the Upstream
          CDN to re-sign the invariant portion of the chunk URIs embedded in
          the HTTP Adaptive Streaming manifest file. </t>

          <t>[MED] The CDNI request routing/Redirection interface should allow
          the use of HTTP cookie to associate the chunks with the HTTP
          Adaptive Stream manifest file (which is verified by the URI
          signature) based on the Authorization Group ID (which is an
          identifier used to correlate the manifest file to the related
          chunks). </t>

          <t>[MED] The CDNI request routing/Redirection interface should allow
          for an efficient method of transferring request routing information
          for multiple chunks from the Downstream CDN to the Upstream CDN as
          part of the recursive request routing process.</t>
        </list></t>
    </section>

    <section title="CDNI Request Routing/Footprint &amp; Capabilities Advertisement Interface Requirements">
      <t/>

      <t>The main function of the CDNI Request Routing Footprint &amp;
      Capabilities Advertisement Interface (FCI) is to allow the Downstream
      CDN to advertise the information regarding its footprint and
      capabilities to the Upstream CDN.</t>

      <t><list counter="reqrouting-fci" hangIndent="4" style="format FCI-%d">
          <t>[HIGH] The CDNI request routing/Footprint &amp; Capabilities
          advertisement interface shall allow the Downstream CDN to
          communicate to the Upstream CDN coarse information about the
          Downstream CDN ability and/or willingness to handle requests from
          the Upstream CDN. For example, this could potentially include a
          binary signal (&ldquo;Downstream CDN ready/not-ready to take
          additional requests from Upstream CDN&rdquo;) to be used in case of
          excessive load or failure condition in the Downstream CDN.</t>

          <t>[MED] The CDNI request routing/Footprint &amp; Capabilities
          advertisement interface should allow the Downstream CDN to
          communicate to the Upstream CDN aggregate information to facilitate
          CDN selection during request routing, such as Downstream CDN
          capabilities, resources and affinities (i.e. Preferences or cost).
          This information could, for example, include:<list style="symbols">
              <t>supported content types and delivery protocols</t>

              <t>footprint (e.g. layer-3 coverage)</t>

              <t>a set of metrics/attributes (e.g. Streaming bandwidth,
              storage resources, distribution and delivery priority)</t>

              <t>a set of affinities (e.g. Preferences, indication of
              distribution/delivery fees)</t>

              <t>information to facilitate request redirection (e.g.
              Reachability information of Downstream CDN Request Routing
              system).</t>
            </list>[Note: Some of this information - such as supported content
          types and delivery protocols- may also potentially be taken into
          account by the distribution system in the Upstream CDN for
          pre-positioning of content and/or metadata in the Downstream CDN in
          case of pre-positioned content acquisition and/or pre-positioned
          CDNI metadata acquisition.]</t>

          <t>[MED] In the case of cascaded redirection, the CDNI request
          routing/Footprint &amp; Capabilities advertisement interface should
          allow the Downstream CDN to also include in the information
          communicated to the Upstream CDN, information on the capabilities,
          resources and affinities of CDNs to which the Downstream CDN may (in
          turn) redirect requests received by the Upstream CDN. In that case,
          the CDNI Request-Routing interface shall prevent looping of such
          information exchange.</t>

          <t>[LOW] The CDNI request routing/Footprint &amp; Capabilities
          advertisement interface may allow the Downstream CDN to communicate
          to the Upstream CDN aggregate information on CDNI administrative
          limits and policy. This information can be taken into account by the
          Upstream CDN Request Routing system in its CDN Selection decisions.
          This information could, for example, include:<list style="symbols">
              <t>maximum number of requests redirected by the Upstream CDN to
              be served simultaneously by the Downstream CDN</t>

              <t>maximum aggregate volume of content (e.g. in Terabytes) to be
              delivered by the Downstream CDN over a time period.</t>
            </list></t>

          <t>[MED] The CDNI request routing/Footprint &amp; Capabilities
          advertisement interface should support advertisement of the
          following types of capabilities:<list style="symbols">
              <t>delivery protocol (e.g., HTTP vs. RTMP)</t>

              <t>acquisition protocol (for acquiring content from an Upstream
              CDN)</t>

              <t>redirection mode (e.g., DNS Redirection vs. HTTP
              Redirection)</t>

              <t>capabilities related to CDNI Logging (e.g., supported logging
              mechanisms)</t>

              <t>capabilities related to CDNI Metadata (e.g., authorization
              algorithms or support for proprietary vendor metadata)</t>
            </list></t>

          <t>[LOW] The CDNI Control interface may allow exchange and
          negotiation of delivery authorization mechanisms to be supported
          across the CDNs (e.g. URI signature based validation).</t>
        </list></t>
    </section>

    <section title="CDNI Metadata Distribution Interface Requirements">
      <t>The primary function of the CDNI Metadata Distribution interface (MI)
      is to allow the Distribution system in interconnected CDNs to
      communicate to ensure Content Distribution Metadata with inter-CDN scope
      can be exchanged across CDNs. We observe that while the CDNI Metadata
      Distribution protocol is currently discussed as a single "protocol",
      further analysis will determine whether the corresponding requirements
      are to be realized over a single interface and protocol, or over
      multiple interfaces and protocols. For example, a subset of the CDNI
      metadata might be conveyed in-band along with the actual content
      acquisition across CDNs (e.g. content MD5 in HTTP header) while another
      subset might require an out-of-band interface &amp; protocol (e.g.
      geo-blocking information).</t>

      <t><list counter="meta-reqs" hangIndent="4" style="format MI-%d">
          <t>[HIGH] The CDNI Metadata Distribution interface shall allow the
          Upstream CDN to provide the Downstream CDN with content distribution
          metadata of inter-CDN scope.</t>

          <t>[HIGH] The CDNI Metadata Distribution interface shall support
          exchange of CDNI metadata for both the dynamic content acquisition
          model and the pre-positioning content acquisition model.</t>

          <t>[HIGH] The CDNI Metadata Distribution interface shall support a
          mode where no, or a subset of, the Metadata is initially
          communicated to the Downstream CDN along with information about
          how/where to acquire the rest of the CDNI Metadata (i.e. Dynamic
          CDNI metadata acquisition).</t>

          <t>[MED] The CDNI Metadata Distribution interface should support a
          mode where all the relevant Metadata is initially communicated to
          the Downstream CDN (i.e. Pre-positioned CDNI metadata
          acquisition).</t>

          <t>[HIGH] Whether in the pre-positioned content acquisition model or
          in the dynamic content acquisition model, the CDNI Metadata
          Distribution interface shall provide the necessary information to
          allow the Downstream CDN to acquire the content from an upstream
          source (e.g. Acquisition protocol and Uniform Resource Identifier in
          Upstream CDN- or rules to construct this URI).</t>

          <t>[HIGH] The CDNI metadata shall allow signaling of one or more
          upstream sources, where each upstream source can be in the Upstream
          CDN, in another CDN, the CSP origin server or any arbitrary source
          designated by the Upstream CDN. Note that some upstream sources
          (e.g. the content origin server) may or may not be willing to serve
          the content to the Downstream CDN, if this policy is known to the
          Upstream CDN then it may omit those sources when exchanging CDNI
          metadata.</t>

          <t>[HIGH] The CDNI Metadata Distribution interface (possibly in
          conjunction with the CDNI Control interface) shall allow the
          Upstream CDN to request addition and modification of CDNI Metadata
          into the Downstream CDN.</t>

          <t>[HIGH] The CDNI Metadata Distribution interface (possibly in
          conjunction with the CDNI Control interface) shall allow removal of
          obsolete CDNI Metadata from the Downstream CDN (this could, for
          example, be achieved via an explicit removal request from the
          Upstream CDN or via expiration of a Time-To-Live associated to the
          Metadata).</t>

          <t>[HIGH] The CDNI Metadata Distribution interface shall allow
          association of CDNI Metadata at the granularity of individual
          object. This is necessary to achieve fine-grain Metadata
          distribution at the level of an individual object when
          necessary.</t>

          <t>[HIGH] The CDNI Metadata Distribution interface shall allow
          association of CDNI Metadata at the granularity of an object set.
          This is necessary to achieve scalable distribution of metadata when
          a large number of objects share the same distribution policy.</t>

          <t>[HIGH] The CDNI Metadata Distribution interface shall support
          multiple levels of inheritance with precedence to more specific
          metadata. For example, the CDNI Metadata Distribution protocol may
          support metadata that is applicable to any content, metadata that is
          applicable to a content collection and metadata that is applicable
          to an individual content where content level metadata overrides
          content collection metadata that overrides metadata for any
          content.</t>

          <t>[HIGH] The CDNI Metadata Distribution interface shall ensure that
          conflicting metadata with overlapping scope are prevented or
          deterministically handled.</t>

          <t>[HIGH] The CDNI Metadata Distribution interface shall allow
          signaling of content distribution control policies. For example,
          this could potentially include:<list style="symbols">
              <t>geo-blocking information (i.e. Information defining
              geographical areas where the content is to be made available or
              blocked)</t>

              <t>availability windows (i.e. Information defining time windows
              during which the content is to be made available or blocked;
              expiration time may also be included to remove content)</t>

              <t>delegation whitelist/blacklist (i.e. Information defining
              which Downstream CDNs the content may/may not be delivered
              through)</t>
            </list></t>

          <t>[HIGH] The CDNI Metadata interface shall be able to exchange a
          set of metadata elements with specified semantics (e.g. start of
          time window, end of time window).</t>

          <t>[HIGH] The CDNI Metadata interface shall allow exchange of opaque
          metadata element, whose semantic is not defined in CDNI but
          established by private CDN agreement.</t>

          <t>[HIGH] The CDNI Metadata Distribution interface shall allow
          signaling of authorization checks and validation that are to be
          performed by the surrogate before delivery. For example, this could
          potentially include:<list style="symbols">
              <t>need to validate URI signed information (e.g. Expiry time,
              Client IP address).</t>
            </list></t>

          <t>[MED] The CDNI Metadata Distribution interface should allow
          signaling of CDNI-relevant surrogate cache behavior parameters. For
          example, this could potentially include:<list style="symbols">
              <t>control of whether the query string of HTTP URI is to be
              ignored by surrogate cache</t>

              <t>enforcement of caching directives by Downstream CDN that are
              different than the ones signalled in the HTTP headers (e.g.
              "Expires" field)</t>

              <t>rate-pacing by Downstream CDN for content delivery (e.g.
              Progressive Download)</t>
            </list></t>

          <t>[HIGH] The CDNI Metadata interface shall provide indication of
          related content (e.g. HTTP Adaptive Bit Rate chunks) by the Content
          Collection ID (CCID) metadata. This could be used by the Downstream
          CDN for operations on the group of content. For example, this could
          potentially include: <list style="symbols">
              <t>content acquisition for the entire set of files when one
              piece of content is requested</t>

              <t>local file management and storage bundles all the files for
              the content</t>

              <t>purging the entire set of files associated with the
              content</t>

              <t>logging of the delivery of the content for the session when
              at least one file in the set was delivered</t>
            </list></t>

          <t>[MED] The CDNI Metadata Distribution interface should support an
          OPTIONAL mechanism allowing the Upstream CDN to indicate to the
          Downstream CDN which CDNI Log fields are to be provided for all, for
          specific sets of, or for specific content items delivered using
          HTTP. A CDNI implementation that does not support this optional CDNI
          Metadata Distribution Interface mechanism MUST ignore this log
          format indication and generate CDNI logging format for HTTP Adaptive
          Streaming using the default set of CDNI Logging fields. (Note: this
          function is not concluded to be in Metadata Interface or Control
          Interface)</t>

          <t>[MED] The CDNI Metadata Distribution interface should allow the
          Upstream CDN to signal to the Downstream CDN the Content Collection
          ID value for all, for specific sets of, or for specific content
          items delivered using HTTP. Whenever the Downstream CDN is
          instructed by the Upstream CDN to report the Content Collection ID
          field in the log records, the Downstream CDN is to use the value
          provided through the CDNI Metadata interface for the corresponding
          content. Note the Session ID field along with Content Collection ID
          may be used for HTTP Adaptive Streaming content.</t>

          <t>[MED] The CDNI Metadata Distribution interface should allow the
          Upstream CDN to signal to the Downstream CDN the Authorization Group
          ID value for all the related HTTP Adaptive Streamin content (i.e.
          manifest file and chunks). The authorization result of a content
          (e.g. manifest file) is transferred over to related content (e.g.
          chunks). [Ed: need to improve wording?]</t>
        </list></t>
    </section>

    <section title="CDNI Logging Interface Requirements">
      <t>This section identifies the requirements related to the CDNI Logging
      interface (LI). We observe that while the CDNI Logging interface is
      currently discussed as a single "protocol", further analysis will
      determine whether the corresponding requirements are to be realized over
      a single interface and protocol, or over multiple interfaces and
      protocols.</t>

      <t><list counter="log-reqs" hangIndent="4" style="format LI-%d">
          <t>[HIGH] The CDNI logging architecture and interface shall ensure
          reliable transfer of CDNI logging information across CDNs.</t>

          <t>[HIGH] The CDNI Logging interface shall provide logging of
          deliveries and incomplete deliveries to User Agents performed by the
          Downstream CDN as a result of request redirection by the Upstream
          CDN.</t>

          <t>[MED] In the case of cascaded CDNs, the CDNI Logging interface
          should allow the Downstream CDN to report to the Upstream CDN
          logging for deliveries and incomplete deliveries performed by the
          Downstream CDN itself as well as logging for deliveries and
          incomplete deliveries performed by cascaded CDNs on behalf of the
          Downstream CDN.</t>

          <t>[HIGH] The CDNI Logging interface shall support batch/offline
          exchange of logging records.</t>

          <t>[MED] The CDNI Logging interface should also support additional
          timing constraints for some types of logging records (e.g. near-real
          time for monitoring and analytics applications)</t>

          <t>[HIGH] The CDNI Logging interface shall define a log file format
          and a set of fields to be exported for various CDNI logging
          events.</t>

          <t>[HIGH] The CDNI Logging interface shall define a transport
          mechanism to exchange CDNI Logging files.</t>

          <t>[MED] The CDNI Logging interface should allow a CDN to query
          another CDN for relevant current logging records (e.g. For on-demand
          access to real-time logging information).</t>

          <t>[LOW] The CDNI Logging interface may support aggregate/
          summarized logs (e.g. total bytes delivered for a content regardless
          of individual User Agents to which it was delivered).</t>

          <t>[LOW] The CDNI Logging interface may support logging of
          performance data for deliveries to User Agents performed by the
          Downstream CDN as a result of request redirection by the Upstream
          CDN. Performance data may include various traffic statistics (the
          specific parameters are to be determined). The CDNI Logging
          interface may support the Upstream CDN to indicate the nature and
          contents of the performance data to be reported by the Downstream
          CDN.</t>

          <t>[MED] The CDNI Logging interface should support logging of
          consumed resources (e.g. storage, bandwidth) to the Upstream CDN for
          deliveries where content is stored by the Downstream CDN for
          delivery to User Agents. The information logged may include the type
          of storage (e.g., Origin, Intermediate, Edge, Cache) as well as the
          amount of storage (e.g., total GB, GB used, per time period, per
          content domain) all of which may impact the cost of the
          services.</t>

          <t>[MED] In the case of cascaded CDNs, the CDNI Logging interface
          should support the Downstream CDN to report consumed resources (e.g.
          storage, bandwidth) to the Upstream CDN where content is stored by
          the Downstream CDN itself as well as logging for storage resources
          when content storage is performed by cascaded CDNs on behalf of the
          Downstream CDN.</t>

          <t>[HIGH] The CDNI Logging interface shall support logging of
          deleted objects from the Downstream CDN to the Upstream CDN as a
          result of explicit delete requests on via the CDNI Control interface
          from the Upstream CDN.</t>

          <t>[HIGH] The CDNI Logging interface shall support extensibility to
          allow proprietary information fields to be carried. These
          information fields must be agreed upon ahead of time between the
          corresponding CDNs.</t>

          <t>[HIGH] The CDNI Logging interface shall support the exchange of
          extensible log file formats to support proprietary information
          fields. These information fields must be agreed upon ahead of time
          between the corresponding CDNs.</t>

          <t>[HIGH] The CDNI Logging interface shall allow a CDN to notify
          another CDN about which CDNI logging information is available for
          transfer and/or no longer available (e.g. it exceeded some logging
          retention period or some logging retention volume).</t>

          <t>[MED] The CDNI Logging interface should support the ability for
          the Downstream CDN to include the Content Collection ID and Session
          ID fields in CDNI log entries generated for HTTP Adaptive Streaming
          content. </t>
        </list></t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="sec" title="CDNI Security Requirements">
      <t>This section identifies the requirements related to the CDNI
      security. Some of those are expected to affect multiple or all
      protocols.</t>

      <t><list counter="sec-reqs" hangIndent="4" style="format SEC-%d">
          <t>[HIGH] All the CDNI interface shall support secure operation over
          unsecured IP connectivity (e.g. The Internet). This includes
          authentication, confidentiality, integrity protection as well as
          protection against spoofing and replay.</t>

          <t>[HIGH] The CDNI solution shall provide sufficient protection
          against Denial of Service attacks. This includes protection against
          spoofed delivery requests sent by user agents directly to a
          Downstream CDN attempting to appear as if they had been redirected
          by a given Upstream CDN when they have not.</t>

          <t>[MED] The CDNI solution should be able to ensure that for any
          given request redirected to a Downstream CDN, the chain of CDN
          Delegation (leading to that request being served by that CDN) can be
          established with non-repudiation.</t>

          <t>[MED] The CDNI solution should be able to ensure that the
          Downstream CDN cannot spoof a transaction log attempting to appear
          as if it corresponds to a request redirected by a given Upstream CDN
          when that request has not been redirected by this Upstream CDN. This
          ensures non-repudiation by the Upstream CDN of transaction logs
          generated by the Downstream CDN for deliveries performed by the
          Downstream CDN on behalf of the Upstream CDN.</t>

          <t>[LOW] The CDNI solution may provide a mechanism allowing an
          Upstream CDN that has credentials to acquire content from the CSP
          origin server (or another CDN), to allow establishment of
          credentials authorizing the Downstream CDN to acquire the content
          from the CSP origin server (or the other CDN) (e.g. In case the
          content cannot be acquired from the Upstream CDN).</t>
        </list></t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>This document makes no request of IANA.</t>

      <t>Note to RFC Editor: this section may be removed on publication as an
      RFC.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>This document discusses CDNI security requirements in <xref
      target="sec"/>.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Authors">
      <t>This document reflects the contributions from the following
      authors:</t>

      <t><list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="Francois Le Faucheur"/>

          <t>Cisco Systems</t>

          <t>flefauch@cisco.com</t>

          <t hangText="Mahesh Viveganandhan"/>

          <t>Cisco Systems</t>

          <t>mvittal@cisco.com</t>

          <t hangText="Grant Watson"/>

          <t>BT</t>

          <t>grant.watson@bt.com</t>
        </list></t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>This document leverages the earlier work of the IETF CDI working
      group in particular as documented in <xref
      target="I-D.cain-request-routing-req"/>, <xref
      target="I-D.amini-cdi-distribution-reqs"/> and <xref
      target="I-D.gilletti-cdnp-aaa-reqs"/>.</t>

      <t>The authors would like to thank Gilles Bertrand, Christophe Caillet,
      Bruce Davie, Phil Eardly, Ben Niven-Jenkins, Agustin Schapira, Emile
      Stephan, Eric Burger, Susan He, Kevin Ma, and Daryl Malas for their
      input. Serge Manning along with Robert Streijl, Vishwa Prasad, Percy
      Tarapore, Mike Geller, and Ramki Krishnan contributed to this document
      by addressing the requirements of the ATIS Cloud Services Forum.</t>

      <t>Ray Brandenburg, Matt Caufield, and Francois Le Faucheur/Gilles
      Bertrand provided valuable inputs for HTTP Adaptive Streaming, CDNI
      Metadata interface, and CDNI Logging interface, respectively.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Appendix: Requirements Mapping">
      <t>The labels and numbers changed in version 6 of this document as part
      of the requirements cleanup and structuring changes due to introduction
      of the new CDNI request routing/Redirection Interface and CDNI request
      routing/Footprint &amp; Capabilities advertisement interface. There are
      some CDNI drafts that have referenced the requirements in this document.
      Therefore, the following table provides the mapping of the requirement
      label and numbering.</t>

      <texttable>
        <ttcol>Version 5</ttcol>

        <ttcol>Version 6</ttcol>

        <c>GEN-13</c>

        <c>Removed</c>

        <c>GEN-14</c>

        <c>GEN-13</c>

        <c>CNTL-#</c>

        <c>CI-# (label changed)</c>

        <c>CNTL-1</c>

        <c>CI-1 and CI-3</c>

        <c>CNTL-2 to CNTL-9</c>

        <c>CI-4 to CI-11</c>

        <c>CNTL-10</c>

        <c>FCI-6</c>

        <c>CNTL-11</c>

        <c>CI-12</c>

        <c>CNTL-12</c>

        <c>CI-2</c>

        <c>REQ-#</c>

        <c>RI-# or FCI-# (label changed)</c>

        <c>REQ-1 to REQ-4</c>

        <c>FCI-1 to FCI-4</c>

        <c>REQ-5 to REQ-19</c>

        <c>RI-1 to RI-15</c>

        <c>REQ-20</c>

        <c>FCI-5</c>

        <c>META-#</c>

        <c>MI-# (label changed)</c>

        <c>META-13</c>

        <c>Removed</c>

        <c>META-14 to META-22</c>

        <c>MI-13 to MI-21</c>

        <c>LOG-#</c>

        <c>LI-# (label changed)</c>

        <c>LOG-4</c>

        <c>Removed</c>

        <c>LOG-5 to LOG-18</c>

        <c>LI-4 to LI-17</c>

        <postamble>Requirement Reference Mapping Table</postamble>
      </texttable>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc ?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6707'
?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6770'
?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2616"?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.davie-cdni-framework'
?>

      <?rfc ?>

      <?rfc ?>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.cain-request-routing-req'
?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.amini-cdi-distribution-reqs'
?>

      <reference anchor="I-D.gilletti-cdnp-aaa-reqs">
        <front>
          <title>CDI AAA Requirements,
          draft-gilletti-cdnp-aaa-reqs-01.txt</title>

          <date month="June" year="2001"/>

          <abstract>
            <t/>
          </abstract>
        </front>
      </reference>
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
