<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY RFC2119 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3688 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3688.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3986 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3986.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5545 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5545.xml">
<!ENTITY W3C.REC-xml-20060816 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml4/reference.W3C.REC-xml-20060816.xml">
]>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="5"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<rfc category="std" docName="draft-douglass-link-extension-00" ipr="trust200902">

  <front>
    <title abbrev="Link Extension to Icalendar">Link Extension to Icalendar</title>

    <!-- add 'role="editor"' below for the editors if appropriate -->

    <author initials="M." surname="Douglass" fullname="Michael Douglass">
      <organization abbrev="RPI">Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>110 8th Street</street>
          <city>Troy</city>
          <region>NY</region>
          <code>12180</code>
          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>
        <email>douglm@rpi.edu</email>
        <uri>http://www.rpi.edu/</uri>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date year="2010" />

    <area>Applications</area>

    <keyword>icalendar</keyword>

    <keyword>link</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>
        This specification introduces a new iCalendar
        property LINK to provide ancillary information for iCalendar
        components.
      </t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>
        The currently existing iCalendar standard <xref target='RFC5545'/> lacks
        a general purpose method for referencing additional, external information
        relating to calendar components.
      </t>

      <t>
        This document proposes a method for referencing typed external
        information that can provide additional information about an iCalendar
        component (such as a VCARD). This method is general purpose and may be
        used anywhere the need to reference additional information is desired.
      </t>

      <t>
        This new LINK property is closely aligned to the LINK header defined in 
        [TODO draft-nottingham-http-link-header]
      </t>

      <section anchor="conventions" title='Conventions Used in This Document'>
        <t>
          The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL
          NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED",
          "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as
          described in <xref target='RFC2119'/>.
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Typed References">
      <t>
        The LINK property defines a typed reference or relation to external 
        meta-data or related resources. By providing type and format information  
        as parameters, clients and servers are able to discover interesting 
        references and make use of them, perhaps for indexing or the 
        presentation of interesting links for the user. 
      </t>

      <t>
        Many of these relations are designed to handle common use cases in event 
        publication. It is generally important to provide information about the 
        organizers of such events. Sponsors also wish to be referenced in a 
        prominent manner. In social calendaring it is often important to 
        identify the active participants in the event, for example a school 
        sports team, and the inactive participants, for example the parents.
      </t>

      <t>
        This property will also allow references to other data that has a time
        components. For example, in the power industry it allows the creation
        of schedules of power usage linked to related information about the 
        amount and cost.
      </t>

      <t>
        For example the <xref target='RFC5545'/> LOCATION property provides only
        an unstructured text value for specifying the location where an event
        (or "TODO" item) will occur. This is inadequate for use cases where
        structured location information (e.g. address, region, country, postal
        code) is required or preferred, and limits widespread adoption of
        iCalendar in those settings. 
      </t>

      <t>
        Using LINK, structured information about the venue such as address,
        city, region/state and postal code can be communicated, perhaps using a
        VCARD object. Servers and clients can retrieve the vcard object when
        storing the event and use it to index by geographic location.
      </t>
      
      <t>
        As another example, a calendar item can reference a video feed for the 
        event. This provides event publishers with a means to attract consumers
        to their sites while providing a service directly accessible from the
        users' calendar client. 
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="new_property_parameters"
             title="New Property Parameters">
      <section anchor="rel"
               title="Rel">
        <t>
        <list style='hanging'>
          <t hangText="Parameter name:">
            REL
          </t>

          <t hangText="Purpose:">
            To specify the relationship of data referenced by a LINK property.
          </t>

          <t hangText="Format Definition:">
            <figure>
              <preamble>
                This parameter is defined by the following notation:
              </preamble>

              <artwork type="abnf">
  relparam      = "REL" "="
                  ("CAL_CONTACT"      ; A contact address
                   "CAL_LOCATION"
                        ; A location reference (a.k.a. "Venue")
                   "CAL_ORGANIZEDBY"  
                        ; An event organizer - NOT a meeting scheduler
                   "CAL_PERFORMER"    ; Performer at an event
                   "CAL_PRINCIPAL_PERFORMER"
                         ; A principal performer at an event
                   "CAL_PRINCIPAL_SPONSOR"   ; A principal sponsor 
                   "CAL_SPONSOR"      ; Sponsor for an event
                   "CAL_PR_CONTACT"   ; Public relations contact
                   
                   "CAL_ACTIVE_PARTICIPANT"  ; e.g. a team, 
                   "CAL_INACTIVE_PARTICIPANT"  ; e.g. parents of a team, 
                   
                   "CAL_VIRTUAL_LOCATION"    ; A Virtual location
                                         ; (a.k.a. "Chatroom")
                   "CAL_TELECONFERENCE_DIALIN"
                   
                   "CAL_TICKETING_OFFICE"  ; Make reservations 
                                           ; and/or pay
                   
                   ; Media feeds
                   "CAL_AUDIO_MEDIA"    ; An audio feed
                   "CAL_SOCIAL_MEDIA"   ; Feed other than Audio/Video
                   "CAL_VIRTUAL_MEDIA"  ; A Virtual World Space
                   
                  / x-name        ; Experimental reference type
                  / iana-token)    ; Other IANA registered type
              </artwork>
            </figure>
          </t>

          <t hangText="Description:">
            This parameter MUST be specified on all LINK properties, and
            defines the type of reference.  This allows programs consuming this
            data to automatically scan for references they support.  For
            example, a mobile device may be able to consume LOCATION references,
            but not other types of reference.
          </t>

          <t hangText="Registration:">
            These relation types are registered in 
            [TODO ref to draft-nottingham-http-link-header].
          </t>
        </list>
        </t>
        
        <section anchor="rel_contact"
                 title="Relation Type CAL_CONTACT">
          <t>
            This type identifies a contact for the event. An appropriate format
            for this reference would be text/vcard allowing clients to display
            rich contact information.
          </t>
        </section>
        
        <section anchor="rel_location"
                 title="Relation Type CAL_LOCATION">
          <t>
            This type identifies the location of the event. An appropriate format
            for this reference would be text/vcard allowing clients to display
            rich location information and possibly link to mapping applications.
          </t>
          
          <t>
            Event consumers can use this reference to index the event by the
            geographic location allowing proximity searching.
          </t>
        </section>
        
        <section anchor="rel_organizedby"
                 title="Relation Type CAL_ORGANIZEDBY">
          <t>
            This type identifies an organizer for the event. An appropriate format
            for this reference would be text/vcard allowing clients to display
            rich information.
          </t>
          
          <t>
            This type is distinct from the ORGANIZER property which is only 
            allowed on scheduling messages. This property allows event 
            organizers to identify themselves.
          </t>
        </section>
        
        <section anchor="rel_performer"
                 title="Relation Type CAL_PERFORMER">
          <t>
            This type identifies a performer for the event. An appropriate format
            for this reference would be text/vcard allowing clients to display
            rich information about the performer.
          </t>
          
          <t>
            This reference allows event consumers to index events by the 
            performer and may appear once for each performer.
          </t>
        </section>
        
        <section anchor="rel_principal_performer"
                 title="Relation Type CAL_PRINCIPAL_PERFORMER">
          <t>
            This type identifies a principal performer for the event. An appropriate format
            for this reference would be text/vcard allowing clients to display
            rich information about the performer.
          </t>
          
          <t>
            This reference allows event consumers to index events by the 
            principal performer.
          </t>
        </section>
        
        <section anchor="rel_active_participant"
                 title="Relation Type CAL_ACTIVE_PARTICIPANT">
          <t>
            This type identifies an active participant in an event. The form 
            for this reference could be text/vcard identifying a group such as 
            a team or an individual.
          </t>
        </section>
        
        <section anchor="rel_inactive_participant"
                 title="Relation Type CAL_INACTIVE_PARTICIPANT">
          <t>
            This type identifies inactive participants for an event. These are
            usually interested parties that may act as spectators, for example, 
            the parents of team members. The form 
            for this reference could be text/vcard identifying a group such as 
            a team or an individual.
          </t>
          
          <t>
            This reference allows event organizers to notify the participants in 
            the event of changes.
          </t>
        </section>
        
        <section anchor="rel_sponsor"
                 title="Relation Type CAL_SPONSOR">
          <t>
            This type identifies a sponsor for the event. An appropriate format
            for this reference would be text/vcard allowing clients to display
            rich information about sponsors or perhaps to insert sponsor logos 
            where appropriate.
          </t>
          
          <t>
            It is assumed that there may be multiple references of this type, 
            each identifying a different sponsor. 
          </t>
        </section>
        
        <section anchor="rel_principal_sponsor"
                 title="Relation Type CAL_PRINCIPAL_SPONSOR">
          <t>
            This type identifies a principal sponsor for the event. 
            An appropriate format
            for this reference would be text/vcard allowing clients to display
            rich information about sponsors or perhaps to insert sponsor logos 
            where appropriate.
          </t>
          
          <t>
            It is assumed that there may be multiple references of this type, 
            each identifying a different sponsor. 
          </t>
        </section>
        
        <section anchor="rel_audio_media"
                 title="Relation Type CAL_AUDIO_MEDIA">
          <t>
            This type identifies an audio feed associated with the event.
          </t>
        </section>
        
        <section anchor="rel_video"
                 title="Relation Type CAL_VIDEO_MEDIA">
          <t>
            This type identifies a video feed associated with the event.
          </t>
        </section>
      </section>
      
      <section anchor="Title"
               title="Title">
        <t>
          <list style='hanging'>
            <t hangText="Parameter name:">
              TITLE
            </t>
  
            <t hangText="Purpose:">
              To provide a human readable title.
            </t>
  
            <t hangText="Format Definition:">
              <figure>
                <preamble>
                  This parameter is defined by the following notation:
                </preamble>
  
                <artwork type="abnf">
  titleparam     = "TITLE" "=" text
                </artwork>
              </figure>
            </t>
  
            <t hangText="Description:">
              This parameter MAY be specified on all LINK properties, and
              provides a human readable label, perhaps for icons or links..
            </t>
          </list>
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="new_properties"
             title="New Properties">
      <section anchor="link"
               title="Link">
        <t>
          <list style='hanging'>
            <t hangText="Property name:">
              LINK
            </t>
  
            <t hangText="Purpose:">
              This property provides a reference to external information about a
              component.
            </t>
  
            <t hangText="Value type:">
              URI
            </t>
  
            <t hangText="Property Parameters:">
              Non-standard, reference type or format type parameters can be
              specified on this property.
            </t>
  
            <t hangText="Conformance:">
              This property MAY be specified in any iCalendar component.
            </t>
  
            <t hangText="Description:">
              When used in a component the value of this property points to
              additional information related to the component.  For example,
              it may reference a VCARD giving detailed information about the
              venue of a VEVENT.
            </t>
  
            <t hangText="Format Definition:">
              <figure>
                <preamble>
                  This property is defined by the following notation:
                </preamble>
  
                <artwork>
  link            = "LINK" linkparam ":" uri CRLF

  linkparam       = *(

                  ; the following are MANDATORY
                  ; but MUST NOT occur more than once

                  (";" relparam) /
                  (";" fmttypeparam) /
                  (";" titleparam) /

                  ; the following is OPTIONAL
                  ; and MAY occur more than once

                  (";" xparam)

                  )

                </artwork>
              </figure>
            </t>
  
            <t hangText="Example:">
              <figure>
                <preamble>
                  The following is an example of this property.  It points to a
                  VCARD version describing the location of a VEVENT.
                </preamble>
  
                <artwork>
                 LINK;REL=LOCATION;TYPE=text/vcard;
                   TITLE=The Egg:
                   http://eventful.com/vcard/venues/V0-001-000361522-8
                </artwork>
              </figure>
            </t>
          </list>
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title='Security Considerations'>
      <t>
       Applications using the LINK property need to be aware of the risks 
       entailed in using the URIs provided as values. See [RFC3986] for 
       a discussion of the security considerations relating to URIs. 
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="iana_considerations" title='IANA Considerations'>

      <!--
      <section anchor="new_rel_registration"
               title="New Reference Type Registration">
        <t>
          This section defines the process to register new or modified
          reference types with IANA.
        </t>

        <section anchor="reftype_registration_procedure"
                 title="Reference Type Registration Procedure">
          <t>
            The IETF will create a mailing list,
            <eref target="mailto:icalreference@ietf.org">icalreference@ietf.org</eref>,
            which can be used for public discussion of reference type
            proposals prior to registration. Use of the mailing list
            is strongly encouraged. The IESG will appoint a designated
            expert who will monitor the
            <eref target="mailto:icalreference@ietf.org">icalreference@ietf.org</eref>
            mailing list and review registrations.
          </t>

          <t>
            Registration of new reference types MUST be reviewed by
            the designated expert and published in an RFC. A Standard
            Tracks RFC is REQUIRED for the registration of reference types.
            A Standard Tracks RFC is also REQUIRED for changes to reference types 
            previously documented in a Standard Tracks RFC.
          </t>

          <t>
            The registration procedure begins when a completed registration
            template, defined in the sections below, is sent to
            <eref target="mailto:icalreference@ietf.org">icalreference@ietf.org</eref>
            and
            <eref target="mailto:iana@iana.org">iana@iana.org</eref>.
            The designated expert is expected to tell IANA and the submitter
            of the registration within two weeks whether the registration
            is approved, approved with minor changes, or rejected with
            cause.  When a registration is rejected with cause, it can be
            re-submitted if the concerns listed in the cause are addressed.
            Decisions made by the designated expert can be appealed to the
            IESG Applications Area Director, then to the IESG. They follow
            the normal appeals procedure for IESG decisions.
          </t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="registration_template_for_reference_types"
                 title="Registration Template for Reference Types" >
          <t>
            A reference type is defined by completing the following template.
            <list style="hanging">
              <t hangText="Reference Type Name:">
                The name of the reference type.
              </t>
              <t hangText="Purpose:">
                The purpose of the reference type.
                Give a short but clear description.
              </t>

              <t hangText="Description:">
                Any special notes about the reference type, how it is to be used,
                etc.
              </t>
              <t hangText="Example(s):">
                One or more examples of use of the use of the reference type.
              </t>
            </list>
          </t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section anchor="initial_relation_type_registries"
               title="Initial Relation Type Registries" >
        <t>
          The IANA is requested to create and maintain the following
          registries for reference types with pointers to
          appropriate reference documents.
        </t>

        <section anchor="reference_types_registry"
                 title="Reference Types Registry">
          <t>
            The following table is to be used to initialize the
            reference types registry.
          </t>
          <texttable>
            <ttcol align="left">Name</ttcol>
            <ttcol align="left">Status</ttcol>
            <ttcol align="left">Reference</ttcol>

            <c>AUDIO</c>
            <c>Current</c>
            <c>RFCXXXX, <xref target="reference_type_audio"/></c>

            <c>CONTACT</c>
            <c>Current</c>
            <c>RFCXXXX, <xref target="reference_type_contact"/></c>

            <c>LOCATION</c>
            <c>Current</c>
            <c>RFCXXXX, <xref target="reference_type_location"/></c>

            <c>ORGANIZEDBY</c>
            <c>Current</c>
            <c>RFCXXXX, <xref target="reference_type_organizedby"/></c>

            <c>PERFORMER</c>
            <c>Current</c>
            <c>RFCXXXX, <xref target="reference_type_performer"/></c>

            <c>PRINCIPAL_PERFORMER</c>
            <c>Current</c>
            <c>RFCXXXX, <xref target="reference_type_principal_performer"/></c>

            <c>SPONSOR</c>
            <c>Current</c>
            <c>RFCXXXX, <xref target="reference_type_sponsor"/></c>

            <c>VIDEO</c>
            <c>Current</c>
            <c>RFCXXXX, <xref target="reference_type_video"/></c>
          </texttable>
        </section>
      </section> -->
    </section>

    <section title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>
        The author would like to thank Chuck Norris of eventful.com for his work 
        which led to the development of this RFC.  
      </t>
      <t>
        The author would also like to thank the members of the Calendaring and
        Scheduling Consortium public events technical committee and the following
        individuals for contributing their ideas and support:
      </t>
      <t>
        Cyrus Daboo, Dan Mendell
      </t>
      <t>
        The authors would also like to thank the Calendaring and
        Scheduling Consortium for advice with this specification.
      </t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <!--  *****BACK MATTER ***** -->

  <back>
    <!-- References split into informative and normative -->

    <!-- There are 2 ways to insert reference entries from the citation libraries:
     1. define an ENTITY at the top, and use "ampersand character"RFC2629; here (as shown)
     2. simply use a PI "less than character"?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119.xml"?> here
        (for I-Ds: include="reference.I-D.narten-iana-considerations-rfc2434bis.xml")

     Both are cited textually in the same manner: by using xref elements.
     If you use the PI option, xml2rfc will, by default, try to find included files in the same
     directory as the including file. You can also define the XML_LIBRARY environment variable
     with a value containing a set of directories to search.  These can be either in the local
     filing system or remote ones accessed by http (http://domain/dir/... ).-->

    <references title="Normative References">
      &RFC2119;
      &RFC5545;
      &RFC3688;
      &RFC3986;
      &W3C.REC-xml-20060816;
    </references>

    <!-- Change Log

v00 2007-10-19  MD    Initial version
                      -->
  </back>
</rfc>
