<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!-- This template is for creating an Internet Draft using xml2rfc,
     which is available here: http://xml.resource.org. -->
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!-- One method to get references from the online citation libraries.
     There has to be one entity for each item to be referenced. 
     An alternate method (rfc include) is described in the references. -->

<!ENTITY RFC2119 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC2131 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2131.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC2865 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2865.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3315 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3315.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6333 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6333.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6733 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6733.xml">
]>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<!-- used by XSLT processors -->
<!-- For a complete list and description of processing instructions (PIs), 
     please see http://xml.resource.org/authoring/README.html. -->
<!-- Below are generally applicable Processing Instructions (PIs) that most I-Ds might want to use.
     (Here they are set differently than their defaults in xml2rfc v1.32) -->
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<!-- give errors regarding ID-nits and DTD validation -->
<!-- control the table of contents (ToC) -->
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<!-- generate a ToC -->
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<!-- the number of levels of subsections in ToC. default: 3 -->
<!-- control references -->
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<!-- use symbolic references tags, i.e, [RFC2119] instead of [1] -->
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<!-- sort the reference entries alphabetically -->
<!-- control vertical white space 
     (using these PIs as follows is recommended by the RFC Editor) -->
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<!-- do not start each main section on a new page -->
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<!-- keep one blank line between list items -->
<!-- end of list of popular I-D processing instructions -->

<rfc category="std" docName="draft-zhou-dime-4over6-provisioning-00" ipr="trust200902">
  <!-- category values: std, bcp, info, exp, and historic
     ipr values: trust200902, noModificationTrust200902, noDerivativesTrust200902
     pre5378Trust200902
     you can add the attributes updates="NNNN" and obsoletes="NNNN" 
     they will automatically be output with "(if approved)" -->

  <!-- ***** FRONT MATTER ***** -->

  <front>
    <!-- The abbreviated title is used in the page header - it is only necessary if the 
         full title is longer than 39 characters -->

    <title abbrev="AVPs For 4over6 CPE Provisioning">Attribute-Value Pairs For Provisioning Customer Equipment Supporting IPv4-Over-IPv6 Transitional Solutions</title>

    <author fullname="Cathy Zhou" initials="C."  surname="Zhou">
      <organization>Huawei Technologies</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Bantian, Longgang District</street>
          <city>Shenzhen</city>
          <code>518129</code>
          <country>P.R. China</country>
        </postal>
        <phone></phone>
        <email>cathy.zhou@huawei.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    
    <author initials="T." surname="Taylor" fullname="T. Taylor">
      <organization>Huawei Technologies</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>
          <city>Ottawa</city>
          <region></region>
          <code></code>
          <country>Canada</country>
        </postal>
        <phone></phone>
        <email>tom.taylor.stds@gmail.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    

    <date year="2013" />

    <!-- Meta-data Declarations -->

    <area>General</area>

    <workgroup>Internet Engineering Task Force</workgroup>

    <!-- WG name at the upperleft corner of the doc,
         IETF is fine for individual submissions.  
	 If this element is not present, the default is "Network Working Group",
         which is used by the RFC Editor as a nod to the history of the IETF. -->

    <keyword>DS-Lite</keyword>
    <keyword>Public IPv4 Over IPv6</keyword>
    <keyword>Light-Weight 4over6</keyword>
    <keyword>MAP-E</keyword>

    <!-- Keywords will be incorporated into HTML output
         files in a meta tag but they have no effect on text or nroff
         output. If you submit your draft to the RFC Editor, the
         keywords will be used for the search engine. -->

    <abstract>
      <t>During the transition from IPv4 to IPv6, customer equipment may
      have to support one of the various transition methods that have been
      or are currently being defined for carrying IPv4 packets over IPv6.
      Work is currently in progress to enumerate the information that needs
      to be provisioned on a customer edge router to support a list of
      transition techniques based on tunneling IPv4 in IPv6, with a view to
      defining reusable components for a reasonable transition path between
      these techniques. To the extent that the provisioning is done
      dynamically, AAA support is needed to provide the information to the
      network server responsible for passing the information to the customer
      equipment. This document specifies Diameter attribute-value pairs to be
      used for that purpose. </t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
    
      <t>A number of transition technologies have been or are being defined
      to allow IPv4 packets to pass between hosts and IPv4 networks over an
      intervening IPv6 network while minimizing the number of public IPv4
      addresses that need to be consumed by the hosts. Different operators
      will deploy different technologies, and sometimes one operator will
      use more than one technology, depending on what is supported by the
      available equipment and upon other factors both technical and
      economic. </t>
      
      <t>Each technique requires the provisioning of some subscriber-
      specific information on the customer edge device. The provisioning may
      be by DHCP or by some other method. This document is indifferent to
      the specific provisioning technique used, but assumes that the
      information originates in the AAA infrastructure. To allow the
      information to be carried in Diameter <xref target="RFC6733"/>, this
      document specifies a number of attribute-value pairs (AVPs) for the
      purpose. </t>
      
      <t>This document takes as its scope the set of transition methods
      provided for by <xref target="I_D.softwire-unified-cpe"/>. That
      document enumerates the information that must be provisioned in the
      customer edge router to support Dual-Stack Lite <xref target="RFC6333"/>,
      Public IPv4 Over IPv6 
      <xref target="I-D.ietf-softwire-public-4over6"/>,
      Light Weight IPv4 Over IPv6 (LW4o6) 
      <xref target="I-D.cui-softwire-b4-translated-ds-lite"/>,
      and Mapping of Address and Port with Encapsulation (MAP-E)
      <xref target="I-D.ietf-softwire-map"/>.</t>
      
      <t>Several documents provide related specifications for RADIUS <xref
      target="RFC2865"/>, for individual transition methods. Potentially
      there could be a reconciliation between the contents of those
      documents and the present one, but that has not been done in the
      present version of this document.</t>
      
      <section title="Requirements Language">
        <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
        "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
        document are to be interpreted as described in 
        <xref target="RFC2119">RFC 2119</xref>.</t>
      </section>
    </section>
    
    <section anchor="reqts" title="Description of the Parameters Required By Each Transition Method">

      <t>This section reviews the parameters that need to be provisioned for
      each of the transition methods listed above. This enumeration provides
      the justification for the AVPs defined in the next section. Since most
      of the transition methods dealt with here are works in progress, this
      section is subject to modification in future versions.</t>
      
      <section anchor="dslite" title="Parameters For Dual-Stack Lite">

        <t>Dual-Stack Lite is documented in <xref target="RFC6333"/>. It
        requires the following parameters to be provisioned at the B4 at the
        customer premises. This enumeration does not include the normal
        provisioning of an IPv6 prefix to the customer equipment. The section
        numbers shown are where these requirements are indicated in 
        <xref target="RFC6333"/>.
        <list style="symbols">
          <t>IPv6 address of the border router (AFTR) (sec. 5.4);</t>
          
          <t>IPv6 address of a DNS recursive server (sec. 5.5). This is probably
          supplied already independently of transition technology, so does not
          have to be covered here.</t>
          
          <t>an indicator that DS-Lite is to be used rather than some other
          transition method (sec. 5.6). Note that <xref target="RFC6333"/>
          says that the choice should be made by unspecified means during
          initialization, while <xref target="I_D.softwire-unified-cpe"/>
          specifies how to infer the intended method from other DHCP
          parameters received. Thus the indicator suggested here may not come
          from AAA.</t>
          
          <t>optionally, the IPv4 address of the B4 interface facing the
          tunnel, where the default value in the absence of provisioning is 
          192.0.0.2 and valid values are 192.0.0.2 through 192.0.0.7 
          (sec. 5.7).</t>
          
        </list>
        </t>
        
        <t>The AFTR may also require an item of per-subscriber information
        (sec. 8.1):
        <list style="symbols">
          <t>the identity of the NAT pool to which the subscriber is to be
          assigned.</t>
        </list>
        </t>

      </section>  <!-- dslite -->
      
      <section anchor="pub4o6" title="Public IPv4 Over IPv6">

        <t>Public IPv4 Over IPv6 is described in
        <xref target="I-D.ietf-softwire-public-4over6"/>. Besides the usual 
        IPv6 prefix or address information, it requires two parameters to be 
        provisioned to the customer equipment: 
        <list style="symbols">
          <t>a public IPv4 address;</t>
          
          <t>IPv6 address of the border router</t>
        </list>
        It also requires per-subscriber provisioning on the border router:
        <list style="symbols">
          <t>binding between the customer IPv4 address and the customer 
          IPv6 prefix, for routing of incoming packets to the correct tunnel.</t>
        </list>
        </t>

      </section>  <!-- pub4o6 -->
      
      <section anchor="lw4o6" title="Light Weight IPv4 Over IPv6 (LW4o6)">

        <t>Light Weight IPv4 Over IPv6 (LW4o6) is documented in 
        <xref target="I-D.cui-softwire-b4-translated-ds-lite"/>. Its
        provisioning requirements are exactly the same as those for Public
        4over6 with one addition:
        <list style="symbols">
          <t>both the customer equipment and the border router are provided with
          a port set identifier identifying the set of ports to which the
          subscriber's incoming and outgoing packets on the public side are
          restricted. The port selection algorithm and port set identifier as
          such are not discussed in the draft. For the present version of this
          document, it is assumed that the algorithm is known in advance and the
          port set identifier has the form of an index ranging from zero to the
          number of subscribers sharing a given address less 1. This is similar
          to the port set identifier in MAP-E, described next.</t>
        </list>
        </t>

      </section>  <!-- lw4o6 -->
      
      <section anchor="map-e" title="Mapping of Address and Port with Encapsulation (MAP-E)">

        <t>Mapping of Address and Port with Encapsulation (MAP-E) is described
        in <xref target="I-D.ietf-softwire-map"/>. MAP-E requires the
        provisioning of the following per-subscriber information at the
        customer edge device: 
        <list style="symbols">
          <t>whether the device is to operate in mesh or hub-and-spoke mode;</t>
          
          <t>the IPv6 address of the border router, also known as the Default
          Mapping rule;</t>
          
          <t>the specially constructed End-user IPv6 prefix for the customer
          edge device. <xref target="I-D.ietf-softwire-map"/> suggests that this
          would be supplied as part of normal IPv6 provisioning, so it can be
          ignored as a requirement here. </t>
          
          <t>the Basic Mapping Rule for the customer edge device. This 
          includes the following parameters:
          <list style="symbols">
            <t>the rule IPv6 prefix and length;</t>
            
            <t>the rule IPv4 prefix and length;</t>
            
            <t>the number of "Extended Address" (EA) bits included in the 
            End-user IPv6 prefix;</t>
            
            <t>of those Extended Address bits, the number that precede the port
            set identifier. This is currently a matter of discussion, whether it
            should default to 4 or 6 or be fixed at either of these values.</t>
          </list>
          </t>
          
          <t>in mesh mode only, zero or more Forwarding Mapping Rules,
          containing the same parameters as the Basic Mapping rule.</t>
            
          <t>optionally, the port set identifier if the EA bits do carry it.</t>
        </list>
        </t>
        
        <t>The border router needs to be configured with the superset of the
        Forwarding MAP Rules passed to the customer sites it serves. Since
        this is not subscriber-specific, even though it introduces no new
        requirements to this document, it is out of scope.</t>

      </section>  <!-- map-e -->
      
      <section anchor="sumreq" title="Summing Up">

        <t>It appears that the following items are common to two or more
        methods and should therefore be specified in method-independent
        fashion:
        <list style="symbols">
          <t>the IPv6 address of the border router;</t>
          
          <t>an IPv4 prefix and length (could be a /32);</t>
          
          <t>a port set identifier;</t>
          
          <t>tentatively, a method indicator, indicating which of the
          above transition methods the customer edge device must use.</t>
        </list>
        </t>
        
        <t>The remaining requirements are method-specific:
        <list style="symbols">
          <t>for DS-Lite, the identity of the NAT pool to which the subscriber
          is assigned;</t>
          
          <t>for Public 4over6 and LW4o6, a binding between a customer IPv6
          prefix or address and an IPv4 address;</t>
          
          <t>for MAP-E, the indication of whether mesh mode or hub-and-spoke
          mode is to be used;</t>
          
          <t>for MAP-E, a Grouped AVP expressing a MAP Rule.</t>
        </list></t>

      </section>  <!-- sumreq -->

    </section>  <!-- reqts -->
    
    
    <section anchor="AVPdefs" title="Attribute-Value Pair Definitions">

      <t>This section provides the specifications for the AVPs needed to
      meet the requirements summarized in <xref target="sumreq"/>. Within
      the context of their usage, all of these AVPs MUST have the M bit set
      and the V bit cleared.</t>
      
      <section anchor="braddr" title="Border Router IPv6 Address">

        <t>The Border-Router-IPv6-Address (AVP Code TBD01) is of type Address
        as defined in Section 4.3 of <xref target="RFC6733"/> and contains the
        IPv6 address of a border router supporting an IPv6 transition method
        which will be used by the customer edge device on which this address
        is provisioned. The address MAY be an anycast address. Since the
        content is an IPv6 address, the AVP Length MUST be set to 26 and the
        first two octets MUST contain 0x0002 (IPv6). </t>

      </section>  <!-- braddr -->
      
      <section anchor="v4pref" title="IPv4 Prefix or Address">

        <t>The IPv4-Prefix-Or-Addr (AVP Code TBD02) is derived from base type
        OctetString. It is a discriminated union representing the combination
        of the prefix length (number of bits) in the first octet, followed by
        the prefix itself, most significant octet first, padded with zeroes at
        the low-order end to an octet boundary. Valid values of the prefix
        length are from 0 to 32, where 0 indicates that the prefix is absent
        and 32 indicates a complete address. Correspondingly, the AVP Length
        can range from 9 to 13.</t>

      </section>  <!-- v4pref -->
      
      <section anchor="v6pref" title="IPv6 Prefix or Address">

        <t>The IPv6-Prefix-Or-Addr (AVP Code TBD03) is derived from base type
        OctetString. It is a discriminated union representing the combination
        of the prefix length (number of bits) in the first octet, followed by
        the prefix itself, most significant octet first, padded with zeroes at
        the low-order end to an octet boundary. Valid values of the prefix
        length are from 0 to 128, where 0 indicates that the prefix is absent
        and 128 indicates a complete address. Correspondingly, the AVP Length
        can range from 9 to 25.</t>

      </section>  <!-- v6pref -->
      
      <section anchor="psid" title="Port Set Identifier">

        <t>The Port-Set-Identifier AVP (AVP Code TBD04) is of type Unsigned32
        and indicates a set of ports defined by an otherwise-specified
        algorithm. For a given shared address, each Port-Set-Identifier value 
        MUST identify a separate set of ports. AVP Length for the 
        Port-Set-Identifier AVP MUST be set to 12.</t>

      </section>  <!-- psid -->
      
      <section anchor="method" title="Transition Method Indicator">

        <t>The Transition-Method AVP (AVP Code TBD05) is of type Enumerated
        and indicates the IPv6 transition method to be used. This document
        specifies the following values: 
        <list style="empty">
          <t>0 NO_METHOD</t>
          
          <t>1 DUAL_STACK</t>
          
          <t>2 DS_LITE</t>
          
          <t>3 PUBLIC_4OVER6</t>
          
          <t>4 LIGHT_WEIGHT_4OVER6</t>
          
          <t>5 MAP_WITH_ENCAPSULATION</t>
        </list>
        NO_METHOD indicates that the network will not support any transition
        method, and expects only IPv6 packets. DUAL_STACK indicates that the
        network will accept either IPv4 or IPv6 packets. [Maybe references
        should be added for the other values?] </t>
        
        <t>The AVP Length for the Transition-Method AVP MUST be set to 12.</t>

      </section>  <!-- method -->
      
      <section anchor="poolid" title="NAT Pool Identifier">

        <t>NAT-Poolid (AVP Code TBD06) is of type Unsigned32 and indicates 
        the NAT pool on a network-based NAT to which a subscriber is to be
        assigned. The set of valid values for this AVP is a local matter.
        The AVP Length for the NAT-Poolid AVP MUST be set to 12.</t>

      </section>  <!-- poolid -->
      
      <section anchor="binding" title="Binding Between An IPv4 Address and IPv6 Address/Prefix Assigned to a Customer Edge Device">

        <t>4to6-Binding (AVP Code TBD07) is of type Grouped. It provides an
        IPv4 address or prefix assigned to a customer edge device, a
        corresponding IPv6 address or prefix assigned to the tunnel interface
        at the customer edge device, and, if the IPv4 address is shared, a
        port set identifier indicating the valid set of ports for this
        customer edge device. The contents of the 4to6-Binding AVP are
        required at the border router when Public 4over6 or Light-Weight
        4over6 is being used. </t> 
        
        <t>If the port set identifier is present, the IPv4 address MUST be
        a full IPv4 address. The port set identifier is relevant only if
        Light-Weight 4over6 is being used.</t>
        
        <t>The syntax of the 4to6-Binding AVP is given as follows, where
        the component AVPs were defined above. The final *[ AVP ] component
        is added for extensibility.</t>
        
        <figure anchor="fig_4to6" title="">
          <artwork>
         4to6-Binding  ::= &lt; AVP Header: TBD07 >
                          { IPv4-Prefix-Or-Addr }
                          { IPv6-Prefix-Or-Addr }
                       0*1{ Port-Set-Identifier }
                         *[ AVP ]
          </artwork>
        </figure>

      </section>  <!-- binding -->
      
      <section anchor="maprule" title="MAP Rule AVP">

        <t>The MAP-Rule AVP (AVP Code TBD08) is of type Grouped, and is used
        only in conjunction with the MAP-E transition method. MAP rules are
        required both by the border router and by the customer edge device.
        The components of the MAP-Rule AVP are the rule IPv4 prefix or
        address, the rule IPv6 prefix, the length in bits of the Extended
        Address field in the End-User IPv6 Prefix assigned to the customer
        edge device, and the offset in a port number beyond which the port set
        identifier begins.</t>
        
        <t>The syntax of the MAP-Rule AVP is as follows:</t>
        
        <figure anchor="fig_map" title="">
          <artwork>
         MAP-Rule      ::= &lt; AVP Header: TBD08 >
                          { IPv4-Prefix-Or-Addr }
                          { IPv6-Prefix-Or-Addr }
                          { EA-Field-Length     }
                          [ PSID-Offset         ]
                         *[ AVP ]
          </artwork>
        </figure>

        <t>The IPv4-Prefix-Or-Addr and IPv6-Prefix-Or-Addr AVPs were defined
        above. The EA-Field-Length AVP (AVP Code TBD09) and PSID-Offset AVP
        (AVP Code TBD10) are of type Unsigned32. The valid range for 
        EA-Field-Length extends from 0 to a maximum value defined by 
        <xref target="I-D.ietf-softwire-map"/>. The valid range for 
        PSID-Offset extends from 0 to 15, with a default value given by 
        <xref target="I-D.ietf-softwire-map"/> if the parameter is absent.</t>

      </section>  <!-- maprule -->

    </section>  <!-- AVPdefs -->


    <section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>TBD</t>
    </section>

    <!-- Possibly a 'Contributors' section ... -->

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>This memo requests to IANA to register the following Diameter AVP
      codes: </t>
      
      <texttable anchor="tt_codes" title="">
        <ttcol align="center">Code</ttcol>
        <ttcol align="left">Attribute Name</ttcol>
        <ttcol align="left">Reference</ttcol>
        
        <c>TBD01</c>
        <c>Border-Router-IPv6-Address</c>
        <c>This document</c>
        
        <c>TBD02</c>
        <c>IPv4-Prefix-Or-Addr</c>
        <c>This document</c>
        
        <c>TBD03</c>
        <c>IPv6-Prefix-Or-Addr</c>
        <c>This document</c>
        
        <c>TBD04</c>
        <c>Port-Set-Identifier</c>
        <c>This document</c>
        
        <c>TBD05</c>
        <c>Transition-Method</c>
        <c>This document</c>
        
        <c>TBD06</c>
        <c>NAT-Poolid</c>
        <c>This document</c>
        
        <c>TBD07</c>
        <c>4to6-Binding</c>
        <c>This document</c>
        
        <c>TBD08</c>
        <c>MAP-Rule</c>
        <c>This document</c>
        
        <c>TBD09</c>
        <c>EA-Field-Length</c>
        <c>This document</c>
        
        <c>TBD10</c>
        <c>PSID-Offset</c>
        <c>This document</c>
        
      </texttable>
      
      <t>This document further requests IANA to establish a new sub-
      directory of the Diameter AVP Specific Values directory entitled
      Transition-Method AVP Values (code TBD05). The initial set of values
      for this registry are as follows:</t>
      
      <texttable anchor="tt_tmval" title="">
        
        <ttcol align="center">AVP Values</ttcol>
        <ttcol align="left">Attribute Name</ttcol>
        <ttcol align="left">Reference</ttcol>
        
        <c>0</c>
        <c>NO_METHOD</c>
        <c>This document.</c>
        
        <c>1</c>
        <c>DUAL_STACK</c>
        <c>This document.</c>
        
        <c>2</c>
        <c>DS_LITE</c>
        <c>This document.</c>
        
        <c>3</c>
        <c>PUBLIC_4OVER6</c>
        <c>This document.</c>
        
        <c>4</c>
        <c>LIGHT_WEIGHT_4OVER6</c>
        <c>This document.</c>
        
        <c>5</c>
        <c>MAP_WITH_ENCAPSULATION</c>
        <c>This document.</c>
        
      </texttable>
          
    </section>

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>To come.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <!--  *****BACK MATTER ***** -->

  <back>
    <!-- References split into informative and normative -->

    <references title="Normative References">
      &RFC2119;
      &RFC6333;
      &RFC6733;
      
   <reference anchor="I_D.softwire-unified-cpe">
    <front>
      <title>Unified IPv4-in-IPv6 Softwire CPE (work in progress)</title>
      <author initials="M." surname="Boucadair" fullname="M. Boucadair">
        <organization>France Telecom</organization>
      </author>
      <author initials="I." surname="Farrer" fullname="I. Farrer">
        <organization>Deutsche Telekom</organization>
      </author>
      <date month="January" year="2013"/>
    </front>
  </reference>
  
  <reference anchor="I-D.cui-softwire-b4-translated-ds-lite">
    <front>
      <title>Lightweight 4over6: An Extension to the DS-Lite Architecture (work in progress)</title>
      <author initials="Y." surname="Cui">
        <organization>Tsinghua University</organization>
      </author>
      <author initials="Q." surname="Sun">
        <organization>China Telecom</organization>
      </author>
      <author initials="M." surname="Boucadair">
        <organization>France Telecom</organization>
      </author>
      <author initials="T." surname="Tsou">
        <organization>Huawei Technologies</organization>
      </author>
      <author initials="Y." surname="Lee">
        <organization>Comcast</organization>
      </author>
      <author initials="I." surname="Farrer">
        <organization>Deutsche Telekom AG</organization>
      </author>
      <date month="February" year="2013"/>
    </front>
  </reference>
  
   <reference anchor="I-D.ietf-softwire-map">
    <front>
      <title>Mapping of Address and Port with Encapsulation (MAP) (work in progress)</title>
      <author initials="O." surname="Troan">
        <organization>Cisco Systems</organization>
      </author>
      <author initials="W." surname="Dec">
        <organization>Cisco Systems</organization>
      </author>
      <author initials="X." surname="Li">
        <organization>CERNET Center/Tsinghua University</organization>
      </author>
      <author initials="C." surname="Bao">
        <organization>CERNET Center/Tsinghua University</organization>
      </author>
      <author initials="S." surname="Matsushima">
        <organization>SoftBank Telecom</organization>
      </author>
      <author initials="T." surname="Murakami">
        <organization>IP Infusion</organization>
      </author>
      <date month="February" year="2013"/>
    </front>
  </reference>
  
   <reference anchor="I-D.ietf-softwire-public-4over6">
    <front>
      <title>Public IPv4 over IPv6 Access Network</title>
      <author initials="Y." surname="Cui">
        <organization>Tsinghua University</organization>
      </author>
      <author initials="J." surname="Wu">
        <organization>Tsinghua University</organization>
      </author>
      <author initials="P." surname="Wu">
        <organization>Tsinghua University</organization>
      </author>
      <author initials="O." surname="Vautrin">
        <organization>Juniper Networks</organization>
      </author>
      <author initials="Y." surname="Lee">
        <organization>Comcast</organization>
      </author>
      <date month="October" year="2012"/>
    </front>
  </reference>
 
 </references>

 <references title="Informative References">
    
      &RFC2131;
      &RFC3315;
      &RFC2865;
      
 </references>

  </back>
</rfc>
