<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="no" ?>
<rfc ipr="trust200902" docName="draft-iab-p2p-archs-03.txt"
category='info'>
<front>
    <title abbrev="P2P Architectures">
       Peer-to-peer (P2P) Architectures
    </title>
    <author initials="G." surname="Camarillo"
      fullname="Gonzalo Camarillo" role="editor">
      <organization>Ericsson</organization>
      <address>
	<postal>
          <street>Hirsalantie 11</street>
	  <code>02420</code> 
	  <city>Jorvas</city> 
	  <country>Finland</country>
 	</postal>
	<email>Gonzalo.Camarillo@ericsson.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date year="2009" />
    <area>IAB</area>
    <workgroup>IAB</workgroup>
    <keyword>P2P, decentralized, architecture</keyword>
    <abstract>
    <t>
In this document we provide a survey of P2P (Peer-to-Peer)
systems. The survey includes a definition and several taxonomies of
P2P systems. This survey also includes a description of which types of
applications can be built with P2P technologies and examples of P2P
applications that are currently in use on the Internet. Finally, we
discuss architectural tradeoffs and provide guidelines for deciding
whether or not a P2P architecture would be suitable to meet the
requirements of a given application.
    </t>
    </abstract>
</front>
<middle>

<section title="Introduction">
<t>
P2P (Peer-to-peer) systems have received a great deal of attention in
the last few years. A large number of scientific publications
investigate different aspects of P2P systems, several scientific
conferences explicitly focus on P2P networking, and there is an
Internet Research Task Force (IRTF) Research Group (RG) on P2P systems
(the Peer-to-Peer RG). There are also several commercial and
non-commercial applications that use P2P principles running on the
Internet. Some of these P2P applications are among the most widely
used applications on the Internet at present.
</t>
<t>
However, despite all the above, engineers designing systems or
developing protocol specifications do not have a common understanding
of P2P systems. More alarming is the fact that many people in the
telecom and datacom industries believe that P2P is synonymous with
illegal activity, such as the illegal exchange of content over the
Internet or P2P botnets.
</t>
<t>
The goal of this document is to discuss the tradeoffs involved in
deciding whether a particular application can be best designed and
implemented using a P2P paradigm or a different model (e.g., a
client-server paradigm). The document also aims to provide
architectural guidelines to assist in making such decisions. This
document provides engineers with a high-level understanding of what
defines a P2P system, what types of P2P systems exist, the
characteristics that can be expected from such systems, and what types
of applications can be implemented using P2P technologies. Such
understanding is essential in order to appreciate the tradeoffs
referred to above.  In addition, we stress the importance of the fact
that P2P systems can be used to implement perfectly legitimate
applications and business models by providing several examples
throughout the document.
</t>

</section>


<section title="Definition of a P2P System"
anchor="sec-def">
<t>
In order to discuss P2P systems, we first need a working definition of
a P2P system. In this section, we provide such a definition. All
discussions in this document apply to systems that comply with that
definition. In addition to providing examples of P2P systems, we
provide a few examples of systems that comply only partially with the
definition and, thus, cannot be strictly considered P2P systems. Since
these systems are not fully P2P compliant, some of the discussions in
this document may apply to them while others may not. We have chosen
to include those examples anyway to stress the fact that P2P and
centralized architectures are not completely disjoint
alternatives. There are many examples of systems that fall, for
instance, somewhere in between a pure P2P system and a centralized
one.
</t>
<t>
P2P is a term used in many contexts, sometimes with slightly different
meanings. It is possible to find several alternative definitions,
which are not all fully equivalent, in the existing scientific
literature. If we include other material (e.g., marketing material) in
our search for a definition on P2P, the diversity of definitions is
even higher.
</t>
<t>
The issue is that there is no clear border between a P2P paradigm and
other supposedly opposite paradigms such as client-server <xref
target="Milojicic2002"/>. In the extremes, some architectures are
clearly P2P while others are clearly client-server. However, there are
architectures that can be considered to be either or both, depending
on the definition for P2P being considered. Consequently, it is
important to understand what is common to all definitions of P2P and
what are the non-common traits some authors include in their own
definitions.
</t>
<t>
We consider a system to be P2P if the elements that form the system
share their resources in order to provide the service the system has
been designed to provide. The elements in the system both provide
services to other elements and request services from other elements.
</t>
<t>
In principle, all the elements in the system should meet the previous
criteria for the system to be considered P2P. However, in practice, a
system can have a few exceptions (i.e., a few nodes that do not meet
the criteria) and still be considered P2P. For example, a P2P system
can still be considered P2P even if it has a centralized enrollment
server. On the other hand, some systems divide endpoints between peers
and clients. Peers both request and provide services while clients
generally only request services. A system where most endpoints behaved
as clients could not strictly be considered P2P.
</t>
<t>
Although most definitions do not state it explicitly, many implicitly
assume that for a system to be P2P, its nodes need to be involved in
transactions that are related to services that do not directly benefit
the nodes.
</t>
<t>
Some authors add that the elements that form the P2P system, which
unsurprisingly are called peers, should be able to communicate
directly between them without passing intermediaries <xref
target="Schollmeier2001"/>. Other authors add that the system should be
self organizing and have decentralized control <xref
target="Roussopoulus2004"/>.
</t>
<t>
Note that the previous definitions are given within the context of a
single individual service. A complex service can be made up of several
individual services. Some of these individual services can consist of
P2P services and some of them can consist of client-server
services. For example, a file sharing client may include a P2P client
to perform the actual file sharing and a web browser to access
additional information on a centralized web server. Additionally,
there are architectures where a client-server system can serve as a
fall back for a service normally provided by a P2P system, or vice
versa.
</t>
<t>
Providing a service typically involves processing or storing
data. According to our definition, in a P2P system, peers share their
processing and storage capacity (i.e., their hardware and software
resources) so that the system can provide a service. For example, if
the service to be provided is a file distribution service, different
peers within the system will store different files. When a given peer
wants to get a particular file, the peer will first discover which
peer or peers have that file and then obtain the file from those
peers.
</t>
<t>
The definition for P2P provides us with a criterion to decide whether
or not a system is P2P. As examples, in the following sections we
apply the definition to the DNS, SIP, P2PSIP, and BitTorrent and
discuss which of these systems are P2P.
</t>

<section title="Applying the P2P Definition to the DNS"
anchor="sec-def-dns">
<t>
The DNS is a hierarchical distributed system that has sometimes been
classified as a hierarchical client-server system and sometimes as a
P2P system <xref target="Milojicic2002"/>.  According to our
definition, the DNS is not a P2P system because DNS resolvers are
service requesters but not service providers. The elements in a system
need to be both service requesters and service providers for the
system to be considered P2P.
</t>
</section>

<section title="Applying the P2P Definition to SIP"
anchor="sec-def-sip">
<t>
SIP <xref target="RFC3261"/> is a rendezvous protocol that allows a
user to locate a remote user and establish a communication session
with that remote user. Once the remote user is located, sessions are
established in a similar way in all SIP systems; directly between the
nodes involved in the session. However, the rendezvous function can be
implemented in different ways: the traditional SIP way and the P2P
way. This section discusses the former. <xref
target="sec-def-p2psip"/> discusses the latter.
</t>
<t>
In traditional SIP, a central server is typically responsible for a
DNS domain. User agents in the domain register with the server. This
way, when a user agent wants to communicate with a remote user agent
in the same domain, the user agent consults the server, which returns
the contact information of the remote user agent. Session
establishment occurs directly between the user agents, without the
involvement of the server.
</t>
<t>
Inter-domain communications in SIP are implemented using server
federations. The servers responsible for each domain form a federation
in which they can communicate with each other. This way, when a user
agent wants to communicate with a remote user agent in a different
domain, the user agent consults its local server, which in turn
consults the server responsible for the remote user agent's domain.
</t>
<t>
SIP user agents act as both clients and servers. A given user agent
can act as a client in a particular transaction and as a server in a
subsequent transaction. However, traditional SIP cannot be considered
a P2P system because user agents only share their resources for their
own benefit. That is, a given user agent is only involved in
transactions related to a service that benefits (somehow) the user
agent itself. For example, any given user agent is only involved in
SIP INVITE transactions (which are used to establish sessions)
intended to establish sessions that involve the user agent. For a
system to be P2P, its nodes need to be involved in transactions that
benefit others. That is, transactions that are related to services
that do not benefit directly the nodes.
</t>
</section>


<section title="Applying the P2P Definition to P2PSIP"
anchor="sec-def-p2psip">
<t>
In addition to the traditional way of using SIP, SIP can also be used
in a way that is generally referred to as P2PSIP (P2PSIP is the name
of the IETF working group developing the technology). In P2PSIP, user
agents do not register their contact information with a central
server. Instead, they register it with an overlay formed by the user
agents in the system.  This way, when a user agent wants to
communicate with a remote user agent, the user agent consults the
overlay, which returns the contact information of the remote user
agent. Session establishment occurs, as usual, directly between the
user agents. P2PSIP is a P2P system because nodes share their
resources by storing data that is not related to them (i.e., contact
information of different user agents) and are involved in transactions
that are related to services that do not revert directly to the nodes
themselves (e.g., the rendezvous of two remote user agents).
</t>
</section>


<section title="Applying the P2P Definition to BitTorrent"
anchor="sec-def-bittorrent">
<t>
BitTorrent <xref target="BitTorrent"/> is a protocol used to
distribute files. The group of endpoints involved in the distribution
of a particular file is called a swarm. The file is divided into
several pieces. An endpoint interested in the file needs to download
all the pieces of the file from other endpoints in the
swarm. Endpoints downloading pieces of the file also upload pieces
they already have to other endpoints in the swarm. An endpoint that
both downloads (because it does not have the complete file yet) and
uploads pieces is called a leecher (note that this definition is
counterintuitive because, in other contexts, a leecher normally means
someone that takes but does not give). When an endpoint has the whole
file (i.e., it has all the pieces of the file) it does not need to
download any pieces any longer. Therefore, it only uploads pieces to
other endpoints. Such an endpoint is called a seeder.
</t>
<t>
BitTorrent systems are P2P systems because endpoints request services
from other endpoints (i.e., download pieces from other endpoints) and
provide services to other endpoints (i.e., upload pieces to other
endpoints). Note, however, that a particular swarm where most
endpoints were infrastructure nodes that had the complete file from
the beginning and, thus, acted all the time as seeders could not be
strictly considered a P2P system because most endpoints would only be
providing services, not requesting them.
</t>
</section>

</section>


<section title="Functions in a P2P system"
anchor="sec-functions">
<t>
P2P systems include several functions. The following functions are
independent of the service provided by the P2P system. They handle how
peers connect to the system.
</t>
<t>
<list style="symbols">
<t>
Enrollment function: nodes joining a P2P system need to obtain valid
credentials to join the system. The enrollment function handles node
authentication and authorization.
</t>
<t>
Peer discovery function: in order to join a P2P system (i.e., to
become a peer), a node needs to establish a connection with one or
more peers that are already part of the system. The peer discovery
function allows nodes to discover peers in the system in order to
connect to them.
</t>
</list>
</t>
<t>
The functions above are provided in a centralized way in some P2P
systems (e.g., through a central enrollment server and a central peer
discovery server, which is sometimes called a bootstrap
server). Taxonomies for P2P systems, which will be discussed in <xref
target="sec-tax-system"/>, do not consider these functions when
classifying P2P systems. Instead, they classify P2P systems based on
how the following set of functions are implemented.
</t>
<t>
The following functions depend on the service provided by the P2P
system. That is, not all P2P systems implement all functions. For
example, a P2P system used only for storing data may not implement the
computing function. In another example, a P2P system used only for
computing may not implement the data storage function. Also, some of
these functions are implemented in a centralized way in some P2P
systems.
</t>
<t>
<list style="symbols">
<t>
Data indexing function: it deals with indexing the data stored in
the system.
</t>
<t>
Data storage function: it deals with storing and retrieving data from
the system.
</t>
<t>
Computation function: it deals with the computing performed by the
system. Such computing can be related to, among other things, data
processing or real-time media processing.
</t>
<t>
Message transport function: it deals with message exchanges between
peers. Depending on how this function is implemented, peers can
exchange protocol messages through a central server, directly between
them, or through peers that provide overlay routing.
</t>
</list>
</t>
<t>
Depending on the service being provided, some of the functions above
may not be needed. <xref target="sec-types-app"/> discusses different
types of P2P applications, which implement different services.
</t>
</section>

<section title="Taxonomies for P2P Systems"
anchor="sec-tax-system">
<t>
Taxonomies classify elements into groups so that they can be studied
more easily. People studying similar elements can focus on common
problem sets. Taxonomies also provide common terminology useful when
discussing issues related to individual elements and groups of
elements within a given taxonomy. In this section, we provide a few
taxonomies for P2P systems in order to facilitate their study and to
present such a common terminology.
</t>
<t>
Given that different authors cannot seem to agree on a single common
definition for P2P, it should not come as a surprise the fact that
there are also many different taxonomies of P2P systems. While
classifying P2P systems according to different traits is something
normal, the fact that different authors use the same term to indicate
different things (e.g., first and second generation P2P systems mean
different things for different authors) sometimes confuses readers.
</t>
<t>
Arguably, the most useful classification of P2P systems has to do with
the way data is indexed. That is, how the data indexing function is
implemented. A P2P index can be centralized, local, or distributed
<xref target="RFC4981"/>. With a centralized index, a central server
keeps references to the data in all peers. With a local index, each
peer only keeps references to its own data. With a distributed index,
references to data reside at several nodes. Napster, early versions of
Gnutella (up to version 0.4), and Distributed Hash Table (DHT)-based
systems are examples of centralized, local, and distributed indexes,
respectively.
</t>
<t>
Indexes can also be classified into semantic and semantic-free. A
semantic index can capture relationships between documents and their
metadata whereas a semantic-free index cannot <xref
target="RFC4981"/>. While semantic indexes allow for richer searches,
they sometimes (depending on their implementation) fail to find the
data even if the data is actually in the system.
</t>
<t>
Some authors classify P2P systems by their level of
decentralization. Hybrid P2P systems need a central entity to provide
their services while pure P2P systems can continue to provide their
services even if any single peer is removed from the system <xref
target="Schollmeier2001"/>. According to this definition, P2P systems
with a centralized index are hybrid P2P systems while systems with
local and distributed indexes are pure P2P systems.
</t>
<t>
Still, some authors classify pure P2P systems by the level of
structure they show <xref target="Alima2005"/>. In unstructured
systems, peers join the system by connecting themselves to any other
existing peers. In structured systems, peers join the system by
connecting themselves to well-defined peers based on their logical
identifiers. The distinction between early unstructured systems (e.g.,
early versions of Gnutella), which used local indexes and had no
structure at all, and structured systems (e.g., DHT-based systems),
which used distributed indexes and had a well-defined structure, was
fairly clear. However, unstructured systems have evolved and now show
a certain level of structure (e.g., some systems have special nodes
with more functionality) and use distributed indexes. Therefore, the
border between unstructured and structured is somewhat blurry.
</t>
<t>
Some authors refer to different generations of P2P systems. For some,
the first, second, and third generations consist of P2P systems using
centralized indexes, flooding-based searches (i.e., using local
indexes), and DHTs (i.e., DHT-based distributed indexes), respectively
<xref target="Foster2003"/>. Other authors consider that second
generation systems can also have non-DHT-based distributed indexes
<xref target="Zhang2006"/>. Yet for other authors, the first and
second generations consist of P2P systems using unstructured
(typically using flooding-based searched) and structured (e.g.,
DHT-based) routing, respectively <xref target="RFC4981"/>. Talking
about generations of P2P systems in a technical context is not useful
(as stated previously, it is more useful to classify systems based on
how they index data) because different generations are defined in
different ways depending on the author and because talking about
generations gives the impression that later generations are better
than earlier ones. Depending on the application to be implemented, a
P2P system of an earlier generation may meet the application's
requirements in a better way than a system of a later generation.
</t>
<t>
As discussed in <xref target="sec-functions"/>, the previous
taxonomies do not consider the enrollment and the peer discovery
functions. For example, a pure P2P system would still be considered
pure even if it had centralized enrollment and peer discovery servers.
</t>
</section>

<section title="P2P Applications"
anchor="sec-types-app">
<t>
P2P applications developed so far can be classified into the following
domains <xref target="Pourebrahimi2005"/> <xref
target="Milojicic2002"/>: content distribution, distributed computing,
collaboration, and platforms.
</t>

<section title="Content Distribution"
anchor="sec-tax-app-file">
<t>
When most people think of P2P, they think of file sharing. Moreover,
they think of illegal file sharing where users exchange material
(e.g., songs, movies, and software in digital format) they are not
legally authorized to distribute. However, despite people's
perception, P2P file sharing systems are not intrinsically illegal.
</t>
<t>
P2P file sharing applications provide one out of many means to store
and distribute content on the Internet. HTTP <xref target="RFC2616"/>
and FTP <xref target="RFC0959"/> servers are examples of other content
distribution mechanisms. People would not claim that HTTP is an
illegal mechanism just because a number of users upload material that
cannot be legally distributed to an HTTP server where other users can
download it. The same way, it is misleading to claim that P2P is
illegal just because some users use it for illegal purposes.
</t>
<t>
P2P content distribution systems are used to implement legitimate
applications and business models that take advantage of the
characteristics of these P2P systems. Examples of legitimate uses of
these systems include the distribution of pre-recorded TV programs
<xref target="Rodriguez2005"/>, Linux distributions <xref
target="Rodriguez2005"/>, game updates <xref target="WoW"/>, and live
TV <xref target="Peltotalo2008"/> <xref target="Octoshape"/> by
parties legally authorized to distribute that content (e.g., the
content owner).
</t>
<t>
The main advantage of P2P content distribution systems is their
scalability. In general, the more popular the content handled, the
more scalable the P2P system is. The peer that has the original
content (i.e., the owner of a file or the source of an audio or video
stream) distributes it to a fraction of the peers interested in the
content and these peers in turn distribute it to other peers also
interested in the content. Note that, in general, there is no
requirement for peers distributing content to be able to access it
(e.g., the content may be encrypted so that peers without the
decryption key are content distributors but not content
consumers). Peers can distribute content to other peers in different
ways. For example, they can distribute the whole content, pieces of
the content (i.e., swarming), or linear combinations of pieces of
content <xref target="Gkantsidis2005"/>. In any case, the end result
is that the peer with the original content does not need to distribute
the whole content to all the peers interested in it, as it would be
the case when using a centralized server. Therefore, the capacity of
the system is not limited by the processing capacity and the bandwidth
of the peer with the original content and, thus, the quality of the
whole service increases.
</t>
<t>
An important area that determines the characteristics of a P2P
distribution system is its peer selection process. Interestingly, the
different parties involved in the distribution have different views on
how peers should be selected. Users are interested in connecting to
peers that have the content they want and also have high bandwidth and
processing capacity, and low latency so that transfers are faster. The
Content Delivery Network (CDN) operator wants peers to connect first
to the peers who have the rarest pieces of the content being
distributed in order to improve the reliability of the system (in case
those peers with the rare pieces of content leave the system). Network
operators prefer peers to perform local transfers within their network
so that their peering and transit agreements are not negatively
affected (i.e., by downloading content from a remote network despite
of the content being available locally). Sometimes, all these
requirements can be met at the same time (e.g., a peer with a rare
piece of content has high bandwidth and processing capacity and is in
the local network). However, other times the system can just try and
reach acceptable tradeoffs when selecting peers. These issues were the
subject of the IETF P2P Infrastructure (P2PI) workshop held in 2008.
</t>
<t>
Network operators also find that, depending on the dimensioning of
their networks (e.g., where the bottlenecks are), the different
traffic patterns generated by P2P or centralized CDNs can be more or
less easily accommodated by the network <xref target="Huang2007"/>.
</t>
<t>
An example of a sensor network based on P2P content distribution and
Delay-tolerant Networking (DTL) is ZebraNet <xref
target="Juang2002"/>. ZebraNet is a network used to track Zebras in
the wild. Each zebra carries a tracking collar that gathers data about
the zebra (e.g., its position) at different times. Mobile stations
communicate wirelessly with the collars in order to gather and
consolidate data from different zebras. Since not all the zebras get
close enough to a mobile station for their collars to be able to
communicate with the station, the collars communicate among them
exchanging the data they have gathered. In this way, a given collar
provides the mobile station with data from different zebras, some of
which may never get close enough to the mobile station. P2P networks
are especially useful in situations where it is impossible to deploy a
communication infrastructure (e.g., due to national park regulations
or potential vandalism) such as in the previous example or when
tracking reindeers in Lapland <xref target="SNC"/> (this project has
focused on DTNs more than on P2P so far but some of its main
constraints are similar to the ones in ZebraNet). Note however that
sensor networks such as ZebraNet cannot be strictly considered P2P
because the only node issuing service requests (i.e., the only node
interested in receiving data) is a central node (i.e., the mobile
station).
</t>

</section>


<section title="Distributed Computing"
anchor="sec-tax-app-comp">
<t>
In P2P distributed computing, each task is divided into independent
subtasks that can be completed in parallel (i.e., no inter-task
communication) and delivered to a peer. The peer completes the subtask
using its resources and returns the result. When all the subtasks are
completed, their results are combined to obtain the result of the
original task.
</t>
<t>
Peers in P2P distributed computing systems are typically distributed
geographically and are connected among them through wide-area
networks. Conversely, in cluster computing, nodes in a cluster are
typically physically close to each other (often in the same room) and
have excellent communication capabilities among them. Consequently,
computer clusters can divide tasks into subtasks that are not
completely independent from one another and that cannot be completed
in parallel. The excellent communication capabilities among the nodes
in the cluster make it possible to synchronize the completion of such
tasks. Since computers in a cluster are so tightly integrated, cluster
computing techniques are not typically considered P2P networking.
</t>
<t>
The main advantage of P2P distributed computing systems is that a
number of regular computers can deliver the performance of a much more
powerful (and typically expensive) computer. Nevertheless, at present
P2P distributed computing can only be applied to tasks that can be
divided into independent subtasks that can be completed in
parallel. Tasks that do not show this characteristic are better
performed by a single powerful computer.
</t>
<t>
Note that even though distributed computing in general can be
considered P2P (which is why we have included it in this section as an
example of a P2P application), most current systems whose main focus
is distributed computing do not fully comply with the definition for
P2P provided in <xref target="sec-def"/>. The reason is that, in those
systems, service requests are typically generated only by a central
node. That is, most nodes do not generate service requests (i.e.,
create tasks). This is why Grid computing <xref target="Foster1999"/>
cannot be strictly considered P2P <xref target="Lua2005"/>. Another
well-known example that cannot strictly be considered P2P either is
SETI@home (Search for Extra-Terrestrial Intelligence) <xref
target="Seti"/>, where the resources of many computers are used to
analyze radio telescope data. MapReduce <xref target="Dean2004"/>, a
programming model for processing large data sets cannot strictly be
considered P2P either for the same reason. On the other hand, a number
of collaboration applications implement distributed computing
functions in a P2P way (see <xref
target="sec-tax-app-collaboration"/>).
</t>
<t>
Another form of distributed computing that cannot be strictly
considered P2P (despite its name) are P2P botnets <xref
target="Grizzard2007"/>. In P2P botnets, service requests, which
usually consist of generating spam or launching Distributed Denial of
Service (DDoS) attacks, are typically generated by a central node (or
a few central nodes). That is why they cannot be strictly considered
P2P. An example of this type of P2P botnet that propagates using a
DHT-based overlay is the Storm botnet <xref target="Kanich2008"/>. In
addition to their distributed propagation techniques, some P2P botnets
also use a distributed command and control channel, which makes it
more difficult to combat them than traditional botnets using
centralized channels <xref target="Cooke2005"/>. DHT-based overlays
can also be used to support the configuration of different types of
radio access networks <xref target="Oechsner2006"/>.
</t>


</section>


<section title="Collaboration"
anchor="sec-tax-app-collaboration">
<t>
P2P collaboration applications include communication applications such
as Voice over IP (VoIP) and Instant Messaging (IM) applications. <xref
target="sec-def-p2psip"/> included discussions on P2PSIP systems,
which are an example of a standard-based P2P collaboration
application. There are also proprietary P2P collaboration applications
on the Internet <xref target="Skype"/>. Collaboration applications
typically provide rendezvous, NAT traversal, and a set of
media-related functions (e.g., media mixing or media
transcoding). Note that some of these functions (e.g., media
transcoding) are, effectively, a form of distributed computing.
</t>
<t>
P2P rendezvous systems are especially useful in situations where there
is no infrastructure. A few people with no Internet connectivity
setting up an ad-hoc system to exchange documents or the members of a
recovery team communicating among themselves in a disaster area are
examples of such situations. P2PSIP is sometimes referred to as
infrastructureless SIP to distinguish it from traditional SIP, which
relies on a rendezvous server infrastructure.
</t>
</section>


<section title="Platforms"
anchor="sec-tax-app-platforms">
<t>
P2P platforms can be used to build applications on top of them. They
provide functionality applications on top of them can use. An example
of such a platform is JXTA <xref target="Gong2001"/>. JXTA provides
peer discovery, grouping of peers, and communications between
peers. The goal with these types of P2P platforms is that they become
the preferred environment for application developers. They take
advantage of the good scalability properties of P2P systems.
</t>
</section>



</section>

<section title="Architectural Tradeoffs and Guidance"
anchor="sec-arch">
<t>
In this document, we have provided a brief overview of P2P
technologies. In order to dispel the notion that P2P technologies can
only be used for illegal purposes, we have discussed a number of
perfectly legitimate applications that have been implemented using
P2P. Examples of these applications include video conferencing
applications <xref target="Skype"/>, the distribution of pre-recorded
TV programs <xref target="Rodriguez2005"/>, Linux distributions <xref
target="Rodriguez2005"/>, game updates <xref target="WoW"/>, and live
TV <xref target="Peltotalo2008"/> <xref target="Octoshape"/> by
parties legally authorized to distribute that content.
</t>
<t>
When deciding whether or not to use a P2P architecture to implement a
given application, it is important to consider the general
characteristics of P2P systems and evaluate them against the
application's requirements. It is not possible to provide any
definitive rule to decide whether or not a particular application
would be implemented best using P2P. Instead, we discuss a set of
tradeoffs to be considered when making architectural decisions and
provide guidance on which types of requirements are better met by a
P2P architecture (security-related aspects are discussed in <xref
target="sec-security"/>). Ultimately, applications' operational
requirements need to be analyzed on a case-by-case basis in order to
decide the most suitable architecture.
</t>
<t>
P2P systems are a good option when there is no existing infrastructure
and deploying it is difficult for some reason. Ad-hoc systems are
usually good candidates to use P2P architectures. Disaster areas where
existing infrastructures have been destroyed or rendered unusable can
also benefit from P2P systems.
</t>
<t>
One of the main features of P2P systems is their scalability. Since
the system can leverage the processing and storage capacity of all the
peers in the system, increases in the system's load are tackled by
having the peers use more of their processing or storage
capacity. Adding new peers generally increases the system's load but
also increases the system's processing and storage capacity. That is,
there is no typically need to update any central servers to be able to
deal with more users or more load <xref
target="Leibniz2007"/>. Adaptive P2P systems tune themselves in order
to operate in the best possible mode when conditions such as number of
peers or churn rate change <xref target="Mahajan2003"/>. In any case,
at present, maintaining a running DHT requires nontrivial operational
efforts <xref target="Rhea2005"/>.
</t>
<t>
Robustness and reliability are important features in many systems. For
many applications to be useful, it is essential that they are
dependable <xref target="RFC4981"/>. While there are many techniques
to make centralized servers highly available, peers in a P2P system
are not generally expected to be highly available (of course, it is
also possible to build a more expensive P2P system with only highly
available peers). P2P systems are designed to cope with peers leaving
the system ungracefully (e.g., by crashing). P2P systems use
techniques such as data replication and redundant routing table
entries to improve the system's reliability. This way, if a peer
crashes, the data it stored is not lost and can still be found in the
system.
</t>
<t>
The performance of a P2P system when compared to a server-based system
depends on many factors (e.g., the dimensioning of the server-based
system). One of the most important factors is the type of task to be
performed. As we discussed in <xref target="sec-tax-app-comp"/>, if
the task that needs to be computed can be divided into independent
subtasks that can be completed in parallel, a P2P
distributed-computing system made up of regular computers may be able
to perform better than even a super computer. If the task at hand
consists of completing database queries, a well-dimensioned
centralized database may be faster than a DHT.
</t>
<t>
The performance of a P2P system can be negatively affected by a lack
of cooperation between the peers in the system. It is important to
have incentives in place in order to minimize the number of free
riders in the system. Incentive systems generally aim to take the P2P
system to optimal levels of cooperation <xref target="Feldman2004"/>.
</t>
<t>
There are tradeoffs between the scalability, robustness, and
performance of a particular P2P system that can be influenced through
the configuration of the system. For example, a P2P database system
where each peer stored all the information in the system would be
robust and have a high performance (i.e., queries would be completed
quickly) but would not be efficient or scalable. If the system needed
to grow, it could be configured so that each node stored only a part
of the information of the whole system in order to increase its
efficiency and scalability at the expense of its robustness and
performance.
</t>
<t>
Energy consumption is another important property of a system. Even
though the overall consumption of a client-server system is generally
lower than that of a P2P system providing the same service, P2P
systems avoid central servers (e.g., server farms) that can
potentially concentrate the consumption of high amounts of energy in a
single geographical location. When the nodes in a system need to be up
and running all the time anyway, it is possible to use those nodes to
perform tasks in a P2P way. However, using battery-powered devices as
peers in a P2P system presents some challenges because a peer
typically consumes more energy than a client in a client-server
architecture where they can go into sleep mode more often <xref
target="Kelenyi2008"/>. Energy-aware P2P protocols may be the solution
to these challenges <xref target="Gurun2006"/>.
</t>
<t>
This section has discussed a set of important system properties and
compared P2P and centralized systems with respect to those
properties. However, the most important factor to take into
consideration is often cost. Both capital and operating costs need to
be taken into account when evaluating the scalability, reliability,
and performance of a system. If updating a server so that it can
tackle more load is inexpensive, a server-based architecture may be
the best option. If a highly-available server is expensive, a P2P
system may be the best choice. With respect to operating costs, as
previously stated, at present, maintaining a running DHT requires
nontrivial operational efforts <xref target="Rhea2005"/>.
</t>
<t>
In short, even though understanding the general properties of P2P and
server-based systems is important, deciding which architecture fits
best a particular application involves obtaining detailed information
about the application and its context. In most scenarios, there are no
easy rules that tell us when to use which architecture.
</t>
</section>


<section title="Security Considerations" anchor="sec-security">
<t>
Security is an important issue that needs to be considered when
choosing an architecture to design a system. The first issue that
needs to be considered is to which extent the nodes in the system can
be trusted. If all the nodes in the system are fully trusted (e.g.,
all the nodes are under the full control of the operator of the system
and will never act in a malicious or otherwise incorrect way), a P2P
architecture can achieve a high level of security. However, if nodes
are not fully trusted and can be expected to behave in malicious ways
(e.g., launching active attacks), providing an acceptable level of
security in a P2P environment becomes significantly more challenging
than in a non-P2P environment because of its distributed ownership,
and lack of centralized control and global knowledge <xref
target="Mondal2006"/>. Ultimately, the level of security provided by a
P2P system largely depends on the proportion of its nodes that behave
maliciously. Providing an acceptable level of security in a P2P system
with a large number of malicious nodes can easily become impossible.
</t>
<t>
P2P systems can be used by attackers to harvest IP addresses in
use. Attackers can passively obtain valid IP addresses of potential
victims without performing active scans because a given peer is
typically connected to multiple peers. In addition to being passive,
this attack is much more efficient than performing scans when the
address space to be scanned is large and sparsely populated (e.g., the
current IPv6 address space). Additionally, in many cases there is a
high correlation between a particular application and a particular
operating system. In this way, an attacker can harvest IP addresses
suitable to launch attacks that exploit vulnerabilities that are
specific to a given operating system.
</t>
<t>
Central elements in centralized architectures become an obvious target
for attacks. P2P systems minimize the amount of central elements and,
thus, are more resilient against attacks targeted only at a few
elements.
</t>
<t>
When designing a P2P system, it is important to consider a number of
threats that are specific to P2P systems. Additionally, more general
threats that apply to other architectures as well are sometimes bigger
in a P2P environment. P2P-specific threats mainly focus on the data
storage functions and the routing of P2P systems.
</t>
<t>
In a P2P system, messages (e.g., service requests) between two given
peers generally traverse a set of intermediate peers that help route
messages between the two peers. Those intermediate peers can attempt
to launch on-path attacks they would not be able to launch if they
were not on the path between the two given peers. An attacker can
attempt to choose a logical location in the P2P overlay that allows it
to launch on-path attacks against a particular victim or a set of
victims. The Sybil <xref target="Douceur2002"/> attack is an example
of such an attack. The attacker chooses its overlay identifier so that
it allows the attacker to launch future attacks. This type of attack
can be mitigated by controlling how peers obtain their identifiers
(e.g., by having a central authority).
</t>
<t>
A trivial passive attack by peers routing messages consists of trying
to access the contents of those messages. Encrypting message parts
that are not required for routing is an obvious defence against this
type of attack.
</t>
<t>
An attacker can create a message and claim that it was actually
created by another peer. The attacker can even take a legitimate
message as a base and modify it to launch the attack. Peer and message
authentication techniques can be used to avoid this type of attack.
</t>
<t>
Attackers can attempt to launch a set of attacks against the storage
function of the P2P system. The following are generic (i.e., non-P2P
specific) attacks. Even if they are generic attacks, the way to avoid
or mitigate them in a P2P system can be more challenging than in other
architectures.
</t>
<t>
An attacker can attempt to store too much data in the system. A quota
system that can be enforced can be used to mitigate this attack.
</t>
<t>
Unauthorized peers can attempt to perform operations on data
objects. Peer authorization in conjunction with peer authentication
avoids unauthorized operations.
</t>
<t>
A peer can return forged data objects claiming they are
legitimate. Data object authentication prevents this attack. However,
a peer can return a previous version of a data object and claim it is
the current version. The use of lifetimes can mitigate this type of
attack.
</t>
<t>
The following are P2P-specific attacks against the data storage
function of a P2P system. An attacker can refuse to store a particular
data object. An attacker can also claim a particular data object does
not exist even if another peer created it and stored it on the
attacker. These DoS (Denial of Service) attacks can be mitigated by
using data replication techniques and performing multiple, typically
parallel, searches.
</t>
<t>
Attackers can attempt to launch a set of attacks against the routing
of the P2P system. An attacker can attempt to modify the routing of
the system in order to be able to launch on-path attacks. Attackers
can use forged routing maintenance messages for this purpose. The
Eclipse attack <xref target="Singh2006"/> is an example of such an
attack. Enforcing structural constraints or enforcing node degree
bounds can mitigate this type of attack.
</t>
<t>
It is possible to launch DoS attacks by modifying or dropping routing
maintenance messages or by creating forged ones. Having nodes get
routing tables from multiple peers can help mitigate this type of
attack.
</t>
<t>
Attackers can launch a DoS attack by creating churn. By leaving and
joining a P2P overlay rapidly many times, a set of attackers can
create large amounts of maintenance traffic and make the routing
structure of the overlay unstable. Limiting the amount of churn per
node is a possible defence against this attack.
</t>


</section>

<section title="IANA Considerations" anchor="sec-iana">
<t>
There are no IANA actions associated with this document.
</t>
</section>

<section title="Acknowledgements" anchor="sec-acks">
<t>
Jouni Maenpaa and Jani Hautakorpi helped with the literature
review. Henning Schulzrinne provided useful ideas on how to define P2P
systems. Bruce Lowekamp, Dan Wing, Dan York, Enrico Marocco, Cullen
Jennings, and Frank Uwe Andersen provided useful comments on this
document. Loa Andersson, Aaron Falk, Barry Leiba, Kurtis Lindqvist,
Dow Street, and Lixia Zhang participated in the IAB discussions on
this document.
</t>
</section>

<section title="IAB Members at the Time of this Writing" anchor="sec-members">
<t>
<artwork>
Marcelo Bagnulo
Gonzalo Camarillo
Stuart Cheshire
Vijay Gill
Russ Housley
John Klensin
Olaf Kolkman
Gregory Lebovitz
Andrew Malis
Danny McPherson
David Oran
Jon Peterson
Dave Thaler 	
</artwork>
</t>
</section>

</middle>
<back>

<section title="Historical Background on Distributed Architectures"
anchor="sec-history">
<t>
In this appendix, we briefly provide historical background on
distributed architectures. Distributed architectures are relevant to
P2P because P2P architectures are a type of distributed
architecture. That is, a distributed architecture is considered P2P if
it meets a set of requirements, which are discussed in <xref
target="sec-def"/>.
</t>
<t>
In centralized architectures (e.g., client-server architectures), a
central server (or very few central servers) undertakes most of the
system's processing and storage. Conversely, decentralized
architectures contain no (or very few) centralized elements.
</t>
<t>
The increasing spread of packet-switched network technologies in the
1970s made it possible to develop operational distributed computer
systems <xref target="Farber1972"/>. Distributed computer systems
received a lot of attention within the research community. Research
focused on distributing the different parts of a computer system, such
as its operating system <xref target="Tanenbaum1981"/> or its
databases <xref target="Gray1983"/>. The idea was to hide from the
user the fact that the system was distributed. That is, the user did
not have to worry or even be aware of the fact that his or her files
were stored in different computers or the fact that his or her tasks
were processed also in a distributed way. Actions such as file
transfers and task allocations were taken care of by the system in an
automated fashion and were transparent to the user.
</t>
<t>
In the middle of the 1980s, building distributed computer systems
using general-purpose off-the-shelf hardware and software was believed
to be not much harder than building large centralized applications
<xref target="Gray1986A"/>. It was understood that distributed systems
had both advantages and disadvantages when compared to centralized
systems. Choosing which type of system to use for a particular
application was a tradeoff that depended on the characteristics and
requirements of the application <xref target="Gray1986B"/>.
</t>
<t>
The client-server paradigm, where a client makes a request to a server
that processes the request and returns the result to the client, was
and is used by many Internet applications. In fact, client-server
architectures were so ubiquitous on the Internet that, unfortunately,
the Internet itself evolved as if the majority of the endpoints on the
Internet were only interested in applications following the
client-server model. With the appearance of Network Address
Translators (NATs) and stateful firewalls, most Internet endpoints
lost the ability to receive connections from remote endpoints unless
they first initiated a connection towards those nodes. While NATs were
designed not to disrupt client-server applications, distributed
applications that relied on nodes receiving connections were
disrupted. In a network full of NATs, these types of distributed
applications could only be run among nodes with public IP
addresses. Of course, most users did not like applications that only
worked some of the time (i.e., when their endpoint happened to have a
public IP address). Therefore, the loss of global connectivity caused
by NATs was one of the reasons why applications that did not follow
the client-server paradigm (e.g., P2P applications) took a relatively
long time to be widely deployed on the public Internet.
</t>
<t>
The design of NAT traversal mechanisms has made it possible to deploy
all types of distributed applications over a network without global
connectivity. While the first NAT traversal mechanisms used by P2P
applications were proprietary <xref target="RFC5128"/>, nowadays there
are standard NAT traversal mechanisms such as Interactive Connectivity
Establishment (ICE) <xref target="I-D.ietf-mmusic-ice"/>. ICE makes it
possible for endpoints to establish connections among them in the
presence of NATs. The recovery of global connectivity among Internet
endpoints has made it possible to deploy many P2P applications on the
public Internet (unfortunately, the fact that global connectivity is
not supported natively at the network layer makes it necessary for
applications to deal with NATs, which can result in highly complex
systems). Some of these P2P applications have been very successful and
are currently used by a large number of users.
</t>
<t>
Another factor that made it possible to deploy distributed
applications was the continuous significant advances in terms of
processing power and storage capacity of personal computers and
networked devices. Eventually, most endpoints on the Internet had
capabilities that previously were exclusively within the reach of
high-end servers. The natural next step was to design distributed
applications that took advantage of all that distributed available
capacity.
</t>

</section>

    <references title="Informative References">

      <reference anchor='Alima2005'>
        <front>
            <title>A Framework for Structured Peer-to-peer Overlay Networks</title>
            <author initials='L.O.' surname='Alima'
                    fullname='L.O. Alima'>
                <organization/>
            </author>
            <author initials='A.' surname='Ghodsi'
                    fullname='A. Ghodsi'>
                <organization/>
            </author>
            <author initials='S.' surname='Haridi'
                    fullname='S. Haridi'>
                <organization/>
            </author>

            <date year='2005' />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name='Global Computing, vol 3267, Lecture Notes in
			  Computer Science: Springer Berlin /
			  Heidelberg, pp. 223-249' value='' />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor='BitTorrent'>
        <front>
            <title>The BitTorrent Protocol Specification Version 11031</title>
            <author initials='B.' surname='Cohen'
                    fullname='Bram Cohen'>
                <organization/>
            </author>
            <date month='February' year='2008' />
        </front>
      </reference>


      <reference anchor='Cooke2005'>
        <front>
            <title>The Zombie roundup: understanding, detecting, and
	    disrupting botnets</title>
            <author initials='E.' surname='Cooke'
                    fullname='Evan Cooke'>
                <organization/>
            </author>
            <author initials='F.' surname='Jahanian'
                    fullname='Farnam Jahanian'>
                <organization/>
            </author>
            <author initials='D.' surname='McPherson'
                    fullname='Danny McPherson'>
                <organization/>
            </author>

            <date  year='2005' />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="Proceedings of the Steps to Reducing
			  Unwanted Traffic on the Internet Workshop" value='' />
      </reference>


      <reference anchor='Dean2004'>
        <front>
            <title>MapReduce: Simplified Data Processing on Large Clusters</title>
            <author initials='J.' surname='Dean'
                    fullname='Jeffrey Dean'>
                <organization/>
            </author>
            <author initials='S.' surname='Ghemawat'
                    fullname='Sanjay Ghemawat'>
                <organization/>
            </author>

            <date month="December" year='2004' />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="Sixth Symposium on Operating System Design
			  and Implementation (OSDI '04)" value='' />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor='Douceur2002'>
        <front>
            <title>The Sybil Attack</title>
            <author initials='J.' surname='Douceur'
                    fullname='J. Douceur'>
                <organization/>
            </author>

            <date  month="March" year='2002' />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="IPTPS 02" value='' />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor='Farber1972'>
        <front>
            <title>The Structure of a Distributed Computer System - The Communications System</title>
            <author initials='D.J.' surname='Farber'
                    fullname='D.J. Farber'>
                <organization/>
            </author>
            <author initials='K.C.' surname='Larson'
                    fullname='K.C. Larson'>
                <organization/>
            </author>

            <date year='1972' />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="Proceedings Symposium on Computer-Communications Networks and Teletraffic, Microwave Research Institute of Polytechnic Institute of Brooklyn pp. 21--27" value='' />
      </reference>	


      <reference anchor='Feldman2004'>
        <front>
            <title>Robust Incentive Techniques for Peer-to-peer Networks</title>
            <author initials='M.' surname='Feldman'
                    fullname='Michal Feldman'>
                <organization/>
            </author>
            <author initials='K.' surname='Lai'
                    fullname='Kevin Lai'>
                <organization/>
            </author>
            <author initials='I.' surname='Stoica'
                    fullname='Ion Stoica'>
                <organization/>
            </author>
            <author initials='J.' surname='Chuang'
                    fullname='John Chuang'>
                <organization/>
            </author>

            <date year='2004' />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="Proceedings of the 5th ACM Conference on
			  Electronic Commerce" value='' />
      </reference>	

      <reference anchor='Foster1999'>
        <front>
            <title>Computational Grids</title>
            <author initials='I.' surname='Foster'
                    fullname='Ian Foster'>
                <organization/>
            </author>

            <date year='1999' />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="Chapter 2 of The Grid: Blueprint for a New Computing Infrastructure" value='' />
      </reference>	

      <reference anchor='Foster2003'>
        <front>
            <title>On Death, Taxes, and the Convergence of
	    Peer-to-Peer and Grid Computing</title>
            <author initials='I.' surname='Foster'
                    fullname='Ian Foster'>
                <organization/>
            </author>
            <author initials='A.' surname='Iamnitchi'
                    fullname='Adriana Iamnitchi'>
                <organization/>
            </author>

            <date year='2003' />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="2nd International Workshop in Peer-to-Peer
			  Systems (IPTPS'02)" value='' />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor='Gkantsidis2005'>
        <front>
            <title>Network Coding for Large Scale Content Distribution</title>
            <author initials='C.' surname='Gkantsidis'
                    fullname='Christos Gkantsidis'>
                <organization/>
            </author>
            <author initials='P.' surname='Rodriguez'
                    fullname='Pablo Rodriguez'>
                <organization/>
            </author>

            <date month="March"  year='2005' />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="IEEE INFOCOM 2005, vol. 4" value='' />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor='Gray1983'>
        <front>
            <title>Solving the Problems of Distributed
            Databases</title>
            <author initials='J.' surname='Gray'
                    fullname='Jim Gray'>
                <organization/>
            </author>
            <author initials='S.' surname='Metz'
                    fullname='Sany Metz'>
                <organization/>
            </author>

            <date year='1983' />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name='Data Communications, pp. 183-192' value='' />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor='Gray1986A'>
        <front>
            <title>An Approach to Decentralized Computer Systems</title>
            <author initials='J.' surname='Gray'
                    fullname='Jim Gray'>
                <organization/>
            </author>

            <date year='1986' />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name='IEEE Transactions on Software Engineering, V
			  12.6, pp. 684-689' value='' />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor='Gray1986B'>
        <front>
            <title>Distributed Systems: Four Case Studies</title>
            <author initials='J.' surname='Gray'
                    fullname='Jim Gray'>
                <organization/>
            </author>
            <author initials='M.' surname='Anderton'
                    fullname='Mark Anderton'>
                <organization/>
            </author>

            <date year='1986' />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name='IEEE Transactions on Computers and Tandem
			  Technical Report 85.5' value='' />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor='Gong2001'>
        <front>
            <title>JXTA: A Network Programming Environment</title>
            <author initials='L.' surname='Gong'
                    fullname='L. Gong'>
                <organization/>
            </author>

            <date year='2001' />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="IEEE Internet Computing, vol. 5, no. 3, pp. 88-95" value='' />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor='Grizzard2007'>
        <front>
            <title>Peer-to-peer botnets: overview and case study</title>
            <author initials='J.B.' surname='Grizzard'
                    fullname='Julian B. Grizzard'>
                <organization/>
            </author>
            <author initials='V.' surname='Sharma'
                    fullname='Vikram Sharma'>
                <organization/>
            </author>
            <author initials='C.' surname='Nunnery'
                    fullname='Chris Nunnery'>
                <organization/>
            </author>
            <author initials='B.B.' surname='Kang'
                    fullname='Brent ByungHoon Kand'>
                <organization/>
            </author>
            <author initials='D.' surname='Dragon'
                    fullname='David Dragon'>
                <organization/>
            </author>

            <date  year='2007' />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="Proceedings of Hot Topics in Understanding Botnets (HotBots'07)" value='' />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor='Gurun2006'>
        <front>
            <title>Energy Consumption and Conservation in Mobile Peer-to-Peer Systems</title>
            <author initials='S.' surname='Gurun'
                    fullname='S. Gurun'>
                <organization/>
            </author>
            <author initials='P.' surname='Nagpurkar'
                    fullname='Priya Nagpurkar'>
                <organization/>
            </author>
            <author initials='B.Y.' surname='Zhao'
                    fullname='Ben Y. Zhao'>
                <organization/>
            </author>

            <date year='2006' />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name='First International Workshop on Decentralized Resource Sharing
in Mobile Computing and Networking (MobiShare 2006)' value='' />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor='Huang2007'>
        <front>
            <title>Challenges of P2P Streaming Technologies for IPTV Services</title>
            <author initials='Y.' surname='Huang'
                    fullname='Y. Huang'>
                <organization/>
            </author>
            <author initials='M.' surname='Rabinovich'
                    fullname='M. Rabinovich'>
                <organization/>
            </author>
            <author initials='Z.' surname='Xiao'
                    fullname='Z. Xiao'>
                <organization/>
            </author>

            <date month='May' year='2006' />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name='IPTC Workshop International World Wide Web
			  Conference, Edinburgh, Scotland, United Kingdom' value='' />
      </reference>

      <?rfc include="reference.I-D.ietf-mmusic-ice" ?>

      <reference anchor='Juang2002'>
        <front>
            <title>Energy-efficient computing for wildlife tracking: design tradeoffs and early experiences with ZebraNet</title>
            <author initials='P.' surname='Juang'
                    fullname='Philo Juang'>
                <organization/>
            </author>
            <author initials='H.' surname='Oki'
                    fullname='Hidekazu Oki'>
                <organization/>
            </author>
            <author initials='Y.' surname='Wang'
                    fullname='Yong Wang'>
                <organization/>
            </author>
            <author initials='M.' surname='Martonosi'
                    fullname='Margaret Martonosi'>
                <organization/>
            </author>
            <author initials='L.S.' surname='Peh'
                    fullname='Li Shiuan Peh'>
                <organization/>
            </author>
            <author initials='D.' surname='Rubenstein'
                    fullname='Daniel Rubenstein'>
                <organization/>
            </author>

            <date year='2002' />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="Proceedings of Conference on Computer and Communications Security (CCS), ACM" value='' />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor='Kanich2008'>
        <front>
            <title>Spamalytics: An Empirical Analysis of Spam Marketing Conversion</title>
            <author initials='C.' surname='Kanich'
                    fullname='C. Kanich'>
                <organization/>
            </author>
            <author initials='K.' surname='Levchenko'
                    fullname='K. Levchenko'>
                <organization/>
            </author>
            <author initials='B.' surname='Enright'
                    fullname='B. Enright'>
                <organization/>
            </author>
            <author initials='G.' surname='Voelker'
                    fullname='G. Voelker'>
                <organization/>
            </author>
            <author initials='V.' surname='Paxson'
                    fullname='V. Paxson'>
                <organization/>
            </author>
            <author initials='S.' surname='Savage'
                    fullname='S. Savage'>
                <organization/>
            </author>

            <date  month="October" year='2008' />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="Proceedings of Conference on Computer and Communications Security (CCS), ACM" value='' />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor='Kelenyi2008'>
        <front>
            <title>Energy Aspects of Peer Cooperation - Measurements
                   with a Mobile DHT System</title>
            <author initials='I.' surname='Kelenyi'
                    fullname='K. Leibniz'>
                <organization/>
            </author>
            <author initials='J.K.' surname='Nurminen'
                    fullname='Jukka K. Nurminen'>
                <organization/>
            </author>

            <date year='2008' />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name='in Proc. of Cognitive and Cooperative Wireless Networks Workshop in the IEEE International Conference on Communications 2008, Beijing, China, pp. 164-168. ' value='' />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor='Leibniz2007'>
        <front>
            <title>Peer-to-Peer vs. Client/Server: Reliability and
	    Efficiency of a Content Distribution Service</title>
            <author initials='K.' surname='Leibniz'
                    fullname='K. Leibniz'>
                <organization/>
            </author>
            <author initials='T.' surname='Hobfeld'
                    fullname='T. Hobfeld'>
                <organization/>
            </author>
            <author initials='N.' surname='Wakamiya'
                    fullname='N. Wakamiya'>
                <organization/>
            </author>
            <author initials='M.' surname='Murata'
                    fullname='M. Murata'>
                <organization/>
            </author>

            <date year='2007' />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name='Lecture Notes in Computer Science, LNCS
			  4516, pp. 1161-1172' value='' />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor='Lua2005'>
        <front>
            <title> A Survey and Comparison of Peer-to-peer Overlay Network Schemes</title>
            <author initials='E.' surname='Keong Lua'
                    fullname='Eng Keon Lua'>
                <organization/>
            </author>
            <author initials='J.' surname='Crowcroft'
                    fullname='Jon Crowcroft'>
                <organization/>
            </author>
            <author initials='M.' surname='Pias'
                    fullname='Marcelo Pias'>
                <organization/>
            </author>
            <author initials='R.' surname='Sharma'
                    fullname='Ravi Sharma'>
                <organization/>
            </author>
            <author initials='S.' surname='Lim'
                    fullname='Steven Lim'>
                <organization/>
            </author>

            <date year='2005' />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="IEEE Communications Surveys & Tutorials, vol. 7,
                          no. 2, Second Quarter 2005, pp. 72 - 93" value='' />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor='Mahajan2003'>
        <front>
            <title>Controlling the Cost of Reliability in Peer-to-Peer
	    Overlays</title>
            <author initials='R.' surname='Mahajan'
                    fullname='Ratul Mahajan'>
                <organization/>
            </author>
            <author initials='M.' surname='Castro'
                    fullname='Miguel Castro'>
                <organization/>
            </author>
            <author initials='A.' surname='Rowstron'
                    fullname='Antony Rowstron'>
                <organization/>
            </author>

            <date year='2003' />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="Proceedings of the 2nd International
			  Workshop on Peer-to-Peer Systems (IPTPS '03)" value='' />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor='Milojicic2002'>
        <front>
            <title>Peer-to-Peer Computing</title>
            <author initials='D.S.' surname='Milojicic'
                    fullname='D.S. Milojicic'>
                <organization/>
            </author>
            <author initials='V.' surname='Kalogeraki'
                    fullname='V. Kalogeraki'>
                <organization/>
            </author>
            <author initials='R.' surname='Lukose'
                    fullname='R. Lukose'>
                <organization/>
            </author>
            <author initials='K.' surname='Nagaraja'
                    fullname='K. Nagaraja'>
                <organization/>
            </author>
            <author initials='J.' surname='Pruyne'
                    fullname='J. Pruyne'>
                <organization/>
            </author>
            <author initials='B.' surname='Richard'
                    fullname='B. Richard'>
                <organization/>
            </author>
            <author initials='S.' surname='Rollins'
                    fullname='S. Rollins'>
                <organization/>
            </author>
            <author initials='Z.' surname='Xu'
                    fullname='Z. Xu'>
                <organization/>
            </author>

            <date month='March' year='2002' />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name='Technical Report, HP' value='' />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor='Mondal2006'>
        <front>
            <title>Privacy, Security and Trust in P2P environments: A
	    Perspective</title>
            <author initials='A.' surname='Mondal'
                    fullname='A. Mondal'>
                <organization/>
            </author>
            <author initials='M.' surname='Kitsuregawa'
                    fullname='M. Kitsuregawa'>
                <organization/>
            </author>


            <date  month="September" year='2006' />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name=" 17th International Conference on Database
			  and Expert Systems Applicationsn 2006 (DEXA'06)" value='' />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor='Octoshape'>
        <front>
            <title>http://www.octoshape.com</title>
            <author>
              <organization></organization>
            </author>
           <date year='' />
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor='Oechsner2006'>
        <front>
            <title>Using Kademlia for the Configuration of
B3G Radio Access Nodes</title>
            <author initials='S.' surname='Oechsner'
                    fullname='Simon Oechsner'>
                <organization/>
            </author>
            <author initials='T.' surname='Hobfeld'
                    fullname='Tobias Hobfeld'>
                <organization/>
            </author>
            <author initials='K.' surname='Tutschku'
                    fullname='Kurt Tutschku'>
                <organization/>
            </author>
            <author initials='F.U.' surname='Andersen'
                    fullname='Frank Uwe Andersen'>
                <organization/>
            </author>
            <author initials='L.' surname='Caviglione'
                    fullname='Luca Caviglione'>
                <organization/>
            </author>

            <date year='2006' />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name='Proceedings of the Fourth Annual IEEE International Conference on Pervasive Computing and Communications Workshops (PERCOMW06)' value='' />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor='Peltotalo2008'>
        <front>
            <title>Peer-to-Peer Streaming Technology Survey</title>
            <author initials='J.' surname='Peltotalo'
                    fullname='J. Peltotalo'>
                <organization/>
            </author>
            <author initials='J.' surname='Harju'
                    fullname='J. Harju'>
                <organization/>
            </author>
            <author initials='A.' surname='Jantunen'
                    fullname='A. Jantunen'>
                <organization/>
            </author>
            <author initials='M.' surname='Saukko'
                    fullname='M. Saukko'>
                <organization/>
            </author>
            <author initials='L.' surname='Vtminen'
                    fullname='L. Vtminen'>
                <organization/>
            </author>

            <date month='April' year='2008' />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name='Seventh International Conference on
			  Networking, Cancun, Mexico, pp. 342-350' value='' />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor='Pourebrahimi2005'>
        <front>
            <title>A Survey of Peer-to-Peer Networks</title>
            <author initials='B.' surname='Pourebrahimi'
                    fullname='B. Pourebrahimi'>
                <organization/>
            </author>
            <author initials='K.L.M.' surname='Bertels'
                    fullname='K.L.M. Bertels'>
                <organization/>
            </author>
            <author initials='S.' surname='Vassiliadis'
                    fullname='S. Vassiliadis'>
                <organization/>
            </author>

            <date month='November' year='2005' />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name='Proceedings of the 16th Annual Workshop on
			  Circuits, Systems, and Signal Processing,
			  ProRisc 2005' value='' />
      </reference>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.0959" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2616" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3261" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4981" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5128" ?>

      <reference anchor='Rhea2005'>
        <front>
            <title>Open DHT: A Public DHT Service and Its Uses</title>
            <author initials='S.' surname='Rhea'
                    fullname='Sean Rhea'>
                <organization/>
            </author>
            <author initials='B.' surname='Godfrey'
                    fullname='Brighten Godfrey'>
                <organization/>
            </author>
            <author initials='B.' surname='Karp'
                    fullname='Brad Karp'>
                <organization/>
            </author>
            <author initials='J.' surname='Kubiatowicz'
                    fullname='John Kubiatowicz'>
                <organization/>
            </author>
            <author initials='S.' surname='Ratnasamy'
                    fullname='Sylvia Ratnasamy'>
                <organization/>
            </author>
            <author initials='S.' surname='Shenker'
                    fullname='Scott Shenker'>
                <organization/>
            </author>
            <author initials='I.' surname='Stoica'
                    fullname='Ion Stoica'>
                <organization/>
            </author>
            <author initials='H.' surname='Yu'
                    fullname='Harlan Yu'>
                <organization/>
            </author>

            <date month="October"  year='2005' />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="ACM/SIGCOMM CCR'05, vol. 35, Issue 4" value='' />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor='Rodriguez2005'>
        <front>
            <title>On the Feasibility of Commercial Legal P2P Content
	    Distribution</title>
            <author initials='P.' surname='Rodriguez'
                    fullname='P. Rodriguez'>
                <organization/>
            </author>
            <author initials='S.' surname='Tan'
                    fullname='S. Tan'>
                <organization/>
            </author>
            <author initials='C.' surname='Gkantsidis'
                    fullname='C. Gkantsidis'>
                <organization/>
            </author>

            <date month='January' year='2006' />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="ACM/SIGCOMM CCR'06" value='' />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor='Roussopoulus2004'>
        <front>
            <title>2 P2P or Not 2 P2P</title>
            <author initials='M.' surname='Roussopoulus'
                    fullname='M. Roussopoulus'>
                <organization/>
            </author>
            <author initials='M.' surname='Baker'
                    fullname='M. Baker'>
                <organization/>
            </author>
            <author initials='D.' surname='Rosenthal'
                    fullname='D. Rosenthal'>
                <organization/>
            </author>
            <author initials='T.' surname='Guili'
                    fullname='T. Guili'>
                <organization/>
            </author>
            <author initials='P.' surname='Maniatis'
                    fullname='P. Maniatis'>
                <organization/>
            </author>
            <author initials='J.' surname='Mogul'
                    fullname='J. Mogul'>
                <organization/>
            </author>

            <date month='February' year='2004' />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="Workshop on Peer-to-Peer Systems" value='' />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor='Schollmeier2001'>
        <front>
            <title>A Definition of Peer-to-Peer Networking for the
	    Classification of Peer-to-Peer Architectures and Applications</title>
            <author initials='R.' surname='Schollmeier'
                    fullname='R. Schollmeier'>
                <organization/>
            </author>

            <date year='2001' />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="In Proceedings of the First International
			  Conference on Peer-to-Peer Computing P2P'01" value='' />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor='Seti'>
        <front>
            <title>http://setiathome.berkeley.edu</title>
            <author>
              <organization></organization>
            </author>
           <date year='' />
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor='Singh2006'>
        <front>
            <title>Eclipse Attacks on Overlay Networks: Threats and Defences</title>
            <author initials='A.' surname='Singh'
                    fullname='A. Singh'>
                <organization/>
            </author>
            <author initials='T.' surname='Ngan'
                    fullname='T. Ngan'>
                <organization/>
            </author>
            <author initials='T.' surname='Druschel'
                    fullname='T. Druschel'>
                <organization/>
            </author>
            <author initials='D.' surname='Wallach'
                    fullname='D. Wallach'>
                <organization/>
            </author>

            <date  month="April" year='2006' />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="INFOCOM 2006" value='' />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor='Skype'>
        <front>
            <title>http://www.skype.com</title>
            <author>
              <organization></organization>
            </author>
           <date year='' />
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor='SNC'>
        <front>
            <title>http://www.snc.sapmi.net</title>
            <author>
              <organization></organization>
            </author>
           <date year='' />
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor='Tanenbaum1981'>
        <front>
            <title>An Overview of the Amoeba Distributed Operating System</title>
            <author initials='A.' surname='Tanenbaum'
                    fullname='Andred Tanenbaum'>
                <organization/>
            </author>
            <author initials='S.' surname='Mullender'
                    fullname='Sape Mullender'>
                <organization/>
            </author>

            <date year='1981' />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="ACM SIGOPS Operating Systems Review" value='' />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor='WoW'>
        <front>
            <title>http://www.worldofwarcraft.com</title>
            <author>
              <organization></organization>
            </author>
           <date year='' />
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor='Zhang2006'>
        <front>
            <title>Recent Advances in Research on P2P Networks</title>
            <author initials='Y.' surname='Zhang'
                    fullname='Y. Zhang'>
                <organization/>
            </author>
            <author initials='C.' surname='Chen'
                    fullname='C. Chen'>
                <organization/>
            </author>
            <author initials='X.' surname='Wang'
                    fullname='X. Wang'>
                <organization/>
            </author>

            <date year='2006' />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="In Proceedings of the Seventh International
			  Conference on Parallel and Distributed
			  Computing, Applications, and Technologies PDCAT'06" value='' />
      </reference>

    </references>

  </back>

</rfc>

<!-- LocalWords: xref CDATA
 -->
