<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!-- comment -->
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd"[]>
<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="no" ?>
<rfc ipr="trust200811" category="std" docName="draft-ietf-simple-msrp-cema-04.txt" obsoletes="" extends="4975" submissionType="IETF" xml:lang="en">
<front>
    <title abbrev="MRSP-CEMA">
		Connection Establishment for Media Anchoring (CEMA) for the Message Session Relay Protocol (MSRP)
	</title>
    <author initials="C.H." surname="Holmberg" fullname="Christer Holmberg">
		<organization>Ericsson</organization>
		<address>
			<postal>
				<street>Hirsalantie 11</street>
				<code>02420</code>
				<city>Jorvas</city>
				<country>Finland</country>
			</postal>
        <email>christer.holmberg@ericsson.com</email>
		</address>
    </author>
    <author initials="S.B." surname="Blau" fullname="Staffan Blau">
		<organization>Ericsson</organization>
		<address>
			<postal>
				<code>12637</code> 
				<city>Stockholm</city>
				<country>Sweden</country>
			</postal>
        <email>staffan.blau@ericsson.com</email>
		</address>
    </author>
	<author fullname="Eric Burger" initials="E.W." surname="Burger">
		<organization>Georgetown University</organization>
		<address>
			<postal>
				<street>Department of Computer Science</street>
				<street>37th and O Streets, NW</street>
				<city>Washington</city>
				<region>DC</region>
				<code>20057-1232</code>
				<country>United States of America</country>
			</postal>
			<phone></phone>
			<facsimile>+1 530 267 7447</facsimile>
			<email>eburger@standardstrack.com</email>
			<uri>http://www.standardstrack.com</uri>
		</address>
    </author>

    <date year="2012" />
    <area>Transport</area>
    <workgroup>SIMPLE Working Group</workgroup>
    <keyword>MSRP</keyword>
    <keyword>CEMA</keyword>
    <keyword>Middlebox</keyword>
    <keyword>IBCF</keyword>
    <keyword>SBC</keyword>
    <keyword>relay</keyword>

    <abstract>
		<t>
			This document defines a Message Session Relay Protocol (MSRP)
			extension, Connection Establishment for Media Anchoring (CEMA). 
			Support of the extension is optional. The extension allows 
			middleboxes to anchor the MSRP connection, without the need for 
			middleboxes to modify the MSRP messages, and thus also enables a 
			secure end-to-end MSRP communication in networks where such middleboxes 
			are deployed. The document also defines a Session Description Protocol 
			(SDP) attribute, 'msrp-cema', that MSRP endpoints use to indicate 
			support of the CEMA extension.
		</t>	  
    </abstract>
</front>

<middle>
    <section title="Introduction" toc="default">
		<t>
			The Message Session Relay Protocol (MSRP) <xref format="default"
			pageno="false" target="RFC4975" /> expects to use MSRP relays
			<xref format="default" pageno="false" target="RFC4976" /> as a means for 
			Network Address Translation (NAT) traversal and policy enforcement.
			However, many Session Initiation Protocol (SIP) <xref format="default"
			pageno="false" target="RFC3261" /> networks, which deploy MSRP, contain 
			middleboxes.  These middleboxes anchor and control media, perform tasks 
			such as NAT traversal, performance monitoring, address 
			domain bridging, interconnect Service Layer Agreement (SLA) policy 
			enforcement, and so on.  One example is the Interconnection Border Control 
			Function (IBCF) <xref format="default" pageno="false" target="GPP23228" />, 
			defined by the 3rd Generation Partnership Project (3GPP). The IBCF controls a
			media relay that handles all types of SIP session media such as voice, video, 
			MSRP, etc.
		</t>
		<t>
			MSRP, as defined in RFC 4975 <xref format="default" pageno="false" 
			target="RFC4975" /> and RFC 4976 <xref format="default" pageno="false" 
			target="RFC4976" />, cannot anchor through middleboxes.  The reason is that 
			MSRP messages have routing information embedded in the message. Without an 
			extension such as CEMA, middleboxes must read the message to change the routing
			information. This occurs because middleboxes modify the address:port information 
			in the Session Description Protocol (SDP) <xref format="default" pageno="false" 
			target="RFC4566" /> c/m-line in order to anchor media. An "active" <xref 
			format="default" pageno="false" target="RFC6135" /> MSRP UA establishes
			the MSRP TCP or TLS connection based on the MSRP URI of the SDP 'path' attribute. 
			This means that the MSRP connection will not be routed through the middlebox, 
			unless the middlebox also modifies the MSRP URI of the topmost SDP 'path' attribute.
 			In many scenarios this will prevent the MSRP connection from being established. 
			In addition, if the middlebox modifies the MSRP URI of the SDP 'path'
			attribute, then the MSRP URI comparison procedure <xref format="default"
			pageno="false" target="RFC4975" />, which requires consistency between the address 
			information in the MSRP messages and the address information carried in the MSRP URI 
			of the SDP 'path' attribute, will fail.
		</t>
		<t>
			The only way to achieve interoperability in this situation is for the middlebox 
			to act as an MSRP back-to-back User Agent (B2BUA). Here the MSRP B2BUA acts as the 
			endpoint for the MSRP signaling and media, performs the corresponding modification 
			in the associated MSRP messages, and originates a new MSRP session towards the actual remote
			endpoint. However, the enabling of MSRP B2BUA functionality requires substantially more 
			resource usage in the middlebox, that normally result in negative performance impact. 
			In addition, the MSRP message needs to be exposed in clear text to the MSRP B2BUA, which 
			violates the end-to-end principle <xref format="default" pageno="false" target="RFC3724"/> .
		</t>
		<t>
			This specification defines an MSRP extension, Connection Establishment for Media 
			Anchoring (CEMA). CEMA in most cases allows MSRP endpoints to communicate through 
			middleboxes, as defined in <xref format="default" pageno="false" target="S.conventions"/>, 
			without a need for the middleboxes to be an MSRP B2BUA. In such cases, middleboxes, that 
			want to anchor the MSRP connection simply modify the SDP c/m-line address information, 
			similar to what it does for non-MSRP media types. MSRP endpoints that support the CEMA 
			extension will use the SDP c/m-line address information for establishing the TCP or TLS 
			connection for sending and receiving MSRP messages.
		</t>
		<t>
			The CEMA extension is fully backward compatible. In scenarios where
			MSRP endpoints do not support the CEMA extension, an MSRP endpoint
			that supports the CEMA extension behaves in the same way as an MSRP
			endpoint that does not support it. The CEMA extension only provides
			an alternative mechanism for negotiating and providing address
			information for the MSRP TCP connection. After the creation of the
			MSRP connection, an MSRP endpoint that supports the CEMA extension 
			acts according to the procedures for creating MSRP messages, performing 
			checks when receiving MSRP messages defined in RFC 4975 and, when it 
			is using a relay for MSRP communications, RFC 4976.
		</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="S.conventions" title="Conventions" toc="default">
		<t>
			The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
			"SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
			document are to be interpreted as described in BCP 14, RFC 2119 <xref
			format="default" pageno="false" target="RFC2119" />.
		</t>
		<t>
			Definitions:
		</t>
		<t>
			Fingerprint Based TLS Authentication: An MSRP endpoint that uses a
			self-signed certificate and sends a fingerprint (i.e., a hash of the 
			self-signed certificate)in SDP to the other MSRP endpoint. This 
			fingerprint binds the TLS key exchange to the signaling plane and 
			authenticates the other endpoint based on trust in the signaling plane.
		</t>
		<t>
			Name Based TLS Authentication: An MSRP endpoint that uses a
			certificate from a trusted certification authority and the other
			endpoint matches the hostname in the received TLS communication
			SubjectAltName extension towards the hostname received in the MSRP
			URI in SDP.
		</t>
		<t>
			B2BUA: This is an abbreviation for back-to-back user agent.
		</t>
		<t>   
			MSRP B2BUA: A network element that terminates an MSRP connection from one 
			MSRP endpoint and reoriginates that connection towards another MSRP 
			endpoint. Note the MSRP B2BUA is distinct from a SIP B2BUA. A SIP B2BUA 
			terminates a SIP session and reoriginates that session towards another SIP 
			endpoint. In the context of MSRP, a SIP endpoint initiates a SIP session
			towards another SIP endpoint. However, that INVITE may go through, for 
			example, an outbound Proxy or inbound Proxy to route to the remote SIP 
			endpoint. As part of that SIP session an MSRP session, that may follow 
			the SIP session path, is negotiated. However, there is no requirement 
			to co-locate the SIP network elements with the MSRP network elements.
		</t>
		<t>
			TLS B2BUA: A network element that terminates security associations (SAs)
			from endpoints, and establishes separate SAs between itself and each endpoint.
		</t>
		<t>
			Middlebox:  A SIP network device that modifies SDP media address:port
			information in order to steer or anchor media flows described in
			the SDP, including TCP and TLS connections used for MSRP communication,
			through a media proxy function controlled by the SIP endpoint.
			In most cases the media proxy function relays the MSRP messages
			without modification, while in some circumstances it acts as a
			MSRP B2BUA.  Other SIP related functions, such as related to
			routing, modification of SIP information etc, performed by the
			Middlebox, and whether it acts a SIP B2BUA or not, is outside
			the scope of this document. Section 5 describes additional
			assumptions regarding how the Middlebox handles MSRP in order to
			support the extension defined in this document.
		</t>
		<t>
			This document reuses the terms answer, answerer, offer and offerer as 
			defined in RFC 3264.
		</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Applicability Statement" toc="default">
		<t>
			This document defines a Message Session Relay Protocol (MSRP)
			extension, Connection Establishment for Media Anchoring (CEMA). 
			Support of the extension is optional. The extension allows 
			Middleboxes to anchor the MSRP connection, without the need for 
			Middleboxes to modify the MSRP messages, and thus also enables a 
			secure end-to-end MSRP communication in networks where such Middleboxes 
			are deployed. The document also defines a Session Description Protocol 
			(SDP) attribute, 'msrp-cema', that MSRP endpoints use to indicate 
			support of the CEMA extension.
		</t>	  
		<t>
			The CEMA extension is primarily intended for MSRP endpoints that
			operate in networks in which Middleboxes that want to anchor media
			connections are deployed, without the need for the Middleboxes to
			enable MSRP B2BUA functionality.  An example of such network is the
			IP Multimedia Subsystem (IMS) defined by the 3rd Generation
			Partnership Project (3GPP), which also has the capability for all 
			endpoints to use Name-based TLS Authentication. The extension is also 
			useful for other MSRP endpoints operating in other networks, but that 
			communicate with MSRP endpoints in networks with such Middleboxes, 
			unless there is a gateway between the networks that by default always 
			enable MSRP B2BUA functionality.
		</t>
		<t>
			This document assumes certain behaviors on the part of Middleboxes, as 
			described in <xref format="default" pageno="false" target="S.assumption"/>. 
			These behaviors are not standardized. If Middleboxes do not behave as assumed, 
			then the CEMA extension does not add any value over base MSRP behavior. MSRP 
			endpoints that support CEMA are required to use RFC 4975 behavior in cases 
			where they detect that the CEMA extension cannot be enabled.
		</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Connection Establishment for Media Anchoring Mechanism" toc="default">
		<section title="General" toc="default">
			<t>
				This section defines how an MSRP endpoint that supports the CEMA
				extension generates SDP offers and answers for MSRP, and which SDP
				information elements the MSRP endpoint uses when creating the TCP
				or TLS connection for sending and receiving MSRP messages.
			</t>
			<t>
				Based on the procedures described in sections 4.2 and 4.3, in the 
				following cases the CEMA extension will not be enabled, and there will 
				be a fallback to the MSRP connection establishment procedures defined 
				in RFC 4975 and RFC 4976:
			</t>
			<t>
				- A non-CEMA-enabled MSRP endpoint becomes "active" 
				<xref format="default" pageno="false" target="RFC6135" /> (no matter whether it uses
				a relay for its MSRP communication or not), as it will always establish 
				the MSRP connection using the SDP 'path' attribute, which contains the address 
				information of the remote MSRP endpoint, instead of using the SDP c/m-line which contains 
				the address information of the Middlebox.
			</t>
			<t>				
				- A non-CEMA-enabled MSRP endpoint that uses a relay for its MSRP communication 
				becomes "passive" <xref format="default" pageno="false" target="RFC6135" />, 
				as it cannot be assumed that the MSRP endpoint inserts the address 
				information of the relay in the SDP c/m-line.
			</t>
			<t>
				- A CEMA-enabled MSRP endpoint that uses a relay for its MSRP communication becomes 
				"active", since if it adds the received SDP c/m-line address information to the ToPath 
				header field of the MSRP message (in order for the relay to establish the MSRP connection 
				towards the Middlebox), the session matching <xref format="default" pageno="false" target="RFC4975" />
				performed by the remote MSRP endpoint will fail.
  			</t>
		</section>

		<section anchor="S.offerer" title="MSRP SDP Offerer Procedures" toc="default">
			<t>
				When a CEMA-enabled offerer sends an SDP offer for MSRP, it
				generates the SDP offer according to the procedures in RFC 4975.  In
				addition, the offerer follows RFC 4976 if it is using a relay for
				MSRP communication. The offerer also performs the following
				additions and modifications:
			</t>	  
			<t>
				1.  The offerer MUST include an SDP 'msrp-cema' attribute in
				the MSRP media description of the SDP offer.
			</t>	  
			<t>
				2.  If the offerer is not using a relay for MSRP communication,
				it MUST include an SDP 'setup' attribute in the MSRP media
				description of the SDP offer, according to the procedures in RFC
				6135 <xref format="default" pageno="false" target="RFC6135" />.
			</t>	  
			<t>
				3.  If the offerer is using a relay for MSRP communication, it
				MUST, in addition to including the address information of the relay in 
				the topmost SDP 'path' attribute, also include the address information of 
				the relay, rather than the address information of itself, in the SDP c/m-line 
				associated with the MSRP media description. In addition, it MUST include 
				an SDP 'setup:actpass' attribute in the MSRP media description of the
				SDP offer.
			</t>	  
			<t>
				When the offerer receives an SDP answer, if the MSRP media
				description of the SDP answer does not contain an SDP 'msrp-cema'
				attribute, and if any of the following criteria below is met, the offerer 
				MUST fallback to RFC 4975 behavior, by sending a new SDP offer according 
				to the procedures in RFC 4975 and RFC 4976. The new offer MUST NOT 
				contain an SDP 'msrp-cema' attribute.
			</t>	  
			<t>
				1. The SDP c/m-line address information associated with the MSRP
				media description does not match <xref format="default" 
				pageno="false" target="S.address"/> the information in the MSRP URI
				of the 'path' attribute(s) (in which case is assumed that 
				the SDP c/m-line contains the address to a Middlebox), and the MSRP
				endpoint will become "passive" (if the MSRP media description of 
				the SDP answer contains an SDP 'setup:active' attribute).
			</t>	  
			<t>
				NOTE: If an MSRP URI contains a domain name, it needs to be resolved
				into an IP address and port before it is checked against the SDP c/m-line
				address information, in order to determine whether the address
				information matches.
			</t>
			<t>
				2. The offerer uses a relay for its MSRP communication, 
				the SDP c/m-line address information associated with the MSRP
				media description does not match the information in the MSRP URI
				of the SDP 'path' attribute(s) (in which case is assumed that 
				the SDP c/m-line contains the address to a Middlebox), and the 
				offerer will become "active" (either by default or if the 
				MSRP media description of the SDP answer contains an SDP 
				'setup:passive' attribute).
			</t>	  
			<t>
				3. The remote MSRP endpoint, acting as an answerer, uses a relay for 
				its MSRP communication, the SDP c/m-line address information associated 
				with the MSRP media description does not match the information in the 
				MSRP URI of the SDP 'path' attributes (in which case is assumed that 
				the SDP c/m-line contains the address to a Middlebox), and the MSRP 
				offerer will become "active" (either by default or if the MSRP media 
				description of the SDP answer contains an SDP 'setup:passive' attribute).
			</t>	  
			<t>
				NOTE: As described in section 5, in the absence of the SDP 'msrp-cema' 
				attribute in the new offer, it is assumed that a Middlebox will act as 
				an MSRP B2BUA in order to anchor MSRP media. 
			</t>	  
			<t>
				The offerer can send the new offer within the existing early
				dialog <xref format="default" pageno="false" target="RFC3261" />, or 
				it can terminate the early dialog and establish a new dialog by 
				sending the new offer in a new initial INVITE request.
			</t>	  
			<t>
				The offerer MAY choose to terminate the session establishment 
				if it can detect that a Middlebox acting as an MSRP B2BUA is not the 
				desired remote MSRP endpoint.
			</t>	  
			<t>
				If the answerer uses a relay for its MSRP communication, and the 
				SDP c/m-line address information associated with the MSRP media 
				description matches one of the SDP 'path' attributes, it is assumed 
				that there is no Middlebox in the network. In that case the offerer 
				MUST fallback to RFC 4975 behavior, but it does not need to send a 
				new SDP offer.
			</t>
			<t>
				In other cases, where none of the criteria above is met, and where the MSRP 
				offerer becomes "active", it MUST use the SDP c/m-line for establishing the 
				MSRP TCP connection. If the offerer becomes "passive", it will wait for 
				the answerer to establish the TCP connection, according to the 
				procedures in RFC 4975.
			</t>
		</section>

		<section title="MSRP SDP Answerer Procedures" toc="default">
			<t>
				If the MSRP media description of the SDP offer does not contain an
				SDP 'msrp-cema' attribute, and the SDP c/m-line address information
				associated with the MSRP media description does not match the
				information in the MSRP URI of the SDP 'path' attribute(s),
				the answerer MUST either reject the 
				offered MSRP connection (by using a zero port value number in the generated 
				SDP answer), or reject the whole SDP offer carrying SIP request with a 
				488 Not Acceptable Here <xref format="default" pageno="false" target="RFC3261" />
				response.
			</t>
			<t>
				NOTE: The reasons for the rejection is that the answerer assumes that
				a middlebox, that do not support the CEMA extension, has modified the c/m-line
				address information of the SDP offer, without enabling MSRP B2BUA functionality.
			</t>
			<t>
				NOTE: If an MSRP URI contains a domain name, it needs to be resolved
				into an IP address and port before it is checked against the SDP c/m-line
				address information, in order to determine whether the address
				information matches.
			</t>
			<t>
				If any of the criteria below is met, the answerer MUST fallback
				to RFC 4975 behavior and generate the associated SDP answer according
				to the procedures in RFC 4975 and RFC 4976. The answerer MUST
				NOT insert an SDP 'msrp-cema' attribute in the MSRP media description
				of the SDP answer.
			</t>	  
			<t>
				1. Both MSRP endpoints are using relays for their MSRP communication.
				The answerer can detect if the remote MSRP endpoint, acting as an
				offerer, is using a relay for its MSRP communication if the MSRP 
				media description of the SDP offer contains multiple SDP 'path' attributes.
			</t>	  
			<t>
				2. The offerer uses a relay for its MSRP communication, and
				will become "active" (either by default or if the MSRP media
				description of the SDP offer contains an SDP 'setup:active'
				attribute). Note that a CEMA-enabled offerer would
				include an SDP 'setup:actpass' attribute in the SDP offer, as
				described in Section 4.2.
			</t>	  
			<t>
				3. The answerer uses a relay for MSRP communication and is not
				able to become "passive" (if the MSRP media description of the offer 
				contains an SDP 'setup:passive' attribute. Note that an offerer 
				is not allowed to include an SDP 'setup:passive' attribute in an SDP 
				offer, as described in RFC 6135.
			</t>	  
			<t>
				In all other cases, the answerer generates the associated SDP
				answer according to the procedures in RFC 4975 and RFC 4976, with the
				following additions and modifications:
			</t>	  
			<t>
				1. The answerer MUST include an SDP 'msrp-cema' attribute in
				the MSRP media description of the SDP answer.
			</t>	  
			<t>
				2. If the answerer is not using a relay for MSRP communication,
				it MUST include an SDP 'setup' attribute in the MSRP media
				description of the answer, according to the procedures in RFC 6135.
			</t>	  
			<t>
				3.  If the answerer is using a relay for MSRP communication, it
				MUST, in addition to including the address information of the relay in 
				the topmost SDP 'path' attribute, also include the address information of 
				the relay, rather than the address information of itself, in the SDP 
				c/m-line associated with the MSRP media description. In addition, the 
				answerer MUST include an SDP 'setup:passive' attribute in the MSRP 
				media description of the SDP answer.
			</t>	  
			<t>
				If the answerer included an SDP 'msrp-cema' attribute in the
				MSRP media description of the SDP answer, and if the answerer
				becomes "active", it MUST use the received SDP c/m-line for
				establishing the MSRP TCP or TLS connection. If the answerer becomes
				"passive", it will wait for the offerer to establish the
				MSRP TCP or TLS connection, according to the procedures in RFC 4975.
			</t>
		</section>

		<section anchor="S.address" title="Address Information Matching" toc="default">
			<t>
				When comparing address information in the SDP c/m-line and an MSRP 
				URI, for address and port equivalence, the address and port values are 
				retrieved in the following ways:
			</t>
			<t>
				- SDP c/m-line address information: The IP address is retrieved from 
				the SDP c- line, and the port from the associated SDP m- line for MSRP.
			</t>
			<t>
				- In case the SDP c- line contains a Fully Qualified Domain Name (FQDN), the 
				IP address is retrieved using DNS.
			</t>
			<t>
				- MSRP URI address information: The IP address and port are retrieved from 
				the authority part of the MSRP URI.
			</t>
			<t>
				- In case the authority part of the MSRP URI contains a Fully Qualified 
				Domain Name (FQDN), the IP address is retrieved using DNS, according 
				to the procedures in section 6.2 of RFC 4975.
			</t>
			<t>
				NOTE: According to RFC 4975, the authority part of the MSRP URI must always 
				contain a port.
			</t>
			<t>
				Before IPv6 addresses are compared for equivalence, they need to be converted 
				into the same representation, using the mechanism defined in RFC 5952 
				<xref format="default" pageno="false" target="RFC5952" />.			
			</t>
			<t>
				NOTE: In case the DNS returns multiple records, each needs to be compared against 
				the SDP c/m- line address information, in order to find at least one match.
			</t>
			<t>
				NOTE: If the authority part of the MSRP URI contains special characters, they are 
				handled according to the procedures in section 6.1 of RFC 4975.
			</t>
		</section>
		
		<section title="Usage With the Alternative Connection Model" toc="default">
			<t>
				An MSRP endpoint that supports the CEMA extension MUST support the
				mechanism defined in RFC 6135, as it extends the number of scenarios
				where one can use the CEMA extension. An example is where an MSRP
				endpoint is using a relay for MSRP communication, and it needs to be
				"passive" in order to use the CEMA extension, instead of doing a
				fallback to RFC 4975 behavior.
			</t>
		</section>
    </section>

	<section title="The SDP 'msrp-cema' attribute" toc="default">
		<section title="General" toc="default">
			<t>
				The SDP 'msrp-cema' attribute is used by MSRP entities to indicate
				support of the CEMA extension, according to the procedures in
				Sections 4.2 and 4.3.
			</t>
		</section>		
		<section title="Syntax" toc="default">
			<t>
				This section describes the syntax extensions to the ABNF syntax
				defined in RFC 4566 required for the SDP 'msrp-cema' attribute.
				The ABNF defined in this specification is conformant to 
				RFC 5234 <xref format="default" pageno="false" target="RFC5234" />.
			</t>
			<figure>
			<artwork align="left" alt="" height="" name="" type="" width="" xml:space="preserve"><![CDATA[		
attribute          /= msrp-cema-attr
;attribute defined in RFC 4566
msrp-cema-attr     = "msrp-cema"
]]></artwork>
			</figure>		
		</section>
	</section>

    <section anchor="S.assumption" title="Middlebox Assumptions" toc="default">
		<section title="General" toc="default">
			<t>
				This document does not specify explicit Middlebox behavior, even
				though Middleboxes enable some of the procedures described here.   
				However, as MSRP endpoints are expected to operate in networks 
				where Middleboxes that want to anchor media are present,
				this document makes certain assumptions regarding to how such
				Middleboxes behave.
			</t>
		</section>

		<section title="MSRP Awareness" toc="default">
			<t>
				In order to support interoperability between UAs that support the
				CEMA extension and UAs that do not support the extension, the
				Middlebox is MSRP aware.  This means that it implements MSRP B2BUA
				functionality. The Middlebox enables that functionality in cases
				where the offerer does not support the CEMA extension. In
				cases where the SDP offer indicates support of the CEMA extension,
				the Middlebox can simply modify the SDP c/m-line address information
				for the MSRP connection.
			</t>
			<t>
				In cases where the Middlebox enables MSRP B2BUA functionality, it
				acts as an MSRP endpoint.  If it does not use the CEMA procedures
				it will never forward the SDP 'msrp-cema' attribute in SDP offers
				and answers.
			</t>
			<t>
				If the Middlebox does not implement MSRP B2BUA functionality, or does 
				not enable it when the SDP 'msrp-cema' attribute is not present in the
				SDP offer, CEMA-enabled MSRP endpoints will in some cases be unable to 
				interoperate with non-CEMA-enabled endpoints across the Middlebox.
			</t>
		</section>

		<section title="TCP Connection Reuse" toc="default">
			<t>
				Middleboxes do not need to parse and modify the MSRP payload when
				endpoints use the CEMA extension. A Middlebox that does not parse
				the MSRP payload probably will not be able to reuse TCP connections
				for multiple MSRP sessions. Instead, in order to associate an MSRP message 
				with a specific session, the Middlebox often assigns a unique local 
				address:port combination for each MSRP session. Due to this, between two 
				Middleboxes there might be a separate connection for each MSRP session.
			</t>
			<t>
				If the Middlebox does not assign a unique address:port combination for 
				each MSRP session, and does not parse MSRP messages, it might end up forwarding 
				MSRP messages towards the wrong destination.
			</t>
		</section>

		<section title="SDP Integrity" toc="default">
			<t>
				This document assumes that Middleboxes are able to modify 
				the SDP address information associated with the MSRP media, and 
				that they are able to modify the SDP address information associated
				with the MSRP media.
			</t>
			<t>
				NOTE: Eventhough the CEMA extension as such works with end-to-end SDP protection, 
				the main advantage of the extension is in networks where Middleboxes are deployed.
			</t>
			<t>
				If the Middlebox is unable to modify SDP payloads due to end-to-end
				integrity protection, it will be unable to anchor MSRP media as the 
				SIP signaling would fail due to integrity violations.
			</t>
		</section>

		<section title="TLS" toc="default">
			<t>
				When UAs use the CEMA extension, this document assumes that Middleboxes 
				relay MSRP media packets at the transport layer. The TLS handshake and resulting 
				security association (SA) can be established peer-to-peer between the MSRP endpoints.  
				The Middlebox will see encrypted MSRP media packets, but is unable to 
				inspect the clear text content.
			</t>
			<t>
				When UAs fall back to RFC 4975 behavior Middleboxes act as TLS B2BUAs.				
				The Middlebox decrypts MSRP media packets received from one MSRP endpoint, and 
				then re-encrypts them before sending them toward the other MSRP endpoint. 
				Middleboxes can inspect and modify the MSRP message content.
			</t>
		</section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="sec-security" title="Security Considerations" toc="default">

		<section anchor="sec-security-gen" title="General" toc="default">
			<t>
				Unless otherwise stated, the security considerations in <xref format="default" 
				pageno="false" target="RFC4975" /> and <xref format="default" pageno="false" 
				target="RFC4976" /> still apply. This section only describes additions and changes 
				introduced by the CEMA extension.
			</t>
			<t>
				In deployments where Middleboxes are always used, which is the main use case 
				for the CEMA extension, the CEMA extension increases the security by enabling the 
				use of end-to-end TLS between the two endpoints. If the key management does not 
				depend on trust in the signaling plane, this greatly increases the security. If 
				the key management depends on trust in the signaling plane, the Middlebox is by 
				definition trusted, but the security is still increased as the cleartext is not 
				available in the Middlebox.
			</t>
		</section>

		<section anchor="sec-security-mitma" title="Man-in-the-Middle Attacks" toc="default">
			<t>
				If TLS is not used to protect MSRP, the CEMA extension might make it easier for a 
				man-in-the-middle to transparently insert itself in the communication between MSRP 
				endpoints in order to monitor or record unprotected MSRP communication. This can be 
				mitigated by the use of TLS. It is therefore RECOMMENDED to use TLS <xref format="default" 
				pageno="false" target="RFC5246" />. It is also recommended to use TLS e2e, which CEMA 
				enables even in the case of Middleboxes. For backward compatibility, a CEMA-enabled 
				MSRP endpoint MUST implement TLS.
			</t>
		</section>
		
		<section anchor="sec-security-tlswom" title="TLS Usage without Middleboxes" toc="default">
			<t>
				If TLS is use without Middleboxes, the security considerations in <xref format="default" 
				pageno="false" target="RFC4975" /> and <xref format="default" pageno="false" target="RFC4976" /> 
				still apply unchanged. Note that this is not the main use case for the CEMA extension.
			</t>
		</section>

		<section anchor="sec-security-tlswm" title="TLS Usage with Middleboxes" toc="default">
			<t>
				This is the main use case for the CEMA extension; the endpoints expect one or more 
				Middlebox.
			</t>
			<t>
				The CEMA extension supports the usage of both name-based authentication and fingerprint 
				based authentication for TLS in the presence of Middleboxes. The use of fingerprint based 
				authentication requires signaling integrity protection. This can e.g. be hop-by-hop 
				cryptographic protection or cryptographic access protection combined with physical trust 
				in other parts of the signaling plane. As stated in section 6.4 Middleboxes cannot be 
				deployed in environments with cryptographic end-to-end SDP integrity protection or encryption. 
			</t>
			<t>
				If a Middlebox acts as a TLS B2BUA, the security considerations are the same as without the 
				CEMA extension. In such case the Middlebox acts as TLS endpoints.
			</t>
			<t>
				If a Middlebox does not act as a TLS B2BUA, TLS is e2e and the Middlebox just forwards the 
				TLS packets. This requires that both peers support the CEMA extension.
			</t>
			<t>
				If fingerprint based authentication is used, the MSRP endpoints might not be able to decide 
				whether the Middlebox acts as a TLS B2BUA or not. But this is not an issue as the signaling 
				network is considered trusted by the endpoint (a requirement to use fingerprint based authentication).
			</t>
		</section>

		<section anchor="sec-security-ackm" title="Authentication, Credentials and Key Management" toc="default">
			<t>
				One issue with usage of TLS (not specific to CEMA) is the availability of a PKI. Endpoints 
				can always provide self-signed certificates.  However, this relies on that the SDP signaling is 
				integrity protected, which may not always be the case.
			</t>
			<t>
				Therefore, in addition to the authentication mechanisms defined in RFC 4975, it is RECOMMENDED 
				that a CEMA-enabled MSRP endpoint also support one of the following authentication and key management 
				mechanisms, that do not rely on integrity protected SDP signaling.
			</t>
			<t>
				1.  Self-signed certificates together with support of interacting with a Certificate Management 
				Service <xref format="default" pageno="false" target="RFC6072" />, to which it publishes its 
				self-signed certificate and from which it fetches on demand the self-signed certificates of other 
				endpoints.
			</t>
			<t>
				2.  TLS-PSK where the pre-shared key is provided by MIKEY-TICKET. MIKEY-TICKET is a ticket based 
				key management service relying on a shared secret (UICC or password) between the endpoint and some 
				AAA server. MIKEY-TICKET is one of two standardized key management protocols in the IP Multimedia 
				Subsystem (IMS).
			</t>
			<t>
				One of the target deployments for CEMA is the 3GPP IMS SIP network. In this environment authentication 
				and credential management is less of a problem as the SDP signaling is mostly considered trusted, service 
				providers provision signed certificates or manage signed certificates on behalf of their subscribers, 
				and MIKEY-TICKET is available. Some of these options require trusting the service provider, but those 
				issues are beyond the scope of this document.
			</t>
			<t>
				Alternate key distribution mechanisms, such as DANE [DANE], PGP <xref format="default" pageno="false" 
				target="RFC6091" />, or some other technology, might become ubiquitous enough to solve the key 
				distribution problem in the future.
			</t>
		</section>

		<section anchor="sec-security-endtls" title="Endpoint procedures for TLS negotiation" toc="default">
			<t>
				The CEMA extension does not change the endpoint procedures for TLS negotiation. As in <xref format="default"
				pageno="false" target="RFC4975" /> the endpoint uses the negotiation mechanisms in SDP and then the TLS 
				handshake to agree on a mechanisms and algorithms that both support. The mechanisms can be divided in three 
				different security levels:
			</t>
			<t>
				-	MSRPS: Security Mechanisms that does not rely on trusted signaling such as name based authentication and MIKEY-TICKET
			</t>
			<t>
				-	MSRPS: Mechanisms that do rely on trusted signaling such as fingerprint based authentication
			</t>
			<t>
				-	MSRP: Unprotected
			</t>
			<t>
				If the endpoint uses security mechanisms that does not rely on trusted signaling the endpoint can detect if a 
				Middlebox is inserted. It is therefore RECOMMENDED to use such a mechanism.
			</t>
			<t>
				If the endpoint uses security mechanisms that rely on trusted signaling the endpoint may not be able to detect 
				if a Middlebox is inserted (by the trusted network operator). To be able to eavesdrop a Middlebox must do an 
				active "attack" on the setup signaling. A Middlebox cannot insert itself at a later point.
			</t>
			<t>
				If Unprotected MSRP is used, the endpoint cannot detect if a Middlebox is inserted and Middleboxes may be 
				inserted at any time during the session.
			</t>
			<t>
				The two new recommended mechanisms <xref format="default" pageno="false" target="RFC6043" />, 
				<xref format="default" pageno="false" target="RFC6072" /> both give end-to-end security without 
				relying on trust in the signaling. <xref format="default" pageno="false" target="RFC6072" /> eases the 
				use and deployment of name based authentication and <xref format="default" pageno="false" target="RFC6043" /> 
				gives the same security properties and should be offered in parallel with name based authentication.
			</t>
			<t>
				The procedures for choosing and offering name based authentication, fingerprint based authentication, and 
				unprotected MSRP as described in <xref format="default" pageno="false" target="RFC4975" /> still apply. 
			</t>
		</section>
		
		<section anchor="sec-security-fpauth" title="Fingerprint Based Authentication" toc="default">
			<t>
				If the endpoint cannot use a key management protocol that does not rely on trust in the signaling 
				such as name based authentication or MIKEY-TICKET, the only alternative is fingerprint based 
				authentication.
			</t>
			<t>
				The use of fingerprint based authentication requires integrity protection of the signaling plane. This 
				can e.g. be end-to-end cryptographic protection, hop-by-hop cryptographic protection, or cryptographic 
				access protection combined with physical trust in other parts of the signaling plane. Unless cryptographic 
				end-to-end SDP integrity protection or encryption is used this may be hard for the endpoint to decide. In 
				the end it is up to the endpoint to decide whether the signaling path is trusted or not.
			</t>
			<t>
				How this decision is done is implementation specific, but normally signaling over the internet SHOULD 
				NOT be trusted. Signaling over a local or closed network MAY be trusted. Such networks can e.g. be a 
				closed enterprise network or a network operated by an operator that the end user trusts. In e.g. IMS 
				the signaling traffic in the access network is integrity protected and the traffic is routed over a 
				closed network separated from the Internet. If the network is not trusted the endpoints SHOULD NOT use 
				fingerprint authentication.
			</t>
			<t>
				It should however be noted that using fingerprint based authentication over an insecure network increases 
				the security compared to unencrypted MSRP as this makes it harder to perform an man-in-the-middle attack. 
				Such an attack needs to be done to both the signaling and the media plane, which may be separated. It does 
				not however give any guarantees that such a man-in-the-middle attack is not taking place. A client using 
				DTLS-SRTP <xref format="default" pageno="false" target="RFC5764" /> for VoIP media security may wish to 
				use fingerprint based authentication also for MSRP media security. 
			</t>
			<t>
				MSRPS with fingerprint based authentication is vulnerable to attacks due to vulnerabilities in the SIP 
				signaling. If there are weaknesses in the integrity protections on the SIP signaling, an attacker may 
				insert malicious middleboxes to alter, record, or otherwise harm the media. With insecure signaling, 
				it can be difficult for an endpoint to even be aware the remote endpoint has any relationship to the 
				expected endpoint.  Securing the SIP signaling does not solve all problems. For example, in a SIPS 
				environment, the endpoints have no cryptographic way of validating that one or more SIP Proxies in the 
				proxy chain are not, in fact, malicious.
			</t>
		</section>

    </section>

    <section title="IANA Considerations" toc="default">
		<section title="IANA Registration of the SDP 'msrp-cema' attribute" toc="default">
			<t>
				This document instructs IANA to add a attribute to the 'att-field 
				(media level only)' registry of the SDP parameters registry, according 
				to the information provided in this section.
			</t>
			<t>
				This section registers a new SDP attribute, 'msrp-cema'. The
				required information for this registration, as specified in RFC 4566,
				is:
			</t>
			<figure>
			<artwork align="left" alt="" height="" name="" type="" width=""
                   xml:space="preserve"><![CDATA[
Contact name: Christer Holmberg

Contact e-mail: christer.holmberg@ericsson.com

Attribute name: msrp-cema

Type of attribute: media level

Purpose: This attribute is used to indicate support of
         the MSRP Connection Establishment for Media
         Anchoring (CEMA) extension defined in 
         RFC XXXX. When present in an MSRP media 
         description of an SDP body, it indicates 
         that the creator of the SDP supports the CEMA
         mechanism.
 
Values: The attribute does not carry a value

Charset dependency: none
]]></artwork>
        </figure>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="sec-acks" title="Acknowledgements" toc="default">
		<t>
			Thanks to Ben Campbell, Remi Denis-Courmont, Nancy Greene, Hadriel
			Kaplan, Adam Roach, Robert Sparks, Salvatore Loreto, Shida Schubert, Ted
			Hardie, Richard L Barnes, Inaki Baz Castillo, Saul Ibarra Corretge,
			Cullen Jennings, Adrian Georgescu and Miguel Garcia for their guidance 
			and input in order to produce this document.
		</t>
		<t>
			Thanks to John Mattsson for his help to restructure the Security
			Considerations section, based on the feedback from IESG.
		</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Change Log">
		<t>[RFC EDITOR NOTE: Please remove this section when publishing]</t>

		<t>Changes from draft-ietf-simple-msrp-cema-03<list style="symbols">
			<t>Security Considerations sections re-written based on IESG comments.</t>
			<t>Changes based on IESG comments from Peter Saint-Andre.</t>
			<t>Changes based on IESG comments from Robert Sparks.</t>
			<t>Changes based on IESG comments from Stephen Farrell.</t>
			<t>Changes based on IESG comments from Pete Resnick.</t>
        </list>
		</t>
		
		<t>Changes from draft-ietf-simple-msrp-cema-02<list style="symbols">
			<t>Changes based on WGLC comments.</t>
			<t>- Editorial changes based on comments from Nancy Greene.</t>
			<t>- Editorial changes based on comments from Saul Ibarra Corretge.</t>
			<t>- Editorial changes based on comments from Christian Schmidt.</t>
			<t>- Editorial changes based on comments from Miguel Garcia.</t>
			<t>Changes based on MMUSIC SDP impact review.</t>
			<t>- Editorial changes based on comments from Miguel Garcia.</t>
        </list>
		</t>

		<t>Changes from draft-ietf-simple-msrp-cema-01<list style="symbols">
			<t>Changes based on comment from Ben Campbell.</t>
			<t>- TLS B2BUA added to definitions section.</t>
			<t>- Middlebox added.</t>
			<t>- Editorial changes.</t>
        </list>
		</t>

		<t>Changes from draft-ietf-simple-msrp-sessmatch-13<list style="symbols">
			<t>Changed the draft name, as was suggested by our AD and work
			group.</t>
			<t>Clean up language use, clarify language, and clean up editorial
			and style issues.</t>
			<t>Formally defined an MSRP B2BUA.</t>
        </list>
		</t>

      <t>Changes from draft-ietf-simple-msrp-sessmatch-12 <list
          style="symbols">
          <t>Extension name changed to Connection Establishment for Media
          Anchoring (CEMA).</t>
          <t>Middlebox definition added.</t>
          <t>ALG terminology replaced with Middlebox.</t>
          <t>SDP attribute name changed to a=msrp-cema.</t>
          <t>Applicability Statement section expanded.</t>
          <t>Re-structuring of MSRP Answerer section.</t>
          <t>Changes based on comments from Sa&uacute;l Ibarra Corretg&eacute;
          (1406111).</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>Changes from draft-ietf-simple-msrp-sessmatch-11 <list
          style="symbols">
          <t>Modification of the sessmatch mechanism.</t>
          <t>- Extension name changed to Alternative Connection Establishment
          (ACE)</t>
          <t>- Session matching procedure no longer updated.</t>
          <t>- SDP c/m-line used for MSRP TCP connection.</t>
          <t>- sessmatch option-tag removed.</t>
          <t>- a=msrp-ace attribute defined.</t>
          <t>- Support of RFC 6135 mandatory.</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>Changes from draft-ietf-simple-msrp-sessmatch-10 <list
          style="symbols">
          <t>Sessmatch option-tag added, based on WG discussions and
          concensus.</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>Changes from draft-ietf-simple-msrp-sessmatch-08 <list
          style="symbols">
          <t>OPEN ISSUE regarding the need for a sessmatch option-tag
          removed.</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>Changes from draft-ietf-simple-msrp-sessmatch-07 <list
          style="symbols">
          <t>Sessmatch defined as an MSRP extension, rather than MSRP
          update</t>

          <t>Additional security considerations text added</t>
        </list></t>
    </section>
</middle>

<back>
    <references title="Normative References">
		<?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119"?>
		<?rfc include="reference.RFC.3261"?>		
		<?rfc include="reference.RFC.4566"?>
		<?rfc include="reference.RFC.4975"?>
		<?rfc include="reference.RFC.4976"?>
		<?rfc include="reference.RFC.5234"?>
		<?rfc include="reference.RFC.6072"?>
		<?rfc include="reference.RFC.6135"?>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
		<?rfc include="reference.RFC.3724"?>
		<?rfc include="reference.RFC.5246"?>
		<?rfc include="reference.RFC.5764"?>
		<?rfc include="reference.RFC.5952"?>
		<?rfc include="reference.RFC.6043"?>
		<?rfc include="reference.RFC.6091"?>
		<reference anchor="GPP23228">
			<front>
				<title>IP Multimedia Subsystem (IMS); Stage 2</title>
				<author>
					<organization>3GPP</organization>
				</author>
				<date day="13" month="June" year="2011" />
			</front>
			<seriesInfo name="3GPP TS" value="23.228 10.5.0" />
			<format target="http://www.3gpp.org/ftp/Specs/html-info/23228.htm" type="HTML" />
		</reference>
		<reference anchor="DANE">
			<front>
				<title>DNS-based Authentication of Named Entities Work Group</title>
				<author>
					<organization></organization>
				</author>
				<date />
			</front>
			<format target="https://datatracker.ietf.org/wg/dane/charter/" type="HTML" />
		</reference>
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
