<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<rfc category="exp" docName="draft-ietf-pcn-3-state-encoding-01"
     ipr="pre5378Trust200902">
  <?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='http://xml.resource.org/authoring/rfc2629.xslt' ?>

  <!-- Alterations to I-D/RFC boilerplate -->

  <?rfc private="" ?>

  <!-- Default private="" Produce an internal memo 2.5pp shorter than an I-D or RFC -->

  <?rfc topblock="yes" ?>

  <!-- Default topblock="yes" put the famous header block on the first page -->

  <?rfc footer="" ?>

  <!-- Default footer="Expires <date>" override the center footer string -->

  <?rfc header="" ?>

  <!-- Default header="Internet-Draft" override the leftmost header string -->

  <?rfc authorship="yes" ?>

  <!-- Default authorship="yes" Render authors' addresses section -->

  <?rfc rfcprocack="yes" ?>

  <!-- Default rfcprocack="no" add a short sentence acknowledging xml2rfc -->

  <?rfc strict="no" ?>

  <!-- Default strict="no" Don't check I-D nits -->

  <?rfc rfcedstyle="no" ?>

  <!-- Default rfcedstyle="yes" attempt to closely follow finer details from the latest observable RFC-Editor style -->

  <!-- IETF process -->

  <?rfc iprnotified="no" ?>

  <!-- Default iprnotified="no" I haven't disclosed existence of IPR to IETF -->

  <!-- ToC format -->

  <?rfc toc="yes" ?>

  <!-- Default toc="no" No Table of Contents -->

  <?rfc tocappendix="yes" ?>

  <!-- Default tocappendix="yes" control whether the word `Appendix' appears in the table-of-content -->

  <?rfc tocdepth="3" ?>

  <!-- Default tocdepth="3" if toc is "yes", then this determines the depth of the table-of-contents -->

  <?rfc tocindent="yes" ?>

  <!-- Default tocindent="yes" if toc is "yes", indent subsections in the table-of-contents -->

  <?rfc tocnarrow="yes" ?>

  <!-- Default tocnarrow="yes" affects horizontal spacing in the table-of-content -->

  <?rfc tocompact="yes" ?>

  <!-- Default tocompact="yes" if toc is "yes", then setting this to "no" will make it a little less compact -->

  <!-- Cross referencing, footnotes, comments -->

  <?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>

  <!-- Default symrefs="no" Don't use anchors, but use numbers for refs -->

  <?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>

  <!-- Default sortrefs="no" Don't sort references into order -->

  <?rfc comments="yes" ?>

  <!-- Default comments="no" Don't render comments -->

  <?rfc inline="no" ?>

  <!-- Default inline="no" if comments is "yes", then render comments inline; otherwise render them in an `Editorial Comments' section -->

  <?rfc editing="no" ?>

  <!-- Default editing="no" Don't insert editing marks for ease of discussing draft versions -->

  <!-- Pagination control -->

  <?rfc compact="yes"?>

  <!-- Default compact="no" Start sections on new pages -->

  <?rfc subcompact="no"?>

  <!-- Default subcompact="(as compact setting)" yes/no is not quite as compact as yes/yes -->

  <?rfc autobreaks="yes" ?>

  <!-- Default autobreaks="yes" avoid widows and orphans (not perfect) -->

  <!-- HTML formatting control -->

  <?rfc emoticonic="yes" ?>

  <!-- Default emoticonic="no" Doesn't prettify HTML format -->

  <?rfc background="" ?>

  <!-- Default background="" when producing a html file, use this image -->

  <?rfc useobject="no" ?>

  <!-- Default useobject="no" use <object> not <src> when outputting HTML -->

  <?rfc linkmailto="yes" ?>

  <!-- Default linkmailto="yes" generate mailto: URL, as appropriate -->

  <front>
    <title abbrev="3 State PCN Encoding">A PCN encoding using 2 DSCPs to
    provide 3 or more states</title>

    <author fullname="Bob Briscoe" initials="B." surname="Briscoe">
      <organization>BT &amp; UCL</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>B54/77, Adastral Park</street>

          <street>Martlesham Heath</street>

          <city>Ipswich</city>

          <code>IP5 3RE</code>

          <country>UK</country>
        </postal>

        <phone>+44 1473 645196</phone>

        <email>bob.briscoe@bt.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Toby Moncaster" initials="T." surname="Moncaster">
      <organization>BT</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>B54/70, Adastral Park</street>

          <street>Martlesham Heath</street>

          <city>Ipswich</city>

          <code>IP5 3RE</code>

          <country>UK</country>
        </postal>

        <phone>+44 1473 648734</phone>

        <email>toby.moncaster@bt.com</email>

        <uri>http://www.cs.ucl.ac.uk/staff/B.Briscoe/</uri>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Michael Menth" initials="M." surname="Menth">
      <organization>University of Wuerzburg</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>room B206, Institute of Computer Science</street>

          <street>Am Hubland</street>

          <city>Wuerzburg</city>

          <code>D-97074</code>

          <country>Germany</country>
        </postal>

        <phone>+49 931 888 6644</phone>

        <email>menth@informatik.uni-wuerzburg.de</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date day="10" month="February" year="2010" />

    <area>Transport</area>

    <workgroup>Congestion and Pre Congestion</workgroup>

    <keyword>Quality of Service</keyword>

    <keyword>QoS</keyword>

    <keyword>Congestion Control</keyword>

    <keyword>Differentiated Services</keyword>

    <keyword>Admission Control</keyword>

    <keyword>Signalling</keyword>

    <keyword>Protocol</keyword>

    <keyword>Pre-emption</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>Pre-congestion notification (PCN) is a mechanism designed to protect
      the Quality of Service of inelastic flows within a controlled domain. It
      does this by marking packets when traffic load on a link is approaching
      or has exceeded a threshold below the physical link rate. This
      experimental encoding scheme specifies how three encoding states can be
      carried in the IP header using a combination of two DSCPs and the ECN
      bits. The Basic scheme only allows for three encoding states. The Full
      scheme provides 6 states, enough for limited end-to-end support for ECN
      as well.</t>
    </abstract>

    <!-- ================================================================ -->
  </front>

  <middle>
    <!-- ================================================================ -->

    <section anchor="pcn_3_enc_intro" title="Introduction">
      <t>The objective of Pre-Congestion Notification (PCN) <xref
      target="RFC5559"></xref> is to protect the quality of service (QoS) of
      inelastic flows within a Diffserv domain, in a simple, scalable and
      robust fashion. The overall rate of the PCN-traffic is metered on every
      link in the PCN-domain, and PCN-packets are appropriately marked when
      certain configured rates are exceeded. These configured rates are below
      the rate of the link thus providing notification before any congestion
      occurs (hence "pre-congestion notification"). The level of marking
      allows the boundary nodes to make decisions about whether to admit or
      block a new flow request, and (in abnormal circumstances) whether to
      terminate some of the existing flows, thereby protecting the QoS of
      previously admitted flows.</t>

      <t>The baseline encoding described in <xref target="RFC5696"></xref>
      provides for deployment scenarios that only require two PCN encoding
      states. This document describes an experimental extension to the
      base-encoding in the IP header that adds two capabilities: <list
          style="symbols">
          <t>the addition of a third PCN encoding state in the IP header</t>

          <t>preservation of the end-to-end semantics of the ECN field even
          though PCN uses the field within a PCN-region that interrupts the
          end-to-end path</t>
        </list> The second of these capabilities is optional and the reasons
      for doing it are discussed in <xref
      target="pcn_3_enc_ecn_support"></xref>.</t>

      <t>As in the baseline encoding, this extension encoding re-uses the ECN
      bits within the IP header within a controlled PCN-domain. This extension
      requires the use of two DSCPs as described later in this document. This
      experimental scheme is one of three that are being proposed within the
      PCN working group. The aim is to allow implementors to decide which
      scheme is most suitable for possible future standardisation.</t>

      <section title="Changes from Previous Drafts (to be removed by the RFC Editor)">
        <t>From draft-ietf-pcn-3-state-encoding-00 to 01:<list style="symbols">
            <t>Removed text implying the two DSCPs have different priority and
            added <xref target="pcn_3_enc_PHB"></xref> specifying they must
            both have the same PHB.</t>

            <t>Made IANA considerations text more precise.</t>

            <t>Changed variable names for DSCP 1 &amp; DSCP 2 to DSCP n &amp;
            DSCP m to be consistent with baseline encoding.</t>

            <t>Updated refs</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>From draft-moncaster-pcn-3-state-encoding-01 to
        draft-ietf-pcn-3-state-encoding-00: <list style="symbols">
            <t>Changed to WG draft. Title changed from "A three state extended
            PCN encoding scheme"</t>

            <t>Imposed new structure on document. This structure is intended
            to be followed by all extensions to the baseline PCN encoding
            scheme.</t>

            <t>Extensive changes throughout to ensure consistency with the
            baseline PCN encoding scheme.</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>From draft-moncaster-pcn-3-state-encoding-00 to 01: <list
            style="symbols">
            <t>Checked terminology for consistency with <xref
            target="RFC5696"></xref></t>

            <t>Minor editorial changes.</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <!-- ================================================================ -->

    <section anchor="pcn_3_enc_Reqs_notation" title="Requirements notation">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
      document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
      target="RFC2119"></xref>.</t>
    </section>

    <!-- ================================================================ -->

    <section anchor="pcn_3_enc_terminology" title="Terminology">
      <t>Most of the terminology used in this document is defined either in
      <xref target="RFC5559"></xref> or in <xref target="RFC5696"></xref>. The
      following additional terms are defined in this document: <list
          style="symbols">
          <t>PCN-flow - a flow covered by a reservation but which hasn't
          signalled that it requires end-to-end ECN support.</t>

          <t>PCN-enabled-ECN-flow - a flow covered by reservation and for
          which the end-to-end transport has explicitly negotiated ECN support
          from the PCN-boundary-nodes.</t>

          <t>Not-marked (xxx), where xxx represents a standard ECN codepoint -
          packets that are PCN capable but carry no PCN mark. Abbreviated as
          NM(xxx). The (xxx) represents the ECN codepoint that the packet
          arrived with at the PCN-ingress-node e.g. NM(CE) represents a PCN
          capable packet that has no PCN marking but which arrived with the
          ECN bits set to congestion experienced.</t>
        </list></t>
    </section>

    <!-- ================================================================ -->

    <section anchor="pcn_3_enc_why"
             title="The Requirement for Three PCN Encoding States">
      <t>The PCN Marking Behaviours document <xref target="RFC5670"></xref>
      describes proposed PCN schemes that require traffic to be metered and
      marked using both Threshold and Excess Traffic schemes. In order to
      achieve this it is necessary to allow for three PCN encoding states. The
      constraints imposed by the way tunnels process the ECN field severely
      limit how to encode these states as explained in <xref
      target="RFC5696"></xref> and <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-tsvwg-ecn-tunnel"></xref>. The obvious way to provide
      one more encoding state than the base encoding is through the use of an
      additional PCN-compatible DiffServ codepoint.</t>

      <t>One aim of this document is to allow for experiments to show whether
      such schemes are better than those that only employ two PCN encoding
      states. As such, the additional DSCP will be taken from the EXP/LU pools
      defined in <xref target="RFC2474"></xref>. If the experiments
      demonstrate that PCN schemes employing three encoding states are
      significantly better than those only employing two, then at a later date
      IANA might be asked to assign a new PCN enabled DSCP from pool 1. Note
      that there are other experimental encoding schemes being considered
      which only use one DSCP but require either alternative tunnel semantics
      (<xref target="I-D.ietf-pcn-3-in-1-encoding"></xref>) or additional
      signalling (<xref target="I-D.ietf-pcn-psdm-encoding"></xref>)in order
      to work.</t>
    </section>

    <!-- ================================================================ -->

    <section anchor="pcn_3_enc_ecn_support"
             title="Adding Limited End-to-End ECN Support to PCN">
      <t><xref target="I-D.sarker-pcn-ecn-pcn-usecases"></xref> suggests a
      number of use-cases where explicit preservation of end-to-end ECN
      semantics might be needed across a PCN domain. One of the use-cases
      suggests that the end-nodes might be running rate-adaptive codecs that
      would respond to ECN marks by reducing their transmission rate. If the
      sending transport sets the ECT codepoint, the setting of the ECN field
      as it arrives at the PCN ingress node will need to be re-instated as it
      leaves the PCN egress node.</t>

      <t>If a PCN region is starting to suffer pre-congestion then it may make
      sense to expose marks generated within the PCN region by forwarding CE
      marks from the PCN egress to such a rate-adaptive endpoint. They would
      be in addition to any CE marks generated elsewhere on the end-to-end
      path. This would allow the endpoints to reduce the traffic rate. This
      will in turn help to alleviate the pre-congestion, potentially averting
      any need for call blocking or termination. However, the 'leaking' of CE
      marks out of the PCN region is potentially dangerous and could violate
      <xref target="RFC4774"></xref> if the end hosts don't understand ECN
      (see section 18.1.4 of <xref target="RFC3168"></xref>).</t>

      <t>Therefore, a PCN region can only support end-to-end ECN if the
      PCN-boundary-nodes are sure that the end-to-end transport is
      ECN-capable. That way the PCN-egress-nodes can ensure that they only
      expose CE marks to those receivers that will correctly interpret them as
      a notification of congestion. The end-points may indicate they are
      ECN-capable through some higher-layer signalling process that sets up
      their reservation with the PCN boundary nodes. The exact process of
      negotiation is beyond the scope of this document but is likely to
      involve explicit two way signalling between the end-host and the
      PCN-domain.</t>

      <t>In the absence of such signalling the default behaviour of the PCN
      egress node will be to clear the ECN field to 00 as in the baseline PCN
      encoding <xref target="RFC5696"></xref>.</t>
    </section>

    <!-- ================================================================ -->

    <section anchor="pcn_3_enc_IP" title="Encoding Three PCN States in IP">
      <t>The three state PCN encoding scheme is based closely on that defined
      in <xref target="RFC5696"></xref> so that there will be no compatibility
      issues if a PCN-domain changes from using the baseline encoding scheme
      to the experimental scheme described here. There are two versions of the
      scheme. The basic three state scheme allows for carrying both
      Threshold-marked (ThM) and Excess-traffic-marked (ETM) traffic. The full
      scheme additionally allows end-to-end ECN to be carried across the
      PCN-domain.</t>

      <section anchor="pcn_3_enc_base" title="Basic Three State Encoding">
        <t><xref target="pcn_3_enc_Tab_3_state_base"></xref> below shows how
        to encode the three PCN states in IP.</t>

        <texttable anchor="pcn_3_enc_Tab_3_state_base"
                   title="Encoding three PCN states in IP">
          <ttcol align="center">DSCP</ttcol>

          <ttcol align="center">Not-ECT (00)</ttcol>

          <ttcol align="center">ECT(0) (10)</ttcol>

          <ttcol align="center">ECT(1) (01)</ttcol>

          <ttcol align="center">CE (11)</ttcol>

          <c>DSCP n</c>

          <c>Not-PCN</c>

          <c>NM</c>

          <c>CU</c>

          <c>ThM</c>

          <c>DSCP m</c>

          <c>Not-PCN</c>

          <c>CU</c>

          <c>CU</c>

          <c>ETM</c>

          <postamble>(where DSCP n is a PCN-compatible DiffServ codepoint (see
          <xref target="RFC5696"></xref>) and DSCP m is a PCN-compatible DSCP
          from the EXP/LU pools as defined in <xref
          target="RFC2474"></xref>)</postamble>
        </texttable>
      </section>

      <section anchor="pcn_3_enc_full" title="Full Three State Encoding">
        <t><xref target="pcn_3_enc_Tab_3_state_full" /> shows how to
        additionally carry the end-to-end ECN state in the IP header.</t>

        <texttable anchor="pcn_3_enc_Tab_3_state_full"
                   title="Encoding three PCN states in IP">
          <ttcol align="center">DSCP</ttcol>

          <ttcol align="center">Not-ECT (00)</ttcol>

          <ttcol align="center">ECT(0) (10)</ttcol>

          <ttcol align="center">ECT(1) (01)</ttcol>

          <ttcol align="center">CE (11)</ttcol>

          <c>DSCP n</c>

          <c>Not-PCN</c>

          <c>NM(Not-ECT)</c>

          <c>NM(CE)</c>

          <c>ThM</c>

          <c>DSCP m</c>

          <c>Not-PCN</c>

          <c>NM(ECT(0))</c>

          <c>NM(ECT(1))</c>

          <c>ETM</c>

          <postamble>(where DSCP n is a PCN-compatible DiffServ codepoint (see
          <xref target="RFC5696" />) and DSCP m is a PCN-compatible DSCP from
          the EXP/LU pools as defined in <xref
          target="RFC2474" />)</postamble>
        </texttable>

        <t>The four different Not-marked (NM) states allow for the addition of
        limited end-to-end ECN support as explained in the previous
        section.</t>

        <note title="Warning">
          <t>In order to comply with this encoding all the nodes within the
          PCN-domain MUST be configured with this encoding scheme. However
          there may be operators who choose not to be fully compliant with the
          scheme. If an operator chooses to leave some PCN-interior-nodes that
          only support two marking states (the baseline encoding <xref
          target="RFC5696" />), then they must be aware of the following:
          Ideally such nodes would be configured to indicate pre-congestion or
          congestion using the ETM state since this would ensure they could
          notify worst-case congestion, however this is not possible since it
          requires the packets to be re-marked to DSCP m (hence altering the
          baseline encoding). This means that such nodes will only be able to
          indicate ThM traffic.</t>
        </note>
      </section>

      <section anchor="pcn_3_enc_PHB"
               title="Common Diffserv Per-Hop Behaviour">
        <t>Packets carrying Diffserv codepoint 'DSCP n' or 'DSCP m' MUST all
        be treated with the same Diffserv PHB <xref target="RFC2474"></xref>.
        The choice of PHB is discussed in <xref target="RFC5559"></xref> and
        <xref target="RFC5696"></xref>.</t>

        <t>Two DSCPs are merely used to provide sufficient PCN encoding
        states, there is no need or intention to provide different scheduling
        or drop preference for each row in the table of PCN codepoints.
        Specifically:<list style="symbols">
            <t>Both DSCPs MUST be served in the same queue to prevent
            reordering within an application flow.</t>

            <t>Both DSCPs MUST be assigned the same drop preference. Note that
            <xref target="RFC5670"></xref> already provides for preferential
            drop of excess-rate-marked packets, so assigning additional drop
            preference at the coarser granularity of each DSCP would be
            incorrect.</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="pcn_3_enc_valid_ingress"
               title="Valid and invalid codepoint transitions at PCN-ingress-nodes">
        <t>A PCN-ingress-node operating the Basic version of the 3-State
        Encoding scheme MUST set the Not-marked codepoint on any arriving
        packet that belongs to a PCN-flow. It MUST set the not-PCN codepoint
        on any other packet.</t>

        <t>A PCN-ingress-node operating the Full version of the 3-State
        Encoding scheme MUST establish whether a packet is a member of a
        PCN-enabled-ECN-flow. If it is, the PCN-ingress-node MUST set the
        appropriate NM(xxx) codepoint depending on the value carried in the
        ECN field of that packet. To be clear: <list style="symbols">
            <t>A packet carrying the not-ECT codepoint in the ECN field MUST
            be assigned the NM(not-ECT) codepoint</t>

            <t>A packet carrying the ECT(0) codepoint in the ECN field MUST be
            assigned the NM(ECT(0)) codepoint</t>

            <t>A packet carrying the ECT(1) codepoint in the ECN field MUST be
            assigned the NM(ECT(1)) codepoint</t>

            <t>A packet carrying the CE codepoint in the ECN field MUST be
            assigned the NM(CE) codepoint</t>
          </list> If it is not a member of such a flow then the behaviour MUST
        be the same as for the Basic version of the Encoding scheme.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="pcn_3_enc_valid_interior"
               title="Valid and invalid codepoint transitions at PCN-interior-nodes">
        <t>A PCN-interior-node MUST obey the following rules: <list
            style="symbols">
            <t>It MUST NOT change the not-PCN codepoint to any other
            codepoint.</t>

            <t>It MAY change any Not-marked codepoint to either the
            Threshold-marked or Excess-traffic-marked codepoints.</t>

            <t>It MUST NOT change a Not-marked codepoint to the not-PCN
            codepoint.</t>

            <t>A Not-marked codepoint MUST NOT be changed to any other
            Not-marked codepoint.</t>

            <t>It MAY change the ThM codepoint to the ETM codepoint but it
            MUST NOT change the ThM codepoint to any other codepoint.</t>

            <t>It MUST NOT change the ETM codepoint to any other
            codepoint.</t>
          </list> Obviously in every case a codepoint can remain unchanged.
        The precise rules governing which valid transition to use are set out
        in <xref target="RFC5670"></xref></t>
      </section>

      <!-- ================================================================ -->

      <section anchor="pcn_3_enc_forward"
               title="Forwarding traffic out of the PCN-domain">
        <t>As each packet exits the PCN-domain, the PCN-egress-node MUST check
        whether it belongs to a PCN-enabled-ECN-flow. If it belongs to such a
        flow then the following rules dictate how the ECN field should be
        reset: <list style="symbols">
            <t>A packet carrying the not-PCN codepoint MUST be given the
            not-ECT codepoint.</t>

            <t>A packet carrying the NM(not-ECT) codepoint MUST be assigned
            the not-ECT codepoint.</t>

            <t>A packet carrying the NM(ECT(0)) codepoint MUST be assigned the
            ECT(0) codepoint.</t>

            <t>A packet carrying the NM(ECT(1)) codepoint MUST be assigned the
            ECT(1) codepoint.</t>

            <t>A packet carrying the NM(CE) codepoint MUST be assigned the CE
            codepoint.</t>

            <t>A packet carrying the ThM codepoint MUST be assigned CE
            codepoint.</t>

            <t>A packet carrying the ETM codepoint MUST be assigned CE
            codepoint.</t>
          </list> If the packet is part of a PCN-flow then it MUST be assigned
        the not-ECT codepoint regardless of which PCN-codepoint it
        carried.</t>

        <t>In addition all packets should have their DSCP reset to the
        appropriate DSCP for the next hop. If the next hop is not another PCN
        region this will not be a PCN-compatible DSCP, and by default will be
        the best-efforts DSCP. Alterntively, higher layer signalling
        mechanisms may allow the DSCP that packets entered the PCN-domain with
        to be reinstated.</t>
      </section>

      <!-- ================================================================ -->
    </section>

    <section anchor="pcn_3_enc_protocol"
             title="PCN-domain support for the PCN extension encoding">
      <t>PCN traffic MUST be marked with a DiffServ codepoint that indicates
      PCN is enabled. To comply with the PCN extension encoding, codepoint
      'DSCP n' MUST be a PCN-compatible DSCP assigned by IANA for use with the
      baseline PCN encoding <xref target="RFC5696"></xref> while 'DSCP m' can
      be a DSCP from pools 2 or 3 for experimental and local use <xref
      target="RFC2474"></xref>. The exact choice of DSCP may vary between
      PCN-domains but MUST be fixed within each PCN-domain.</t>

      <section anchor="pcn_3_enc_transport"
               title="End-to-End transport behaviour compliant with the PCN extension encoding">
        <t>Transports wishing to use both PCN and end-to-end ECN MUST
        establish that their path supports this combination. Support of
        end-to-end ECN by PCN-boundary-nodes is OPTIONAL. Therefore transports
        MUST check with both the PCN-ingress-node and PCN-egress-node for each
        flow. The sending of such a request MUST NOT be taken to mean the
        request has been granted. The PCN-boundary-nodes MAY choose to inform
        the end-node of a successful request. The exact mechanism for such
        negotiation is beyond the scope of this document. A transport that
        receives no response or a negative response to a request to support
        end-to-end ECN within a flow reservation MUST set the ECN field of all
        subsequent packets in that flow to Not-ECT if it wishes to guarantee
        that the flow will receive PCN treatment.</t>

        <t>If a domain wishes to use the full scheme described in <xref
        target="pcn_3_enc_Tab_3_state_full"></xref> all nodes in that domain
        MUST be configured to understand the full scheme.</t>

        <t>If either of a PCN ingress-egress pair does not support end-to-end
        ECN or if the end-to-end transport does not request support for
        end-to-end ECN then the PCN-boundary-nodes MUST assume the packet
        belongs to a PCN-flow.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <!-- ================================================================ -->

    <section title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>This document asks IANA to assign one DiffServ codepoint from Pool 2
      or Pool 3 (for experimental/local use)<xref target="RFC2474"></xref>.
      Should this experimental PCN scheme prove sufficiently successful then
      IANA will be requested in a later document to assign a dedicated
      DiffServ codepoint from pool 1 for standards use and the experimental
      codepoint will be returned to its IANA pool.</t>
    </section>

    <!-- ================================================================ -->

    <section anchor="pcn_3_enc_security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>The security concerns relating to this extended PCN encoding are
      essentially the same as those in <xref target="RFC5696"></xref>.</t>

      <t>This extension coding gives end-to-end support for the ECN nonce
      <xref target="RFC3540"></xref>, which is intended to protect the sender
      against the receiver or against network elements concealing a congestion
      experienced marking or a lost packet. PCN-based reservations combined
      with end-to-end ECN are intended for partially inelastic traffic using
      rate-adaptive codecs. Therefore the end-to-end transport is unlikely to
      be TCP, but at this time the nonce has only been defined for TCP
      transports.</t>
    </section>

    <!-- ================================================================ -->

    <section anchor="pcn_3_enc_Conclusions" title="Conclusions">
      <t>This document describes an extended encoding scheme for PCN that
      provides for three encoding states as well as optional support for
      end-to-end ECN. The encoding scheme builds on the baseline encoding
      described in <xref target="RFC5696"></xref>. Using this encoding scheme
      it is possible for operators to conduct experiments to check whether the
      addition of an extra encoding state will significantly improve the
      performance of PCN. It will also allow experiments to determine whether
      there is a need for end-to-end ECN support within the PCN-domain (as
      against end-to-end ECN support through the use of IP-in-IP tunnelling or
      by downgrading the traffic to a lower service class).</t>
    </section>

    <!-- ================================================================ -->

    <section anchor="pcn_enc_Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>This document builds extensively on work done in the PCN working
      group by Kwok Ho Chan, Georgios Karagiannis, Philip Eardley, Joe Babiarz
      and others. Full details of alternative schemes that were considered for
      adoption can be found in the document <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-pcn-encoding-comparison"></xref>.</t>
    </section>

    <!-- ================================================================ -->

    <section anchor="pcn_enc_Comments_Solicited" title="Comments Solicited">
      <t>(Section to be removed by RFC_Editor) Comments and questions are
      encouraged and very welcome. They can be addressed to the IETF Transport
      Area working group mailing list &lt;tsvwg@ietf.org&gt;, and/or to the
      authors.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <!-- ================================================================ -->

    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119" ?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4774" ?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5670"    ?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5696" ?>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.I-D.ietf-tsvwg-ecn-tunnel" ?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2474" ?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3168" ?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3540" ?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5559"    ?>

      <?rfc include="reference.I-D.ietf-pcn-encoding-comparison"    ?>

      <?rfc include="reference.I-D.sarker-pcn-ecn-pcn-usecases"  ?>

      <?rfc include="reference.I-D.ietf-pcn-3-in-1-encoding"    ?>

      <?rfc include="reference.I-D.ietf-pcn-psdm-encoding"    ?>
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
