<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
        <!ENTITY rfc2119 PUBLIC ''
                'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml'>
        ]>

<rfc category="info" ipr="trust200902" docName="draft-newton-weirds-arin-whoisrws-00">

    <?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>

    <?rfc toc="yes" ?>
    <?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
    <?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
    <?rfc iprnotified="no" ?>
    <?rfc strict="yes" ?>

    <front>
        <title>ARIN's RESTful Web Service for Whois Data</title>
        <author initials='A.L' surname="Newton" fullname='Andrew Lee Newton'>
            <organization>American Registry for Internet Numbers</organization>
        </author>
        <date/>
        <abstract>
            <t>This document describes the RESTful Web Service for Whois data as implemented
                and fielded by the American Registry for Internet Numbers (ARIN). ARIN calls
                this service Whois-RWS.
            </t>
            <t>The purpose of this document is to facilitate discussion and serve as input into a
                standards process in this area, currently being discussed on the
                WHOIS-based Extensible Internet Registration Data Service (WEIRDS)
                mailing list (https://www.ietf.org/mailman/listinfo/weirds).
            </t>
            <t>
                Please excuse this very rough initial draft. It is roughly based on information
                currently published on ARIN's website. However, future revisions of this document
                are planned, including discussions on lessons learned by ARIN from the
                deployment of Whois-RWS and thoughts on a future, unified standard.
            </t>
        </abstract>
    </front>

    <middle>
        <section title="Requirements notation">
            <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL",
                "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY",
                and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as
                described in<xref target="RFC2119"/>.
            </t>
        </section>

        <section title="Background">
            <t>ARIN offers public access to ARIN registration data via a number of services.
                Traditionally, these services are known in the industry as "Whois" in reference to
                the public data service of the ARPANET, precursor of today's modern Internet. Whois
                services are offered by all the Regional Internet Registries (RIRs), most Internet
                Routing Registries (IRRs) and most domain name registries and registrars.
            </t>
            <t>
                Traditionally, Whois services have been offered using the NICNAME/WHOIS protocol as
                described by RFC 954 and RFC 3912. This protocol is a simple, text based TCP
                protocol registered with in the Internet Assigned Numbers Authority (IANA) for
                well-known port 43. RFC 3912, the most recent specification for the protocol, does
                not define either data types or data formats. As a consequence, Whois data varies
                from service provider to service provider and is far from ideal for programmatic
                consumption.
            </t>
            <t>
                ARIN provides to the general public services for
                read-only access to ARIN's registration data. These services include a user-friendly
                web site (http://whois.arin.net), a RESTful Web Service, and a NICNAME/WHOIS port 43
                service. For the purposes of programmatic consumption, ARIN recommends the use of
                the RESTful Web Service and strongly discourages the use of the NICNAME/WHOIS port
                43 service.
            </t>
            <t>
                This document describes the RESTful Web Service for ARIN's Whois data, which is
                known as Whois-RWS.
            </t>
        </section>

        <section title="Data Model">

            <t>
                ARIN's Whois-RWS data model is composed of six first order objects: networks,
                autonomous
                system numbers, delegations, organizations, points of contact, and customers. Each
                of these types, except delegations, is directly addressable in a Whois service via a
                handle (i.e. identifier). Within the Whois RESTful Web Service, these handles are
                part of URLs that may be used to identify objects in ARIN's Whois registration
                database by external, non-ARIN systems.
            </t>

            <section title="Networks and Autonomous System Numbers">
                <t>
                    Networks and Autonomous System Numbers (ASNs) are collectively referred to as
                    "resources" in ARIN parlance (this should not be confused with the term
                    "resources" in the context of RESTful Web Services and Resource Oriented
                    Architectures). They are the pieces of information assigned or allocated to
                    organizations for the coordinated administration and operation of the Internet.
                </t>
                <t>
                    Networks signify the allocation or assignment of IP address space and the
                    contiguous IP CIDR blocks that make up that IP address space. Handles for IPv4
                    networks start with "NET-", and handles for IPv6 networks start with "NET6-".
                </t>
                <t>
                    Autonomous System Numbers (ASNs) are used for the proper routing of Internet
                    packets. ARIN assigns ASNs in ranges, therefore a single ASN is part of an ASN
                    range allocation. The handles for these registrations start with "AS" and are
                    usually appended with the first number of the ASN range.
                </t>
            </section>

            <section title="Delegations">
                <t>
                    Delegations contain the information necessary for Reverse DNS, including the
                    associated nameservers, and DNS DS record information. Unlike the other first
                    order objects, delegations do not have a Handle. Rather, they are directly
                    addressable in a Whois service via a delegation name (i.e. 0.192.in-addr.arpa.).
                </t>
            </section>

            <section title="Organizations and Customers">
                <t>
                    Organizations are the registrants of resources and have a direct relationship
                    with ARIN. Organizations may be associated with many resources. Customers do not
                    have a direct relationship with ARIN and, at present, may only be associated
                    with one network registration.
                </t>
                <t>
                    Customer handles start with "C", while organization handles have no prefix.
                </t>
            </section>

            <section title="Points of Contact">
                <t>
                    A Point of Contact (POC) is the registration of names, mailboxes, and/or phone
                    numbers which fulfill technical or administrative functions on behalf of either
                    an organization or a resource. POC handles are usually appended with "-ARIN"
                    though there are a few exceptions.
                </t>
            </section>

            <section title="General Query Behavior">
                <t>
                    For the first order objects addressable via handle, ARIN's Whois services also
                    allow for searching against names and other appropriate fields contained within
                    those objects. Unless otherwise specified, these searches are case insensitive.
                    Because ARIN's networks are composed of multiple CIDR based network blocks,
                    searches by IP address or CIDR notation may sometimes yield what may, at first
                    blush, appear incorrect. For instance, a search for a particular CIDR block may
                    yield a network that covers the given CIDR block and additional CIDR blocks
                    composing the network, while a search by an IP address will always yield the
                    network or networks in which the IP address falls.
                </t>
            </section>
        </section>

        <section title="Use of REST over HTTP">

            <section title="Data Formats and Versions">
                <t>
                    RESTful web services are not strictly tied to XML. ARIN's Whois RESTful Web
                    Service offers data in XML, JSON, plain text, and HTML (actually, XHTML).
                    However, ARIN's first order data format is XML as there are many format and
                    validation tools readily available for it, and the other formats are offered on
                    a best-effort basis.
                </t>
                <t>
                    If no desired format is specified, XML is the default format.
                </t>
                <t>
                    Specifying a desired data format may be accomplished in one of two ways: either
                    using the HTTP Accept header or using "file extensions".
                    A "file extension" appends a DOS like file extension to the path.
                </t>
                <t>
                    Though there only exists one version of this RESTful interface, it is possible
                    that the "data model" of the structured data such as XML and JSON that is output
                    by this service will need revision. Should it be possible for ARIN to provide a
                    backward compatible version, the HTTP Accept header is the mechanism for
                    specifying the desired version as well as the data format.
                </t>
                <t>
                    The MIME type used in the Accept header will follow the format of
                    "application/arin.whoisrws-{version}+{format}". To use the latest version
                    of this service you would simply use the default MIME types of
                    "application/xml" or "application/json".
                </t>
                <texttable anchor='accept_header_values'>
                    <preamble>The following table lists the data types and their associated MIME
                        types and file extensions.
                    </preamble>
                    <ttcol align='center'>Data Type</ttcol>
                    <ttcol align='center'>Current Version MIME Type</ttcol>
                    <ttcol align='center'>Version 1 MIME Type</ttcol>
                    <ttcol align='center'>File Extension</ttcol>
                    <c>XML</c>
                    <c>application/xml</c>
                    <c>application/arin.whoisrws-v1+xml</c>
                    <c>xml</c>
                    <c>JSON</c>
                    <c>application/json</c>
                    <c>application/arin.whoisrws-v1+json</c>
                    <c>json</c>
                    <c>plain text</c>
                    <c>text/plain</c>
                    <c></c>
                    <c>txt</c>
                    <c>HTML</c>
                    <c>text/html</c>
                    <c></c>
                    <c>html</c>
                </texttable>
            </section>
            <section title="Schemas">
                <t>Relax NG stuff goes here.</t>
                <t>Explanation of JSON and Badgerfish goes here.</t>
            </section>

            <section title="Resource Oriented URLs">
                <t>
                    URLs point to resources. A typical URL might be
                    http://whois.arin.net/rest/poc/ALN-ARIN,
                    which is a URL pointing to the author of this document.
                    Conceptually, this can be broken into a
                    base URL
                    and the resource identifier:
                    <list style="hanging">
                        <t hangText="base URL:">http://whois.arin.net/rest</t>
                        <t hangText="resource:">/poc/ALN-ARIN</t>
                    </list>
                    The base URL is just where ARIN is hosting the service.
                    The real interesting parts are the bits that identify the resources:
                    <list style="hanging">
                        <t hangText="/poc">
                            this indicates the resource is a Point of Contact.
                        </t>
                        <t hangText="/ALN-ARIN">
                            this is the unique identifier for the Point of Contact, or the POC
                            Handle.
                        </t>
                    </list>
                </t>
                <t>
                    The Whois-RWS data model has six types of addressable resources.
                    These are reflected in Whois-RWS in the following way:
                    <list style="hanging">
                        <t hangText="/poc">
                            point of contact
                        </t>
                        <t hangText="/org">
                            organization
                        </t>
                        <t hangText="/net">
                            a network
                        </t>
                        <t hangText="/asn">
                            autonomous system number(s)
                        </t>
                        <t hangText="/customer">
                            a customer of an organization
                        </t>
                        <t hangText="/rdns">
                            delegations in the reverse DNS
                        </t>
                    </list>
                </t>
                <section title="Resources Related to Resources">
                    <t>
                        In the ARIN Whois data model, resources have relationships to other
                        resources. Getting references to these resources can be accomplished by
                        addressing the resource in question and applying a resource type qualifier.
                    </t>
                    <t>
                        Here is the list of relationships (where "XXXX" signifies a handle):
                        <list style="hanging">
                            <t hangText="/poc/XXXX">
                                <list style="hanging">
                                    <t hangText="/orgs (i.e. /poc/XXXX/orgs)">lists the
                                        organizations associated with a given POC
                                    </t>
                                    <t hangText="/asns (i.e. /poc/XXXX/asns)">lists the autonomous
                                        system numbers associated with a given POC
                                    </t>
                                    <t hangText="/nets (i.e. /poc/XXXX/nets)">lists the networks
                                        associated with a given POC
                                    </t>
                                </list>
                            </t>
                            <t hangText="/org/XXXX">
                                <list style="hanging">
                                    <t hangText="/pocs (i.e. /org/XXXX/pocs)">lists the points of
                                        contact associated with a given organization
                                    </t>
                                    <t hangText="/asns (i.e. /org/XXXX/asns)">lists the autonomous
                                        system numbers associated with a given organization
                                    </t>
                                    <t hangText="/nets (i.e. /org/XXXX/nets)">lists the networks
                                        associated with a given organization
                                    </t>
                                </list>
                            </t>
                            <t hangText="/asn/XXXX">
                                <list style="hanging">
                                    <t hangText="/pocs (i.e. /asn/XXXX/pocs)">lists the points of
                                        contact associated with a given autonomous system number
                                    </t>
                                </list>
                            </t>
                            <t hangText="/net/XXXX">
                                <list style="hanging">
                                    <t hangText="/pocs (i.e. /net/XXXX/pocs)">lists the points of
                                        contact associated with a given network
                                    </t>
                                    <t hangText="/parent (i.e. /net/XXXX/parent)">lists the parnet
                                        network of a given network
                                    </t>
                                    <t hangText="/children (i.e. /net/XXXX/children)">lists the
                                        child networks associated with a given network
                                    </t>
                                    <t hangText="/rdns (i.e. /net/XXXX/rdns)">lists the reverse DNS
                                        delegations associated with a given network
                                    </t>
                                </list>
                            </t>
                            <t hangText="/rdns/XXXX">
                                <list style="hanging">
                                    <t hangText="/nets (i.e. /rdns/XXXX/nets)">lists the networks
                                        associated with a given reverse DNS delegation
                                    </t>
                                </list>
                            </t>
                        </list>
                    </t>
                </section>
                <section title="Unrelated Lists of Resources">
                    <t>
                        Unrelated lists of resources may be addressed using URL matrix parameters.
                        As an example, to find organizations with the name "ARIN", the /orgs list is
                        appended with the matrix parameter name to form /orgs;name=ARIN (this is
                        without the base URL).
                    </t>
                    <t>
                        Here is the list of resources and their supported matrix parameters:
                        <list style="hanging">
                            <t hangText="/orgs">
                                <list style="hanging">
                                    <t hangText="handle">the handle of the organization</t>
                                    <t hangText="name">the name of the organization</t>
                                    <t hangText="dba">the "doing-business-as" name of the
                                        organization
                                    </t>
                                </list>
                            </t>
                            <t hangText="/customers">
                                <list style="hanging">
                                    <t hangText="handle">the handle of the customer</t>
                                    <t hangText="name">the name of the customer</t>
                                </list>
                            </t>
                            <t hangText="/pocs">
                                <list style="hanging">
                                    <t hangText="handle">the handle of the POC</t>
                                    <t hangText="domain">the domain name of an email address of the
                                        POC
                                    </t>
                                    <t hangText="first">the first name of the POC</t>
                                    <t hangText="middle">the middle name of the POC</t>
                                    <t hangText="last">the last name of the POC</t>
                                    <t hangText="company">the company name registered by the POC</t>
                                    <t hangText="city">the city registered by the POC</t>
                                </list>
                            </t>
                            <t hangText="/asns">
                                <list style="hanging">
                                    <t hangText="handle">the handle of the autonomous system
                                        number
                                    </t>
                                    <t hangText="name">the name of the autonomous system number</t>
                                </list>
                            </t>
                            <t hangText="/nets">
                                <list style="hanging">
                                    <t hangText="handle">the handle of the network</t>
                                    <t hangText="name">the name of the network</t>
                                </list>
                            </t>
                        </list>
                    </t>
                </section>
                <section title="IP Addresses">
                    <t>
                        In the ARIN data model, an IP "network" is a set of associated IP address
                        blocks and the information related to these IP address blocks and the set as
                        a whole. A network can be composed of one IP address block or of multiple IP
                        address blocks. Networks are also hierarchical, meaning that a network can
                        have a parent and can have children. An IP address or range of IP addresses
                        can therefore fall within the IP address block of multiple networks.
                    </t>
                    <t>
                        To get the networks that a particular IP address may fall within, one can
                        use the /ip/XX.XX.XX.XX resource, where XX.XX.XX.XX signifies the IP
                        address.
                    </t>
                    <t>
                        Networks may be looked up as well by supplying the full CIDR notation of a
                        range. To use the full CIDR notation, the resource looks like
                        /cidr/XX.XX.XX.XX/YY where XX.XX.XX.XX is the IP address prefix and YY is
                        the CIDR length.
                    </t>
                    <t>
                        Resources relative to the networks may be fetched using the /less and /more
                        path prefixes. /less will find the networks that are less specific in scope
                        (or wider), and /more will find the networks that are more specific in scope
                        (or narrower).
                    </t>
                </section>
                <section title="Aggregate Resources">
                    <t>
                        Though Whois-RWS breaks down the ARIN data model into distinct resources,
                        end users have been accustomed to seeing many related resources with one
                        query over the NICNAME/WHOIS port 43 service. While this can be accomplished
                        by any Whois-RWS clients with multiple queries, an aggregate resources
                        can reduce the number of queries and make this use case easier on client
                        implementers.
                    </t>
                    <t>
                        For resources under /org, /net, /asn, and /ip, the URL may be appended with
                        "/pft" to produce an aggregate resource which includes the resource being
                        queried and related resources. If you can guess what /pft means, I'll buy
                        you
                        a beer.
                    </t>
                </section>
                <section title="Query Parameters">
                    <section title="Showing More of Detail">
                        <t>
                            By default, lists of resources only show references to the resources.
                            However, lists can be expanded to show full detail by tacking on a
                            showDetails=true URL query parameter
                            (e.g.http://whois.arin.net/rest/org/ARIN/pocs?showDetails=true). This
                            query parameter also forces a resource to list its related resources in
                            line.
                        </t>
                    </section>
                    <section title="Showing Only Points of Contact">
                        <t>
                            Some organizations have many, many associated resources. Having all
                            those resources returned when gathering information about an
                            organization maybe very undesirable. To allow getting all the POCs of an
                            organization without taking the penalty of retrieving all the resources
                            of the organization, the showPocs=true parameter may be used. This
                            parameter is only recognized when an organization's information is
                            referenced by handle.
                        </t>
                    </section>
                    <section title="Showing ARIN Resources">
                        <t>
                            In the past, ARIN's NICNAME/WHOIS service yielded a "No Match" result
                            for searches of IP address space unallocated by ARIN but within ARIN's
                            IP address pool. This was somewhat confusing and could possibly mislead
                            a person into thinking the address space is simply unallocated to any
                            available address pool (in other words, still held by the IANA). This
                            has been changed in ARIN's NICNAME/WHOIS service so it will return the
                            appropriate ARIN network allocation for IP addresses unallocated by
                            ARIN. By default, the RESTful service will also return the appropriate
                            ARIN network allocation for IP addresses unallocated by ARIN to ARIN
                            constituents.
                        </t>
                        <t>
                            If the behavior is desired, the showARIN=false query parameter may be
                            used on IP and CIDR queries.
                        </t>
                    </section>
                </section>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section title="HTTP Caching">
            <t>
                One of the advantages of a RESTful Web Service is that HTTP infrastructure may be
                employed to make it more reliable and/or robust. HTTP caching is one such tool to
                help with these goals. ARIN employs caching at multiple levels and customized to
                address the query pattern seen against ARIN's services.
            </t>
            <t>
                If HTTP caching is be employed on the client side, there are a number of issues to
                consider to craft a custom caching solution.
            </t>
            <t>
                First caching should be restricted to URLs that have the highest likelihood of
                remaining in the cache using the caches retention strategy. In almost any scenario,
                caching RESTful resources under /rest/ip will lead to a large dataset and a low
                cache hit ratio. However, it is likely acceptable to cache resources under
                /rest/org, /rest/poc, and /rest/net. It is recommended that cache statistics be
                available for proper cache tuning.
            </t>

            <t>
                Second, many HTTP caches base the cache objects on URLs. However, the Accept header
                dictates the content of the object and may not be part of the cache key of cached
                objects. Therefore it is possible to get a cached object of one type when another
                type was requested. For instance, /rest/poc/KOSTE-ARIN might return XML when JSON
                was requested. To overcome this, it is advisable to use file extensions to specify
                data format as file extensions are part of the URL.
            </t>
        </section>

        <section title="Security Considerations">
            <t>Of course there are some... but I'm not gonna tell you what they are.</t>
            <t>Seriously.... to be discussed in future revisions.</t>
        </section>
        <section title="Lessons Learned">
            <t>to be discussed in a future revision, the lessons we have learned from this</t>
        </section>
    </middle>

    <back>
        <references title='Normative References'>&rfc2119;</references>
    </back>

</rfc>