<?xml version="1.0"?> 
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
  <!ENTITY rfc2119 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml'> 
  <!ENTITY rfc5023 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5023.xml'>
  <!ENTITY rfc5988 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5988.xml'>
]>
<?rfc toc="yes"?> 
<?rfc strict="yes"?> 
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?> 
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?> 
<?rfc compact="yes"?> 
<rfc category="std" ipr="trust200811" docName="draft-snell-additional-link-relations-04"> 
  <front> 
    <title abbrev="Additional Link Relations"> 
      Additional Link Relation Types
    </title> 
 
    <author initials="J.M." surname="Snell" fullname="James M Snell"> 
      <address> 
        <email>jasnell@gmail.com</email> 
      </address> 
    </author> 
    
    <date month="May" year="2012" /> 
 
    <area>Applications</area> 
    <keyword>I-D</keyword> 
    <keyword>http</keyword> 
    <keyword>link</keyword> 
    <keyword>rel</keyword>
 
    <abstract> 
      <t>This specification defines a number of additional Link Relation Types
      that can used for a variety of purposes..</t> 
    </abstract> 
 
  </front> 
  
  <middle> 
    <section anchor="intro" title="Introduction"> 
 
      <t>This specification defines a number of additional Link Relation Types
      for a variety of common linking scenarios.</t> 
      
      <t>In this document, the key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", 
      "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" 
      are to be  interpreted as described in <xref target="RFC2119" />.</t> 
  
    </section> 
        
    <section anchor="about" title="&quot;about&quot;">
    
      <t>The "about" Link relation can be used to refer to a resource
      that is the subject of the link's context. Multiple subjects can be 
      indicated through the use of multiple "about" link relations.</t>
      
      <t>For example, if the context resource is a review about a particular
      product, the "about" link can be used to reference the URL of the 
      product:</t>
      
      <figure><artwork>
  HTTP/1.1 200 OK
  Content-Type: application/json
  Link: &lt;http://store.example.org/product/abc&gt;; rel="about"
  
  {...}
      </artwork></figure>
    
    </section>
        
    <section anchor="preview" title="&quot;preview&quot;">
    
      <t>The "preview" Link relation can be usd to refer to a resource
      that serves as a preview of the link's context, for instance, a 
      screen capture of a video, or a brief snippet of audio from a 
      song.</t>
    
    </section>
        
    <section anchor="privacy-policy" title="&quot;privacy-policy&quot;">

      <t>The "privacy-policy" Link relation can be used to refer to a 
      resource describing the privacy policy associated with the link's
      context. The privacy policy can be any resource that discloses what
      personal information about the user is collected, and how that 
      personal information is stored, used, managed and disclosed to other
      parties.</t>
      
      <t>For example, an HTTP server that collects personal information 
      about a user throughout the course of the user's interaction with 
      the service can include "privacy-policy" Links within all HTTP 
      Responses using any combination of Link headers or links embedded 
      in the response payload:</t>

      <figure><preamble>An example showing various locations where 
      privacy-policy links can potentially appear:</preamble><artwork>
  HTTP/1.1 200 OK
  Content-Type: text/html
  Link: &lt;/privacy-policy.html&gt;; rel="privacy-policy"
  
  &lt;html&gt;
    &lt;head&gt;
      ...
      &lt;link rel="privacy-policy" href="/privacy-policy.html"&gt;
      ...
    &lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;body&gt;
      ...
      &lt;a rel="privacy-policy" href="/privacy-policy.html"&gt;
        Privacy Policy
      &lt;/a&gt;
      ...
    &lt;/body&gt;    
  &lt;/html&gt;
      </artwork></figure>
      
      <t>Note that in the absence of clear legal obligations placed on an 
      entity either through contract or law, the presence of a "privacy-policy" 
      Link does not constitute a legally binding obligation on the part of the 
      service. The linked resource MUST be interpreted as only a description of 
      the expected practice.</t>
      
      <t>Publishers of privacy policy resources linked to using the "privacy-policy"
      Link relation type SHOULD provide a clear and simple mechanism
      for signaling when changes to the Privacy Policy resource have been made, 
      such as generating a new Entity Tag for the resource or generating a hash
      over the Privacy Policy's content.</t>
      
    </section>
    
    <section anchor="terms-of-service" title="&quot;terms-of-service&quot;">
    
      <t>The "terms-of-service" Link relation can be used to refer to a 
      resource describing the Terms of Service associated with the link's
      context. The Terms of Service can be any resource that describes the 
      rules to which a consumer of the service must agree to follow when 
      using the service provided by the link's context.</t>
      
      <t>For example, an HTTP server can include "terms-of-service" Links
      within all HTTP Responses using any combination of Link headers or 
      links embedded in the response payload:</t>
      
      <figure><preamble>An example showing various places where terms-of-service
      links can potentially appear:</preamble><artwork>
  HTTP/1.1 200 OK
  Content-Type: text/html
  Link: &lt;/tos.html&gt;; rel="terms-of-service"
  
  &lt;html&gt;
    &lt;head&gt;
      ...
      &lt;link rel="terms-of-service" href="/tos.html"&gt;
      ...
    &lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;body&gt;
      ...
      &lt;a rel="terms-of-service" href="/tos.html"&gt;
        Privacy Policy
      &lt;/a&gt;
      ...
    &lt;/body&gt;    
  &lt;/html&gt;
      </artwork></figure>
      
      <t>It must be noted that the Terms of Service linked to using this
      link relation carries no legal weight and can be ignored with impunity
      in the absence of an explicit, legally enforceable contract. The 
      linked Terms of Service are simply a notice of the terms that may be 
      expected to apply once a contract is established.</t>
    
    </section>
    
    <section anchor="type" title="&quot;type&quot;">
    
      <t>The "type" Link relation can be used to indicate that the context
      resource is an instance of the resource identified by the target IRI.</t>
      
      <figure><artwork>
  HTTP/1.1 200 OK
  Content-Type: text/plain
  Link: &lt;http://example.org/Person/givenName&gt;; type="type"
  
  Sally
      </artwork></figure>
      
      <t>Note that, when used within an HTTP message as in the example, 
      the "type" specified by the type link relation MUST NOT be
      confused with the media type of the payload itself as given by the 
      Content-Type header. The "type" link relation references the payload's 
      abstract semantic type whereas the Content-Type header identifies the 
      specific serialization format of the payload.</t>
      
      <t>If the context can be considered to be an instance of multiple 
      semantic types, multiple "type" link relations can be used.</t>
      
    </section>
      
    <section title="IANA Considerations"> 
      
      <t>The Registry of Link Relations should be updated with the following
      entries:</t>
      
      <t><list style="symbols">
        <t>Relation Name: about</t>
        <t>Description: Refers to a resource that is the subject of the link's
        context.</t>
        <t>Reference: This specification.</t>
      </list></t>
      
      <t><list style="symbols">
        <t>Relation Name: preview</t>
        <t>Description: Refers to a resource that provides a preview of the 
        link's context.</t>
        <t>Reference: This specification.</t>
      </list></t>
      
      <t><list style="symbols">
        <t>Relation Name: privacy-policy</t>
        <t>Description: Refers to a Privacy Policy associated with the link's
        context.</t>
        <t>Reference: This specification.</t>
      </list></t>
      
      <t><list style="symbols">
        <t>Relation Name: terms-of-service</t>
        <t>Description: Refers to the Terms of Service associated with the 
        link's context.</t>
        <t>Reference: This specification.</t>
      </list></t>
      
      <t><list style="symbols">
        <t>Relation Name: type</t>
        <t>Description: Refers to a resource identifying the abstract semantic
        type the link's context is considered to be an instance of.</t>
        <t>Reference: This specification.</t>
      </list></t>
      
    </section> 
 
    <section title="Security Considerations"> 
    
      <t>There are no additional security concerns introduced by this
      document.</t>
    
    </section> 
  </middle> 
 
  <back>
    <references title="Normative References"> 
      &rfc2119;
    </references>
    <references title="Informative References">
      &rfc5023;
      &rfc5988;
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc> 
 