<?xml version="1.0"?> 
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
  <!ENTITY rfc2119 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml'> 
  <!ENTITY rfc5023 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5023.xml'>
  <!ENTITY rfc5988 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5988.xml'>
]>
<?rfc toc="yes"?> 
<?rfc strict="yes"?> 
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?> 
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?> 
<?rfc compact="yes"?> 
<rfc category="std" ipr="trust200811" docName="draft-snell-additional-link-relations-01"> 
  <front> 
    <title abbrev="HTTP Prefer"> 
      Additional Link Relation Types
    </title> 
 
    <author initials="J.M." surname="Snell" fullname="James M Snell"> 
      <address> 
        <email>jasnell@gmail.com</email> 
      </address> 
    </author> 
    
    <date month="February" year="2012" /> 
 
    <area>Applications</area> 
    <keyword>I-D</keyword> 
    <keyword>http</keyword> 
    <keyword>link</keyword> 
    <keyword>rel</keyword>
 
    <abstract> 
      <t>This specification defines a number of additional Link Relation Types.</t> 
    </abstract> 
 
  </front> 
  
  <middle> 
    <section anchor="intro" title="Introduction"> 
 
      <t>This specification defines a number of additional Link Relation Types
      for a variety of common linking scenarios.</t> 
      
      <t>In this document, the key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", 
      "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" 
      are to be  interpreted as described in <xref target="RFC2119" />.</t> 
  
    </section> 
        
    <section anchor="implements" title="&quot;implements&quot;">
    
      <t>The "implements" Link relation can be used to refer to a  
      resource that specifies the behavior implemented by the link's
      context. Links using the "implements" link relation
      can point either to formal specification documents such as RFC's, 
      Internet-Drafts, W3C Recommendations, or to informal and possibly
      vendor specific documents that describe implementation details.</t>
      
      <t>For example, an HTTP client that implements the Atom Publishing 
      Protocol <xref target="RFC5023"/> could include an "implements" 
      Link (per <xref target="RFC5988"/>) within the HTTP Request referencing
      RFC 5023:</t>
      
      <figure><artwork>
  POST /collection HTTP/1.1
  Host: example.org
  Content-Type: application/atom+xml; type=entry
  Link: &lt;http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc5023&gt;; rel="implements"
  
  &lt;entry ...
      </artwork></figure>
    
      <t>Multiple "implements" Links can be used to indicate that multiple 
      specifications have been implemented.</t>
    </section>
    
    <section anchor="privacy-policy" title="&quot;privacy-policy&quot;">

      <t>The "privacy-policy" Link relation can be used to refer to a 
      resource describing the privacy policy associated with the link's
      context. The privacy policy can be any resource that discloses what
      personal information about the user is collected, and how that 
      personal information is stored, used, managed and disclosed to other
      parties.</t>
      
      <t>For example, an HTTP server that collects personal information 
      about a user throughout the course of the user's interaction with 
      the service can include "privacy-policy" Links within all HTTP 
      Responses using any combination of Link headers or links embedded 
      in the response payload:</t>

      <figure><artwork>
  HTTP/1.1 200 OK
  Content-Type: text/html
  Link: &lt;/privacy-policy.html&gt;; rel="privacy-policy"
  
  &lt;html&gt;
    &lt;head&gt;
      ...
      &lt;link rel="privacy-policy" href="/privacy-policy.html"&gt;
      ...
    &lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;body&gt;
      ...
      &lt;a rel="privacy-policy" href="/privacy-policy.html"&gt;
        Privacy Policy
      &lt;/a&gt;
      ...
    &lt;/body&gt;    
  &lt;/html&gt;
      </artwork></figure>
      
      <t>Note that in the absence of clear legal obligations placed on an 
      entity either through contract or law, the presence of a "privacy-policy" 
      Link does not constitute a legally binding obligation on the part of the 
      service. The linked resource MUST be interpreted as only a description of 
      the expected practice.</t>
      
    </section>
    
    <section anchor="terms-of-service" title="&quot;terms-of-service&quot;">
    
      <t>The "terms-of-service" Link relation can be used to refer to a 
      resource describing the Terms of Service associated with the link's
      context. The Terms of Service can be any resource that describes the 
      rules to which a consumer of the service must agree to follow when 
      using the service provided by the link's context.</t>
      
      <t>For example, an HTTP server can include "terms-of-service" Links
      within all HTTP Responses using any combination of Link headers or 
      links embedded in the response payload:</t>
      
      <figure><artwork>
  HTTP/1.1 200 OK
  Content-Type: text/html
  Link: &lt;/tos.html&gt;; rel="terms-of-service"
  
  &lt;html&gt;
    &lt;head&gt;
      ...
      &lt;link rel="terms-of-service" href="/tos.html"&gt;
      ...
    &lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;body&gt;
      ...
      &lt;a rel="terms-of-service" href="/tos.html"&gt;
        Privacy Policy
      &lt;/a&gt;
      ...
    &lt;/body&gt;    
  &lt;/html&gt;
      </artwork></figure>
      
      <t>It must be noted that the Terms of Service linked to using this
      link relation carries no legal weight and can be ignored with impunity
      in the absence of an explicit, legally enforceable contract. The 
      linked Terms of Service are simply a notice of the terms that may be 
      expected to apply once a contract is established.</t>
    
    </section>
      
    <section title="IANA Considerations"> 
      
      <t>The Registry of Link Relations should be updated with the following
      entries:</t>
      
      <t><list style="symbols">
        <t>Relation Name: implements</t>
        <t>Description: Refers to a specification implemented by the link's
        context.</t>
        <t>Reference: This specification.</t>
      </list></t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
        <t>Relation Name: privacy-policy</t>
        <t>Description: Refers to a Privacy Policy associated with the link's
        context.</t>
        <t>Reference: This specification.</t>
      </list></t>
      
      <t><list style="symbols">
        <t>Relation Name: terms-of-service</t>
        <t>Description: Refers to the Terms of Service associated with the 
        link's context.</t>
        <t>Reference: This specification.</t>
      </list></t>
      
    </section> 
 
    <section title="Security Considerations"> 
      
      <t>Implementors should note that the presence of a "privacy-policy"
      Link provides no guarantee that personal information collected and used
      by a resource will be handled in the manner described by the linked 
      resource.</t>
      
      <t>Publishers of Privacy Policy resources linked to using the "privacy-policy"
      Link relation type SHOULD provide a clear and simple mechanism
      for signaling when changes to the Privacy Policy resource have been made, 
      such as generating a new Entity Tag for the resource or generating a hash
      over the Privacy Policy's content.</t>
    
      <t>There are no additional security concerns introduced by the 
      "terms-of-service" and "implements" Link relations.</t>
    
    </section> 
  </middle> 
 
  <back>
    <references title="Normative References"> 
      &rfc2119;
    </references>
    <references title="Informative References">
      &rfc5023;
      &rfc5988;
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc> 
 