<?xml version="1.0"?> 
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
  <!ENTITY rfc5988 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5988.xml'>
]>
<?rfc toc="yes"?> 
<?rfc strict="yes"?> 
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?> 
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?> 
<?rfc compact="yes"?> 
<rfc category="info" ipr="trust200811" docName="draft-snell-more-link-relations-00"> 
  <front> 
    <title abbrev="More Link Relations"> 
      Additional Link Relations and the urn:social Namespace
    </title> 
 
    <author initials="J.M." surname="Snell" fullname="James M Snell"> 
      <address> 
        <email>jasnell@gmail.com</email> 
      </address> 
    </author> 
    
    <date month="August" year="2013" /> 
 
    <area>Applications</area> 
    <keyword>I-D</keyword> 
    <keyword>http</keyword> 
    <keyword>link</keyword> 
    <keyword>rel</keyword>
 
    <abstract> 
      <t>
        This specification defines a number of additional 
        Link Relation Types that can used for a variety of 
        purposes..</t> 
    </abstract> 
 
  </front> 
  
  <middle> 
    <section anchor="intro" title="Introduction"> 
 
      <t>
        This specification defines and adds the following additional 
        link relation types to the IANA Registry of Link Relations
        established by <xref target="RFC5988"/>: to, bto, cc, bcc, 
        from, bfrom, source, generator, provider, location, alias and
        mentionedBy. Further, this specification proposes a new 
        'social' URN namespace.
      </t>
      
      <t>
        Note that this document is a work-in-progress draft specification
        that does not yet represent a "standard". It is the intention of 
        this specification to propose a few new ideas and openly solicit 
        feedback on their definition and use. While this document might 
        eventually evolve into an RFC the ideas described herein have not 
        yet been broadly implemented and have definitions that may evolve
        through successive iterations of this draft.
      </t>
      
    </section> 
    
    <section title="The 'social' URN Namespace">
      
      <t>
        This specification defines the 'social' URN namespace having the 
        following structure:
      </t>
      
      <figure><artwork>urn:social:{NSS}</artwork></figure>
      
      <t>
        The Namespace Specific String (NSS) MUST be one of:
        <list style="symbols">
          <t>everyone</t>
          <t>direct</t>
          <t>extended</t>
          <t>peer</t>
          <t>subordinate</t>
          <t>superior</t>
          <t>common</t>
          <t>interested</t>
          <t>self</t>
        </list>
      </t>
      
      <t>
        Within any given social networking system, there is an available
        population of entities. Each NSS term represent specific subsets of 
        this population and are defined in terms of these subsets relative 
        to a fixed context. For example, if the fixed content is a person,
        the "urn:social:direct" URN identifies the subset of the total 
        population that is directly connected to the context person within 
        the social graph, while the "urn:social:extended" URN identifies the
        subset that is directly or indirectly connected to the context 
        person.
      </t>
      
      <t>
        The 'social' URN namespace is defined to be intentionally 
        ambiguous and contextually dependent. The specific interpretation
        of each NSS depends entirely on how and where the NSS is being 
        used.
      </t>
      
      <section title="urn:social:everyone">
        <t>
          The "urn:social:everyone" URN identifies the subset of the total
          population that is visible to the context.
        </t>
      </section>
      
      <section title="urn:social:direct">
        <t>
          The "urn:social:direct" URN identifies the subset of the total
          population that is both visible to and directly connection to 
          the context.
        </t>
      </section>
      
      <section title="urn:social:extended">
        <t>
          The "urn:social:extended" URN identifies the subset of the total
          population that is visible to and connected either directly or 
          indirectly to the context.
        </t>
      </section>
      
      <section title="urn:social:peer">
        <t>
          The "urn:social:peer" URN identifies the subset of the total
          population that is both visible to the context and considered 
          to be a "peer".
        </t>
        <t>
          Peer relationships exist only within social networking populations
          in which there exist hierarchical divisions and relationships 
          between members of the population. An example of such a network 
          would be a company or similarly structured organization. Peers 
          may or may not be directly or indirectly connected to the target
          resource but are considered, instead, to share the same hierarchical
          position within the social network.
        </t>
      </section>
      
      <section title="urn:social:subordinate">
        <t>
          The "urn:social:subordinate" URN identifies the subset of the
          total population that is both visible to the context and 
          considered to be "subordinate" to the context.
        </t>
        <t>
          Subordinate relationships exist only within social networking
          populations in which there exist hierarchical divisions and 
          relationships between members of the population. An example of
          such a network would be a company or similarly structured
          organization. Subordinates may or may not be directly or 
          indirectly connected to the target resource but are considered,
          instead, to share a lower hierarchical position within the social
          network.
        </t>
      </section>
      
      <section title="urn:social:superior">
        <t>
          The "urn:social:superior" URN identifies the subset of the
          total population that is both visible to the context and 
          considered to be "superior" to the context.
        </t>
        <t>
          Superior relationships exist only within social networking
          populations in which there exist hierarchical divisions and 
          relationships between members of the population. An example of
          such a network would be a company or similarly structured
          organization. Superiors may or may not be directly or 
          indirectly connected to the target resource but are considered,
          instead, to share a higher hierarchical position within the social
          network.
        </t>
      </section>
      
      <section title="urn:social:common">
        <t>
          The "urn:social:common" URN identifies the subset of the total
          population that is both visible to the context and 
          is determined to share the same common interests as the 
          context.
        </t>
        <t>
          Determination of "shared interest" is dependent entirely on the
          application.
        </t>
      </section>
      
      <section title="urn:social:interested">
        <t>
          The "urn:social:interested" URN identifies the subset of the 
          total population that is both visible to the context and has 
          an express interest in the context. Examples of members of the
          "interested" subset are those who have elected to "follow" the
          activity of the context resource.
        </t>
      </section>
      
      <section title="urn:social:self">
        <t>
          The "urn:social:self" URN identifies the context resource 
          itself as a member of the total population.
        </t>
      </section>
      
    </section>
                              
    <section title="IANA Considerations"> 
      
      <t>
        The following Link Relations are added to the IANA Registry of 
        Link Relations.
      </t>
      
      <texttable>
        <ttcol>Name</ttcol>
        <ttcol>Description</ttcol>
        
        <c>to</c>
        <c>
          Refers to a resource that is considered to be part of the
          public primary audience of the link's context.
        </c>
        
        <c>bto</c>
        <c>
          Refers to a resource that is considered to be part of the
          private primary audience of the link's context.
        </c>
        
        <c>cc</c>
        <c>
          Refers to a resource that is considered to be part of the 
          public secondary audience of the link's context.
        </c>
        
        <c>bcc</c>
        <c>
          Refers to a resource that is considered to be part of the 
          private secondary audience of the link's context.
        </c>
        
        <c>from</c>
        <c>
          Refers to a resource that is publicly considered to be the originator
          of the link's context.
        </c>
        
        <c>bfrom</c>
        <c>
          Refers to a resource that is privately considered to be the orignator
          of the link's context.
        </c>
        
        <c>source</c>
        <c>
          Refers to the original source of information contained by the 
          context resource.
        </c>
        
        <c>provider</c>
        <c>
          Refers to the resource that provided the context resource. 
          Typically, this would be used to identify the entity publishing
          the resource. 
        </c>
        
        <c>generator</c>
        <c>
          Refers to the resource that generated the context resource.
          Typically, this would be used to identify the software application
          that created the context resource.
        </c>
        
        <c>mentionedBy</c>
        <c>
          Refers to a resource that mentions the context resource in some 
          fashion. This, for example, would be used when an article mentions
          another article, or a social status update mentions a particular
          user, etc.
        </c>
        
        <c>location</c>
        <c>
          References a URI/IRI that represents a physical or logical location
          with which the context resource is associated.
        </c>
        
      </texttable>
            
    </section> 
 
    <section title="Security Considerations"> 
    
      <t>There are no additional security concerns introduced by this
      document.</t>
    
    </section> 
  </middle> 
 
  <back>
    <references title="Informative References">
      &rfc5988;
    </references>
    
    <section title="Examples">
    
      <figure><preamble>Using targeting link relations and the urn:social namespace:</preamble><artwork><![CDATA[
    POST /alerts HTTP/1.1
    Host: example.org
    Content-Type: text/plain
    Authorization: Basic {Base64 Credentials}
    Link: <urn:social:everyone>; rel="to"
    Link: <urn:social:extended>; rel="cc"
    Link: <urn:social:self>; rel="bfrom"
  
    Test message
      ]]></artwork></figure>
    
 
      <figure><preamble>Using publication link relations:</preamble><artwork><![CDATA[
    <html>
      <head>
        ...
        <link 
          rel="source" 
          href="http://example.net/post/1" />
        <link 
          rel="provider" 
          href="http://example.org" />
        <link 
          rel="generator" 
          href="http://example.com/software/app/1.1" />
        ...
      </head>
      <body>...</body>
    </html>
  

      ]]></artwork></figure>
    
      <figure><preamble>Using the alias and location relations:</preamble><artwork><![CDATA[
    Link: <geo:37.786971,-122.399677>; rel="location"
      ]]></artwork></figure>
    
      <figure><preamble>Using the mentionedBy relation:</preamble><artwork><![CDATA[
    LINK /articles/1 HTTP/1.1
    Host: example.org
    Link: <articles/2>; rel="mentionedBy"
      ]]></artwork></figure>
 
    </section>
    
  </back>
  
</rfc> 
 