<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<?rfc rfcedstyle="yes"?>
<rfc category="info" docName="draft-boucadair-chaining-requirements-02"
     ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="SFC Requirements">Requirements for Service Function
    Chaining</title>

    <author fullname="Mohamed Boucadair" initials="M." surname="Boucadair">
      <organization>France Telecom</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>

          <city>Rennes</city>

          <region></region>

          <code>35000</code>

          <country>France</country>
        </postal>

        <email>mohamed.boucadair@orange.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Christian Jacquenet" initials="C." surname="Jacquenet">
      <organization>France Telecom</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>

          <city>Rennes</city>

          <region></region>

          <code>35000</code>

          <country>France</country>
        </postal>

        <email>christian.jacquenet@orange.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Yuanlong Jiang" initials="Y." surname="Jiang">
      <organization>Huawei Technologies Co., Ltd.</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Bantian, Longgang district</street>

          <city>Shenzhen 518129,</city>

          <region></region>

          <code></code>

          <country>China</country>
        </postal>

        <email>jiangyuanlong@huawei.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Ron Parker" initials="R." surname="Parker">
      <organization>Affirmed Networks</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>

          <city>Acton,</city>

          <region></region>

          <code>MA</code>

          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>

        <email>Ron_Parker@affirmednetworks.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Carlos Pignataro " initials="C." surname="Pignataro">
      <organization>Cisco Systems, Inc.</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>

          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>

        <email>cpignata@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date day="05" month="September" year="2013" />

    <abstract>
      <t>This document identifies the requirements for the Service Function
      Chaining.</t>
    </abstract>

    <note title="Requirements Language">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
      document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
      target="RFC2119">RFC 2119</xref>.</t>
    </note>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>This document identifies the requirements for the Service Function
      Chaining (SFC).</t>

      <t>The overall problem space is described in <xref
      target="I-D.quinn-nsc-problem-statement"></xref>. The Service Function
      Chaining Framework is documented in <xref
      target="I-D.boucadair-service-chaining-framework"></xref>.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Terminology">
      <t>The reader should be familiar with the terms defined in <xref
      target="I-D.boucadair-service-chaining-framework"></xref> and <xref
      target="I-D.quinn-nsc-problem-statement"></xref>.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Detailed Requirements List">
      <t>The following set of functional requirements should be considered for
      the design of the Service Function Chaining solution:<?rfc subcompact="no" ?><list
          hangIndent="9" style="format REQ#%d:">
          <t>The solution MUST NOT make any assumption on whether Service
          Functions (SF) are deployed directly on physical hardware, as one or
          more Virtual Machines, or any combination thereof.</t>

          <t>The solution MUST NOT make any assumption on whether Service
          Functions each reside on a separate addressable Network Element,
          horizontal scaling of Service Functions, are co-resident on a single
          addressable Network Element, or any combination thereof. <list
              hangIndent="11" style="empty">
              <t>Note: Communications between Service Functions co-resident on
              same Network Element are considered implementation-specific.
              These considerations are out of scope of the SFC specification
              effort.</t>
            </list></t>

          <t>The solution MUST NOT require any IANA registry for Service
          Functions.</t>

          <t>The solution MUST NOT assume predefined order of Service
          Functions. In particular, the solution MUST NOT require any IANA
          registry to store typical Service Function Chains.</t>

          <t>The identification of instantiated Service Function Chains is
          local to each administrative domain; it is policy-based and
          deployment-specific.</t>

          <t>The solution MUST allow multiple instances of a given Service
          Function ( i.e., a Service Function can be embedded in multiple
          Network Elements).<list hangIndent="11" style="letters">
              <t>This is used for load-balancing, load-sharing, prevent from
              failures (e.g., hot or cold standby protection mechanism),
              accommodate planned maintenance operations, etc.</t>

              <t>How these multiple devices are involved in the service
              delivery is deployment-specific.</t>
            </list></t>

          <t>The solution MUST allow for multiple Service Chains to be
          simultaneously enforced within an administrative domain.</t>

          <t>The solution MUST allow the same Service Function to be involved
          in multiple Service Function Chains.</t>

          <t>The solution MUST support multiple SFC-enabled domains be
          deployed within the same administrative domain.</t>

          <t>The solution MUST be able to associate the same or distinct
          Service Function Chains for each direction (inbound/outbound) of the
          traffic. In particular, unidirectional Service Function Chains,
          bi-directional Service Function Chains, or any combination thereof
          MUST be supported.</t>

          <t>The solution MUST be able to dynamically enforce Service Function
          Chains. In particular, the solution MUST allow the update or the
          withdrawal of existing Service Function Chains, the definition of a
          new Service Function Chain, the addition of new Service Functions
          without having any impact on other existing Service Functions or
          other Service Function Chains.</t>

          <t>The solution MUST provide means to control the SF-inferred
          information to be leaked outside an SFC-enabled domain. In
          particular, an administrative entity MUST be able to prevent Service
          Function Chaining logic and related policies from being exposed
          outside its administrative domain.</t>

          <t>The solution SHOULD minimize fragmentation; in particular a
          minimal set of SFC-specific information should be conveyed in the
          data packet.</t>

          <t>The solution MUST NOT make any assumption on how RIBs (Routing
          Information Bases) and FIBs (Forwarding Information Bases) are
          populated. Particularly, the solution does not make any assumption
          on protocols and mechanisms used to build these tables.</t>

          <t>The solution MUST be transport independent.<list hangIndent="11"
              style="letters">
              <t>The Service Function chaining should operate regardless of
              the network transport used by the administrative entity. In
              particular, the solution can be used whatever the switching
              technologies deployed in the underlying transport
              infrastructure.</t>

              <t>Techniques such as MPLS are neither required nor
              excluded.</t>
            </list></t>

          <t>The solution MUST allow for chaining logics where involved
          Service Functions are not within the same layer 3 subnet.</t>

          <t>The solution MUST NOT exclude Service Functions to be within the
          same IP subnet (this is deployment-specific).</t>

          <t>An administrative entity, grouping its Service Functions within
          the same IP subnet, SHOULD be able to avoid encapsulation overhead
          .</t>

          <t>The solution MUST NOT make any assumption on how the traffic is
          to be bound to a given chaining policy. In other words,
          classification rules are deployment-specific and policy-based. For
          instance, classification can rely on a subset of the information
          carried in a received packet such as 5-tuple classification.</t>

          <t>The solution MUST support classifying traffic into Service
          Function Chains.</t>

          <t>The solution MUST NOT require every Service Function be
          co-located with a SFC Classifier; this is a deployment-specific
          decision.</t>

          <t>The solution MAY allow reclassification at the Service Functions
          (i.e., a Service Function can also be co-located with a classifier).
          The configuration of classification rules in such context are the
          responsibility of the administrative entity managing that
          SFC-enabled domain.</t>

          <t>The solution MUST be able to forward the traffic between two
          Service Functions (involved in the same Service Function Chain)
          without relying on the original destination address in a data
          packet.</t>

          <t>The solution MUST allow for the association of a context with the
          data packets. In particular:<list hangIndent="11" style="letters">
              <t>The solution MUST support the ability to invoke
              differentiated sets of policies for a Service Function (called
              Profiles). A profile denotes a set of policies configured to a
              local Service Function (e.g., content-filter-child,
              content-filter-adult).<list hangIndent="11" style="letters">
                  <t>Few profiles should be assumed per Service Function to
                  accommodate the need for scalable solutions.</t>

                  <t>Finer-grained of policies should be configured directly
                  to each Service Function; no need to overload the design of
                  Service Function Chains with policies of low-level
                  granularity.</t>
                </list></t>

              <t>[NOTE: The following items will be detailed further in next
              revisions: (1) provide a generic definition of the "context",
              (2) discuss whether the context have a meaning for a given
              SFC-enabled domain or it is SF-specific, (3) provide examples,
              etc.]</t>
            </list></t>

          <t>The solution MUST allow for Operations, Administration, and
          Maintenance (OAM) features <xref target="RFC6291"></xref>. In
          particular, <list hangIndent="11" style="letters">
              <t>Support means to verify the completion of the forwarding
              actions derived from the contents of the SF Map until the Border
              Node is reached (see Section 3.4.1 of <xref
              target="RFC5706"></xref>).</t>

              <t>Support means to ensure coherent classification rules are
              installed to all SFC Classifiers.</t>

              <t>Support means to correlate between the classification
              policies and observed forwarding actions.</t>

              <t>Support in-band liveness and functionality checking of
              instantiated Service Function Chains.</t>
            </list></t>

          <t>The solution MUST prevent the same Service Function to be invoked
          multiple times in the context of the same Service Function Chain (at
          the risk of generating Service Function Loop).</t>

          <t>The solution MUST allow for load-balancing.<list hangIndent="11"
              style="letters">
              <t>Load-balancing may be provided by legacy technologies or
              protocols (e.g., make use of load-balancers)</t>

              <t>Load-balancing may be part of the Service Function
              itself.</t>

              <t>Load-balancer may be considered as a Service Function
              element.</t>

              <t>Because of the possible complications, load balancing SHOULD
              NOT be driven by the SFC Classifier.</t>
            </list></t>

          <t>The solution MUST separate provisioning-related aspects from the
          actual handling of packets (including forwarding decisions).</t>

          <t>The solution SHOULD means to detect the liveness of involved
          Service Functions.</t>

          <t>Means to dynamically discover Service Functions SHOULD be
          supported.</t>

          <t>Service Functions may be reachable using IPv4 and/or IPv6. The
          administrative domain entity MUST be able to define and enforce
          policies with regards to the address family to be used when invoking
          a Service Function. <list hangIndent="11" style="letters">
              <t>A Service Function Chain may be composed of IPv4 addresses,
              IPv6 addresses, or a mix of both IPv4 and IPv6 addresses.</t>

              <t>Multiple Service Functions can be reachable using the same IP
              address. Each of these Service Functions is unambiguously
              identified with a Service Function Identifier.</t>
            </list></t>

          <t>The solution MUST allow for gradual deployment in legacy
          infrastructures, and therefore coexist with legacy technologies that
          cannot support SFC-specific capabilities, such as SFC Map
          interpretation and processing. The solution MUST be able to work in
          a domain that may be partly composed of opaque elements, i.e.,
          elements that do not support SFC-specific capabilities.</t>

          <t>The solution MUST be able to provide different SLAs (Service
          Level Agreements, <xref
          target="I-D.boucadair-connectivity-provisioning-profile"></xref>).
          In particular,<list style="letters">
              <t>The solution MUST allow for different levels of service to be
              provided for traffic streams (e.g., configure Classes of Service
              (CoSes)).</t>

              <t>The solution MUST be compatible with Diffserv <xref
              target="RFC2475"></xref>.</t>
            </list></t>
        </list><?rfc subcompact="no" ?></t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="iana" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>Authors of this document do not require any action from IANA.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>Below are listed some security-related requirements to be taken into
      account when designing the Service Function Chaining solution:</t>

      <t><list hangIndent="12" style="format SEC_REQ#%d:">
          <t>The solution MUST provide means to prevent leaking any
          information that would be used as a hint to guess internal
          engineering practices (e.g., network topology, service
          infrastructure topology, hints on the enabled mechanisms to protect
          internal service infrastructures, etc.).</t>

          <t>The solution MUST support means to defend against
          denial-of-service and theft of service (e.g., illegitimate access to
          the service). For example, a user should not be granted access to
          connectivity services it didn't subscribed to such as illegitimate
          access to network resources.</t>

          <t>The solution MUST NOT interfere with IPsec <xref
          target="RFC4301"></xref> (in particular IPsec integrity checks).</t>
        </list></t>
    </section>

    <section title="Contributors">
      <t>The following individuals contributed text to the document:<figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[   Hongyu Li
   Huawei Technologies Co., Ltd.
   Bantian, Longgang district
   Shenzhen 518129,
   China

   EMail: hongyu.lihongyu@huawei.com

   Jim Guichard
   Cisco Systems, Inc.
   USA

   EMail: jguichar@cisco.com

   Paul Quinn
   Cisco Systems, Inc.
   USA

   Email: paulq@cisco.com]]></artwork>
        </figure></t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>Many thanks to K. Gray for his review.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119"?>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.I-D.boucadair-service-chaining-framework"?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6291'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.boucadair-connectivity-provisioning-profile'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.2475'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.4301'?>

      <?rfc include="reference.I-D.quinn-nsc-problem-statement"?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.5706'?>
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
