<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="rfc2629.xslt" ?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc strict="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="2"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="yes" ?>
<!--<?rfc rfcedstyle="yes"?>-->
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<!-- noModification3978 -->
<rfc category="info" docName="draft-iana-rfc2754-to-historic-01"
     ipr="trust200902" obsoletes="2754">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="RFC 2754 to Historic Status">Request to Move RFC 2754 to
    Historic Status</title>

    <author fullname="Mark McFadden" initials="M." surname="McFadden">
      <organization abbrev="ICANN">Internet Corporation for Assigned Names and
      Numbers</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>4676 Admiralty Way, Suite 330</street>

          <code>90292</code>

          <city>Marina del Rey</city>

          <country>United States</country>
        </postal>

        <phone>+1-608-628-2674</phone>

        <email>mark.mcfadden@icann.org</email>

        <uri>http://www.iana.org</uri>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date day="20" month="May" year="2010" />

    <keyword>RFC2754</keyword>

    <keyword>historic</keyword>

    <keyword>RPS</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>RFC 2754 requested that each time IANA made an address assignment, it
      was to create appropriate inetnum and as-block objects and digitally
      sign them. The purpose was to distribute the IANA-held public key in
      software implementations of the Distributed Routing Policy System. In
      practice, this was never done on the public Internet. This document
      requests that RFC 2754 be moved to historic status.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>The Internet Assigned Numbers Authority (IANA) (www.iana.org) is
      charged with allocating parameter values for fields in protocols which
      have been designed, created or are maintained by the Internet
      Engineering Task Force (IETF). RFC 2754 <xref target="RFC2754"></xref>
      requests that the IANA create a repository of Routing Policy System
      Language (RPSL) objects and digitally sign them. The RFC identifies the
      initial objects to be signed and also requests that each time IANA makes
      an address assignment it also create new objects as needed and sign them
      as well. In practice, this was never done in the public Internet. During
      a detailed review of IANA's protocol registration activities in support
      of the IETF, this request for IANA action was identified.</t>

      <t>This document obsoletes RFC 2754 <xref target="RFC2754"></xref>,
      recommends that it be moved to historic status, and directs IANA to not
      move forward with the IANA Actions in that RFC.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Details">
      <t>RFC 2754 <xref target="RFC2754"></xref> requests that the IANA create
      a repository of RPSL objects and digitally sign them. The RFC identifies
      the initial objects to be signed and also requests that each time IANA
      makes an address assignment it also create new objects as needed and
      sign them as well.</t>

      <t>During a review of RFCs in 2009 it became apparent that the IANA
      actions requested in RFC 2754 were never done. In the intervening time,
      another technology appears to be taking the role once envisioned for
      Distributed RPSL. Implementation of the IANA actions in RFC 2754 would
      now require significant implementation complexity. In the face of
      alternative technology, and given that the requested actions have not
      been implemented in the public Internet, it is proposed to reclassify
      RFC 2754 <xref target="RFC2754"></xref> as historic and to direct the
      IANA not to pursue or implement the IANA requests in that document.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Terminology">
      <t>The word "allocation" designates a block of addresses managed by a
      registry for the purpose of making assignments and allocations. The word
      "assignment" designates a block of addresses, or a single address,
      registered to an end-user for use on a specific network, or set of
      networks.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>IANA is instructed not to pursue or implement the IANA actions
      requested in RFC 2754. <xref target="RFC2754"></xref></t>
    </section>

    <section title="Security Considerations">
      <t>The intended signature of inetnum and as-block objects never took
      place in the public Internet. Moving RFC 2754 <xref
      target="RFC2754"></xref> to historic status would have no known impact
      on the security of the Internet.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Acknowledgments">
      <t>The author would like to thank Alfred Hines, Russ Housley, Leo
      Vegoda, Terry Manderson, Michelle Cotton and David Conrad for their
      constructive feedback and comments.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <!-- REFERENCE TEMPLATE

        <reference anchor="reference.XXX">

                <front>

                        <title>XXX</title>

                        <author initials="X." surname="XXX"
fullname="XXX">

                                <organization
abbrev="XXX">XXX</organization>

                                <address>

                                        <postal>

                                                <street>XXX</street>

                                                <city>XXX</city>

                                                <region>XXX</region>

                                                <code>XXX</code>

                                                <country>XXX</country>

                                        </postal>

                                        <phone>XXX</phone>

                                        <facsimile>XXX</facsimile>

                                        <email>XXX</email>

                                        <uri>XXX</uri>

                                </address>


                        </author>

                        <date month="XXX" year="XXX"/>

                </front>

                <seriesInfo name="XXX" value="XXX"/>

                <format type="XXX" target="XXX"/>                       

        </reference>

        -->

  <back>
    <references title="Informative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2754" ?>
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
