<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
  <!ENTITY rfc1034 PUBLIC ''
    'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1034.xml'>
  <!ENTITY rfc1035 PUBLIC ''
    'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1035.xml'>
  <!ENTITY rfc2671 PUBLIC ''
    'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2671.xml'>
  <!ENTITY rfc4786 PUBLIC ''
    'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4786.xml'>
  <!ENTITY rfc4892 PUBLIC ''
    'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4892.xml'>
  <!ENTITY rfc5001 PUBLIC ''
    'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5001.xml'>
  <!ENTITY rfc6304 PUBLIC ''
    'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6304.xml'>
]>

<rfc category="info" ipr="trust200902"
  docName="draft-jabley-dnsop-anycast-mapping-02">

  <?rfc toc="yes" ?>
  <?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
  <?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
  <?rfc iprnotified="no" ?>
  <?rfc strict="yes" ?>

  <front>
    <title abbrev="L-Root Anycast Node Identification">
      A Summary of Various Mechanisms Deployed at L-Root for
      the Identification of Anycast Nodes</title>

    <author initials='J.' surname="Abley" fullname='Joe Abley'>
      <organization>ICANN</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>12025 Waterfront Drive</street>
          <street>Suite 300</street>
          <city>Los Angeles</city>
          <region>CA</region>
          <code>90094-2536</code>
          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>
        <phone>+1 519 670 9327</phone>
        <email>joe.abley@icann.org</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date day="24" month="June" year="2013"/>

    <abstract>
      <t>Anycast is a deployment technique commonly employed for
	authoritative-only servers in the Domain Name System (DNS).
	L-Root, one of the thirteen root servers, is deployed in
	this fashion.</t>

      <t>Various techniques have been used to map deployed anycast
	infrastructure externally, i.e. without reference to inside
	knowledge about where and how such infrastructure has been
	deployed. Motivations for performing such measurement
	exercises include operational troubleshooting and infrastructure
	risk assessment. In the specific case of L-Root, the ability
	to measure and map anycast infrastructure using the techniques
	mentioned in this document is provided for reasons of
	operational transparency.</t>

      <t>This document describes all facilities deployed at L-Root
	to facilitate mapping of its infrastructure and serves as
	documentation for L-Root as a measurable service.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>The Domain Name System (DNS) is described in <xref
	target="RFC1034"/> and <xref target="RFC1035"/>. L-Root,
	one of the thirteen root servers, is deployed using <xref
	target="RFC4786">anycast</xref>; its service addresses,
	published in the A and AAAA Resource Record (RR) Sets for
	"L.ROOT-SERVERS.NET", are made available from a substantial
	number of semi-autonomous servers deployed throughout the
	Internet. A list of locations served by L-Root can be found
	at <eref target="http://www.root-servers.org"/>.</t>

      <t><xref target="Fan2013"/> describes a technique using open
	DNS resolvers to distribute mapping queries to the service
	addresses of authoritative-only servers. This technique
	relies upon the ability to acquire meaningful information
	about individual anycast nodes by means of an IN-class
	query. At the time the experiments described in that paper
	were conducted, such ability existed with <xref
	target="RFC6304">AS112 servers</xref> but not with any
	root server. Modifications were subsequently made to the
	infrastructure of the L-Root service to facilitate this
	technique.</t>

      <t>This document describes all facilities currently provided
        at L-Root to aid node identification.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Conventions Used in this Document">
      <t>This document contains several examples of commands typed
        at a Unix (or Unix-like) command line to illustrate use of the
        various mechanisms available to identify L-Root nodes. Such
        examples are presented in this document with lines typed by
        the user preceded by the "%" prompt character; a bare "%"
        character indicates the end of the output resulting from the
        command.</t>

      <t>In some cases the output shown in examples is too long to
	be represented directly in the text. In those cases a
	backslash character ("\") is used to indicate continuation.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Naming Scheme for L-Root Nodes">
      <t>Individual L-Root nodes have structured hostnames that
        are constructed as follows:

        <list style="empty">
          <t>&lt;IATA Code&gt;&lt;NN&gt;.L.ROOT-SERVERS.ORG</t>
        </list>

        where

        <list style="symbols">
	  <t>&lt;IATA Code&gt; is chosen from the list of three-character
	    airport codes published by the International Air Transport
	    Association (IATA) in the <eref
	    target="http://www.iata.org/publications/Pages/coding.aspx">IATA
	    Airline Coding Directory</eref>; and</t>

          <t>&lt;NN&gt; is a two-digit numeric code used to distinguish
            between two different locations in the vicinity of the same
            airport.</t>
        </list>

        Where multiple airports exist in the vicinity of a single
        L-Root node, one is arbitrarily chosen.</t>

      <t>More granular location data published for L-Root nodes
	(e.g. see <xref target="useofidentity"/>) is derived from the
	location of the airport, not the actual location of the
	node.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Identification of L-Root Nodes">
      <t>L-Root service is provided using a single IPv4 address
	(199.7.83.42) and a single IPv6 address (2001:500:3::42).
	It should be noted that it is preferable to refer to the
	service using its DNS name (L.ROOT-SERVERS.NET) rather than
	literal addresses, since addresses can change from time to
	time.</t>

      <t>At the time of writing there are 273 separate name server
	elements ("nodes") deployed in 143 locations which together
	provide L-Root service. A DNS query sent to an L-Root service
	address will be routed towards exactly one of those nodes
        for processing, and the corresponding DNS response will
        be originated from the same node. Queries from different
        clients may be routed to different nodes.</t>

      <t>The following sections provide a summary of all mechanisms
        provided by L-Root to allow a client to identify which L-Root
        node is being used.</t>

      <t>Using <xref target="hostbind">HOSTNAME.BIND/CH/TXT</xref>,
        <xref target="idserver">ID.SERVER/CH/TXT</xref> or
	<xref target="useofidentity">IDENTITY.L.ROOT-SERVERS.ORG/IN/TXT
	or .../IN/A</xref> to identify a node for the purposes of
	reporting a problem is frequently reasonable, but it should
	be acknowledged that there is potential for re-routing
	between successive queries: an observed problem might relate
	to one node, whilst a subsequent query using one of those
	three techniques could be answered by a different node. Use
	of the NSID option can obviate this possibility (see <xref
	target="nsid"/>).</t>

      <section title="Use of NSID" anchor="nsid">
        <t>L-Root supports the use of the <xref target="RFC5001">Name
          Server Identifier (NSID) Option</xref> to return the identity
          of an L-Root node along with the response to a DNS query.
          The NSID payload of such responses is the fully-qualified
          hostname of the responding L-Root node.</t>

	<t>The NSID option allows the identification of a node
	  sending a specific, requested response to the client.
	  This is of particular use if (for example) there is a
	  desire to identify unequivocally what node is responding
	  with a particularly troublesome response; the output of
	  the diagnostic tool dig with NSID requested provides the
	  problem response with the node identification, and its
	  output in that case could form the basis of a useful
	  trouble report.</t>

	<t>NSID is specified as an <xref target="RFC2671">EDNS0
	  option</xref>. Clients that do not support EDNS0 signalling
	  (or depend on other systems that do not support EDNS0)
	  may find this mechanism unavailable.</t>

        <t>The NSID option can be specified using the widely-used
          diagnostic tool "dig" using the "+nsid" option, as shown
          below. Note that long lines have been truncated for the
          purposes of this document ("\" at the end of a line
          indicates continuation).</t>

        <figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[
% dig -4 @L.ROOT-SERVERS.NET . SOA +nsid \
  +norec +noall +comments
; <<>> DiG 9.6.-ESV-R3 <<>> -4 @L.ROOT-SERVERS.NET . SOA +nsid \
  +norec +noall +comments
; (1 server found)
;; global options: +cmd
;; Got answer:
;; ->>HEADER<<- opcode: QUERY, status: NOERROR, id: 14913
;; flags: qr aa; QUERY: 1, ANSWER: 1, AUTHORITY: 13, ADDITIONAL: 23

;; OPT PSEUDOSECTION:
; EDNS: version: 0, flags:; udp: 4096
; NSID: 79 74 7a 30 31 2e 6c 2e 72 6f 6f 74 2d 73 65 72 76 65 72 73 \
  2e 6f 72 67  (y) (t) (z) (0) (1) (.) (l) (.) (r) (o) (o) (t) (-) \
  (s) (e) (r) (v) (e) (r) (s) (.) (o) (r) (g)
%]]>
          </artwork>
        </figure>

        <figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[
% dig -6 @L.ROOT-SERVERS.NET . SOA +nsid \
  +norec +noall +comments
; <<>> DiG 9.6.-ESV-R3 <<>> -6 @L.ROOT-SERVERS.NET . SOA +nsid \
  +norec +noall +comments
; (1 server found)
;; global options: +cmd
;; Got answer:
;; ->>HEADER<<- opcode: QUERY, status: NOERROR, id: 33374
;; flags: qr aa; QUERY: 1, ANSWER: 1, AUTHORITY: 13, ADDITIONAL: 23

;; OPT PSEUDOSECTION:
; EDNS: version: 0, flags:; udp: 4096
; NSID: 79 74 7a 30 31 2e 6c 2e 72 6f 6f 74 2d 73 65 72 76 65 72 73 \
  2e 6f 72 67  (y) (t) (z) (0) (1) (.) (l) (.) (r) (o) (o) (t) (-) \
  (s) (e) (r) (v) (e) (r) (s) (.) (o) (r) (g)
%]]>
          </artwork>
        </figure>
      </section>

      <section title="Use of HOSTNAME.BIND/CH/TXT" anchor="hostbind">
	<t>L-Root supports the use of HOSTNAME.BIND/CH/TXT queries
	  to return the identity of an L-Root node. The TXT RDATA
	  returned is the fully-qualified hostname of the responding
	  L-Root node.</t>

        <t>The HOSTNAME.BIND/CH/TXT convention is described in
          <xref target="RFC4892"/>.</t>

        <figure>
          <artwork>
% dig -4 @L.ROOT-SERVERS.NET HOSTNAME.BIND CH TXT +short
"ytz01.l.root-servers.org"
%

% dig -6 @L.ROOT-SERVERS.NET HOSTNAME.BIND CH TXT +short
"ytz01.l.root-servers.org"
% 
          </artwork>
        </figure>
      </section>

      <section title="Use of ID.SERVER/CH/TXT" anchor="idserver">
        <t>L-Root supports the use of ID.SERVER/CH/TXT queries
          to return the identity of an L-Root node. The TXT RDATA
          returned is the fully-qualified hostname of the responding
          L-Root node.</t>

	<t>ID.SERVER/CH/TXT functions identically (apart from the
	  QNAME) to HOSTNAME.BIND/CH/TXT, as discussed in <xref
	  target="hostbind"/>.  The discussion there relating to
	  the possibility of re-routing between successive queries
	  also follows for ID.SERVER/CH/TXT.</t>

        <t>The ID.SERVER/CH/TXT convention is described in
          <xref target="RFC4892"/>.</t>

        <figure>
          <artwork>
% dig -4 @L.ROOT-SERVERS.NET ID.SERVER CH TXT +short
"ytz01.l.root-servers.org"
% 

% dig -6 @L.ROOT-SERVERS.NET ID.SERVER CH TXT +short
"ytz01.l.root-servers.org"
% 
          </artwork>
        </figure>
      </section>

      <section title="Use of IDENTITY.L.ROOT-SERVERS.ORG/IN/TXT and .../IN/A"
        anchor="useofidentity">
	<t>The operator of L-Root has distributed a separate DNS
	  service in parallel with L-Root, operating on precisely
	  the same set of nodes. Measurements of this separate
	  service should give results which are representative of
	  L-Root. Further discussion of this service can be found
          in <xref target="identity"/>.</t>

        <t>The fully-qualified DNS name IDENTITY.L.ROOT-SERVERS.ORG
          (note the use of ORG, not NET) has associated TXT and A
          RR Sets which are unique to the responding node. Clients
          are hence able to issue queries for
          IDENTITY.L.ROOT-SERVERS.ORG/IN/A and
          IDENTITY.L.ROOT-SERVERS.ORG/IN/TXT and use the results both
          to identify individual nodes and to distinguish between
          responses generated by different nodes.</t>

        <t>The TXT record returned in the response to such queries
          is structured as follows:

          <list style="numbers">
            <t>The fully-qualified host name of the node responding
              to the query;</t>

            <t>The city in which the node is located;</t>

            <t>The region in which the node is located;</t>

            <t>The economy in which the node is located; and</t>

            <t>The ICANN region in which the node is located.</t>
          </list>
        </t>

        <t>The A record returned in the response to such queries
          is guaranteed to be unique to the responding node.</t>

	<t>Since in this case identity data is published using
	  IN-class resource records, it is not necessary to send
	  queries directly towards L-Root in order to obtain results.
	  Responses can be obtained through recursive servers, the
	  responses in those cases being the identity of L-Root as
	  observed through the recursive server used rather than
	  the "closest" L-Root node to the client. This facilitates
	  some degree of remote troubleshooting, since a query for
	  IDENTITY.L.ROOT-SERVERS.ORG/IN/TXT or .../IN/A directed
	  a remote recursive resolver can help illustrate which
	  L-Root node is being used by that server (or was used
	  when the cache was populated).</t>

	<t>A related caching effect is that responses to
	  IDENTITY.L.ROOT-SERVERS.ORG/IN/A and
	  IDENTITY.L.ROOT-SERVERS.ORG/IN/TXT may be cached at
	  different times, and may hence persist in a cache for
	  overlapping periods of time. One possible visible effect
	  is that the responses to .../IN/A and .../IN/TXT as
	  presented from a cache may appear to be incoherent (i.e.
	  refer to different nodes) despite queries against of the
	  cache happening (near) simultaneously. Caches may also
	  discard the published TTLs in responses from the authoritative
	  server and replace them with longer TTLs, as a matter of
	  local policy. Interpretation of responses for these queries
	  from caches should therefore be carried out with these
	  possible effects in mind.</t>

        <t>It has been observed that IDENTITY.L.ROOT-SERVERS.ORG/IN/A
	  queries offer a useful mechanism for troubleshooting DNS
	  problems with non-technical users, since such users can
	  often be walked through the process of looking up an A
	  record (e.g. as a side effect of utilities such as ping)
	  far easier than they can be instructed on how use
	  DNS-specific tools such as dig.</t>

        <figure>
          <artwork>
% dig IDENTITY.L.ROOT-SERVERS.ORG TXT +short                  
"ytz01.l.root-servers.org" "Toronto" "Ontario" "Canada" "NorthAmerica"
% 

% dig IDENTITY.L.ROOT-SERVERS.ORG A +short  
67.215.199.91
% 
          </artwork>
        </figure>
      </section>

      <section title="Use of NODES.L.ROOT-SERVERS.ORG/IN/TXT">
        <t>The fully-qualified DNS name NODES.L.ROOT-SERVERS.ORG
          (note again the use of ORG, not NET) provides multiple
          TXT RRs, one per node, and represents the effective
          concatenation of all possible responses to the query
          IDENTITY.L.ROOT-SERVERS.ORG/IN/TXT.</t>

        <t>Note that in the example below we have forced dig to
	  send the query over TCP, since we expect the response to
	  be too large for UDP transport to accommodate. Note also
	  that the list shown is truncated for clarity, and can be
	  expected to change from time to time as new L-Root nodes
	  are provisioned and old ones decommissioned.</t>

	<figure>
	  <artwork>
% dig NODES.L.ROOT-SERVERS.ORG TXT +short +tcp | head -10
"abj01.l.root-servers.org" "Abidjan" "" "Cote d'Ivoire" "Africa"
"abj02.l.root-servers.org" "Abidjan" "" "Cote d'Ivoire" "Africa"
"akl01.l.root-servers.org" "Mangere" "" "New Zealand" "AsiaPacific"
"akl41.l.root-servers.org" "Mangere" "" "New Zealand" "AsiaPacific"
"akl42.l.root-servers.org" "Mangere" "" "New Zealand" "AsiaPacific"
"akl43.l.root-servers.org" "Mangere" "" "New Zealand" "AsiaPacific"
"akl44.l.root-servers.org" "Mangere" "" "New Zealand" "AsiaPacific"
"ams01.l.root-servers.org" "Haarlemmermeer" "" "Netherlands" "Europe"
"anc01.l.root-servers.org" "Anchorage" "Alaska" "United States" \
  "NorthAmerica"
%
	  </artwork>
	</figure>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Provisioning of IDENTITY.L.ROOT-SERVERS.ORG"
      anchor="identity">
      <t>Individual L-Root nodes run a dedicated, separate
        authority-only DNS server process which serves the
        IDENTITY.L.ROOT-SERVERS.ORG zone. The contents of that
        zone are unique to every node, and hence each responding
        node will generate a node-specific response.</t>

     <t>The contents of the IDENTITY.L.ROOT-SERVERS.ORG zone are
        hence deliberately incoherent, the apparent zone contents
        depending on the node responding to the corresponding
        query.</t>

      <t>The IDENTITY.L.ROOT-SERVERS.ORG zone is delegated to the
        single name server BEACON.L.ROOT-SERVERS.ORG, numbered
        on IPv4 and IPv6 addresses that are covered by the same
        routing advertisements that cover the L-Root service
        addresses. Reachability of BEACON.L.ROOT-SERVERS.ORG
        is hence well-aligned with the reachability of
        L.ROOT-SERVERS.NET, and hence measurement of the IDENTITY
        service ought to give similar results to measurement of
        the L-Root service.</t>

      <t>It is considered best practice always to delegate a
	DNS zone to more than one name server; however, as described,
	the IDENTITY.L.ROOT-SERVERS.ORG zone is delegated to just
	one server. Ordinarily this would present a risk of failure
	if that single server is not available; however, given the
	purpose of the delegation in this case and that the expected
	mitigation of a failure in a single node is the routing of
	a query to a different node, delegation to a single server
	in this particular use-case is effective.</t>

      <t>The L.ROOT-SERVERS.ORG zone is signed using DNSSEC, and
	hence secure responses for BEACON.L.ROOT-SERVERS.ORG and
	NODES.L.ROOT-SERVERS.ORG are available. IDENTITY.L.ROOT-SERVERS.ORG
	is an insecure delegation from the L.ROOT-SERVERS.ORG zone,
	however, following the operational preference to serve
	static data from each node for that zone, and the disinclination
	to distribute key materials and zone signing machinery to
	every node.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Security Considerations">
      <t>Some operators of anycast services choose not to disclose
	locations (or even numbers) of nodes, citing security
	concerns. The operator of L-Root considers that none of the
	published information described in this document is truly
	secret, since any service element which provides service
	to the Internet can be can never truly be obscured from
	view.  Given that location information can be found regardless
	of any conscious, deliberate disclosure, and since easy
	access to this information has diagnostic value, the operator
	of L-Root has adopted a policy of operational
	transparency.</t>

      <t>The information presented in this document presents no new
        threat to the Internet.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>This document makes no request of the IANA.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>The aspects of the L-Root service that were deployed to
	facilitate IN-class mapping were discussed and implemented
	as part of an informal collaboration with Xun Fan, John
	Heidemann and Ramesh Govidan, whose contributions are
	acknowledged.</t>

      <t>Helpful reviews and comments from Gaurab Upadhaya, Hugo
	Salgado, Brian Dixon, Bob Harold and Paul Hoffman on earlier
	versions of this document were very much appreciated.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      &rfc1034;
      &rfc1035;
      &rfc2671;
      &rfc4786;
      &rfc4892;
      &rfc5001;
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      &rfc6304;

      <reference anchor="Fan2013">
        <front>
          <title>Evaluating Anycast in the Domain Name System</title>
          <author initials="X." surname="Fan" fullname="Xun Fan">
            <organization abbrev="ISI">University of California
              Information Sciences Institute</organization>
            <address/>
          </author>
          <author initials="J." surname="Heidemann" fullname="John Heidemann">
            <organization abbrev="ISI">University of California
              Information Sciences Institute</organization>
            <address/>
          </author>
          <author initials="R." surname="Govidan" fullname="Ramesh Govidan">
            <organization abbrev="ISI">University of California
              Information Sciences Institute</organization>
            <address/>
          </author>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="Proceedings of the IEEE Infocom"
          value="Turin, Italy, April 2013"/>
        <format type="PDF" target="http://www.isi.edu/~johnh/PAPERS/Fan13a.pdf"/>
      </reference>
    </references>

    <section title="Editorial Notes">
      <t>This section (and sub-sections) to be removed prior to
        publication.</t>

      <section title="Change History">
        <t>
          <list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="00">Initial idea, circulated for the purposes of
              entertainment.</t>

            <t hangText="01">Added some commentary of use-cases of NSID
	      vs various/CH/TXT. Moved discussion of IN-class queries
	      from the NODES section to the IDENTITY section. Added
	      a note about DNSSEC for IDENTITY, NODES. Updated
	      acknowledgements section.</t>

            <t hangText="02">Clarified re-routing impact on HOSTNAME.BIND,
              ID.SERVER, LOCATION.L queries vs. NSID as not just applying
              to HOSTNAME.BIND. Fixed typos and absurd malapropisms.
              Cleaned up prompts in command-line examples and added text
              to clarify how such examples should be interpreted.</t>
	  </list>
	</t>
      </section>
    </section>
  </back>
</rfc>

