<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
  <!ENTITY rfc1035 PUBLIC ''
    'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1035.xml'>
  <!ENTITY rfc1918 PUBLIC ''
    'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1918.xml'>
  <!ENTITY rfc2308 PUBLIC ''
    'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2308.xml'>
  <!ENTITY rfc3172 PUBLIC ''
    'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3172.xml'>
  <!ENTITY rfc4033 PUBLIC ''
    'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4033.xml'>
  <!ENTITY rfc4786 PUBLIC ''
    'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4786.xml'>
  <!ENTITY rfc5737 PUBLIC ''
    'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5737.xml'>
  <!ENTITY rfc6303 PUBLIC ''
    'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6303.xml'>
  <!ENTITY rfc6304 PUBLIC ''
    'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6304.xml'>
  <!ENTITY rfc6672 PUBLIC ''
    'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6672.xml'>
]>

<rfc category="info" ipr="trust200902"
  docName="draft-jabley-dnsop-as112-dname-01"
  updates="6304">

  <?rfc toc="yes" ?>
  <?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
  <?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
  <?rfc iprnotified="no" ?>
  <?rfc strict="yes" ?>

  <front>
    <title>AS112 Redirection using DNAME</title>

    <author initials='J.' surname="Abley" fullname='Joe Abley'>
      <organization>ICANN</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>12025 Waterfront Drive, Suite 300</street>
          <city>Los Angeles</city>
          <region>CA</region>
          <code>90094-2536</code>
          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>
        <phone>+1 519 670 9327</phone>
        <email>joe.abley@icann.org</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author initials="B.P." surname="Dickson" fullname="Brian Dickson">
      <organization/>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>703 Palmer Drive</street>
          <city>Herndon</city>
          <region>VA</region>
          <code>20170</code>
        </postal>
        <email>brian.peter.dickson@gmail.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author initials="W." surname="Kumari" fullname="Warren Kumari">
      <organization>Google</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>1600 Amphitheatre Parkway</street>
          <city>Mountain View</city>
          <region>CA</region>
          <code>94043</code>
        </postal>
        <email>warren@kumari.net</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author initials="G." surname="Michaelson" fullname="George Michaelson">
      <organization>APNIC</organization>
      <address>
        <email>ggm@apnic.net</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date month="October" year="2013"/>

    <abstract>
      <t>Many sites connected to the Internet make use of IPv4
	addresses that are not globally unique.  Examples are the
	addresses designated in RFC 1918 for private use within
	individual sites.</t>

      <t>Devices in such environments may occasionally originate
	Domain Name System (DNS) queries (so-called "reverse lookups")
	corresponding to those private-use addresses.  Since the
	addresses concerned have only local significance, it is
	good practice for site administrators to ensure that such
	queries are answered locally.  However, it is not uncommon
	for such queries to follow the normal delegation path in
	the public DNS instead of being answered within the site.</t>

      <t>It is not possible for public DNS servers to give useful
	answers to such queries.  In addition, due to the wide
	deployment of private-use addresses and the continuing
	growth of the Internet, the volume of such queries is large
	and growing.  The AS112 project aims to provide a distributed
	sink for such queries in order to reduce the load on the
	IN-ADDR.ARPA authoritative servers.  The AS112 project is
	named after the Autonomous System Number (ASN) that was
	assigned to it.</t>

      <t>The AS112 project does not accommodate the addition and
	removal of DNS zones elegantly. Since additional zones of
	definitively local significance are known to exist, this
	presents a problem. This document describes modifications
	to the deployment and use of AS112 infrastructure that will
	allow zones to be added and dropped much more easily.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>The AS112 project is described in detail in <xref
        target="RFC6304"/>.</t>

      <t>The AS112 nameservers (PRISONER.IANA.ORG,
        BLACKHOLE-1.IANA.ORG and BLACKHOLE-2.IANA.ORG) are required
        to answer authoritatively for each and every zone that is
        delegated to them.</t>

      <t>If a zone is delegated to AS112 nameservers without those
	nameservers being configured ahead of time to answer
	authoritatively for that zone, there is a detrimental impact
	on clients following referrals for queries within that zone.
	This misconfiguration is colloquially known as a "lame
	delegation".</t>

      <t>AS112 nameserver operators are only loosely-coordinated,
	and hence adding support for a new zone (or, correspondingly,
	removing support for a zone that is no longer delegated to
	the AS112 nameservers) is difficult to accomplish with
	accuracy; testing AS112 nameservers remotely to see whether
	they are configured to answer authoritatively for a particular
	zone is similarly challenging since AS112 nodes are distributed
	using <xref target="RFC4786">anycast</xref>.</t>

      <t>This document proposes that instead of delegating individual
	zones to AS112 nameservers, <xref target="RFC6672">DNAME</xref>
	redirection be used instead.  This approach has the advantage
	that query traffic for arbitrary parts of the namespace can
	be directed to AS112 servers without those servers having
	to be reconfigured every time a zone is added or removed.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Design Overview">
      <t>A new zone, EMPTY.AS112.ARPA, is delegated to a single
	nameserver BLACKHOLE.AS112.ARPA (IPv4 address TBAv4-1, IPv6
	address TBAv6-1).</t>

      <t>The IPv4 address TBAv4-1 has been assigned by the IANA
	such that the address is coverable by a single IPv4 /24
	prefix, and that no other address covered by that prefix
	is in use. The IPv6 address TBAv6-1 has been similarly
	assigned such that no other address within a covering /48
	is in use. This addressing plan accommodates the anycast
        distribution of the BLACKHOLE.AS112.ARPA service using a
        single IPv4 service prefix and a single IPv6 service prefix.
        See <xref target="RFC4786"/> for more discussion of anycast
        service distribution; see <xref target="iana"/> for the specific
	requests this document makes of the IANA.</t>

      <t>Some or all of the existing AS112 nodes should be extended
	to support these new nameserver addresses, and to host the
	EMPTY.AS112.ARPA zone. See <xref target="extensions"/> for
	guidance to AS112 server operators.</t>

      <t>Each part of the DNS namespace for which it is desirable to
	sink queries at AS112 nameservers should be redirected to
	the EMPTY.AS112.ARPA zone using <xref target="RFC6672">DNAME</xref>.
        See <xref target="redirection"/> for guidance to zone
        administrators.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="AS112 Operations">
      <section title="Extensions to Support DNAME Redirection"
          anchor="extensions">
	<t>The guidance provided in <xref target="RFC6304"/> is
	  extended to include configuration of the TBAv4-1, and
	  TBAv6-1 addresses, and the corresponding announcement of
	  covering routes for those addresses, and to host the
	  EMPTY.AS112.ARPA zone.</t>

        <t>IPv4-only AS112 nodes should only configure the TBAv4-1
	  nameserver address; IPv6-only AS112 nodes should only
	  configure the TBAv6-1 nameserver address.</t>

        <t>It is only necessary for a single AS112 server operator
	  to implement these extensions for this mechanism to
	  function as intended. It is beneficial if many more than
	  one AS112 server operators make these changes, however,
	  since that provides for greater distribution and capacity
          for the nameservers serving the EMPTY.AS112.ARPA zone.
	  It is not necessary for all AS112 server operators to
	  make these changes for the mechanism to be viable.</t>

        <t>Detailed instructions for the implementation of these
          extensions is included in <xref target="6304bis"/>.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Redirection of Query Traffic to AS112 Servers"
          anchor="redirection">
        <t>Once the EMPTY.AS112.ARPA zone has been deployed using the
	  nameservers described in <xref target="extensions"/>,
	  redirections may be installed in the DNS namespace for
	  queries that are intended to be answered by the AS112
	  infrastructure.</t>

	<t>For example, reverse queries corresponding to <xref
	  target="RFC5737">TEST-NET-1 (192.0.2.0/24)</xref> could
	  be redirected to AS112 nameservers by installing a DNAME
	  resource record in the 192.IN-ADDR.ARPA zone, as illustrated
	  in <xref target="TEST-NET-1"/>.</t>

        <figure anchor="TEST-NET-1">
          <artwork>
  $ORIGIN 192.IN-ADDR.ARPA.
  ...
  2.0.IN-ADDR.ARPA.  IN  DNAME  EMPTY.AS112.ARPA.
  ...
          </artwork>
        </figure>

	<t>There is no practical limit to the number of redirections
	  that can be configured in this fashion.  Redirection of
	  a particular part of the namespace to EMPTY.AS112.ARPA
	  can be removed at any time, under the control of the
	  administrators of the corresponding part of the DNS
	  namespace. No changes to deployed AS112 nodes incorporating
	  the extensions described in this document are required
	  to support additional redirections. A list of possible
	  candidates for AS112 redirection can be found in <xref
	  target="candidates"/>.</t>

	<t>DNAME resource records deployed for this purpose can be
	  signed with <xref target="RFC4033">DNSSEC</xref>, providing
	  a secure means of authenticating the legitimacy of each
	  redirection.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Continuity of AS112 Operations">
      <t>Existing guidance to AS112 server operators to accept and
        respond to queries directed at the PRISONER.IANA.ORG,
        BLACKHOLE-1.IANA.ORG and BLACKHOLE-2.IANA.ORG nameservers
        should continue to be followed, and no changes to the
        delegation of existing zones hosted on AS112 servers
	should occur.  These measures are intended to provide
	continuity of operations for zones currently delegated to
	AS112 servers and avoid any accidental client impact due
	to the changes proposed in this document.</t>

      <t>Once it has become empirically and quantitatively clear that 
	the EMPTY.AS112.ARPA zone is well-hosted to the extent that
	it is thought that the existing, unmodified AS112 servers
	host 10.IN-ADDR.ARPA, the decision might be made to replace
	the delegation of those <xref target="RFC1918"/> zones with
	DNAME redirection. Once implemented, the PRISONER.IANA.ORG,
	BLACKHOLE-1.IANA.ORG and BLACKHOLE-2.IANA.ORG nameservers
	could be retired. This document gives no such direction to
	the IANA, however.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Candidate Zones for AS112 Redirection"
        anchor="candidates">
      <t>All zones listed in <xref target="RFC6303"/> are candidates
        for AS112 redirection.</t>

      <t>Since no pre-provisioning is required on the part of AS112
        operators to facilitate sinking of any name in the DNS namespace
        by AS112 infrastructure, this mechanism supports AS112 redirection
        by any zone owner in the DNS.</t>

      <t>This document is simply concerned with provision of the
	AS112 redirection service, and does not specify that any
	particular AS112 redirection be put in place.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="DNAME Deployment Considerations">
      <t>DNAME was specified a significant time following the original
        implementations of <xref target="RFC1035"/>, and hence universal
        deployment cannot be expected. <xref target="RFC6672"/> specifies
        a fall-back mechanism which makes use of synthesised CNAME RRSets
        for this reason. The expectation that design choices in the
        DNAME specification ought to mitigate any lack of deployment is
        reviewed below. Experimental validation of those expectations is
        included in <xref target="experiment"/>.</t>

      <t>It is a fundamental design requirement of AS112 service that
        responses be cached. We can safely declare DNAME support on the
        authoritative server to be a prerequisite for DNAME redirection,
        but the cases where individual elements in resolver chains do
        not support DNAME processing deserve closer examination.</t>

      <t>The expected behaviour when a DNAME response is supplied to a
	resolver that does not support DNAME is that the accompanying,
	synthesised CNAME will be accepted and cached. Re-query
	frequency will be determined by the TTLs returned by the
	DNAME-responding authoritative servers.</t>

      <t>Resolution of the CNAME target is straightforward and
	functions exactly as the AS112 project has operated since
	it was deployed.  The <xref target="RFC2308">negative
	caching</xref> of the CNAME target follows the parameters
	defined in the target zone, EMPTY.AS112.ARPA. This has the
	side-effects that all redirected names ultimately landing
	on an AS112 node will be negatively-cached with the same
	parameters, but this lack of flexibility seems non-controversial;
	the effect of reducing the negative cache TTL would be
	increased query volume on the AS112 node operator concerned,
	and hence controls seem well-aligned with operation.</t>

      <t>Validating resolvers (i.e. those requesting and processing
	<xref target="RFC4033">DNSSEC</xref> metadata) are required
	to implement DNAME, and hence should not make use of
	synthesised CNAME RRs. The lack of signature over a received
	CNAME RR should hence not limit the ability to sign the
	redirection point, and for those signatures to be validated.</t>

      <t>In the case where a recursive server implements DNAME, but
	DNAME is not implemented in a stub resolver, CNAME synthesis
	will again provide a viable path.</t>

      <t>DNAME support on AS112 nodes themselves is never required
        under this proposal.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="IAB Considerations">
      <t>This document proposes a delegation within the ARPA domain,
        and, in accordance with <xref target="RFC3172"/>, IAB review
        and approval of the delegation of AS112.ARPA as described
        in <xref target="iana"/> is required.</t>

      <t>Once IAB approval has been obtained, this section may be
        removed prior to publication or updated to include text that
        confirms the IAB's decision, at the IAB's discretion.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="IANA Considerations" anchor="iana">
      <section title="Address Assignment">
	<t>The IANA is requested to assign one IPv4 /24 netblock
	  and one IPv6 /48 netblock that, to the best of their
	  knowledge, should be suitable for announcement as a single
	  IPv4 /24 prefix and a single IPv6 prefix on the global
	  Internet, respectively.</t>

        <t>Once assigned, all occurrences of TBAv4 in this document
	  should be replaced by the IPv4 netblock assigned, in
	  conventional notation. Occurrences of TBAv4-1 should be
	  replaced with an address from the netblock with lowest
	  octet set to 1. Similarly, all occurrences of TBAv6 in
	  this document should be replaced by the IPv6 netblock
	  assigned, in conventional notation, and TBAv6-1 replaced
	  with an address from that netblock with the lowest 48
	  bits set to the value 1. Once those changes are made, this
          paragraph may be removed prior to publication.</t>

        <t>The netblocks assigned by the IANA for this purpose are
          TBAv4 and TBAv6.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Hosting of AS112.ARPA" anchor="hosting">
	<t>The IANA is requested to host and sign the zone AS112.ARPA
	  using nameservers and DNSSEC signing infrastructure of their
          choosing, as shown in <xref target="as112arpa"/>. SOA RDATA
          may be adjusted by the IANA to suit their operational
          requirements.</t>

        <figure anchor="as112arpa">
          <artwork>
  $ORIGIN AS112.ARPA.
  $TTL 3600

  @       IN      SOA     BLACKHOLE.AS112.ARPA. NOC.DNS.ICANN.ORG. (
                                  1               ; serial
                                  10800           ; refresh
                                  3600            ; retry
                                  1209600         ; expire
                                  3600 )          ; negative cache TTL

                  NS      A.IANA-SERVERS.NET.
                  NS      B.IANA-SERVERS.NET.
                  NS      C.IANA-SERVERS.NET.

  BLACKHOLE       A       TBAv4-1
                  AAAA    TBAv6-1

  EMPTY           NS      BLACKHOLE
          </artwork>
        </figure>
      </section>

      <section title="Delegation of AS112.ARPA">
        <t>Once the AS112.ARPA zone is being hosted in production,
	  the IANA is requested to arrange delegation from the ARPA
	  zone according to normal IANA procedure for ARPA zone
	  management, to the nameservers used in carrying out the
          direction in <xref target="hosting"/>. The following
          metadata is suggested for the delegation, but may be
          changed by the IANA if required:</t>

        <texttable>
          <ttcol>Name</ttcol>
          <ttcol>Value</ttcol>

          <c>Domain:</c>
          <c>AS112.ARPA</c>

          <c>Administrative Contact:</c>
          <c>Internet Architecture Board (IAB) c/o IETF Administrative
            Support Activity, ISOC</c>

          <c>Technical Contact:</c>
          <c>Internet Assigned Numbers Authority (IANA)</c>

          <c>Nameservers:</c>
          <c>As chosen by the IANA, see <xref target="hosting"/></c>

          <c>DS-RDATA:</c>
          <c>As chosen by the IANA, see <xref target="hosting"/></c>
        </texttable>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Security Considerations">
      <t>This document presents no known additional security concerns
        to the Internet.</t>

      <t>For security considerations relating to AS112 service in
        general, see <xref target="RFC6304"/>.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>Your name here, etc.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      &rfc1035;
      &rfc2308;
      &rfc6304;
      &rfc6672;
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      &rfc1918;
      &rfc3172;
      &rfc4033;
      &rfc4786;
      &rfc5737;
      &rfc6303;
    </references>

    <section title="Assessing Support for DNAME in the Real World"
        anchor="experiment">
      <t>To measure the extent to which the DNAME construct is
	supported in the Internet, we have used an experimental
	technique to test the DNS resolvers used by end hosts, and
	derive from the test a measurement of DNAME support within
	the Internet.</t>

      <section title="Methodology">
	<t>The test was conducted by loading a user's browser with
	  4 URLs to retrieve.  The first three comprise the test
	  setup, while the final URL communicates the result the
	  the experiment controller. The URLs are:

          <list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="A">http://a.&lt;unique_string&gt;.dname.example.com/1x1.png?<vspace blankLines="0"/>a.&lt;unique_string&gt;.dname</t>

            <t hangText="B">http://b.dname.example.com/1x1.png?<vspace blankLines="0"/>b.&lt;unique_string&gt;.dname</t>

            <t hangText="C">http://c.&lt;unique_string&gt;.target.example.net/1x1.png?<vspace blankLines="0"/>c.&lt;unique_string&gt;.target</t>

            <t hangText="D">http://results.recorder.example.net/1x1.png?<vspace blankLines="0"/>results.&lt;unique_string&gt;?za=&lt;a_result&gt;&zb=&lt;b_result&gt;&zc=&lt;c_result&gt;
            </t>
          </list>
        </t>

	<t>The A URL is designed to test the end users capability
	  to resolve a name that has never been seen before, so that
	  the resolution of this domain name will reliably result
	  in a query at the authoritative name server. This is
	  intended to test the use of domain names where there is
	  a dynamic component that also uses the DNAME construct.</t>

	<t>The B URL is deliberately designed to be cached by caching
	  resolvers that are used in the process of resolving the
	  domain name.</t>

	<t>The C URL is a control URL. This is a unique URL, similar
	  to A, but does not refer to a DNAME structure.</t>

        <t>The D URL uses a static cacheable domain name.</t>

	<t>The &lt;unique_string&gt; value is common to the four
	  URLs used in each individual instance of this test, but
	  varies from test to test. The result is that each end
	  user is presented with a unique string.</t>

        <t>The contents of the EXAMPLE.COM, TARGET.EXAMPLE.NET and
          RECORDER.EXAMPLE.NET zones are shown in
          <xref target="experiment-zones"/>.</t>

        <figure anchor="experiment-zones">
          <artwork>
  $ORIGIN EXAMPLE.COM.
  ...
  DNAME.             IN  DNAME  TARGET.EXAMPLE.NET.
  ...

  $ORIGIN TARGET.EXAMPLE.NET.
  ...
  B                  IN  A      192.0.2.0
  *                  IN  A      192.0.2.0
  ...

  $ORIGIN RECORDER.EXAMPLE.NET.
  ...
  RESULTS            IN  A      192.0.2.0
  ...
          </artwork>
        </figure>

	<t>The first three URLs (A, B and C) are loaded as tasks
	  into the user's browser upon execution of the test's
	  script.  The script starts a timer with each of these
	  URLs to measure the elapsed time to fetch the URL. The
	  script then waits for the three fetches to complete, or
	  10 seconds, whichever occurs first. The script then loads
	  the results of the three timers into the GET arguments
	  of the D URL, and performs a fetch to pass these results
	  back to the experiment's server.</t>

        <t>Logs on the web server reached at RESULTS.EXAMPLE.NET
	  will include entries of the form shown in <xref
	  target="experiment-results"/>. If any of the URLs fail
	  to load within 10 secords the D URL will report the failure
	  as a "null" timer value.</t>

       <figure anchor="experiment-results">
          <artwork>
  GET /1x1.png?results.&lt;unique_string&gt;?za=1822&zb=1674&zc=1582
  GET /1x1.png?results.&lt;unique_string&gt;?za=null&zb=null&zc=161
          </artwork>
       </figure>

	<t>The script has been encoded in Adobe Flash with a simple
	  image in the form of an online advertisement. An online
	  advertisement network has been used to distribute the
	  script. The script is invoked when the advertisement is
	  presented in the end user's browser or application, and
	  does not require the user to click on the supplied image
	  in any way.  The advertisement placement parameters were
	  set to to broadest possible scope to sample users from
	  across the entire internet.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Results">
	<t>The test was loaded into an advertisement distributed
          on the 2013-10-10 and 2013-10-11.</t>

        <texttable anchor="table_ex">
          <ttcol align='left'> </ttcol>
          <ttcol align='right'>Count</ttcol>
          <ttcol align='right'>Percentage</ttcol>

          <c>Recorded Results:</c><c>338,478</c><c></c>
          <c>A or B Loaded:</c><c>331,896</c><c>98.1%</c>
          <c>A Fail and B Fail:</c><c>6,492</c><c>1.9%</c>
          <c>A Fail and B Load:</c><c>4,249</c><c>1.3%</c>
          <c>A Load and B Fail:</c><c>1,624</c><c>0.5%</c>
          <c>C Fail:</c><c>9,355</c><c>2.8%</c>
        </texttable>

	<t>These results indicate that at most 1.9% of tested
	  clients use DNS resolvers that fail to resolve a domain
	  name that contains a DNAME redirection.  However the
	  failure rate of slightly lower than 3% for the control
	  URL indicates that the failure rate for the DNAME construct
	  lies within the bounds of error within the experimental
	  framework. We conclude that there is no evidence of a
	  consistent failure on the part of deployed DNS resolvers
	  to correctly resolve a DNAME construct.</t>

	<t>This experiment was conducted by Geoff Huston and George
	  Michaelson.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Updates to RFC6304" anchor="6304bis">
      <t>The following changes are required to <xref target="RFC6304"/>
        to provide support for AS112 redirection. It is proposed that
        a successor document to <xref target="RFC6304"/> be prepared
        for joint publication with this document in the interests of
        providing clear advice to prospective new AS112 operators. The
        following sub-sections are hence provided mainly only to describe
        the scope of the changes required for 6304bis, and are not
        intended for publication in this document. References to this
        section in this document should ultimately be replaced with
        references to 6304bis.</t>

      <section title="Changes to Section 2.1, Zones">
        <t>The list of zones that the AS112 nameserver should answer
          authoritatively for is extended to include EMPTY.AS112.ARPA.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Changes to Section 2.2, Nameservers">
        <t>The nameserver BLACKHOLE.AS112.ARPA (IPv4 address
          TBAv4-1, IPv6 address TBAv6-1) is added to the list of nameserver
          addresses that the AS112 node should support. The IPv4 prefix
          TBAv4/24 and the IPv6 prefix TBAv6/48 are added as new prefixes
          to be originated.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Changes to Section 3.4, Routing Software">
        <t>The sample configuration provided in this section is extended
          to accommodate the IPv4 and IPv6 service prefixes associated
          with AS112 redirection, TBAv4/24 and TBAv6/48, respectively.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Changes to Section 3.5, DNS Software">
        <t>The sample configuration provided in this section is extended
          to accommodate the TBAv4-1 and TBAv6-1 addresses and the
          EMPTY.AS112.ARPA zone. The contents of the EMPTY.AS112.ARPA
          zone should be specified (nameservers differ from that
          included as "db.empty").</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Changes to Section 3.6, Testing a Newly Installed Node">
        <t>Testing should be extended to test for correct hosting of the
          EMPTY.AS112.ARPA zone.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Changes to Section 6, On the Future of AS112 Nodes">
        <t>A reference to this document should be included.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Changes to Section 8, Security Considerations">
        <t>Mention should be made that AS112 redirection, as specified
          in this document, supports DNSSEC in the sense that the DNAME
          records which signal the redirection can be signed.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Changes to Appendix A, History">
        <t>A reference to this document should be included.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Editorial Notes">
      <t>This section (and sub-sections) to be removed prior to
        publication.</t>

      <section title="Change History">
        <t>
          <list style="hanging">
	    <t hangText="00">Initial write-up of Brian's idea,
	      circulated for the purposes of entertainment.</t>

            <t hangText="01">Some particularly egregious spelling
              mistakes fixed.</t>

            <t hangText="02">Warren Kumari and George Michaelson added
              as co-authors. Intended status changed to informational.
              Appendix on DNAME testing added, describing an experiment
              conducted by Geoff Huston and George Michaelson.</t>
	  </list>
	</t>
      </section>
    </section>
  </back>
</rfc>

