<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
  <!ENTITY rfc1034 PUBLIC ''
    'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1034.xml'>
  <!ENTITY rfc1035 PUBLIC ''
    'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1035.xml'>
  <!ENTITY rfc4033 PUBLIC ''
    'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4033.xml'>
  <!ENTITY rfc4034 PUBLIC ''
    'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4034.xml'>
  <!ENTITY rfc4035 PUBLIC ''
    'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4035.xml'>
  <!ENTITY rfc5011 PUBLIC ''
    'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5011.xml'>
  <!ENTITY rfc5905 PUBLIC ''
    'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5905.xml'>
  <!ENTITY I-D.jabley-dnssec-trust-anchor PUBLIC ''
    'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.draft-jabley-dnssec-trust-anchor-01.xml'>
]>

<rfc category="bcp" ipr="trust200902"
 docName="draft-jabley-dnsop-validator-bootstrap-00">

<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc iprnotified="no" ?>
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>

  <front>
    <title abbrev="Validator Boostrap">Establishing an Appropriate Root
      Zone DNSSEC Trust Anchor at Startup</title>

    <author initials='J.' surname="Abley" fullname='Joe Abley'>
      <organization>ICANN</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>4676 Admiralty Way, Suite 330</street>
          <city>Marina del Rey</city>
          <region>CA</region>
          <code>90292</code>
          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>
        <phone>+1 519 670 9327</phone>
        <email>joe.abley@icann.org</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Dave Knight" initials="D." surname="Knight">
      <organization>ICANN</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>4676 Admiralty Way, Suite 330</street>
          <city>Marina del Rey</city>
          <region>CA</region>
          <code>90292</code>
          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>
        <phone>+1 310 913 4512</phone>
        <email>dave.knight@icann.org</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date day="31" month="January" year="2011"/>

    <abstract>
      <t>Domain Name System Security Extensions (DNSSEC) allow
	cryptographic signatures to be used to validate responses
	received from the Domain Name System (DNS). A DNS client
	which validates such signatures is known as a validator.</t>

      <t>The choice of appropriate root zone trust anchor for a
	validator is expected to vary over time as the corresponding
	cryptographic keys used in DNSSEC are changed.</t>

      <t>This document provides guidance on how validators
	might determine an appropriate trust anchor for the root
	zone to use at start-up, or when other mechanisms intended
	to allow key rollover to be tolerated gracefully are not
	available.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Definitions">
      <t>The terms Key Signing Key (KSK) and Trust Anchor are used
        as defined in <xref target="RFC4033"/>.</t>

      <t>The term Validator is used in this document to mean a
        Validating Security-Aware Stub Resolver, as defined in
        <xref target="RFC4033"/>.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Introduction" anchor="introduction">
      <t>The Domain Name System (DNS) is described
	in <xref target="RFC1034"/> and <xref target="RFC1035"/>.
        DNS Security Extensions (DNSSEC) are described in
        <xref target="RFC4033"/>, <xref target="RFC4034"/> and
        <xref target="RFC4035"/>.</t>

      <t>The root zone of the DNS was signed using DNSSEC in July
        2011, and many top-level domain registries have since
        signed their zones, installing secure delegations for
        them in the root zone. A single trust anchor for the root
        zone is hence increasingly sufficient for validators.</t>

      <t>Validators are deployed in a variety of environments, and
        there is variation in the amount of system administration
        that might reasonably be expected to be available. For
        example, embedded devices might never be administered by a
        human operator, whereas validators deployed on general-purpose
        operating systems in enterprise networks might have
        technical staff available to assist with their configuration.</t>

      <t>This document includes descriptions of mechanisms
        for validator bootstrapping, intended to be sufficient for
        embedded devices. The implementation of those mechanisms
        might be automatic in the case of unattended devices, or
        manual, carried out by a systems administrator, depending
        on local circumstances.</t>

      <t>The choice of appropriate trust anchor for a DNSSEC Validator
	is expected to vary over time as the corresponding KSK used
	in the root zone is changed. The DNSSEC Policy and Practice
	Statement (DPS) for the root zone KSK maintainer <xref
	target="KSK-DPS"/> specifies that scheduled KSK rollover
	will be undertaken according to the semantics specified in
	<xref target="RFC5011"/>. Validators which are able to
	recognise and accommodate those semantics should need no
	additional support to be able to maintain an appropriate
	trust anchor over a root zone KSK rollover event.</t>

      <t>The possibility remains, however, that <xref target="RFC5011"/>
        signalling will not be available
	to a validator: e.g. certain classes of emergency KSK
	rollover may require a compromised KSK to be discarded more
	quickly than <xref target="RFC5011"/> specifies, or a
	validator might be off-line over the whole key-roll event.</t>

      <t>This document provides guidance on how DNSSEC Validators
	might determine an appropriate set of trust anchors to use
	at start-up, or when other mechanisms intended to allow key
	rollover to be tolerated gracefully are not available.</t>

      <t>The bootstrapping procedures described in this document
	are also expected to be useful for a deployed, running
	validator which is not able to accommodate a KSK roll using
	<xref target="RFC5011"/> signalling.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Summary of Approach">
      <t>A validator that has no valid trust anchor initialises itself
        as follows.</t>

      <section title="Initial State">
        <t>A validator in its initial state is capable of sending and
          receiving DNS queries and responses, but is not capable of
          validating signatures received in responses.</t>

        <t>A validator must confirm that its local clock is
          sufficiently accurate before trust anchors can be
          established, and before processing of DNSSEC signatures
          can proceed. Discussion of timing considerations can be found
          in <xref target="timing"/>.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Trust Anchor Retrieval">
        <t>Once the local clock has been synchronised, a validator
          may proceed to gather candidate trust anchors for consideration.
          Discussion of trust anchor retrieval can be found in
          <xref target="retrieval"/>.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Trust Anchor Selection">
        <t>Once a set of candidate trust anchors has been obtained,
          a validator attempts to find one trust anchor in the set
          which is appropriate for use. This process involves
          verification of cryptographic signatures, and is discussed
          in <xref target="selection"/>.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Full Operation">
        <t>The validator now has an accurate trust anchor for the
          root zone, and is capable of validating signatures on
          responses from the DNS.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Timing Considerations" anchor="timing">
      <t>DNSSEC signatures are valid for particular periods of time,
	as specified by the administrator of the zone containing
	the signatures. It follows that any validator must maintain
	an accurate local clock in order to verify that signatures are
        accurate.</t>

      <t>Trust anchors correspond to KSKs in particular zones. Zone
        administrators may choose to replace KSKs from time to time,
        e.g. due to a key compromise or local key management policy, and
        the corresponding appropriate choice in trust anchor will change
        as KSKs are replaced.</t>

      <t>Trust anchors for the root zone in particular are published
	with intended validity periods, as discussed in
	<xref target="retrieval"/>. A validator making use of such
	trust anchors also requires an accurate local clock in order
	to avoid configuring a local trust anchor which corresponds
	to an old key.</t>

      <t>Validators should take appropriate steps to ensure that
	their local clocks are set with sufficient accuracy, and
	in the case where local clocks are set with reference to
	external time sources over a network <xref target="RFC5905"/>
	that the time information received from those sources is
	authentic.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Retrieval of Candidate Trust Anchors" anchor="retrieval">
      <t>Candidate trust anchors may be retrieved using several
        mechanisms. The process of gaining trust in particular
        candidate trust anchors before using them is discussed
        in <xref target="selection"/>.</t>

      <section title="Retrieval of Trust Anchors from Local Sources">
        <t>A trust anchor which is packaged with validator software
	  can never be trusted, since the corresponding root zone
	  KSK may have rolled since the software was packaged, and
	  the trust anchor may be derived from a root zone KSK that
	  was retired due to compromise.</t>

        <t>Validators should never use local trust anchors for
          bootstrapping.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Retrieval of Trust Anchors from the DNS">
	<t>The current root zone trust anchor is a hash (in DS RDATA
	  format) of a member of the root zone apex DNSKEY RRSet
	  that has the SEP bit set. Such a trust anchor could be
          derived from a response to the query ". IN DNSKEY?",
          but there is no mechanism available to trust the result:
          without an existing, accurate trust anchor the validator
          has no means to gauge the authenticity of the response.</t>

        <t>Validators should never derive trust anchors from
          DNSKEY RRSets obtained from the DNS.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Retrieval of Trust Anchors from the Root Zone
         KSK Manager">
        <t>The Root Zone KSK Manager publishes trust anchors
          corresponding to the root zone KSK as described in
          <xref target="I-D.jabley-dnssec-trust-anchor"/>.</t>

        <t>A full history of previously-published trust anchors,
	  including the trust anchor recommended for immediate use,
	  is made available in an XML document at the following
          stable URLs:

          <list style="symbols">
            <t><eref target="http://data.iana.org/root-anchors/root-anchors.xml"/></t>
            <t><eref target="https://data.iana.org/root-anchors/root-anchors.xml"/></t>
          </list>

	  Validity periods for each trust anchor packaged in the
	  root-anchors.xml document are provided as XML attributes,
	  allowing an appropriate trust anchor for immediate use
	  to be identified (but see <xref target="timing"/>).</t>

        <t>Individual trust anchors are also packaged as X.509
	  identity certificates, signed by various Certificate
	  Authorities (CAs). URLs to allow those certificates to
	  be retrieved are included as optional elements in the XML
	  document.</t>

	<t>For automatic bootstrapping, the recommended approach
	  is as follows.

          <list style="numbers">
	    <t>Retrieve <eref
	      target="http://data.iana.org/root-anchors/root-anchors.xml"/></t>

            <t>Identify the trust anchors which are valid for current
              use, with reference to the current time and date.</t>

            <t>Retrieve the corresponding X.509 identity certificates
              for the key identified in the previous step, for use
              in establishing trust in the retrieved trust anchor
              (see <xref target="selection"/>).</t>
	  </list>
	</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Establishing Trust in Candidate Trust Anchors"
        anchor="selection">
      <t>Once a candidate trust anchor has been retrieved, the validator
	must establish that it is authentic before it can be used.
	This document recommends that this be carried out by checking
	the signatures on each of the X.509 identity certificates
	retrieved in the previous step until a certificate is found
	which matches a CA trust anchor.</t>

      <t>This verification phase requires that validators ship with
	a useful set of CA trust anchors, and that corresponding
	identity certificates are published by the root zone KSK
	manager.  In some cases validator implementors may decide
	to use commercial CA services, perhaps a subset of the
	"browser list" that is commonly distributed with web browsers;
	alternatively a vendor may instantiate its own CA and make
	arrangements with the root zone KSK manager to have the
	corresponding identity certificate locations published in
	root-anchors.xml.</t>

      <t>The CA trust anchors packaged with validators should
        have an expected lifetime in excess of the anticipated
        life of the validator. As a protection against CA failure,
        validators are recommended to ship with more than one CA
        trust anchor.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Failure to Locate a Valid Trust Anchor">
      <t>A validator that has failed to locate a valid trust anchor
	may re-try the retrieval and trust establishment phases
	indefinitely, but must not perform validation on DNS responses
	until a valid trust anchor has been identified.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="IANA Considerations" anchor="iana">
      <t>This document has no IANA actions.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Security Considerations">
      <t>This document discusses an approach for automatic configuration
        of trust anchors in a DNSSEC validator.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      &rfc1034;
      &rfc1035;
      &rfc4033;
      &rfc4034;
      &rfc4035;
      &rfc5011;
      &rfc5905;

      &I-D.jabley-dnssec-trust-anchor;

      <reference anchor="KSK-DPS">
        <front>
	  <title abbrev="Root Zone KSK Operator DPS">DNSSEC Practice
	    Statement for the Root Zone KSK Operator</title>

          <author fullname="Fredrik Ljunggren" initials="F." surname="Ljunggren">
            <organization abbrev="Kirei">Kirei AB</organization>
            <address>
              <postal>
                <street>P.O. Box 53204</street>
                <city>Goteborg</city>
                <code>SE-400 16</code>
                <country>Sweden</country>
              </postal>
              <email>fredrik@kirei.se</email>
            </address>
          </author>

          <author fullname="Tomofumi Okubo" initials="T." surname="Okubo">
            <organization abbrev="VeriSign">VeriSign Inc.</organization>
            <address>
              <postal>
                <street>21345 Ridgetop Circle</street>
                <city>Dulles</city>
                <region>VA</region>
                <code>20166-6503</code>
                <country>USA</country>
              </postal>
              <email>tookubo@verisign.com</email>
            </address>
          </author>
          <author fullname="Richard Lamb" initials="R." surname="Lamb">
            <organization abbrev="ICANN">Internet Corporation For Assigned Names and
            Numbers</organization>
            <address>
              <postal>
                <street>4676 Admiralty Way, Suite 330</street>
                <city>Marina del Ray</city>
                <region>CA</region>
                <code>90292</code>
                <country>USA</country>
              </postal>
              <email>richard.lamb@icann.org</email>
            </address>
          </author>

          <author fullname="Jakob Schlyter" initials="J." surname="Schlyter">
            <organization abbrev="Kirei">Kirei AB</organization>
            <address>
              <postal>
                <street>P.O. Box 53204</street>
                <city>Goteborg</city>
                <code>SE-400 16</code>
                <country>Sweden</country>
              </postal>
              <email>jakob@kirei.se</email>
            </address>
          </author>
        
          <date day="21" month="May" year="2010" />
        
          <keyword>DNS</keyword>
          <keyword>DNSSEC</keyword>
        </front>

        <format type="TXT"
          target="https://www.iana.org/dnssec/icann-dps.txt" />
      </reference>

    </references>

    <section title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>This document contains material first discussed at VeriSign
	and ICANN during the deployment of DNSSEC in the root zone,
	and also draws upon subsequent technical discussion from
	public mailing lists.  The contributions of all those who
	voiced opinions are acknowledged.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Editorial Notes">
      <t>This section (and sub-sections) to be removed prior to
        publication.</t>

      <section title="Discussion">
        <t>This is not a working group document. However, the topics
	  discussed in this document are consistent with the general
	  subject area of the DNSOP working group, and discussion
	  of this document could reasonably take place on the
	  corresponding mailing list.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Change History">
        <t>
          <list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="00">Initial draft.</t>
          </list>
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>
  </back>
</rfc>

