<?xml version='1.0'?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM 'rfc2629.dtd'>
<?rfc toc="yes" symrefs="yes" ?>

<rfc ipr="trust200902" category="info" docName="draft-ietf-codec-guidelines-06">

<front>
<title abbrev="Codec Guidelines">Guidelines for the Codec Development Within the IETF</title>


<author initials="JM." surname="Valin" fullname="Jean-Marc Valin">
<organization>Mozilla</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street>650 Castro Street</street>
<city>Mountain View</city>
<region>CA</region>
<code>94041</code>
<country>USA</country>
</postal>
<email>jmvalin@jmvalin.ca</email>
</address>
</author>

<author initials="S." surname="Borilin" fullname="Slava Borilin">
<organization>SPIRIT DSP</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street></street>
<city></city>
<region></region>
<code></code>
<country></country>
</postal>
<email>borilin@spiritdsp.net</email>
</address>
</author>

<author initials="K." surname="Vos" fullname="Koen Vos">
<organization>Skype Technologies S.A.</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street>Stadsgarden 6</street>
<city>Stockholm</city>
<region></region>
<code>11645</code>
<country>Sweden</country>
</postal>
<email>koen.vos@skype.net</email>
</address>
</author>

<author initials="C." surname="Montgomery" fullname="Christopher Montgomery">
<organization>Xiph.Org Foundation</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street></street>
<city></city>
<region></region>
<code></code>
<country></country>
</postal>
<email>xiphmont@xiph.org</email>
</address>
</author>

<author initials="R." surname="Chen" fullname="Raymond (Juin-Hwey) Chen">
<organization>Broadcom Corporation</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street></street>
<city></city>
<region></region>
<code></code>
<country></country>
</postal>
<email>rchen@broadcom.com</email>
</address>
</author>


<date day="31" month="October" year="2011" />

<area>General</area>

<workgroup></workgroup>

<abstract>
<t>
This document provides general guidelines for work on developing and specifying
a codec within the IETF. These guidelines cover the
development process, evaluation, requirements conformance, and 
intellectual property issues. 
</t>
</abstract>
</front>

<middle>

<section anchor="introduction" title="Introduction">
<t>
This document describes a suggested process for work at the IETF on standardization
of a codec that is optimized for use in interactive Internet applications and that
can be widely implemented and easily distributed among application developers,
service operators, and end users.</t>

</section>

<section anchor="process" title="Development Process">
<t>The process outlined here is intended to make the 
work on a codec within the IETF transparent, predictable, and well organized,
in a way that is consistent with <xref target="PROCESS"/>.
Such work might involve development of 
a completely new codec, adaptation of an existing codec to meet 
the requirements of the working group, or 
integration between two or more existing codecs that results in an improved
codec combining the best aspects of each.  To enable such procedural
transparency, the contributor of an existing codec must be willing to cede 
change control to the IETF and should have sufficient knowledge of the codec to assist
in the work of adapting it or applying some of its technology to the development or improvemnet of other codecs. 
Furthermore, contributors need to be aware that any codec that results from
work within the IETF is likely to be different from any existing codec that
was contributed to the Internet Standards Process.
</t>

<t>
Work on audio codec development is expected to proceed as follows:

<list style="numbers">
<t>
IETF participants will identify the requirements to be met by
an Internet codec, in the form of an Internet-Draft.
</t>
<t>
Interested parties are encouraged to make contributions proposing existing or
new codecs, or elements thereof, to the codec WG as long as these 
contributions are within the scope of the WG.  Ideally, these
contributions should be in the form of Internet Drafts, although other forms of
contributions are also possible, as discussed in <xref target="PROCESS"/>.  
</t>

<t>Given the importance
of IPR to the activities of the working group, any IPR disclosures must
be made in a timely way. Contributors are required, as described in
<xref target="IPR"/>, to disclose any known IPR, both first and third party. Timely
disclosures are particularly important, since those disclosures may be
material to the decision process of the working group.
</t>

<t>
As contributions are received and discussed within the working group, the group should gain a clearer understanding of what is achievable within the design space.  As a result, the authors of the requirements document should iteratively clarify and improve their document to reflect the emerging working group consensus.  This is likely to involve collaboration with IETF working groups in other areas, such as collaboration with working groups in the Transport area to identify important aspects of packet transmission over the Internet and to understand the degree of rate adaptation desirable, and with working groups in the RAI area to ensure that information about and negotiation of the codec can be easily represented at the signaling layer.  In parallel with this work, interested parties should evaluate the contributions at a higher level to see which requirements might be met by each codec.
</t>
<t>
Once a sufficient number of proposals has been received, the interested
parties will identify the strengths, weaknesses, and innovative aspects of 
the contributed codecs.  This step will consider not only the codecs as a 
whole, but also key features of the individual algorithms (predictors, 
quantizers, transforms, etc.).
</t>

<t>
Interested parties are encouraged to collaborate together and combine
the best ideas from the various codec contributions into a consolidated
codec definition, representing the merging of some of the contributions.
Through this iterative process, the number of proposals will reduce and
consensus will generally form around one of them. At that point, the
working group should adopt that document as a working group item,
forming a baseline codec.
</t>

<t>
IETF participants should then attempt to iteratively add to or improve each component of 
the baseline codec reference implementation, where by "component" we mean 
individual algorithms such as 
predictors, transforms, quantizers, and entropy coders.  The participants 
should proceed by trying new designs, applying ideas from the contributed 
codecs, evaluating "proof of concept" ideas, and using their expertise in 
codec development to improve the baseline codec.  Any aspect of the 
baseline codec might be changed (even the fundamental principles of 
the codec) or the participants might start over entirely by scrapping the
baseline codec and designing a completely new one.  The overriding 
goal shall be to design a codec that will meet the requirements defined in
the requirements document.  Given the IETF's open standards process, any 
interested party will be able to contribute to this work, whether or not 
they submitted an Internet-Draft for one of the contributed codecs.  The 
codec itself should be normatively specified with code in an Internet-Draft.
</t>
<t>
In parallel with work on the codec reference implementation, developers and
other interested parties should perform 
evaluation of the codec as described under <xref target="evaluation"/>, 
IETF participants should define (within the PAYLOAD Working Group) the codec's 
payload format for use with the Real-time Transport Protocol 
<xref target="RTP"/>. Ideally, application developers should test the codec by implementing
it in code and deploying it in actual Internet applications. Unfortunately,
developers will frequently wait until RFC or until a stable bitstream is
guaranteed before deployment. As such, this is a nice-to-have and not a
requirement for this process. Lab implementations are certainly encouraged.
</t>

<t>
The group will produce a testing results document. The document will be a living document that captures testing done before the codec stabilized, after it has stabilized, and after the codec specification is issued as an RFC. The document serves the purpose of helping the group determine whether the codec meets the requirements. Any testing done after the codec RFC is issued helps implementors understand the final performance of the codec. The process of testing is described in <xref target="evaluation"/>.
</t>
</list>
</t>

</section>

<section anchor="evaluation" title="Evaluation, Testing, and Characterization">
<t>
Lab evaluation of the codec being developed should happen throughout the development process 
because it will help ensure that progress is being made toward fulfillment of the requirements.  There are many ways 
in which continuous evaluation can be performed.  For minor, uncontroversial 
changes to the codec it should usually be sufficient to use objective 
  measurements (e.g., PESQ <xref target="ITU-T P.862"/>, PEAQ <xref target="ITU-R BS.1387-1"/>, and segmental signal-to-noise ratio) validated by informal subjective evaluation.
For more complex changes (e.g., when psychoacoustic aspects are involved) or 
for controversial issues, internal testing should be performed.  An example of
internal testing would be to have individual participants rate the decoded samples 
  using one of the established testing methodologies, such as <xref target="ITU-R BS.1534"/> (MUSHRA).
</t>
<t>
Throughout the process, it will be important to make use of the Internet
community at large for real-world distributed testing.  This will enable many different
people with different equipment and use cases to test the codec and report any
problems they experience.  In the same way, third-party developers will 
be encouraged to integrate the codec into their software (with a warning about the bit-stream not 
being final) and provide feedback on its performance in real-world use cases.
</t>
<t>
Characterization of the final codec must be based on the reference 
implementation only (and not on any "private implementation").  This can be 
performed by independent testing labs or, if this is not possible, using 
the testing labs of the organizations that contribute to the Internet Standards
Process.  Packet loss robustness should 
be evaluated using actual loss patterns collected from use over the Internet, 
rather than theoretical models. The goals of the characterization phase are to:

<list style="symbols">
<t>ensure that the requirements have been fulfilled</t>
<t>guide the IESG in its evaluation of the resulting work</t>
<t>assist application developers in understanding whether the codec is suitable for
a particular application</t>
</list>
</t>

<t>
The exact methodology for the characterization phase can be determined the working group.
Because the IETF does not have testing resources of its own, it has to rely on the resources
of its participants. For this reason, even if the group agrees that a particular test
is important, if no one volunteers to do it, or if volunteers do not complete it in a timely
fashion, then that test should be discarded. This ensures that only
important tests be done, and in particular those tests which are important to
participants. 
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="normative" title="Specifying the Codec">

<t>Specifying a codec requires careful consideration around what is
required vs. what is left to the implementation. The following text
provides suggestions for consideration by the working group:

<list style="numbers">
<t>
Any audio codec specified by the codec Working Group must include source code for a normative software implementation,
documented in an Internet Draft destined for standards track RFC.
This implementation will be used to verify conformance of an implementation. Although
a text description of the algorithm should be provided, its use should be limited to
helping the reader in understanding the source code. Should the description contradict
the source code, the latter shall take precedence. For convenience, the source code may be
provided in compressed form, with base64 encoding.
</t>

<t>
Because of the size and complexity of most codecs, it is possible that even
after publishing the RFC, bugs will be found in the reference implementation,
or differences between the implementation and the text description.
An errata of the RFC should be maintained. Although a public software
repository containing the current reference implementation is desirable, the
normative implementation would still be the RFC.
</t>

<t>
It is the intention of the group to allow the greatest possible choice of freedom in
implementing the specification.  Accordingly, the number of binding RFC2119
keywords will be the minimum that still allows interoperable
implementations. In practice this 
generally means that only the decoder needs to be normative, so that the encoder 
can improve over time.  This also enables different trade-offs between quality and 
complexity.
</t>

<t>
To reduce the risk of bias towards certain CPU/DSP architectures, ideally 
the decoder specification should not require "bit-exact" conformance with the
reference implementation.  In that case, the output 
of a decoder implementation should only be "close enough" to the output of the 
reference decoder and a comparison tool should be provided along with the codec to
verify objectively that the output of a decoder is likely to be perceptually 
indistinguishable from that of the reference decoder.  An implementation
may still wish to produce an output that is bit-exact with the reference implementation
to simplify the testing procedure.
</t>

<t>
To ensure freedom of implementation, decoder-side only error concealment
does not need to be specified, although the reference implementation should
include the same packet loss concealment (PLC) algorithm as used in the testing phase. Is it up to 
the working group to decide whether minimum 
requirements on PLC quality will be required for compliance with the 
specification. Obviously, any information signaled in the bitstream intended 
to aid PLC needs to be specified.
</t>

<t>
An encoder implementation should not be required to make use of all the
"features" (tools) in the bit-stream definition.  However, the codec specification 
may require that an encoder implementation be able to generate any possible bit-rate.
Unless a particular "profile" is defined in the specification, the decoder must be 
able to decode all features of the bit-stream.  The decoder must also be able
to handle any combination of bits, even combinations that cannot be generated
by the reference encoder.  It is recommended that the decoder specification
shall define how the decoder should react to "impossible" packets (e.g. reject, consider as valid). 
However, an encoder must never generate such packets that do not conform to the 
bit-stream definition.
</t>

<t>
Compressed test vectors should be provided as a means to verify conformance 
with the decoder specification.  These test vectors should be designed to 
exercise as much of the decoder code as possible.
</t>

<t>
While the exact encoder will not be specified, it is recommended to specify
objective measurement targets for an encoder, below which use of a particular
encoder implementation is not recommended.  For example, one such specification
could be: "the use of an encoder whose PESQ MOS is better than 0.1 below the 
reference encoder in the following conditions is not recommended".
</t>
</list>
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="ipr" title="Intellectual Property">

<t>Producing an unencumbered codec is desirable for the following reasons:

<list style="symbols">
<t>It is the experience of a wide variety of application developers and service 
providers that encumbrances such as licensing and royalties make it difficult
to implement, deploy, and distribute multimedia applications for use by the Internet
community.</t>

<t>
It is beneficial to have low-cost options whenever possible, because
innovation - the hallmark of the Internet - is hampered when small
development teams cannot deploy an application because of usage-based
licensing fees and royalties.
</t>

<t>Many market segments are moving away from selling hard-coded hardware 
devices and toward freely distributing end-user software; this is true of
numerous large application providers and even telcos themselves.</t>

<t>Compatibility with the licensing of typical open source applications 
implies the need to avoid encumbrances, including 
even the requirement to obtain a license for implementation, deployment,
or use (even if the license does not require the payment of a fee).</t>

</list>
</t>

<t>
Therefore, a codec that can be widely implemented and easily distributed among
application developers, service operators, and end users is preferred.
Many existing codecs that might fulfill some or most of the technical
attributes listed above are encumbered in various ways.  For example,
patent holders might require that those wishing to implement the codec
in software, deploy the codec in a service, or distribute the codec in
software or hardware need to request a license, enter into a business
agreement, pay licensing fees or royalties, or adhere to
other special conditions or restrictions.

Because such encumbrances have made it difficult to widely implement and
easily distribute high-quality codecs across the entire Internet
community, the working group prefers unencumbered technologies in a way
that is consistent with BCP 78 and BCP 79.  In particular, the working
group shall heed the preference stated in BCP 79: "In general, IETF
working groups prefer technologies with no known IPR claims or, for
technologies with claims against them, an offer of royalty-free
licensing."  Although this preference cannot guarantee that the working
group will produce an unencumbered codec, the working group shall follow
BCP 79, and adhere to the spirit of BCP 79. The working group cannot
explicitly rule out the possibility of adopting encumbered technologies;
however, the working group will try to avoid encumbered technologies
that require royalties or other encumbrances that would prevent such
technologies from being easy to redistribute and use.
</t>

<t>
When considering license terms for technologies with IPR claims agains them, 
some members of the working group have expressed their preference for license terms which:
<list style='symbols'>

<t>are available to all, worldwide, whether or not they are working group
participants</t>
<t>extend to all essential claims owned or controlled by the licensor</t>
<t>do not require payment of royalties, fees or other consideration</t>

<t>do not require licensees to adhere to restrictions on usage
(though, licenses which apply only to implementation of the standard are
acceptable)</t>

<t>do not otherwise impede the ability of the codec to be implemented
in open-source software projects</t>
</list>
</t>


<t>The following guidelines will help to maximize the odds that the
codec will be unencumbered:</t>

<t>
  <list style='numbers'>
    <t>In accordance with BCP 79 <xref target="IPR"/>, contributed codecs 
	   should preferably use technologies with no known IPR claims or 
	   technologies with an offer of royalty-free licensing.</t>
    <t>As described in BCP 79, the working group should use technologies that 
	are perceived by the participants to be safer with regard to IPR issues.</t>
    <t>Contributors must disclose IPR as specified in BCP 79.</t>
    <t>In cases where no royalty-free license can be obtained regarding a patent, BCP 79 suggests that the working group consider alternative algorithms or methods, even if they result in lower quality, higher complexity, or otherwise less desirable characteristics.</t>
    <t>In accordance with BCP 78 <xref target="TRUST"/>, the source code for the reference implementation must be made available under a BSD-style license (or whatever license is defined as acceptable by the IETF Trust when the Internet-Draft defining the reference implementation is published).</t>
  </list>
</t>

<t>
Many IPR licenses specify that a license is granted only for
technologies which are adopted by the IETF as a standard. While
reasonable, this has the unintended side-effect of discouraging
implementation prior to RFC status. Real-world implementation is
beneficial for evaluation of the codec. As such, entities making IPR
license statements are encouraged to use wording which permits early
implementation and deployment.
</t>

<t>
IETF participants should be aware that, given the way patents work in most 
countries, the resulting codec can never be guaranteed to be free of patent 
claims because some patents may not be known to the contributors, some patent 
applications may not be disclosed at the time the codec is developed, and 
only courts of law can determine the validity and breadth of patent claims.  
However, these observations are no different within the Internet Standards 
Process than they are for standardization of codecs within other SDOs (or 
development of codecs outside the context of any SDO), and furthermore are 
no different for codecs than for other technologies worked on within the 
IETF.  In all these cases, the best approach is to minimize the risk of 
unknowingly incurring encumbrance on existing patents.  Despite these 
precautions, participants need to understand that, practically speaking, it 
is nearly impossible to <spanx style="emph">guarantee</spanx> that implementers will not incur encumbrance 
on existing patents.
</t>

</section>

<section anchor="SDOs" title="Relationship with Other SDOs">
<t>
It is understood that other SDOs are also involved in the codec development and 
standardization, including but not necessarily limited to:
<list style="symbols">
   <t>The Telecommunication Standardization Sector (ITU-T) of the International Telecommunication Union (ITU), in particular Study Group 16</t>
   <t>The Moving Picture Experts Group (MPEG) of the International Organization
for Standardization and International Electrotechnical Commission (ISO/IEC)</t>
   <t>The European Telecommunications Standards Institute (ETSI)</t>
   <t>The 3rd Generation Partnership Project (3GPP)</t>
   <t>The 3rd Generation Partnership Project 2 (3GPP2)</t>
</list>
</t>

<t>It is important to ensure that such work does not constitute uncoordinated protocol development, of the kind described in <xref target='UNCOORD'/> in the following principle:</t>

  <t><list style='empty'><t>[T]he IAB considers an essential principle of the protocol development process that only one SDO maintains design authority for a given protocol, with that SDO having ultimate authority over the allocation of protocol parameter code-points; defining the intended semantics, interpretation, and actions associated with those code-points.</t></list></t>

<t>The work envisioned by this guidelines document is not uncoordinated in
the sense described in the foregoing quote, since the intention of this
process is that two possible outcomes might occur: </t>
<t>
  <list style='numbers'>
    <t>The IETF adopts an existing audio codec, and specifies that it is the
"anointed" IETF Internet codec. In such a case, codec ownership lies
entirely with the SDO which produced the codec, and not with the IETF, OR</t>
    <t>The IETF produces a new codec. Even if this codec uses concepts,
algorithms, codepoints, or even source code from a codec produced by
another SDO, the IETF codec is a specification unto itself and under
complete control of the IETF. Any changes or enhancements made by the original
SDO to the codecs whose components the IETF used are not applicable to
the IETF codec. Such changes would be incorporated as a consequence of a
revision or extension of the IETF RFC.</t>

  </list>
</t>

<t>Although there is already sufficient codec expertise available among IETF participants to complete the envisioned work, additional contributions are welcome within the framework of the Internet Standards Process, in the following ways:</t>

<t>
  <list style="symbols">
    <t>Individuals who are technical contributors to codec work within other SDOs can participate directly in codec work within the IETF.</t>
    <t>Other SDOs can contribute their expertise (e.g., codec characterization and evaluation techniques) and thus facilitate the testing of a codec produced by the IETF.</t>
    <t>Any SDO can provide input to IETF work through liaison statements.</t>
  </list>
</t>

<t>However, it is important to note that final responsibility for the development process and the resulting codec will remain with the IETF as governed by BCP 9 <xref target="PROCESS"/>.</t>

<t>Finally, there is precedent for the contribution of codecs developed elsewhere to the ITU-T (e.g., AMR Wideband was standardized originally within 3GPP).  This is a model to explore as the IETF coordinates further with the ITU-T in accordance with the collaboration guidelines defined in <xref target='COLLAB'/>.</t>

</section>

<section anchor="security" title="Security Considerations">

<t>
The procedural guidelines for codec development do not have security
considerations.  However, the resulting codec needs to take appropriate
security considerations into account, as outlined in 
<xref target="SECGUIDE"/> and in the security considerations of 
<xref target="codec-requirements"/>. More specifically, the resulting codec
must avoid being subject to denial of service <xref target="DOS"/> and
buffer overflows, and should take into consideration the impact of VBR
<xref target="srtp-vbr"/>.
</t>

</section> 


<section title="IANA Considerations ">
<t>
This document has no actions for IANA.
</t>
</section>


<section anchor="Acknowledgments" title="Acknowledgments">
<t>
We would like to thank all the other people who contributed directly or indirectly
to this document, including Jason Fischl, Gregory Maxwell, Alan Duric, 
Jonathan Christensen, Julian Spittka, Michael Knappe, Timothy B. Terriberry, Christian Hoene, Stephan Wenger and Henry Sinnreich. 
We also like to thank Cullen Jennings and Gregory Lebovitz for their advice. Special thanks
to Peter Saint-Andre, who originally co-authored this document.
</t>
</section> 

</middle>

<back>

<references title="Normative References">

<reference anchor='IPR'>
<front>
<title>Intellectual Property Rights in IETF Technology</title>
<author initials='S.' surname='Bradner' fullname='S. Bradner'>
<organization /></author>
<date year='2005' month='March' />
<abstract>
<t>The IETF policies about Intellectual Property Rights (IPR), such as patent rights, relative to technologies developed in the IETF are designed to ensure that IETF working groups and participants have as much information about any IPR constraints on a technical proposal as possible.  The policies are also intended to benefit the Internet community and the public at large, while respecting the legitimate rights of IPR holders.  This memo details the IETF policies concerning IPR related to technology worked on within the IETF.  It also describes the objectives that the policies are designed to meet.  This memo updates RFC 2026 and, with RFC 3978, replaces Section 10 of RFC 2026.  This memo also updates paragraph 4 of Section 3.2 of RFC 2028, for all purposes, including reference [2] in RFC 2418.  This document specifies an Internet Best Current Practices for the Internet Community, and requests discussion and suggestions for improvements.</t></abstract></front>
<seriesInfo name='BCP' value='79' />
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='3979' />
<format type='TXT' octets='41366' target='ftp://ftp.isi.edu/in-notes/rfc3979.txt' />
</reference>

<reference anchor='PROCESS'>
<front>
<title abbrev='Internet Standards Process'>The Internet Standards Process -- Revision 3</title>
<author initials='S.' surname='Bradner' fullname='Scott O. Bradner'>
<organization>Harvard University</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street>1350 Mass. Ave.</street>
<city>Cambridge</city>
<region>MA</region>
<code>02138</code>
<country>US</country></postal>
<phone>+1 617 495 3864</phone>
<email>sob@harvard.edu</email></address></author>
<date year='1996' month='October' />
<abstract>
<t>This memo documents the process used by the Internet community for the standardization of protocols and procedures.  It defines the stages in the standardization process, the requirements for moving a document between stages and the types of documents used during this process.  It also addresses the intellectual property rights and copyright issues associated with the standards process.</t></abstract></front>
<seriesInfo name='BCP' value='9' />
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='2026' />
<format type='TXT' octets='86731' target='ftp://ftp.isi.edu/in-notes/rfc2026.txt' />
</reference>

<reference anchor='TRUST'>
<front>
<title>Rights Contributors Provide to the IETF Trust</title>
<author initials='S.' surname='Bradner' fullname='S. Bradner'>
<organization /></author>
<author initials='J.' surname='Contreras' fullname='J. Contreras'>
<organization /></author>
<date year='2008' month='November' />
<abstract>
<t>The IETF policies about rights in Contributions to the IETF are designed to ensure that such Contributions can be made available to the IETF and Internet communities while permitting the authors to retain as many rights as possible.  This memo details the IETF policies on rights in Contributions to the IETF.  It also describes the objectives that the policies are designed to meet.  This memo obsoletes RFCs 3978 and 4748 and, with BCP 79 and RFC 5377, replaces Section 10 of RFC 2026.  This document specifies an Internet Best Current Practices for the Internet Community, and requests discussion and suggestions for improvements.</t></abstract></front>
<seriesInfo name='BCP' value='78' />
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='5378' />
<format type='TXT' octets='37980' target='ftp://ftp.isi.edu/in-notes/rfc5378.txt' />
</reference>

</references> 

<references title="Informative References">

<reference anchor='COLLAB'>
<front>
<title>Internet Engineering Task Force and International Telecommunication Union - Telecommunications Standardization Sector Collaboration Guidelines</title>
<author initials='G.' surname='Fishman' fullname='G. Fishman'>
<organization /></author>
<author initials='S.' surname='Bradner' fullname='S. Bradner'>
<organization /></author>
<date year='2002' month='August' /></front>
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='3356' />
<format type='TXT' octets='27149' target='ftp://ftp.isi.edu/in-notes/rfc3356.txt' />
</reference>

<reference anchor='DOS'>
<front>
<title>Internet Denial-of-Service Considerations</title>
<author initials='M.' surname='Handley' fullname='M. Handley'>
<organization /></author>
<author initials='E.' surname='Rescorla' fullname='E. Rescorla'>
<organization /></author>
<author>
<organization>IAB</organization></author>
<date year='2006' month='December' />
<abstract>
<t>This document provides an overview of possible avenues for denial-of-service (DoS) attack on Internet systems.  The aim is to encourage protocol designers and network engineers towards designs that are more robust.  We discuss partial solutions that reduce the effectiveness of attacks, and how some solutions might inadvertently open up alternative vulnerabilities.  This memo provides information for the Internet community.</t></abstract></front>
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='4732' />
<format type='TXT' octets='91844' target='ftp://ftp.isi.edu/in-notes/rfc4732.txt' />
</reference>


<reference anchor='RTP'>
<front>
<title>RTP: A Transport Protocol for Real-Time Applications</title>
<author initials='H.' surname='Schulzrinne' fullname='H. Schulzrinne'>
<organization /></author>
<author initials='S.' surname='Casner' fullname='S. Casner'>
<organization /></author>
<author initials='R.' surname='Frederick' fullname='R. Frederick'>
<organization /></author>
<author initials='V.' surname='Jacobson' fullname='V. Jacobson'>
<organization /></author>
<date year='2003' month='July' />
<abstract>
<t>This memorandum describes RTP, the real-time transport protocol.  RTP provides end-to-end network transport functions suitable for applications transmitting real-time data, such as audio, video or simulation data, over multicast or unicast network services.  RTP does not address resource reservation and does not guarantee quality-of- service for real-time services.  The data transport is augmented by a control protocol (RTCP) to allow monitoring of the data delivery in a manner scalable to large multicast networks, and to provide minimal control and identification functionality.  RTP and RTCP are designed to be independent of the underlying transport and network layers.  The protocol supports the use of RTP-level translators and mixers.  Most of the text in this memorandum is identical to RFC 1889 which it obsoletes.  There are no changes in the packet formats on the wire, only changes to the rules and algorithms governing how the protocol is used.  The biggest change is an enhancement to the scalable timer algorithm for calculating when to send RTCP packets in order to minimize transmission in excess of the intended rate when many participants join a session simultaneously. [STANDARDS TRACK]</t></abstract></front>
<seriesInfo name='STD' value='64' />
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='3550' />
<format type='TXT' octets='259985' target='ftp://ftp.isi.edu/in-notes/rfc3550.txt' />
<format type='PS' octets='630740' target='ftp://ftp.isi.edu/in-notes/rfc3550.ps' />
<format type='PDF' octets='504117' target='ftp://ftp.isi.edu/in-notes/rfc3550.pdf' />
</reference>


<reference anchor='SECGUIDE'>
<front>
<title>Guidelines for Writing RFC Text on Security Considerations</title>
<author initials='E.' surname='Rescorla' fullname='E. Rescorla'>
<organization /></author>
<author initials='B.' surname='Korver' fullname='B. Korver'>
<organization /></author>
<date year='2003' month='July' />
<abstract>
<t>All RFCs are required to have a Security Considerations section.  Historically, such sections have been relatively weak.  This document provides guidelines to RFC authors on how to write a good Security Considerations section.  This document specifies an Internet Best Current Practices for the Internet Community, and requests discussion and suggestions for improvements.</t></abstract></front>

<seriesInfo name='BCP' value='72' />
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='3552' />
<format type='TXT' octets='110393' target='ftp://ftp.isi.edu/in-notes/rfc3552.txt' />
</reference>

<reference anchor='codec-requirements'>
<front>
<title>Requirements for an Internet Audio Codec</title>
<author initials='JM.' surname='Valin' fullname='J.M. Valin'>
<organization /></author>
<author initials='K.' surname='Vos' fullname='K. Vos'>
<organization /></author>
<date year='2011' month='August' />
<abstract>
<t>This document provides specific requirements for an Internet audio
   codec.  These requirements address quality, sampling rate, bit-rate,
   and packet-loss robustness, as well as other desirable properties.
   </t></abstract></front>
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='6366' />
</reference>

<reference anchor='srtp-vbr'>
<front>
<title>Guidelines for the use of Variable Bit Rate Audio with Secure RTP</title>
<author initials='C.' surname='Perkins' fullname='C. Perkins'>
    <organization />
</author>
<author initials='JM.' surname='Valin' fullname='JM. Valin'>
    <organization />
</author>
<date month='July' year='2011' />
<abstract><t>This memo discusses potential security issues that arise when using
   variable bit rate audio with the secure RTP profile.  Guidelines to
   mitigate these issues are suggested.</t></abstract>
</front>
<seriesInfo name='Internet-Draft' value='draft-ietf-avtcore-srtp-vbr' />
</reference>

<reference anchor='UNCOORD'>
<front>
<title>Uncoordinated Protocol Development Considered Harmful</title>
<author initials='S' surname='Bryant' fullname='Stewart Bryant'>
    <organization />
</author>
<author initials='M' surname='Morrow' fullname='Monique Morrow'>
    <organization />
</author>
<date month='November' year='2009' />
<abstract><t>This document identifies problems that may result from the absence of formal coordination and joint development on protocols of mutual interest between standards development organizations.  Some of these problems may cause significant harm to the Internet.  The document suggests that a robust procedure is required prevent this from occurring in the future.  The IAB has selected a number of case studies, such as T-MPLS, as recent examples to describe hazard to the Internet architecture as a result of uncoordinated adaptation of a protocol.  This experience has resulted in a considerable improvement in the relationship between the IETF and the ITU-T.  In particular, this was achieved via the establishment of the "Joint working team on MPLS-TP" .  In addition, the leadership of the two organisations agreed to improve inter-organizational working practices so as to avoid conflict in the future between ITU-T Recommendations and IETF RFCs.  Whilst we use ITU-T - IETF interactions in these case studies, the scope of the document extends to all SDO that have an overlapping protocol interest with the IETF.</t></abstract>
</front>
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='5704' />
<format type='TXT'
        target='ftp://ftp.isi.edu/in-notes/rfc5704.txt' />
</reference>


<reference anchor='ITU-R BS.1534'>
<front>
<title>Method for the subjective assessment of intermediate quality levels of coding systems</title>
<author/>
<date year='2003' month='January' />
<abstract>
<t>This recommendation describes the MUltiple Stimuli with Hidden Reference and Anchors (MUSHRA) methodology</t></abstract></front>
<seriesInfo name='ITU-R Recommendation' value='BS.1534' />
</reference>

<reference anchor='ITU-T P.862'>
<front>
<title>Perceptual evaluation of speech quality (PESQ): An objective method for end-to-end speech quality assessment of narrow-band telephone networks and speech codecs</title>
<author/>
<date year='2007' month='October' />
</front>
<seriesInfo name='ITU-T Recommendation' value='P.862' />
</reference>


<reference anchor='ITU-R BS.1387-1'>
<front>
<title>Method for objective measurements of perceived audio quality</title>
<author/>
<date year='2001' month='November' />
</front>
<seriesInfo name='ITU-R Recommendation' value='BS.1387-1' />
</reference>

</references> 

</back>

</rfc>
