<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="no"?>
<?rfc comments="no"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<rfc category="info" docName="draft-weingarten-mpls-smp-requirements-01.txt"
     ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="MPLS SMP Req">Requirements for MPLS Shared Mesh Protection</title>

    <author fullname="Yaacov Weingarten" initials="Y." surname="Weingarten">
      <organization></organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>34 Hagefen St. </street>

          <city>Karnei Shomron</city>

          <region />

          <code>4485500</code>

          <country>Israel</country>
        </postal>

        <phone></phone>
         <email>wyaacov@gmail.com</email>

      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Sam Aldrin" initials="S." surname="Aldrin">
      <organization>Huawei Technologies</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>2330 Central Express Way</street>
		  
		  <city>Santa Clara</city>

          <region>CA</region>

          <code>95951</code>

          <country>United States</country>
        </postal>

        <email>aldrin.ietf@gmail.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Ping Pan" initials="P." surname="Pan">
      <organization>Infinera</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>

          <city></city>

          <region></region>

          <code></code>

          <country></country>
        </postal>

        <email>ppan@infinera.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

<!-- <author fullname="Daniel King" initials="D." surname="King"> 
      <organization>Old Dog Consulting</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>

          <city></city>

          <region></region>

          <code></code>

          <country>United Kingdom</country>
        </postal>

        <email>daniel@olddog.co.uk</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Diego Caviglia" initials="D." surname="Caviglia">
      <organization>Ericsson</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Via A. Negrone 1/A</street>

          <city>Genova</city>

          <region>Sestri Ponente</region>

          <code></code>

          <country>Italy</country>
        </postal>

        <email>diego.caviglia@ericsson.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
-->

    <date year="2012" />

    <abstract>
      <t>This document presents the basic network objectives for the behavior of 
	  shared mesh protection (SMP) not based on control-plane support.  This is an 
	  expansion of the basic requirements presented in the MPLS Transport Profile 
	  Requirements (RFC5654) and MPLS Transport Profile Survivability Framework 
	  (RFC6372) documents.  This document should be used as a basis for the 
	  definition of the mechanism that would be used to implement SMP for MPLS-TP 
	  data paths, in networks that do not employ a control plane for their operation.</t>

<!--      <t>This document is a product of a joint Internet Engineering Task Force
      (IETF) / International Telecommunications Union Telecommunications
      Standardization Sector (ITU-T) effort to include an MPLS Transport
      Profile within the IETF MPLS and PWE3 architectures to support the
      capabilities and functionalities of a packet transport network as
      defined by the ITU-T.</t> -->
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>MPLS transport networks can be characterized as being a network of 
	  connections between nodes within a mesh of nodes and the links between them.  
	  The connections, that may be between neighboring nodes, i.e. spanning a 
	  single physical link, or spanning a path of several nodes, constitute the 
	  Label Switched Paths (LSP) that transport packets between the endpoints
	  of these paths.  The survivability of these connections, as described in 
	  <xref target="RFC6372" />, is a critical aspect for various service 
	  providers that are bound by Service Level Agreements (SLA) with their 
	  customers.</t>
	  
	  <t>MPLS provides control-plane tools to support various survivability
	  schemes (Editor's note - add references).  In addition, recent efforts in
	  the IETF have started providing for data-plane tools to address aspects of
	  data protection.  In particular, <xref target="RFC6378" /> defines a set of
	  triggers and coordination protocol for 1:1 and 1+1 linear protection of p2p
	  paths.</t>
	  
	  <t>When considering a full-mesh network and the protection of different
	  paths that criss-cross the mesh, it is possible to conserve the amount of
	  protection resources needed to protect the different data paths.  As pointed
	  out in <xref target="RFC6372" /> and <xref target="RFC4428" />, applying 1+1
	  linear protection, requires that resources are allocated and used by both 
	  the working and protection paths.  Applying 1:1 protection requires that all
	  of the resources are allocated, but allows the resources of the protection
	  path to be utilized for pre-emptible extra traffic.  Extending this to 1:n
	  or m:n protection allows the resources of the protection path to be shared 
	  in the protection of several working paths.  However, there is a limitation
	  in 1:n protection architectures - that all of the n+1 paths must have 
	  identical endpoints.</t>
	  
	  <t>As described in <xref target="RFC6372" /> Shared Mesh Protection (SMP) 
	  supports a form of sharing protection resources, while providing protection 
	  for multiple data paths that may not have common endpoints and do not share 
	  common points of failure.  It should be noted that some protection resources 
	  may not be shared by multiple protection paths, while other resources are 
	  shared.  The basic configuration for data paths that employ SMP is shown in 
	  <xref target="Fig1" />.  In this figure, we show two working paths [ABCDE] and 
	  [VWXYZ] that are protected employing 1:1 linear protection by protection paths 
	  [APQRE] and [VPQRZ] respectively.  The segment [PQR] and all of its protection 
	  resources are shared by both of the protection paths.</t>
	  
        <figure anchor="Fig1" title="Basic SMP architecture">
          <artwork><![CDATA[

             A----B----C----D----E
              \                 /
               \               /
                \             /
                 P-----Q-----R
                /             \
               /               \
              /                 \
             V----W----X----Y----Z

		  ]]></artwork>
        </figure>
	  
	  <section title="Protection or Restoration">
	    <t><xref target="RFC6372" />, based upon the definitions in <xref 
		target="RFC4427" />, differentiates between &quot;protection&quot; and 
		&quot;restoration&quot; dependent upon the dynamism of the resource
		allocation.  In SMP, the resources of the protection paths are reserved
		at the time of path creation.  However, the full allocation of the resources,
		at least for the shared segments, will only be finalized when the protection 
		path is actually activated.  Therefore, for the purists	&ndash; regarding 
		the terminology &ndash; SMP lies somewhere between protection and restoration.</t>
		</section>
		
	  <section title="Scope of document">
	    <t><xref target="RFC5654" /> establishes that MPLS-TP should support 
		shared protection (Requirement 68) and that MPLS-TP must support sharing of 
		protection resources (Requirement 69).This document presents the network 
		objectives and a framework for applying SMP within an MPLS network, without 
		the use of control-plane protocols.  There are existing control-plane 
		solutions for SMP within MPLS, however we address those networks that for 
		some reason, e.g. service provider preferences or limitations, do not employ 
		a full control plane operation, or require service restoration faster than 
		achievable with control plane mechanisms.</t>
		
		<t>The network objectives will also address possible additional restrictions
		of the behavior of SMP in statically configured operator networks. Definition 
		of logic and specific protocol messaging is out of scope of this document.</t>
		
	    <section title="Relationship to MPLS-TP">
	      <t>While some of the restrictions presented by this framework originate 
		  from the considerations of transport networks, there is no real constraint
		  of the information presented here being applied to general MPLS networks,
		  and not necessarily as part of the Transport Profile of MPLS.</t>
		  </section>
		</section>

        <section title="Contributing Authors">
          <t>David Allan, Gregory Mirsky, Daniel King, Jeong-Dong Ryoo, Taesik Cheung</t>
          </section>
		</section>

      <section title="Terminology and Notation">
        <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
        "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
        document are to be interpreted as described in <xref target="RFC2119" />.</t>
	  
        <t>The terminology used in this document is based on the terminology
        defined in the MPLS-TP Survivability Framework document <xref target=
		"RFC6372"/> which in-turn is based on <xref target="RFC4427" />.</t>
		
        <section title="Acronyms">
          <texttable align="left" style="none">
          <preamble>This draft uses the following acronyms:</preamble>

          <ttcol align="left"></ttcol>

          <ttcol align="left"></ttcol>

          <c>LSP</c>

          <c>Label Switched Path</c>

          <c>SLA</c>

          <c>Service Level Agreement</c>

          <c>SMP</c>

          <c>Shared Mesh Protection</c>

          <c>SRLG</c>

          <c>Shared Risk Link Group</c>
          </texttable>
		</section>
      </section>

	<section title="SMP Architecture">
      <t><xref target="Fig1" /> shows a very basic configuration of working and 
	  protection paths that may employ SMP.  We may consider a slightly more involved
	  configuration, such as the one in <xref target="Fig2" /> in order to identify
	  certain basic characteristics of an SMP mesh network.</t>

        <figure anchor="Fig2" title="Larger sample SMP architecture">
          <artwork><![CDATA[

             A----B----C----D----E---N
              \            /    /    \
               \          M ---/--    \
                \             /   \    \
                 P-----Q-----R-----S----T
                /|      \     \     \    \
               / F---G---H    J--K---L    \
              /                            \
             V------W-------X-------Y-------Z

		  ]]></artwork>
        </figure>
	
	  <t>Consider the network presented in <xref target="Fig2" />.  There are
	  five working paths &ndash; [ABCDE], [MDEN], [FGH], [JKL], and [VWXYZ].  
	  Each of these has a corresponding protection path &ndash; [APQRE] (p1), 
	  [MSTN] (p2), [FPQH] (p3), [JRSL] (p4), and [VPQRSTZ] (p5).  The following 
	  segments are shared by two or more of the protection paths &ndash; [PQ] 
	  is shared by p1, p3, and p5, [QR] is shared by p1 and p5, [RS] is shared 
	  by p4 and p5, and [ST] is shared by p2 and p5.  In addition, we assume that 
	  the available protection resources for these shared segments are not 
	  sufficient to support the complete traffic capacity of the respective working 
	  paths that may use the protection paths.  We can further observe that
	  the main feature of the network that defines it as an SMP network is the 
	  fact that the segment [PQRST] is the union of all the shared segments of 
	  other protection paths (p1, p2, p3 and p4) while being a whole shared 
	  segment of one of the protection paths (p5).</t>
	  
	  <t>In other words, the main feature of an SMP &quot;protection domain&quot; 
	  will be the segment that is the union of all the shared segments of the
	  protection paths.  We can further identify &quot;protection group&quot; as
	  the different protection paths that share a common segment.  For example,
	  referring to <xref target="Fig2" />, we have the following protection groups
	  &ndash; {p1, p3, p5} for [PQ], {p1, p5} for [QR], {p4, p5} for [RS], {p2, p5}
	  for [ST].</t>
	  
	  <t>Typical deployment of SMP would require various network planning activities.
	  These would include:
	    <list style="symbols">
		<t>Identification of key services that require protection, and determining
		the number of working and protection paths.</t>

		<t>Reviewing network topology to determine which working or protection paths
		are required to be disjointed from each other, and exclude specified
		resources such as links, nodes, or shared risk link groups (SRLGs).</t>
		
		<t>Determining the size (bandwidth) of the shared resource</t>
		</list></t>
	  
	  <section title="Coordination of resources">
	    <t>When a protection switch is triggered by any fault condition or operator
		command, the SMP network must perform two operations almost simultaneously 
		&ndash; switch data traffic over to a protection path and verify that the
		shared resources are allocated for this protection path.  The allocation 
		of resources is dependent upon their availability at each of the shared 
		segments.</t>

		<t>When the reserved resources of the shared segments are allocated 
		for a particular protection path, there may not be sufficient resources 
		available for an additional protection path.  This then implies that if an
		additional working path triggers a protection switch, the allocation of the
		resources may fail and MUST be treated as described below in <xref target=
		"multiSF" />.  In order to optimize the operation of the allocation and
		preparing for cases of multiple working path failures, the allocation of
		the shared resources SHALL be coordinated between the different working
		paths in the SMP network.</t>
	    </section>
	  </section>
	  
	  <section title="SMP Network Objectives">
	    <section title="Configuration and resource reservation">
	    <t>SMP is a survivability mechanism that is based on pre-configuration of 
		the network working paths and the corresponding protection paths.  This 
		configuration may be based on either a control protocol or static configuration
		by the management system.  The protection relationship between the working
		and protection paths SHOULD be configured and the shared segments of the 
		protection path must be identified prior to use of the protection paths.</t>
		
		<t>As opposed to the case of simple linear protection, where the relationship
		between the working and protection paths is defined, the resources for the
		protection path may be fully committed for the unshared portions of the 
		protection path.  The protection path in the case of SMP consists of segments 
		that are dedicated to the protection of the related working path and also 
		segments that are shared with other protection paths.  On the shared segments, 
		the protection resources may be	reserved but would not be allocated until 
		requested as part of a protection switch.</t>
		
		<section title="Checking resource availability">
		  <t>When a working path identifies a protection switching trigger it MUST 
		  verify that the necessary protection resources are available on the protection
		  path.  The resources may not be available because they have been allocated 
		  to the protection of a higher priority working path, as described above.</t>
		  </section>
		</section>
		
		<section title="Control plane or data plane">
		  <t>As stated in both <xref target="RFC6372" /> and <xref target="RFC4428" />,
		  full control of SMP, including both configuration and the coordination of
		  the protection switching is potentially very complex.  Therefore, it is 
		  suggested that this be carried out under the control of a dynamic control
		  plane similar to GMPLS <xref target="RFC3945" />.  In fact, implementations
		  for SMP with GMPLS exist and the general principles of its operation are 
		  well known, if not fully documented.</t>
		  
		  <t>There are, however, operators, in particular in the transport sector,
		  that do not operate their MPLS networks under the control of a control
		  plane and require the ability of performing SMP protection while
		  utilizing data-plane tools for coordination of the protection switching.
		  This requirement is emphasized in different areas of <xref target=
		  "RFC5654" /> for MPLS-TP environments.  Therefore, it is imperative that
		  it be possible to perform all of the coordination needed for SMP via data
		  plane operations.</t>
		  </section>
		  
		<section anchor="multiSF" title="Multiple triggers">
		  <t>If more than one working path is triggering a protection switch there
		  are different possible actions that the SMP network may apply.  The 
		  basic MPLS action MAY allow all of the protection paths to share
		  the resources of the shared segments, for those networks that support
		  multiplexing packets over the shared segments.  For those networks,
		  in particular for networks that support the requirements in <xref
		  target="RFC5654" /> [and in particular support for requirement 58], that 
		  require the exclusive use of the protection resources, the following 
		  behavior SHOULD be supported:</t>
		  
		  <t><list style="symbols">
		    <t>Relative priority MAY be assigned to each of the working paths
			that share a common protection segment</t>
			<t>Resources of the shared segments SHALL be allocated to the protection
			path according to the highest priority amongst those requesting use of the 
			resources.</t>
			<t>If multiple protection paths of equal priority are requesting allocation
			of the shared resources, the resources SHOULD be allocated on a first
			come first served basis.  Tie-breaking rules SHALL be defined by the 
			SMP process.</t>
			<t>If the protection resources are currently in use by a protection 
			path, whose working path has a lower priority, resources SHALL be allocated 
			to the path with higher priority. Traffic with lower priority MAY use 
			available resources or MAY be interrupted.</t>
			<t>When trigerred, protection switching action SHOULD be initiated 
			immediately to minimize service interruption time.  If the protection
			resources are already allocated to a higher priority protection path
			the protection switching MAY not be performed.</t>
			<t>Once a protection path occupies the resource of a shared segments 
			successfully, the traffic on that protection path SHALL NOT be interrupted 
			by any protection traffic whose priority is equal or lower than the 
			protecting path currently in-use.</t>
			<t>During preemption, shared segment resources MAY be used by both 
			existing traffic (that is being preempted) and higher priority traffic 
			for a short period.</t>
			<t>During preemption, if there is an oversubscription of resources 
			protected traffic SHOULD be treated as defined in <xref target="RFC5712" /> 
			or <xref target="RFC3209" /></t>
		    </list></t>
		  </section>

		<section title="Notification">
		  <t>When a working path identifies a trigger for implementing a switchover to 
		  the protection path, it SHOULD attempt to switchover the traffic to the 
		  protection path and requesting the allocation of the resources for this 
		  protected traffic.  If the necessary shared resources are in use by a 
		  protection path of higher priority or are unavailable to be allocated to 
		  the protection path, a notification SHALL be sent to both endpoints of 
		  the requesting working path and the switchover MAY not be completed.</t>
		  
		  <t>Similarly, if preemption is supported and as a result of the allocation
		  of resources to a different working path that triggered a protection switch, 
		  the resources currently allocated for a particular working path are being 
		  preempted then a notification SHALL be sent to the endpoints of the working 
		  path whose traffic is being preempted indicating that the resources are 
		  being preempted.</t>
		  </section>
		  
		<section title="Protection switching time">
		  <t>Protection switching time refers to the transfer time (Tt) defined in 
		  <xref target="G.808.1" /> and recovery switching time defined in <xref 
		  target="RFC4427" />, and is defined as the interval after a switching 
		  trigger is identified until the traffic begins to be transmitted on the 
		  protection path.  This time is exclusive of the time needed to initiate 
		  the protection switching process after a failure occurred, and the time 
		  needed to complete preemption of existing traffic on the shared segments
		  as described in <xref target="multiSF" />.  The former, which is known 
		  as detection and correlation time in <xref target="RFC4427" /> is related 
		  to the OAM or management process, but the latter is related to the SMP 
		  process. Support for a protection switching time of 50ms is dependent 
		  upon the initial switchover to the protection path, but the preemption 
		  time SHOULD also be taken into account to minimize total service 
		  interruption time.</t>
		  </section>

		<section title="Timers">
		    <t>In order to prevent multiple switching actions for a single switching
			trigger, SMP SHOULD be controlled a hold-off timer that would allow 
			lower level mechanisms to complete their switching actions before 
			invoking SMP protection actions.</t>
			
			<t>In addition, to prevent an unstable recovering working path from 
			invoking intermittent switching operation, SMP SHOULD employ a 
			wait-to-restore timer during any reversion switching.</t>
		  </section>
		</section>

    <section anchor="Manage" title="Managability Considerations">
      <t>To be added in future version.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>To be added in future version.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>This document makes no request of IANA.</t>

      <t>Note to RFC Editor: this section may be removed on publication as an
      RFC.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>TBD</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
 
      <!-- Begin inclusion reference.RFC.2119.xml. -->

      <reference anchor="RFC2119">
        <front>
          <title abbrev="KeyW">Key words for use in RFCs to Indicate
          Requirement Levels</title>

          <author fullname="S. Bradner" initials="S." surname="Bradner">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date month="March" year="1997" />

          <abstract>
            <t>Defines the normative terms used in RFCs.</t>
          </abstract>
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="BCP" value="14" />

        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="2119" />
      </reference>

      <!-- End inclusion reference.RFC.2119.xml. -->
	  
      <!-- Begin inclusion reference.draft.MPLS.TP.Reqs -->

      <reference anchor="RFC5654">
        <front>
          <title>Requirements for the Transport Profile of MPLS</title>

          <author fullname="Ben Niven-Jenkins" initials="B."
                  surname="Niven-Jenkins">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="T. Nadeau" initials="T." surname="Nadeau">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="C. Pignataro" initials="C." surname="Pignataro">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date month="Sept" year="2009" />

          <abstract>
            <t>Lists the requirements for MPLS-TP with cross reference</t>
          </abstract>
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="5654" />
      </reference>

      <!-- End inclusion reference.draft.MPLS.TP.Reqs -->

      <!-- Begin inclusion reference.draft.MPLS.TP.Surviavbility Framework -->

      <reference anchor="RFC6372">
        <front>
          <title>MPLS-TP Survivability Framework</title>

          <author fullname="Nurit Sprecher" initials="N." surname="Sprecher">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="Adrian Farrel" initials="A." surname="Farrel">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date month="Sept" year="2011" />

          <abstract>
            <t>Network survivability is the network's ability to restore
            traffic delivery following failure of network resources or an
            attack on the network. It plays a critical role in the delivery of
            guaranteed services in transport networks to meet the requirements
            expressed in Service Level Agreements (SLAs).</t>

            <t>The Transport Profile of Multiprotocol Label Switching
            (MPLS-TP) is a packet transport technology based on the MPLS data
            plane and re-using many aspects of the MPLS management and control
            planes.</t>

            <t>This document provides a framework for the provision of
            survivability functions in the data plane of an MPLS-TP network
            using tools provided by the management plane and the control plane
            as well as techniques inherent in the data plane itself.</t>
          </abstract>
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="6372" />
      </reference>

      <!-- End inclusion reference.draft.MPLS.TP.Survivability FWk -->

      <!-- Begin inclusion reference.draft.MPLS.TP.Linear Protection -->

      <reference anchor="RFC6378">
        <front>
          <title>MPLS-TP Linear Protection</title>

          <author fullname="Nurit Sprecher" initials="N." surname="Sprecher">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="Stewart Bryant" initials="S." surname="Bryant">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="Eric Osborne" initials="E." surname="Osborne">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="Annamaria Fulignoli" initials="A."
                  surname="Fulignoli">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="Yaacov Weingarten" initials="Y."
                  surname="Weingarten">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date month="Nov" year="2011" />

          <abstract>
            <t>The MPLS Transport Profile (MPLS-TP) being specified jointly by
            IETF and ITU-T includes requirements documents and framework
            documents. The framework documents define the basic architecture
            that is needed in order to support various aspects of the required
            behavior. This document addresses the functionality described in
            the Survivability Framework document [11] and defines a protocol
            that may be used to fulfill the function of the Protection State
            Coordination for linear protection, as described in that
            document.</t>
          </abstract>
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="6378" />
      </reference>

      <!-- End inclusion reference.draft.MPLS.TP.Linear Protection -->

      <!-- Begin inclusion reference.RFC.3945 -->

      <reference anchor="RFC3945">
        <front>
          <title>Generalized Multi-Protocol Label Switching (GMPLS) Architecture</title>

          <author fullname="Eric Mannie" initials="E." surname="Mannie">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date month="Oct" year="2004" />

          <abstract>
            <t>Future data and transmission networks will consist of elements such
			as routers, switches, Dense Wavelength Division Multiplexing (DWDM)
			systems, Add-Drop Multiplexors (ADMs), photonic cross-connects (PXCs),
			optical cross-connects (OXCs), etc. that will use Generalized
			Multi-Protocol Label Switching (GMPLS) to dynamically provision
			resources and to provide network survivability using protection and
			restoration techniques.</t>

			<t>This document describes the architecture of GMPLS.  GMPLS extends
			MPLS to encompass time-division (e.g., SONET/SDH, PDH, G.709),
			wavelength (lambdas), and spatial switching (e.g., incoming port or
			fiber to outgoing port or fiber).  The focus of GMPLS is on the control 
			plane of these various layers since each of them can use physically 
			diverse data or forwarding planes.  The intention is to cover both 
			the signaling and the routing part of that control plane.</t>
          </abstract>
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="3945" />
      </reference>

      <!-- End inclusion reference.RFC.3945 -->

      <!-- Begin inclusion reference.ITU.G.808.1 -->

      <reference anchor="G.808.1">
        <front>
          <title>Generic Protection Switching - Linear trail and subnetwork protection</title>

          <author>
            <organization>ITU</organization>
          </author>

          <date month="Feb" year="2010" />

          <abstract>
            <t>ITU Protection Definitions</t>
          </abstract>
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="ITU-T" value="G.808.1" />
      </reference>

      <!-- End inclusion reference.ITU.808.1 -->

      <!-- Begin inclusion reference.RFC.4427 -->

      <reference anchor="RFC4427">
        <front>
          <title>Recovery (Protection and Restoration) Terminology for
          GMPLS</title>

          <author fullname="Eric Mannie" initials="E." surname="Mannie">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="Dimitri Papadimitriou" initials="D."
                  surname="Papadimitriou">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date month="March" year="2006" />

          <abstract>
            <t>This document defines a common terminology for Generalized
            Multi- Protocol Label Switching (GMPLS)-based recovery mechanisms
            (i.e., protection and restoration). The terminology is independent
            of the underlying transport technologies covered by GMPLS.</t>
          </abstract>
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="4427" />
      </reference>

      <!-- End inclusion reference.RFC.4427 -->

      <!-- Begin inclusion reference.RFC.4428 -->

      <reference anchor="RFC4428">
        <front>
          <title>Analysis of Generalized Multi-Protocol Label Switching (GMPLS)-based
      Recovery Mechanisms (including Protection and Restoration)</title>

          <author fullname="Eric Mannie" initials="E." surname="Mannie">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="Dimitri Papadimitriou" initials="D."
                  surname="Papadimitriou">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date month="March" year="2006" />

          <abstract>
            <t>This document provides an analysis grid to evaluate, compare, and
			contrast the Generalized Multi-Protocol Label Switching (GMPLS)
			protocol suite capabilities with the recovery mechanisms currently
			proposed at the IETF CCAMP Working Group.  A detailed analysis of
			each of the recovery phases is provided using the terminology defined
			in RFC 4427.  This document focuses on transport plane survivability
			and recovery issues and not on control plane resilience and related
			aspects.</t>
          </abstract>
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="4428" />
      </reference>

      <!-- End inclusion reference.RFC.4428 -->

      <!-- Begin inclusion reference.RFC.5712 -->

      <reference anchor="RFC5712">
        <front>
          <title>Recovery (Protection and Restoration) Terminology for
          GMPLS</title>

          <author fullname="M. Meyer" initials="M." surname="Meyer">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="JP. Vasseur" initials="JP."
                  surname="Vasseur">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date month="January" year="2010" />

          <abstract>
            <t>This document specifies Multiprotocol Label Switching (MPLS) Traffic
			Engineering Soft Preemption, a suite of protocol modifications
			extending the concept of preemption with the goal of reducing or
			eliminating traffic disruption of preempted Traffic Engineering Label
			Switched Paths (TE LSPs).  Initially, MPLS RSVP-TE was defined with
			support for only immediate TE LSP displacement upon preemption.  The
			utilization of a reroute request notification helps more gracefully
			mitigate the reroute process of preempted TE LSP.  For the brief
			period soft preemption is activated, reservations (though not
			necessarily traffic levels) are in effect under-provisioned until the
			TE LSP(s) can be rerouted.  For this reason, the feature is
			primarily, but not exclusively, interesting in MPLS-enabled IP
			networks with Differentiated Services and Traffic Engineering
			capabilities.</t>
          </abstract>
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="5712" />
      </reference>

      <!-- End inclusion reference.RFC.5712 -->

      <!-- Begin inclusion reference.RFC.3209 -->

      <reference anchor="RFC3209">
        <front>
          <title>RSVP-TE: Extensions to RSVP for LSP Tunnels</title>

          <author fullname="D. Awduche" initials="D." surname="Awduche">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="Lou Berger" initials="L." surname="Berger">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="D. Gan" initials="D." surname="Gan">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="T.Li" initials="T." surname="Li">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="V. Srinivasan" initials="V." surname="Srinivasan">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date month="December" year="2001" />

          <abstract>
            <t></t>
          </abstract>
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="3209" />
      </reference>

      <!-- End inclusion reference.RFC.3209 -->
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
