<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
    <!ENTITY rfc2119 PUBLIC '' 
      'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml'>
]>

<rfc category="info" ipr="pre5378Trust200902" docName="draft-blanchet-newprep-problem-statement-00.txt">
  <?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
  <?rfc toc="yes" ?>
  <?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
  <?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
  <?rfc iprnotified="no" ?>
  <?rfc strict="yes" ?>
  <?rfc compact="yes" ?>
  <front>
    <title>NewPrep Problem Statement</title>
    <author initials="M." surname="Blanchet Ed." fullname="Marc Blanchet">
      <organization>Viagenie</organization>
      <address>
    <postal>
      <street>2600 boul. Laurier, suite 625</street>
      <city>Quebec</city>
      <region>QC</region>
      <code>G1V 4W1</code>
      <country>Canada</country>
    </postal>
    <email>Marc.Blanchet@viagenie.ca</email>
    <uri>http://www.viagenie.ca</uri>
  </address>
    </author>
    <date month="March" year="2010"/>
    <abstract>
      <t>
Using Unicode codepoints in protocol strings requires preparation of the string.
Internationalized Domain Names(idn) initial work defined and used Stringprep and Nameprep. Other protocols have defined Stringprep profiles. New approach different from Stringprep/Nameprep is used for a revision of IDN. This document summarize the characteristics of both approach and provides guidance to protocol designers for handling internationalized strings.
      </t>
    </abstract>
  </front>
  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>
As part of the Internationalized Domain Names(idn) initial work <xref target="RFC3490"/><xref target="RFC3491"/><xref target="RFC3492"/>, the unicode-based strings needed to be prepared and normalized to enable their use in the DNS with exact match mechanism. The method, called Nameprep <xref target="RFC3491"/>, was specific to idn, but was generalized as Stringprep <xref target="RFC3454"/>, to help other protocols with similar needs, but with different constraints than idn.
</t>
<t>Strinprep defines a framework where protocols defines their Stringprep profiles. Known IETF specifications using Strinprep are:
<list style="symbols">
<t>The Nameprep profile<xref target="RFC3490"/> for use in Internationalized Domain Names (IDNs)</t>
<t>The iSCSI profile <xref target="RFC3722"/> for use in Internet Small Computer Systems Interface (iSCSI) Names</t>
<t>The Nodeprep and Resourceprep profiles <xref target="RFC3920"/> for use in the Extensible Messaging and Presence Protocol (XMPP)</t>
<t>The Policy MIB profile <xref target="RFC4011"/> for use in the Simple Network Management Protocol (SNMP)</t>
<t>The SASLprep profile <xref target="RFC4013"/> for use in the Simple Authentication and Security Layer (SASL)</t>
<t>The trace profile <xref target="RFC4505"/> for use with the SASL ANONYMOUS mechanism</t>
<t> The LDAP profile <xref target="RFC4518"/> for use with LDAP</t>
</list>
</t>
<t>Based on findings <xref target="RFC4690"/> on early deployments of idn, 
IDNs specifications have been updated /* note to add ref to idnabis RFCs*/  and do not use stringprep/nameprep anymore. Instead, a complete table of the supported Unicode codepoints is defined. This table is based on some properties of the codepoints as defined by Unicode and some specific exceptions. It also defines an algorithm to update the table with new versions of the Unicode codepoints database.
</t>
<t>
Do other protocols, either current users of Stringprep or other protocols, would benefit from the new approach for idns?
The aim of this document is to provide advice on the preparation of internationalized strings to protocol designers of current stringprep profiles as well as for new protocols. 
</t>
</section>
<section title="Key Characteristics of Stringprep">
<t>
Stringprep is used to prepare a string and output a string or an error. The output string is normalized so that it could be compared with others in a protocol. The functions and operations done by Stringprep are: mapping, normalization, prohibition and bidirectional string processing. Many functions use or may use Unicode specifications such as the normalization rules /* note to add ref to unicode normalization rules docs*/.
</t>
<t>Functions provided by Stringprep are typically needed for many network protocols that handles internationalized strings.
</t>
<t>Stringprep has the following key characteristics:
<list style="symbols">
<t>Based on Unicode 3.2</t>
<t>Defines a list of codepoints that are specially processed, such as removed</t>
<t>Codepoints not specifically listed are only normalized by Unicode normalization rules</t>
</list>
</t>
</section>
<section title="Key Characteristics of IDNAbis">
<t>IDNAbis method has the following key characteristics:
<list style="symbols">
<t>Based on Unicode 5.2</t>
<t>Each Unicode codepoint is tagged</t>
<t>Basic table is created algorithmatically using some properties of the Unicode codepoint database.</t>
<t>Some exceptions are specially handled</t>
<t>An exception table(currently empty) is provisionned in case a future version of Unicode introduces a new character or a change in a character that creates a compatibility issue with previous tables.</t>
<t>IANA registers the whole codepoint table for each Unicode database version.</t>
</list>
</t>
<t>When Unicode releases a new version of the codepoint database, the table has to be regenerated and registered by IANA. Exceptions may appear in the new table. In this case, an expert will have to manually resolve the exceptions.</t>
</section>
<section title="Protocols already using Stringprep">
<t>Possible options are:
<list style="symbols">
<t>Leave it as is.</t>
<t>Update Stringprep to new version of Unicode. Update protocol profile to new version of Stringprep.</t>
<t>Define a generalized version of IDNAbis for protocols. Update protocol to use the new method.</t>
</list>
</t>
</section>
<section title="Protocols looking for preparing internationalized strings">
<t>Possible options are:
<list style="symbols">
<t>Use Stringprep as is. Define a profile for it</t>
<t>Use IDNAbis.</t>
<t>Define a generalized version of IDNAbis for protocols. Define protocol to use the new method.</t>
</list>
</t>
</section>
<section title="Generalizing IDNAbis for other protocols">
<t>A generalized version of IDNAbis to be used for other protocols might be interesting to do. Similar to Stringprep but using the IDNAbis approach.</t>
</section>
<section title="Summary">
<t>When this document matures enough, then appropriate summary and conclusions will be written...</t>
    </section>
<section title="Security Considerations">
<t>TBD</t>
</section>
<section title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>
        This document has no actions for IANA.
      </t>
    </section>
    <section title="Discussion home for this draft">
      <t>
        This document is intended to define the problem space discussed in the newprep@ietf.org mailing list.
      </t>
    </section>
  </middle>
  <back>
    <references title="Informative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3454" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3490" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3491" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3492" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3722" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3920" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4011" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4013" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4505" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4518" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4690" ?>
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
