<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!-- This template is for creating an Internet Draft using xml2rfc,
     which is available here: http://xml.resource.org. -->
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY RFC1034    PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1034.xml'>
<!ENTITY RFC2119    PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml'>
<!ENTITY RFC2617    PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2617.xml'>
<!ENTITY RFC3966    PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3966.xml'>
<!ENTITY RFC3986    PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3986.xml'>
<!ENTITY RFC4759    PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4759.xml'>
<!ENTITY RFC4769    PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4769.xml'>
<!ENTITY RFC6116    PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6116.xml'>
<!ENTITY RFC6117    PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6117.xml'>
<!ENTITY I-D.ietf-appsawg-webfinger  PUBLIC '' 
'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-appsawg-webfinger.xml'>
<!ENTITY I-D.ietf-appsawg-acct-uri  PUBLIC '' 
'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-appsawg-acct-uri.xml'>
]>

<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='http://xml.resource.org/authoring/rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc tocompact="no" ?>
<?rfc tocindent="no" ?>
<?rfc comments="yes" ?>
<?rfc inline="yes" ?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc iprnotified="no" ?>
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="yes"?>

<rfc
  category="exp"
  ipr="trust200902"
  docName="draft-goix-appsawg-enum-acct-uri-01">

  <front>
    <title abbrev="Enum Service ACCT URI Registration">
    ENUM Service Registration for acct URI
    </title>
    
    <author initials='L.' surname="Goix" fullname='Laurent-Walter Goix'>
      <organization>Telecom Italia</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>P.za Einaudi, 8</street>
          <city>Milano</city>
          <code>20124</code>
          <country>Italy</country>
        </postal>
        <email>laurentwalter.goix@telecomitalia.it</email>
      </address>
    </author>
	
    <author initials="K." surname="Li" fullname="Kepeng Li">
      <organization abbrev="Huawei Technologies">Huawei Technologies</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Huawei Base, Bantian, Longgang District</street>
          <city>Shenzhen</city>
          <code>518129</code>
          <country>P. R. China</country>
        </postal>
        <phone>+86-755-28971807</phone>
        <email>likepeng@huawei.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    
    <date year="2013" />

    <area>Applications</area>
    <workgroup>appsawg</workgroup>

    <abstract>
      <t>      
   This document registers a Telephone Number Mapping (ENUM) service for
   'acct:' URIs (Uniform Resource Identifiers).
       </t>
    </abstract>

  </front>

  <middle>
    <section anchor="intro" title="Introduction">
      <t>
	 ENUM (E.164 Number Mapping, <xref target='RFC6116' />) is a system that uses DNS
   (Domain Name Service, <xref target='RFC1034' />) to translate telephone numbers,
   such as '+44 1632 960123', into URIs 
   (Uniform Resource Identifiers, <xref target='RFC3986' />),
   such as 'acct:user@example.com'.  ENUM exists primarily to
   facilitate the interconnection of systems that rely on telephone
   numbers with those that use URIs to identify resources.
       </t>
       <t>
   <xref target='I-D.ietf-appsawg-webfinger' /> 
   is proposing a generic mechanism to discover information
   about resources, including those identified
   through an account based on the 'acct:' URI scheme.   
   <xref target='I-D.ietf-appsawg-acct-uri' /> 
   defines the 'acct' URI scheme as a way to identify a
   user's account at a service provider.
       </t>
       <t>
   This document registers an enumservice for advertising acct URI information
   associated with an E.164 number.
       </t>   
      </section>
      
       <section anchor="terms" title="Terminology">
        <t>
          The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
          "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in
          this document are to be interpreted as described in <xref target='RFC2119' />.
        </t>        
      </section>
	
	<section title="Use cases">
		<section title="Routing of mobile social communications">
		   <t>
		 The Open Mobile Alliance (OMA) Social Network Web (SNeW) Enabler Release <xref target='OMA-SNeW-ER' /> has introduced a number of
		Social Networking functionalities to mobile subscribers
		identified by their MSISDN, amongst which the ability of following each other's social activities across service providers.
		Such functionality requires the global 
		resolution of the MSISDN to the corresponding account and provider, in an analogous way as MMS routing, to identify the target endpoint for the related messages.
		Although alternatives solutions exist (e.g. based on mobile network operations and/or proprietary lookup techniques), ENUM provides a globally accessible mechanism for enabling resolution from network entities on behalf of an endpoint, or from an endpoint itself.
		</t>
		<t>
		For example, a user of a service provider could request  to follow the social activities of user '+44 1632 960123', triggering a network entity to perform an ENUM query, eventually followed by a Webfinger query, to route this request to the appropriate target provider and endpoint.
		</t>
		<t>
		A similar mechanism can apply to other types of social networking-related messages or other communications targeted to a mobile subscriber.
		</t> 
		</section>   
		<section title="Reverse phone lookup">
		   <t>
		Yet in another example, an address book endpoint could issue an ENUM query looking for a user's account to discover additional personal information about that user given his phone number, such as avatar and full name. 
		</t>
		<t>
		Similarly, an endpoint could trigger this resolution process during inbound and/or outbound calls to discover additional personal information about the remote party.
		   </t>      
		   <t>
		   The provision of an ENUM record to map a phone number 
		   into an account may be useful for businesses or 
		   professional workers to identify themselves publicly 
		   (in a similar way as vCard enum records), or be used 
		   in conjunction with privacy policies to provide a 
		   more controlled view on some personal details.
		</t>
		</section>   
    </section>
    
    <section anchor="ianar" title="IANA Registration">
       <t>       
	As defined in <xref target='RFC6117' />,
	the following is a template covering information needed for the 
	registration of the enumservice specified in this document:
       </t>
       <figure>
	   <artwork><![CDATA[
           <record>
             <class>Application-Based, Common</class>
             <type>acct</type>
             <urischeme>acct</urischeme>
             <functionalspec>
               <paragraph>
                 This enumservice indicates that the resource
                 can be addressed by the associated URI enabling the 
				 use of 
<xref target='I-D.ietf-appsawg-webfinger' /> 
				 to discover additional information.
               </paragraph>
             </functionalspec>
             <security>
               See <xref target="security" />.
             </security>
             <usage>COMMON</usage>
             <registrationdocs>
               This document.
             </registrationdocs>
             <requesters>
               <xref type="person" data="Laurent_Walter_Goix"/>
             </requesters>
           </record>

           <people>
             <person id="Laurent_Walter_Goix">
               <name>Laurent-Walter Goix</name>
               <org>Telecom Italia</org>
               <uri>mailto:laurentwalter.goix@telecomitalia.it</uri>
               <updated>2013-01-25</updated>
             </person>
           </people>      
        ]]></artwork></figure>
    </section>
    
     <section anchor="examples" title="Examples">
      <t>
      The following is an example of the use of the enumservice 
	  registered by this document in a NAPTR resource record for phone
	  number +44 1632 960123.
      </t>
      <t>
     $ORIGIN 3.2.1.0.6.9.2.3.6.1.4.4.e164.arpa.
      </t>
	  <t>
	  IN NAPTR 10 100 "u" "E2U+acct" "!^.*$!acct:441632960123@foo.com!"	. 
	  </t>
      <t>
      IN NAPTR 10 101 "u" "E2U+acct" "!^.*$!acct:john.doe@example.com!"     .
      </t>
      <t>
      Note that in the first record, the revealed 
	  information is limited to the domain of the service 
	  provider serving that user a the userpart of the acct URI simply 
	  replicates the phone number.
      </t>
     </section>
    
     <section anchor="dns" title="DNS Considerations">
     <t>
        If no "E2U+acct" NAPTR record exist for the requested number,
		the resolution process over issuing ENUM queries may be 
		recursively performed over E.164 numbers identified by other NAPTR records for
   the requested number pointing to "tel" URIs <xref target='RFC3966' />. 
    Whilst this
   process is useful to support, amongst others, number portability as
   per <xref target='RFC4769' />, Section 4, 
   this may also create potential loops in
   this resolution process.  As such ENUM clients performing such ENUM
   queries over "tel" URIs to identify "acct" URIs SHOULD understand the
   "enumdi" indicator defined in <xref target='RFC4759' />.
    In particular, if the
   result of the query does not include "E2U+acct" NAPTR records, and
   includes a NAPTR resource record containing a "tel" URI that has the
   same E.164 number, or a "tel" URI with the "enumdi" parameter set,
   that client SHOULD NOT perform subsequent ENUM queries over such
   numbers and SHOULD consider that the original requested number 
   cannot be mapped.
   </t>
   <t>
   Furthermore the client MAY stop performing subsequent ENUM queries
   after the fifth recursive query as suggested in
    <xref target='RFC6116' /> section
   5.2.1.
    </t>   
     </section>
    
     <section anchor="security" title="Security Considerations">
       <t>
         DNS, as used by ENUM, is a global, distributed database.  Should
   implementers of this specification use e164.arpa or any other
   publicly available domain as the tree for maintaining PSTN
   enumservice data, this information would be visible to anyone
   anonymously.  
      </t>
       <t>
   As noted earlier, carriers, service providers, and other users may
   choose not to publish such information in the public e164.arpa tree.
   They may instead simply publish this in an internal ENUM
   infrastructure that is only able to be queried by trusted elements of
   their network, thus limiting threats.
      </t>
       <t>
   Per se, this enumservice does not introduce specific security considerations beyond
   <xref target='RFC6116' />, section 7. However, it has to be acknowledged that the
   proposed enumservice could lead to the discovery or disclosure of
   Personally Identifiable Information (PII) when used in combination with 
   the WebFinger protocol. 
   Please see <xref target='I-D.ietf-appsawg-webfinger' />
   , section 10 for additional information regarding WebFinger security.
      </t>
   <t>
   Linking telephone numbers to Personally Identifiable 
   Information (PII) is a very sensitive topic, because it 
   provides a "reverse lookup" from the phone number to its owner. 
   Publication of such PII is covered by data-protection law 
   in many legislations. In most cases, the explicit consent
    of the affected individual is required.
   </t> 
   <t>
    Users MUST therefore carefully consider the information  
    provided in the resource identified by the ENUM record as 
    well as in the record itself. Considerations SHOULD include 
    serving information only to entities of the user's choice 
    and/or limiting the comprehension of the information provided
     based on the identity of the requestor.
   </t>
        <t>
   It is important to remind that the ENUM record itself does not 
   need to contain any personal information but only contains a pointer to
    an account identifier. This identifier may be queried through the 
	Webfinger protocol to discover pointers to personal information (e.g. 
    social network information) and an authorisation mechanism 
    may be in place in that context with any level of granularity although it is out of scope of this document.
    </t>
   <t>
	Technically, ENUM records themselves could contain pointers to the same endpoints discoverable through Webfinger. 
	However the visibility of ENUM records cannot be controlled based on the requesting entity. In that context the 
	simple mapping of the phone number to the account identifier, notwithstanding the disclosure of the association 
	itself, still enables the reuse of more advanced access policies.
    </t>        
      </section>

    <section anchor="ianac" title="IANA Considerations">
       <t>   
       This document requests the IANA registration of the enumservice with
   Type "acct" according to the definitions in this document, 
   <xref target='RFC6116' /> and <xref target='RFC6117' />.  
       </t>
       <t>
      Details of the registration are given in <xref target="ianar" />.
       </t>
     </section>  
    
    <section anchor="acknowledgement" title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>  
   The authors would like to thank Gonzalo Salgueiro, Paul Jones,
   Lawrence Conroy, Enrico Marocco and Bert Greevenbosch
   for their valuable feedback to
   improve this document.      
      </t>
    </section>

  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      &I-D.ietf-appsawg-webfinger;
      &I-D.ietf-appsawg-acct-uri;
      &RFC1034;
      &RFC2119;
      &RFC2617;
      &RFC3966;
      &RFC3986;
      &RFC4759;
      &RFC4769;
      &RFC6116;
      &RFC6117;         
    </references>
    <references title="Informative References">
      <reference anchor="OMA-SNeW-ER">
        <front>
          <title>Social Network Web Enabler</title>
          <author>
            <organization>Open Mobile Alliance</organization>
          </author>
          <date month="Dec" year="2012"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="OMA-ER-SNeW-V1_0" value="20121217-D"/>
      </reference>
    </references>

  </back>
</rfc>    