<?xml version='1.0'?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM 'rfc2629.dtd'>
<?rfc toc='yes'?>
<?rfc symrefs='yes'?>
<?rfc compact='yes'?>
<?rfc subcompact='no'?>

<rfc category='info' ipr='trust200902' docName="draft-wilkinson-afs3-standardisation-00"
     submissionType="independent">
   <front>
    <title>Options for AFS Standardisation</title>
    <author initials="S." surname="Wilkinson" fullname="Simon Wilkinson">
      <organization abbrev="University of Edinburgh">School of Informatics, University of Edinburgh</organization>
      <address>
	<postal>
	  <street>Informatics Forum</street>
	  <street>10 Crichton Street</street>	
          <city>Edinburgh</city>
	  <code>EH8 9AB</code>
	  <country>Scotland</country>
        </postal>
        <email>sxw@inf.ed.ac.uk</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date month="June" year="2010"/>

    <abstract>
  <t>With the impending formation of the foundation to house OpenAFS, the increasing pace
  of OpenAFS development, and the emergence of other AFS implementations, there
  is a growing need for a more formal, independent, standardisation body.</t>

  <t>This document seeks to define an initial form for that body.</t>
  </abstract>
</front>
<middle>
  <section anchor="intro" title="Introduction">

    <t>The formation of a foundation to provide a home for OpenAFS was announced at the 
       Best Practices Workshop at NJIT in 2008.
       At that meeting, concerns were raised regarding the mechanism for standardising
       extensions to the AFS protocol. In particular, the view was expressed that, as a 
       matter of good governance, it was undesirable to have the 
       standardisation of the protocol in the grasp of a single vendor.
    </t>

    <t>This document defines a standardisation process that is practically independent
       of this foundation. At this time there 
       are insufficient resources, both human and financial, to create a 
       separate legal entity to house the standards work. It is also 
       apparent that standardising extensions to the AFS protocol is unlikely 
       to be a good fit for any other, existing, standards organisation. This 
       means that the body must exist, for legal purposes, as part of the
       foundation, and mechanisms must be found to ensure its 
       day-to-day independence within it. These mechanisms should sufficiently 
       encapsulate the standards process so it is possible to either donate it 
       to another standards body, or to spin it off into its own foundation, 
       should this be desirable at some future point.
    </t>

    <t>Retaining this independence sets us a number of simple ground rules:
      <list style='numbers'>
        <t>It must be impossible for the foundation to use its position to 
           standardise its ideas against the wishes of the community, or to 
	   prevent the standardisation of items approved by the community.
        </t>
        <t>It must be impossible for the foundation to control the 
	   distribution, or implementation, of standards developed by the 
	   group
	</t>
	<t>It must be impossible for the foundation to prevent the membership 
	   of the group by any person or organisation.
	</t>
        <t>Should an irreparable breakdown of trust occur between the 
	   standardisation group and the foundation, it must be possible to 
	   move the standardisation effort elsewhere.
        </t>
      </list>
    </t>

    <t>Until recently, standardisation of extensions to AFS has occurred in 
       a relatively adhoc fashion, with informal proposals generally being 
       sent to and discussed on the afs3-standardization@grand.central.org list. 
       The issuing of
       code points, and other numeric registrations is then handled by the
       grand.central.org registrar (Jeffrey Hutzelman). This process has only
       been in place for a couple of years - extensions which predate it lack
       formal specification, and extensions which have been through it are
       often only documented in the mailing list archives.
    </t>

    <t>This lack of specifications for many recent additions 
       to AFS causes significant issues for implementers outside of the OpenAFS project.
       In order to preserve the ability of third parties to create their own
       AFS implementations, it is vital that there is a clear set of 
       definitions of AFS RPCs and code points that is independent of the
       OpenAFS source code. Any successful standardisation process must
       establish, and maintain, a repository of specifications for all public extensions 
       and refinements whoever they are designed and implemented by.</t>

    <t>To achieve this the process must allow participation by all, without regard for
       their organisational affiliation, so anyone
       with an interest in the development of the AFS protocol may contribute
       ideas and proposals.
     </t>

    <t>It would seem unwise to devote a large amount of energy now in defining
       rules and procedures to cater for all eventualities. Instead, I believe 
       we should do the minimum necessary work in order to formally create a 
       standardisation group satisfying the above goals to coincide with the 
       formation of the foundation. That group may then further define and 
       refine its policies as it deems necessary.
    </t>
</section>

<section title="The proposed model">

    <t>This section proposes a model for AFS standardisation, designed to build upon
       as many existing resources as possible. It is loosely based on, and borrows heavily
       upon, the IETF processes as documented in <xref target='RFC2026'>RFC2026</xref> and
       <eref target="http://ietf.org/IESG/content/procdocs.html">http://ietf.org/IESG/content/procdocs.html</eref>.
    </t>

    <section title="The Standardisation Group">
      <t>The standardisation group consists of a mailing list. Membership
	 of this mailing list is freely open to all with an interest in 
	 AFS standardisation. The list of mailing list members is freely available to
	 all subscribers, and defines the membership of the AFS Standardisation Group.</t>

      <t>Discussions amongst the group are expected to occur upon this
	 mailing list. In order to ensure open participation decisions of 
	 the group must only be made on the list, and not at any other
	 meetings that may occur.</t>

      <t>In essence, this simply formalises the existing 
	 afs3-standardization@grand.central.org mailing list. It is proposed that
	 this list be the initial home of the standardisation group, and 
	 its current membership be the initial members of the group. </t>

    </section>

    <section title="Group Chairs">
      <t>The standardisation group has two chairs. These chairs have a
	 number of responsibilities to the group, and the wider AFS 
	 community. These responsibilities are discussed throughout this document, but in
	 summary they comprise of
         <list style='symbols'>
	   <t>Judgement of group opinion by determining rough consensus</t>
	   <t>Encouraging momentum and forwards progress of group discussions and 
	      proposals</t>
           <t>Maintenance of the Standards Web site, including maintaining lists of 
	      proposals and standards and their statuses</t>
         </list>
     </t>
     <t>A successful chair will require a high level of organisational
	and people skills, and the respect of the wider AFS community.
	They will not necessarily need a high degree
	of specific technical knowledge, as they are expected to interpret
	and act upon the will of the wider standardisation group, rather
	than imposing their personal views.
     </t>

      <section title="Appointment Term">
      <t>Each chair serves a term of 2 years, with their terms offset by a
	 year from each other. This means a chair will be replaced every year,
	 with the other chair remaining to provide continuity. The outgoing
	 chair's term ends on the last day of September of the appropriate year. 
      </t>	 
      </section>

      <section title="Election procedure">
	 <t>Chairs are appointed by an election run by one or more vote-takers. 
	    In normal operation, the vote-takers are the current standardisation
	    group chairs. In the event that no chair is available to act as a 
	    vote-taker, then the registrars will perform the vote-taking role.  
	    If a vote-taker wishes to stand in an election, they must recuse 
	    themselves from the vote-taking role. Vote-takers who are also 
	    eligible voters may vote in the same manner as any other voter.
         </t>

	 <t>At the start of the election process (typically the first of August
	    each year) the vote-takers send the mailing list a request for
	    nominations, accompanied by a list of currently eligible voters</t>

         <t>Eligibility to vote is determined by those who are subscribed to, 
	    or have posted to, the standardisation group during the time period 
	    from the 1st of June to the 1st July of the appropriate year.</t>

         <t>Nominations shall be sent to both the vote-takers, and the 
            afs3-standardization mailing list. Any consenting individual may
	    be nominated, but shall be both proposed and seconded by eligible
	    voters. Self-nomination is not permitted. In order to maintain 
	    balance between the two chairs, it is highly desirable that a 
	    candidate should not have the same affiliation as the remaining chair. 
         </t>

	 <t>Nominations are open for 14 days from the day the call is issued. 
	    Seven days after the nomination period has ended, if more than one 
	    candidate has emerged, the vote-takers will issue a call for votes, 
	    which will last for 14 days. In the event of no eligible nominations 
	    being received, the vote-takers may, at their discretion, appoint an 
	    interim candidate to serve the full term. The results of the election 
	    would be announced one week after the close of voting, with the new 
	    chair taking office from the 1st October
         </t>

	 <t>Votes are submitted by email to all of the vote-takers. The
	    vote-takers shall make no public pronouncements regarding the number or
	    character of votes received until the end of the election period. At
	    the end of the election, each vote-taker shall independently count the
	    votes received and post to the group list the total number of votes
	    received by each candidate, and the email addresses of all those
	    who voted. Under no circumstances shall the nature of individual votes
	    be revealed. The candidate who receives the most votes is elected as
	    the incoming chair. If voting is tied, then the vote-takers shall 
	    collectively have a single casting vote. </t>

         <t>At their discretion, the vote-takers may vary the above timeline, within the 
	    following constraints
	    <list style="symbols">
              <t>The new chair must take office on 1st October</t>
	      <t>The eligibility cut-off must be 1st July</t>
	      <t>The nominations period must last a minimum of 14 days</t>
	      <t>The voting period must last a minimum of 14 days</t>
	      <t>Results must be announced within 7 days of the close of voting</t>
	    </list>
	    The timeline to be used must be announced with the call for nominations.
         </t>
      </section>
      <section title="Mid-term vacancies">
	 <t>In the event of the outgoing chair position becoming vacant on
            or after June 1, but before October 1, then the office will remain
	    vacant until it is filled by the winner of the regular election
         </t>
         <t>If the returning chair position becomes vacant after June 1, but
	    before the start of nominations for the regular election, then 
	    the election will select two candidates, with the returning
	    chair's position being filled by the candidate with the second
	    highest number of votes.
	 </t>
	 <t>If the returning chair's position becomes vacant between the 
	    opening of nominations, and the conclusion of the election, then
	    the office remains vacant during the election, and the incoming
	    chair shall hold a new election as soon as practical after 
	    taking office.
	 </t>
	 <t>In the event of any chair's position becoming vacant at any
 	    other time, the remaining chair (or the registrars, in the
	    event of no chair remaining) shall run an election as soon as
	    is reasonably practicable.
	 </t>
	 <t>When the election process must be started at an unusual time, 
            the normal timeline is used, subject to the vote-taker's
	    discretion, except that the new chair must take office two 
	    months after the call for nominations.  The eligibility 
	    cut-off remains the most recent July 1, as defined above.
	 </t>
      </section>

      <section title="Recall Procedure">

      <t>In the event of a substantial breakdown of trust between the 
	 chairs and the rest of the standardisation group, a recall procedure
	 may be employed to remove one, or both, of the chairs from their
	 position. The use of this procedure is likely to be severely damaging
	 to the community, and so should only be considered as a last resort.
      </t>

      <t>Recall shall be performed by means of a public ballot. The proposers
	 of the recall shall post their proposal to the afs3-standardization
	 list, which triggers a 7 day public voting period. Group members
	 then publicly post to the list indicating their agreement or
	 disagreement with the proposal. A successful recall requires a 
	 majority of those posting to agree, and for more than 20% of the
	 groups total membership to have voted.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="The Standardisation Process">
      <t>The standardisation process is similar to that of an IETF working 
         group with proposals being submitted as drafts and refined by group 
         members. When a document is judged to be ready the chairs issue
         a call for opinions and determine the views of the group.
	 If the chairs determine that the group has achieved a rough consensus that the 
	 document should be approved then it advances to experimental status, code 
	 points are issued for the protocol elements, and developers proceed to create
	 implementations. The document may then be further refined based on
	 the experience of these implementors. Providing one successful
	 implementation exists, and the group achieves rough consensus that it is still 
	 worthy of standardisation, the document then advances to 'standard'
	 status, reserved code points are marked as such, and it is published as part of 
	 an archival series.
      </t>

      <section title="Drafts">
      <t>Proposals for standardisation are made as Internet Drafts.
         These documents must be compliant with all of the provisions of
	 the IETF's <xref target='ID-Guide'>Guidelines to Authors of Internet 
         Drafts</xref> and the documents it
	 references. Note that it is not permissible for documents that wish
	 to progress through the AFS standardisation process to prohibit 
	 modification or derivative works, or to bar publication as an RFC. 
	 Drafts should be named as individual contributions, and contain the string
	 afs3-stds within their name.
      </t>
 
      <t>Proposals are submitted by adding the draft to the Internet-Drafts Directory,
	 and mailing a pointer to the resulting entry to the afs3-standardization list.
	 During the quiet periods prior to IETF conferences, drafts may be sent directly
	 to the list, but should be uploaded once the quiet period ends.</t>
  
      <t>Drafts which define new RPCs must include suitable RPCL definitions
	 for those RPCs. Drafts must not include code points for new RPCs,
	 error codes, or similar items, until those code points have been
	 issued by the registrars. The registrars will not normally allocate these 
	 code points to a standardisation group document until a draft has achieved 
	 consensus within the group.
      </t>
      <t>The group chairs will maintain a web page containing a list of all
	 of the drafts currently under consideration by the group. These
	 will simply be pointers into the I-D repository - our drafts will
	 have the same 6 month expiry period.
      </t>
      <section title="Copyright">
	      <t>All drafts published through the I-D and RFC Editor process must already
         license certain rights to the IETF, as described in section 4 of BCP 78.
         Documents published as part of the AFS standardisation process must also
         grant certain additional licenses, and include the following copyright
	 statement.
     </t>
     <figure>
       <artwork>

   Copyright (C) &lt;author(s)&gt; (year).

   By submitting this Internet-Draft, I accept the provisions of
   Section 4 of BCP 78.

   In addition, by submitting this Internet-Draft, to the extent that
   this Internet-Draft or any portion thereof is protected by copyright
   and other rights of authorship, the Contributor, and each named
   co-Contributor, and the organization he or she represents or is
   sponsored by (if any) grant a perpetual, irrevocable, non-exclusive,
   royalty-free, world-wide right and license to any and all persons
   under all intellectual property rights in this Internet-Draft:

   (A) to copy, publish, display, and distribute this Internet-Draft,

   (B) to prepare or allow the preparation of translations of this
       Internet-Draft into languages other than English,

   (C) to prepare and distribute derivative works (other than
       translations) that are based on or incorporate all or part of
       this Internet-Draft, or comment upon it, the license to such
       derivative works not granting to any party any more rights than
       the license to this Internet-Draft,

   (D) to reproduce any trademarks, service marks, or trade names
       which are included in this Internet-Draft solely in connection
       with the reproduction, distribution, or publication of this
       Internet-Draft and derivative works thereof as permitted by
       this paragraph and/or by section 4 of BCP 78, and

   (E) to extract, copy, publish, display, distribute, modify, and
       incorporate into other works, for any purpose, any executable
       code or code fragments that are included in this Internet-Draft,
       it being understood that the licenses granted under this
       paragraph (E) shall not be deemed to grant any right under any
       patent, patent application, or other similar intellectual 
       property right disclosed by me.

   This document and the information contained herein are provided on an
   "AS IS" basis and THE CONTRIBUTOR, THE ORGANIZATION HE/SHE REPRESENTS
   OR IS SPONSORED BY (IF ANY), THE INTERNET SOCIETY, THE IETF TRUST,
   AND THE INTERNET ENGINEERING TASK FORCE DISCLAIM ALL WARRANTIES,
   EXPRESS OR IMPLIED, INCLUDING BUT NOT LIMITED TO ANY WARRANTY THAT
   THE USE OF THE INFORMATION HEREIN WILL NOT INFRINGE ANY RIGHTS OR ANY
   IMPLIED WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY OR FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR
   PURPOSE.
          </artwork>
      </figure>
      <t>The above text may be directly incorporated into the Copyright section of
	 the document, or by incorporating a reference to this document.</t>
      <figure>
	 <artwork>
   Copyright (C) &lt;author(s)&gt; (year).
   
   By submitting this Internet-Draft, I accept the provisions of 
   Section 4 of BCP 78, and of Section 2.3.1.1 of the AFS 
   standardisation document
	 </artwork>
      </figure>
      </section>
      </section>

      <section title="The Registrar">
      <t>The registrar maintains a register of protocol constants for the AFS 
	 protocols. A number of registries already exist for the
	 core AFS protocols, and additional registries may be added as required
	 by extensions to the protocol. The registrar's function is to maintain
	 these lists for the community - to make them publicly available, and
	 to allocate entries as required.</t>

      <t>Unlike the rest of the systems outlined in this document, the AFS community
	 has had the benefit of the services of a volunteer registrar for a 
	 number of years. What follows proposes changes in order to formalise
         the relationship between registrar and standardisation group, and
         to deal with single points of failure.</t> 

      <t>The registrar would allocate protocol constants on demand. These registrations 
	 may be for 'experimental' items, 'standard' items, or for private extensions. 
	 Both experimental and standard items are allocated by documents advancing 
	 through our standardisation process. Private extensions would be allocated 
	 entries upon request. Private extensions do not require public documentation.
      </t>

      <t>In addition to these allocation roles, the registrar will serve
	 as a vote counter of last resort, for chair elections where no 
	 incumbent chair is available to perform the count.</t>

      <t>This combination of roles makes it difficult for a single individual
	 to serve as registrar. Instead, it is proposed to expand the role of
	 registrar to include a number of individuals from the community.</t>

      <t>The registrars set their own procedures for
	 adding new registrars, removing registrars, and determining the
	 size of the group.  In the event there are no registrars, a new
	 group will be formed consisting of one representative from each
	 active AFS implementation and one representative chosen by the
	 chairs.</t>

      <t>The registries themselves will be held as a set of collaboratively
	 editable documents, to which all of the registrars will have equal
	 access.
	 The registrars must make the current set of registries available to
	 the community, including versions in the preferred source form.</t>

     </section>

      <section title="Document States and Series">
	<t>Documents may be either a draft, experimental, or a standard.
	   Advancing between these states requires the consensus of the 
	   standardisation group, and only experimental and standard items
	   may have protocol code points assigned to them. (Private extensions
   	   may also have code points, but as these are not part of the
   	   standardisation process, we won't consider them further here)</t>

        <t>For a document to advance to 'standard', at least one implementation
           must exist of all of the protocol elements defined within the
	   document - these implementations do not have to all be within the
	   same product.</t>

        <t>As noted earlier, the group chairs are responsible for maintaining 
           lists of documents at each of these stages. Draft documents are
	   held within the IETF's Internet Drafts repository, as are 
	   experimental	documents. It is the responsibility of the group chairs
	   to ensure that experimental documents which are still being actively
	   worked upon are kept current within the internet draft collection.
        </t>

	<t>The intention is that standard documents will be submitted by their 
	   authors to the RFC-Editor
	   as an individual submission. Upon successful completion of the
	   RFC-Editor process, the resulting RFCs should be linked to by
	   the group chairs, and referenced by the relevant registries.
           Whilst this usage appears consistent with the individual submission
	   process, it needs to be confirmed that the RFC Editor is happy with this.
        </t>
       </section>

       <section title="Decision making and consensus">
	 <t>Decisions of the standardisation group are achieved by rough
	    consensus, as determined by the group chairs. It should be noted
	    that, beyond determining consensus, the chairs have no veto or
	    casting vote. In fact, they should be careful to avoid their
	    own personal beliefs interfering when judging the opinion of
	    the group. </t>
         <t>For document actions, the document authors request that the
            chair determine whether there is consensus within the group.
	    The chair issues a consensus call, with a clear cut off point
	    (typically 1 week) during which group participants are invited
	    to review the document, and express their opinions both for and against.
	    At the end of this period, the chair should have amassed
	    sufficient information to determine whether there is a rough
	    consensus for the document to advance.
	 </t>
       </section>
     </section>

     <section title="Patents">
       <t>The use of the Internet-Draft process, and of the RFC Editor Individual
	  Submissions process for document publishing, means that the terms
	  of BCP-79 apply with respect to patent notification.
       </t>
     </section>

     <section title="Relationship with the foundation">
       <t>The day to day operation of the standardisation group is independent of 
	  the foundation.</t>
     </section>
   </section>

   <section title="Bootstrapping the Process">
     <t>Should the proposals in this document be accepted, we need to consider
	how to bootstrap the process. I propose that once consensus has been
	reached on this document, we elect two chairs in the manner described
	above, with a start date to be determined. The chair with the 
	lower number of votes would serve a 1 year term, the chair with the
	higher number, 2 years as normal. </t>

     <t>The registrars would be initially comprised of the
	current registrar, plus a representative from all of the currently
	available AFS implementations (IBM, OpenAFS, kAFS and Arla) who wish
	to participate.</t>
 
     <t>A document describing the standardisation process would be the first
	task for the resulting group and would be used to pilot the entire
	document publishing process.
     </t>
   </section>
   <section title="Security Considerations">
     <t>As this memo describes a process, rather than a protocol, no security considerations
	are raised by its contents.</t>
   </section>
   <section title="IANA Considerations">
     <t>This memo includes no request to IANA.</t>
   </section>
</middle>
<back>
<references>
  <reference anchor='RFC2026'>
    <front>
      <title abbrev='Internet Standards Process'>
        The Internet Standards Process -- Revision 3
      </title>
      <author initials='S.' surname='Bradner' fullname='Scott O. Bradner'>
        <organization>Harvard University</organization>
        <address>
          <postal>
            <street>1350 Mass. Ave.</street>
            <city>Cambridge</city>
            <region>MA</region>
            <code>02138</code>
	    <country>US</country>
          </postal>
          <phone>+1 617 495 3864</phone>
          <email>sob@harvard.edu</email>
        </address>
      </author>
      <date year='1996' month='October' />
      <abstract>
        <t>This memo documents the process used by the Internet community 
           for the standardisation of protocols and procedures.  It defines
	   the stages in the standardisation process, the requirements for 
	   moving a document between stages and the types of documents 
	   used during this process.  It also addresses the intellectual 
	   property rights and copyright issues associated with the 
	   standards process.
	</t>
      </abstract>
    </front>
    <seriesInfo name='BCP' value='9' />
    <seriesInfo name='RFC' value='2026' />
    <format type='TXT' octets='86731' target='ftp://ftp.isi.edu/in-notes/rfc2026.txt' />
  </reference>
  <reference anchor='RFC3979'>
    <front>
      <title>Intellectual Property Rights in IETF Technology</title>
      <author initials='S.' surname='Bradner' fullname='S. Bradner'>
	<organization />
      </author>
      <date year='2005' month='March' />
      <abstract>
        <t>The IETF policies about Intellectual Property Rights (IPR), such as patent 
	   rights, relative to technologies developed in the IETF are designed to ensure 
	   that IETF working groups and participants have as much information about any 
	   IPR constraints on a technical proposal as possible.  The policies are also 
	   intended to benefit the Internet community and the public at large, while 
	   respecting the legitimate rights of IPR holders.  This memo details the 
	   IETF policies concerning IPR related to technology worked on within the IETF.  
	   It also describes the objectives that the policies are designed to meet.  
	   This memo updates RFC 2026 and, with RFC 3978, replaces Section 10 of RFC 2026.  
	   This memo also updates paragraph 4 of Section 3.2 of RFC 2028, for all purposes,
	   including reference [2] in RFC 2418.  This document specifies an Internet 
	   Best Current Practices for the Internet Community, and requests discussion and 
	   suggestions for improvements.</t>
      </abstract>
    </front>
    <seriesInfo name='BCP' value='79' />
    <seriesInfo name='RFC' value='3979' />
    <format type='TXT' octets='41366' target='ftp://ftp.isi.edu/in-notes/rfc3979.txt' />
  </reference>
  <reference anchor="ID-Guide" target="http://www.ietf.org/ietf/1id-guidelines.html">
    <front>
      <title>I-D Guidelines</title>
      <author initials='B.' surname='Fenner (for the IESG)' 
	      fullname="B. Fenner (for the IESG)">
        <organization>Arastra, Inc.</organization>
      </author>
      <date year='2008' month='February' day='27' />
    </front>
    <format type='HTML' target="http://www.ietf.org/ietf/1id-guidelines.html" />
  </reference>
</references>
</back>
</rfc>

