<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">

<rfc ipr="trust200902"
     docName="draft-keranen-ipv6day-measurements-03"
     category="info">

<?rfc toc="yes"?> <?rfc symrefs="yes"?> <?rfc autobreaks="yes"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?> <?rfc compact="yes"?> <?rfc subcompact="no"?>

<front>

  <title abbrev="IPv6 Day Measurements">Some Measurements on World
  IPv6 Day from End-User Perspective</title>

    <author fullname="Ari Keranen" initials="A." surname="Keranen">
      <organization>Ericsson</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street/>
          <city>Jorvas</city>
          <code>02420</code>
          <country>Finland</country>
        </postal>
        <email>ari.keranen@ericsson.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author initials="J" surname="Arkko" fullname="Jari Arkko">
      <organization>Ericsson</organization>
      <address>
	<postal>
	  <street/>
	  <city>Jorvas</city> <code>02420</code>
	  <country>Finland</country>
	</postal>
	<email>jari.arkko@piuha.net</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date year="2012" />

    <keyword>IPv6</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t> During the World IPv6 Day on June 8th, 2011, several key
      content providers enabled their networks to offer both IPv4 and
      IPv6 services. Hundreds of organizations participated in this
      effort, and in the months and weeks leading up to the event
      worked hard on preparing their networks to support this event.
      The event was largely unnoticed by the general public, which is
      a good thing since it means that no major problems were
      detected. For the Internet, however, there was a major change on
      such a small timescale. This memo discusses measurements that
      the authors made from the perspective of an end-user with good
      IPv4 and IPv6 connectivity. Our measurements include the number
      of most popular networks providing AAAA records for their
      service as well as delay and connection failure statistics. </t>
    </abstract>

</front>

<middle>

<section anchor="intro" title="Introduction">

  <t> Many large content providers participated in World IPv6 Day on
  June 8, 2011. On that day, IPv6 <xref target="RFC2460"/> was enabled
  by default for 24 hours on numerous networks and sites that
  previously supported only IPv4. The aim was to identify any
  remaining issues with widespread IPv6 usage in these networks. Most
  of the potential problems associated with using IPv6 are, after all,
  of a practical nature, such as: ensuring that the necessary
  components have IPv6 turned on; that configurations are correct; and
  that any implementation bugs have been removed.</t>

  <t> Some content providers have been reluctant to enable IPv6. The
  reasons for this include delays for applications attempting to
  connect over broken IPv6 links before falling back to IPv4 <xref
  target="RFC6555"/>, and unreliable IPv6
  connectivity. Bad IPv6 routing has been behind many of the
  problems. Among the causes are broken 6to4 tunneling protocol <xref
  target="RFC3056"/> connectivity, experimental IPv6 setups that are
  untested and unmonitored, and configuration problems with
  firewalls. The situation is improving as more users and operators
  put IPv6 to use and fix the problems that emerge.</t>

  <t> World IPv6 Day event was largely unnoticed by the general
  public, which is a good thing since it means that no major problems
  were detected.  Existing IPv4 connectivity was not damaged by IPv6
  and also new IPv6 connectivity worked as expected in vast majority
  of cases. For the Internet, however, there was a major change on
  such a small timescale. This memo discusses measurements that the
  authors made from the perspective of an end-user with well-working
  IPv4 and IPv6 connectivity. Our measurements include the number of
  most popular networks providing AAAA records for their service as
  well as delay and connection failure statistics.</t>

  <t> The rest of this memo is structured as follows. <xref
  target="goals"/> discusses the goals of our measurements, <xref
  target="method"/> describes our measurement methodology, <xref
  target="results"/> gives our preliminary results, and <xref
  target="concl"/> draws some conclusions.</t>

</section>

<section anchor="goals" title="Motivation and Goals">

  <t> Practical IPv6 deployment plans benefit from accurate
  information about the extent to which IPv6 can be used for
  communication, and how its characteristics differ from those of
  IPv4. For instance, operators planning to deploy dual-stack
  networking may wish to understand what fraction of their traffic
  would move to IPv6. This information is useful for estimating the
  necessary capacity to deal with the IPv6 traffic and impacts to the
  operator's IPv4 infrastructure or carrier-grade NAT devices as their
  traffic is reduced. Network owners also wish to understand the
  extent to which they can expect different delay characteristics or
  problems with IPv6 connectivity. The goals of our measurements were
  to help with these topics by answering the following questions:

  <list style="symbols">
    <t> What fraction of most popular Internet sites offer AAAA
    records? How did the World IPv6 Day change the situation?</t>
    <t> How do the traffic characteristics differ between IPv4 and
    IPv6 on sites offering AAAA records? Are the connection failure
    rates similar? How are RTTs impacted? </t>
  </list></t>

  <t> There have been many measurements about some of these aspects
  from a service provider perspective, such as the Google studies on
  which end users have broken connectivity towards them. Our
  measurements start from a different angle, by assuming good
  dual-stack connectivity at the measurement end, and then probing the
  rest of the Internet to understand, for instance, how likely there
  are to be IPv6 connectivity problems, or what the delay differences
  are between IPv4 and IPv6. Similar studies have been performed by
  the Comcast IPv6 Adoption Monitor <xref target="IPv6Monitor"/> and
  RIPE NCC <xref target="RIPEv6Day"/>. </t>

</section>

<section anchor="method" title="Measurement Methodology">

  <t> We used the top 10,000 sites of the Alexa 1 million most popular
  sites list <xref target="Alexa"/> from June 1st 2011. For each
  domain name in the list, we performed DNS queries with different
  host names. For IPv4 addresses (A records) we used host name "www"
  and also performed a query with just the domain name. For IPv6
  addresses (AAAA records) we used also different combinations of host
  names that have been used for IPv6 sites, namely "www6", "ipv6",
  "v6", "ipv6.www", "www.ipv6", "v6.www", and "www.v6". </t>
    
  <t> All DNS queries were initiated in the order listed above (first
  "www" and just the domain name for A-records, then "www", domain
  name, and different IPv6-host names for AAAA records) but the
  queries were done in parallel (i.e., without waiting for the
  previous query to finish). The first response for A and AAAA records
  and the corresponding host names were recorded. The queries had 3
  second re-transmission timeout and if there wasn't any response for
  10 seconds, all remaining queries for the site were canceled. We
  used a custom-made Perl script and the Net::DNS <xref
  target="net-dns"/> module for the DNS queries. </t>
    
  <t> The measurement script used a bind9 DNS server running on the
  same host as was performing the measurement. The DNS cache of the
  server was flushed before each measurement run in order to detect
  the changes in the DNS records in real-time. The host, and thus the
  DNS server, was not part of DNS IPv6 whitelisting agreements. </t>
    
  <t> After obtaining IP addresses for the site, if a site had both A
  and AAAA records, a simple C program was used to create TCP
  connections to the port 80 (HTTP) simultaneously using both IPv4 and
  IPv6 to the (first) IP addresses discovered from the DNS. The
  connection setup was repeated up to 10 times, giving up after the
  first failed attempt (but only after normal TCP
  re-transmissions). The connection setup delay was measured by
  recording the time immediately before and after the connect system
  call. The host used for measurements is a regular Linux PC with
  2.6.32 version kernel and dual-stack Internet connection via
  Ethernet. </t>

  <t> The measurements were started one week before the World IPv6 Day
  (on Wednesday, June 1st, 17:30 UTC) and were running until July
  11th, once every three hours. One test run takes from two to two and
  a half hours to complete. </t>

  <t> The accuracy and generality of the measurement results is
  limited by several factors. While we ran the tests in three
  different sites, most of the results discussed in this document
  present snapshots of the situation from just one measurement point,
  the Ericsson Research Finland premises, near Helsinki. Also, since
  one measurement run takes quite a long time, the network
  characteristics and DNS records may change even during a single
  run. The first DNS response was used for the TCP connectivity tests
  and this selection may result in selection of a non-optimal host;
  yet, a slight preference is given to the "www" and only-domain-name
  records since their queries were started before the others. While
  the host performing the measurements was otherwise idle, the local
  network was in regular office use during the measurements. The
  connectivity setup delay is collected in user space, with regular,
  non real-time, kernel implementation, resulting in small
  inaccuracies in the timing information. </t>

</section>

<section anchor="results" title="Measurement Results">

<section title="DNS AAAA Records">
  <t> The number of top 10,000 sites with AAAA DNS records before,
  during, and after the World IPv6 Day, is shown in <xref
  target="DNS-top10k"/>. The measurements performed during the World
  IPv6 Day are shown on the light gray background. </t>

  <t> When the measurements began on June 1st, there were 245 sites
  (2.45%) of the top 10,000 sites with both A and AAAA record. During
  the following days the number of such sites slowly increased,
  reaching 306 sites at the measurement that was started 22:30 UTC on
  June 7th, the evening before the World IPv6 Day. When the World IPv6
  Day officially started, the following measurement (1:30 UTC)
  recorded 383 sites, and the next one 472 sites. During the day the
  number of sites with AAAA records peaked at 491 (4.91% of the
  measured 10,000 sites) at 19:30 UTC. </t>

  <t> When the World IPv6 Day was over, the number of AAAA records
  dropped nearly as fast as it had increased just 24 hours
  earlier. However, the number of sites stabilized around 310 and did
  not drop below 300 since, resulting in over 3% of the top 10,000
  sites still having AAAA records at the end of our measurements. </t>

  <t> While 274 sites had IPv6 enabled in their DNS for some of the
  tested host names one day before the World IPv6 Day, only 116 had it
  for the "www" host name that is commonly used when accessing a web
  site. The number of "www" host names with AAAA records more than
  tripled during the World IPv6 Day reaching 374 sites for 3
  consecutive measurement runs (i.e., for at least 6 hours). Also the
  number of AAAA records for the "www" host name dropped steeply after
  the day and remained at around 160 sites since. </t>

  <t> Similar but more pronounced trends can be seen if only top 100
  of the most popular sites are taken into considerations, as show in
  <xref target="DNS-top100"/>.  Here, the number of sites with some of
  the tested host names having an AAAA record was initially 14, jumped
  to 36 during the day, and eventually dropped to 13. Also, while none
  of the top 100 sites apparently had an AAAA record for their "www"
  host name before and after the World IPv6 day, during the day the
  number peaked at 30. Thus, roughly one third of the 100 most popular
  sites had IPv6 enabled for the World IPv6 Day. </t>

  <t> Two other test sites in Sweden and Canada experienced similar
  trends with the DNS records. However, one of the sites used an
  external DNS server that was part of whitelisting agreements. There
  the number of sites with AAAA records before the World IPv6 Day was
  already higher (above 400) and hence the impact of the day was
  smaller as the amount of sites increased to same numbers as seen by
  the test site in Finland. With the whitelisted DNS server the level
  of sites remained above 450 after the day. </t>

</section>

<section title="TCP Connection Setup">

  <t> To test whether the IP addresses given by the DNS actually
  provide connectivity to the web site, and if there is any difference
  in the connection setup delay and failure rates with IPv4 and IPv6,
  we attempted to create TCP connections for all domains that
  contained both A and AAAA DNS records. The fraction of sites for
  which the first DNS response gave addresses that were not accessible
  with TCP to port 80 over IPv4 or IPv6 is shown in <xref
  target="TCP-fails"/>.
  </t>

  <t> There is a baseline failure rate with IPv4 around 1-3% that is
  fairly static throughout the test period. For hosts with AAAA
  records, the fraction of inaccessible sites was much higher: in the
  beginning up to one fourth of the tested hosts did not respond to
  TCP connection attempts. Much of this was likely due to the various
  test sites with different "IPv6 prefixes" (as discussed in <xref
  target="method"/>); in the first run more than half of the tested
  sites with AAAA records used them for the first DNS response. Also,
  some of the hosts may not even be supposed to be accessed with HTTP
  but provide AAAA records for other purposes while some sites had
  clear configuration errors, such as localhost or link-local IPv6
  addresses. </t>

  <t> As the World IPv6 Day came closer, the number of inaccessible
  IPv6 sites decreased slowly and the number of sites with AAAA
  records increased at the same time, resulting in the failure ratio
  dropping to roughly 20% before the day. During the day the number of
  IPv6 sites increased rapidly but also the number of failures
  decreased and hence, at the end of the day, the failure ratio
  dropped to just above 10%. After the World IPv6 Day when many of the
  participating IPv6 hosts were taken off-line, the fraction of failed
  sites for IPv6 increased. However, since there was no increase in
  the absolute number of failed sites, the fraction of inaccessible
  sites remained at a lower level, between 15% and 20%, than before
  the day. </t>

</section>

<section title="TCP Connection Delays">

  <t> For sites that were accessible with both IPv4 and IPv6, we
  measured the time difference between establishing a TCP connection
  with IPv4 and IPv6. We took the median (as defined in Section 11.3
  of <xref target="RFC2330"/>) of the time differences of all 10
  connections, and then median and mean (of the median) over all
  sites; the result is shown in <xref
  target="timediff"/>. </t>

  <t> In general, the delay differences are small: median of medians
  stays less than 3ms off from zero (i.e., IPv4 and IPv6 delays being
  equal) and even the mean, which is more sensitive to outliers, stays
  most of the time within +/- 5ms; with the greatest spikes reaching
  to roughly -15ms (i.e., mean of median IPv6 delays being 15ms larger
  than for IPv4 delays). Closer inspection of the results shows that
  the spikes are often caused by only one or a handful of sites with
  bad connectivity and multiple re-transmissions of TCP SYN and ACK
  packets resulting in connection setup delays an order of magnitude
  larger. </t>

  <t> Surprisingly the median delay for IPv6 connections is in most
  cases equal to or smaller than the IPv4 delay, but during the World
  IPv6 Day, the IPv6 delays increased slightly and became (as median)
  slower than their IPv4 counterparts. One reason for such an effect
  was that some of the sites that enabled IPv6 for the World IPv6 Day,
  had extremely low, less than 10ms, IPv4 delay (e.g., due to Content
  Delivery Network (CDN) provider hosting the IPv4 site), but
  "regular", over hundred millisecond, delay for the IPv6 host. </t>

  <t> More detailed analysis of the TCP connection setup delay
  differences, and the reasons behind them, is left for future
  work. </t>

</section>

</section>

<section anchor="concl" title="Conclusions">

  <t> The World IPv6 Day had a very visible impact to the availability
  of content over IPv6, particularly when considering the top 100
  content providers. It is difficult to find other examples of bigger
  one day swings in some characteristic of the Internet. However, the
  impact on end users was small, given that when dual-stack works
  correctly it should not be visible at the user level and that IPv6
  availability for end users themselves is small.</t>

  <t> The key conclusions are as follows:

  <list style="symbols">

    <t> The day caused a large jump in the number of content providers
    providing AAAA DNS records on that day.</t>

    <t> The day caused a smaller but apparently permanent increase in
    the number of content providers supporting AAAA.</t>

    <t> Large and sudden swings in the relative amount of IPv4 vs. IPv6
    traffic are possible merely by supporting a dual-stack access
    network and having a few large content providers offer their
    service either globally or to this particular network over
    IPv6.</t>

    <t> Large fraction of sites that published AAAA records for a name
    under their domain (be it "www" or "www6" or something else) were
    actually not responding to TCP SYN requests on IPv6. This fraction
    is far higher than that which we've seen in our previous
    measurements, and we are still determining why that is the
    case. Measurement errors or problems on our side of the network
    cannot be ruled out at this stage. In any case, it is also clear
    that as new sites join, incomplete or in-progress configurations
    create more connectivity problems in the IPv6 Internet than we've
    seen before. Other measurements are needed to verify what the
    general level IPv6 connectivity is to addresses publicly listed in
    AAAA records. </t>

    <t> Even if the overall level of connection failures was high,
    activities on and around the IPv6 day appear to have caused a
    significant permanent drop in the number of failures. </t>
    
    <t> When IPv6 and IPv4 connectivity were both available, the delay
    characteristics appear very similar. In other words, most of the
    providers that made IPv6 connectivity available appear to provide
    a production quality network.  TCP connection setup delay
    differences due to RTT differences between IPv4 and IPv6
    connections are in general low. In the remaining differences in
    our measurements, random packet loss plays a major role. However,
    some sites can experience considerable differences simply because
    of different content distribution mechanisms used for IPv4 and
    IPv6 content. </t>
  </list>

  <t> It is promising that the amount of most popular Internet content
  on IPv6 was surprisingly high, roughly one third of top 100 sites
  (during the IPv6 day or with whitelisting enabled).  However, other
  content on the Internet forms a long tail that is harder to move to
  IPv6. For instance, only 3% of the 10,000 most popular web sites
  provided their content over IPv6 before the IPv6 day. On a positive
  note, the top 100 sites form a very large part of overall Internet
  traffic <xref target="Labovitz"/> and thus even the top sites moving
  to IPv6 could represent a significant fraction of Internet traffic
  on IPv6. However, this requires that users are enabled to use IPv6
  in their access networks. We believe that this should be the goal of
  future global IPv6 efforts. </t>

  </t>

</section>


<section anchor="seccons" title='Security Considerations'>

   <t>Security issues have not been discussed in this memo.</t>

</section>

<section anchor="ianacons" title='IANA Considerations'>

   <t>This memo has no IANA implications.</t>

</section>


</middle>
<back>


<references title="Normative References">

  <reference anchor="timediff" target="http://users.piuha.net/akeranen/drafts/v6day/mda.pdf">
    <front>
      <title>TCP connection setup delay differences [RFC editor:
      please change the references to the graphs to refer to the PDF
      version of the document]</title>
      <author initials='A.' surname='Keranen' fullname='A. Keranen'>
	<organization>Ericsson</organization>
      </author>
      <date year="2011" month="June"/>
    </front>
  </reference>


  <reference anchor="DNS-top10k" target="http://users.piuha.net/akeranen/drafts/v6day/v6sites.pdf">
    <front>
      <title>Number of sites with AAAA DNS records in the top 10,000 most popular sites</title>
      <author initials='A.' surname='Keranen' fullname='A. Keranen'>
	<organization>Ericsson</organization>
      </author>
      <date year="2011" month="June"/>
    </front>
  </reference>

  <reference anchor="DNS-top100" target="http://users.piuha.net/akeranen/drafts/v6day/v6sites-top100.pdf">
    <front>
      <title>Number of sites with AAAA DNS records in the top 100 most popular sites</title>
      <author initials='A.' surname='Keranen' fullname='A. Keranen'>
	<organization>Ericsson</organization>
      </author>
      <date year="2011" month="June"/>
    </front>
  </reference>

  <reference anchor="TCP-fails" target="http://users.piuha.net/akeranen/drafts/v6day/tcp-fails.pdf">
    <front>
      <title>TCP connection setup failure ratio (for the first DNS response)</title>
      <author initials='A.' surname='Keranen' fullname='A. Keranen'>
	<organization>Ericsson</organization>
      </author>
      <date year="2011" month="June"/>
    </front>
  </reference>

</references>

<references title="Informative References">

  <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2330.xml"?>
  <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2460.xml"?>
  <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3056.xml"?>
  <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6555.xml"?>

  <reference anchor='net-dns' target="http://www.net-dns.org/">
    <front>
      <title>Net::DNS</title>
      <author initials="M." surname="Fuhr"/>
    </front>
  </reference>

  <reference anchor='IPv6Monitor' target="http://ipv6monitor.comcast.net">
    <front>
      <title>IPv6 Adoption Monitor</title>
      <author>
	<organization>Comcast</organization>
      </author>
      <author>
	<organization>University of Pennsylvania</organization>
      </author>
    </front>
  </reference>

  <reference anchor='RIPEv6Day' target="http://v6day.ripe.net/">
    <front>
      <title>World IPv6 Day Measurements</title>
      <author>
	<organization>RIPE NCC</organization>
      </author>
    </front>
  </reference>

  <reference anchor='Alexa' target="http://s3.amazonaws.com/alexa-static/top-1m.csv.zip">
    <front>
      <title>Alexa Top 1,000,000 Sites</title>
      <author>
	<organization>Alexa the Web Information Company</organization>
      </author>
    </front>
  </reference>

  <reference anchor='Labovitz'>
    <front>
      <title>Internet Inter-Domain Traffic</title>
      <author initials="C." surname="Labovitz"/>
      <author initials="S." surname="Iekel-Johnson"/>
      <author initials="D." surname="McPherson"/>
      <author initials="J." surname="Oberheide"/>
      <author initials="F."surname="Jahanian"/>
      <date year="2010" month="August"/>
    </front>
    <seriesInfo name="Proceedings of ACM SIGCOMM" value="2010"/>
  </reference>

</references>

<section anchor="ack" title='Acknowledgments'>
  
  <t> The authors would like to thank Suresh Krishnan, Fredrik
  Garneij, Lorenzo Colitti, Jason Livingood, Alain Durand, Emile Aben,
  Jan Melen, and Tero Kauppinen for interesting discussions in this
  problem space. Thanks also to Tom Petch and Bob Hinden for thorough
  reviews and many helpful comments. </t>

</section>

</back>
</rfc>
