<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc iprnotified="no" ?>
<?rfc strict="no" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="yes" ?>
<rfc category="info" docName="draft-mraihi-totp-timebased-05.txt" ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="HOTPTimeBased">TOTP: Time-based One-time Password Algorithm</title>

    <author fullname="David M'Raihi" initials="D." surname="M'Raihi">
      <organization>Verisign, Inc.</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>685 E. Middlefield Road</street>

          <city>Mountain View</city>

          <region>CA</region>

          <code>94043</code>

          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>

        <email>dmraihi@verisign.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
	
    <author fullname="Salah Machani" initials="S." surname="Machani">
      <organization>Diversinet Corp.</organization>
    
    <address>
        <postal>
          <street>2225 Sheppard Avenue East, Suite 1801</street>

          <city>Toronto</city>

          <region>Ontario</region>

          <code>M2J 5C2</code>

          <country>Canada</country>
        </postal>

        <email>smachani@diversinet.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Mingliang Pei" initials="M." surname="Pei">
      <organization>Verisign, Inc.</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>685 E. Middlefield Road</street>

          <city>Mountain View</city>

          <region>CA</region>

          <code>94043</code>

          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>

        <email>mpei@verisign.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
         
    <author fullname="Johan Rydell" initials="J." surname="Rydell">
      <organization>Portwise, Inc.</organization>
    
    <address>
        <postal>
          <street>275 Hawthorne Ave, Suite 119</street>

          <city>Palo Alto</city>

          <region>CA</region>

          <code>94301</code>

          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>

        <email>johan.rydell@portwise.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    
    <date day="8" month="March" year="2010" />

    <area>General</area>

    <workgroup>Internet Engineering Task Force</workgroup>

    <abstract>
      <t>This document describes an extension of one-time password (OTP) algorithm, namely
      the HAMC-Based One-Time Password (HOTP) Algorithm as defined in RFC 4226,  
      to support time-based moving factor. The HOTP algorithm specifies an event
      based OTP algorithm where the moving factor is an event counter. The present work 
      bases the moving factor on a time value.  A time-based variant of the OTP algorithm 
      provides short-lived OTP values, which are desirable for enhanced security.</t>
      
      <t>The proposed algorithm can be used across a wide range of network applications ranging from 
      remote Virtual Private Network (VPN) access, Wi-Fi network logon to transaction-oriented Web
      applications. The authors believe that a common and shared algorithm will facilitate adoption of 
      two-factor authentication on the Internet by enabling interoperability across commercial and 
      open-source implementations.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <!-- ////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////// -->

    <section anchor="Section-Introduction" title="Introduction">
      <section title="Scope">
        <t>This document describes an extension of one-time password (OTP) algorithm 
        HOTP as defined in <xref target="RFC4226"></xref> to support time based moving factor.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section title="Background">
        <t>As defined in <xref target="RFC4226"></xref> the HOTP algorithm is based on the HMAC-SHA-1 algorithm, as specified in <xref target="RFC2104"></xref> applied to an increasing counter value representing the message in the HMAC computation.</t>

		<t>Basically, the output of the HMAC-SHA-1 calculation is truncated to obtain user-friendly values:</t>
                              <t>HOTP(K,C) = Truncate(HMAC-SHA-1(K,C))</t>
		<t>where Truncate represents the function that can convert an HMAC-SHA-1 value into an HOTP value. <vspace blankLines="1" /></t>
		
		<t>TOTP is the time-based variant of this algorithm where a value T derived from a time reference and a time step replaces the counter C in the HOTP computation.</t>

		<t>The default HMAC-SHA-1 function could be replaced by HMAC-SHA-256 or HMAC-SHA-512 to leverage HMAC implementations based on SHA-256 or SHA-512 hash functions.</t>              
      </section>
    </section>

    <!-- ////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////// -->

    <section anchor="terms" title="Notation and Terminology">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
      document are to be interpreted as described in <xref target="RFC2119"></xref></t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="AlgorithmRequirements" title="Algorithm Requirements">
                
      	<t> This section summarizes the requirements taken into account for designing the TOTP algorithm. </t>
        
    	<t> R1 - The prover (e.g. token, soft token) and verifier (authentication or validation server) MUST have access to the Unix Time </t>
    
    	<t> R2 - The prover and verifier MUST either share a same secret or the knowledge of a secret transformation to generate a shared secret </t>
 
    	<t> R3 - The algorithm MUST use HOTP [RFC4226] as a key building block. </t>
     
    	<t> R4 - The prover and verifier MUST use the same time step value X. </t>
     
    	<t> R5 - There MUST be a unique secret (key) for each prover. </t>
    
    	<t> R6 - The keys SHOULD be randomly generated or derived using a key derivation algorithms. </t>
    
    	<t> R7 - The keys MAY be stored in a tamper-resistant device and SHOULD be protected against unauthorized access and usage. </t>
    
    	<t> R8 - The TOTP algorithm SHOULD be used for online application. </t>
      
    </section>

    <!-- ////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////// -->
   
    <section anchor="Section-Time-based-Variant" title="TOTP Algorithm">

        <t>This variant of the HOTP algorithm specifies the calculation of a one-time 
        password value, based on a representation of the counter as a time factor.</t>

        <section anchor="Notations" title="Notations">
        	<t>- X represents the time step in seconds (default value X = 30 seconds) and is a system parameter;</t>
			<t>- T0 is the Unix time to start counting time steps (default value is 0, Unix epoch) and is also a system parameter.</t>
		</section>

    	<section title="Description">
    		<t> Basically, we define TOTP as TOTP = HOTP(K, T) where T is an integer and represents the number of time steps between 
    		the initial counter time T0 and the current Unix time (i.e. the number of seconds elapsed since midnight UTC of January 1, 1970).</t>
			
    		<t> More specifically T = (Current Unix time - T0) / X where:</t>
			<t>- X represents the time step in seconds (default value X = 30 seconds) and is a system parameter;</t>
			<t>- T0 is the Unix time to start counting time steps (default value is 0, Unix epoch) and is also a system parameter;</t>
			<t>- The default floor function is used in the computation. For example, with T0 = 0 and time step X = 30, T = 1 if the current 
			Unix time is 59 seconds and T = 2 if the current Unix time is 60 seconds.</t>
	    </section>
    
	</section>
    
    <!-- ////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////// -->

    <section anchor="Section-Security" title="Security Considerations">
      <section title="General">
  
    <t> The security and strength of this algorithm depends on the 
    properties of the underlying building block HOTP, which is a 
    construction based on HMAC <xref target="RFC2104"></xref> using
    SHA-1 as the hash function. </t> 
     
    <t> The conclusion of the security analysis detailed in 
    <xref target="RFC4226"></xref> is that, for all practical 
    purposes, the outputs of the dynamic truncation on distinct 
    inputs are uniformly and independently distributed strings. </t>
     
    <t> The analysis demonstrates that the best possible attack against the 
    HOTP function is the brute force attack. </t>

    <t> As indicated in the algorithm requirement section, keys SHOULD be 
    chosen at random or using a cryptographically strong pseudo-random 
    generator properly seeded with a random value. </t> 
    
    <t> Keys SHOULD be of the length of the HMAC output to facilitate
    interoperability. </t>
    
    <t> We RECOMMEND following the recommendations in 
    <xref target="RFC4086"></xref> for all pseudo-random and 
    random generations. The pseudo-random numbers used for
    generating the keys SHOULD successfully pass the 
    randomness test specified in <xref target="CN"></xref> or
    a similar well-recognized test. </t>
     
    <t> All the communications SHOULD take place over a secure 
    channel e.g. SSL/TLS, IPsec connections. </t>
  
    <t> We also RECOMMEND storing the keys securely in the 
    validation system, and more specifically encrypting them using 
    tamper-resistant hardware encryption and exposing them only when 
    required: for example, the key is decrypted when needed to verify 
    an OTP value, and re-encrypted immediately to limit exposure in 
    the RAM for a short period of time. </t>
    
    <t> The key store MUST be in a secure area, to avoid as much as possible 
    direct attack on the validation system and secrets database. 
    Particularly, access to the key material should be limited to programs 
    and processes required by the validation system only. </t>
     
    </section>

      <section title="Validation and Time-step Size">
         <t>An OTP generated within the same Time-step will be the same.  
            When an OTP is received at a validation system, it doesn't 
            know a client's exact timestamp when an OTP was generated. The
            validation system may typically use the timestamp when an OTP is 
            received for OTP comparison. Due to the network latency for an OTP
            to transmit from a requesting application to a validation system
            and user's actual input time of an OTP to a receiving system, such
            timestamp gap between the actual OTP generation time and server's
            receiving time may be large. The receiving time at the validation
            system and the actual OTP generation may not fall within the 
            same Time-step window that produce the same OTP. When an OTP
            is generated at the end of a Time-step window, the receiving time
            most likely falls into the next Time-step window. 
            A validation system SHOULD typically set a policy for an 
            acceptable OTP transmission delay window for validation. 
            The validation system should compare OTPs not only with the 
            receiving timestamp but also the past timesteps that are 
            within the transmission delay. A larger acceptable delay window
            would introduce some OTP attack window. We RECOMMEND that 
            at most one time step is allowed as the network delay. </t>

          <t>The Time-step size has impact on both security and usability.
            A larger Time-step size means larger validity window for an OTP
            to be accepted by a validation system. There are the following
            implications with a larger Time-step size.</t>

         <t>At first, a larger Time-step size exposes larger window for
            attack. When an OTP is generated and exposed to a third party
            before it is consumed, the third party can consume the OTP within
            the Time-step window.</t>

         <t>We RECOMMEND default Time-step size for 30 seconds.</t>

         <t>Secondly, the next different OTP must be generated in the next 
            Time-step window. A user must wait till the clock moves to the
            next Time-step window from the last submission. The waiting time
            may not be exactly the length of Time-step depending on when
            the last OTP was generated. For example, if the last OTP was 
            generated at the half way in a Time-step window, the waiting
            time for the next OTP is half of length of Time-step. In general,
            a larger Time-step window means larger waiting time for
            a user to get the next valid OTP after the last successfully 
            OTP validation. A too large window, for example 10 minutes,
            most probably won't be suitable for typical internet login 
            use cases; a user may not be able to get the next OTP within
            10 minutes and therefore re-login back to the same site
            in 10 minutes. The default Time-step size 30 seconds is 
            recommended.</t>
            
      </section>
     
    </section>

     <section title="Resynchronization">
        <t> Because of possible clock drifts between a client and a validation
            server, we RECOMMEND that the validator be set with a specific
            limit to the number of time steps a prover can be 'out of synch' 
            before being not validated/rejected.</t>
            
        <t> This limit can be set both forward and backwards from the calculated
            time step on receipt of the OTP value. If the time step is 30 seconds 
            as recommended, and the validator is set to only accept 2 time step 
            backwards then the maximum elapsed time drift would be around 
            89 seconds, i.e. 29 seconds in the calculated time step and 60 for 
            two backward time steps. </t>
            
 	<t> This would mean the validator could perform a validation against
 	    the current time and then further two validations for each backward
            step (for a total of 3 validations). Upon successful validation,
            the validation server can record the detected clock drift for
            the token in terms of number of Time-step. When a new OTP
            is received after this step, the validator can validate the OTP with
            current timestamp adjusted with recorded number of Time-step clock 
            drifts for the token.</t>
           
        <t> Also, it is important to note that the longer a prover has not sent 
            an OTP to a validation system, the longer (potentially) the accumulated 
            clock drift between the prover and the verifier. In such cases, 
            the default synchronization may not be proper when the drift exceeds 
            beyond allowed threshold. Additional authentication measures SHOULD 
            be used for the validation system to safely authenticate the prover. </t>
     </section>
    
    <!-- ////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////// -->
    
    <section title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>The OTP algorithm defined in this document can be referred by a URI defined in a 
      separate document. <xref target="ALGP" /> is such an attempt that defines various OTP related algorithm URIs. There is no registration needed in this document.</t>
      <t></t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Section-Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>The authors of this draft would like to thank the following people
   for their contributions and support to make this a better
   specification: Hannes Tschofenig, Jonathan Tuliani, David Dix, Siddharth Bajaj, 
   Stu Veath, Shuh Chang, Oanh Hoang, John Huang, and Siddhartha Mohapatra.
</t>
    </section>

    <!-- ////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////////// -->
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative references">
      <reference anchor="RFC4226" target="http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc4226.txt">
        <front>
          <title>HOTP: An HMAC-Based One-Time Password Algorithm</title>

          <author initials="D." surname="M'Raihi">
            <organization>VeriSign</organization>
          </author>
          
          <author initials="M." surname="Bellare">
            <organization>UCSD</organization>
          </author>
          
          <author initials="F." surname="Hoornaert">
            <organization>Vasco</organization>
          </author>
          
          <author initials="D." surname="Naccache">
            <organization>Gemplus</organization>
          </author>

          <author initials="O." surname="Ranen">
            <organization>Aladdin</organization>
          </author>
                    
          <date month="December" year="2005" />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="4226" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RFC4086" target="http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc4086.txt">
        <front>
		<title>Randomness Recommendations for Security</title>

          <author initials="D." surname="Eastlake">
            <organization>Motorola Lab</organization>
          </author>

          <author initials="J." surname="Schiller">
            <organization>MIT</organization>
          </author>

          <author initials="S." surname="Crocker">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <date month="June" year="2005" />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="4086" />
      </reference>
      
      <reference anchor="RFC2119" target="http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc2119.txt">
        <front>
          <title>Key words for use in RFCs to Indicate Requirement
          Levels</title>

          <author fullname="">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date month="March" year="1997" />
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="BCP" value="14" />

        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="2119" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RFC2104" target="http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc2104.txt">
        <front>
		<title>HMAC: Keyed-Hashing for Message Authentication</title>

          <author initials="H." surname="Krawczyk">
            <organization>IBM</organization>
          </author>

          <author initials="M." surname="Bellare">
            <organization>UCSD</organization>
          </author>

          <author initials="R." surname="Canetti">
            <organization>IBM</organization>
          </author>

          <date month="February" year="1997" />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="2104" />
      </reference>
	</references>
	
      <references title="Informative References">
      
      <reference anchor="ALGP" target="http://tools.ietf.org/id/draft-hoyer-keyprov-pskc-algorithm-profiles-00.txt">
        <front>
		<title>Additional Portable Symmetric Key Container (PSKC) Algorithm Profiles</title>

          <author initials="P." surname="Hoyer">
            <organization>ActivIdentity</organization>
          </author>

          <author initials="M." surname="Pei">
            <organization>VeriSign</organization>
          </author>

          <author initials="S." surname="Machani">
            <organization>Diversinet</organization>
          </author>

          <author initials="A." surname="Doherty">
            <organization>RSA, The Security Division of EMC</organization>
          </author>

          <date month="December" year="2008" />
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="CN" target="http://www.gemplus.com/smart/rd/publications/pdf/CN99maur.pdf">
        <front>
		<title>An accurate evaluation of Maurer's universal test</title>

          <author initials="J.S." surname="Coron">
            <organization>University of Luxembourg</organization>
          </author>

          <author initials="D." surname="Naccache">
            <organization>ENS</organization>
          </author>

          <date month="February" year="1999" />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="LNCS" value="1556" />

      </reference>
              
    </references>

    <section anchor="Section-Reference-Impl" title="TOTP Algorithm: Reference Implementation">
        <figure>
		<preamble/>
		<artwork><![CDATA[        
import java.lang.reflect.UndeclaredThrowableException;
import java.security.GeneralSecurityException;
import java.text.DateFormat;
import java.text.SimpleDateFormat;
import java.util.Calendar;
import java.util.Date;
import javax.crypto.Mac;
import javax.crypto.spec.SecretKeySpec;
import java.math.BigInteger;
import java.util.TimeZone;

/**
 * This an example implementation of the OATH TOTP algorithm. 
 * Visit www.openauthentication.org for more information.
 * 
 * @author Johan Rydell, PortWise, Inc.
 */
public class TOTP {

    private TOTP() {}


    /**
     * This method uses the JCE to provide the crypto
     * algorithm.
     * HMAC computes a Hashed Message Authentication Code with the
     * crypto hash algorithm as a parameter.
     *
     * @param crypto     the crypto algorithm (HmacSHA1, HmacSHA256, 
     *                            HmacSHA512)
     * @param keyBytes   the bytes to use for the HMAC key
     * @param text       the message or text to be authenticated.
     */
    private static byte[] hmac_sha1(String crypto, byte[] keyBytes, 
        byte[] text)
    {
        try {
            Mac hmac;
            hmac = Mac.getInstance(crypto);
            SecretKeySpec macKey =
                new SecretKeySpec(keyBytes, "RAW");
            hmac.init(macKey);
            return hmac.doFinal(text);
        } catch (GeneralSecurityException gse) {
            throw new UndeclaredThrowableException(gse);
        }
    }    


    /**
     * This method converts HEX string to Byte[]
     *
     * @param hex   the HEX string
     * 
     * @return      A byte array  
     */
    private static byte[] hexStr2Bytes(String hex){
        // Adding one byte to get the right conversion
        // values starting with "0" can be converted
        byte[] bArray = new BigInteger("10" + hex,16).toByteArray();    

        // Copy all the REAL bytes, not the "first"
        byte[] ret = new byte[bArray.length - 1];
        for (int i = 0; i < ret.length ; i++) 
            ret[i] = bArray[i+1];
        return ret;
    }


    private static final int[] DIGITS_POWER
    // 0 1  2   3    4     5      6       7        8                 
    = {1,10,100,1000,10000,100000,1000000,10000000,100000000 };


    /**
     * This method generates an TOTP value for the given
     * set of parameters.
     *
     * @param key   the shared secret, HEX encoded
     * @param time     a value that reflects a time 
     * @param returnDigits     number of digits to return 
     * 
     * @return      A numeric String in base 10 that includes
     *              {@link truncationDigits} digits 
     */
    public static String generateTOTP(String key,
            String time,
            String returnDigits)
    {
        return generateTOTP(key, time, returnDigits, "HmacSHA1");
    }


    /**
     * This method generates an TOTP value for the given
     * set of parameters.
     *
     * @param key   the shared secret, HEX encoded
     * @param time     a value that reflects a time 
     * @param returnDigits     number of digits to return 
     * 
     * @return      A numeric String in base 10 that includes
     *              {@link truncationDigits} digits 
     */
    public static String generateTOTP256(String key,
            String time,
            String returnDigits)
    {
        return generateTOTP(key, time, returnDigits, "HmacSHA256");
    }


    /**
     * This method generates an TOTP value for the given
     * set of parameters.
     *
     * @param key   the shared secret, HEX encoded
     * @param time     a value that reflects a time 
     * @param returnDigits     number of digits to return 
     * 
     * @return      A numeric String in base 10 that includes
     *              {@link truncationDigits} digits 
     */
    public static String generateTOTP512(String key,
            String time,
            String returnDigits)
    {
        return generateTOTP(key, time, returnDigits, "HmacSHA512");
    }


    /**
     * This method generates an TOTP value for the given
     * set of parameters.
     *
     * @param key   the shared secret, HEX encoded
     * @param time     a value that reflects a time 
     * @param returnDigits     number of digits to return 
     * @param crypto    the crypto function to use 
     * 
     * @return      A numeric String in base 10 that includes
     *              {@link truncationDigits} digits 
     */
    private static String generateTOTP(String key,
            String time,
            String returnDigits,
            String crypto)
    {
        int codeDigits = Integer.decode(returnDigits).intValue();
        String result = null;
        byte[] hash;

        // Using the counter
        // First 8 bytes are for the movingFactor
        // Complaint with base RFC 4226 (HOTP)
        while(time.length() < 16 )
            time = "0" + time;

        // Get the HEX in a Byte[]
        byte[] msg = hexStr2Bytes(time);

        // Adding one byte to get the right conversion
        byte[] k = hexStr2Bytes(key);

        hash = hmac_sha1(crypto, k, msg);

        // put selected bytes into result int
        int offset = hash[hash.length - 1] & 0xf;

        int binary =
            ((hash[offset] & 0x7f) << 24) | 
            ((hash[offset + 1] & 0xff) << 16) | 
            ((hash[offset + 2] & 0xff) << 8) | 
            (hash[offset + 3] & 0xff);

        int otp = binary % DIGITS_POWER[codeDigits];

        result = Integer.toString(otp);
        while (result.length() < codeDigits) {
            result = "0" + result;
        }
        return result;
    }

    public static void main(String[] args) {

        String seed = "3132333435363738393031323334353637383930";
        long T0 = 0;
        long X = 30;
        long testTime[] = {59, 1111111109, 1111111111, 
                           1234567890, 2000000000};

        String steps = "0";
        DateFormat df = new SimpleDateFormat("yyyy-MM-dd HH:mm:ss");
        df.setTimeZone(TimeZone.getTimeZone("UTC"));

        try{
            System.out.println(
              "+--------------+-----------------------+" +
              "------------------+--------+--------+");
            System.out.println(
              "|  Time(sec)   |   Time (UTC format)   " +
              "| Value of T(Hex)  |  TOTP  | Mode   |");
            System.out.println(
              "+--------------+-----------------------+" +
              "------------------+--------+--------+");

            for(int i=0; i<testTime.length; i++) {       
                long T = (testTime[i] - T0)/X;
                steps = Long.toHexString(T).toUpperCase();
                while(steps.length() < 16) steps = "0" + steps;
                String fmtTime = String.format("%1$-10s", testTime[i]);
                String utcTime = df.format(new Date(testTime[i]*1000));
                System.out.print("|  " + fmtTime + "  |  " + utcTime +  
                                 "  | " + steps + " |");
                System.out.println(generateTOTP(seed, steps, "8", 
                                 "HmacSHA1") + "| SHA1   |");
                System.out.print("|  " + fmtTime + "  |  " + utcTime +  
                                 "  | " + steps + " |");
                System.out.println(generateTOTP(seed, steps, "8", 
                                 "HmacSHA256") + "| SHA256 |");
                System.out.print("|  " + fmtTime + "  |  " + utcTime +  
                                 "  | " + steps + " |");
                System.out.println(generateTOTP(seed, steps, "8", 
                                 "HmacSHA512") + "| SHA512 |");

                System.out.println(
                  "+--------------+-----------------------+" +
                  "------------------+--------+--------+");
            }
        }catch (final Exception e){
            System.out.println("Error : " + e);
        }
    }
}
            ]]></artwork>
            <postamble/>
	</figure>        
    </section>
    <section anchor="Section-Test-Vectors" title="Test Vectors">
      <t>This section provides test values that can be used for HOTP time-based 
      variant algorithm interoperability test.</t>
      
      <t>The test token shared secret uses the ASCII string value 
      "12345678901234567890". 
      
      With Time Step X = 30, and Unix epoch as initial value to count time steps
      where T0 = 0, the TOTP algorithm will display the following  values 
      for specified modes and timestamps.</t>
      
            
      <texttable anchor="TOTPTable" title="TOTP Table">
          <ttcol align="center">Time (sec)</ttcol>
          <ttcol align="center">UTC Time</ttcol>          
          <ttcol align="center">Value of T (hex)</ttcol>          
          <ttcol align="center">TOTP</ttcol>
          <ttcol align="center">Mode</ttcol>

          <c>59</c>
          <c>1970-01-01 00:00:59</c>
          <c>0000000000000001</c>
          <c>94287082</c>
          <c>SHA1</c>
          
          <c>59</c>
          <c>1970-01-01 00:00:59</c>
          <c>0000000000000001</c>
          <c>32247374</c>
          <c>SHA256</c>
          
          <c>59</c>
          <c>1970-01-01 00:00:59</c>
          <c>0000000000000001</c>
          <c>69342147</c>
          <c>SHA512</c>

          <c>1111111109</c>
          <c>2005-03-18 01:58:29</c>
          <c>00000000023523EC</c>
          <c>07081804</c>
          <c>SHA1</c>
          
		  <c>1111111109</c>
          <c>2005-03-18 01:58:29</c>
          <c>00000000023523EC</c>
          <c>34756375</c>
          <c>SHA256</c>
          
          <c>1111111109</c>
          <c>2005-03-18 01:58:29</c>
          <c>00000000023523EC</c>
          <c>63049338</c>
          <c>SHA512</c>
                    
          <c>1111111111</c>
          <c>2005-03-18 01:58:31</c>
          <c>00000000023523ED</c>
          <c>14050471</c>
          <c>SHA1</c>
          
          <c>1111111111</c>
          <c>2005-03-18 01:58:31</c>
          <c>00000000023523ED</c>
          <c>74584430</c>
          <c>SHA256</c>
          
          <c>1111111111</c>
          <c>2005-03-18 01:58:31</c>
          <c>00000000023523ED</c>
          <c>54380122</c>
          <c>SHA512</c>
          
          <c>1234567890</c>
          <c>2009-02-13 23:31:30</c>
          <c>000000000273EF07</c>
          <c>89005924</c>
          <c>SHA1</c>
         
          <c>1234567890</c>
          <c>2009-02-13 23:31:30</c>
          <c>000000000273EF07</c>
          <c>42829826</c>
          <c>SHA256</c>
          
          <c>1234567890</c>
          <c>2009-02-13 23:31:30</c>
          <c>000000000273EF07</c>
          <c>76671578</c>
          <c>SHA512</c>
          
          <c>2000000000</c>
          <c>2033-05-18 03:33:20</c>
          <c>0000000003F940AA</c>
          <c>69279037</c>
          <c>SHA1</c>

          <c>2000000000</c>
          <c>2033-05-18 03:33:20</c>
          <c>0000000003F940AA</c>
          <c>78428693</c>
          <c>SHA256</c>

          <c>2000000000</c>
          <c>2033-05-18 03:33:20</c>
          <c>0000000003F940AA</c>
          <c>56464532</c>
          <c>SHA512</c>
                                        
        </texttable>     
    </section>    
</back>
</rfc>
