<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY RFC2119 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3261 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3261.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3264 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3264.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4145 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4145.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4474 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4474.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4566 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4566.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4572 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4572.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5245 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5245.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5280 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5280.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5389 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5389.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5479 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5479.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5763 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5763.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5764 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5764.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6347 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6347.xml">

]>




<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="no" ?>
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>

<rfc ipr="trust200902" category="std" docName="draft-ietf-mmusic-udptl-dtls-01" obsoletes="" updates="" submissionType="IETF" xml:lang="en">
	<front>
		<title abbrev="UDPTL over DTLS">
			UDP Transport Layer (UDPTL) over Datagram Transport Layer Security (DTLS)
		</title>
    		<author initials="C.H." surname="Holmberg" fullname="Christer Holmberg">
			<organization>Ericsson</organization>
			<address>
				<postal>
					<street>Hirsalantie 11</street>
					<code>02420</code>
					<city>Jorvas</city>
					<country>Finland</country>
				</postal>
				<email>christer.holmberg@ericsson.com</email>
			</address>
		</author>
		<author initials="I.S." surname="Sedlacek" fullname="Ivo Sedlacek">
			<organization>Ericsson</organization>
			<address>
				<postal>
					<street>Sokolovska 79</street>
					<code>18600</code>
					<city>Praha</city>
					<country>Czech Republic</country>
				</postal>
				<email>ivo.sedlacek@ericsson.com</email>
			</address>
		</author>
		<author initials="G.S" surname="Salgueiro" fullname="Gonzalo Salgueiro">
			<organization abbrev="Cisco">Cisco Systems, Inc.</organization>
			<address>
				<postal>
					<street>7200-12 Kit Creek Road</street>
					<city>Research Triangle Park</city>
					<region>NC</region>
					<code>27709</code>
					<country>US</country>
				</postal>
				<email>gsalguei@cisco.com</email>
			</address>
		</author>

		<date year="2013" />
		<area>Transport</area>
		<workgroup>MMUSIC Working Group</workgroup>
		<keyword>SDP</keyword>
		<keyword>SIP</keyword>
		<keyword>DTLS</keyword>
		<keyword>UDPTL</keyword>
		<keyword>fax</keyword>
		<keyword>transport</keyword>
		<abstract>
			<t>
				This document specifies how the UDP Transport Layer (UDPTL) protocol can be transported 
				over the Datagram Transport Layer Security (DTLS) protocol, how the usage of UDPTL over 
				DTLS is indicated in the Session Description Protocol (SDP), and how UDPTL over DTLS is 
				negotiated in a session established using the Session Initiation Protocol (SIP).
			</t>
		</abstract>
	</front>
	
	<middle>
		<section title="Introduction" toc="default">
			<t>
  				While telephony encryption devices have been traditionally used for
   				highly sensitive documents, secure fax on the Public Switched
   				Telephone Network (PSTN) was not as widely considered or prioritized
   				because of the challenges involved with physical access to telephony
   				equipment. As real-time communications transition to IP networks,
   				where information might potentially be intercepted or spoofed, an
   				appropriate level of security for fax that offers integrity and
   				confidentiality protection is vital. Some of the security mechanisms
   				for securing fax include:
			</t>
			<t>
			<list style="symbols">
			<t>
				<xref target="ITU.T30.2005" pageno="false" format="default" /> Annex H specifies 
				integrity and confidentiality protection of fax in application layer, independent 
				of protocol for fax transport.
			</t>
			<t>
				<xref target="ITU.T38.2010" pageno="false" format="default" /> specifies fax 
				transport over RTP/SAVP which enables integrity and confidentiality protection 
				of fax in IP network.
			</t>
			</list>
			</t>
			<t>
				Despite these mechanisms to secure fax, there is no transport layer
				security offering integrity and confidentiality protection for UDPTL
				<xref target="ITU.T38.2010" pageno="false" format="default" />, the 
				overwhelmingly predominant fax transport protocol. The protocol stack 
				for fax transport using UDPTL is shown in Table 1.
			</t>
			<texttable anchor="table_UDPTL_UDP_stack" title="Protocol stack for UDPTL over UDP" style="all">
				<ttcol align='center'>Protocol</ttcol>
				<c>Internet facsimile protocol</c>
				<c>UDPTL</c>
				<c>UDP</c>
				<c>IP</c>
			</texttable>
			<t>
				The 3rd Generation Partnership Project (3GPP) has performed a study on how to 
				provide secure fax in the IP Multimedia Subsystem (IMS) and concluded that 
				secure fax shall be transported using UDPTL over DTLS.
			</t>
			<t>
				This document specifies fax transport using UDPTL over DTLS <xref target="RFC6347" 
				pageno="false" format="default"/>, which enables integrity and confidentiality 
				protection of fax in IP networks. The protocol stack for integrity and 
				confidentiality protected fax transport using UDPTL over DTLS is shown in 
				<xref target="table_UDPTL_DTLS_UDP_stack" pageno="false" format="default"/>.
			</t>
			<texttable anchor="table_UDPTL_DTLS_UDP_stack" title="Protocol stack for UDPTL over UDP" style="all">
				<ttcol align='center'>Protocol</ttcol>
				<c>Internet facsimile protocol</c>
				<c>UDPTL</c>
				<c>DTLS</c>
				<c>UDP</c>
				<c>IP</c>
			</texttable>
			<t>
				The primary motivations for the mechanism in this document are:
				<list style="symbols">
					<t>
						The design of DTLS <xref target="RFC6347" pageno="false" format="default"/> is 
						clearly defined, well understood and implementations are widely available.
					</t>
					<t>
						No DTLS extensions are required in order to enable UDPTL transport over DTLS.
					</t>
					<t>
						Fax transport using UDPTL over DTLS only requires insertion of the DTLS layer between 
						the UDPTL layer and the UDP layer, as shown in <xref target="table_UDPTL_DTLS_UDP_stack" 
						pageno="false" format="default"/>. The UDPTL layer and layers above UDPTL layer require 
						no modification.
					</t>
					<t>
						UDPTL <xref target="ITU.T38.2010" pageno="false" format="default" /> is by far the 
						most widely deployed fax transport protocol in IP networks.
					</t>
					<t>
						3GPP needs a mechanism to transport UDPTL over DTLS, in order to provide secure 
						fax in IMS networks.
					</t>
				</list>
			</t>
			<t>
				This document specifies the transport of UDPTL over DTLS using the DTLS record 
				layer "application_data" packets <xref target="RFC6347" pageno="false" format="default"/>.
			</t>
			<t>
				Since the DTLS record layer "application_data" packet does not indicate whether 
				it carries UDPTL, or some other protocol, the usage of a dedicated DTLS association 
				for transport of UDPTL needs to be negotiated, e.g. using the Session Description 
				Protocol (SDP) <xref target="RFC4566" pageno="false" format="default"/> and the SDP 
				offer/answer mechanism <xref target="RFC3264" pageno="false" format="default"/>.
			</t>
			<t>
				Therefore, this document specifies a new &lt;proto&gt; value <xref target="RFC4566" 
				pageno="false" format="default"/> for the SDP media description ("m=" line) 
				<xref target="RFC3264" pageno="false" format="default"/>, in order to indicate 
				UDPTL over DTLS in SDP messages <xref target="RFC4566" pageno="false" format="default"/>.
			</t>
		</section>
		<section title="Conventions" toc="default">
			<t>
				The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", 
				"SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted 
				as described in BCP 14, RFC 2119 <xref target="RFC2119" pageno="false" format="default" />.
			</t>
			<t>
				DTLS uses the term "session" to refer to a long-lived set of
				keying material that spans DTLS associations. In this document,
				in order to be consistent with SIP/SDP usage of "session" terminology, 
				we use it to refer to a multimedia session and use the term "DTLS session" 
				to refer to the DTLS construct. We use the term "DTLS association" to refer 
				to a particular DTLS cipher suite and keying material set that is associated 
				with a single host/port quartet. The same DTLS session can be used to 
				establish the keying material for multiple DTLS associations. For 
				consistency with other SIP/SDP usage, we use the term "connection" when 
				what's being referred to is a multimedia stream that is not specifically 
				DTLS.
			</t>
		</section>
		<section title="Secure Channel" toc="default">
			<section title="Secure Channel Establishment" toc="default">
				<t>
					The SDP offer/answer mechanism <xref target="RFC3264" pageno="false" format="default" /> 
					is used by other protocols, e.g. the Session Initiation Protocol (SIP) <xref target="RFC3261" 
					pageno="false" format="default" />, to negotiate and establish multimedia sessions.
				</t>
				<t>
					In addition to the usual contents of an SDP media description ("m=" line) specified for 
					UDPTL over the UDP, each SDP media description for UDPTL over DTLS over the UDP will also 
					contain several SDP attributes, as specified in <xref target="RFC4145" pageno="false" 
					format="default" /> and <xref target="RFC4572" pageno="false" format="default" />.
				</t>
				<t>
					The SDP offer and SDP answer MUST conform to the following requirements:
					<list style="symbols">
						<t>
							The endpoint MUST set the "proto" field of the "m=" line to the token specified in 
							<xref target="table_SDP_proto_values" pageno="false" format="default" />.
						</t>
						<t>
							The endpoint MUST use the SDP setup attribute <xref target="RFC4145" pageno="false" 
							format="default" />. The offerer SHOULD assign the SDP setup attribute with a
							setup:actpass value, and MAY assign the SDP setup attribute with a setup:active value or 
							setup:passive value. The offerer MUST NOT assign the SDP setup attribute with a 
							setup:holdconn value. If the offerer assigns the SDP setup attribute with a setup:actpass value
							or setup:passive value, it MUST be prepared to receive a DTLS client_hello message before it receives 
							the SDP answer. If the answerer accepts the media stream, then it MUST assign the SDP setup 
							attribute with either a setup:active value or setup:passive value, according to the procedures in <xref 
							target="RFC4145" pageno="false" format="default" />. The answerer MUST NOT assign an 
							SDP setup attribute with a setup:holdconn value. Whichever party is active, it MUST initiate 
							a DTLS handshake by sending a ClientHello over each flow (host/port quartet).
						</t>
						<t>
							The endpoint MUST use the SDP certificate fingerprint attribute 
							<xref target="RFC4572" pageno="false" format="default" />.
						</t>
						<t>
							The certificate presented during the DTLS handshake MUST match the 
							fingerprint exchanged via the signaling path in the SDP.
						</t>
						<t>
							If the fingerprint does not match the hashed certificate, then the
							endpoint MUST tear down the media session immediately.  Note that
							it is permissible to wait until the other side's fingerprint has
							been received before establishing the connection; however, this
							may have undesirable latency effects.
						</t>
						<t>
							The endpoint MUST NOT use the SDP connection attribute <xref target="RFC4145" pageno="false"
							format="default" />.
						</t>
					</list>
				</t>
			</section>
			<section title="Secure Channel Usage" toc="default">
				<t>
					DTLS is used as specified in <xref target="RFC6347" pageno="false" format="default" />. 
					Once the DTLS handshake is completed, the UDPTL packets SHALL be transported in DTLS record 
					layer "application_data" packets.
				</t>
			</section>
		</section>

		<section title="Miscellaneous Considerations" toc="default">
			<section title="Anonymous Calls" toc="default">
				<t>
					When making anonymous calls, a new self-signed certificate SHOULD be
					used for each call and the content of the subjectAltName attribute inside 
					the certificate MUST NOT contain information that either allows correlation 
					or identification of the user making anonymous calls.
				</t>
			</section>
			<section title="Middlebox Interaction" toc="default">
				<t>
					The procedures defined for SRTP-DTLS in Section 6.7 of <xref target="RFC5763" 
					pageno="false" format="default" /> for interaction with middleboxes also apply 
					to UDPTL over DTLS.
				</t>
				<t>
					The procedures defined for SRTP-DTLS in Section 5.1.2 of <xref target="RFC5764" 
					pageno="false" format="default" /> for distinguishing DTLS and STUN packets also 
					apply to UDPTL over DTLS.
				</t>
				<t>
					Editor's note: The complete SRTP-DTLS implementation is not needed. Only 
					the parts for interaction with middleboxes in RFC5763 and for distinguishing 
					DTLS and STUN packets in RFC5764 are needed. Should those be copied into this 
					document?
				</t>
			</section>
			<section title="Rekeying" toc="default">
				<t>
					After the DTLS handshake caused by rekeying has completed, because of possible 
					packet reordering on the wire, packets protected by the previous set of keys can 
					arrive. To compensate for this fact, receivers SHOULD maintain both sets of keys 
					for some time in order to be able to decrypt and verify older packets. The duration 
					of maintaining the previous set of keys after the finish of the DTLS handshake is 
					out of scope for this document.
				</t>
			</section>
		</section>
		<section anchor="section.sec" title="Security Considerations">
			<t>
				DTLS media signaled with SIP requires a mechanism to ensure that the
				communicating peers' certificates are correct.
			</t>
			<t>
				The standard DTLS strategy for authenticating the communicating
				parties is to give the server (and optionally the client) a PKIX
				<xref target="RFC5280" pageno="false" format="default" /> certificate. 
				The client then verifies the certificate and checks that the name in 
				the certificate matches the server's domain name. This works because 
				there are a relatively small number of servers with well-defined names; 
				a situation that does not usually occur in the VoIP context.
			</t>
			<t>
				The design described in this document is intended to leverage the
				authenticity of the signaling channel (while not requiring
				confidentiality). As long as each side of the connection can verify
				the integrity of the SDP received from the other side, then the DTLS
				handshake cannot be hijacked via a man-in-the-middle attack.  This
				integrity protection is easily provided by the caller to the callee
				(see sample message flow in Annex A.2) via the SIP Identity <xref target="RFC4474" 
				pageno="false" format="default" /> mechanism. Other mechanisms, such as the 
				S/MIME mechanism <xref target="RFC3261" pageno="false" format="default" />, 
				or perhaps future mechanisms yet to be specified could also serve this purpose.
			</t>
			<t>
				While this mechanism can still be used without such integrity
				mechanisms, the security provided is limited to defense against
				passive attack by intermediaries.  An active attack on the signaling
				plus an active attack on the media plane can allow an attacker to
				attack the connection (R-SIG-MEDIA in the notation of <xref target="RFC5479" 
				pageno="false" format="default" />).
			</t>
		</section>
		<section anchor="section.iana" title="IANA Considerations">
			<t>
				This document updates the "Session Description Protocol (SDP) Parameters" registry as 
				specified in Section 8.2.2 of <xref target="RFC4566" pageno="false" format="default"/>.
				Specifically, it adds the values in <xref target="table_SDP_proto_values" 
				pageno="false" format="default"/> to the table for the SDP "proto" field
				registry.
			</t>
			<texttable anchor="table_SDP_proto_values" title='SDP "proto" field values'>
				<ttcol align='center'>Type</ttcol>
				<ttcol align='center'>SDP Name</ttcol>
				<ttcol align='center'>Reference</ttcol>
				<c>proto</c>
				<c>UDP/TLS/UDPTL</c>
				<c>[RFC-XXXX]</c>
			</texttable>
			<t>
				[RFC EDITOR NOTE: Please replace RFC-XXXX with the RFC number of this document.]
			</t>
		</section>
		<section title="Acknowledgments">
			<t>
				Special thanks to Peter Dawes, who provided comments on the initial version of the draft, and to
				Paul E. Jones, James Rafferty and Albrecht Schwarz who provided valuable feedback and input on the
				MMUSIC mailing list.       
			</t>
		</section>
		<section title="Change Log">
			<t>
				[RFC EDITOR NOTE: Please remove this section when publishing]
			</t>
			<t>
				Changes from draft-ietf-mmusic-udptl-dtls-00
				<list style="symbols">
					<t>SDP offerer is allowed to assign an a=setup:active or a=setup:passive value, in 
					addition to the recommended a=setup:actpass (http://www.ietf.org/mail-archive/web/mmusic/current/msg12331.html).</t>
					<t>The example for secure fax replacing audio stream in audio-only session 
					added (http://www.ietf.org/mail-archive/web/mmusic/current/msg12428.html).</t>
					<t>Editor's note on the connection attribute resolved by prohibiting usage of the 
					SDP connection attribute (http://www.ietf.org/mail-archive/web/mmusic/current/msg12772.html).</t>
					<t>Editorial corrections.</t>
				</list>
			</t>			
			<t>
				Changes from draft-holmberg-mmusic-udptl-dtls-02
				<list style="symbols">
					<t>Milestone adopted - draft-ietf-mmusic version of the draft submitted.</t>
				</list>
			</t>			
			<t>
				Changes from draft-holmberg-mmusic-udptl-dtls-01
				<list style="symbols">
					<t>Gonzalo Salgueiro added as co-author.</t>
					<t>PSTN comparison text and Introduction text modified.</t>
				</list>
			</t>
			<t>
				Changes from draft-holmberg-mmusic-udptl-dtls-00
				<list style="symbols">
					<t>Text about T.30 added.</t>
					<t>Latest version of T.38 referenced.</t>
					<t>Additional text about the need for secure fax in IP networks.</t>
				</list>
			</t>
			<t>
				Changes from draft-holmberg-dispatch-udptl-dtls-00
				<list style="symbols">
					<t>WG changed to MMUSIC.</t>
					<t>Added text about 3GPP need for UDPTL/DTLS.</t>
				</list>
			</t>
		</section>
	</middle>
	<back>
		<references title="Normative References">
			<?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119"?>
			<?rfc include="reference.RFC.3261"?>
			<?rfc include="reference.RFC.3264"?>
			<?rfc include="reference.RFC.4145"?>
			<?rfc include="reference.RFC.4474"?>
			<?rfc include="reference.RFC.4566"?>
			<?rfc include="reference.RFC.4572"?>			
			<?rfc include="reference.RFC.5280"?>			
			<?rfc include="reference.RFC.5763"?>
			<?rfc include="reference.RFC.5764"?>
			<?rfc include="reference.RFC.6347"?>
			<reference anchor="ITU.T30.2005">
				<front>
					<title>Procedures for document facsimile transmission in the general switched telephone network</title>
					<author>
						<organization>International Telecommunications Union</organization>
					</author>
					<date month="September" year="2005"/>
				</front>
				<seriesInfo name="ITU-T" value="Recommendation T.30"/>
			</reference>
			<reference anchor="ITU.T38.2010">
				<front>
					<title>Procedures for real-time Group 3 facsimile communication over IP networks</title>
					<author>
						<organization>International Telecommunications Union</organization>
					</author>
					<date month="September" year="2010"/>
				</front>
				<seriesInfo name="ITU-T" value="Recommendation T.38"/>
			</reference>
		</references>
		<references title="Informative References">
			<?rfc include="reference.RFC.5479"?>
		</references>
      <section anchor="section.example" title="Example">
        <section title="General">
          <t>
				Prior to establishing the session, both Alice and Bob generate self-signed certificates
				which are used for a single session or, more likely, reused for multiple sessions.
          </t>
          <t>
				The SIP signaling from Alice to her proxy is transported over TLS to ensure an integrity 
				protected channel between Alice and her identity service. Transport between proxies should 
				also be protected somehow.
          </t>
          <t>
				Only one element is shown for Alice's and Bob's proxies for the purposes of simplification.
          </t>
          <t>
				For the sake of brevity and simplicity, only the mandatory SDP T.38
				attributes are shown.
          </t>
        </section>

        <section title="Basic Message Flow with Identity">
          <t>
            <xref target="example_1_figure" pageno="false" format="default" /> shows an example message flow of session establishment for T.38 fax securely transported using UDPTL over DTLS.
          </t>
          <t>
            In this example flow, Alice acts as the passive endpoint of DTLS association and Bob acts as the active endpoint of DTLS association.
          </t>
          <t>
            <figure anchor="example_1_figure" title="Basic message flow with Identity">
              <artwork><![CDATA[
Alice                    Proxies                   Bob
  | (1) SIP INVITE         |                        |
  |----------------------->|                        |
  |                        | (2) SIP INVITE         |
  |                        |----------------------->|
  |                        |   (3) DTLS ClientHello |
  |<------------------------------------------------|
  |    (4) remaining messages of DTLS handshake     |
  |<----------------------------------------------->|
  |                        |                        |
  |                        |                        |
  |                        |         (5) SIP 200 OK |
  |                        |<-----------------------|
  |         (6) SIP 200 OK |                        |
  |<-----------------------|                        |
  | (7) SIP ACK            |                        |
  |------------------------------------------------>|
  |      (8) T.38 message using UDPTL over DTLS     |
  |<----------------------------------------------->|
  |                        |                        |
           ]]></artwork>
            </figure>
          </t>
          <t>
            <list style="hanging">
              <t hangText="Message (1):">
                <vspace blankLines="1"/>
                <xref target="example_1_message_1" pageno="false" format="default" /> shows the initial INVITE request sent by Alice to Alice's proxy. The initial INVITE request contains an SDP offer.
              </t>
              <t>
                <vspace blankLines="1"/>
					The "m=" line in the SDP offer indicates T.38 fax using UDPTL over DTLS.
              </t>
              <t>
                <vspace blankLines="1"/>
					The SDP setup:actpass attribute in the SDP offer indicates that Alice has requested to be either the active or passive endpoint.
              </t>
              <t>
                <vspace blankLines="1"/>
					The SDP fingerprint attribute in the SDP offer indicates the certificate fingerprint computed from Alice's self-signed certificate.
              </t>
              <t>
                <vspace blankLines="2"/>
              </t>
              <t>
                <figure anchor="example_1_message_1" title="Message (1)">
                  <artwork><![CDATA[
INVITE sip:bob@example.com SIP/2.0
To: <sip:bob@example.com>
From: "Alice"<sip:alice@example.com>;tag=843c7b0b
Via: SIP/2.0/TLS ua1.example.com;branch=z9hG4bK-0e53sadfkasldkfj
Contact: <sip:alice@ua1.example.com>
Call-ID: 6076913b1c39c212@REVMTEpG
CSeq: 1 INVITE
Allow: INVITE, ACK, CANCEL, OPTIONS, BYE, UPDATE
Max-Forwards: 70
Content-Type: application/sdp
Content-Length: xxxx
Supported: from-change

v=0
o=- 1181923068 1181923196 IN IP4 ua1.example.com
s=-
c=IN IP4 ua1.example.com
t=0 0
m=image 6056 UDP/TLS/UDPTL t38
a=setup:actpass
a=fingerprint: SHA-1 \
  4A:AD:B9:B1:3F:82:18:3B:54:02:12:DF:3E:5D:49:6B:19:E5:7C:AB
a=T38FaxRateManagement:transferredTCF
               ]]></artwork>
                </figure>
                <vspace blankLines="1"/>
              </t>

              <t hangText="Message (2):">
                <vspace blankLines="1"/>
                <xref target="example_1_message_2" pageno="false" format="default" /> shows the SIP INVITE request sent by Bob's proxy to Bob.
                </t>
                <t>
                <vspace blankLines="1"/>
					The SIP INVITE request contains an Identity header field and
					an Identity-Info header fields inserted by Alice's proxy.
                </t>
                <t>
                <vspace blankLines="1"/>
					When received, Bob verifies the identity provided in the SIP INVITE request.
                <vspace blankLines="2"/>

                <figure anchor="example_1_message_2" title="Message (2)">
                  <artwork><![CDATA[
INVITE sip:bob@ua2.example.com SIP/2.0
To: <sip:bob@example.com>
From: "Alice"<sip:alice@example.com>;tag=843c7b0b
Via: SIP/2.0/TLS proxy.example.com;branch=z9hG4bK-0e53sadfkasldk
Via: SIP/2.0/TLS ua1.example.com;branch=z9hG4bK-0e53sadfkasldkfj
Record-Route: <sip:proxy.example.com;lr>
Contact: <sip:alice@ua1.example.com>
Call-ID: 6076913b1c39c212@REVMTEpG
CSeq: 1 INVITE
Allow: INVITE, ACK, CANCEL, OPTIONS, BYE, UPDATE
Max-Forwards: 69
Identity: CyI4+nAkHrH3ntmaxgr01TMxTmtjP7MASwliNRdupRI1vpkXRvZXx1ja9k
          3W+v1PDsy32MaqZi0M5WfEkXxbgTnPYW0jIoK8HMyY1VT7egt0kk4XrKFC
          HYWGCl0nB2sNsM9CG4hq+YJZTMaSROoMUBhikVIjnQ8ykeD6UXNOyfI=
Identity-Info: https://example.com/cert
Content-Type: application/sdp
Content-Length: xxxx
Supported: from-change

v=0
o=- 1181923068 1181923196 IN IP4 ua1.example.com
s=-
c=IN IP4 ua1.example.com
t=0 0
m=image 6056 UDP/TLS/UDPTL t38
a=setup:actpass
a=fingerprint: SHA-1 \
  4A:AD:B9:B1:3F:82:18:3B:54:02:12:DF:3E:5D:49:6B:19:E5:7C:AB
a=T38FaxRateManagement:transferredTCF
               ]]></artwork>
                </figure>
                <vspace blankLines="1"/>
              </t>
              <t hangText="Message (3):">
                <vspace blankLines="1"/>
					Assuming that Alice's identity is valid, Bob sends a DTLS ClientHello directly to Alice.
                <vspace blankLines="1"/>
              </t>

              <t hangText="Message (4):">
                <vspace blankLines="1"/>
					Alice and Bob exchange further messages of DTLS handshake (HelloVerifyRequest, ClientHello, ServerHello, Certificate, ServerKeyExchange, CertificateRequest, ServerHelloDone, Certificate, ClientKeyExchange, CertificateVerify, ChangeCipherSpec, Finished).
              </t>
              <t>
                <vspace blankLines="1"/>
					When Bob receives the certificate of Alice via DTLS, Bob checks whether the certificate fingerprint calculated from the Alice's certificate received via DTLS matches the certificate fingerprint received in the a=fingerprint SDP attribute of <xref target="example_1_message_2" pageno="false" format="default" />. In this message flow, the check is successful and thus session setup continues.
                <vspace blankLines="1"/>
              </t>

              <t hangText="Message (5):">
                <vspace blankLines="1"/>
                <xref target="example_1_message_5" pageno="false" format="default" /> shows a SIP 200 (OK) response to the initial SIP INVITE request, sent by Bob to Bob's proxy. The SIP 200 (OK) response contains an SDP answer.
              </t>
              <t>
                <vspace blankLines="1"/>
					The "m=" line in the SDP answer indicates T.38 fax using UDPTL over DTLS.
              </t>
              <t>
                <vspace blankLines="1"/>
					The SDP setup:active attribute in the SDP answer indicates that Bob has requested to be the active endpoint.
              </t>
              <t>
                <vspace blankLines="1"/>
					The SDP fingerprint attribute in the SDP answer indicates the certificate fingerprint computed from Bob's self-signed certificate.
              </t>
              <t>
                <vspace blankLines="2"/>
              </t>

              <t>
                <figure anchor="example_1_message_5" title="Message (5)">
                  <artwork><![CDATA[
SIP/2.0 200 OK
To: <sip:bob@example.com>;tag=6418913922105372816
From: "Alice" <sip:alice@example.com>;tag=843c7b0b
Via: SIP/2.0/TLS proxy.example.com:5061;branch=z9hG4bK-0e53sadfkasldk
Via: SIP/2.0/TLS ua1.example.com;branch=z9hG4bK-0e53sadfkasldkfj
Record-Route: <sip:proxy.example.com;lr>
Call-ID: 6076913b1c39c212@REVMTEpG
CSeq: 1 INVITE
Contact: <sip:bob@ua2.example.com>
Content-Type: application/sdp
Content-Length: xxxx
Supported: from-change

v=0
o=- 8965454521 2105372818 IN IP4 ua2.example.com
s=-
c=IN IP4 ua2.example.com
t=0 0
m=image 12000 UDP/TLS/UDPTL t38
a=setup:active
a=fingerprint: SHA-1 \
  FF:FF:FF:B1:3F:82:18:3B:54:02:12:DF:3E:5D:49:6B:19:E5:7C:AB
a=T38FaxRateManagement:transferredTCF
               ]]></artwork>
                </figure>
                <vspace blankLines="1"/>
              </t>

              <t hangText="Message (6):">
                <vspace blankLines="1"/>
                <xref target="example_1_message_6" pageno="false" format="default" /> shows a SIP 200 (OK) response to the initial SIP INVITE request, sent by Alice's proxy to Alice.
                Alice checks if the certificate fingerprint calculated from the Bob's certificate received via DTLS is the same as the certificate fingerprint received in the a=fingerprint SDP attribute of <xref target="example_1_message_6" pageno="false" format="default" />. In this message flow, the check is successful and thus session setup continues.
                <vspace blankLines="1"/>
              </t>

              <t>
                <figure anchor="example_1_message_6" align="center" title="Message (6)">
                  <artwork><![CDATA[
SIP/2.0 200 OK
To: <sip:bob@example.com>;tag=6418913922105372816
From: "Alice" <sip:alice@example.com>;tag=843c7b0b
Via: SIP/2.0/TLS ua1.example.com;branch=z9hG4bK-0e53sadfkasldkfj
Record-Route: <sip:proxy.example.com;lr>
Call-ID: 6076913b1c39c212@REVMTEpG
CSeq: 1 INVITE
Contact: <sip:bob@ua2.example.com>
Content-Type: application/sdp
Content-Length: xxxx
Supported: from-change

v=0
o=- 8965454521 2105372818 IN IP4 ua2.example.com
s=-
c=IN IP4 ua2.example.com
t=0 0
m=image 12000 UDP/TLS/UDPTL t38
a=setup:active
a=fingerprint: SHA-1 \
  FF:FF:FF:B1:3F:82:18:3B:54:02:12:DF:3E:5D:49:6B:19:E5:7C:AB
a=T38FaxRateManagement:transferredTCF
               ]]></artwork>
                </figure>
                <vspace blankLines="1"/>
              </t>

              <t hangText="Message (7):">
                <vspace blankLines="1"/>
					Alice sends the SIP ACK request to Bob.
                <vspace blankLines="1"/>
              </t>

              <t hangText="Message (8):">
                <vspace blankLines="1"/>
					At this point, Bob and Alice can exchange T.38 fax securely transported using UDPTL over DTLS.
                <vspace blankLines="1"/>
              </t>

            </list>
          </t>
        </section>
		<section title="Message Flow Of T.38 Fax Replacing Audio Media Stream in An Existing Audio-Only Session">
			<t>
				<xref target="example_2_figure" pageno="false" format="default" /> focuses on T.38 fax securely transported using UDPTL over DTLS replacing audio media stream in an existing audio-only session.
			</t>
			<t>
				In this example flow, Alice acts as the passive endpoint of DTLS association and Bob acts as the active endpoint of DTLS association.
			</t>
			<t>
            <figure anchor="example_2_figure" title="Message Flow Of T.38 Fax Replacing Audio Media Stream in An Existing Audio-Only Session">
              <artwork><![CDATA[
Alice                    Proxies                   Bob
  |                        |                        |
  |        (1) Audio-only session initiation        |
  |<-----------------------+----------------------->|
  |                        |                        |
  | (2) SIP re-INVITE      |                        |
  |------------------------------------------------>|
  |                        |   (3) DTLS ClientHello |
  |<------------------------------------------------|
  |    (4) remaining messages of DTLS handshake     |
  |<----------------------------------------------->|
  |                        |                        |
  |                        |                        |
  |                        |         (5) SIP 200 OK |
  |<------------------------------------------------|
  | (6) SIP ACK            |                        |
  |------------------------------------------------>|
  |      (7) T.38 message using UDPTL over DTLS     |
  |<----------------------------------------------->|
  |                        |                        |
           ]]></artwork>
            </figure>
			</t>
			<t>
				<list style="hanging">
				<t hangText="Message (1):">
                <vspace blankLines="1"/>
                Session establishment of audio-only session. The proxies decide not to record-route.
                <vspace blankLines="1"/>
				</t>
				<t hangText="Message (2):">
                <vspace blankLines="1"/>
                Alice sends SIP re-INVITE request. SDP offer included in the SIP re-INVITE request shown in <xref target="example_2_message_2" pageno="false" format="default" />.
				</t>
				<t>
                <vspace blankLines="1"/>
				The first "m=" line in the SDP offer indicates audio media stream being removed. The second "m=" line in the SDP offer indicates T.38 fax using UDPTL over DTLS being added.
				</t>
				<t>
                <vspace blankLines="1"/>
				The SDP setup:actpass attribute in the SDP offer indicates that Alice has requested to be either the active or passive endpoint.
				</t>
				<t>
                <vspace blankLines="1"/>
				The SDP fingerprint attribute in the SDP offer indicates the certificate fingerprint computed from Alice's self-signed certificate.
				</t>
				<t>
                <vspace blankLines="2"/>
				</t>
				<t>
                <figure anchor="example_2_message_2" title="SDP offer of message (2)">
                <artwork><![CDATA[
v=0
o=- 2465353433 3524244442 IN IP4 ua1.example.com
s=-
c=IN IP4 ua1.example.com
t=0 0
m=audio 0 UDP/TLS/RTP/SAVP 0
m=image 46056 UDP/TLS/UDPTL t38
a=setup:actpass
a=fingerprint: SHA-1 \
  4A:AD:B9:B1:3F:82:18:3B:54:02:12:DF:3E:5D:49:6B:19:E5:7C:AB
a=T38FaxRateManagement:transferredTCF
               ]]></artwork>
                </figure>
                <vspace blankLines="1"/>
              </t>

              <t hangText="Message (3):">
                <vspace blankLines="1"/>
					 Bob sends a DTLS ClientHello directly to Alice.
                <vspace blankLines="1"/>
              </t>

              <t hangText="Message (4):">
                <vspace blankLines="1"/>
					Alice and Bob exchange further messages of DTLS handshake (HelloVerifyRequest, ClientHello, ServerHello, Certificate, ServerKeyExchange, CertificateRequest, ServerHelloDone, Certificate, ClientKeyExchange, CertificateVerify, ChangeCipherSpec, Finished).
              </t>
              <t>
                <vspace blankLines="1"/>
					When Bob receives Alice's certificate via DTLS, Bob checks whether the certificate fingerprint calculated from Alice's certificate received via DTLS matches the certificate fingerprint received in the a=fingerprint SDP attribute of <xref target="example_2_message_2" pageno="false" format="default" />. In this message flow, the check is successful and thus session setup continues.
                <vspace blankLines="1"/>
              </t>

              <t hangText="Message (5):">
                <vspace blankLines="1"/>
                Bob sends a SIP 200 (OK) response to the SIP re-INVITE request. The SIP 200 (OK) response contains an SDP answer shown in <xref target="example_2_message_5" pageno="false" format="default" />.
              </t>
              <t>
                <vspace blankLines="1"/>
					The first "m=" line in the SDP offer indicates audio media stream being removed. The second "m=" line in the SDP answer indicates T.38 fax using UDPTL over DTLS being added.
              </t>
              <t>
                <vspace blankLines="1"/>
					The SDP setup:active attribute in the SDP answer indicates that Bob has requested to be the active endpoint.
              </t>
              <t>
                <vspace blankLines="1"/>
					The SDP fingerprint attribute in the SDP answer indicates the certificate fingerprint computed from Bob's self-signed certificate.
              </t>
              <t>
                <vspace blankLines="2"/>
              </t>

              <t>
                <figure anchor="example_2_message_5" title="SDP answer of message (5)">
                  <artwork><![CDATA[
v=0
o=- 4423478999 5424222292 IN IP4 ua2.example.com
s=-
c=IN IP4 ua2.example.com
t=0 0
m=audio 0 UDP/TLS/RTP/SAVP 0
m=image 32000 UDP/TLS/UDPTL t38
a=setup:active
a=fingerprint: SHA-1 \
  FF:FF:FF:B1:3F:82:18:3B:54:02:12:DF:3E:5D:49:6B:19:E5:7C:AB
a=T38FaxRateManagement:transferredTCF
               ]]></artwork>
                </figure>
                <vspace blankLines="1"/>
              </t>
              <t hangText="Message (6):">
              <vspace blankLines="1"/>
					Alice sends the SIP ACK request to Bob.
                <vspace blankLines="1"/>
              </t>

              <t hangText="Message (7):">
                <vspace blankLines="1"/>
					At this point, Bob and Alice can exchange T.38 fax securely transported using UDPTL over DTLS.
                <vspace blankLines="1"/>
              </t>
            </list>
          </t>
        </section>
      </section>
	</back>
</rfc>

