<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<rfc category="std" docName="draft-ietf-mif-dhcpv6-route-option-02"
     ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="">DHCPv6 Route Options</title>

    <author fullname="Wojciech Dec" initials="W" role="editor" surname="Dec">
      <organization>Cisco Systems</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Haarlerbergweg 13-19</street>
          <city>1101 CH Amsterdam</city>
          <country>The Netherlands</country>
        </postal>

        <email>wdec@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Tomasz Mrugalski" initials="T" surname="Mrugalski">
      <organization abbrev="ISC">Internet Systems Consortium, Inc.
      </organization>
      <address>
	<postal>
	  <street>950 Charter Street</street>
	  <city>Redwood City</city>
	  <region>CA</region>
	  <code>94063</code>
	  <country>USA</country>
	</postal>
	<phone>+1 650 423 1345</phone>
	<email>tomasz.mrugalski@gmail.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Tao Sun" initials="T" surname="Sun">
      <organization>China Mobile</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Unit2, 28 Xuanwumenxi Ave</street>

          <city>Beijing</city>

          <region>Xuanwu District</region>

          <code>100053</code>

          <country>China</country>
        </postal>

        <phone></phone>

        <email>suntao@chinamobile.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Behcet Sarikaya" initials="B" surname="Sarikaya">
      <organization>Huawei USA</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>1700 Alma Dr. Suite 500</street>

          <city>Plano</city>

          <region>TX</region>

          <code>75075</code>

          <country>United States</country>
        </postal>

        <phone>+1 972-509-5599</phone>

        <facsimile></facsimile>

        <email>sarikaya@ieee.org</email>

        <uri></uri>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date day="26" month="July" year="2011" />

    <abstract>
      <t>This document describes DHCPv6 Route Options for provisioning IPv6
      routes on DHCPv6 client nodes. This is expected to improve the ability
      of an operator to configure and influence a nodes' ability to pick an
      appropriate route to a destination when this node is multi-homed and
      where other means of route configuration may be impractical.</t>
    </abstract>

    <note title="Requirements Language">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
      document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
      target="RFC2119">RFC 2119</xref>.</t>
    </note>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>The Neighbor Discovery (ND) protocol <xref
      target="RFC4861"></xref> provides a mechanism for hosts to discover one
      or more default routers on a directly connected network segment.
      Extensions to the Router Advertisement (RA) protocol defined in <xref
      target="RFC4191"></xref> allow hosts to discover the preferences for
      multiple default routers on a given link, as well as any specific routes
      advertised by these routers. This allows network administrators to
      better handle multi-homed host topologies and influence the route
      selection by the host. This ND based mechanism however is sub optimal or
      impractical in some multi-homing scenarios, where DHCPv6 <xref
      target="RFC3315"></xref>is seen to be more viable.</t>

      <t>This draft defines the DHCPv6 Route Options for provisioning IPv6
      routes on DHCPv6 clients. The proposed option is primarily envisaged for
      use by DHCPv6 client nodes that are capable of making basic IP routing
      decisions and maintaining an IPv6 routing table, broadly in line with
      the capabilities of a generic host as described in <xref
      target="RFC4191"></xref>.</t>

      <t>Throughout the document the words node and client are used as a
      reference to the device with such routing capabilities, hosting the
      DHCPv6 client software. The route information is taken to be equivalent
      to static routing, and limited in the number of required routes to a
      handful.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Problem overview">
      <t>The solution described in this document applies to multi-homed
      scenarios including ones where the client is simultaneously connected to
      multiple access network (e.g. WiFi and 3G). The following scenario is
      used to illustrate the problem as found in typical multi-homed
      residential access networks. It is duly noted that the problem is not
      specific to IPv6, occurring also with IPv4, where it is today solved by
      means of DHCPv4 classless route information option <xref
      target="RFC3442"></xref>, or alternative configuration mechanisms.</t>

      <t>In multi-homed networks, a given user's node may be connected to more
      than one gateways. Such connectivity may be realized by means of
      dedicated physical or logical links that may also be shared with other
      users nodes. In such multi-homed networks it is quite common for the
      network operator to offer the delivery of a particular type of IP
      service via a particular gateway, where the service can be characterised
      by means of specific destination IP network prefixes. Thus, from an IP
      routing perspective in order for the user node to select the appropriate
      gateway for a given destination IP prefix, recourse needs to be made to
      classic longest destination match IP routing, with the node acquiring
      such prefixes into its routing table. This is typically the remit of
      dynamic Internal Gateway Protocols (IGPs), which however are rarely used
      by operators in residential access networks. This is primarily due to
      operational costs and a desire to contain the complexity of user nodes
      and IP Edge devices to a minimum. While, IP Route configuration may be
      achieved using the ICMPv6 extensions defined in <xref
      target="RFC4191"></xref>, this mechanism does not lend itself to other
      operational constraints such as the desire to control the route
      information on a per node basis, the ability to determine whether a
      given node is actually capable of receiveing/processing such route
      information. A preferred mechanism, and one that additionally also lends
      itself to centralized management independent of the management of the
      gateways, is that of using the DHCP protocol for conveying route
      information to the nodes.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="solution" title="DHCPv6 Based Solution">
      <t>A DHCPv6 based solution allows an operator an on demand and node
      specific means of configuring static routing information. Such a
      solution also fits into network environments where the operator prefers
      to manage RG configuration information from a centralized DHCP server.
      <xref target="I-D.troan-multihoming-without-nat66"></xref> provides
      additional background to the need for a DHCPv6 solution to the
      problem.</t>

      <t>In terms of the high level operation of the solution defined in this
      draft, a DHCPv6 client interested in obtaining routing information
      request the route option using the DHCPv6 Option Request Option (ORO)
      sent to a server. A Server, when configured to do so, provides the
      requested route information as part of a nested options structure
      covering; the next-hop address; the destination prefix; the route
      metric; any additional options applicable to the destination or
      next-hop. The overall DHCPv6 design follow a similar approach to that
      used in the design of the IA_NA, IA_TA and IA_PD options in <xref
      target="RFC3633"></xref>.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="formats" title="DHCPv6 Route Options">
      <t>A DHCPv6 client interested in obtaining routing information includes
      the OPTION_IA_RT as par of its DHCPv6 Option Request Option (ORO) in
      messages directed to a server (as allowed by <xref
      target="RFC3315"></xref>, i.e. Solicit, Request, Renew, Rebind, Confirm or
      Information-request messages). A Server, when configured to do so,
      provides the requested route information using the OPTION_IA_RT option
      in messages sent in response (Advertise, and Reply). So as to allow the
      route option to be both extensible, as well as conveying detailed info
      for routes, use is made of a nested options structure. An IA_RT conveys
      one or more OPTION_NEXT_HOP options that specify the IPv6 next hop
      addresses. Each OPTION_NEXT_HOP conveys in turn one or more
      OPTION_RT_PREFIX options that represents the IPv6 destination prefixes
      reachable via the given next hop. The Formats of the OPTION_IA_RT,
      OPTION_NEXT_HOP and OPTION_RT_PREFIX are defined in the following
      sub-sections</t>

      <t>The DHCPv6 Route Option format borrows from the principles of the
      Route Information Option defined in <xref target="RFC4191"></xref>. One
      notable exception with respect to <xref target="RFC4191"></xref> is
      however that a Route Lifetime element is not defined. The information
      conveyed by the DHCPv6 Route Option is considered valid until changed or
      refreshed by general events that trigger DHCPv6 or route table state
      changes on a node, thus not requiring a specific route lifetime. In the
      event that it is desired for the client to request a refresh of the
      route information (and other stateless DHCPv6 options), use of the
      generic DHCPv6 Information Refresh Time Option, as specified in <xref
      target="RFC4242"></xref> is envisaged.</t>

      <section anchor="ia-rt-format" title="DHCPv6 Route Option Format">
        <t>To separate routing information from other options conveyed in a
        DHCPv6 message, the DHCPv6 Route Option is defined and is used to
        convey to a client one or more IPv6 routes. Each IPv6 route consists
        of an IPv6 next hop address, an IPv6 destination prefix (a.k.a. the
        destination subnet), and a host preference value for the route.
        Elements of such route (e.g. Next hops and prefixes associated with
        them) are conveyed in IA_RT's options, rather than in the IA_RT option
        itself.</t>

        <figure align="center" anchor="ia-rt-option-format"
                title="IPv6 Routes Option Format">
          <artwork><![CDATA[ 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|         OPTION_IA_RT          |          option-len           |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                                                               |
.                           IA_RT options                       .
.                                                               .
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
]]></artwork>
        </figure>

        <t><list hangIndent="10" style="hanging">
            <t hangText="option-code:">OPTION_IA_RT (TBD).</t>

            <t hangText="option-len:">Length of the IA_RT options field.</t>

            <t hangText="IA_RT options:">Options associated with this IA_RT.
            This includes, but is not limited to, OPTION_NEXT_HOP options that
            specify next hop addresses.</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>The Route option MUST NOT appear in the following DHCPv6 messages:
        Solicit, Request, Renew, Rebind, Information-Request. The Route Option
        MAY appear in ADVERTISE and REPLY messages.</t>

	<t>If there is more than one route available via specific next
	hop, server MUST send only one OPTION_NEXT_HOP for that next
	hop, which contains multiple OPTION_RT_PREFIX options. Server
	MUST NOT send more than one identical (i.e. with equal next
	hop address field) OPTION_NEXT_HOP option.</t>
	
        <t>Discussion: Traditionally, grouping options (IA_NA, IA_TA and
        IA_RD) contain an identifier field (IAID) that must be unique among
        identifiers generated by one client. It is used to differentiate
        between several options of the same type (e.g. several IA_NA options)
        that may be used simultaneously. However, it is assumed that client
        will never use more than one IA_RT option therefore such an identifier
        is not needed.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="next-hop-format" title="Next Hop Option Format">
        <t>The Next Hop Option defines the IPv6 address of the next hop,
        usually corresponding to a specific next-hop router. For each next hop
        address there can be one or more prefixes reachable via that next
        hop.</t>

        <figure align="center" anchor="next-hop-option-format"
                title="IPv6 Route Option Format">
          <artwork><![CDATA[ 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|        OPTION_NEXT_HOP        |          option-len           |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                                                               |
|                    IPv6 Next Hop Address                      |
|                       (16 octets)                             |
|                                                               |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                                                               |
|                        NEXT_HOP options                       |
.                                                               .
.                                                               .
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
]]></artwork>
        </figure>

        <t><list hangIndent="10" style="hanging">
            <t hangText="option-code:">OPTION_NEXT_HOP (TBD).</t>

            <t hangText="option-len:">16 + Length of NEXT_HOP options
            field.</t>

            <t hangText="IPv6 Next Hop Address:">16 octet long field that
            specified IPv6 address of the next hop.</t>

            <t hangText="NEXT_HOP options:">Options associated with this Next
            Hop. This includes, but is not limited to, one or more
            OPTION_RT_PREFIX options that specify prefixes reachable through
            the given next hop.</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="rt-prefix-format" title="Route Prefix Option Format">
        <t>The Route Prefix Option is used to convey information about a
        single prefix that represents the destination network. The Route
        Prefix Option is used as a sub-option in the previously defined Next
        Hop Option.</t>

        <figure align="center" anchor="rt-prefix-option-format"
                title="Route Prefix Option Format">
          <artwork><![CDATA[ 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|       OPTION_RT_PREFIX        |          option-len           |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
| Prefix-Length |     Metric    |                               | 
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+                               |
|                            Prefix                             |
|                          (16 octets)                          |
|                                                               |
|                               +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                               |                               |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+                               |
.                                                               .
.                         RT_PREFIX options                     .
.                                                               .
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
]]></artwork>
        </figure>

        <t><list hangIndent="10" style="hanging">
            <t hangText="option-code:">OPTION_RT_PREFIX (TBD).</t>

            <t hangText="option-len:">18 + length of RT_PREFIX options.</t>

            <t hangText="Prefix Length:">8-bit unsigned integer. The length in
            bits of the IP Prefix. The value ranges from 0 to 128. This field
            represents the number of valid leading bits in the prefix.</t>

            <t hangText="Metric:">Route Metric. 8-bit signed integer. The
            Route Metric indicates whether to prefer the next hop associated
            with this prefix over others, when multiple identical prefixes
            (for different next hops) have been received.</t>

            <t hangText="Prefix:">Fixed length 16 octet field containing an
            IPv6 prefix.</t>

            <t hangText="RT_PREFIX options:">Options specific to this
            particular prefix.</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <!--
      <section title="Conveying multiple Routes" />

      <t>A single option can be used to covey multiple prefixes for the same
      or different next hops. The example below illustrates a route option
      with two routes, consisting of Prefix A and Prefix B with the same next
      hop addresses Next Hop 1, and a Prefix C with Next Hop 2. Example of
      such option is presented in <xref target="option-example" />.</t>

      <figure align="center" anchor="option-example"
              title="IPv6 Route Option Format Example">
        <artwork><![CDATA[  0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|         OPTION_ROUTE          |          option-len           |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                                                               |
|                    IPv6 Next Hop Address 1                    |
|                       (16 octets)                             |
|                                                               |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
| NH1-Prefix-Len|Prefix A Length|  Reserved |Prf|  Prefix A     | 
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+               |
|                       (16 octets)                             |
|                                                               |
|                                                               |
|                                               +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+              
|                                               |Prefix B Length|
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|  Reserved |Prf|        Prefix B                               | 
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+                                               |
|                       (16 octets)                             |
|                                                               |
|                                                               |
|               +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|               |     IPv6 Next Hop Address 2                   |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+                                               |
|                                                               |
|                                                               |
|                                                               |
|               +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|               | NH2-Prefix-Len|Prefix C Length|  Reserved |Prf|                                            
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                        Prefix C                               |
|                                                               |
|                       (16 octets)                             |
|                                                               |
|                                                               |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
]]></artwork>
      </figure>
    </section> -->

    <section anchor="server" title="DHCPv6 Server Behavior">
      <t>When configured to do so s DHCPv6 server shall provide the Routes
      Option in ADVERTISE and REPLY messages sent to a client that requested
      the route option. Each Next Hop Option sent by the server must convey at
      least one Route Prefix Option.</t>

      <t>Servers SHOULD NOT send Route Option to clients that did not
      explicitly requested it, using the ORO.</t>

      <t>Servers MUST NOT send Route Option in messages other than ADVERTISE
      or REPLY.</t>

      <t>Servers MAY also include Status Code Option, defined in Section 22.13
      of the <xref target="RFC3315"></xref> to indicate the status of the
      operation.</t>

      <t>Servers MUST include the Status Code Option, if the requested routing
      configuration was not successful and SHOULD use status codes as defined
      in <xref target="RFC3315"></xref> and <xref
      target="RFC3633"></xref>.</t>

      <t>The maximum number of routing information in one DHCPv6 message
      depend on the maximum DHCPv6 message size defined in <xref
      target="RFC3315"></xref></t>

      <t>Discussion: How should server indicate that there are no specific
      routes for this particular client? The reasonable behavior is to return
      empty IA_RT option, possibly with Status Code indicating Success.
      Another approach could be to simply not return any IA_RT option.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="client" title="DHCPv6 Client Behavior">
      <t>A DHCPv6 client compliant with this specification MUST request the
      Route Option (option value TBD) in an Option Request Option (ORO) in the
      following messages: Solicit, Request, Renew, Rebind, Information-Request
      or Reconfigure. The messages are to be sent as and when specified by
      <xref target="RFC3315"></xref>.</t>

      <t>When processing a received Route Option a client MUST substitute a
      received 0::0 value in the Next Hop Option with the source IPv6 address
      of the received DHCPv6 message. It MUST also associate a received Link
      Local next hop addresses with the interface on which the client received
      the DHCPv6 message containing the route option. Such a substitution
      and/or association is useful in cases where the DHCPv6 server operator
      does not directly know the IPv6 next-hop address, other than knowing it
      is that of a DHCPv6 relay agent on the client LAN segment. DHCPv6
      Packets relayed to the client are sourced by the relay using this
      relay's IPv6 address, which could be a link local address.</t>

      <t>The Client MAY refresh assigned route information periodically. The
      generic DHCPv6 Information Refresh Time Option, as specified in <xref
      target="RFC4242"></xref>, can be used when it is desired for the client
      to periodically refresh of route information.</t>

      <t>The routes conveyed by the Route Option should be considered as
      complimentary to any other static route learning and maintenance
      mechanism used by, or on the client with one modification: The client
      MUST flush DHCPv6 installed routes following a link flap event on the
      DHCPv6 client interface over which the routes were installed. This
      requirement is necessary to automate the flushing of routes for clients
      that may move to a different network.</t>

      <t>Client MUST confirm that routers announced over DHCPv6 are
      reachable, using one of methods suitable for specific network
      type. The most common mechanism is Neighbor Unreachability
      Detection (NUD), specified in <xref target="RFC4861"/>. Client
      SHOULD use NUD to verify that received routers are reachable
      before adjusting its routing tables. Client MAY use other
      reachibality verification mechanisms specific to used network
      technology. To avoid potential long-lived routing black holes,
      client MAY periodically confirm that router is still
      reachable.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>A DHCPv6 option number of TBD for the introduced Route Option. IANA
      is requested to allocate three DHCPv6 option codes referencing this
      document: OPTION_IA_RT, OPTION_NEXT_HOP and OPTION_RT_PREFIX.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>The overall security considerations discussed in <xref
      target="RFC3315"></xref> apply also to this document. The Route option
      could be used by malicious parties to misdirect traffic sent by the
      client either as part of a denial of service or man-in-the-middle
      attack. An alternative denial of service attack could also be realized
      by means of using the route option to overflowing any known memory
      limitations of the client, or to exceed the client's ability to handle
      the number of next hop addresses.</t>

      <t>Neither of the above considerations are new and specific to the
      proposed route option. The mechanisms identified for securing DHCPv6 as
      well as reasonable checks performed by client implementations are deemed
      sufficient in addressing these problems.</t>

      <t>It is essential that clients verify that announced routers are
      indeed reachable, as specified in <xref target="client"/>. Failing to
      do so may create black hole routing problem.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Acknowledgements"
             title="Contributors and Acknowledgements">
      <t>This document would not have been possible without the significant
      contribution provided by: Arifumi Matsumoto, Hui Deng, Richard Johnson,
      Zhen Cao.</t>

      <t>The authors would also like to thank Alfred Hines, Ralph Droms, Ted
      Lemon, Ole Troan, Dave Oran, Dave Ward and Joel Halpern  for their 
      comments and useful suggestions.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3315"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3633"?>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3442"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4191"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4242"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4861"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.I-D.troan-multihoming-without-nat66"?>
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
