<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY rfc2119 PUBLIC '' 
'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml'>
]>

<rfc category="info" ipr="trust200902" docName="draft-sheng-weirds-icann-rws-dnrd-00">

    <?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
    <?rfc toc="yes"?>
    <?rfc strict="yes"?>
    <?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
    <?rfc compact="yes"?>
    <?rfc subcompact="no"?>
    <?rfc tocdepth="2"?>
    <?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
    <?rfc comments="yes" ?>
    <?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>

    <front>
        
        <title abbrev="RWS-DNRD">
            
            A RESTful Web Service for Domain Name Registration Data (RWS-DNRD)     
        </title>
                
        <author initials="S." surname="Sheng" fullname="Steve Sheng">
            <organization abbrev="ICANN">
                Internet Corporation for Assigned Names and Numbers
            </organization>
            <address>
                <postal>
                    <street>4676 Admiralty Way, Suite 330</street>
                    <country>United States of America</country>
                    <code>90292</code> <city>Marina del Rey</city>
                </postal>
                <phone>+1.310.823.9358</phone>
                <email>steve.sheng@icann.org</email>
            </address>
        </author>
        
        <author initials="F." surname="Arias" fullname="Francisco Arias">
            <organization abbrev="ICANN">
                Internet Corporation for Assigned Names and Numbers
            </organization>
            <address>
                <postal>
                    <street>4676 Admiralty Way, Suite 330</street>
                    <country>United States of America</country>
                    <code>90292</code> <city>Marina del Rey</city>
                </postal>
                <phone>+1.310.823.9358</phone>
                <email>francisco.arias@icann.org</email>
            </address>
        </author>
        
        <date month="June" year="2011"/>
        
        <area> Applications </area>
        
        <keyword>Whois</keyword>       
        <keyword>Registry</keyword>
        <keyword>Domain Name</keyword>
        <keyword>RESTful</keyword>
        <keyword>Directory Service</keyword>
               
        <abstract>
            <t>
                This document describes a pilot RESTful Web Service for querying Domain Name Registration Data (aka WHOIS data). 
            </t>
            <t>
                The purpose of this document is to facilitate discussion and serve as
                input into a standards process in this area, currently being
                discussed on the WHOIS-based Extensible Internet Registration Data
                Service (WEIRDS) mailing list
                (https://www.ietf.org/mailman/listinfo/weirds).
            </t>
        </abstract>
                
    </front>
    
    
    <middle>

        <section title="Introduction">
            <t>
                This document describes a pilot implemention by ICANN staff for querying domain name registration data through a RESTful Web-based 
                Interface. The service is implemented using the HTTP protocol <xref target="RFC2616"/> 
                and conforms to the architectural constraints of REST  <xref target="REST"/>. 
            </t>
  

            <section title="Domain Name Registration Data">
                <t>
                    Domain Name Registration Data are data that a registrant provides when s/he 
                    acquires or is assigned a domain name. By contract with the Internet Corporation for Assigned
                    Names and Numbers (hereinafter ICANN), domain name system registries - domain registries and registrars as 
                    defined by <xref target="RFC3707"/> - 
                    are to provide public access to some of these data both via the WHOIS protocol (<xref target="RFC3912"/>) as well as via 
                    a web interface.                     
                </t>
            </section> 
            
            <section title="REST and RESTful Web Service">
                <t>
                    REST stands for Representational State Transfer. It is a set of architectural constraints 
                    that is developed as an abstract model of the Web architecture. These constraints include: 
                    client-server model, stateless, cacheable, layered system, code on demand (optional), and 
                    uniform interface. REST was used to guide the redesign of the Hypertext 
                    Transfer Protocol (HTTP) and Uniform Resource Identifiers. It is widely regarded as 
                    the architecture of the Web today. Principles of REST have been used to design other 
                    protocols such as the ATOM publishing protocol.
                </t>
                <t>
                    A RESTful web service is a web service implemented using HTTP and the principles of REST. 
                    It is a collection of resources, with three defined aspects: 1) The "verbs" of the service 
                    are strictly those defined by the HTTP methods GET, PUT, POST, and DELETE, 2) The "verbs" 
                    are used to act upon resources, and 3) resources are addressable using URLs. </t> 

            </section>
            <section title="Why RESTful?">
                
                <t> Compared to the WHOIS protocol as defined in RFC 3912, we felt the RESTful approach
                    offers the following advantages: </t>
<t>
                <list>
                     <t> Standardized output and error format: The base response output format is XML, which when paired with a well-defined schema would allow for automated processing.</t>
                     <t> Support for internationalisation: RWS has complete support for internationalised registration data, as well as IDNs with U-labels, 
                         by using the XML data format, which uses Unicode.</t>                     
                     <t> Authentication and access control: HTTP, the transport for RWS, already supports authentication, and by means of using these capabilities, RWS makes technically possible to implement granular permissions over registration data if required.</t>
                     <t> Addressable Whois Service: RWS requires the use of a URI/URL standard structure for each object/resource. This has the additional benefit of providing a widely recognized manner to refer unambiguously to objects in Whois.</t>
                     <t> Increased Usability: Some of the inherent capabilities of the HTTP protocol (such as redirects) can be used to provide 
                         additional functionality such as automatic referrals to more specific WHOIS data sources without requiring specialized parsing 
                         by the client. </t>
                    <t> Authenticity of Origin: RWS provided over HTTPS offers confidence in the origin of the information.</t>
                    <t> Leverage existing infrastructure and expertise: RWS is HTTP-based and can be supported using popular web server infrastructures. Web administration is a skill-set and resource likely already commonplace inside registries and registrars. Similarly, RWS can benefit from existing technology to implement load-balance servers, cache answers to minimize network traffic, etc.</t>
                 </list>                                  
</t>
            </section>                       
        </section>
        
        
        <section title="Terminology">
            <t>
                For convenience, this implementation can be referred to as the "RESTful Web Service for Domain Name Registration Data" 
                or "RWS - DNRD". The following terminology is used by this specification:
                <list>
                    
                    <t>
                        Domain Name Registration Data (aka WHOIS data) - refers to the data that registrants provide when registering a
                        domain name. Part of these data are sometimes contractually required to be made publicly available, these includes the name of the registrant, 
                        name servers, the expiration date of the registration, etc. (see section 3.3 section of Registrar Accreditation Agreement).         
                    </t>
  
                    <t>
                        URI - A Uniform Resource Identifier as defined in <xref target="RFC3986"/>.
                    </t>
                    <t>
                        IRI - An internationalized Resource Identifier as defined in <xref target="RFC3987"/>.
                    </t>
                    <t>
                        Resource - A network-accessible data object or service identified by an URI, as 
                        defined in <xref target="RFC2616"/>. In this context, resources refers to the 
                        registration data objects.
                    </t>
                    <t>
                        Representation - An entity included with a request or response as defined in 
                        <xref target="RFC2616"/>.
                    </t>
                </list>
            </t>
        </section>
                
        <section title="Implmentation Description">

            <t>
                ICANN's RWS-DNRD specifies the URL structure, the methods to be used, the 
                responses and its format, and the result codes.
            </t>
            <t>
                As its name implies RWS-DNRD is Web-based, i.e., uses HTTP <xref target="RFC2616"/> as its 
                transport. Given its RESTful nature it only uses the standard HTTP methods. And given
                it is read-only, it only usea the GET and HEAD methods.
            </t>

            <section title="The Request" anchor="request">
                <t>
                    The server accepts standard HTTP "GET" requests for the resources it serves. The client sends its request with the following URI structure. 
                </t>
                
            <section title="URL structure" anchor="urlStructure">
              
              <t>
              <list>
                <t> Meta Data - URL: / Display information about resources, URI scheme and allowed operations
                </t>
                
                <t> Domain Name Request -  /domain/&lt;name&gt;/ 
                    example: http://whois.test/domain/example.test/       
      
                </t>
                <t> Contact Request - /contact/&lt;id&gt;/
                example: http://whois.test/conact/CID-4005/     </t>
                

                <t> Host Request - /host/&lt;name&gt;/
                  example: http://whois.test/host/ns1.example.test/       
                    
                </t>
              </list>
                  </t>
                
            </section>
            
        </section>
            
            <section title="The Response" anchor="response">
                <t>
                    The RWS-RDNRD server provide responses in XML format as specified below and can offer responses
                    in other formats; currently only HTML and plain text. The client signals the preferred format 
                    using the standard HTTP "Accept:" header. The client can also signal the preferred format by 
                    adding a DOS-file-style extension to the resource. For example, "/xreg/rsrc1.xml". If the 
                    client specifies no preferred format, the server responds in XML. If the client signals 
                    one format with the HTTP "Accept:" header and another with the extension style, the server 
                    ignores the preference signaled with the former.
                </t> 
                <t>
                    The pilot implementation currently support the following values for the Accept header: application/xml 
                    for XML, text/html for HTML, and text/plain for plain text.
                </t>
                
                <t>
                    The root element for a RWS-DNRD response is &lt;rws&gt;.
                    This element contains one or more &lt;result&gt; elements that are explained in the following section.   
                </t>
                <t>Example of root element object:</t>
                <t>
                    <figure><artwork><![CDATA[

<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rws:rws xmlns:rws="urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:rws-1.0"
    ...
    <rws:result>
    ...
    </rws:result>
    
    <rws:result>
    ...
    </rws:result>
    ...
</rws:rws>]]>

                    </artwork></figure>
                </t>
                
                
             <section title="Response for Domain Names">
                 <t> Example Query: http://whois.test/domain/example.test/   </t>  
                 
                 <t> Response: </t>
                 
                 <t>
                     
                     <figure><artwork>
                         <![CDATA[
                                         
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rws xmlns="urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:rws-1.0" 
     xmlns:rws="urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:rws-1.0">
  <result>
    <rws:domain xmlns="urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:rwsDomain-1.0" 
         xmlns:rwsDomain="urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:rwsDomain-1.0">
      <name>example.test</name>
      <roid>9690-TEST</roid>
      <status s="clientHold"/>
      <status s="clientRenewProhibited"/>
      <status s="clientUpdateProhibited"/>

      <registrant href="/contact/4447">4447</registrant>
      <contact type="admin" href="/contact/4447">4447</contact>
      <contact type="tech" href="/contact/4447">4447</contact>
      <ns>
        <hostObj href="/host/ns1.example.test">
            ns1.example.test
        </hostObj>
        <hostObj href="/host/ns2.example.test">
            ns2.example.test
        </hostObj>
        <hostObj href="/host/ns3.example.test">
            ns3.example.test
        </hostObj>
      </ns>
      <clID>793</clID>
      <clName>XYZ Corporation</clName>
      <crID>1289</crID>
      <crDate>1992-07-26T09:10:56Z</crDate>

      <exDate>2019-01-21T10:11:18Z</exDate>
    </rws:domain>
  </result>
</rws>
             
                     
                     ]]>
                     </artwork></figure>
                 </t>
             </section>
            
                <section title="Response for Contacts">
                    <t> Example Query: http://whois.test/conact/4447/   </t>  
                    
                    <t> Response:  </t>
                    
                    <t>
                        
                        <figure><artwork>
                            <![CDATA[

<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rws xmlns="urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:rws-1.0" 
     xmlns:rws="urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:rws-1.0">
  <result>
    <rws:contact xmlns="urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:rwsContact-1.0" 
         xmlns:rwsContact="urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:rwsContact-1.0">
      <id>4447</id>
      <roid>4447-TEST</roid>
      <status s="clientDeleteProhibited"/>
      <status s="clientTransferProhibited"/>
      <status s="ok"/>

      <rwsContact:postalInfo 
         xmlns="urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:contact-1.0" type="int">
        <name>Nova D Janes</name>
        <addr>
          <street>1755 XYZ Avenue</street>
          <city>ABC</city>
          <sp>PA</sp>
          <pc>15206</pc>
          <cc>US</cc>
        </addr>
      </rwsContact:postalInfo>
      <voice>+1.1234567890</voice>
      <fax>+1.1234567890</fax>
      <email>Nova.D.Janes@xyz.com</email>
      <clID>1289</clID>
      <crID>1289</crID>
      <crDate>1995-11-29T03:17:09Z</crDate>
      <trDate>1997-02-10T21:56:43Z</trDate>
    </rws:contact>
  </result>
</rws>
                     
                     ]]>
                        </artwork></figure>
                    </t>
                <section title="Response for Host Names">
                    <t> Example Query: http://whois.test/host/ns1.example.test/   </t>  
                    
                    <t> Response: </t>
                    
                    <t>
                        
                        <figure><artwork>
                            <![CDATA[
                     
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rws xmlns="urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:rws-1.0" 
    xmlns:rws="urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:rws-1.0">
  <result>
    <rws:host xmlns="urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:rwsHost-1.0">
      <name>ns1.example.test</name>
      <roid>8998-TEST</roid>
      <status s="ok"/>
      <status s="clientDeleteProhibited"/>
      <status s="serverDeleteProhibited"/>

      <addr ip="v4">188.17.219.3</addr>
      <clID>1289</clID>
      <crID>1289</crID>
      <crDate>1995-01-12T01:26:27Z</crDate>
      <upID>1289</upID>
      <upDate>2005-03-01T08:43:11Z</upDate>

    </rws:host>
  </result>
</rws>

                     ]]>
                        </artwork></figure>
                    </t>
                </section>
            
                </section>
                
             
             
             
            </section>
            
                            
        </section> 
       

        <section title="Error Codes" anchor="resultCodes">
            <t>
                In compliance with the REST paradigm any error information is returned in the form of a 
                standard HTTP response with an HTTP status code describing the error and a text/plain body 
                message describing the exception causing the error response. In this version we are using only 
                standard HTTP codes (http://www.iana.org/assignments/http-status-codes).
            </t>
            <t>
                We plan to define specialized error codes in the future. 
            </t>
        </section>
            

        <section title="Formal XML Syntax" anchor="formalSyntax">
           <t>
               The formal syntax presented here is a complete schema representation
               suitable for automated validation of an XML instance. We base our implementation on the 
               Extension Provisioning Protocol (EPP). We reference and include the following EPP schemas: 

               <list>

                   <t>  <xref target="RFC5730"/> - Extensible Provisioning Protocol (EPP) </t>
                   <t>  <xref target="RFC5731"/> - Extensible Provisioning Protocol (EPP) Domain Name Mapping </t>
                   <t>  <xref target="RFC5732"/> - Extensible Provisioning Protocol (EPP) Host Mapping </t>
                   <t>  <xref target="RFC5733"/> - Extensible Provisioning Protocol (EPP) Contact Mapping </t>
                   
                   </list>
           </t>
                        
            <section title ="Contact XML Schema">
                
                <figure><artwork>
                    <![CDATA[
                
<schema targetNamespace="urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:rwsContact-1.0" 
     elementFormDefault="qualified">
     
<!--
Import common element types.
-->
<import namespace="urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:eppcom-1.0"/>
<import namespace="urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:rws-1.0" />
<import namespace="urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:contact-1.0" />
    
<annotation>
    <documentation>
        RESTful Whois schema for contact.
    </documentation>
</annotation>

<!--
Child elements of Contact object
-->
<complexType name="rwsContactType">
 <sequence>
   <element name="id" type="eppcom:clIDType"/>
   <element name="roid" type="eppcom:roidType"/>
   <element name="status" type="contact:statusType" maxOccurs="7"/>
   <element name="postalInfo" type="contact:postalInfoType" 
       maxOccurs="2"/>
   <element name="voice" type="contact:e164Type" minOccurs="0"/>
   <element name="fax" type="contact:e164Type" minOccurs="0"/>
   <element name="email" type="eppcom:minTokenType"/>
   <element name="clID" type="eppcom:clIDType"/>
   <element name="crID" type="eppcom:clIDType"/>
   <element name="crDate" type="dateTime"/>
   <element name="upID" type="eppcom:clIDType" minOccurs="0"/>
   <element name="upDate" type="dateTime" minOccurs="0"/>
   <element name="trDate" type="dateTime" minOccurs="0"/>
   <element name="extension" type="rws:extAnyType" minOccurs="0"/>
 </sequence>
</complexType>

<!--
End of schema.
-->
</schema>
                
                
                
                ]]>
             </artwork>   
                </figure>
                
                </section>
            
            
           <section title="Domain Name XML Schema">
                    
               <figure><artwork>
                   <![CDATA[

<schema targetNamespace="urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:rwsDomain-1.0" 
     elementFormDefault="qualified">

<!--
Import common element types
-->
<import namespace="urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:eppcom-1.0" />
<import namespace="urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:domain-1.0" />
<import namespace="urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:contact-1.0" />
<import namespace="urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:rws-1.0" />

<annotation>
  <documentation>
     RESTful Whois schema for domains
  </documentation>
</annotation>

<!--
Child elements of a Domain object
-->
<complexType name="rwsDomainType">
  <sequence>
	<element name="name" type="eppcom:labelType"/>
	<element name="uName" type="eppcom:labelType" minOccurs="0"/>
	<element name="roid" type="eppcom:roidType"/>
	<element name="status" type="domain:statusType"
       maxOccurs="unbounded"/>
    <element name="registrant" type="rwsDomain:registrantType" 
       minOccurs="0"/>
	<element name="contact" type="rwsDomain:contactType" 
	   minOccurs="0" maxOccurs="unbounded"/>
	<element name="ns" type="rwsDomain:nsType" minOccurs="0"/>
	<element name="host" type="rwsDomain:hostObjType" 
	   minOccurs="0" maxOccurs="unbounded"/>
	<element name="clID" type="eppcom:clIDType"/>
	<element name="clName" type="contact:postalLineType"/>
	<element name="crID" type="eppcom:clIDType" minOccurs="0"/>
	<element name="crDate" type="dateTime" minOccurs="0"/>
	<element name="upID" type="eppcom:clIDType" minOccurs="0"/>
	<element name="upDate" type="dateTime" minOccurs="0"/>
	<element name="exDate" type="dateTime" minOccurs="0"/>
	<element name="trDate" type="dateTime" minOccurs="0"/>
	<element name="extension" type="rws:extAnyType" 
	   minOccurs="0"/>
  </sequence>
</complexType>

<complexType name="registrantType">
    <simpleContent>
        <extension base="eppcom:clIDType">
            <attribute name="href" type="anyURI"/>
        </extension>
    </simpleContent>
</complexType>

<complexType name="contactType">
    <simpleContent>
        <extension base="eppcom:clIDType">
            <attribute name="type" type="domain:contactAttrType"/>
            <attribute name="href" type="anyURI"/>
        </extension>
    </simpleContent>
</complexType>

<complexType name="nsType">
    <choice>
        <element name="hostObj" type="rwsDomain:hostObjType" 
            maxOccurs="unbounded"/>
        <element name="hostAttr" type="domain:hostAttrType" 
            maxOccurs="unbounded"/>
    </choice>
</complexType>

<complexType name="hostObjType">
    <simpleContent>
        <extension base="eppcom:labelType">
            <attribute name="href" type="anyURI"/>
        </extension>
    </simpleContent>
</complexType>

<!--
  End of schema.
-->
</schema>

]]>
</artwork></figure>       
            </section>

<section title="Host XML Schema">
    
    <figure><artwork>
        <![CDATA[
        
<schema targetNamespace="urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:rwsHost-1.0" 
    elementFormDefault="qualified">
    
<!--
Import common element types
-->
<import namespace="urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:eppcom-1.0" />
<import namespace="urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:rws-1.0" />
<import namespace="urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:host-1.0" />
    
<annotation>
    <documentation>
       RESTful Whois schema for hosts
    </documentation>
</annotation>

<!--
Child elements of Host object
-->
<complexType name="rwsHostType">
  <sequence>
     <element name="name" type="eppcom:labelType"/>
     <element name="roid" type="eppcom:roidType"/>
     <element name="status" type="host:statusType" maxOccurs="7"/>
     <element name="addr" type="host:addrType" minOccurs="0" 
        maxOccurs="unbounded"/>
     <element name="clID" type="eppcom:clIDType"/>
     <element name="crID" type="eppcom:clIDType"/>
     <element name="crDate" type="dateTime"/>
     <element name="upID" type="eppcom:clIDType" minOccurs="0"/>
     <element name="upDate" type="dateTime" minOccurs="0"/>
     <element name="trDate" type="dateTime" minOccurs="0"/>
     <element name="extension" type="rws:extAnyType" minOccurs="0"/>
  </sequence>
</complexType>

<!--
End of schema.
-->
</schema>

]]>
    </artwork></figure>
    
    </section>

            <section title="RWS XML Schema">
            
                <figure><artwork>
                    <![CDATA[
                    
<schema targetNamespace="urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:rws-1.0" 
    elementFormDefault="qualified">

<!--
    Import common element types
-->
<import namespace="urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:eppcom-1.0" />
<import namespace="urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:rwsContact-1.0" />
<import namespace="urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:rwsHost-1.0" />
<import namespace="urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:rwsDomain-1.0" />

<annotation>
    <documentation>
            RESTful Whois schema
    </documentation>
</annotation>

<!--
    Root element
-->
<element name="rws" type="rws:rwsType"/>
<attribute name="uri" type="anyURI"/>

<!--
    RWS types
-->
<complexType name="rwsType">
  <sequence>
    <element name="result" type="rws:resultType" minOccurs="0"
        maxOccurs="unbounded"/>
  </sequence>
</complexType>

<complexType name="resultType">
  <choice>
    <element name="domain" type="rwsDomain:rwsDomainType"/>
    <element name="contact" type="rwsContact:rwsContactType"/>
    <element name="host" type="rwsHost:rwsHostType"/>
    <element name="extension" type="rws:extAnyType"/>
  </choice>
</complexType>

<!--
    Extension framework type
-->
<complexType name="extAnyType">
  <sequence>
    <any namespace="##other" maxOccurs="unbounded"/>
  </sequence>
</complexType>

<!--
    End of schema.
-->
</schema>
]]>
                </artwork></figure>
            </section>
            
        </section>


        
    
        <section title="Internationalization Considerations">
            <t>
                Information published in RWS is represented in XML, which provides native support for encoding 
                information using the Unicode character set and its more compact representations including 
                UTF-8. Conformant XML processors recognize both UTF-8 and UTF-16. Though XML includes 
                provisions to identify and use other character encodings through use of an "encoding" attribute 
                in an &lt;?xml?&gt; declaration, use of UTF-8 is preferred.
            </t>
        </section>


        <section title="IANA Considerations">
            <t>
                TBD
            </t>
        </section>


        <section title="Security Considerations">
      
            <section title="URIs and IRIs">
                <t>
                    RWS-DNRD implementations use URIs and IRIs.  See Section 7 of <xref target="RFC3986"/> and 
                    Section 8 of <xref target="RFC3987"/> for security considerations related to their handling 
                    and use.
                </t>
            </section>
        </section>
        
        
        <section title="Acknowledgments">
            <t>
                The authors would like to acknowledge the following individuals for their input: 
                Andrew Sullivan, and Dave Piscitello.
            </t>
        </section>
                                
    </middle>

    <back>
        
        <references title='Normative References'>	
            
            <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2616" ?>
            <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3986" ?>
            <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3987" ?>
            <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5730" ?>
            <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5731" ?>
            <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5732" ?>
            <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5733" ?>
            
            <reference anchor="REST">
                <front>
                    <title>
                        Principled Design of the Modern Web Architecture
                    </title>
                    <author initials="R." surname="Fielding" fullname="Roy T. Fielding"/> 
                    <author initials="R." surname="Taylor" fullname="Soy T. Fielding"/> 
                    <date month="May" year="2002"/>
                </front>
                <seriesInfo name="ACM Transactions on Internet Technology" value="Vol. 2, No. 2"/>	
            </reference>
            
        </references>
        
        <references title='Informative References'>
            
            <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3707" ?>
            <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3912" ?>
            
        </references>

        
    </back>


</rfc>
