<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY rfc2119 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc6489 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6489.xml">
<!ENTITY ietf-pkix-cmc-serverkeygeneration SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.draft-ietf-pkix-cmc-serverkeygeneration-00.xml">
<!ENTITY ietf-sidr-bgpsec-reqs SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.draft-ietf-sidr-bgpsec-reqs-03.xml">
<!ENTITY ietf-sidr-bgpsec-ops SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.draft-ietf-sidr-bgpsec-ops-05.xml">
<!ENTITY ietf-sidr-rtr-keying SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.draft-ietf-sidr-rtr-keying-00.xml">
<!ENTITY ietf-pkix-est SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.draft-ietf-pkix-est-02.xml">
]>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc iprnotified="no" ?>
<?rfc strict="no" ?>
<rfc category="std" docName="draft-ietf-sidr-bgpsec-rollover-01"
     ipr="trust200902" updates="">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="BGPSEC rollover">BGPSEC router key rollover as an
    alternative to beaconing</title>

    <author fullname="Roque Gagliano" initials="R.G.M." surname="Gagliano">
      <organization>Cisco Systems</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Avenue des Uttins 5</street>

          <city>Rolle</city>

          <region>VD</region>

          <code>1180</code>

          <country>Switzerland</country>
        </postal>

        <email>rogaglia@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Keyur Patel" initials="K.P." surname="Patel">
      <organization>Cisco Systems</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>170 W. Tasman Driv</street>

          <city>San Jose</city>

          <region>CA</region>

          <code>95134</code>

          <country>CA</country>
        </postal>

        <email>keyupate@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Brian Weis" initials="B.W." surname="Weis">
      <organization>Cisco Systems</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>170 W. Tasman Driv</street>

          <city>San Jose</city>

          <region>CA</region>

          <code>95134</code>

          <country>CA</country>
        </postal>

        <email>bew@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date month="October" year="2012"/>

    <abstract>
      <t>BGPSEC will need to address the impact from regular and emergency
      rollover processes for the BGPSEC End-Entity (EE) certificates that will
      be performed by Certificate Authorities (CAs) participating at the
      Resource Public Key Infrastructure (RPKI). This document provides
      general recommendations for that process and specifies how this process
      is used to control BGPSEC's window of exposure to replay attacks.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Requirements notation">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
      document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
      target="RFC2119"/>.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>In BGPSEC, a key rollover (or re-keying) is the process of changing a
      router's key pair (or pairs), issuing the corresponding new End-Entity
      certificate and (if the old certificate is still valid) revoking the old
      certificate. This process will need to happen at regular intervals,
      normally due to local policies at each network. This document provides
      general recommendations for that process that Certificate Practice
      Statements (CPS) documents MAY reference.</t>

      <t>When a router receives (or creates depending of the key provisioning
      mechanism to be selected) a new key pair, this key pair will be used to
      sign new BGP UPDATE messages that are originated or that transit through
      the BGP speaker. Additionally, the BGP speaker MUST refresh its outbound
      BGP UPDATE messages to update its respective BGPSEC attribute by
      including the correspondent signature performed with the new key. When
      the rollover process finishes, the old BGPSEC certificate (and its key)
      will not longer be valid and thus any BGP UPDATE that includes a BGPSEC
      attribute with a signature performed by the old key will be invalid.
      Consequently, if the router do not refresh its outbound BGP UPDATE
      messages, routing information may be lost after the rollover process is
      finished.</t>

      <t>As a key rollover process invalidates BGP UPDATE messages signed with
      the old key, frequent key rollover processes could be used to control
      BGPSEC's window of exposure to replay attacks as required by <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-sidr-bgpsec-reqs"/>. This document explores the
      operational environment to achieve this goal.</t>

      <t>In <xref target="I-D.ietf-sidr-rtr-keying"/>, the "operator-driven"
      method is introduced and it enables that a key pair could be shared
      among different BGP Speakers. In this scenario, the roll-over of the
      correspondent BGPSEC certificate will impact all the BGP Speakers
      sharing the same private key.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="BGPSEC" title="Key rollover in BGPSEC">
      <t>A BGPSEC EE certificate (as any X.509 certificate) will required a
      rollover process due to causes such as: <list hangIndent="6"
          style="hanging">
          <t hangText="BGPSEC scheduled rollover:">BGPSEC certificates have an
          expiration date (NotValidAfter) that requires a frequent rollover
          process. The validity period for these certificates is typically
          expressed at the CA's CPS document.</t>

          <t hangText="BGPSEC certificate fields changes:">Information
          contained in a BGPSEC certificate (such as the ASN or the Subject)
          may need to be changed.</t>

          <t hangText="BGPSEC emergency rollover">Some special circumstances
          (such as a compromised key) may require the replacement of a BGPSEC
          certificate.</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>In most of these cases (probably excepting when the key has been
      compromised), it is possible to generate a new certificate without
      changing the key pair. This practice simplifies the rollover process as
      the correspondent BGP speakers do not even need to be aware of the
      changes to its correspondent certificate. However, not replacing the
      certificate key for a long period of time increases the risk that the
      certificate key may be compromised.</t>

      <section anchor="re-keying"
               title="A proposed process for BGPSEC key rollover">
        <t>The BGPSEC key rollover process should be dependent of the key
        provisioning mechanisms that would be in place. The key provisioning
        mechanisms for BGPSEC are not yet fully documented (see <xref
        target="I-D.ietf-sidr-rtr-keying"/> as a work in progress document).
        We will assume that an automatic provisioning mechanism will be in
        place. (A possible provisioning mechanism is the Enrollment over
        Secure Transport (EST) <xref target="I-D.ietf-pkix-est"/>). That
        protocol will allow BGPSEC code to include automatic re-keying scripts
        with minimum development cost.</t>

        <t>If we work under the assumption that an automatic mechanism will
        exist to rollover a BGPSEC certificate, a possible process could be:
        <list style="numbers">
            <t>New Certificate Pre-Publication: The first step in the rollover
            mechanism is to pre-publish the new public key in a new
            certificate. In order to accomplish this goal, the new key pair
            and certificate will need to be generated and published at the
            appropriate RPKI repository publication point. The details of this
            process will vary as they depend on whether the keys are assigned
            per-BGP speaker or shared, whether the keys are generated on each
            BGP speaker or in a central location and wether the RPKI
            repository is locally or externally hosted.</t>

            <t>Staging Period: A staging period will be required from the time
            a new certificate is published in the RPKI global repository until
            the time it is fetched by RPKI caches around the globe. The exact
            minimum staging time is not clear and will require experimental
            results from RPKI operations. RPKI repository design documents
            mention a lower limit of 24 hours (NOTE: need reference only one I
            found is the ops document). If rollovers will be done frequently
            and we want to avoid the stage period, an administrator can always
            provision two certificate for every router. In this case when the
            rollover operation is needed, the relying parties around the globe
            would already have the new keys. A staging period may not be
            possible to implement during emergency key rollover, in which case
            routing information may be lost.</t>

            <t>Twilight: At this moment, the BGP speaker that hold the private
            key that has been rolled-over will stop using the OLD key for
            signing and start using the NEW key. Also, the router will
            generate appropriate BGP UPDATES just as in the typical operation
            of refreshing out-bound BGP polices. This operation may generate a
            great number of BGP UPDATE messages (due to the need to refresh
            BGP outbound policies). In any given BGP SPEAKER, the Twilight
            moment may be different for every peer in order to distribute the
            system load (probably in the order of minutes to avoid reaching
            any expiration time).</t>

            <t>Certificate Revocation: This is an optional step. As part of
            the rollover process, a CA MAY decide to revoke the OLD
            certificate by publishing its serial number on the CA's CRL. On
            the other side, the CA will just let the OLD certificate to expire
            and not revoke it. This chose will depend on the reasons that
            motivated the rollover process.</t>

            <t>RPKI-Router Protocol Withdrawals: Either due to the revocation
            of the OLD certificate or to the expiration of the OLD
            certificate's validation, the RPKI relying parties around the
            globe will need to communicate to their RTR peers that the OLD
            certificate's public key is not longer valid (rtr withdrawal
            message). It is not documented yet what will be a router's
            reaction to a RTR withdrawal message but it should include the
            removal of any RIB entry that includes a BGPSEC attribute signed
            with that key and the generation of the correspondent BGP
            WITHDRAWALs (either implicit or explicit).</t>
          </list>The proposed rollover mechanism will depend on the existence
        of an automatic provisioning process for BGPSEC certificates. It will
        require a staging mechanism based on the RPKI propagation time of
        around 24hours, and it will generate BGP UPDATES for all prefixes in
        the router been re-keyed.</t>

        <t>The first two steps (New Certificate Pre-Publication and Staging
        Period) could happen ahead of time from the rest of the process as
        each network operators could prepare itself to accelerate a future key
        roll-over.</t>

        <t>When a new BGPSEC certificate is generated without changing its
        key, steps 3 (Twilight) and 5 (RPKI-Router Protocol Withdrawals)
        SHOULD not be executed.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="replay"
             title="BGPSEC key rollover as a measure against replays attacks in BGPSEC">
      <t>There are two typical generic measures to mitigate replay attacks in
      any protocol: the addition of a timestamp or the addition of a serial
      number. Currently BGPSEC offers a timestamp (expiration time) as a
      protection against re-play attacks of BGPSEC attributes. The process
      requires all BGP Speakers that originate a BGP UPDATE to re-advertise
      ("beacon") the message before it expires. This requirement changes a
      long standing BGP operational practice and the community has been
      searching for alternatives.</t>

      <section anchor="requirements"
               title="BGPSEC Replay attack window requirement">
        <t>In <xref target="I-D.ietf-sidr-bgpsec-reqs"/> Section 4.3, the need
        to limit the vulnerability to replay attacks is described. One
        important comment is that during a windows of exposure, a replay
        attack is effective only if there was a downstream topology change
        that makes the signed AS path not longer current. In other words, if
        there have been no topology changes, no security threat comes from a
        replay of a BGP UPDATE message (the signed information is still
        valid)</t>

        <t>The BGPSEC Ops document <xref target="I-D.ietf-sidr-bgpsec-ops"/>
        gives some ideas of requirements for the size of the BGPSEC windows of
        exposure to replay attacks. At that document, it is stated that for
        the vast majority of the prefixes, the requirement will be in the
        order of days or weeks. For a very small but critical fraction of the
        prefixes, the requirement may be in the order of hours.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="proposal"
               title="BGPSEC key rollover as a mechanism to protect against replay attacks">
        <t>The question we would like to ask is: can the key rollover process
        earlier described provide a similar protection against replay attacks
        without the need for beaconing?</t>

        <t>The answer is that YES when the window requirement is in the order
        of days and the BGP speaker re-keying is the edge router of the origin
        AS and the full process is completed (i.e. the OLD and NEW certificate
        do not share the same key). By using re-keying, you are letting the
        BGPSEC certificate validation time as your timestamp against replay
        attacks. However, the use of frequent key rollovers comes with an
        additional administrative cost and risks if the process fails. As
        documented before, re-keying should be supported by automatic tools
        and for the great majority of the Internet it will be done with good
        lead time to correct any risk.</t>

        <t>For a transit AS that also originates BGP UPDATES for its own
        prefixes, the key rollover process may generate a large number of
        UPDATE messages (even the complete Default Free Zone or DFZ). For this
        reason, it is recommended that routers in this scenario been
        provisioned with two certificates: one to sign BGP UPDATES in transit
        and a second one to sign BGP UPDATE for prefixes originated in its AS.
        Only the second certificate (for prefixes originated in its AS) should
        be rolled-over frequently as a means of limiting replay attach
        windows. The transit BGPSEC certificate is expected to be longer
        living than the origin BGPSEC certificate.</t>

        <t>Advantage of Re-keying as replay attack protection mechanism: <list
            style="numbers">
            <t>Does not require beaconing</t>

            <t>All expiration policies are maintained in RPKI</t>

            <t>Most of the additional administrative cost is paid by the
            provider that wants to protect its infrastructure (RP load will
            increase as there is a need to validate more BGPSEC
            certificates)</t>

            <t>Can be implemented in coordination with planned topology
            changes by either origin ASes or transit ASes (if I am changing
            providers, I rollover)</t>

            <t>Eliminates the discussion on who has the authority over the
            expiration time</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>Disadvantage of Re-keying as replay attack protection mechanism:
        <list style="numbers">
            <t>More administrative load due to frequent rollover, although how
            frequent is still not clear. Some initial ideas in <xref
            target="I-D.ietf-sidr-bgpsec-ops"/></t>

            <t>Minimum window size bounded by RPKI propagation time to RPKI
            caches for new certificate and CRL (2x propagation time). If
            pre-provisioning done ahead of time the minimum windows size is
            reduced (to 1x propagation time for the CRL). However, more
            experimentation is needed when RPKI and RPs are more massively
            deployed.</t>

            <t>Increases dynamics and size of RPKI repository.</t>

            <t>More load on RPKI caches, but they are meant to do this
            work.</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>No IANA considerations</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Security Considerations">
      <t>No security considerations.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>We would like to acknowledge Randy Bush, Sriram Kotikalapudi, Stephen
      Kent and Sandy Murphy.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      &rfc2119;

      &rfc6489;
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      &ietf-pkix-cmc-serverkeygeneration;

      &ietf-pkix-est;

      &ietf-sidr-bgpsec-reqs;

      &ietf-sidr-bgpsec-ops;

      &ietf-sidr-rtr-keying;
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
