<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8">
<!DOCTYPE RFC SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt'?>
<?rfc toc='yes'?>
<?rfc tocompact='yes'?>
<?rfc tocdepth='6'?>
<?rfc tocindent='no'?>
<?rfc symrefs='yes'?>
<?rfc compact='yes'?>
<rfc ipr="pre5378Trust200902" category="info" docName="draft-ietf-rohc-hcoipsec-12" obsoletes="" updates="" submissionType="IETF" xml:lang="en">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="Integration of ROHC over IPsec SAs">Integration of Robust Header Compression (ROHC) over IPsec Security Associations</title>
    <author initials="E." surname="Ertekin" fullname="Emre Ertekin">
      <organization>Booz Allen Hamilton</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>5220 Pacific Concourse Drive, Suite 200</street>
          <city>Los Angeles</city>
          <region>CA</region>
          <code>90045</code>
          <country>US</country>
        </postal>
        <email>ertekin_emre@bah.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author initials="R." surname="Jasani" fullname="Rohan Jasani">
      <organization>Booz Allen Hamilton</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>13200 Woodland Park Dr.</street>
          <city>Herndon</city>
          <region>VA</region>
          <code>20171</code>
          <country>US</country>
        </postal>
        <email>ro@breakcheck.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author initials="C." surname="Christou" fullname="Chris Christou">
      <organization>Booz Allen Hamilton</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>13200 Woodland Park Dr.</street>
          <city>Herndon</city>
          <region>VA</region>
          <code>20171</code>
          <country>US</country>
        </postal>
        <email>christou_chris@bah.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author initials="C." surname="Bormann" fullname="Carsten Bormann">
      <organization>Universitaet Bremen TZI</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Postfach 330440</street>
          <city>Bremen  D-28334</city>
          <country>Germany</country>
        </postal>
        <email>cabo@tzi.org</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date month="December" year="2009" />
    <abstract>
      <t>IP Security (IPsec) provides various security services for IP traffic.  However, the benefits of IPsec come at the cost of increased overhead.  This document outlines a framework for integrating Robust Header Compression (ROHC) over IPsec (ROHCoIPsec).  By compressing the inner headers of IP packets, ROHCoIPsec proposes to reduce the amount of overhead associated with the transmission of traffic over IPsec Security Associations (SAs).</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>
  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction" toc="default">
      <t>
   This document outlines a framework for integrating ROHC [ROHC] over
   IPsec [IPSEC] (ROHCoIPsec).  The goal of ROHCoIPsec is to reduce the
   protocol overhead associated with packets traversing between IPsec SA
   endpoints.  This can be achieved by compressing the transport layer
   header (e.g., UDP, TCP, etc.) and inner IP header of packets at the
   ingress of the IPsec tunnel, and decompressing these headers at the
   egress.
			</t>
      <t>
   For ROHCoIPsec, this document assumes that ROHC will be used to
   compress the inner headers of IP packets traversing an IPsec tunnel.
   However, since current specifications for ROHC detail its operation
   on a hop-by-hop basis, it requires extensions to enable its
   operation over IPsec SAs.  This document outlines a framework for 
   extending the usage of ROHC to operate at IPsec SA endpoints.
			</t>
      <t>
   ROHCoIPsec targets the application of ROHC to tunnel mode SAs.
   Transport mode SAs only encrypt/authenticate the payload of an IP
   packet, leaving the IP header untouched.  Intermediate routers
   subsequently use this IP header to route the packet to a decryption
   device.  Therefore, if ROHC is to operate over IPsec transport-mode
   SAs, (de)compression functionality can only be applied to the
   transport layer headers, and not to the IP header.  Because current
   ROHC specifications do not include support for the compression of
   transport layer headers alone, the ROHCoIPsec framework outlined by
   this document describes the application of ROHC to tunnel mode SAs.
			</t>
    </section>
    <section title="Audience" toc="default">
      <t>
   The authors target members of both the ROHC and IPsec communities who
   may consider extending the ROHC and IPsec protocols to meet the
   requirements put forth in this document.  In addition, this document
   is directed towards vendors developing IPsec devices that will be
   deployed in bandwidth-constrained IP networks.
			</t>
    </section>
    <section title="Terminology" toc="default">
      <t>ROHC Process</t>
      <t>
        <list>
          <t>Generic reference to a ROHC instance (as defined in RFC 3759 [ROHC-TERM]), or any supporting ROHC components.</t>
        </list>
        <t>Compressed Traffic</t>
        <t>
          <list>
            <t>Traffic that is processed through the ROHC compressor and decompressor instances.  Packet headers are compressed and decompressed using a specific header compression profile. </t>
          </list>
        </t>
        <t>Uncompressed Traffic</t>
        <t>
          <list>
            <t>Traffic that is not processed by the ROHC compressor instance. Instead, this type of traffic bypasses the ROHC process.</t>
          </list>
        </t>
      </t>
      <t>IPsec Process</t>
      <t>
        <list>
          <t>Generic reference to the Internet Protocol Security (IPsec) process.</t>
        </list>
      </t>
      <t>Next Header</t>
      <t>
        <list>
          <t>Refers to the Protocol (IPv4) or Next Header (IPv6, Extension) field.</t>
        </list>
      </t>
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in RFC 2119 [BRA97].</t>
    </section>
    <section title="Problem Statement: IPsec Packet Overhead" toc="default">
      <t>
   IPsec mechanisms provide various security services for IP networks.
   However, the benefits of IPsec come at the cost of increased per-
   packet overhead.  For example, traffic flow confidentiality
   (generally leveraged at security gateways) requires the tunneling of
   IP packets between IPsec implementations.  Although these IPsec
   tunnels will effectively mask the source-destination patterns that an
   intruder can ascertain, tunneling comes at the cost of increased
   packet overhead.  Specifically, an ESP tunnel mode SA applied to an
   IPv6 flow results in at least 50 bytes of additional overhead per
   packet.  This additional overhead may be undesirable for many
   bandwidth-constrained wireless and/or satellite communications
   networks, as these types of infrastructure are not overprovisioned.
   ROHC applied on a per-hop basis over bandwidth-constrained links will
   also suffer from reduced performance when encryption is used on the
   tunneled header, since encrypted headers cannot be compressed.
   Consequently, the additional overhead incurred by an IPsec tunnel may
   result in the inefficient utilization of bandwidth.
			</t>
      <t>
   Packet overhead is particularly significant for traffic profiles
   characterized by small packet payloads (e.g. various voice codecs).
   If these small packets are afforded the security
   services of an IPsec tunnel mode SA, the amount of per-packet
   overhead is increased.  Thus, a mechanism is needed to reduce the
   overhead associated with such flows.
			</t>
    </section>
    <section title="Overview of the ROHCoIPsec Framework" toc="default">
      <section title="ROHCoIPsec Assumptions" toc="default">
        <t>
   The goal of ROHCoIPsec is to provide efficient transport of IP
   packets between IPsec devices without compromising the security
   services offered by IPsec.  The ROHCoIPsec framework has
   been developed based on the following assumptions:
			</t>
        <list style="symbols">
          <t>
ROHC will be leveraged to reduce the amount of overhead associated with unicast IP packets traversing an IPsec SA
				</t>
        </list>
        <list style="symbols">
          <t>
ROHC will be instantiated at the IPsec SA endpoints, and will be applied on a per-SA basis
				</t>
        </list>
        <list style="symbols">
          <t>
Once the decompression operation completes, decompressed packet headers will be identical to the original packet headers before compression
				</t>
        </list>
      </section>
      <section title="Summary of the ROHCoIPsec Framework" toc="default">
        <t>
   ROHC reduces packet overhead in a network by exploiting intra- and
   inter-packet redundancies of network and transport-layer header
   fields of a flow.
			</t>
        <t>Current ROHC protocol specifications compress packet headers on a hop-by-hop basis.  However, IPsec SAs are instantiated between two IPsec endpoints.  Therefore, various extensions to both ROHC and IPsec need to be defined to ensure the successful operation of the ROHC protocol at IPsec SA endpoints.	</t>
        <t>The specification of ROHC over IPsec SAs is straightforward, since SA endpoints provide source/destination pairs where (de)compression operations can take place.  Compression of the inner IP and upper layer protocol headers in such a manner offers a reduction of packet overhead between the two SA endpoints.  Since ROHC will now operate between IPsec endpoints (over multiple intermediate nodes which are transparent to an IPsec SA), it is imperative to ensure that its performance will not be severely impacted due to increased packet reordering and/or packet loss between the compressor and decompressor.</t>
        <t>
   In addition, ROHC can no longer rely on the underlying link layer for
   ROHC channel parameter configuration and packet identification.  The
   ROHCoIPsec framework proposes that ROHC channel parameter
   configuration is accomplished by an SA management protocol (e.g.,
   IKEv2 [IKEV2]), while identification of compressed header packets is
   achieved through the Next Header field of the security protocol
   (e.g., AH [AH], ESP [ESP]) header.
			</t>
        <t>Using the ROHCoIPsec framework proposed below, outbound and inbound IP traffic processing at an IPsec device needs to be modified. For an outbound packet, a ROHCoIPsec implementation will compress appropriate packet headers, and subsequently encrypt and/or integrity-protect the packet.  For tunnel mode SAs, compression may be applied to the transport layer and the inner IP headers.  For inbound packets, an IPsec device must first decrypt and/or integrity-check the packet.  Then decompression of the inner packet headers is performed.  After decompression, the packet is checked against the access controls imposed on all inbound traffic associated with the SA (as specified in RFC 4301 [IPSEC]).

			</t>
        <t>
          <list style="empty">
            <t>Note: Compression of inner headers is independent from compression of the security protocol (e.g., ESP) and outer IP headers.  ROHC profiles have been defined to allow for the compression of the security protocol and the outer IP header on a hop-by-hop basis.  The applicability of ROHCoIPsec and hop-by-hop ROHC on an IPv4 ESP-processed packet [ESP] is shown below in Figure 1.</t>

	    <t><figure title="" suppress-title="false" align="center" alt="" width="" height=""><artwork xml:space="preserve" name="" type="" align="left" alt="" width="" height="">
		<![CDATA[
            -----------------------------------------------------------
      IPv4  | new IP hdr  |     | orig IP hdr   |   |    | ESP   | ESP|
            |(any options)| ESP | (any options) |TCP|Data|Trailer| ICV|
            -----------------------------------------------------------
            |<-------(1)------->|<------(2)-------->|
                          
            (1) Compressed hop-by-hop by the ROHC [ROHC] ESP/IP profile 
            (2) Compressed end-to-end by the ROHCoIPsec [IPSEC-ROHC]
                TCP/IP profile
		]]></artwork></figure></t>
	      <t><postamble>Figure 1. Applicability of hop-by-hop ROHC and ROHCoIPsec on an IPv4 ESP-processed packet.</postamble></t>
          </list>
        </t>
        <t>If IPsec NULL encryption is applied to packets, ROHC may still be applied to the inner headers at the IPsec SA endpoints.  However, this poses challenges for intermediary devices (within the unprotected domain) inspecting ESP-NULL encrypted packets, since these intermediary devices will require additional functionality to determine the content of the ROHC packets.</t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section title="Details of the ROHCoIPsec Framework" toc="default">
      <section title="ROHC and IPsec Integration" toc="default">
        <t>
   Figure 2 illustrates the components required to integrate ROHC with
   the IPsec process, i.e., ROHCoIPsec.
			</t>
        <t>
          <figure title="" suppress-title="false" align="center" alt="" width="" height="">
            <artwork xml:space="preserve" name="" type="" align="left" alt="" width="" height=""><![CDATA[
               +-------------------------------+
               | ROHC Module                   |
               |                               |
               |                               |
     +-----+   |     +-----+     +---------+   |
     |     |   |     |     |     |  ROHC   |   |
   --|  A  |---------|  B  |-----| Process |------> Path 1
     |     |   |     |     |     |         |   |   (ROHC-enabled SA)
     +-----+   |     +-----+     +---------+   |
        |      |        |                      |
        |      |        |-------------------------> Path 2
        |      |                               |   (ROHC-enabled SA,
        |      +-------------------------------+  but no compression)
        |
        |
        |
        | 
        +-----------------------------------------> Path 3
                                                   (ROHC-disabled SA)
                                    ]]></artwork>
          <postamble>     Figure 2. Integration of ROHC with IPsec.</postamble>
          </figure>
        </t>
        
   <t>The process illustrated in Figure 2 augments the IPsec processing
   model for outbound IP traffic (protected-to-unprotected).  Initial
   IPsec processing is consistent with RFC 4301 [IPSEC] (Steps 1-2, Section 5.1).</t>

   <t>Block A: The ROHC data item (part of the SA state information) retrieved from
   the "relevant SAD entry" ([IPSEC], Section 5.1, Step3a) determines if
   the traffic traversing the SA is handed to the ROHC module.  Packets selected to a ROHC-disabled SA MUST
   follow normal IPsec processing and MUST NOT be sent to the ROHC
   module (Figure 2, Path 3).  Conversely, packets selected to a ROHC-enabled 
   SA MUST be sent to the ROHC module.</t>

   <t>Block B: This step determines if the packet can be compressed.  If 
   the packet is compressed, an Integrity Algorithm MAY be used to
   compute an Integrity Check Value (ICV) for the uncompressed packet
   ([IPSEC-ROHC], Section 4.2; [IKE-ROHC], Section 3.1).  The Next Header field of the security protocol header
   (e.g., ESP, AH) MUST be populated with a "ROHC" protocol number [PROTOCOL], 
   inner packet headers MUST be compressed, and the computed ICV MAY be appended to the packet (Figure 2, Path 1).
   However, if it is determined that the packet will not be compressed (e.g., due to one
   the reasons described in Section 6.1.3), the Next Header field MUST be
   populated with the appropriate value indicating the next level
   protocol (Figure 2, Path 2), and ROHC processing MUST NOT be applied to the packet.</t>

   <t>After the ROHC process completes, IPsec
   processing resumes, as described in Section 5.1, Step3a, of RFC 4301 [IPSEC].</t>

   <t>The process illustrated in Figure 2 also augments the IPsec
   processing model for inbound IP traffic (unprotected-to-protected).
   For inbound packets, IPsec processing is performed ([IPSEC], Section
   5.2, Steps 1-3) followed by AH or ESP processing ([IPSEC], Section
   5.2, Step 4).</t>

   <t>Block A: After AH or ESP processing, the ROHC data item
   retrieved from the SAD entry will indicate if traffic traversing the
   SA is processed by the ROHC module ([IPSEC], Section 5.2, Step 3a).
   Packets traversing a ROHC-disabled SA MUST follow normal IPsec
   processing and MUST NOT be sent to the ROHC module.  Conversely,
   packets traversing a ROHC-enabled SA MUST be sent to the ROHC
   module.</t> 

   <t>Block B: The decision at Block B is determined by the value of the
   Next Header field of the security protocol header.  If the
   Next Header field does not indicate a ROHC header, the decompressor
   MUST NOT attempt decompression (Figure 2, Path 2).  If the Next Header 
   field indicates a ROHC header, decompression is applied.  After decompression, 
   the signaled ROHCoIPsec Integrity Algorithm, MAY be used to
   compute an ICV value for the decompressed packet.  This ICV, if present, is
   compared to the ICV that was calculated at the compressor: if the ICVs match, the packet 
   is forwarded by the ROHC module (Figure 2, Path 1); otherwise, the packet MUST be dropped.
   Once the ROHC module completes processing, IPsec processing resumes, as described
   in Section 5.2, Step 4 of RFC 4301 [IPSEC].</t>

   <t>When there is a single SA between a compressor and decompressor, 
   ROHC MUST operate in unidirectional mode, as described in Section 5 of 
   RFC 3759 [ROHC-TERM].  When there is a pair of SAs instantiated between 
   ROHCoIPsec implementations, ROHC MAY operate in bidirectional mode, 
   where an SA pair represents a bidirectional ROHC channel (as 
   described in Section 6.1 and 6.2 of RFC 3759[ROHC-TERM]).</t>

   <t>Note that to further reduce the size of an IPsec-protected packet,
   ROHCoIPsec and IPcomp [IPCOMP] can be implemented in a nested
   fashion.  This process is detailed in [IPSEC-ROHC], Section 4.4.
			</t>
   
   <section title="Header Compression Protocol Considerations" toc="default">
   <t>ROHCv2 [ROHCV2] profiles include various mechanisms that provide 
   increased robustness over reordering channels.  These mechanisms SHOULD 
   be adopted for ROHC to operate efficiently over IPsec SAs.</t>

   <t> A ROHC decompressor
   implemented within IPsec architecture MAY leverage additional
   mechanisms to improve performance over reordering channels (either
   due to random events, or to an attacker intentionally reordering
   packets).  Specifically, IPsec's sequence number MAY be used by the
   decompressor to identify a packet as "sequentially late".  This
   knowledge will increase the likelihood of successful decompression of
   a reordered packet.</t>

   <t>Additionally, ROHCoIPsec implementations SHOULD minimize the amount
   of feedback sent from the decompressor to the compressor.  If a ROHC
   feedback channel is not used sparingly, the overall gains from
   ROHCoIPsec can be significantly reduced.  More specifically, any
   feedback sent from the decompressor to the compressor MUST be
   processed by IPsec, and tunneled back to the compressor (as
   designated by the SA associated with FEEDBACK_FOR).  As such, some 
   implementation alternatives can be considered, including the following:
			<list style="symbols"><t>Eliminate feedback traffic altogether by operating only in ROHC Unidirectional mode (U-mode)</t></list>
			<list style="symbols"><t>Piggyback ROHC feedback messages within the feedback element (i.e., on ROHC traffic that normally traverses the SA designated by FEEDBACK_FOR).</t></list></t>
   </section>
   
   <section title="Initialization and Negotiation of the ROHC Channel" toc="default">
          <t>
   Hop-by-hop ROHC typically uses the underlying link layer (e.g., PPP) to negotiate ROHC
   channel parameters.  In the case of ROHCoIPsec, channel parameters
   can be set manually (i.e., administratively
   configured for manual SAs), or negotiated by IKEv2.  The extensions required for IKEv2 to support ROHC
   channel parameter negotiation are detailed in [IKE-ROHC].
				</t>
          <t>
   If the ROHC protocol requires bidirectional communications, two SAs
   MUST be instantiated between the IPsec implementations.  One of the
   two SAs is used for carrying ROHC-traffic from the compressor to the
   decompressor, while the other is used to communicate ROHC-feedback
   from the decompressor to the compressor.  Note that the requirement
   for two SAs aligns with the operation of IKE, which creates SAs in
   pairs by default.  However, IPsec implementations will dictate how decompressor
   feedback received on one SA is associated with a compressor on the
   other SA.  An IPsec implementation MUST relay the feedback 
   received by the decompressor on an inbound SA to the compressor 
   associated with the corresponding outbound SA.
				</t>
   </section>
   
   <section title="Encapsulation and Identification of Header Compressed Packets" toc="default">
          <t>
   As indicated in Section 6.1, new state information (i.e., a new ROHC
   data item) is defined for each SA.  The ROHC data item MUST be used by the
   IPsec process to determine whether it sends all traffic traversing a
   given SA to the ROHC module (ROHC-enabled) or bypasses the ROHC
   module and sends the traffic through regular IPsec processing (ROHC-
   disabled).
				</t>
          <t>
   The Next Header field of the IPsec security protocol (e.g., AH or
   ESP) header MUST be used to demultiplex header-compressed traffic from
   uncompressed traffic traversing an ROHC-enabled SA.  This
   functionality is needed in situations where packets traversing a
   ROHC-enabled SA contain uncompressed headers.  Such situations
   may occur when, for example, a compressor supports strictly n
   compressed flows and cannot compress the n+1 flow that arrives.
   Another example is when traffic is selected
   to a ROHC-enabled SA, but cannot be compressed by the ROHC process
   because the appropriate ROHC Profile has not been signaled for use.
   As a result, the decompressor MUST be
   able to identify packets with uncompressed headers and MUST NOT attempt to
   decompress them.  The Next Header field is used to demultiplex these
   header-compressed and uncompressed packets where the ROHC protocol
   number will indicate that the packet contains compressed headers.  To
   accomplish this, an official IANA allocation from the Protocol ID
   registry [PROTOCOL] is required.
				</t>
          <t>
   The ROHC Data Item, IANA Protocol ID allocation, and other IPsec
   extensions to support ROHCoIPsec, are specified in [IPSEC-ROHC].
				</t>
        </section>
        <section title="Motivation for the ROHC ICV" toc="default">

	<t>Although ROHC was designed to tolerate packet loss and reordering,
      the algorithm does not guarantee that packets reconstructed at the
      decompressor are identical to the original packet.  As
      stated in Section 5.2 of RFC 4224 [REORDR], the consequences of packet
      reordering between ROHC peers may include undetected decompression failures,
      where erroneous packets are constructed and forwarded to upper layers.
      </t>

	<t>When using IPsec integrity protection, a packet received
      at the egress of an IPsec tunnel is identical to the packet that was
      processed at the ingress (given that the key is not compromised, etc.).
      </t>

	<t>When ROHC is integrated into the IPsec processing framework,
      the ROHC processed packet is protected by the AH/ESP ICV.  However,
      bits in the original IP header are not protected by this ICV.  Therefore,
      under certain circumstances, erroneous packets may be constructed and
      forwarded into the protected domain.
      </t>

	<t>To ensure the integrity of the original IP header within the
      ROHCoIPsec-processing model, an additional integrity check MAY be applied
      before the packet is compressed.  This integrity check will ensure that
      erroneous packets are not forwarded into the protected domain.  The
      specifics of this integrity check are documented in Section 4.2 of [IPSEC-ROHC].
      </t>
        </section>
	  <section title="Path MTU Considerations" toc="default">
		<t>By encapsulating IP packets with AH/ESP and tunneling IP headers, IPsec increases the size of IP packets.  This increase
		   may result in Path MTU issues in the unprotected domain.  Several approaches to resolving these path MTU issues
		   are documented in Section 8 of RFC 4301[IPSEC]; approaches include fragmenting the packet before or after 
		   IPsec processing (if the packet's DF bit is clear), or possibly discarding packets (if the packet's DF bit is set).</t>
		<t>The addition of ROHC within the IPsec processing model may result in a similar path MTU challenges.  For example, under certain circumstances,
		   ROHC headers are larger than the original uncompressed headers.  In addition, if an integrity algorithm is used to validate packet headers,
                   the resulting ICV will increase the size of packets.  Both of these properties of ROHCoIPsec increase the size of 
		   packets, and therefore may result in additional challenges associated with path MTU.</t>
		<t>Approaches to addressing these path MTU issues are specified in Section 4.3 of [IPSEC-ROHC].</t>
	  </section>
      </section>
      <section title="ROHCoIPsec Framework Summary" toc="default">
        <t>To summarize, the following items are needed to achieve ROHCoIPsec:</t>
        <list style="symbols">
          <t>IKEv2 Extensions to Support ROHCoIPsec</t>
          <t>IPsec Extensions to Support ROHCoIPsec</t>
        </list>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section title="Security Considerations" toc="default">
      <t>
   A malfunctioning ROHC compressor (i.e., the compressor located at the
   ingress of the IPsec tunnel) has the ability to send packets to the
   decompressor (i.e., the decompressor located at the egress of the
   IPsec tunnel) that do not match the original packets emitted from the
   end-hosts.  Such a scenario will result in decreased efficiency
   between compressor and decompressor.  Furthermore, this may result in
   Denial of Service, as the decompression of a significant number of
   invalid packets may drain the resources of an IPsec device.
		</t>
    </section>
    <section title="IANA Considerations" toc="default">
      <t>None.</t>
    </section>
    <section title="Acknowledgments" toc="default">
      <t>
   The authors would like to thank Mr. Sean O'Keeffe, Mr. James Kohler,
   and Ms. Linda Noone of the Department of Defense, and well as Mr.
   Rich Espy of OPnet for their contributions and support in the
   development of this document.</t>

   <t>The authors would also like to thank Mr. Yoav Nir, and Mr. 
   Robert A Stangarone Jr.: both served as committed document reviewers 
   for this specification.</t>

   <t>In addition, the authors would like to
   thank the following for their numerous reviews and comments to this
   document:
		</t>
      <t>
        <list style="symbols">
	    <t>Mr. Magnus Westerlund</t>
          <t>Dr. Stephen Kent </t>
          <t>Mr. Pasi Eronen</t>
          <t>Dr. Joseph Touch</t>
          <t>Mr. Tero Kivinen</t>
	    <t>Dr. Jonah Pezeshki</t>
          <t>Mr. Lars-Erik Jonsson</t>
          <t>Mr. Jan Vilhuber</t>
          <t>Mr. Dan Wing</t>
          <t>Mr. Kristopher Sandlund</t>
          <t>Mr. Ghyslain Pelletier</t>
        </list>
      </t>
      <t>
   Finally, the authors would also like to thank Mr. Tom Conkle, Ms.
   Renee Esposito, Mr. Etzel Brower, and Ms. Michele Casey of Booz Allen
   Hamilton for their assistance in completing this work.
		</t>
    </section>
  </middle>
  <back>
    <references title="Informative References">
	<reference anchor="ROHC">
	   <front>
		<title> The RObust Header Compression (ROHC) Framework</title>
		<author initials="L-E." surname="Jonsson" fullname="L-E. Jonsson">
				<organization/>
		</author>
		<author initials="G." surname="Pelletier" fullname="G. Pelletier">
			<organization/>
		</author>
		<author initials="K." surname="Sandlund" fullname="K. Sandlund">
			<organization/>
		</author>
		<date month="July" year="2007"/>
	</front>
	<seriesInfo name="RFC" value="4995"/>
	</reference>
      <reference anchor="IPSEC">
        <front>
          <title>Security Architecture for the Internet Protocol</title>
          <author initials="S." surname="Kent" fullname="S. Kent">
            <organization />
          </author>
          <author initials="K." surname="Seo" fullname="K. Seo">
            <organization />
          </author>
          <date month="December" year="2005" />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="4301" />
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="ROHC-TERM">
        <front>
          <title>Robust Header Compression (ROHC): Terminology and Channel Mapping Examples</title>
          <author initials="L-E." surname="Jonsson" fullname="L-E. Jonsson">
            <organization />
          </author>
          <date month="April" year="2004" />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="3759" />
      </reference>
     <reference anchor="BRA97">
       <front>
         <title>Key words for use in RFCs to Indicate Requirement Levels</title>
         <author initials="S." surname="Bradner" fullname="S. Bradner">
           <organization />
         </author>
         <date month="March" year="1997" />
       </front>
       <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="2119" />
     </reference>
      <reference anchor="IKEV2">
        <front>
          <title>Internet Key Exchange (IKEv2) Protocol</title>
          <author initials="C." surname="Kaufman">
            <organization />
          </author>
          <date month="December" year="2005" />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="4306" />
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="ESP">
        <front>
          <title>IP Encapsulating Security Payload (ESP)</title>
          <author initials="S." surname="Kent" fullname="S. Kent">
            <organization />
          </author>
          <date month="December" year="2005" />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="4303" />
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="AH">
        <front>
          <title>IP Authentication Header</title>
          <author initials="S." surname="Kent" fullname="S. Kent">
            <organization />
          </author>
          <date month="December" year="2005" />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="4302" />
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="IPSEC-ROHC">
        <front>
          <title>IPsec Extensions to Support ROHCoIPsec</title>
          <author initials="E." surname="Ertekin">
            <organization />
          </author>
	  <author initials="C." surname="Christou">
            <organization />
          </author>
	  <author initials="C." surname="Bormann">
            <organization />
          </author>
          <date month="December" year="2009" />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="work in progress" value="" />
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="IKE-ROHC">
        <front>
          <title>IKEv2 Extensions to Support ROHCoIPsec</title>
          <author initials="E." surname="Ertekin">
            <organization />
          </author>
	  <author initials="C." surname="Christou">
            <organization />
          </author>
          <author initials="R." surname="Jasani">
            <organization />
          </author>
          <author initials="T." surname="Kivinen">
            <organization />
          </author>
          <author initials="C." surname="Bormann">
            <organization />
          </author>
          <date month="December" year="2009" />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="work in progress" value="" />
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="PROTOCOL">
        <front>
          <title>Assigned Internet Protocol Numbers, IANA registry at: http://www.iana.org/assignments/protocol-numbers</title>
          <author surname="IANA">
            <organization />
          </author>
          <date month="June" year="2009" />
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="IPCOMP">
        <front>
          <title>IP Payload Compression Protocol (IPComp)</title>
          <author initials="A." surname="Shacham" fullname="A. Shacham">
            <organization />
          </author>
          <author initials="R." surname="Monsour" fullname="R. Monsour">
            <organization />
          </author>
          <author intials="R." surname="Pereira" fullname="R. Pereira">
            <organization />
          </author>
          <author intials="M." surname="Thomas" fullname="M. Thomas">
            <organization />
          </author>
          <date month="September" year="2001" />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="3173" />
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="ROHCV2">
        <front>
          <title>RObust Header Compression Version 2 (ROHCv2): Profiles for RTP, UDP, IP, ESP and UDP Lite</title>
          <author initials="G." surname="Pelletier">
            <organization />
          </author>
          <author initials="K." surname="Sandlund">
            <organization />
          </author>
          <date month="April" year="2008" />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="5225" />
      </reference>     
      <reference anchor="REORDR">
        <front>
          <title>Robust Header Compression (ROHC): ROHC over Channels That Can Reorder Packets</title>
          <author initials="G." surname="Pelletier">
            <organization />
          </author>
	    <author initials="L-E." surname="Jonsson">
            <organization />
          </author>
	    <author initials="K." surname="Sandlund">
            <organization />
          </author>
          <date month="January" year="2006" />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="4224" />
      </reference>
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>