<?xml version = '1.0'?>
<?rfc rfcedstyle='yes'?>
<?rfc rfcprocack='yes'?>
<?rfc toc='yes'?>
<?rfc symrefs='yes'?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "../xml2rfc-1.35pre1/rfc2629.dtd" [

      <!ENTITY rfc793      PUBLIC '' '../rfc-bib/reference.RFC.0793.xml'>
      <!ENTITY rfc2119     PUBLIC '' '../rfc-bib/reference.RFC.2119.xml'>
      <!ENTITY rfc4960     PUBLIC '' '../rfc-bib/reference.RFC.4960.xml'>
      <!ENTITY rfc2759     PUBLIC '' '../rfc-bib/reference.RFC.2759.xml'>
      <!ENTITY rfc3748     PUBLIC '' '../rfc-bib/reference.RFC.3748.xml'>
      <!ENTITY rfc5191     PUBLIC '' '../rfc-bib/reference.RFC.5191.xml'>
      <!ENTITY rfc5216     PUBLIC '' '../rfc-bib/reference.RFC.5216.xml'>

    ]>
<rfc ipr='trust200902' docName='draft-winter-abfab-eapapplicability-00' category='std'>
  <front>
    <title abbrev="EAP Applicability" >Update to the EAP Applicability Statement</title>
    <author fullname="Stefan Winter" initials="S." surname="Winter" >
	<organization abbrev="RESTENA" >Fondation RESTENA</organization>
	<address>
		<postal>
			<street>6, rue Richard Coudenhove-Kalergi</street>
			<city>Luxembourg</city>
			<code>1359</code>
			<country>LUXEMBOURG</country>
		</postal>
		<phone>+352 424409 1</phone>
		<facsimile>+352 422473</facsimile>
		<email>stefan.winter@restena.lu</email>
		<uri>http://www.restena.lu.</uri>
	</address>
    </author>
    <date day="01" month="June" year="2011" />
    <area>Security Area</area>
    <workgroup>ABFAB Working Group</workgroup>
    <keyword>EAP</keyword>
    <keyword>AAA</keyword>
    <abstract>
	    <t>This document updates the EAP applicability statement from RFC3748 to reflect recent usage of the EAP protocol in unprecedented contexts.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>
  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction" anchor="intro">
<t>The EAP applicability statement in <xref target="RFC3748" /> defines the scope of the Extensible Authentication Protocol to be "for use in network access authentication, where IP layer connectivity may not be available.", and states that "Use of EAP for other purposes, such as bulk data transport, is NOT RECOMMENDED.".</t>
<t>While the recommendation against usage of EAP for bulk data transport is still valid, some of the other provisions in the applicability statement have turned out to be too narrow. <xref target="otheruses" /> lists numerous examples where EAP is being used for more than authentication and/or more than network access. <xref target="newstatement" /> provides new text to update the paragraph 1.3. "Applicablity" in <xref target="RFC3748" />.</t>
	<section title="Requirements Language" anchor="reqlang">
		<t>In this document, several words are used to signify the
requirements of the specification.  The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT",
"REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED", "MAY",
and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in RFC 2119.
<xref target="RFC2119" /></t>
	</section>
    </section>
    <section title="Uses of EAP beyond the original applicability statement" anchor="otheruses">
        <section title="Communication of authorisation information: EAP-MSCHAPv2; more examples solicited">
<t>MSCHAPv2 <xref target="RFC2759" /> can be transported over EAP. It contains packet exchanges to authenticate users, which fits into the scope of the original EAP applicability statement. However, MSCHAPv2 also allows to check for and signal (lack of) authorisation of an authenticated user to use a service. For example, an MSCHAPv2 failure packet as defined in section 6 of <xref target="RFC2759" /> can indicate condition 646 "Restricted Logon hours". This determination is an authorisation check which happens subsequent to the authentication step (a user needs to be positively identified to correlate his identity to a list of permitted logon hours). </t>
<t>This use of EAP is not covered by the EAP applicability statement since it goes beyond user authentication. However, EAP-MSCHAPv2 is in massive deployment. It is thus due to extend the EAP applicability statement to include "user authorisation".</t>
        </section>
	<section title="Equipment Auditing: NEA PT over EAP">
<t>The IETF working group "Network Endpoint Assessment", nea, is chartered to define exchange information about the state of a user's equipment during network authentication. One of the channels over which to transport this information is EAP; either embedded within other EAP methods or as a stand-alone EAP method. The information exchanged is unrelated to user authentication - the information covers the state of the computing device only, independently of the user who is using it.</t>
<t>This use of EAP is not covered by the EAP applicability statement since it goes beyond user authentication. However, there are multiple implementations of NEA information transport, some in wide deployment (e.g. recent implementations of PEAP with "Statement of Health (SoH)" support. It is thus due to extend the EAP applicability statement to include "Equipment Auditing".</t>
	</section>
	<section title="Account Management: EAP-MSCHAPv2">
<t>EAP-MSCHAPv2 has more wide-reaching capabilities than the ones listed in point 1. It includes limited support for user account management, namely the possibility for a user to change his password, should it have expired. This is defined in section 7 of <xref target="RFC2759" />.</t>
<t>This use of EAP is not covered by the EAP applicability statement since it goes beyond user authentication. It is left open in this -00 draft whether such a capability should be considered in the applicability of EAP. The reason being that this use goes dangerously close to the use of EAP as "bulk data transport"; account management typically being a administratively independent action from the actual admission decision. This should be discussed in the relevant working group(s). </t>
        </section>
	<section title="EAP over IP: PANA">
<t>The PANA protocol <xref target="RFC5191" /> carries EAP payloads over UDP. The original EAP applicability statement states that EAP is applicable in cases where "IP layer connectivity may not be available". The wording in the applicability statement leaves open whether the transport of EAP over IP is in scope or not. Since protocols which carry EAP over IP already exist and have been deployed, it is due to make this use case explicit and reflect it in the revised applicability statement. The statement needs to take into account though that EAP requires ordering guarantees from its lower layers, which are not delivered by IP in itself. This limits the use of EAP to transport layers which are on top of IP, and provide their own ordering guarantees.</t>
        </section>
        <section title="EAP for application-layer access: ABFAB">
<t>Ongoing work in the IETF (abfab working group) specifies the use of EAP over GSSAPI over a AAA protocol for generic application layer access. Using EAP in this context has in the past been repelled due to the lack of channel bindings. Without channel bindings, a peer does not know what service is being contacted. In most network access use cases all access servers that are served by a particular EAP server are providing the same or very similar types of service.  The peer does not need to differentiate between different access network services supported by the same EAP server.</t>
<t>However as additional services use EAP for authentication, the distinction of which service is being contacted becomes more important. Consider an environment with multiple printers; if a peer printed a document in the wrong location then potentially sensitive information might be printing in a location where the user associated with the peer would be unable to retrieve it. It is also likely that services might have different security properties. For example, it might be more likely that a low-value service is compromised than some high value service. If the high-value service could be impersonated by a low-value service then the security of the overall system would be limited by the security of the lower value service.</t>
<t>This distinction is present in any environment where peers' security depends on which service they reach. However it is particularly acute in a federated environment where multiple organizations are involved. It is very likely that these organizations will have different security policies and practices. It is very likely that the goals of these organizations will not entirely be aligned. In many situations one organization could gain value by being able to impersonate another. In this environment, authenticating the EAP server is insufficient: the peer must also authenticate which service it contacts. [Discussed: is authentication the right word here?]</t>
<t>For these reasons, channel binding MUST be implemented by peers, EAP servers and AAA servers in environments where EAP authentication is used to access services beyond the network. In additon, channel binding MUST default to being required by peers for non-network authentication. If the EAP server is aware that authentication is for something other than a network service, it too MUST default to requiring channel binding. Operators need to carefully consider the security implications before relaxing these requirements. One potentially serious attack exists when channel binding is not required and EAP authentication is introduced into an existing non-network service. A device can be created that impersonates a Network Access Service to peers, but actually proxies the authentication to the service that newly accepts EAP auths may decrease the security of this service even for users who previously used non-EAP means of authentication to the service.</t>
<t>In parallel to ABFAB, there is other ongoing work on Channel Binding in the IETF (emu working group). The introduction of channel bindings into EAP mitigates the impersonation threat and makes EAP suitable for use beyond network authentication. Pending issuance of a Channel Binding RFC, it is thus due to extend the EAP applicability statement to include non-network access contexts if - and only if - this context mandates channel bindings.</t>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section title="Summary of changes" anchor="new">
	<t>The new text for the EAP Applicability statement is stated in the next section. It is meant to replace section 1.3 of <xref target="RFC3748" />. Its main changes are the widened scope (generic resource admission instead of only network authentication), the explicit mention of transporting EAP over IP, and the requirement for channel bindings if used for anything but network access.</t>
<t>This document also updates references to EAP-TLS and SCTP, whose original RFCs have been obsoleted by newer specifications.</t>
<t>With the new text, the acronym EAP can be seen to stand for "Extensible Admission-Control Protocol".</t>
    </section>
    <section title="Revised EAP applicability statement" anchor="newstatement">
        <t>EAP was designed for use in network access authentication, where IP
   layer connectivity may not be available. Under some circumstances, it may 
   also be used for generic resource admission decisions. Use of EAP for other
   purposes, such as bulk data transport, is NOT RECOMMENDED.</t>
        <t>Generic resource admission decisions may require the transport of any
   of the following:
<list style="symbols"><t>user credentials</t><t>machine credentials</t><t>machine configuration details for equipment auditing</t><t>authorisation information</t><t>accessed application properties</t></list></t>
<t> The use of EAP over IP is recommended if - and only if - it is transported over a transport layer on top of IP which provides ordering guarantees.</t>
<t> The use of EAP for generic application access is recommended if - and only if - EAP channel bindings are implemented.</t>
<t>Since EAP does not require IP connectivity, it provides just enough
   support for the reliable transport of authentication protocols, and
   no more.</t><t>EAP is a lock-step protocol which only supports a single packet in
   flight.  As a result, EAP cannot efficiently transport bulk data,
   unlike transport protocols such as TCP <xref target="RFC0793" /> or SCTP <xref target="RFC4960" />.</t>
<t>While EAP provides support for retransmission, it assumes ordering
   guarantees provided by the lower layer, so out of order reception is
   not supported.</t><t>Since EAP does not support fragmentation and reassembly, EAP
   authentication methods generating payloads larger than the minimum
   EAP MTU need to provide fragmentation support.</t><t>While authentication methods such as EAP-TLS <xref target="RFC5216" /> provide
   support for fragmentation and reassembly, the EAP methods defined in
   this document do not.  As a result, if the EAP packet size exceeds
   the EAP MTU of the link, these methods will encounter difficulties.</t>
<t>EAP authentication is initiated by the server (authenticator),
   whereas many authentication protocols are initiated by the client
   (peer).  As a result, it may be necessary for an authentication
   algorithm to add one or two additional messages (at most one
   roundtrip) in order to run over EAP.</t><t>Where certificate-based authentication is supported, the number of
   additional roundtrips may be much larger due to fragmentation of
   certificate chains.  In general, a fragmented EAP packet will require
   as many round-trips to send as there are fragments.  For example, a
   certificate chain 14960 octets in size would require ten round-trips
   to send with a 1496 octet EAP MTU.</t><t>Where EAP runs over a lower layer in which significant packet loss is
   experienced, or where the connection between the authenticator and
   authentication server experiences significant packet loss, EAP
   methods requiring many round-trips can experience difficulties.  In
   these situations, use of EAP methods with fewer roundtrips is
   advisable.</t>

    </section>
    <section title="Security Considerations" anchor="security">
<t>Lots.</t>
    </section>
    <section title="IANA Considerations" anchor="iana">
<t>This document has no actions for IANA.</t>
    </section>
    <section title="Acknowledgements" anchor="acks"><t>Large amounts of helpful text and insightful thoughts were contributed by Sam Hartman, Painless Security, and Joe Salowey, Cisco Systems.</t></section>
  </middle>
  <back>
	  <references title="Normative References">
		  &rfc2119;
		  &rfc3748;
		  &rfc5191;
                  &rfc5216;
          </references>	
	  <references title="Informational References">
		  &rfc793;
                  &rfc2759;
		  &rfc4960;
	  </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
