<?xml version = '1.0'?>
<?rfc rfcedstyle='yes'?>
<?rfc rfcprocack='yes'?>
<?rfc toc='yes'?>
<?rfc symrefs='yes'?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "../xml2rfc-1.36/rfc2629.dtd" [

      <!ENTITY rfc2866     PUBLIC '' '../rfc-bib/reference.RFC.2866.xml'>
      <!ENTITY rfc2119     PUBLIC '' '../rfc-bib/reference.RFC.2119.xml'>
      <!ENTITY extensions  PUBLIC '' '../i-d-bib/reference.I-D.ietf-radext-radius-extensions.xml'>

    ]>
<rfc ipr='trust200902' docName='draft-winter-radext-fancyaccounting-02' category='std'>
  <front>
    <title abbrev="RADIUS Fancy Accounting" >RADIUS Accounting for traffic classes</title>
    <author fullname="Stefan Winter" initials="S." surname="Winter" >
	<organization abbrev="RESTENA" >Fondation RESTENA</organization>
	<address>
		<postal>
			<street>6, rue Richard Coudenhove-Kalergi</street>
			<city>Luxembourg</city>
			<code>1359</code>
			<country>LUXEMBOURG</country>
		</postal>
		<phone>+352 424409 1</phone>
		<facsimile>+352 422473</facsimile>
		<email>stefan.winter@restena.lu</email>
		<uri>http://www.restena.lu.</uri>
	</address>
    </author>
    <date day="16" month="July" year="2012" />
    <area>Operations and Management Area</area>
    <workgroup>RADIUS Extensions Working Group</workgroup>
    <keyword>RADIUS</keyword>
    <keyword>AAA</keyword>
    <keyword>Accounting</keyword>
    <abstract>
	    <t>This document specifies new attributes for RADIUS Accounting to enable NAS reporting of subsets of the total traffic in a user session.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>
  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction" anchor="intro">
<t>RADIUS Accounting <xref target="RFC2866" /> defines counters for octets and packets, both in the incoming and outgoing direction.  Usage of these counters enables an operator create volume-based billing models and to execute proper capacity planning on its infrastructure.</t>
<t> The Accounting model is based on the assumption that all traffic in a user session is treated equally; i.e. that there are no differences in the billing model of one class of traffic over another.</t>
<t> Actual deployments suggest that this assumption is no longer valid. In particular, different traffic classes are defined with DSCP; and billing the use of these traffic classes separately is an understandable request.</t>
<t> Plus, the introduction of dual-stack operation on links creates an understandable interest of getting separate statistics about the amount of IPv4 vs. IPv6 usage on a link; be it for billing or statistical reasons.</t>  
<t>This document defines Accounting attributes that supplement (but not replace) the accounting counters in RFC2866. It utilizes the new "extended attributes" in RADIUS (<xref target="I-D.ietf-radext-radius-extensions" />) to a) group accounting reports about traffic classes together and b) enable 64-Bit counts in a single attribute with the Integer64 datatype.</t>
	<section title="Requirements Language" anchor="reqlang">
		<t>In this document, several words are used to signify the
requirements of the specification.  The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT",
"REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED", "MAY",
and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in RFC 2119.
<xref target="RFC2119" /></t>
	</section>
    </section>
    <section title="Definitions" anchor="def">
	<section title="Acct-Traffic-Class attribute">
	<t>The attribute Acct-Traffic-Class is a TLV container for a group of sub-attributes which specify the class of traffic that is being reported about, and the amount of traffic in a user session that falls into this class.
	<list>	
		<t>Attribute: 245.1 Acct-Traffic-Class</t>
		<t>Type: TLV</t>
		<t>Length: >3 octets</t>
	</list>
	</t>
	<t>There can be multiple instances of this attribute in a Accounting-Interim-Update or a Accounting-Stop packet. The attribute MUST NOT be present in an Accounting-Start packet.</t>
	<t> It is not required that the sum of all traffic in all instances is the total sum of octets and packets in the user's session. I.e.  the traffic classes used in the Accounting packet do not need to partition the total traffic in non-overlapping segments.</t>
	<t>The total number of octets and packets in a user session continues to be sent in the RFC2866 attributes.</t>
		<section title="Acct-Traffic-Class-Name attribute">
			<t> The attribute Acct-Traffic-Class-Name, sub-attribute in the group Acct-Traffic-Class, defines the class of traffic for which the other attributes in the instance of Acct-Traffic-Class count octets and packets. Every group instance MUST contain exactly one Acct-Traffic-Class-Name.
		<list>
			<t>Attribute: 245.1.2 Acct-Traffic-Class-Name</t>
			<t>Type: STRING</t>
			<t>Value: 1-250 octets</t>
		</list>
		There are two options for the value of this attribute.
		</t>
		<t>Option 1: Acct-Traffic-Class-Name string starting with the substring "urn:". Usage of this option implies that the traffic name is in the form of a URN and requires that a public specification of this URN exists. That specification must include the type of traffic being counted with this traffic class, and the exact definition of where in the network packets the byte-count starts and ends. This document defines a set of known, well-defined traffic accounting classes in an IANA-managed registry in <xref target="iana-registry"/>. New values for this registry are assigned on expert review basis.</t>
		<t>Option 2: Acct-Traffic-Class-Name string not starting with "urn:". This option is for local use of special-purpose accounting as defined by the NAS administrator, where no defined URN matches the meaning of the traffic to be counted. The meaning of the content needs to be communicated out-of-band between the NAS and RADIUS Server operator. Example: Acct-Traffic-Class-Name = "UDP traffic to AS2606".
		</t>
		</section>
		<section title="Acct-Traffic-Class-Input-Octets attribute">
			<t> The attribute Acct-Traffic-Class-Input-Octets, sub-attribute in the group Acct-Traffic-Class, carries the number of octets that belong to the class of traffic indicated by Acct-Traffic-Class-Name and have been sent to the entity for which the accounting packet was generated. It MUST occur at most once inside every instance of the Acct-Traffic-Class TLV. If a traffic parameter value is transmitted in this attribute in an Accouting-Request "Interim Update", then the final value of that traffic parameter MUST be reported in the corresponding Accounting-Request "Stop".
		<list>
			<t>Attribute: 245.1.3 Acct-Traffic-Class-Input-Octets</t>
			<t>Type: Integer64</t>
			<t>Value: number of octets sent to entity, matching the class of traffic</t>
		</list>
		</t>
		</section>
                <section title="Acct-Traffic-Class-Output-Octets attribute">
                        <t> The attribute Acct-Traffic-Class-Output-Octets, sub-attribute in the group Acct-Traffic-Class, carries the number of octets that belong to the class of traffic indicated by Acct-Traffic-Class-Name and have been sent from the entity for which the accounting packet was generated. It MUST occur at most once inside every instance of the Acct-Traffic-Class TLV. If a traffic parameter value is transmitted in this attribute in an Accouting-Request "Interim Update", then the final value of that traffic parameter MUST be reported in the corresponding Accounting-Request "Stop".
		<list>
                        <t>Attribute: 245.1.4 Acct-Traffic-Class-Output-Octets</t>
			<t>Type: Integer64</t>
			<t>Value: number of octets sent from entity, matching the class of traffic</t>
		</list>
		</t>
                </section>
                <section title="Acct-Traffic-Class-Input-Packets attribute">
                        <t> The attribute Acct-Traffic-Class-Input-Packets, sub-attribute in the group Acct-Traffic-Class, carries the number of packets that belong to the class of traffic indicated by Acct-Traffic-Class-Name and have been sent to the entity for which the accounting packet was generated. It MUST occur at most once inside every instance of the Acct-Traffic-Class TLV. If a traffic parameter value is transmitted in this attribute in an Accouting-Request "Interim Update", then the final value of that traffic parameter MUST be reported in the corresponding Accounting-Request "Stop".
		<list>
                        <t>Attribute: 245.1.5 Acct-Traffic-Class-Input-Packets</t>
			<t>Type: Integer64</t>
			<t>Value: number of packets sent to entity, matching the class of traffic</t>
		</list>
		</t>
                </section>
                <section title="Acct-Traffic-Class-Output-Packets attribute">
                        <t> The attribute Acct-Traffic-Class-Output-Packets, sub-attribute in the group Acct-Traffic-Class, carries the number of packets that belong to the class of traffic indicated by Acct-Traffic-Class-Name and have been sent from the entity for which the accounting packet was generated. It MUST occur at most once inside every instance of the Acct-Traffic-Class TLV. If a traffic parameter value is transmitted in this attribute in an Accouting-Request "Interim Update", then the final value of that traffic parameter MUST be reported in the corresponding Accounting-Request "Stop".
		<list>
 			<t>Attribute: 245.1.6 Acct-Traffic-Class-Output-Packets</t>
			<t>Type: Integer64</t>
			<t>Value: number of packets sent from entity, matching the class of traffic</t>
		</list>
		</t>
                </section>
	</section>
	<section title="URN values for attribute Acct-Traffic-Class-Name" anchor="iana-registry">
	<t>The following URN values are defined for RADIUS Accounting Traffic Classes:
		<list>
                        <t>Name: "urn:ietf:radius-accounting:ip:4"
                                <list>
					<t>Purpose: volume count of IPv4 payloads</t> 
                                        <t>Start of byte count: 1st byte of the IP header of the packet</t>
                                        <t>End of byte count: last byte of IP layer of the packet</t>
                                </list>
                        </t>
			<t>Name: "urn:ietf:radius-accounting:ip:6"
				<list>
					<t>Purpose: volume count of IPv6 payloads</t>
					<t>Start of byte count: 1st byte of the IP header of the packet</t>
					<t>End of byte count: last byte of IP layer of the packet</t>
				</list>
			</t>
			<t>Name: "urn:ietf:radius-accounting:dscp:0"
                                <list>
                                        <t>Purpose: volume count of packet payloads with DSCP = 0</t>
                                        <t>Start of byte count: 1st byte of the IP header of the packet</t>
                                        <t>End of byte count: last byte of IP layer of the packet</t>
                                </list>
                        </t>
			<t>Name: "urn:ietf:radius-accounting:tcp"
                                <list>
                                        <t>Purpose: volume count of TCP packets</t>
                                        <t>Start of byte count: 1st byte of the TCP header of the packet</t>
                                        <t>End of byte count: last byte of TCP layer of the packet</t>
                                </list>
                        </t>
			<t>Name: "urn:ietf:radius-accounting:udp"
                                <list>
                                        <t>Purpose: volume count of UDP payloads</t>
                                        <t>Start of byte count: 1st byte of the UDP header of the packet</t>
                                        <t>End of byte count: last byte of UDP layer of the packet</t>
                                </list>
                        </t>
		</list>
		(more values to be added...)
	</t>
	</section>
	</section>
	<section title="Example">
		<t>A NAS is configured to create statistics regarding IPv6 usage of CPE for statistical reasons, and of the amount of HTTP traffic sent to the example.com web site for billing reasons.</t> 
		<t>User john@example.com starts a user session, transfers 1200 Bytes in 10 packets via IPv6 to the internet, and receives 4500 Bytes in 30 packets over IPv6 from the internet.</t>
		<t>In the same session, The user visits the IPv4-only example.com web site by sending 6000 bytes in 4 packets to the web site, and receiving 450000 Bytes in 35 packets from the web site.</t>
		<t>Then, the user terminates the session and an Accounting-Stop packet is generated.</t>
		<t>The NAS sends the recorded octet and packet values to his RADIUS Accounting server.  Since there is no URN value for "Traffic on TCP/80 to example.com, all IP versions" for use in the Acct-Traffic-Class-Name attribute, the NAS has been configured to indicate this class of traffic in a corresponding custom string. The relevant attributes in the Accounting-Stop packet are:</t>
<t>Acct-Traffic-Class
<list>
<t>    Acct-Traffic-Class-Name           = "urn:ietf:radius-accunting:ip:6"</t>
<t>    Acct-Traffic-Class-Input-Octets   = 4500</t>
<t>    Acct-Traffic-Class-Output-Octets  = 1200</t>
<t>    Acct-Traffic-Class-Input-Packets  = 30</t>
<t>    Acct-Traffic-Class-Output-Packets = 10</t>
</list>
</t>
<t>Acct-Traffic-Class
<list>
<t>    Acct-Traffic-Class-Name           = "Traffic on TCP/80 to example.com, all IP versions"</t>
<t>    Acct-Traffic-Class-Input-Octets   = 450000</t>
<t>    Acct-Traffic-Class-Output-Octets  = 6000</t>
<t>    Acct-Traffic-Class-Input-Packets  = 35</t>
<t>    Acct-Traffic-Class-Output-Packets = 4</t>
</list>
</t>
	</section>
	<section title="Attribute Occurence Table" anchor="occurence">
		<figure title="Attribute Occurence" anchor="occurence-table">
			<preamble>
			This table lists the allowed occurences of the previously defined attributes in Accounting packets.
			</preamble>
			<artwork>
Start  Interim  Stop  Reply  Attribute
-----  -------  ----  -----  ---------------------------------
0      0-n      0-s   0      Acct-Traffic-Class
0      0-m      0-t   0      Acct-Traffic-Class-Name
0      0-o      0-u   0      Acct-Traffic-Class-Input-Octets
0      0-p      0-v   0      Acct-Traffic-Class-Output-Octets
0      0-q      0-w   0      Acct-Traffic-Class-Input-Packets
0      0-r      0-x   0      Acct-Traffic-Class-Output-Packets
</artwork>
		</figure>
	<t>Note 1: since all sub-attributes occur at most once inside any given Acct-Traffic-Class TLV, the sub-attributes can not occur more often than the TLV itself. I.e. m&lt;n, o&lt;n, p&lt;n, q&lt;n, and r&lt;n.</t>
	<t>Note 2: if Acct-Traffic-Class TLVs and their sub-attributes have been sent in Interim-Updates, they MUST also occur in the subsequent Stop packet; while the Stop packet MAY contain additional Acct-Traffic-Class instances. I.e. in the table above: s>=n, t>=m, u>=o, v>=p,w>=q, and x>=r.</t>
	</section>
    <section title="Security Considerations" anchor="security">
	    <t> Reveals user's traffic usage patterns. Shouldn't be sent unencrpyptedly.</t>
    </section>
    <section title="IANA Considerations" anchor="iana">
	    <t>This document has actions for IANA. TBD later.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>
  <back>
	  <references title="Normative References">
		  &rfc2866;
                  &rfc2119;
		  &extensions;

          </references>	
  </back>
</rfc>
