<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<!-- Some of the more generally applicable PIs that most I-Ds might want to use -->
<!-- Try to enforce the ID-nits conventions and DTD validity -->
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<!-- Items used when reviewing the document -->
<?rfc comments="no" ?>
<!-- Controls display of <cref> elements -->
<?rfc inline="no" ?>
<!-- When no, put comments at end in comments section,
                                 otherwise, put inline -->
<?rfc editing="no" ?>
<!-- When yes, insert editing marks: editing marks consist of a 
                                 string such as <29> printed in the blank line at the 
                                 beginning of each paragraph of text. -->
<!-- Create Table of Contents (ToC) and set some options for it.  
         Note the ToC may be omitted for very short documents,but idnits insists on a ToC 
         if the document has more than 15 pages. -->
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<!-- If "yes" eliminates blank lines before main section entries. -->
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<!-- Sets the number of levels of sections/subsections... in ToC -->
<!-- Choose the options for the references. 
         Some like symbolic tags in the references (and citations) and others prefer 
         numbers. The RFC Editor always uses symbolic tags.
         The tags used are the anchor attributes of the references. -->
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<!-- If "yes", causes the references to be sorted in order of tags.
                                 This doesn't have any effect unless symrefs is "yes" also. -->
<!-- These two save paper: Just setting compact to "yes" makes savings by not starting each 
         main section on a new page but does not omit the blank lines between list items. 
         If subcompact is also "yes" the blank lines between list items are also omitted. -->
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<!-- end of list of popular I-D processing instructions -->
<!-- end of list of processing instructions -->
<rfc category="info" docName="draft-baker-v6ops-greynet-05" ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="">IPv4 and IPv6 Greynets</title>

    <author fullname="Fred Baker" initials="F.J." surname="Baker">
      <organization>Cisco Systems</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>

          <city>Santa Barbara</city>

          <code>93117</code>

          <region>California</region>

          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>

        <email>fred@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Warren Harrop" initials="W." surname="Harrop">
      <organization>CAIA, Swinburne University of Technology</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>

          <city>Hawthorn</city>

          <code>3122</code>

          <region>Victoria</region>

          <country>Australia</country>
        </postal>

        <email>wazz@bud.cc.swin.edu.au</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Grenville Armitage" initials="G." surname="Armitage">
      <organization>CAIA, Swinburne University of Technology</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>

          <city>Hawthorn</city>

          <code>3122</code>

          <region>Victoria</region>

          <country>Australia</country>
        </postal>

        <email>garmitage@swin.edu.au</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date year="2010" />

    <area>Operations</area>

    <workgroup>IPv6 Operations</workgroup>

    <abstract>
      <t>This note discusses a feature to support building Greynets for IPv4
      and IPv6.</t>
    </abstract>

    <!--		
		<note title='Foreword'>
		</note>
		-->

    <!--
    <note title="Requirements">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
      document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
      target="RFC2119"></xref>.</t>
    </note>
    -->

    <!--
            <?rfc needLines='10' ?>
            <texttable anchor='table_example' title='A Very Simple Table'>
                <preamble>Tables use ttcol to define column headers and widths.
                Every cell then has a &quot;c&quot; element for its content.</preamble>
 <ttcol align='center'>ttcol #1</ttcol>
                    <ttcol align='center'>ttcol #2</ttcol>
                      <c>c #1</c>		<c>c #2</c>
                      <c>c #3</c>		<c>c #4</c>
                      <c>c #5</c>		<c>c #6</c>
                <postamble>which is a very simple example.</postamble>
            </texttable>
    -->
  </front>

  <middle>
    <!--		
			<t>There are multiple list styles: 'symbols', 'letters', 'numbers',
'hanging', 'format', etc.</t>
			<t>
				<list style='symbols'>
					<t>First bullet</t>
					<t>Second bullet</t>
				</list>
			</t>
-->

    <!--
<figure anchor='reference' title='Figure'>
<artwork align='center'>
<![CDATA[
	ASCII artwork goes here... 
]]>
</artwork>
</figure>
-->

    <section anchor="intro" title="Introduction">
      <t>Darknets, also called "Network Telescopes" among other things, have
      been deployed by several organizations including CAIDA, Team Cymru, and
      the University of Michigan, to look at traffic directed to addresses in
      blocks that are not in actual use. Such traffic becomes visible by
      either direct capture (it is routed to a collector) or by virtue of its
      backscatter (its resulting in ICMP traffic or transport layer
      resets).</t>

      <t>Darknets, of course, have two problems. As their address spaces
      become known, attackers stop probing them, so they are less effective.
      Also, the administrators of those prefixes are pressured by RIR policy
      and business requirements to deploy them in active networks.</t>

      <t><xref target="Harrop"></xref> defines a 'Greynet' by extension, in
      these words:</t>

      <t><list style="empty">
          <t>Darknets are often proposed to monitor for anomalous, externally
          sourced traffic, and require large, contiguous blocks of unused IP
          addresses - not always feasible for enterprise network operators. We
          introduce and evaluate the Greynet - a region of IP address space
          that is sparsely populated with "darknet" addresses interspersed
          with active (or "lit") IP addresses. Based on a small sample of
          traffic collected within a university campus network we saw that
          relatively sparse greynets can achieve useful levels of network scan
          detection.</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>In other words, instead of setting aside prefixes that an attacker
      might attempt to probe and in so doing court discovery, Harrop proposed
      that individual (or small groups of adjacent) addresses in subnets be
      set aside for the purpose, using different host identifiers in each
      subnet to make it more difficult for an address scan to detect them. The
      concept has value in the sense that it is harder to map the addresses or
      prefixes out of an attacker's search pattern, as their presence is more
      obscure. Harrop's research was carried out using <xref
      target="RFC0791">IPv4</xref>, and yielded interesting information.</t>

      <section anchor="history" title="History and experience">
        <t>The research supporting this proposal includes two prototypes, one
        with <xref target="RFC0791">IPv4</xref> and one with <xref
        target="RFC2460">IPv6</xref>. Both have limitations, being research
        experiments as opposed to deployment of a finished product.</t>

        <t>The original research was done by Warren Harrop and documented in
        <xref target="Harrop"></xref>. This was IPv4-only. His premise was
        that one would put a virtual or physical machine on a LAN that one was
        not otherwise using, and use it to identify scans of various kinds. As
        reported in his paper, the concept worked effectively in a prototype
        deployment at Swinburne University CAIA. The basic reason was that
        there was a reasonable expectation on the part of a potential attacker
        that a given address might be represented, and there was no pattern
        that would enable the attacker to predict which addresses were being
        used in this way.</t>

        <t>Baker's addition to his concept started from the router, the idea
        that the router would be highly likely to encounter any such scan if
        it came from off-LAN, and the fact that the router would have to use
        ARP or ND to identify - or fail to identify - the machine in question.
        In effect, any address that is not currently instantiated in the
        subnet acts as a greynet trigger address. This obviously also works
        for any system that would implement ARP or Neighbor Discovery, but the
        router is an obvious focal point in any subnet.</t>

        <t>Tim Chown, School of Electronics and Computer Science, University
        of Southampton, offered privately to do some research on it, and had
        Owen Stephens do a Linux prototype in spring 2010. They demonstrated
        that the technology was straightforward to implement and in fact
        worked in a prototype IPv6 implementation.</t>

        <t>The question that remains with IPv6 address scanning is the
        likelihood that the attack would occur at all. Tim originally argued
        in <xref target="RFC5157"></xref> that address scans were impossible
        due to the sheer number of possibilities. There are, however, ways to
        limit the field; for example, one can observe that a company buys a
        certain kind of machine or NIC, and therefore its probable EUI-64
        addresses are limited to a much smaller range than 2^64 - more like
        2^24 addresses on a given subnet - or one can observe DNS, SMTP
        envelopes, XMPP messages, FTP, HTTP, etc, that carry IP addresses in
        other ways. We have not yet seen such attacks in the wild that I know
        of, but as IPv6 becomes more widely used, one has to believe that such
        things will happen. Such attacks can be limited by the use of <xref
        target="RFC4941">Privacy Addresses</xref>, which periodically change,
        rendering historical information less useful, but the fact is that
        such analytic methods exist. Greynets are a tool that can be used to
        isolate and analyze them.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="deployment" title="Deploying Greynets">
      <t>Corporate IT departments and other network operators frequently run
      collectors or other kinds of sensors. A collector is a computer system
      on the Internet that is expressly set up to attract and "trap" nefarious
      attempts to penetrate computer systems. Such systems may simply record
      the attempt or the datagram that initiated the attempt
      (darknets/greynets), or they may act as a decoy, luring in potential
      attacks in order to study their activities and study their methods
      (honey pots).</t>

      <t>To accomplish this, we separate nefarious traffic from that which is
      likely normal and important, studying one and facilitating the
      other.</t>

      <section anchor="routing" title="Deployment using routing - Darknets">
        <t>One obvious way to isolate and identify nefarious traffic is to
        realize that it is sent to a prefix or address that is not
        instantiated. If a campus uses an IPv4 /24 prefix or an IPv6 /56
        prefix but contains less than 100 actual subnets, for example, we
        might use only odd numbered subnets (128 of the 256 available in that
        prefix), and not quite all of those. Knowing that the active prefixes
        are more specific and therefore attract appropriate traffic, we might
        also advertise the default prefix from the collector, attracting
        traffic directed to the uninstantiated prefixes in that routing
        domain.</t>

        <t>A second question involves mimicking a host under attack; the
        collector may simply record this uninvited traffic, or may reply as a
        honeypot system.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="non_neighbors"
               title="Deployment using sparse address space - Greynets">
        <t>IPv4 subnets usually have some unallocated space in them, if only
        because CIDR allocates O(2^n) addresses to an IP Subnet and there are
        not exactly that many systems there.</t>

        <t>Similarly, with active IPv6 prefixes, even a very large switched
        LAN is likely to use a small fraction of the available addresses. This
        is by design, as discussed in section 2.5.1 of <xref
        target="RFC4291"></xref>. If the addresses are distributed reasonably
        randomly among the possible values, the likelihood of an attacker
        guessing what addresses are in actual use is limited. This gives us an
        opportunity with respect to unused addresses within a IP prefix.</t>

        <t>Routers use <xref target="RFC0826">IPv4 ARP</xref> and <xref
        target="RFC4861">IPv6 Neighbor Discovery</xref> to determine the MAC
        address of a neighbor to which a datagram needs to be sent. Both
        specifications intend that when a datagram arrives at a router serving
        the target prefix, but which doesn't know the MAC address of the
        intended destination, it should: <list style="symbols">
            <t>Enqueue the datagram,</t>

            <t>Emit a Neighbor Solicitation or ARP Request,</t>

            <t>Await a Neighbor Advertisement or ARP Response, and</t>

            <t>On receipt, dequeue and forward the datagram.</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>Once the host's MAC address is in the router's tables (and in so
        doing the address proven valid), the matter is not an issue.</t>

        <t>In <xref target="Harrop"></xref>, the Greynet is described as being
        instantiated on an end-host that replies to ARP Requests for all
        'dark' IP addresses. However, a small modification to router behavior
        can augment this model. As well as queuing or dropping a datagram that
        has triggered an ARP Request or Neighbor Solicitation, the router
        forwards a copy of this datagram over an independent link to the
        Greynet's analytic equipment. This independent link may be a different
        physical interface, a circuit, VLAN, tunnel, UDP or other
        encapsulation, or in fact any place such a datagram could be handled.
        Depending on the requirements of the receiving collector, one could
        also imagine summarizing information in a form similar to <xref
        target="RFC5101">IPFIX</xref><xref target="RFC5610"></xref>.</t>

        <t>The analytic equipment will now receive two types of datagrams. Of
        most interest will be those destined for 'dark' IP addresses. Of less
        interest will be the irregular case where a datagram arrives for a
        legitimate local neighbor who has, for some temporary reason, no MAC
        address in the router's tables. Datagrams arriving for an IP
        destination for which an ARP reply (or Neighbor Advertisement) has not
        yet received might also be forwarded to the analytical equipment over
        the independent link - or might not, if they are considered to be
        unlikely to provide new analytic information.</t>

        <t>Analytic equipment, depending on the router to recognize 'dark' IP
        addresses in this manner, can easily track arrival patterns of
        datagrams destined to unused parts of the network. It may also
        optionally chose to respond to such datagrams, acting as a honeypot to
        elicit further datagrams from the remote source.</t>

        <t>If the collector replies directly, the attacker may be able to
        identify the fact through information in or about the datagram -
        datagrams sent to the same IP Subnet may come back with different TTL
        values, for example. Hence, it may be advisable for the collector to
        send the reply back through the tunnel and therefore as if from the
        same IP Subnet. Naturally the collector in this scenario should not
        respond to datagrams destined for 'lit' IP addresses - the intended
        destination will eventually respond to the router's ARP or Neighbor
        Solicitation anyway.</t>

        <t>One implication of this model is that ddos attacks terminate on
        router subnets within a network, as opposed to stopping on
        inter-router links.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Other filters">
        <t>An obvious extension of the concept would include traffic
        identified by other filters as appropriate to send to the collector.
        For example, one might configure the system to forward traffic failing
        a unicast reverse forwarding path (uRPF) check <xref
        target="RFC2827"></xref> to the collector via the same tunnel.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="sowhat" title="Implications for router design">
      <t>The implication for router design applies to the IPv4 ARP and IPv6
      Neighbor Discovery algorithms. It might be interesting to provide, under
      configuration control, the ability to forward arriving datagrams that
      trigger an ARP Request or Neighbor Solicit, and then fail to receive the
      intended response, to an interface, circuit, VLAN, or tunnel to an
      analytic system.</t>
    </section>

    <!-- possibly a 'Contributors' section ... -->

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>This memo asks the IANA for no new parameters.</t>

      <t>Note to RFC Editor: This section will have served its purpose if it
      correctly tells IANA that no new assignments or registries are required,
      or if those assignments or registries are created during the RFC
      publication process. From the author's perspective, it may therefore be
      removed upon publication as an RFC at the RFC Editor's discretion.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>This note describes a tool for managing IPv4 and IPv6 network
      security. Like any tool, it has limitations and possible attacks. If
      discarding traffic under overload is a good thing, then holding and
      subsequently forwarding the traffic instead places a potential load on
      the network and the router in question, and as such represents a
      possible attack. Such an attack has obvious mitigations, however; one
      simply, in a manner the operator deems appropriate, selects a subset of
      the traffic to forward and discards the rest. In addition, this attack
      is not new; it is only changed in character. A stream that would
      instantiate the attack today results in a load of ARP or Neighbor
      Solicit messages that all listening hosts must intelligently discard.
      The new attack additionally consumes bandwidth that is presumably set
      aside specifically for that purpose.</t>

      <t>The question of exactly what subset of traffic is interesting and
      economical to forward is intentionally left open. Key questions in
      algorithm design include what can be learned from a given sample (are
      bursts happening, and if so with what data?), what the impact on the
      router and other equipment in question is, how that might be mitigated,
      etc. Possible selection algorithms dependent only on state and
      algorithms typically available in a router include: <list
          style="symbols">
          <t>All datagrams triggering an ARP Request or Neighbor Solicit,</t>

          <t>The subset of those that are not responded to within some stated
          interval and are therefore likely dark,</t>

          <t>The subset of those that are new; if the address is currently
          being solicited, forwarding redundant data may not be useful.</t>

          <t>All such datagrams up to some rate,</t>

          <t>All such datagrams matching (or not matching) a specified filter
          rule,</t>

          <t>etc.</t>
        </list></t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>Algorithms for learning about Internet attack behavior by observing
      backscatter traffic have been used by CAIDA, University of Michigan,
      Team Cymru, and others. Harrop extended them in his research. This
      formulation of the notion originated in a discussion among the authors
      in 2005. This note grew out of a conversation with Paul Vixie and Rhette
      Marsh on Internet traffic sensors; they also made useful comments on it.
      Albert Manfredi commented on the distinction between a LAN (as defined
      by IEEE 802) and an IP subnet.</t>

      <t>Tim Chown <xref target="RFC5157"></xref> has observed that, at least
      at this time, address scanning attacks in IPv6 have not been reported in
      the wild. Rhette Marsh has suggested the structure of such an attack,
      however, and Fred Baker has suggested approaches based on addressing
      information exchanged by applications. Hence, we believe that such
      issues may be relevant to IPv6 in the future, when IPv6 is a more
      interesting target.</t>

      <t>Tim Chown and Owen Stephens tested the proposal, and made useful
      comments that have been incorporated in this text. His fundamental
      comment was, however, that "it works".</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <!-- references split to informative and normative -->

    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.0791' ?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.0826' ?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.2460'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.4291' ?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.4861'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.4941'?>

      <reference anchor="Harrop">
        <front>
          <title>Greynets: a definition and evaluation of sparsely populated
          darknets</title>

          <author fullname="Warren Harrop" initials="W." surname="Harrop">
            <organization>Swinburne University of Technology, Melbourne,
            Australia</organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="Grenville Armitage" initials="G."
                  surname="Armitage">
            <organization>Swinburne University of Technology, Melbourne,
            Australia</organization>
          </author>

          <date month="" year="2005" />
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="IEEE LCN"
                    value="IEEE 30th Conference on Local Computer Networks" />

        <format target="http://ieeexplore.ieee.org/ielx5/10397/33047/01550875.pdf?tp="
                type="PDF" />
      </reference>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative references">
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.2827' ?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5101" ?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.5157'?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5610" ?>
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
