<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="D:\draft\rfc2629xslt\rfc2629xslt\rfc2629.xslt"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<rfc category="info" docName="draft-zhao-lisp-mn-extension-02"
     ipr="trust200902" obsoletes="" submissionType="independent" updates=""
     xml:lang="en">
  <?rfc toc="yes" ?>

  <?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>

  <?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>

  <front>
    <title abbrev="LISP Mobile Node extension">LISP Mobile Node
    extension</title>

    <author fullname="Ningxia Zhao" initials="Ningxia" surname="Zhao">
      <organization>ZTE Corporation</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>4F,RD Building 2,Zijinghua Road No.68</street>

          <region>Yuhuatai District,Nanjing 210012</region>

          <country>P.R.China</country>
        </postal>

        <phone>+86-025-5287-7612</phone>

        <email>zhao.ningxia@zte.com.cn</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Jiong Shen" initials="Jiong" surname="Shen">
      <organization>ZTE Corporation</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>4F,RD Building 2,Zijinghua Road No.68</street>

          <region>Yuhuatai District,Nanjing 210012</region>

          <country>P.R.China</country>
        </postal>

        <phone>+86-025-5287-7612</phone>

        <email>wang.jun17@zte.com.cn</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Mo Sun" initials="Mo" surname="Sun">
      <organization>ZTE Corporation</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>C1-04,RD Building 1,Zijinghua Road No.68</street>

          <region>Yuhuatai District,Nanjing 210012</region>

          <country>P.R.China</country>
        </postal>

        <phone>+86-025-5287-2045</phone>

        <email>meng.yu@zte.com.cn</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date day="30" month="October" year="2011" />

    <area>Standard</area>

    <workgroup>PPSP Working Group</workgroup>

    <keyword>Internet Draft</keyword>

    <keyword>I-D</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>LISP describes a network-based protocol that enables separation of IP
      addresses into two new numbering spaces: Endpoint Identifiers (EIDs) and
      Routing Locators (RLOCs). No changes are required to either host
      protocol stacks or to the "core" of the Internet infrastructure. The
      LISP Mobile Node extension design described in this document uses
      standard LISP functionality to provide scalable mobility for LISP mobile
      nodes.</t>

      <t>This document extends the lisp, it introduces some contents that lisp
      does not include but the author think it is important and recommendation
      them to be considered in the lisp.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction" toc="default">
      <t>LISP defines protocol mechanisms for mapping from EIDs to RLOCs, the
      lisp-MN specifies the behavior of the LISP Mobile Node, it has
      introduced some aspects of lisp-MN, but there are some other important
      areas have not considered.</t>

      <t>The LISP Mobile Node extension design described in this document uses
      standard LISP functionality to provide scalable mobility for the mobile
      node in the LISP site.</t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>The EID-to-RLOC mapping update operation has not be considered.
          When a MN in the LISP site roams onto a new network, it receives a
          new RLOC, the lisp-MN Map-Registers it's new RLOC to its configured
          Map-Server, then the lisp-MN sends packet to its peer side by the
          new RLOC. But before the peer side receives the packet the lisp-MN
          sent, the peer side will send packet to lisp-MN by the old RLOC or
          the peer side must query the MS to obtain the lisp-MN's RLOC and
          then the peer side updates its cache of the EID-to-RLOC mapping and
          send packet by the new RLOC, this will cause a problem, the packet
          the lisp-MN to receive from its peer side will be missed or delayed
          when the LISP-MN roams onto a new network. So how to update the
          previous EID-to-RLOC mapping cached in the lisp-MN's peer side must
          be considered.</t>

          <t>The deregister has not be considered. When a MN in the lisp site
          is shutdown or the user initiates to interrupt the network
          connection or the contract is limited, the lisp-MN needn't continue
          attach to the network, the lisp-MN or the network will initiate the
          process of the Map-Unregister.</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>This document specifies the LISP-MN extension operation, which
      includes two aspects, the EID-to-RLOC Mapping Update Operation and the
      Map-Unregister Operation.</t>

      <t>Design goals for the LISP-MN extension design include:</t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>The LISP-MN extension design described in this document based on
          the Lisp, this document does not change any contents of the
          LISP.</t>

          <t>The LISP-MN extension design described in this document uses
          standard LISP functionality.</t>

          <t>This document only do some extension of the lisp and only
          introduces the contents the author think must be supplemented to the
          lisp .</t>

          <t>The LISP-MN extension design is built from the existing LISP
          components: the MN in lisp site, its corresponding side in
          communication , the existing Map-Server [LISP-MS] and the
          Interworking <xref target="LISP-INTERWORK"></xref>
          infrastructures.</t>
        </list></t>
    </section>

    <section title="new section">
      <t></t>
    </section>

    <section title="Terminology" toc="default">
      <t>This section defines the terms used in this document.</t>

      <t>LISP Mobile Node (LISP-MN): A LISP capable fast roaming mobile
      hand-set.</t>

      <t>Endpoint ID (EID): This is the traditional LISP EID [LISP], and is
      the address that a LISP mobile node uses as its address for transport
      connections. A LISP mobile node never changes its EID, which is
      typically a /32 or /128 prefix and is assigned to a loopback interface.
      Note that the mobile node can have multiple EIDs, and these EIDs can be
      from different address families.</t>

      <t>Routing Locator (RLOC): This is the traditional LISP RLOC, and is in
      general a routable address that can be used to reach a mobile node. Note
      that there are cases in which an mobile node may receive an address that
      it thinks is an RLOC (perhaps via DHCP) which is either an EID or an RFC
      1918 address <xref target="RFC1918"></xref>[RFC1918]. This could happen
      if, for example, if the mobile node roams into a LISP domain or a domain
      behind a Network Address Translator (NAT).</t>

      <t>Map-cache: A data structure which contains an EID-prefix, its
      associated RLOCs, and the associated policy. Map-caches are typically
      found in ITRs and PITRs.</t>

      <t>Map Update: A Map update is the lisp-MN notifies the correspondent to
      change the EID-to-RLOC mapping when the lisp-MN move to another location
      in the communication process.</t>

      <t>Map Unregister: A Map Unregister is the lisp-MN notifies the MS<xref
      target="LISP-Map-Server"></xref> to unbind the EID-to-RLOC mapping when
      the lisp-MN needn&rsquo;t to attached to the network.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="LISP Extension Operation" toc="default">
      <t>The LISP Extension Operation described in this document uses the
      ETR/ITR or theLISP-MN to provide scalable fast mobility and the
      Map-Unregister operation.</t>

      <section title=" EID-to-RLOC Mapping Update Operation">
        <t>This section provides the EID-to-RLOC mapping update operation.</t>

        <t>After a roaming event, a LISP-MN must immediately register its new
        EID-to-RLOC mapping with its configured Map-Server(s). In addition,
        the Lisp-MN sends the EID-to-RLOC mapping update request to its peer
        side to inform the peer side the LISP-MN which is ongoing
        communication has moved to a new location and the Lisp-MN has received
        a new RLOC, the EID-to-RLOC mapping update request message carries the
        EID and the new RLOC of the Lisp-MN. After received the EID-to-RLOC
        mapping update request, the peer side updates the EID-to-RLOC mapping
        cached in its local, that is in the local cache use the new RLOC
        instead of the old RLOC in the EID-to-RLOC mapping, then the peer side
        returns he EID-to-RLOC mapping update response (Update Response)
        message to the lisp-MN. The EID-to-RLOC mapping update operation
        improves the efficiency of data transmission and decreases the
        occurrence of packet latency and packet loss when a roaming event
        occurs in communication .</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Map-Unregister Operation">
        <t>When the MN in a lisp site is shutdown or the user initiates to
        interrupt the network connection, the MN needn't continue register to
        the network, the lisp-MN will initiate the process of the
        Map-Unregister.</t>

        <t>The lisp-MN sends a map-unregister to its configured Map-Server(s)
        to delete the EID-to-RLOC mapping stored in this MS.</t>

        <t>After received the Map-Unregister Request, the MS removes the
        EID-to-RLOC mapping stored in it and sends the Map-Unregister response
        to the lisp-MN, the message in this process carries the instructions
        indicates the success or failure of the Map-Unregister operation. The
        Map-Unregister process is completed.</t>

        <t>The Map-Unregister Operation also inclueds another scenario, when
        the lisp network detects the contact of the host is limited (how does
        the network detect the contact of the host is limited is out of this
        scope), the network will initiate the process of the
        Map-Unregister.</t>

        <t>When the lisp network detects the contact of the host is limited,
        the network side informs the MS the host be listed in the black. Then
        the MS removes the EID-to-RLOC mapping stored in it and sends a
        map-unregister to the ETR and the ITR which communications with the
        host&#65292; The MS can inform the ITR based on which has queried the
        MS for the EID-to-RLOC mapping of the host and TTL has not
        expired.</t>

        <t>After received the Map-Unregister Request, the ITR removes the
        EID-to-RLOC mapping stored in its cache and sends the Map-Unregister
        response to the MS, the ETR sets rules to prevent the flow to and from
        the black host according to EID of the black host and sends the
        Map-Unregister response to the MS.The Map-Unregister process is
        completed.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="LISP Extension Message" toc="default">
      <t></t>

      <section title="LISP Packet Type Allocations">
        <t>This section will be the authoritative source for allocating LISP
        Type values. Current allocations are:</t>

        <t><list style="symbols">
            <t>LISP Map-Update: 5 b'0101'</t>

            <t>LISP Map-Unregister: 6 b'0110'</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>

      <section title="Map-Update Message Format">
        <t>The Map-Update message format is:</t>

        <figure anchor="service-discovery" title="Map-Update Message Format">
          <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[ 
        0                   1                   2                   3
        0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
       +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
       |Type=5 |P|              Reserved               | Record Count  |
       +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
       |                         Nonce . . .                           |
       +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
       |                         . . . Nonce                           |
   +-> +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |   |                          Record  TTL                          |
   |   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   R   | Locator Count | EID mask-len  | ACT |A|      Reserved         |
   e   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   c   | Rsvd  |  Map-Version Number   |       EID-prefix-AFI          |
   o   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   r   |                          EID-prefix                           |
   d   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |  /|    Priority   |    Weight     |  M Priority   |   M Weight    |
   | L +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   | o |        Unused Flags     |L|p|R|           Loc-AFI             |
   | c +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |  \|                             Locator                           |
   +-> +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
       |                     Mapping Protocol Data                     |
       +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+


]]></artwork>
        </figure>

        <t>Packet field descriptions:</t>

        <t>Type: 5 (Map-Update)</t>

        <t>The Map-Update message has the same contents as a Map-Register
        message. See Map-Register section in LISP <xref
        target="LISP"></xref>for field descriptions.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Map-Unregister Message Format">
        <t>The Map-Unregister message format is:</t>

        <t><figure align="center">
            <artwork align="left" xml:space="preserve"><![CDATA[
        0                   1                   2                   3
        0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
       +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
       |Type=6 |P|              Reserved               | Record Count  |
       +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
       |                         Nonce . . .                           |
       +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
       |                         . . . Nonce                           |
   +-> +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |   |                          Record  TTL                          |
   |   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   R   | Locator Count | EID mask-len  | ACT |A|      Reserved         |
   e   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   c   | Rsvd  |  Map-Version Number   |       EID-prefix-AFI          |
   o   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   r   |                          EID-prefix                           |
   d   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |  /|    Priority   |    Weight     |  M Priority   |   M Weight    |
   | L +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   | o |        Unused Flags     |L|p|R|           Loc-AFI             |
   | c +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |  \|                             Locator                           |
   +-> +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
       |                     Mapping Protocol Data                     |
       +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+

]]></artwork>
          </figure> Packet field descriptions:</t>

        <t>Type: 6 (Map-Unregister)</t>

        <t>The EID-prefix in this message including the length is zero and the
        length in non-zero, when the length is zero, the EID-prefix just equal
        to the EID.</t>

        <t>Because one EID maybe mapping to multiple RLOCs, so the
        Map-Unregister operation including two cases. One case is to remove
        all the RLOC mapping to the EID when the Map-Unregister occurs, this
        time the Map-Unregister Message Format does not contain the field of
        the Locator. The second case is only remove one specific RLOC mapping
        to the EID when the Map-Unregister occurs, this time the
        Map-Unregister Message Format just contains the field of the Locator
        which must be canceled.</t>

        <t>The other field of the Map-Unregister message just has the same
        contents as a Map-Register message. See Map-Register section in LISP
        <xref target="LISP"></xref> for field descriptions.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Security Considerations" toc="default">
      <t>Security for the LISP-MN design builds upon the security fundamentals
      found in LISP [LISP] for data-plane security and the LISP Map Server
      [LISP-MS] registration security. Security issues unique to the LISP-MN
      design are considered below.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="IANA Considerations" toc="default">
      <t>This document creates no new requirements on IANA namespaces .<xref
      target="RFC5226"></xref></t>
    </section>

    <section title="Acknowledgments" toc="default">
      <t>TBD</t>

      <t></t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <reference anchor="RFC1918">
        <front>
          <title>Address Allocation for Private Internets</title>

          <author initials="Y." surname="Rekhter">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author initials="R." surname="Moskowitz">
            <organization></organization>

            <address>
              <postal>
                <street></street>

                <city></city>

                <region></region>

                <code></code>

                <country></country>
              </postal>

              <phone></phone>

              <facsimile></facsimile>

              <email></email>

              <uri></uri>
            </address>
          </author>

          <date year="1996" />
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RFC5226">
        <front>
          <title>Guidelines for Writing an IANA Considerations Section in
          RFCs</title>

          <author initials="T." surname="Narten">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author initials="H." surname="Alvestrand">
            <organization></organization>

            <address>
              <postal>
                <street></street>

                <city></city>

                <region></region>

                <code></code>

                <country></country>
              </postal>

              <phone></phone>

              <facsimile></facsimile>

              <email></email>

              <uri></uri>
            </address>
          </author>

          <date month="May" year="2008" />
        </front>
      </reference>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <reference anchor="LISP-Map-Server">
        <front>
          <title>LISP Map Server</title>

          <author initials="D." surname="Farinacci"></author>

          <author initials="V." surname="Fuller"></author>

          <date month="June" year="2011" />
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="draft-ietf-lisp-ms-08" value="work in progress" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="LISP-INTERWORK">
        <front>
          <title>Interworking LISP with IPv4 and IPv6</title>

          <author initials="D." surname="Lewis">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author initials="D." surname="Meyer">
            <organization></organization>

            <address>
              <postal>
                <street></street>

                <city></city>

                <region></region>

                <code></code>

                <country></country>
              </postal>

              <phone></phone>

              <facsimile></facsimile>

              <email></email>

              <uri></uri>
            </address>
          </author>

          <author initials="D." surname="Farinacci">
            <organization></organization>

            <address>
              <postal>
                <street></street>

                <city></city>

                <region></region>

                <code></code>

                <country></country>
              </postal>

              <phone></phone>

              <facsimile></facsimile>

              <email></email>

              <uri></uri>
            </address>
          </author>

          <author initials="V." surname="Fuller">
            <organization></organization>

            <address>
              <postal>
                <street></street>

                <city></city>

                <region></region>

                <code></code>

                <country></country>
              </postal>

              <phone></phone>

              <facsimile></facsimile>

              <email></email>

              <uri></uri>
            </address>
          </author>

          <date month="March" year="2011" />
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="LISP">
        <front>
          <title>Locator/ID Separation Protocol (LISP)</title>

          <author initials="D." surname="Farinacci">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author initials="V." surname="Fuller">
            <organization></organization>

            <address>
              <postal>
                <street></street>

                <city></city>

                <region></region>

                <code></code>

                <country></country>
              </postal>

              <phone></phone>

              <facsimile></facsimile>

              <email></email>

              <uri></uri>
            </address>
          </author>

          <author initials="D." surname="Meyer">
            <organization></organization>

            <address>
              <postal>
                <street></street>

                <city></city>

                <region></region>

                <code></code>

                <country></country>
              </postal>

              <phone></phone>

              <facsimile></facsimile>

              <email></email>

              <uri></uri>
            </address>
          </author>

          <author initials="D." surname="Lewis">
            <organization></organization>

            <address>
              <postal>
                <street></street>

                <city></city>

                <region></region>

                <code></code>

                <country></country>
              </postal>

              <phone></phone>

              <facsimile></facsimile>

              <email></email>

              <uri></uri>
            </address>
          </author>

          <date month="April" year="2011" />
        </front>
      </reference>
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
