<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY rfc2021 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2021.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc2863 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2863.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc3418 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3418.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc2119 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc2578 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2578.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc2579 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2579.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc2580 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2580.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc3410 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3410.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc4001 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4001.xml">
]>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<?rfc strict="no"?>
<?rfc rfcedstyle="yes"?>
<rfc category="exp" docName="draft-ietf-manet-report-mib-03" ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="The REPORT-SAMPLED-MIB">Definition of Managed Objects for
    Performance Reporting</title>

    <author fullname="Robert G. Cole" initials="R.G." surname="Cole">
      <organization>US Army CERDEC</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>6010 Frankford Road</street>
          <city>Aberdeen Proving Ground</city>
          <region>Maryland</region>
          <code>21005</code>
          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>

        <phone>+1 443 395 8744</phone>
        <email>robert.g.cole@us.army.mil</email>
        <uri>http://www.cs.jhu.edu/~rgcole/</uri>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Joseph Macker" initials="J.M." surname="Macker">
      <organization>Naval Research Laboratory</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>
          <city>Washington</city>
          <region>D.C.</region>
          <code>20375</code>
          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>

        <email>macker@itd.nrl.navy.mil</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Andy Bierman" initials="A." surname="Bierman">
      <organization>YumaWorks, Inc.</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>
          <city>Redwood City</city>
          <region>CA</region>
          <code>94065</code>
          <country></country>
        </postal>

        <email>andy@yumaworks.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date />

    <area>Operations and Management</area>

    <workgroup>Internet Engineering Task Force</workgroup>

    <keyword>Network Management</keyword>
    <keyword>Management Information Base</keyword>
    <keyword>MIB</keyword>
    <keyword>SMIv2</keyword>
    <keyword>Reporting</keyword>
    <keyword>MANET</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>This memo defines a portion of the Management Information Base (MIB)
      for use with network management protocols in the Internet community. In
      particular, it describes objects for configuring autonomous
      report generation on any device that supports MIBs containing
      counter and gauge objects for performance monitoring.
      This allows a management station
      to instruct a device to build off-line reports 
      to be collected asynchronously by
      the management station.  Further, this REPORT-SAMPLED-MIB can be configured in a
      proxy configuration where the report generation is performed on a device
      in close network proximity to the device containing the referenced counter
      objects.  Hence, this capability allows network operators to reduce
      the SNMP polling traffic burden on Mobile Ad-Hoc and Disruption Tolerant
      Networks which is typical of SNMP performance management applications.
      </t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>This memo defines a portion of the Management Information Base (MIB)
      for use with network management protocols in the Internet community. In
      particular, it describes objects for configuring autonomous, off-line report
      generation for performance monitoring on any device supporting 
      MIBs containing variables that resolve to type Integer32 
      (i.e., Integer32, Counter, Gauge, or TimeTicks).  This REPORT-SAMPLED-MIB
      allows for the report generation to occur on the same device as containing the
      referenced counter object or on a device in close network proximity
      to the device with the referenced counter object.
      This should be useful to devices or networks where efficient use
      of bandwidth is of concern or where intermittent connectivity
      is common.  Hence, the REPORT-SAMPLED-MIB is useful for devices managed over
      some Mobile Ad-Hoc Networks (MANETs) or Disruption Tolerant Networks (DTNs).</t>

      <t>This version of the  REPORT-SAMPLED-MIB offers one type of off-line reporting.  
      The MIB offers a means to collect sampled data related to defined
      MIB objects.  This type of reporting is contained in 
      the reportSampledGroup.  Other types of report data are possible, including
      statistical data and historical data.  However, it was felt wise to
      focus on a more limited scope off-line reporting capability and
      gain experimental use and application prior to expending energy
      developing a more extensive capability.</t>

      <t>For the collection of sampled data, the REPORT-SAMPLED-MIB
      draws directly from the usrHistoryGroup from RMON 2
      <xref target="RFC2021"></xref> through application of the 
      'AUGMENTS' clause.
.
      Here the reportSampledControlTable allows the user to
      define aspects of the report for sampled data, including
      the number of MIB objects to be sampled and the nature of the
      sampling frequency and overall report duration.  This
      group uses the notion of buckets, which contain sampled data
      from a set of identified MIB objects sampled at the same time point.
      The report consists of the buckets, 
      each containing sets of sampled
      data from the selected MIB objects but at 
      the specific sampling times.
      The reportSampledObjectTable allows the user to identify
      the multiple MIB objects to be sampled.  The reportSampledDataTable
      contains the storage of the reported sampled data contained within
      buckets, one bucket for each time sampling instance.</t>

    </section>


    <section title="The Internet-Standard Management Framework">
      <t>For a detailed overview of the documents that describe the current
      Internet-Standard Management Framework, please refer to section 7 of RFC
      3410 <xref target="RFC3410"></xref>.</t>

      <t>Managed objects are accessed via a virtual information store, termed
      the Management Information Base or MIB. MIB objects are generally
      accessed through the Simple Network Management Protocol (SNMP). Objects
      in the MIB are defined using the mechanisms defined in the Structure of
      Management Information (SMI). This memo specifies a MIB module that is
      compliant to the SMIv2, which is described in STD 58, RFC 2578 <xref
      target="RFC2578"></xref>, STD 58, RFC 2579 <xref
      target="RFC2579"></xref> and STD 58, RFC 2580 <xref
      target="RFC2580"></xref>.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Conventions">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
      document are to be interpreted as described in RFC 2119 <xref
      target="RFC2119"></xref>.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Overview">
      <t>The REPORT-SAMPLED-MIB references performance objects in other MIBs
         (and in other devices) and
         generates off-line performance reports related to those referenced objects.
         The REPORT-SAMPLED-MIB can be coincident with the other MIB or can reside
         on another device in close network proximity to the device
         containing the referenced performance related object.</t>

      <section title="REPORT-SAMPLED-MIB Management Model">
        <t>This section describes the management model for the
        REPORT-SAMPLED-MIB process.  
        </t>

        <t>Figure 1 illustrates a potential use of the REPORT-SAMPLED-MIB
           for the generation of off-line, remotely generated reports.
           The management station on the left hand side of the illustration
           instructs the remote device to create reports through manipulation
           of the ReportCntrl Objects in the REPORT-SAMPLED-MIB resident on the
           remote device.  The reports instruct the device to monitor the
           status of specified counters (on other MIBs and potentially
           on other devices in close network proximity) periodically.
           The reports are stored locally
           until the management station decides to pull them off the
           device.  The figure shows a case where the REPORT-SAMPLED-MIB generates
           a notification that Report_2 has completed, prompting the management
           station to pull Report_2 from the device.</t>

      <figure>
         <preamble />
            <artwork><![CDATA[
Mgmt       Device
Station
                       REPORT-SAMPLED-MIB         MIB_1
                       +---------+        +-----+
                       |         |        |     |
 Build_Rep_1           |+-------+|        +--+  |
    +----------------->||cntrl_1||<------>|PC|  |
                       |+-------+|<-+     +--+--+
                       |         |  |
                       |         |  |     MIB_2
                       |         |  |     +-----+
                       |            |     |     |
                       |         |  |     +--+  |
                       |         |  +---->|PC|  |
 Build_Rep_2           |+-------+|    +-->+--+--+
    +----------------->||cntrl_2||<---+
                       |+-------+|
                       |         |
                       |         |
 Build_Rep_3           |+-------+|
    +----------------->||cntrl_3||<---+   MIB_n
                       |+-------+|    |   +-----+
                       |         |    |   |     |
                       |+-----+  |    |   +--+  |
                       ||Rep_1|  |    +-->|PC|  |
                       |+-----+  |        +--+--+
                       |         |
                       |+-----+  |
    <------------------||Rep_2|  |
 Notf_Rep_2            |+-----+  |
                       |         |
                       |+-----+  |
                       ||Rep_3|  |
                       |+-----+  |
 Get_Rep_2             |         |
    +----------------->|         |
                       |         |
    <-----------------+|         |
 Send_Rep_2            +---------+


Figure 1: REPORT-SAMPLED-MIB front-end report generation process.
           ]]></artwork>
         <postamble />
      </figure>

      <t>This version of the REPORT-SAMPLED-MIB provides for the collection of sampled data
         instead of statistical data.  It does this by augmenting
         the usrHistory group from RMON2 
         <xref target="RFC2021"></xref> which allows for the
         generation of reports collecting the sampled object values binned
         for the purpose of aggregation and efficiency of collection.
         These are defined within the reportSampledGroup.  The model
         used for this type of report generation is based upon three
         tables.  The reportSampledControlTable defines aspects of the
         report generation related to duration of the reporting interval,
         the bin (or bucket) sizes for the report, and the number of object
         values collected for each bucket.  The reportUsrHistoryObjectTable
         identifies the specific MIB objects whose values are binned
         within the report.  And the reportSampledDataTable contains
         the binned data values collected for the report.</t>

      </section>


      <section title="Terms">
        <t>The following definitions apply throughout this document:</t>

        <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>Control - Objects defined within this document which set the
             parameters for specific reports to be generated offline on the
             the remote managed device.</t>

          <t>Data - Objects which hold the sampled report data.</t>
        </list></t>
      </section>
    </section>


    <section title="Structure of the MIB Module">
      <t>This section presents the structure of the REPORT-SAMPLED-MIB module. The
      objects are arranged into the following groups:</t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
        <t>reportSampledMIBNotifications - defines the notifications associated with the
        REPORT-SAMPLED-MIB.</t>

        <t>reportSampledMIBObjects - defines the objects forming the basis for the 
        REPORT-SAMPLED-MIB. These objects are divided up by function into the following
        groups (currently only one group is defined):</t>

        <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>Sampled Group - This group contains the objects which
          support the generation (collection) of reports exposing
          sampled data values.</t>
        </list></t>

        <t>reportSampledMIBConformance - Defines a variety of conformance of
        implementations of this REPORT-SAMPLED-MIB.</t>
      </list></t>



      <section title="Textual Conventions">
        <!--Generic and Common Textual Conventions 
        can be found summarized at 
        http://www.ops.ietf.org/mib-common-tcs.html-->

        <t>No textual conventions are used in the REPORT-SAMPLED-MIB.</t>

      </section>


      <section title="The Sampled Group">
        <t>The Sampled Group contains tables which allows for the development
           of reports based upon sampling the referenced counter objects
           at specified intervals.  The development of this group within the
           REPORT-SAMPLED-MIB which augments the User History group
           from the RMON 2 MIB <xref target="RFC2021"></xref>.  
           The Sampled Group is composed of:</t>

        <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>reportSampledControlTable - allows for the setting of the parameters 
             of the report.</t>

          <t>reportSampledObjectTable - sets the referenced objects to be sampled
             during the test.  With this capability, the management application
             can reference multiple objects, all of which are sampled during the
             test and reported out through the reportSampledData Table.</t>

          <t>reportSampledDataTable - contains the reports.</t>
        </list></t>

      </section>


      <section title="The Notifications Group">
        <t>The Notifications Sub-tree contains the list of notifications
        supported within the REPORT-SAMPLED-MIB and their intended purpose or utility.
        The single notification defined within this MIB module is the
        'reportSampledNewDataReport'.   This notification is sent by the
        agent upon completion of a given report on the device.  The notification
        contains the following objects:
        'usrHistoryControlOwner', the entity that configured this report entry,
        and the 'reportSampledReportIndex', the index of the data table 
        for this report.  Collectively, these objects allow the management
        application to pull the completed report from the agent.
        </t>
      </section>


      <section title="Tables and Indexing">
        <t>The REPORT-SAMPLED-MIB module contains a number of tables which record
           data related to:
        </t>
        <t><list style='symbols'>  
           <t>the control and generation of remote performance reports,</t> 
           <t>the storage of remote performance reports, and</t>
           <t>the notification of remote report completion.</t>  
        </list></t>

        <t>The REPORT-SAMPLED-MIB module's tables are indexed via the following constructs:
        </t>
        <t><list style='symbols'>  
           <t>usrHistoryControlIndex - from the RMON2-MIB  <xref target="RFC2021"></xref>, 
	   an index that uniquely 
              identifies an entry in the usrHistoryControlTable.  
              Each such entry defines a set of samples at a particular interval 
              for a specified set of MIB instances available from the managed system.</t> 
           <t>usrHistoryObjectIndex - from the RMON2-MIB, 
              an index used to uniquely identify an entry in the
              usrHistoryObject table from the RMON2-MIB.  
              Each such entry defines a
	   MIB instance to be collected periodically.</t> 
           <t>reportSampledReportIndex - an index that uniquely identifies 
              the particular report an entry is associated with among the set of reports
              requested through the reportSampledControlNumber in the
              reportSampledControlEntry.</t> 
           <t>reportSampledSampleIndex - an index that uniquely identifies 
              the particular sample this entry represents among all samples associated 
              with the same reportSampledControlEntry.</t> 
        </list></t>

        <t>These tables and their indexing are:
        </t>
        <t><list style='symbols'>
           <t>reportSampledControlTable - this table contains a list
              of data-collection configuration entries defining aspects
              of the reports.  These include, e.g., number of reports, their
              start and stop times, etc.
              This table 'AUGMENTS { usrHistoryControlEntry }'.</t>
           <t>reportSampledObjectTable - this table contains a list
              of data-collection configuration entries which identify
              specific MIB entries on other devices to monitor.
              This table 'AUGMENTS { usrHistoryObjectEntry }'.</t>
           <t>reportSampledTable - this table contains a list
              of historical samples collected for the report.
              This table has 'INDEX { usrHistoryControlIndex, 
              reportSampledReportIndex, reportSampledSampleIndex, 
              usrHistoryObjectIndex }'.</t>
         </list></t>
      </section>

    </section>


    <section title="Relationship to Other MIB Modules">
      <t>The text of this section specifies the relationship of the
      MIB modules contained in this document to other standards, particularly
      to standards containing other MIB modules. Definitions imported from
      other MIB modules and other MIB modules that SHOULD be implemented in
      conjunction with the MIB module contained within this document are
      identified in this section.</t>

      <section title="Relationship to the SNMPv2-MIB">
        <t>The 'system' group in the SNMPv2-MIB <xref target="RFC3418"></xref>
        is defined as being mandatory for all systems, and the objects apply
        to the entity as a whole. The 'system' group provides identification
        of the management entity and certain other system-wide data. The
        REPORT-SAMPLED-MIB does not duplicate those objects.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Relationship to the RMON2-MIB">
        <t>The REPORT-SAMPLED-MIB is closely related to the RMON2-MIB
           <xref target="RFC2021"></xref> usrHistoryGroup.
           Specifically, the reportSampledGroup is a direct copy of the RMON2
           User History Group, with the names changed to comply with the
           naming conventions within the REPORT-SAMPLED-MIB.
           Further, the design and use of the control tables within the 
           REPORT-SAMPLED-MIB draw exactly from the definition of these table structures
           in the earlier RMON MIBs through the use of the 'AUGMENTS' clause
           within the 'reportSampledControlTable' and the
           'reportSampledTable' in this MIB module.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="MIB modules required for IMPORTS">
        <t>Citations are not permitted within a MIB module, but any
        module mentioned in an IMPORTS clause or document mentioned in a
        REFERENCE clause is a Normative reference, and must be cited someplace
        within the narrative sections. Therefore, the imported items in this MIB
        module, such as Textual Conventions, that are not already cited, are
        cited in this section. Since relationships to other MIB modules
        should be described in the narrative text, this section will
        cite modules from which Textual Conventions are imported.</t>

        <t>The REPORT-SAMPLED-MIB module IMPORTS objects from 
        SNMPv2-SMI <xref target="RFC2578"></xref>, 
        SNMPv2-TC <xref target="RFC2579"></xref>,
        SNMPv2-CONF <xref target="RFC2580"></xref>, 
        IF-MIB <xref target="RFC2863"></xref>, and
        INET-ADDRESS-MIB <xref target="RFC4001"></xref>.
        Significantly, the REPORT-SAMPLED-MIB module also IMPORTS objects
        from the RMON2-MIB module <xref target="RFC2021"></xref>.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <!-- Definitions section -->

    <!-- This section contains the MIB module(s) defined by the specification.
         These MIB modules MUST be written in SMIv2 [RFC2578] [RFC2579]
         [RFC2580].

         See Section 4 of RFC 4181 for guidelines on SMIv2 usage.

	 See Appendix C of RFC 4181 for suggested naming conventions

         A list of tools that can help automate the process of 
         checking mib definitions can be found at 
         http://www.ops.ietf.org/mib-review-tools.html
    -->

    <section title="Definitions">
      <t></t>

      <figure>
        <artwork><![CDATA[

REPORT-SAMPLED-MIB DEFINITIONS ::= BEGIN

IMPORTS

   MODULE-IDENTITY, OBJECT-TYPE, NOTIFICATION-TYPE,
   Gauge32, Integer32, experimental
      FROM SNMPv2-SMI                          -- [RFC2578]

   TimeStamp
      FROM SNMPv2-TC                           -- [RFC2579]

   MODULE-COMPLIANCE, OBJECT-GROUP, 
   NOTIFICATION-GROUP
      FROM SNMPv2-CONF                         -- [RFC2580]

   usrHistoryControlEntry, usrHistoryObjectEntry,
   usrHistoryControlIndex, usrHistoryControlOwner, 
   usrHistoryObjectIndex
--   usrHistoryControlObjects, usrHistoryControlBucketsRequested,
--   usrHistoryControlBucketsGranted, usrHistoryControlInterval,
--   usrHistoryControlStatus, 
--   usrHistoryObjectVariable, usrHistoryObjectSampleType
      FROM RMON2-MIB                           -- [RFC2021]

   InetAddress, InetAddressType
      FROM INET-ADDRESS-MIB                    -- [RFC4001]
   ;

reportSampledMIB MODULE-IDENTITY
   LAST-UPDATED "201211051300Z"  -- November 05, 2012
   ORGANIZATION "IETF MANET Working Group"
   CONTACT-INFO
      "WG E-Mail: manet@ietf.org

       WG Chairs: sratliff@cisco.com
                  jmacker@nrl.navy.mil


       Editors:   Robert G. Cole
                  US Army CERDEC
                  6010 Frankford Road
                  Aberdeen Proving Ground, MD 21005
                  USA
                  +1 443 395-8744
                  robert.g.cole@us.army.mil

                  Joseph Macker
                  Naval Research Laboratory
                  Washington, D.C. 20375
                  USA
                  macker@itd.nrl.navy.mil

                  Andy Bierman
                  YumaWorks, Inc.
                  andy@yumaworks.com"
   DESCRIPTION
      "This MIB module contains managed object definitions for
       the autonmous reporting of performance object counters.  
       Copyright (C) The IETF Trust (2009). This version
       of this MIB module is part of RFC xxxx; see the RFC
       itself for full legal notices."

     -- Revision History
     REVISION    "201211051300Z"   -- November 05, 2012
     DESCRIPTION
        "The seventh draft of this MIB module published as
         draft-ietf-manet-report-mib-03.txt.

         Revisions to this draft include 
         a) Added a 'Tables and Indexing' section to the
            body of this document.
         b) Added an 'Applicability Statement' section
            to the body of this document."
     REVISION    "201201311300Z"   -- January 31, 2012
     DESCRIPTION
        "The sixth draft of this MIB module published as
         draft-ietf-manet-report-mib-02.txt.

         Revisions to this draft include 
         a) Pulled the statistical and historical reporting
            from the MIB module and left only the sampled
            reporting, in order to greatly simplify the
            first instance of this reporting MIB module.
         b) Renamed the module, the REPORT-SAMPLED-MIB 
            module.
         c) Leveraged the RMON2-MIB module more effectively
            through the use of the AUGMENTS clause.
         d) Changed the module to 'experimental'."
     REVISION    "201102171300Z"   -- February 17, 2011
     DESCRIPTION
        "The fifth draft of this MIB module published as
         draft-ietf-manet-report-mib-01.txt.  This document
         has been promoted to a MANET Working Group
         draft.  

         Revisions to this draft include 
         a) Proposed changes to the statsReport table to
            simplify communications between device and
            mgmt application,
         b) Added Notifications,
         c) Changed the reporting structure of the 
            Sampled and the History reporting
            to align with the structure of the
            Statistics reports for the purpose of
            allowing for efficient notification and 
            collection of data reports.
         d) Ran through smilint to clean up all errors
            and most warning.  A few still remain."
     REVISION    "201007051300Z"   -- July 05, 2010
     DESCRIPTION
        "The fourth draft of this MIB module published as
         draft-ietf-manet-report-mib-00.txt.  This document
         has been promoted to a MANET Working Group
         draft.  

         Significant revisions to this draft include 
         a) added support for proxy configurations through
         the addition of address objects associated with
         the referenced counter objects associated with the
         performance reports."
     REVISION    "201003021300Z"   -- March 02, 2010
     DESCRIPTION
        "The third draft of this MIB module published as
         draft-cole-manet-report-mib-02.txt.  Significant
         revisions to this draft include a) changed naming
         of usrHistoryGroup to sampledGroup and  b) added
         a historyGroup."
     REVISION    "200910251300Z"   -- October 25, 2009
     DESCRIPTION
        "The second draft of this MIB module published as
         draft-cole-manet-report-mib-01.txt.  Significant
         revisions to this draft include a) the inclusion of
         raw data collection borrow blatently from the
         usrHistory Group within RMON2, b) the deletion of
         the CurrentHistoryTable from version -00, 
         c) modifications to the overall structure of the
         MIB, and d) the definition of various Compliance
         options for implementations related to this MIB."
     REVISION    "200904281300Z"   -- April 28, 2009
     DESCRIPTION
        "Initial draft of this MIB module published as
         draft-cole-manet-report-mib-00.txt."
     -- RFC-Editor assigns XXXX
     ::= { experimental 998 }   -- to be assigned by IANA



-- TEXTUAL CONVENTIONs
-- None


--
-- Top-Level Object Identifier Assignments
--

reportSampledMIBNotifications OBJECT IDENTIFIER 
                              ::= { reportSampledMIB 0 }
reportSampledMIBObjects       OBJECT IDENTIFIER 
                              ::= { reportSampledMIB 1 }
reportSampledMIBConformance   OBJECT IDENTIFIER 
                              ::= { reportSampledMIB 2 }


reportSampledGroup            OBJECT IDENTIFIER 
                              ::= { reportSampledMIBObjects 1 }

--      Then, the reportSampledGroup assignments are :
--             reportSampledControlTable    - 1
--             reportSampledObjectTable     - 2   
--             reportSampledDataTable       - 3



reportSampledControlTable OBJECT-TYPE
    SYNTAX SEQUENCE OF SampledControlEntry
    MAX-ACCESS not-accessible
    STATUS current
    DESCRIPTION
        "A list of data-collection configuration entries.
         This table augments the 'usrHistoryControlTable'
         from RMON2-MIB (RFC 2021)."
    REFERENCE
        "RFC 2021 - Remote Network Monitoring Management
         Information Base Version 2 (RMON2-MIB),
         Waldbusser, S., January 1997."
    ::= { reportSampledGroup 1 }


reportSampledControlEntry OBJECT-TYPE
    SYNTAX SampledControlEntry
    MAX-ACCESS not-accessible
    STATUS current
    DESCRIPTION
        "A list of parameters that set up a group of user-defined
        MIB objects to be sampled periodically (called a
        bucket-group).

        For example, an instance of reportSampledControlInterval
        might be named reportSampledControlInterval.1"
    AUGMENTS { usrHistoryControlEntry }
    ::= { reportSampledControlTable 1 }

SampledControlEntry ::= SEQUENCE {
    reportSampledControlRequestedNumber   Integer32,
    reportSampledControlReportNumber      Integer32
}

reportSampledControlRequestedNumber OBJECT-TYPE
    SYNTAX Integer32 (1..127)
    MAX-ACCESS read-create
    STATUS current
    DESCRIPTION
        "The number of reports to be generated and stored by this
         agent for this report request.  

        This object may not be modified if the associated
        reportSampledControlStatus object is equal to active(1)."
    DEFVAL { 1 }
    ::= { reportSampledControlEntry 1 }

reportSampledControlReportNumber OBJECT-TYPE
    SYNTAX Integer32 (1..127)
    MAX-ACCESS read-only
    STATUS current
    DESCRIPTION
        "The number of the current report in progress.  The first
         report is assigned a number equal to '1'.  Each successive
         report number is incremented by unity.  When the last report
         is completed, this value is set to
         reportSampledControlRequestedNumber + 1."
    ::= { reportSampledControlEntry 2 }


-- Object table

reportSampledObjectTable OBJECT-TYPE
    SYNTAX SEQUENCE OF SampledObjectEntry
    MAX-ACCESS not-accessible
    STATUS current
    DESCRIPTION
        "A list of data-collection configuration entries.
         This table augments the 'usrHistoryObjectTable'
         from the RMON2-MIB (RFC 2021)."
    REFERENCE
        "RFC 2021 - Remote Network Monitoring Management
         Information Base Version 2 (RMON2-MIB),
         Waldbusser, S., January 1997."
    ::= { reportSampledGroup 2 }

reportSampledObjectEntry OBJECT-TYPE
    SYNTAX SampledObjectEntry
    MAX-ACCESS not-accessible
    STATUS current
    DESCRIPTION
        "A list of MIB instances to be sampled periodically.

        Entries in this table are created when an associated
        reportSampledControlObjects object is created.

        The usrHistoryControlIndex value in the index is
        that of the associated reportSampledControlEntry.

        For example, an instance of reportSampledObjectVariable 
        might be reportSampledObjectVariable.1.3"
    AUGMENTS { usrHistoryObjectEntry }
    ::= { reportSampledObjectTable 1 }

SampledObjectEntry ::= SEQUENCE {
    reportSampledObjectIpAddrType        InetAddressType,
    reportSampledObjectIPAddress         InetAddress
}

reportSampledObjectIpAddrType  OBJECT-TYPE
    SYNTAX      InetAddressType
    MAX-ACCESS  read-create
    STATUS      current
    DESCRIPTION
        "This identifies the IP address type
        of the IP address associated with the
        secondary counter object to be
        monitored within this report.

        Only the values ipv4(1) and
        ipv6(2) are supported.

        This object may not be modified if the associated
        reportStatsControlStatus object is equal to active(1)."
    ::= { reportSampledObjectEntry 1 }   

reportSampledObjectIPAddress  OBJECT-TYPE
    SYNTAX      InetAddress (SIZE(4|16))
    MAX-ACCESS  read-create
    STATUS      current
    DESCRIPTION
        "This identifies the IP addree of the
        secondary counter object to be
        monitored within this report.

        This object may not be modified if the associated
        reportStatsControlStatus object is equal to active(1)."
    ::= { reportSampledObjectEntry 2 }   


-- data table
reportSampledTable OBJECT-TYPE
    SYNTAX SEQUENCE OF SampledEntry
    MAX-ACCESS not-accessible
    STATUS current
    DESCRIPTION
        "A list of user defined history entries."
    ::= { reportSampledGroup 3 }

reportSampledEntry OBJECT-TYPE
    SYNTAX SampledEntry
    MAX-ACCESS not-accessible
    STATUS current
    DESCRIPTION
        "A historical sample of user-defined variables.  This sample
        is associated with the reportSampledControlEntry which set 
        up the parameters for a regular collection of these samples.

        The usrHistoryControlIndex value, from the RMON2-MIB
        (RFC 2021), in the index identifies the 
        reportSampledControlEntry on whose behalf this entry 
        was created.

        The usrHistoryObjectIndex value in the index identifies
        the reportSampledObjectEntry on whose behalf this entry 
        was created.

        For example, an instance of reportSampledAbsValue, which 
        represents the 14th sample of a variable collected as 
        specified by reportSampledControlEntry.1 and 
        reportSampledObjectEntry.1.5, would be named 
        reportSampledAbsValue.1.14.5"
    REFERENCE
        "RFC 2021 - Remote Network Monitoring Management
         Information Base Version 2 (RMON2-MIB),
         Waldbusser, S., January 1997."
    INDEX { usrHistoryControlIndex, reportSampledReportIndex,
            reportSampledSampleIndex, usrHistoryObjectIndex }
    ::= { reportSampledTable 1 }

SampledEntry ::= SEQUENCE {
    reportSampledReportIndex   Integer32,
    reportSampledReportID      Integer32,
    reportSampledSampleIndex   Integer32,
    reportSampledIntervalStart TimeStamp,
    reportSampledIntervalEnd   TimeStamp,
    reportSampledAbsValue      Gauge32,
    reportSampledValStatus     INTEGER
}

reportSampledReportIndex OBJECT-TYPE
    SYNTAX     Integer32 (1..127)
    MAX-ACCESS not-accessible
    STATUS     current
    DESCRIPTION
        "An index that uniquely identifies the particular report
        this entry is associated with among the set of reports
        requested through the reportSampledControlNumber in the
        reportSampledControlEntry. This index starts at 1 and
        increases by one as each new report is generated."
    ::= { reportSampledEntry 1 }

reportSampledReportID OBJECT-TYPE
    SYNTAX     Integer32 (1..127)
    MAX-ACCESS read-only
    STATUS     current
    DESCRIPTION
        "An ID that uniquely identifies the particular report
        this entry is associated with among the set of reports
        requested through the reportSampledControlNumber in the
        reportSampledControlEntry. This ID is set to equal the
        value of the reportSampledReportIndex."
    ::= { reportSampledEntry 2 }

reportSampledSampleIndex OBJECT-TYPE
    SYNTAX     Integer32 (1..2147483647)
    MAX-ACCESS not-accessible
    STATUS     current
    DESCRIPTION
        "An index that uniquely identifies the particular sample this
        entry represents among all samples associated with the same
        reportSampledControlEntry. This index starts at 1 and
        increases by one as each new sample is taken."
    ::= { reportSampledEntry 3 }

reportSampledIntervalStart OBJECT-TYPE
    SYNTAX TimeStamp
    MAX-ACCESS read-only
    STATUS current
    DESCRIPTION
        "The value of sysUpTime at the start of the interval over
        which this sample was measured.  If the probe keeps track of
        the time of day, it should start the first sample of the
        history at a time such that when the next hour of the day
        begins, a sample is started at that instant.

        Note that following this rule may require the probe to delay
        collecting the first sample of the history, as each sample
        must be of the same interval. Also note that the sample which
        is currently being collected is not accessible in this table
        until the end of its interval."
    ::= { reportSampledEntry 4 }

reportSampledIntervalEnd OBJECT-TYPE
    SYNTAX TimeStamp
    MAX-ACCESS read-only
    STATUS current
    DESCRIPTION
        "The value of sysUpTime at the end of the interval over which
        this sample was measured."
    ::= { reportSampledEntry 5 }

reportSampledAbsValue OBJECT-TYPE
    SYNTAX Gauge32
    MAX-ACCESS read-only
    STATUS current
    DESCRIPTION
        "The absolute value (i.e. unsigned value) of the
        user-specified statistic during the last sampling period. The
        value during the current sampling period is not made available
        until the period is completed.

        To obtain the true value for this sampling interval, the
        associated instance of reportSampledValStatus must 
        be checked, and reportSampledAbsValue adjusted as necessary.

        If the MIB instance could not be accessed during the sampling
        interval, then this object will have a value of zero and the
        associated instance of reportSampledValStatus will be set to
        'valueNotAvailable(1)'."
    ::= { reportSampledEntry 6 }


reportSampledValStatus OBJECT-TYPE
    SYNTAX INTEGER {
        valueNotAvailable(1),
        valuePositive(2),
        valueNegative(3)
    }
    MAX-ACCESS read-only
    STATUS current
    DESCRIPTION
        "This object indicates the validity and sign of the data in
        the associated instance of reportSampledAbsValue.

        If the MIB instance could not be accessed during the sampling
        interval, then 'valueNotAvailable(1)' will be returned.

        If the sample is valid and actual value of the sample is
        greater than or equal to zero then 'valuePositive(2)' is
        returned.

        If the sample is valid and the actual value of the sample is
        less than zero, 'valueNegative(3)' will be returned. The
        associated instance of reportSampledAbsValue should be
        multiplied by -1 to obtain the true sample value."
    ::= { reportSampledEntry 7 }



--
-- Notifications
--

reportSampledNotificationObjects OBJECT IDENTIFIER 
                                 ::= {reportSampledMIBNotifications 0}


   -- reportSampledNotificationObjects

   reportSampledNewDataReport NOTIFICATION-TYPE
          OBJECTS { usrHistoryControlOwner, -- The entity that
                             --   configured this entry
                    reportSampledReportID   -- The ID of the
                             --   data table for this report
                  }
          STATUS       current
          DESCRIPTION
             "reportSampledNewDataReport is a notification sent  
              when a new report is completed from the
              reportSampledControlTable.  The notification carries
              the index from the control table that established
              this report and the index from the data table that
              holds this report.  Indication of the new report
              is when the reportSampledControlReportNumber
              is incremented."
          ::= { reportSampledNotificationObjects 1 }



--
-- Compliance Statements
--

-- Mandatory for Sampled will include all.

reportSampledCompliances  OBJECT IDENTIFIER 
                          ::= { reportSampledMIBConformance 1 }
reportSampledMIBGroups    OBJECT IDENTIFIER 
                          ::= { reportSampledMIBConformance 2 }


reportSampledCompliance  MODULE-COMPLIANCE
   STATUS current
   DESCRIPTION "The Sampled basic implementation requirements for 
                managed network entities that implement
                the REPORT Sampled process." 
   MODULE  -- this module
   MANDATORY-GROUPS { reportSampledLocalGroup }
::= { reportSampledCompliances 1 }

reportSampledNotificationCompliance  MODULE-COMPLIANCE
   STATUS current
   DESCRIPTION "The Sampled Notification implementation 
                requirements for managed network entities 
                that implement the REPORT process." 
   MODULE  -- this module
   MANDATORY-GROUPS { reportSampledNotificationObjectGroup }
::= { reportSampledCompliances 2 }



-- Units of Conformance

reportSampledLocalGroup  OBJECT-GROUP
   OBJECTS {
            reportSampledControlRequestedNumber,
            reportSampledControlReportNumber,
            reportSampledObjectIpAddrType,
            reportSampledObjectIPAddress,
            reportSampledReportID,
            reportSampledIntervalStart,
            reportSampledIntervalEnd,
            reportSampledAbsValue,
            reportSampledValStatus
   }
   STATUS  current
   DESCRIPTION
      "Set of REPORT state objects implemented
       in this module."
::= { reportSampledMIBGroups 1 }

--reportSampledImportedGroup  OBJECT-GROUP
--   OBJECTS {
--            usrHistoryControlObjects,
--            usrHistoryControlBucketsRequested,
--            usrHistoryControlBucketsGranted,
--            usrHistoryControlInterval,
--            usrHistoryControlOwner,
--            usrHistoryControlStatus,
--            usrHistoryObjectVariable,
--            usrHistoryObjectSampleType
--   }
--   STATUS  current
--   DESCRIPTION
--      "Set of REPORT state objects implemented
--       in this module."
--::= { reportSampledMIBGroups 2 }

reportSampledNotificationObjectGroup  NOTIFICATION-GROUP
   NOTIFICATIONS {
            reportSampledNewDataReport
   }
   STATUS  current
   DESCRIPTION
      "Set of REPORT notifications implemented
       in this module for the Sampled reports."
::= { reportSampledMIBGroups 3 }

END

	]]></artwork>
      </figure>
    </section>

    <section title="Security Considerations">
      <t>This REPORT-SAMPLED-MIB defines a capability where the local device
         may poll other remote devices to collect performance data
         accessible through other MIB modules on the remote devices.
         These capabilities defined within the REPORT-SAMPLED-MIB are control-able
         by a network management application through SNMP.  As such,
         a network management application could potentially use the REPORT-SAMPLED-MIB
         as a mechanism to implement a Distributed Denial-of-Service (DDoS)
         attack against remote devices. Care should be taken to secure access
         to the REPORT-SAMPLED-MIB agent.  Specifically, access control mechanisms
         and authentication mechanisms (via SNMPv3) should always be used
         for SNMP SET operations.  Further, some objects may contain data
         deemed sensitive and authentication and encryption mechanisms
         (via SNMPv3) should be used for SNMP GET operations.
        </t>

      <t>There are a number of management objects defined in this MIB module
      with a MAX-ACCESS clause of read-write and/or read-create. Such objects
      may be considered sensitive or vulnerable in some network environments.
      The support for SET operations in a non-secure environment without
      proper protection can have a negative effect on network operations.</t>

      <t>These are the tables and objects and their
      sensitivity/vulnerability:</t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>The reportSampledControlTable is a writable table
             whose columnar objects are read-create.  The following
             objects with MAX ACCESS of read-create and their security
             sensitivities are:</t>
                 <t><list style="symbols">
                     <t>usrHistoryControlBucketRequested - this object identifies the
                        requested number of buckets (or intervals) requested for each
                        identified object for each report instance.  As such, this related
                        to the total device memory necessary to hold the collected
                        data for the identified reports.  The device must determine
                        whether it has the necessary storage.  If not, the device can
                        indicate the available storage through the 
                        usrHistoryControlBucketGranted object within this table.
                        The device to protect itself against memory overruns.</t>
                     <t>usrHistoryControlInterval - this object identifies the
                        time interval being sampling events.  If set too low, the
                        device may not be able to sample the object on remote
                        devices fast enough to satisfy the requested interval.  Further,
                        setting this value too low could be used to overwhelm
                        the processing capabilities of the remote agent, resulting
                        in a Denial-of-Service (DoS) attack.</t>
                     <t>reportSampledControlRequestedNumber - this object identifies
                        the requested number of consecutive reports of this type to
                        be generated and stored in this device.  When, the value of this
                        object should be considered in the local device's estimates of
                        memory consumption related to this control table row.</t>
                     <t>usrHistoryControlOwner - this objects provides a name
                        associated with the presumed identity of the application
                        configuring this report.  If the local device or management applications
                        attribute any authority to the values contained in this object, then
                        it is critical to secure access to setting or modifying the
                        value of this object.</t>
                     <t>usrHistoryControlStatus - this is the RowStatus object controlling
                        the configuration of this table row.</t>
                 </list></t>
             
          <t>The reportSampledObjectTable is a writable table
             whose columnar objects are read-create.  The following
             objects with MAX ACCESS of read-create and their security
             sensitivities are:</t>
                 <t><list style="symbols">
                     <t>usrHistoryObjectVariable - this object identifies the specific
                        OID on a (potentially) remote agent whose counter or gauge
                        values are to be collected for the reports.  If, for whatever
                        reason, the values of this OID collected within the report
                        is deemed sensitive, then the SNMP GET operations issued
                        to collect these values should use SNMPv3 authentication and
                        encryption mechanisms to protect.</t>
                     <t>reportSampledObjectIpAddrType - this object identifies the
                        address type associated with the address of the agent whose
                        OID data is being collected for the report.</t>
                     <t>reportSampledObjectIpAddress - this object identifies the
                        address associated with the address of the agent whose
                        OID data is being collected for the report.  If the address
                        of the remote devices is deemed sensitive, then the SNMP SETs
                        which write or the SNMP GET which collect this information
                        should be protected using SNMPv3 authentication and encryption
                        mechanisms.</t>
                     <t>usrHistoryObjectSampleType - this object identifies the
                        the way in which data values are to be stored within the 
                        reports.</t>
                 </list></t>
             
        </list></t>


      <t>SNMP versions prior to SNMPv3 did not include adequate security. Even
      if the network itself is secure (for example by using IPSec), even then,
      there is no control as to who on the secure network is allowed to access
      and GET/SET (read/change/create/delete) the objects in this MIB
      module.</t>

      <t>It is RECOMMENDED that implementers consider the security features as
      provided by the SNMPv3 framework (see <xref target="RFC3410"></xref>,
      section 8), including full support for the SNMPv3 cryptographic
      mechanisms (for authentication and privacy).</t>

      <t>Further, deployment of SNMP versions prior to SNMPv3 is NOT
      RECOMMENDED. Instead, it is RECOMMENDED to deploy SNMPv3 and to enable
      cryptographic security. It is then a customer/operator responsibility to
      ensure that the SNMP entity giving access to an instance of this MIB
      module is properly configured to give access to the objects only to
      those principals (users) that have legitimate rights to indeed GET or
      SET (change/create/delete) them.</t>
    </section>


    <section title="Applicability Statement">
      <t>This document describes objects for configuring parameters of the
         remote report generation process on a router or close device.  
         This MIB module, denoted REPORT-SAMPLED-MIB, 
         also reports performance information and notifications.
         The REPORT-SAMPLED-MIB provides for the remote control, collection and notification
         of performance reports on devices.
         As such, it eliminates the need for periodic polling for counters from
         remote management stations as a means for generating performance reports.
         This is hoped to greatly reduce management overhead on the MANET.
         This sections provides some examples of how this MIB module can be used in
         MANET network deployments.
         A fuller discussion of MANET network management use cases and
         challenges will be provided elsewhere.
      </t>

      <t>In the following, two scenarios are listed where this MIB module is useful, i.e.,
      </t>
      <t><list style='symbols'>
            <t>For Mobile vehicles with Low Bandwidth Satellite Link to a Fixed NOC - Here
               the vehicles carrying the MANET routers carry multiple wireless interfaces, 
               one of which is a relatively low-bandwidth on-the-move satellite connection 
               which interconnects a fix NOC to the nodes of the MANET.
               Standards-based methods for monitoring and fault management from the fixed NOC
               are necessary for this deployment option. 
               However, to reduce polling overhead over the low bandwidth communications
               links, the REPORT-SAMPLED-MIB can be deployed the remote MANET
               nodes for the remote generation of performance reports.</t>
            <t>For Fixed NOC and Mobile Local Manager in Larger Vehicles - for larger
               vehicles, a hierarchical network management arrangement is useful.  
               Centralized network management is performed from a fixed NOC 
               while local management is performed locally from within the vehicles.
               Standards-based
               methods for configuration, monitoring, fault and performance management
               are necessary for this deployment option. </t>
         </list>
      </t>
    </section>


    <section title="IANA Considerations">
      <figure>
        <preamble></preamble>

        <artwork><![CDATA[
     The MIB module in this document uses the following IANA-assigned
     OBJECT IDENTIFIER values recorded in the SMI Numbers registry: 
      
     Descriptor        OBJECT IDENTIFIER value
     ----------        -----------------------

     reportSampledMIB  { experimental XXX }
      	]]></artwork>

        <postamble></postamble>
      </figure>

      <t></t>
    </section>


    <!-- The Author's Addresses section will be generated 
         automatically by XML2RFC from the front information -->

    <section title="Contributors">
      <t>This MIB document uses the template authored by D. Harrington which
      is based on contributions from the MIB Doctors, especially Juergen
      Schoenwaelder, Dave Perkins, C.M.Heard and Randy Presuhn.</t>

      <t><!--[TODO] Change this section to mention contributors to your 
             MIB module document.--></t>
    </section>

    <section title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>We would like to thank Bert Wijnen for
         pointing out the existence of the usrHistory group within
         RMON2 and in answering our numerous
         questions on the usrHistory group.  Further, we wish to
         thank U. Herberg for promoting additions to this MIB through
         his thoughtful consideration of performance monitoring
         requirements for other MIBs within the MANET WG, e.g., 
         NHDP and OLSR MIBs.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <!-- References Section -->

    <!-- Section 4.7f of [RFC2223bis] specifies the requirements for the
   references sections.  In particular, there MUST be separate lists of
   normative and informative references, each in a separate section.
   The style SHOULD follow that of recently published RFCs.

   The standard MIB boilerplate available at
   http://www.ops.ietf.org/mib-boilerplate.html includes lists of
   normative and informative references that MUST appear in all IETF
   specifications that contain MIB modules.  If items from other MIB
   modules appear in an IMPORTS statement in the Definitions section,
   then the specifications containing those MIB modules MUST be included
   in the list of normative references.  When items are imported from an
   IANA-maintained MIB module the corresponding normative reference
   SHALL point to the on-line version of that MIB module.  It is the
   policy of the RFC Editor that all references must be cited in the
   text;  such citations MUST appear in the overview section where
   documents containing imported definitions (other those already
   mentioned in the MIB boilerplate) are required to be mentioned (cf.
   Section 3.2).

In general, each normative reference SHOULD point to the most recent
version of the specification in question.
-->

    <references title="Normative References">

      &rfc2021;

      &rfc2863;

      &rfc3418;

      &rfc2119;

      &rfc2578;

      &rfc2579;

      &rfc2580;

      &rfc4001;

    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <!-- <t>[TODO] RFC3410 is required to support the boilerplate text.</t>-->

      &rfc3410;



    </references>

    <!--
<section anchor="appendix" title="Appendix A">
	<t>You can add appendices just as regular sections, the only
difference is that they go under "back" element, and get letters 
instead of numbers</t>
</section>
-->

    <section title="Change Log ">
      <t>Changes from draft-ietf-manet-report-mib-01 to 
         draft-ietf-manet-report-mib-02 draft.</t>
      <t><list style="numbers">
          <t>Stripped the Statistical and the Historical 
             Reports from this draft in order to greatly
             simplify the initial development and experiments
             of this MIB module.</t>
          <t>Changed the RFC category to Experimental.</t>
          <t>Completed the Security section. </t>
          <t>Relied upon the AUGMENTS statement to simplify 
             further this MIB definition.</t>
      </list></t>

      <t>Changes from draft-ietf-manet-report-mib-00 to 
         draft-ietf-manet-report-mib-01 draft.</t>
      <t><list style="numbers">
          <t>Proposed additions to the statsReports in order
             to potentially simplify data transmission to
             management applications.</t>
          <t>Added some Notification definitions
             and their relationship to the three reports'
             structure, i.e., statsReports, sampledReports,
             and historyReports.</t>
          <t>In the process of adding notifications for the
             Sampled and the History reports, decided to restructure
             the reports from their previously rolling storage
             model to the fixed interval reporting used all along
             in the Statistics reporting.  This allows the agent to
             notify the management application that a report has
             completed and that it is ready to be pulled from the
             agent storage.</t>
          <t>Ran MIB through smilint checker and cleaned up
             all errors and most warnings.  A few warnings remain
             to be addressed.</t>
          <t>Cleaned up textual material.</t>
      </list></t>

      <t>Changes from draft-cole-manet-report-mib-02 to 
         draft-ietf-manet-report-mib-00 draft.</t>
      <t><list style="numbers">
          <t>Major change was the incorporation of the
             IP address objects associated with all objects
             of type 'OBJECT IDENTIFIER'.  This allows the 
             REPORT-SAMPLED-MIB to exist as a proxy report generation
             capability on a device separate but in close
             proximity to the device monitoring the
             referenced object.</t>
          <t>Cleaned up the up front text, reducing the 
             repetition with the object descriptions in the
             MIB.</t>
          <t>Worked on and added sections discussing the
             relationship to other MIBs.</t>
      </list></t>

      <t>Changes from draft-cole-manet-report-mib-01 to 
         draft-cole-manet-report-mib-02 draft.</t>
      <t><list style="numbers">
          <t>Restructured the MIB somewhat to now offer the three
             reporting capabilities in increasing order of detail:
             a) statistical reports, b) sampled reports, and
             c) historical reports.</t>
          <t>Renamed the usrHistoryGroup and elements to
             samplingGroup.  This is in line with its actual capabilities.</t>
          <t>Added a new historyGroup which provides a history of change events.</t>
          <t>Updated the4 Conformance section to reflect the above changes and
             additions.  But did not yet run smilint to check MIB syntax.</t>
      </list></t>

      <t>Changes from draft-cole-manet-report-mib-00 to 
         draft-cole-manet-report-mib-01 draft.</t>
      <t><list style="numbers">
          <t>Added (copied) the usrHistory group from RMON2 into the REPORT-SAMPLED-MIB.</t>
          <t>Restructured the MIB to account for the inclusion of the
             reportSampledGroup.</t>
          <t>Dropped the reportCurReportsTable as this did not make sense within the
             context of the REPORT-SAMPLED-MIB.</t>
          <t>Added the Compliance and Conformance material.  Defined several Compliance
             Groups to all for base implementations of the REPORT-SAMPLED-MIB for only statistical
             reports, for only historical reports or for both.  Allow for enhanced
             implementations to address higher capacity issues and 
             extension to metric reporting for statistical reporting.</t>
          <t>Ran the MIB through the smilint checker and in the process corrected numerous
             typos, omissions, TEXTUAL CONVENTIONS, IMPORTS, etc.</t>
          <t>Updated main text to reflect changes.</t>
      </list></t>
    </section>

    <section title="Open Issues">
      <t>This section contains the set of open issues related to the
      development and design of the REPORT-SAMPLED-MIB. This section will not be present
      in the final version of the MIB and will be removed once all the open
      issues have been resolved.</t>

      <t><list style="numbers">
          <t>Identify all objects requiring non-volatile storage in their
          DESCRIPTION clauses.</t>
        </list></t>
    </section>

    <section title="">
       <figure>
          <preamble />

             <artwork><![CDATA[
***************************************************************
* Note to the RFC Editor (to be removed prior to publication) *
*                                                             *
* 1) The reference to RFCXXXX within the DESCRIPTION clauses  *
* of the MIB module point to this draft and are to be         *
* assigned by the RFC Editor.                                 *
*                                                             *
* 2) The reference to RFCXXX2 throughout this document point  *
* to the current draft-ietf-manet-report-xx.txt.  This        *
* need to be replaced with the XXX RFC number.                *
*                                                             *
***************************************************************
              ]]></artwork>
           <postamble></postamble>
        </figure>
     </section>

  </back>
</rfc>
