<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY RFC2119 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3552 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3552.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC2818 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2818.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3261 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3261.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5479 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5479.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4347 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4347.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4568 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4568.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5763 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5763.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4251 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4251.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3760 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3760.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6189 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6189.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5245 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5245.xml">


<!ENTITY I-D.abarth-origin SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.abarth-origin">
<!ENTITY I-D.ietf-hybi-thewebsocketprotocol SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-hybi-thewebsocketprotocol">
]>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="rfc2629.xslt" ?>
<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc colonspace="yes" ?>
<?rfc rfcedstyle="no" ?>
<!-- Don't change this. It breaks stuff -->
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<rfc category="std" docName="draft-rescorla-rtcweb-security-00"
     ipr="pre5378Trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="RTC-Web Security">Security Considerations for RTC-Web</title>

    <author fullname="Eric Rescorla" initials="E.K." surname="Rescorla">
      <organization>RTFM, Inc.</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>2064 Edgewood Drive</street>

          <city>Palo Alto</city>

          <region>CA</region>

          <code>94303</code>

          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>

        <phone>+1 650 678 2350</phone>

        <email>ekr@rtfm.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date day="5" month="June" year="2011" />

    <area>RAI</area>

    <workgroup>RTC-Web</workgroup>

    <abstract>
      <t>
	The Real-Time Communications on the Web (RTC-Web) working group is tasked with
	standardizing protocols for real-time communications between Web browsers. The
	two major use cases for RTC-Web technology are real-time audio and/or video calls
	and direct data transfer. Unlike most conventional real-time systems
	(e.g., SIP-based soft phones) RTC-Web communications are directly controlled
	by some Web server, which poses new security challenges.
	For instance, a Web browser might expose a JavaScript
	API which allows a server to place a video call. Unrestricted access to such
	an API would allow any site which a user visited to "bug" a user's computer,
	capturing any activity which passed in front of their camera. This document
	defines the RTC-Web threat model and defines an architecture which provides
	security within that threat model.
      </t>
    </abstract>

    <note title="Legal">
      <t>THIS DOCUMENT AND THE INFORMATION CONTAINED THEREIN ARE PROVIDED ON
      AN &ldquo;AS IS&rdquo; BASIS AND THE CONTRIBUTOR, THE ORGANIZATION
      HE/SHE REPRESENTS OR IS SPONSORED BY (IF ANY), THE INTERNET SOCIETY, THE
      IETF TRUST, AND THE INTERNET ENGINEERING TASK FORCE, DISCLAIM ALL
      WARRANTIES, EXPRESS OR IMPLIED, INCLUDING BUT NOT LIMITED TO ANY
      WARRANTY THAT THE USE OF THE INFORMATION THEREIN WILL NOT INFRINGE ANY
      RIGHTS OR ANY IMPLIED WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY OR FITNESS FOR A
      PARTICULAR PURPOSE.</t>
    </note>
  </front>


  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction" anchor="sec.introduction">
      <t>
	The Real-Time Communications on the Web (RTC-Web) working group is tasked with
	standardizing protocols for real-time communications between Web browsers. The
	two major use cases for RTC-Web technology are real-time audio and/or video calls
	and direct data transfer. Unlike most conventional real-time systems, 
	(e.g., SIP-based<xref target="RFC3261"></xref> soft phones) RTC-Web communications are directly controlled
	by some Web server. A simple case is shown below.
      </t>

      <figure title="A simple RTC-Web system" anchor="fig.simple">
	<artwork><![CDATA[
                            +----------------+
                            |                |
                            |   Web Server   |
                            |                |
                            +----------------+
                                ^        ^
                               /          \
                       HTTP   /            \   HTTP
                             /              \                               
                            /                \                               
                           v                  v
                        JS API              JS API
                  +-----------+            +-----------+
                  |           |    Media   |           |
                  |  Browser  |<---------->|  Browser  |
                  |           |            |           |                  
                  +-----------+            +-----------+
 	]]></artwork>
      </figure>
      <t>
	In the system shown in <xref target="fig.simple"/>, Alice and Bob both have
	RTC-Web enabled browsers and they visit some Web server which operates a
	calling service. Each of their browsers exposes standardized JavaScript calling APIs
	which are used by the Web server to set up a call between Alice and Bob.
	While this system is topologically similar to a conventional SIP-based
	system (with the Web server acting as the signaling service and browsers
	acting as softphones), control has moved to the central Web server;
	the browser simply provides API points that are used by the calling service.
	As with any Web application, the Web server can move logic between 
	the server and JavaScript in the browser, but regardless of where the 
	code is executing, it is ultimately under control of the server.
      </t>
      <t>
	It should be immediately apparent that this type of system poses new
	security challenges beyond those of a conventional VoIP system. In particular,
	it needs to contend with malicious calling services.
	For example, if the calling service
	can cause the browser to make a call at any time to any callee of its
	choice, then this facility can be used to bug a user's computer without
	their knowledge, simply by placing a call to some recording service.
	More subtly, if the exposed APIs allow the server to instruct the
	browser to send arbitrary content, then they can be used to bypass
	firewalls or mount denial of service attacks. Any successful system
	will need to be resistant to this and other attacks.
      </t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="sec-term" title="Terminology">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
      document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
      target="RFC2119">RFC 2119</xref>.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="The Browser Threat Model" anchor="sec.web-security">
      <t>
	The security requirements for RTC-Web follow directly from the 
	requirement that the browser's job is to protect the user. 
	Huang et al. <xref target="huang-w2sp"/> summarize the core browser security guarantee as:
      </t>
      <t>
	<list style="hanging">
	  <t>
	    Users can safely visit arbitrary web sites and execute scripts provided by those sites.
	  </t>
	</list>
      </t>
      <t></t>
      <t>
	It is important to realize that this includes sites hosting arbitrary malicious
	scripts. The motivation for this requirement is simple: it is trivial for attackers
	to divert users to sites of their choice. For instance, an attacker can purchase
	display advertisements which direct the user (either automatically or via user
	clicking) to their site, at which point the browser will execute the attacker's
	scripts. Thus, it is important that it be safe to view arbitrarily malicious pages.
	Of course, browsers inevitably have bugs which cause them to fall short of this
	goal, but any new RTC-Web functionality must be designed with the intent to 
	meet this standard. The remainder of this section provides more background 
	on the existing Web security model.
      </t>
      <t>
	In this model, then, the browser acts as a TRUSTED COMPUTING BASE (TCB) both
	from the user's perspective and to some extent from the server's. While HTML
	and JS provided by the server can cause the browser to execute a variety of
	actions, those scripts operate in a sandbox that isolates them both from
	the user's computer and from each other, as detailed below.
      </t>
      <t>
	Conventionally, we refer to either WEB ATTACKERS, who are able to induce
	you to visit their sites but do not control the network, and NETWORK
	ATTACKERS, who are able to control your network. Network attackers correspond
	to the <xref target="RFC3552"/> "Internet Threat Model". In general, it
	is desirable to build a system which is secure against both kinds of
	attackers, but realistically many sites do not run HTTPS <xref target="RFC2818"/> and so
	our ability to defend against network attackers is necessarily somewhat
	limited. Most of the rest of this section is devoted to web attackers,
	with the assumption that protection against network attackers is 
	provided by running HTTPS.
      </t>
      <section title="Access to Local Resources" anchor="sec.resources">
	<t>
	  While the browser has access to local resources such as keying material,
	  files, the camera and the microphone, it strictly limits or forbids web
	  servers from accessing those same resources. For instance, while it is possible
	  to produce an HTML form which will allow file upload, a script cannot do
	  so without user consent and in fact cannot even suggest a specific file
	  (e.g., /etc/passwd); the user must explicitly select the file and consent
	  to its upload. [Note: in many cases browsers are explicitly designed to 
	  avoid dialogs with the semantics of "click here to screw yourself", as
	  extensive research shows that users are prone to consent under such
	  circumstances.]
	</t>
	<t>
	  Similarly, while Flash SWFs can access the camera and microphone, they
	  explicitly require that the user consent to that access. In addition,
	  some resources simply cannot be accessed from the browser at all. For
	  instance, there is no real way to run specific executables directly from a 
	  script (though the user can of course be induced to download executable
	  files and run them).
	</t>
      </section>
      <section title="Same Origin Policy" anchor="sec.same-origin">
	<t>
	  Many other resources are accessible but isolated. For instance, 
	  while scripts are allowed to make HTTP requests via the XMLHttpRequest() API
	  those requests are not allowed to be made to any server, but rather solely
	  to the same ORIGIN from whence the script came.<xref target="I-D.abarth-origin"/>
	  (although CORS <xref target="CORS"/> and WebSockets 
	  <xref target="I-D.ietf-hybi-thewebsocketprotocol"/> provides a escape hatch from this restriction,
	  as described below. This SAME ORIGIN POLICY (SOP) prevents server A
	  from mounting attacks on server B via the user's browser, which protects both
	  the user (e.g., from misuse of his credentials) and the server (e.g., from DoS attack).
	</t>
	<t>
	  More generally, SOP forces scripts from each site to run in their own, isolated,
	  sandboxes. While there are techniques to allow them to interact, those interactions
	  generally must be mutually consensual (by each site) and are limited to certain
	  channels. For instance, multiple pages/browser panes from the same origin
	  can read each other's JS variables, but pages from the different origins--or 
	  even iframes from different origins on the same page--cannot.
	</t>
	<!-- TODO: Picture -->
	  
      </section>
      <section title="Bypassing SOP: CORS, WebSockets, and consent to communicate" anchor="sec.cors-etc">
	<t>
	  While SOP serves an important security function, it also makes it inconvenient to
	  write certain classes of applications. In particular, mash-ups, in which a script
	  from origin A uses resources from origin B, can only be achieved via a certain amount of hackery.
	  The W3C Cross-Origin Resource Sharing (CORS) spec <xref target="CORS"/> is a response to this 
	  demand. In CORS, when a script from origin A executes what would otherwise be a forbidden
	  cross-origin request, the browser instead contacts the target server to determine
	  whether it is willing to allow cross-origin requests from A. If it is so willing,
	  the browser then allows the request. This consent verification process is designed
	  to safely allow cross-origin requests.
	</t>
	<t>
	  While CORS is designed to allow cross-origin HTTP requests, WebSockets <xref target="I-D.ietf-hybi-thewebsocketprotocol"/> allows
	  cross-origin establishment of transparent channels. Once a WebSockets connection
	  has been established from a script to a site, the script can exchange any traffic it
	  likes without being required to frame it as a series of HTTP request/response
	  transactions. As with CORS, a WebSockets transaction starts with a consent verification
	  stage to avoid allowing scripts to simply send arbitrary data to another origin.
	</t>
	<t>
	  While consent verification is conceptually simple--just do a handshake before you
	  start exchanging the real data--experience has shown that designing a
	  correct consent verification system is difficult. In particular, Huang et al. <xref target="huang-w2sp"/>
	  have shown vulnerabilities in the existing Java and Flash consent verification 
	  techniques and in a simplified version of the WebSockets handshake. In particular,
	  it is important to be wary of CROSS-PROTOCOL attacks in which the attacking script
	  generates traffic which is acceptable to some non-Web protocol state machine.
	  In order to resist this form of attack, WebSockets incorporates a masking technique
	  intended to randomize the bits on the wire, thus making it more difficult to generate
	  traffic which resembles a given protocol.
	</t>
      </section>		
    </section>      
 
    <section title="Security for RTC-Web Applications" anchor="sec.rtc-web">
      <section title="Access to Local Devices" anchor="sec.rtc-dev-access">
	<t>
	  As discussed in <xref target="sec.introduction"/>, allowing arbitrary
	  sites to initiate calls violates the core Web security guarantee;
	  without some access restrictions on local devices, any malicious site
	  could simply bug a user. At minimum, then, it MUST NOT be possible for
	  arbitrary sites to initiate calls to arbitrary location without user
	  consent. This immediately raises the question, however, of what should
	  be the scope of user consent.
	</t>
	<t>
	  As discussed in <xref target="sec.same-origin"/>, the basic unit of
	  Web sandboxing is the origin, and so it is natural to scope consent
	  to origin. Specifically, a script from origin A MUST only be allowed
	  to initiate communications (and hence to access camera and microphone)
	  if the user has specifically authorized access for that origin. 
	  It is of course technically possible to have coarser-scoped permissions,
	  but because the Web model is scoped to origin, this creates a difficult
	  mismatch.
	</t>
	<t>
	  Arguably, origin is not fine-grained enough. Consider the situation where
	  Alice visits a site and authorizes it to make a single call. If consent is
	  expressed solely in terms of origin, then at any future visit to that
	  site (including one induced via mash-up or ad network), the site can
	  bug Alice's computer. While in principle Alice could grant and then 
	  revoke the privilege, in practice privileges accumulate; if we are concerned
	  about this attack, something else is needed. There are a number of potential countermeasures to
	  this sort of issue.
	</t>
	<t><list style="hanging">
	  <t hangText="Individual Consent"></t><t>Ask the user for permission for each call.</t>
	  <t></t>
	  <t hangText="Callee-oriented Consent"></t><t>Only allow calls to a given user.</t>
	  <t></t>	  
	  <t hangText="Cryptographic Consent"></t><t>Only allow calls to a given set of peer keying material.</t>
	</list>
	</t>
	<t>
	  Unfortunately, none of these approaches is really satisfactory. Individual consent puts the
	  user's approval in the UI flow for every call. Not only does this quickly become annoying
	  but it rapidly trains the user to simply click "OK", at which point the consent becomes
	  useless.
	</t>
	<t>
	  The other two options are designed to restrict calls to a given target. Unfortunately, 
	  Callee-oriented consent does not work because the malicious site can claim that the
	  user is calling any user of his choice. The fix for this is to tie calls to a
	  specific set of cryptographic keying material, but that breaks any portability for
	  the callee's client, and is thus problematic. (<xref target="sec.key-continuity"/>)
	</t>
	<t>
	  While this is primarily a question not for IETF, it should be clear that there is no
	  really good answer. In general, if you cannot trust the site which you have authorized
	  for calling not to bug you then your security situation is not really ideal. 
	  It is RECOMMENDED that
	  browsers have explicit (and obvious) indicators that they are in a call in order
	  to mitigate this risk.
	</t>
	<t>
	  The above recommendations provide security against web attackers. However, if a
	  legitimate site is fetched over HTTP rather than HTTPS, a network attacker can inject
	  code to initiate calls as if it were that origin, thus bypassing origin
	  restrictions. Note that this form of attack is also possible if a site
	  embeds active content (e.g., JavaScript) that is fetched over
	  HTTP or from an untrusted site, because that JavaScript is executed
	  in the security context of the page <xref target="finer-grained"/>.
	  Therefore, it is RECOMMENDED that 
	  sites which embed RTC-Web functionality serve that functionality only
	  over HTTPS and that browsers disallow execution of calling functionality
	  in origins which contain mixed content. Note: this issue is not restricted
	  to PAGES which contain mixed content. If a page from a given origin ever loads mixed content
	  then it is possible for a network attacker to infect the browser's notion of that
	  origin semi-permanently.
	</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Communications Consent Verification" anchor="sec.rtc-comm-consent">
	<t>
	  As discussed in <xref target="sec.cors-etc"/>, allowing web applications unrestricted access 
	  to
	  the via the browser network introduces the risk of using the browser as an attack platform against
	  machines which would not otherwise be accessible to the malicious site, for
	  instance because they are topologically restricted (e.g., behind a firewall or NAT).
	  In order to prevent this form of attack as well as cross-protocol attacks it is
	  important to require that the target of traffic explicitly consent to receiving
	  the traffic in question. Until that consent has been verified for a given endpoint,
	  traffic other than the consent handshake MUST NOT be sent to that endpoint.
	</t>
	<section title="ICE" anchor="sec.ice">
	  <t>
	  Verifying receiver consent requires some sort of explicit handshake, but conveniently
	  we already need one in order to do NAT hole-punching. ICE <xref target="RFC5245"/> includes a handshake
	  designed to verify that the receiving element wishes to receive traffic from the
	  sender. It is important to remember here that the site initiating ICE is 
	  presumed malicious; in order for the handshake to be secure the receiving
	  element MUST demonstrate receipt/knowledge of some value not available to 
	  the site (thus preventing it from forging responses). In order to achieve this
	  objective with ICE, the STUN transaction IDs must be generated by the browser
	  and MUST NOT be made available to the 
	  initiating script, even via a diagnostic interface.
	  </t>
	</section>
	<section title="Masking" anchor="sec.masking">
	  <t>
	    Once consent is verified, there still is some concern about misinterpretation
	    attacks as described by Huang et al.<xref target="huang-w2sp"/>.
	    As long as communication is limited to
	    UDP, then this risk is probably limited, thus masking is not required
	    for UDP. However, 
	    with TCP the risk of transparent proxies becomes much more severe. If TCP
	    is to be used, then WebSockets style masking MUST be employed.
	    <!-- [TODO: DNS injection?].-->
	  </t>
	</section>
	<section title="Backward Compatibility">
	  <t>
	    A requirement to use ICE limits compatibility with legacy non-ICE clients.
	    It seems unsafe to completely remove the requirement for some check, but
	    it might be possible to merely require a one-sided check where the 
	    legacy client was a STUN responder. It's unclear whether that is in
	    fact simpler than doing ICE-Lite.
	  </t>
	</section>
      </section>

      <section title="Communications Security" anchor="sec.rtc-comsec">
	<t>
	  Finally, we consider a problem familiar from the SIP world: communications security.
	  For obvious reasons, it MUST be possible for the communicating parties to establish
	  a channel which is secure against both message recovery and message modification.
	  (See <xref target="RFC5479"/> for more details.) 
	  This service must be provided for both data and voice/video.
	  Ideally the same security mechanisms would be used for both types of content.
	  Technology for providing this
	  service (for instance, DTLS <xref target="RFC4347"/> and
	  DTLS-SRTP <xref target="RFC5763"/>) is well understood. However, we must
	  examine this technology to the RTC-Web context, where the threat
	  model is somewhat different.
	</t>
	<t>
	  In general, it is important to understand that unlike a conventional SIP proxy,
	  the calling service (i.e., the Web server) controls not only the channel
	  between the communicating endpoints but also the application running on
	  the user's browser.
	  While in principle it is possible for the browser to cut the calling service
	  out of the loop and directly present trusted information (and perhaps get
	  consent), practice in modern browsers is to avoid this whenever possible.
	  "In-flow" modal dialogs which require the user to consent to specific 
	  actions are particularly disfavored as human factors research indicates
	  that unless they are made extremely invasive, users simply agree to
	  them without actually consciously giving consent. <xref target="abarth-rtcweb"/>.
	  Thus, nearly all the UI will necessarily be rendered by the
	  browser but under control of the calling service. This likely includes the
	  peer's identity information, which, after all, is only meaningful in
	  the context of some calling service.
	</t>
	<t>
	  This limitation does not mean that preventing attack by the calling service
	  is completely hopeless. However, we need to distinguish between two
	  classes of attack:
	</t>
	<t><list style="hanging">
	  <t hangText="Retrospective compromise of calling service."></t><t>The calling service is
	  is non-malicious during a call but subsequently is compromised and wishes to 
	  attack an older call.</t>
	  <t></t>
	  <t hangText="During-call attack by calling service."></t><t>The calling service is compromised
	  during the call it wishes to attack.</t>
	  </list>
	  </t>
	<t>
	  Providing security against the former type of attack is practical using the
	  techniques discussed in <xref target="sec.retrospective-compromise"/>.
	  However, it is extremely difficult to prevent a 
	  trusted but malicious calling service from actively attacking a user's calls,
	  either by mounting a MITM attack or by diverting them entirely.
	  (Note that this attack applies equally to a network attacker if communications
	  to the calling service are not secured.) We discuss some potential approaches
	  and why they are likely to be impractical in <xref target="sec.during-attack"/>.
	</t>
	<section title="Protecting Against Retrospective Compromise" anchor="sec.retrospective-compromise">
	  <t>
	    In a retrospective attack, the calling service was uncompromised during
	    the call, but that an attacker subsequently wants to recover the content of the
	    call. We assume that the attacker has access to the protected media stream
	    as well as having full control of the calling service. 
	  </t>
	  <t>
	    If the calling service has access to the traffic keying material 
	    (as in SDES <xref target="RFC4568"/>), then retrospective attack
	    is trivial.
	    This form of attack is particularly serious in the Web context because
	    it is standard practice in Web services to run extensive logging and monitoring. Thus, it is highly
	    likely that if the traffic key is part of any HTTP request it will be logged somewhere and thus
	    subject to subsequent compromise. It is this consideration that makes an automatic, public key-based
	    key exchange mechanism imperative for RTC-Web (this is a good idea for any communications
	    security system) and this mechanism SHOULD provide perfect forward secrecy (PFS).
	    The signaling channel/calling service can be used to authenticate this mechanism.
	  </t>
	  <t>
	    In addition, the system MUST NOT provide any APIs to extract either long-term
	    keying material or to directly access any stored traffic keys.
	    Otherwise, an attacker who subsequently compromised the calling service
	    might be able to use those APIs to recover the traffic keys and thus
	    compromise the traffic.
	  </t>
	</section>
	<section title="Protecting Against During-Call Attack" anchor="sec.during-attack">
	  <t>
	    Protecting against attacks during a call is a more difficult proposition. Even 
	    if the calling service cannot directly access keying material (as recommended
	    in the previous section), it can simply mount a man-in-the-middle attack
	    on the connection, telling Alice that she is calling Bob and Bob that
	    he is calling Alice, while in fact the calling service is acting as
	    a calling bridge and capturing all the traffic. While in theory it 
	    is possible to construct techniques which protect against this form of
	    attack, in practice these techniques all require far too much user
	    intervention to be practical, given the user interface constraints
	    described in <xref target="abarth-rtcweb"/>.
	  </t>
	  <section title="Key Continuity" anchor="sec.key-continuity">
	    <t>
	      One natural approach is to use "key continuity". While a malicious
	      calling service can present any identity it chooses to the user,
	      it cannot produce a private key that maps to a given public key.
	      Thus, it is possible for the browser to note a given user's
	      public key and generate an alarm whenever that user's key 
	      changes. SSH <xref target="RFC4251"/> uses a similar technique.
	      (Note that the need to avoid explicit user consent on every call
	      precludes the browser requiring an immediate manual check of the peer's key).
	    </t>
	    <t>
	      Unfortunately, this sort of key continuity mechanism is far less
	      useful in the RTC-Web context. First, much of the virtue of 
	      RTC-Web (and any Web application) is that it is not bound to 
	      particular piece of client software. Thus, it will be not only
	      possible but routine for a user to use multiple browsers
	      on different computers which will of course have different
	      keying material (SACRED <xref target="RFC3760"/> notwithstanding.)
	      Thus, users will frequently be alerted to key mismatches which
	      are in fact completely legitimate, with the result that they
	      are trained to simply click through them. As it is known that
	      users routinely will click through far more dire warnings
	      <xref target="cranor-wolf"/>, it seems extremely unlikely that
	      any key continuity mechanism will be effective rather than
	      simply annoying.
	    </t>
	    <t>
	      Moreover, it is trivial to bypass even this kind of mechanism.
	      Recall that unlike the case of SSH, the browser never directly
	      gets the peer's identity from the user. Rather, it is provided
	      by the calling service. Even enabling a mechanism of this type
	      would require an API to allow the calling service to tell the
	      browser "this is a call to user X". All the calling service
	      needs to do to avoid triggering a key continuity warning 
	      is to tell the browser that "this is a call to user Y"
	      where Y is close to X.
	      Even if the user actually checks the other side's name
	      (which all available evidence indicates is unlikely), 
	      this would require (a) the browser to trusted UI
	      to provide the name and (b) the user to not be fooled by
	      similar appearing names. 
	    </t>
	  </section>
	  <section title="Short Authentication Strings" anchor="sec.sas">
	    <t>
	      ZRTP <xref target="RFC6189"/> uses a "short authentication string" (SAS) which is derived
	      from the key agreement protocol. This SAS is designed to be read over
	      the voice channel and if confirmed by both sides precludes MITM
	      attack. The intention is that the SAS is used once and then key
	      continuity (though a different mechanism from that discussed
	      above) is used thereafter. 
	    </t>
	    <t>
	      Unfortunately, the SAS does not offer a practical solution to the
	      problem of a compromised calling service.	"Voice conversion" systems, which modify
	      voice from one speaker to make it sound like another,
	      are an active area of research. 
	      These systems are already good enough to fool both
	      automatic recognition systems <xref target="farus-conversion"/> and 
	      humans <xref target="kain-conversion"/> in many cases, and are of course likely
	      to improve in future, especially in an environment where the user just wants
	      to get on with the phone call.
	      Thus, even if SAS is effective today, it is likely not to be so for much longer.
	      Moreover, it is possible for an attacker
	      who controls the browser to allow the SAS to succeed and then simulate call failure
	      and reconnect, trusting that the user will not notice that
	      the "no SAS" indicator has been set (which seems likely).
	    </t>
	    <t>
	      Even were SAS secure if used, it seems exceedingly unlikely
	      that users will actually use it. As discussed above, the
	      browser UI constraints preclude requiring the SAS exchange
	      prior to completing the call and so it must be voluntary;
	      at most the browser will provide some UI indicator that the
	      SAS has not yet been checked. However, it 
	      it is well-known that when faced with 
	      optional mechanisms such as fingerprints, users simply do not
	      check them <xref target="whitten-johnny"/> Thus, it is 
	      highly unlikely that users will ever perform the SAS exchange.
	    </t>
	    <t>
	      Once uses have checked the SAS once, key continuity
	      is required to avoid them needing to check it on every call.
	      However, this is problematic for reasons indicated in
	      <xref target="sec.key-continuity"/>.
	      In principle it is of course possible to render a different
	      UI element to indicate that calls are using an unauthenticated
	      set of keying material (recall that the attacker can just present
	      a slightly different name so that the attack shows the
	      same UI as a call to a new device or to someone you haven't
	      called before) but as a practical matter, users simply ignore
	      such indicators even in the rather more dire case of mixed
	      content warnings.
	    </t>
	  </section>
	</section>
	
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Security Considerations" anchor="sec.sec_cons">
      <t>This entire document is about security.</t>
    </section>

        <section title="Acknowledgements">
      <t></t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      &RFC2119;
    </references>
    <references title="Informative References">
      &RFC3261;
      &RFC3552;
      &RFC2818;
      &RFC5479;
      &RFC5763;
      &RFC4347;
      &RFC4568;
      &RFC4251;
      &RFC3760;
      &RFC6189;
      &RFC5245;
      &I-D.abarth-origin;
      &I-D.ietf-hybi-thewebsocketprotocol;

      <reference anchor="abarth-rtcweb">
	<front>
	  <title>Prompting the user is security failure</title>
	  
	  <author initials="A." surname="Barth">
	    <organization></organization>
	  </author>
	  

	</front>
	<seriesInfo name="" value="RTC-Web Workshop"/>
	<format target="http://rtc-web.alvestrand.com/home/papers/barth-security-prompt.pdf?attredirects=0" type="PDF"/>
      </reference>
      
      <reference anchor="whitten-johnny">
	<front>
	  <title>Why Johnny Can't Encrypt: A Usability Evaluation of PGP 5.0</title>
	  
	  <author initials="A." surname="Whitten">
	    <organization></organization>
	  </author>

	  <author initials="J.D." surname="Tygar">
	    <organization></organization>
	  </author>
	</front>
	<seriesInfo name="" value="Proceedings of the 8th USENIX Security Symposium, 1999"/>
      </reference>


      <reference anchor="cranor-wolf">
	<front>
	  <title>Crying Wolf: An Empirical Study of SSL Warning Effectiveness</title>

	  <author initials="J." surname="Sunshine">
	    <organization></organization>
	  </author>

	  <author initials="S." surname="Egelman">
	    <organization></organization>
	  </author>
	  <author initials="H." surname="Almuhimedi">
	    <organization></organization>
	  </author>
	  <author initials="N." surname="Atri">
	    <organization></organization>
	  </author>
	  <author initials="L." surname="cranor">
	    <organization></organization>
	  </author>
	</front>

	<seriesInfo name="" value="Proceedings of the 18th USENIX Security Symposium, 2009"/>

      </reference>


      <reference anchor="kain-conversion">
	<front>
	  <title>Design and Evaluation of a Voice Conversion Algorithm based on Spectral Envelope Mapping and Residual Prediction</title>
	  
	  <author initials="A." surname="Kain">
	    <organization></organization>
	  </author>
	  

	  <author initials="M." surname="Macon">
	    <organization></organization>
	  </author>
	</front>

	<seriesInfo name="" value="Proceedings of ICASSP, May 2001"/>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="farus-conversion">
	<front>
	  <title>Speaker Recognition Robustness to Voice Conversion</title>
	  
	  <author initials="M." surname="Farrus">
	    <organization></organization>
	  </author>
	  <author initials="D." surname="Erro">
	    <organization></organization>
	  </author>
	  <author initials="J." surname="Hernando">
	    <organization></organization>
	  </author>

	</front>
      </reference>


      <reference anchor="huang-w2sp">
	<front>
	  <title>Talking to Yourself for Fun and Profit</title>
	  
	  <author initials="L-S." surname="Huang">
	    <organization></organization>
	  </author>
	  <author initials="E.Y." surname="Chen">
	    <organization></organization>
	  </author>
	  <author initials="A." surname="Barth">
	    <organization></organization>
	  </author>
	  <author initials="E." surname="Rescorla">
	    <organization></organization>
	  </author>
	  <author initials="C." surname="Jackson">
	    <organization></organization>
	  </author>
	</front>

	<seriesInfo name="" value="W2SP, 2011"/>
      </reference>

      


      <reference anchor="finer-grained">
	<front>
	  <title>Beware of Finer-Grained Origins</title>

	  <author initials="A." surname="Barth">
	    <organization></organization>
	  </author>
	  <author initials="C." surname="Jackson">
	    <organization></organization>
	  </author>
	</front>

	<seriesInfo name="" value="W2SP, 2008"/>
      </reference>


      <reference anchor="CORS">
	<front>
	  <title>Cross-Origin Resource Sharing</title>
	  
	  <author initials="A." surname="van Kesteren">
	    <organization></organization>
	  </author>
	</front>
	<format target="http://www.w3.org/TR/cors/" type="TXT"/>
      </reference>


    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>

