<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY RFC2119 PUBLIC ''
'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml'>
<!ENTITY RFC3588 PUBLIC ''
'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3588.xml'>
<!ENTITY RFC2915 PUBLIC ''
'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2915.xml'>
<!ENTITY RFC3403 PUBLIC ''
'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3403.xml'>
<!ENTITY RFC1035 PUBLIC ''
'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1035.xml'>
<!ENTITY RFC2782 PUBLIC ''
'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2782.xml'>
]>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<rfc category="std"
     docName="draft-jones-dime-extended-naptr-01"
     ipr="pre5378Trust200902"
     updates="3588">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="dime-extended-naptr">Diameter Extended NAPTR</title>

    <author fullname="Mark Jones" initials="M" surname="Jones">
      <organization>Bridgewater Systems</organization>

      <address>
        <email>mark.jones@bridgewatersystems.com</email>
      </address>
      </author>

      <author initials="J" surname="Korhonen" fullname="Jouni Korhonen">
         <organization>Nokia Siemens Networks</organization>
         <address>
            <email>jouni.nospam@gmail.com</email>
         </address>
      </author>

    <date year="2009" />

    <area>Operations and Management</area>

    <workgroup>Individual Submission</workgroup>

    <keyword>NAPTR</keyword>

    <keyword>Diameter</keyword>

    <keyword>Services Field</keyword>

    <keyword>Peer Discovery</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>This document describes an extended format for the NAPTR service 
      fields used in dynamic Diameter agent discovery. The extended format
      allows NAPTR queries to contain Diameter Application-Id information.</t>
    </abstract>

    <note title="Requirements Language">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
      document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
      target="RFC2119"/>.</t>
    </note>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>The Diameter base protocol <xref target="RFC3588"/> specifies three 
      mechanisms for the Diameter peer discovery. One of these involves the 
      Diameter implementation performing a NAPTR query <xref 
      target="RFC3403"/> for a server in a particular realm. 
      These NAPTR records provide a mapping from a domain, to the SRV record 
      <xref target="RFC2782"/> for contacting a server with the specific
      transport protocol in the NAPTR services field. </t>
      <t>Section 11.6 of RFC 3588 defines the following 
      NAPTR service fields:
      <figure><artwork><![CDATA[
      Services Field               Protocol
      AAA+D2T                       TCP
      AAA+D2S                       SCTP          
  ]]></artwork></figure></t>
      <t>However, foreseen network topologies require border AAA nodes that 
      will be specialized by Diameter application and the NAPTR service
      field does not allow a Diameter implementation to determine the 
      application supported by the AAA node. Without this information,
      a Diameter implementation must connect and perform a capability
      negotiation with each candidate AAA node. This document addresses
      this problem by specifying an extended NAPTR service field format 
      that permits discovery of Diameter peers that support a specific 
      Diameter application.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Terminology">
      <t>The Diameter base protocol specification (Section 1.4 of RFC 3588)
      defines most of the terminology used in this document. </t>
    </section>

    <section title="Extended NAPTR Service Field">
      <t>The Extended NAPTR service field ABNF specification for the 
      discovery of Diameter agents supporting a specific Diameter 
      application is show below.
      
      <figure><artwork><![CDATA[
      naptr-svc-field     = "AAA+D2" < protocol> [ *appln-list ]
    
      protocol            = "T" / "S"
                            ; "T" for TCP and "S" for SCTP.

      appln-list          = "+AP:" appln-id [ *( "," appln-id ) ]
                            ; Comma separated list of application 
                            ; identifiers prefixed by "+AP:".

      appln-id            = *DIGIT
                            ; Application identifier expressed as a
                            ; decimal integer.
  ]]></artwork></figure>
      </t>
      <t>For example, a NAPTR service field value of:
      </t>
      <t><list style="hanging">
        <t hangText="'AAA+D2S+AP:6'">
          <vspace blankLines="1"/>
          Means 
          that the Diameter node in the SRV record supports the Diameter 
          Session Initiation Protocol (SIP) Application ('6') and SCTP as the
          transport protocol.
        </t>
        <t hangText="'AAA+D2S+AP:6,1,5,4294967295'">
          <vspace blankLines="1"/>
          Means 
          that the Diameter node in the SRV record supports the Diameter 
          Session Initiation Protocol (SIP) Application ('6'), NASREQ Application
          ('1'), EAP Application ('5') and SCTP as the transport protocol.
          The Diameter node also provides Relay functionality ('4294967295').
        </t>
      </list>
      </t>
      <t>The maximum length of the NAPTR service field is 256 octets including
         one octet length field (see Section 4.1 of RFC 3403 and Section 3.3 of
         <xref target="RFC1035"/>). The DNS administrator of some domain
         SHOULD also provision base RFC 3588 style NAPTR records in order to
         guarantee backwards compatibility with legacy RFC 3588 compliant
         Diameter peers. If the DNS administrator provisions 
         both extended NAPTR records as defined in this specification and 
         legacy RFC 3588 NAPTR records, then the extended NAPTR records 
         MUST have higher priority (e.g. lower order and/or preference 
         values) than legacy NAPTR records.
      </t>
    </section>
    
    <section title="Extended NAPTR-based Diameter Peer Discovery">
      <t>The basic Diameter Peer Discover principles are described in
         Section 5.2 of <xref target="RFC3588"/>. This specification 
         extends the NAPTR query procedure in the Diameter peer discovery 
         mechanism by allowing the querying node to determine which 
         applications are supported by resolved Diameter peers.
         </t> 
      <t>The extended format NAPTR records provide a mapping from a domain, 
         to the SRV record for contacting a server supporting a specific
         transport protocol and Diameter application. The resource record
         will contain an empty regular expression and a replacement
         value, which is the SRV record for that particular transport
         protocol.  If the server supports multiple transport
         protocols, there will be multiple NAPTR records, each with a
         different Services Field value and potentially different list
         of supported Diameter applications.</t>
      <t>The assumption for this mechanism to work is that the DNS 
         administrator of the queried domain has first provisioned the DNS
         with extended format NAPTR entries. The steps below replace the 
         NAPTR query procedure steps in Section 5.2 of <xref target="RFC3588"/>.
      </t>
      <t><list style="hanging">
        <t hangText="a.">The Diameter implementation performs a NAPTR query for
           a server in a particular realm. The Diameter implementation has 
           to know in advance which realm to look for a Diameter agent in and 
           which Application Identifier it is interested in.  The realm could
           be deduced, for example, from the 'realm' in a NAI that a Diameter
           implementation needed to perform a Diameter operation on.
        </t>
        <t hangText="b.">If the returned NAPTR service fields contain entries
           formatted as "AAA+D2X+AP:Y" where "X" indicates the transport protocol 
           and "Y" is a comma-separated list of Application Identifiers, 
           the target realm supports the extended format for 
           NAPTR-based Diameter peer discovery defined in this document.
           <list style="hanging">
           <t>If "X" matches a transport protocol supported by the client and 
           "Y" contains the required Application Identifier,
           the client resolves the "replacement" field entry to a target
           host using the lookup method appropriate for the "flags" field.
           </t>
           <t>If "X" does not match a transport protocol supported by the client 
           or "Y" does not contain the required Application Identifier,
           the peer discovery is abandoned.
           </t>
           </list>
           </t>
        <t hangText="c.">If the returned NAPTR service fields contain entries
           formatted as "AAA+D2X" where "X" indicates the transport protocol, 
           the target realm supports the NAPTR-based Diameter 
           peer discovery defined in <xref target="RFC3588"/>.
           <list style="hanging">
           <t>If "X" matches a transport protocol supported by the client,
           the client resolves the "replacement" field entry to a target
           host using the lookup method appropriate for the "flags" field.
           </t>
           <t>If "X" does not match a transport protocol supported by the client,
           the peer discovery is abandoned.
           </t>
           </list>
        </t>
        <t hangText="d.">If the target realm does not support NAPTR-based Diameter 
        peer discovery, the client proceeds with the next peer discovery mechanism
        described in Section 5.2 of <xref target="RFC3588"/>.
        </t>
      </list>
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>Section 11.6 of <xref target="RFC3588"/> defines a IANA registry for the 
      NAPTR Services Field entries. Although this document does not define a new 
      transport protocol, it is proposed to add the following entries to the 
      existing registry to reflect the extended format of the NAPTR Services Field:
      </t>
      <figure>
      <artwork><![CDATA[ 
      Services Field               Protocol
      AAA+D2T+AP:x                  TCP
      AAA+D2S+AP:x                  SCTP
   ]]></artwork></figure>
      <t>Editor's Note: IANA is currently missing the registry for the NAPTR Service
      Fields defined in <xref target="RFC3588"/>. This oversight will need to
      be resolved for this document to proceed.</t> 
    </section>

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>This document specifies an enhancement to the NAPTR service
      field format defined in the Diameter base protocol and the same security
      considerations described in RFC 3588 are
      applicable to this document. No further extensions are required beyond
      the security mechanisms offered by RFC 3588.
      However, a malicious host doing NAPTR queries learns applications 
      supported by Diameter agents in a certain realm faster, which might
      help the malicious host to scan potential targets for an attack 
      more efficiently when some applications have known vulnerabilities.</t>
    </section>

  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      &RFC2119;
      &RFC3588;
      &RFC3403;
      &RFC1035;
      &RFC2782;
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>