<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<rfc category="info" docName="draft-ietf-karp-routing-tcp-analysis-05.txt"
     ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="BGP, LDP, PCEP and MSDP Analysis">Analysis of BGP, LDP,
    PCEP and MSDP Issues According to KARP Design Guide</title>

    <author fullname="Mahesh Jethanandani" initials="M."
            surname="Jethanandani">
      <organization>Ciena Corporation</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>1741 Technology Drive</street>

          <city>San Jose</city>

          <region>CA</region>

          <code>95110</code>

          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>

        <phone>+ (408) 436-3313</phone>

        <email>mjethanandani@gmail.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Keyur Patel" initials="K." surname="Patel">
      <organization>Cisco Systems, Inc</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>170 Tasman Drive</street>

          <city>San Jose</city>

          <region>CA</region>

          <code>95134</code>

          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>

        <phone>+1 (408) 526-7183</phone>

        <email>keyupate@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Lianshu Zheng" initials="L." surname="Zheng">
      <organization>Huawei Technologies</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>

          <city></city>

          <region></region>

          <code></code>

          <country>China</country>
        </postal>

        <phone>+86 (10) 82882008</phone>

        <facsimile></facsimile>

        <email>vero.zheng@huawei.com</email>

        <uri></uri>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date day="18" month="October" year="2012" />

    <area>Network</area>

    <workgroup>Routing Working Group</workgroup>

    <keyword>Internet-Draft</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>This document analyzes <xref target="RFC4271">Border Gateway Protocol
      (BGP)</xref>, <xref target="RFC5036">Label Distribution Protocol
      (LDP)</xref>, <xref target="RFC5440">Path Computation Element Protocol
      (PCEP)</xref> and <xref target="RFC3618">Multicast Source Distribution
      Protocol (MSDP)</xref> according to guidelines set forth in section 4.2
      of <xref target="RFC6518">Keying and Authentication for Routing
      Protocols Design Guidelines </xref>.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>In March 2006 the Internet Architecture Board (IAB) in its "Unwanted
      Internet Traffic" workshop documented in <xref target="RFC4948">Report
      from the IAB workshop on Unwanted Traffic March 9-10, 2006</xref>
      described an attack on core routing infrastructure as an ideal attack
      with the most amount of damage. Four main steps were identified for that
      tightening:</t>

      <t><list style="numbers">
          <t>Create secure mechanisms and practices for operating routers.</t>

          <t>Clean up the Internet Routing Registry [IRR] repository, and
          securing both the database and the access, so that it can be used
          for routing verifications.</t>

          <t>Create specifications for cryptographic validation of routing
          message content.</t>

          <t>Secure the routing protocols' packets on the wire.</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>In order to secure the routing protocols this document performs an
      initial analysis of the current state of BGP, LDP, PCEP and MSDP
      according to the requirements of <xref target="RFC6518">KARP Design
      Guidelines </xref>. Section 4.2 of the document uses the term "state"
      which will be referred to as the "state of the security method". Thus a
      term like "Define Optimal State" would be referred to as "Define Optimal
      State of the Security Method". This document builds on several previous
      analysis efforts into routing security. The OPSEC working group
      published <xref target="RFC6039">Issues with existing Cryptographic
      Protection Methods for Routing Protocols </xref> an analysis of
      cryptographic issues with routing protocols and <xref
      target="draft-ietf-karp-ospf-analysis-03">Analysis of OSPF Security
      According to KARP Design Guide</xref>.</t>

      <t>Section 2 of this document looks at the current state of security
      method for the four routing protocols, BGP, LDP, PCEP and MSDP. Section
      3 examines what the optimal state of the security method would be for
      the four routing protocols according to <xref target="RFC6518">KARP
      Design Guidelines </xref> and Section 4 does a analysis of the gap
      between the existing state of the security method and the optimal state
      of the security method for protocols and suggests some areas where
      improvement is needed.</t>

      <section title="Conventions Used in This Document">
        <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
        "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
        document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
        target="RFC2119">RFC 2119</xref>.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Abbreviations">
        <t>AS - Autonomous Systems</t>

        <t>BGP - Border Gateway Protocol</t>

        <t>DoS - Denial of Service</t>

        <t>GTSM - Generalized TTL Security Mechanism</t>

        <t>KARP - Key and Authentication for Routing Protocols</t>

        <t>KDF - Key Derivation Function</t>

        <t>KEK - Key Encrypting Key</t>

        <t>KMP - Key Management Protocol</t>

        <t>LDP - Label Distribution Protocol</t>

        <t>LSR - Label Switch Routers</t>

        <t>MAC - Message Authentication Code</t>

        <t>MKT - Master Key Tuple</t>

        <t>MSDP - Multicast Source Distribution Protocol</t>

        <t>MD5 - Message Digest algorithm 5</t>

        <t>OSPF - OPen Shortest Path First</t>

        <t>PCEP - Path Computation Element Protocol</t>

        <t>TCP - Transmission Control Protocol</t>

        <t>TTL - Time To Live</t>

        <t>UDP - User Datagram Protocol</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Current Assessment of BGP, LDP, PCEP and MSDP">
      <t>This section assesses the transport protocols for any authentication
      or integrity mechanisms used by the protocol. It describes the current
      security mechanisms if any used by BGP, LDP, PCEP and MSDP.</t>

      <section title="Transport layer">
        <t>At a transport layer, routing protocols are subject to a variety of
        DoS attacks as outlined in <xref target="RFC4732">Internet
        Denial-of-Service Considerations</xref>. Such attacks can cause the
        routing protocol to become congested with the result that routing
        updates are supplied too slowly to be useful. In extreme cases, these
        attacks prevent routers from converging after a change.</t>

        <t>Routing protocols use several methods to protect themselves. Those
        that use TCP as a transport protocol use access lists to accept
        packets only from known sources. These access lists also help protect
        edge routers from attacks originating from outside the protected
        domain. In addition for edge routers running eBGP, TCP LISTEN is run
        only on interfaces on which its peers have been discovered or via
        which routing sessions are expected (as specified in router
        configuration databases).</t>

        <t><xref target="RFC5082">Generalized TTL Security Mechanism (GTSM)
        </xref> describes a generalized Time to Live (TTL) security mechanism
        to protect a protocol stack from CPU-utilization based attacks.<xref
        target="RFC5961"> TCP Robustness</xref> recommends some TCP level
        mitigations against spoofing attacks targeted towards long-lived
        routing protocol sessions.</t>

        <t>Even when BGP, LDP, PCEP and MSDP sessions use access lists they
        are vulnerable to spoofing and man in the middle attacks.
        Authentication and integrity checks allow the receiver of a routing
        protocol update to know that the message genuinely comes from the node
        that purports to have sent it, and to know whether the message has
        been modified. Sometimes routers can be subjected to a large number of
        authentication and integrity requests, exhausting connection resources
        on the router in a way that deny genuine requests.</t>

        <t><xref target="RFC2385">TCP MD5</xref> has been obsoleted by <xref
        target="RFC5925">TCP-AO</xref>. However it is still widely used to
        authenticate TCP based routing protocols such as BGP. It provides a
        way for carrying a MD5 digest in a TCP segment. This digest acts like
        a signature for that segment, computed using information known only to
        the connection end points. The MD5 key used to compute the digest is
        stored locally on the router. This option is used by routing protocols
        to provide for session level protection against the introduction of
        spoofed TCP segments into any existing TCP streams, in particular TCP
        Reset segments. TCP MD5 does not provide a generic mechanism to
        support key roll-over.</t>

        <t>The Message Authentication Codes (MACs) used by the TCP MD5 option
        is considered too weak both because of the use of the hash function
        and because of the way the secret key used by TCP MD5 is managed.
        <xref target="RFC5925">TCP-AO </xref> and its companion document <xref
        target="RFC5926">Crypto Algorithms for TCP-AO</xref> describe steps
        towards correcting both the MAC weakness and the management of secret
        keys. For MAC it specifies two MAC algorithms that MUST be supported.
        They are HMAC-SHA-1-96 as specified in <xref
        target="RFC2104">HMAC</xref> and AES-128-CMAC-96 as specified in <xref
        target="NIST-SP800-38B">NIST-SP800-38B</xref>. Cryptographic research
        suggests that both these MAC algorithms defined are fairly secure.
        TCP-AO allows additional MACs to be added in the future.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Keying mechanisms">
        <t>For <xref target="RFC5925">TCP-AO</xref> there is no Key Management
        Protocol (KMP) used to manage the keys that are employed to generate
        the Message Authentication Code (MAC). TCP-AO allows for a master key
        to be configured manually or for it to be managed via a out of band
        mechanism.</t>

        <t>It should be noted that most routers configured with static keys
        have not seen the key changed ever. The common reason given for not
        changing the key is the difficulty in coordinating the change between
        pairs of routers when using TCP MD5. It is well known that the longer
        the same key is used, the greater the chance that it can be guessed or
        exposed e.g. when an administrator with knowledge of the keys leaves
        the company.</t>

        <t>For point-to-point key management <xref
        target="RFC5996">IKEv2</xref> provides for automated key exchange
        under a SA and can be used for a comprehensive Key Management Protocol
        (KMP) solution.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="LDP">
        <t>Section 5 of <xref target="RFC5036">LDP</xref> states that LDP is
        subject to two different types of attacks: spoofing, and denial of
        service attacks. In addition, LDP distributes labels in the clear,
        enabling hackers to see what labels are being distributed. The
        attacker can use that information to spoof a connection and distribute
        a different set of labels causing traffic to be dropped.</t>

        <section title="Spoofing attacks">
          <t>A spoofing attack against LDP can occur both during the discovery
          phase and during the session communication phase.</t>

          <section title="Discovery exchanges using UDP">
            <t>Label Switching Routers (LSRs) indicate their willingness to
            establish and maintain LDP sessions by periodically sending Hello
            messages. Receipt of a Hello message serves to create a new "Hello
            adjacency", if one does not already exist, or to refresh an
            existing one.</t>

            <t>Unlike all other LDP messages, the Hello messages are sent
            using UDP. This means that they cannot benefit from the security
            mechanisms available with TCP. <xref target="RFC5036">LDP</xref>
            does not provide any security mechanisms for use with Hello
            messages except for some configuration which may help protect
            against bogus discovery events. These configurations include
            directly connected links and interfaces. Routers that do not use
            directly connected links have to use Extended Hello messages.</t>

            <t>Spoofing a Hello packet for an existing adjacency can cause the
            adjacency to time out and result in termination of the associated
            session. This can occur when the spoofed Hello message specifies a
            small Hold Time, causing the receiver to expect Hello messages
            within this interval, while the true neighbor continues sending
            Hello messages at the lower, previously agreed to frequency.</t>

            <t>Spoofing a Hello packet can also cause the LDP session to be
            terminated. This can occur when the spoofed Hello specifies a
            different Transport Address from the previously agreed one between
            neighbors. Spoofed Hello messages are observed and reported as
            real problem in production networks.</t>
          </section>

          <section title="Session communication using TCP">
            <t>LDP like other TCP based routing protocols specifies use of the
            TCP MD5 Signature Option to provide for the authenticity and
            integrity of session messages. As stated above, MD5 authentication
            is considered too weak for this application. A stronger hashing
            algorithm e.g SHA1, which is supported by <xref
            target="RFC5925">TCP-AO</xref> could be deployed to take care of
            the weakness.</t>

            <t>Alternatively, one could move to using TCP-AO which provides
            for stronger MACs, makes it easier to setup manual keys and
            protects against replays.</t>
          </section>
        </section>

        <section title="Privacy Issues">
          <t>LDP provides no mechanism for protecting the privacy of label
          distribution. The security requirements of label distribution are
          similar to other routing protocols that need to distribute routing
          information.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Denial of Service Attacks">
          <t>LDP is subject to Denial of Service (DoS) attacks both in its
          discovery mode and in session mode. These are documented in Section
          5.3 of <xref target="RFC5036">LDP</xref>.</t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section title="PCEP">
        <t>Attacks on <xref target="RFC5440">PCEP</xref> may result in damage
        to active networks. These include computation responses, which if
        changed can cause protocols like LDP to setup sub-optimal or
        inappropriate LSPs. In addition, PCE itself can be attacked by a
        variety of DoS attacks. Such attacks can cause path computations to be
        supplied too slowly to be of any value particularly as it relates to
        recovery or establishment of LSPs.</t>

        <t>As RFC 5440 states, PCEP could be the target of the following
        attacks.</t>

        <t><list style="symbols">
            <t>Spoofing (PCC or PCE implementation)</t>

            <t>Snooping (message interception)</t>

            <t>Falsification</t>

            <t>Denial of Service</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>In inter-Autonomous Systems (AS) scenarios where PCE-to-PCE
        communication is required, attacks may be particularly significant
        with commercial as well as service-level agreement implications.</t>

        <t>Additionally, snooping of PCEP requests and responses may give an
        attacker information about the operation of the network. By viewing
        the PCEP messages an attacker can determine the pattern of service
        establishment in the network and can know where traffic is being
        routed, thereby making the network susceptible to targeted attacks and
        the data within specific LSPs vulnerable.</t>

        <t>Ensuring PCEP communication privacy is of key importance,
        especially in an inter-AS context, where PCEP communication end-points
        do not reside in the same AS. An attacker that intercepts a PCE
        message could obtain sensitive information related to computed paths
        and resources.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="MSDP">
        <t>Similar to BGP and LDP, Multicast Source Distribution Protocol
        (MSDP) uses <xref target="RFC2385">TCP MD5</xref> to protect TCP
        sessions via the TCP MD5 option. But with a weak MD5 authentication,
        TCP MD5 is not considered strong enough for this application.</t>

        <t>MSDP also advocates imposing a limit on number of source address
        and group addresses (S,G) that can be cached within the protocol and
        thereby mitigate state explosion due to any denial of service and
        other attacks.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Optimal State for BGP, LDP, PCEP, and MSDP">
      <t>The ideal state of the security method for BGP, LDP, PCEP and MSDP
      protocols are when they can withstand any of the known types of
      attacks.</t>

      <t>Additionally, Key Management Protocol (KMP) for the routing sessions
      should help negotiate unique, pair wise random keys without
      administrator involvement. It should also negotiate Security Association
      (SA) parameter required for the session connection, including key life
      times. It should keep track of those lifetimes and negotiate new keys
      and parameters before they expire and do so without administrator
      involvement. In the event of a breach, including when an administrator
      with knowledge of the keys leaves the company, the keys should be
      changed immediately.</t>

      <t>The DoS attacks for BGP, LDP, PCEP and MSDP are attacks to the
      transport protocol, TCP for the most part and UDP in case of discovery
      phase of LDP. TCP and UDP should be able to withstand any of DoS
      scenarios by dropping packets that are attack packets in a way that does
      not impact legitimate packets.</t>

      <t>The routing protocols should provide a mechanism to authenticate the
      routing information carried within the payload.</t>

      <section title="LDP">
        <t>To harden LDP against its current vulnerability to spoofing
        attacks, LDP needs to be upgraded such that an implementation is able
        to determine the authenticity of the neighbors sending the Hello
        message.</t>

        <t>There is currently no requirement to protect the privacy of label
        distribution as labels are carried in the clear like other routing
        information.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Gap Analysis for BGP, LDP, PCEP and MSDP">
      <t>This section outlines the differences between the current state of
      the security methods for routing protocols and the desired state of the
      security methods as outlined in section 4.2 of <xref
      target="RFC6518">KARP Design Guidelines </xref>. As that document
      states, these routing protocols fall into the category of one-to-one
      peering messages and will use peer keying protocol. It covers issues
      that are common to the four protocols in this section, leaving protocol
      specific issues to sub-sections.</t>

      <t>At a transport level these routing protocols are subject to some of
      the same attacks that TCP applications are subject to. These include DoS
      and spoofing attacks. <xref target="RFC4732">Internet Denial-of-Service
      Considerations</xref> outlines some solutions. <xref
      target="RFC4953">Defending TCP Against Spoofing Attacks</xref>
      recommends ways to prevent spoofing attacks. In addition <xref
      target="RFC5961"> Improving TCP's Robustness to Blind In-Window
      Attacks.</xref> should also be followed and implemented to strengthen
      TCP.</t>

      <t>Routers lack comprehensive key management and keys derived from it
      that they can use to authenticate data. As an example <xref
      target="RFC5925">TCP-AO</xref>, talks about coordinating keys derived
      from Master Key Table (MKT) between endpoints, but the MKT itself has to
      be configured manually or through an out of band mechanism. Also TCP-AO
      does not address the issue of connectionless reset, as it applies to
      routers that do not store MKT across reboots.</t>

      <t>Authentication, tamper protection, and encryption all require the use
      of keys by sender and receiver. An automated KMP therefore has to
      include a way to distribute MKT between two end points with little or no
      administration overhead. It has to cover automatic key rollover. It is
      expected that authentication will cover the packet, i.e. the payload and
      the TCP header and will not cover the frame i.e. the link layer 2
      header.</t>

      <t>There are two methods of automatic key rollover. Implicit key
      rollover can be initiated after certain volume of data gets exchanged or
      when a certain time has elapsed. This does not require explicit
      signaling nor should it result in a reset of the TCP connection in a way
      that the links/adjacencies are affected. On the other hand, explicit key
      rollover requires an out of band key signaling mechanism. It can be
      triggered by either side and can be done anytime a security parameter
      changes e.g. an attack has happened, or a system administrator with
      access to the keys has left the company. An example of this is <xref
      target="RFC5996">IKEv2</xref> but it could be any other new mechanisms
      also.</t>

      <t>As stated earlier <xref target="RFC5925">TCP-AO</xref> and its
      accompanying document <xref target="RFC5926">Crypto Algorithms for
      TCP-AO </xref> suggest that two MAC algorithms that MUST be supported
      are HMAC-SHA-1-96 as specified in <xref target="RFC2104">HMAC</xref> and
      AES-128-CMAC-96 as specified in <xref
      target="NIST-SP800-38B">NIST-SP800-38B</xref>.</t>

      <t>There is a need to protect authenticity and validity of the
      routing/label information that is carried in the payload of the
      sessions. However, that is outside the scope of this document and is
      being addressed by SIDR WG. Similar mechanisms could be used for
      intra-domain protocols.</t>

      <section title="LDP">
        <t>As described in <xref target="RFC5036">LDP</xref>, the threat of
        spoofed Basic Hellos can be reduced by only accepting Basic Hellos on
        interfaces that LSRs trust, employing <xref
        target="RFC5082">GTSM</xref> and ignoring Basic Hellos not addressed
        to the "all routers on this subnet" multicast group. Spoofing attacks
        via Targeted Hellos are potentially a more serious threat. An LSR can
        reduce the threat of spoofed Extended Hellos by filtering them and
        accepting Hellos from sources permitted by an access lists. However,
        performing the filtering using access lists requires LSR resource, and
        the LSR is still vulnerable to the IP source address spoofing.
        Spoofing attacks can be solved by being able to authenticate the Hello
        messages, and an LSR can be configured to only accept Hello messages
        from specific peers when authentication is in use.</t>

        <t><xref target="draft-zheng-mpls-ldp-hello-crypto-auth-04">LDP Hello
        Cryptographic Authentication</xref> suggest a new Cryptographic
        Authentication TLV that can be used as an authentication mechanism to
        secure Hello messages.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="PCEP">
        <t>Path Computation Element (PCE) discovery according to <xref
        target="RFC5440">its RFC</xref> is a significant feature for the
        successful deployment of PCEP in large networks. This mechanism allows
        a Path Computation Client (PCC) to discover the existence of suitable
        PCEs within the network without the necessity of configuration. It
        should be obvious that, where PCEs are discovered and not configured,
        the PCC cannot know the correct key to use. There are different
        approaches to retain some aspect of security, but all of them require
        use of a keys and a keying mechanism, the need for which has been
        discussed above.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Transition and Deployment Considerations">
      <t>As stated in <xref target="RFC6518">KARP Design Guidelines</xref> it
      is imperative that the new authentication and security mechanisms
      defined support incremental deployment, as it is not feasible to deploy
      the new routing protocol authentication mechanism overnight.</t>

      <t>Typically authentication and security in a peer-to-peer protocol
      requires that both parties agree to the mechanisms that will be used. If
      an agreement is not reached the setup of the new mechanism will fail or
      will be deferred. Upon failure, the routing protocols can fallback to
      the mechanisms that were already in place e.g. use static keys if that
      was the mechanism in place. It is usually not possible for one end to
      use the new mechanism while the other end uses the old. Policies can be
      put in place to retry upgrading after a said period of time, so a manual
      coordination is not required.</t>

      <t>If the automatic KMP requires use of public/private keys to exchange
      key material, the required CA root certificates may need to be installed
      to verify authenticity of requests initiated by a peer. Such a step does
      not require coordination with the peer except to decide what CA
      authority will be used.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Security Considerations">
      <t>This section describes security considerations that BGP, LDP, PCEP
      and MSDP should try to meet.</t>

      <t>As with all routing protocols, they need protection from both on-path
      and off-path blind attacks. A better way to protect them would be with
      per-packet protection using a cryptographic MAC. In order to provide for
      the MAC, keys are needed.</t>

      <t>Once keys are used, mechanisms are required to support key rollover.
      This should cover both manual and automatic key rollover. Multiple
      approaches could be used. However since the existing mechanisms provide
      a protocol field to identify the key as well as management mechanisms to
      introduce and retire new keys, focusing on the existing mechanism as a
      starting point is prudent.</t>

      <t>Finally, replay protection is required. The replay mechanism needs to
      be sufficient to prevent an attacker from creating a denial of service
      or disrupting the integrity of the routing protocol by replaying
      packets. It is important that an attacker not be able to disrupt service
      by capturing packets and waiting for replay state to be lost.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>We would like to thank Brian Weis for encouraging us to write this
      draft and to Anantha Ramaiah and Mach Chen for providing comments on
      it.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <reference anchor="draft-ietf-karp-threats-reqs">
        <front>
          <title>KARP Threats and Requirements</title>

          <author fullname="Gregory M. Lebovitz" initials="G"
                  surname="Lebovitz">
            <organization>Juniper Networks, Inc</organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="Manav Bhatia" initials="M" surname="Bhatia">
            <organization>Alcatel-Lucent</organization>

            <address>
              <postal>
                <street></street>

                <city></city>

                <region></region>

                <code></code>

                <country></country>
              </postal>

              <phone></phone>

              <facsimile></facsimile>

              <email></email>

              <uri></uri>
            </address>
          </author>

          <date day="09" month="March" year="2012" />
        </front>
      </reference>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6518'?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2385"?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.5926'?>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.2104'
?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.2119'
?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.2409'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.3547'
?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.3618'?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4271"
?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.4732'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.4948'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.4953'?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5036"
?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.5082'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.5440'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.5925'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.5961'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.5996'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6039'?>

      <reference anchor="draft-ietf-karp-ospf-analysis-03">
        <front>
          <title>Analysis of OSPF Security According to KARP Design
          Guide</title>

          <author fullname="Sam Hartman" initials="S" surname="Hartman">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date day="12" month="March" year="2012" />
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="NIST-SP800-38B">
        <front>
          <title>Recommendation for Block Cipher Modes of Operation: The CMAC
          Mode for Authentication</title>

          <author fullname="Morris Dworking" surname="Dworking">
            <organization>National Institute of Standards and
            Technology</organization>
          </author>

          <date month="May" year="2005" />
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="draft-zheng-mpls-ldp-hello-crypto-auth-04">
        <front>
          <title>LDP Hello Cryptographic Authentication</title>

          <author fullname="Lianshu Zheng" surname="Zheng">
            <organization>Huawei Technologies, Ltd</organization>
          </author>

          <date day="10" month="May" year="2012" />
        </front>
      </reference>
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
