<?xml version='1.0' ?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM 'rfc2629.dtd' [ 
  <!ENTITY rfc2119 SYSTEM "reference.RFC.2119.xml">
]>

<rfc ipr='trust200902' category='info' docName="DOCNAME">

<?rfc toc='yes'?>
<?rfc compact='yes'?>
<?rfc sortrefs='yes'?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>

<front>
  <title abbrev='P2P simulation survey'>Peer-to-peer simulation
  frameworks: a survey</title>

  <author initials="V.K.G." surname="Gurbani" fullname="Vijay K. Gurbani">
    <organization>Bell Labs, Alcatel-Lucent</organization>
    <address>
      <postal>
	<street>1960 Lucent Lane, Rm 9C-533</street>
	<city>Naperville</city> <region>IL</region>
	<code>60563</code>
	<country>USA</country>
      </postal> 
      <email>vkg@bell-labs.com</email>
    </address>
  </author>

  <date year='2011' />
  <area>IRTF</area>
  <workgroup>P2P Research Group</workgroup>
  <keyword>P2P</keyword>
  <keyword>Simulator Framework</keyword>
  <keyword>Simulation</keyword>

  <abstract>
    <t>Peer-to-peer (p2p) protocols, like all distributed protocols,
    are complex, and therefore harder to debug and study in the wild.
    This is more true of existing p2p protocols, where changing the
    behaviour of the protocol --- however minor the change may be ---
    may result in unknown manifestations on the dynamics of the swarm
    using that protocol.  In lieu of the unintended consequences of
    perturbing a live swarm, researchers have resorted to simulation 
    frameworks.  However, simulation results obtained from one simulator
    are often hard to reproduce when using another simulation framework.
    This document surveys existing simulator frameworks prevalent in 
    simulating p2p protocols today in order to quantify any assumptions
    and characteristics inherent in the simulator.  This, we hope, will
    aid future researchers in choosing the right simulation framework 
    for their abstraction.</t>
  </abstract>
</front>

<middle>

  <section title="Introduction" anchor="sec:intro">

   <t>Peer-to-peer (p2p) protocols, like all distributed protocols,
    are complex, and therefore harder to debug and study in the wild.
    This is more true of existing p2p protocols, where changing the
    behaviour of the protocol --- however minor the change may be ---
    may result in unknown manifestations on the dynamics of the swarm
    using that protocol.</t>

    <t>Researchers contemplating on changing the behavior of an existing
    p2p protocol have to be careful still, least they inadvertently 
    do more harm than good by introducing their changes.  Furthermore,
    any changes to an existing p2p protocol or a newly developed p2p
    protocol must be tested and evaluated for validity and reproducibility
    by the research community.  While analytical and mathematical 
    modeling (fluid models, optimization and linear programming) is 
    easily validated, it is harder to validate empirical experiments
    due to the dynamic nature of the networks, hosts, and interconnections
    between them.  Simulation frameworks are attractive since they
    provide a controlled environment under which new behavior of p2p 
    protocols can be studied and quantified.</t>

    <t>The good news is that there is a plethora of simulation frameworks
    for p2p protocols available today, some of them are surveyed in 
    Naicken et al. <xref target="naicken"/>.  However, that survey is
    dated and does not include simulation frameworks like ns-3
    <xref target="ns-3"/> and ProtoPeer <xref target="protopeer"/> that have 
    become available since the survey was published.</t>

    <t>The aim of this document is to update the state-of-art with 
    respect to p2p simulation frameworks available today.  We will
    survey simulator frameworks prevalent --- and actively used ---
    in simulating p2p protocols today in order to quantify any assumptions
    and characteristics inherent in the simulator.  This, we hope, will
    aid future researchers in choosing the right simulation framework 
    for their abstraction.</t>

  </section> <!-- sec:intro -->

  <section title="Terminology">

    <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL
    NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED",  "MAY", and
    "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in
    <xref target="RFC2119">RFC 2119</xref>.</t>

  </section>

  <section anchor="sec:criteria" title="Criteria for evaluating simulation 
           frameworks">

   <t>This is a non-exhaustive list of all criteria that we should
   evaluate when surveying a simulation framework.</t>

   <t><list style="symbols">
    <t>Type of simulator: flow-level, message-level, or packet-
    level.  Advantages and disadvantages of each.</t>
    <t>Does the simulator specifically target p2p networks?  Some
    like ns-3 are general purpose simulators, but p2p models can be
    constructed and evaluated over a general-purpose simulator.</t>
    <t>Level of documentation (APIs, wiki, etc.)</t>
    <t>Support for building models: script level, compiled language, 
    through a visualization editor, etc.</t>
    <t>System limitations imposed by the simulator framework, if any.</t>
    <t>Learning curves associated with the simulator framework.</t>
    <t>Support for trace-driven simulation (i.e., using live traces to inject
    events in the simulator queue.</t>
    <t>Scalability of the simulator.</t>
    <t>Whether or not the simulator framework supports distributed 
    simulations synchronized on a common time source or event queue.</t>
    <t>Support for transitioning from a simulation environment to actual
    system implementation (or, can the code developed for a simulator be 
    used with minimal or no modifications in a real host)? 
    See Galuba et al. <xref target="protopeer"/>.</t>
    <t>Support for modeling link-level (delay, latency, loss, data rate) and 
    host-level characteristics (i.e., simulate both low-level events 
    and application PDUs).</t>
    <t>Support for interfacing real hosts that inject events into 
    the simulator.</t>
    <t>Support for collecting statistics and measurements from 
    the models.</t>
    <t>Visualization tools for creating topologies, viewing the
    simulation in action, etc.</t>
    <t>Support for importing existing topologies (GT-ITM) and others.</t>
    <t>Support for exporting topologies in a standard graph markup
    language.</t>
    <t>Should we focus on only academic and research simulators or
    commercial simulators as well?</t>
    <t>...</t>
   </list></t>
  
  </section> <!-- sec:criteria -->

  <section anchor="sec:simul-frameworks" 
           title="List of simulation frameworks">

   <t>A list of simulation frameworks that we can survey appears
   below (original list is in Naicken et al. <xref target="naicken"/>, I
   have added a couple more simulators).  This is a rather exhaustive list,
   however, going forward, we should focus on those frameworks that are: newer, 
   actively in use today, and those frameworks that are actively used
   today and have been surveyed before, but could stand to be looked 
   at again in light of hardware and software advances in the last 
   few years (multi-cores, parallel programming, etc.):</t>
 
   <t><list style="symbols">
    <t>ns-3 <xref target="ns-3"/>.</t>
    <t>ProtoPeer <xref target="protopeer"/>.</t>
    <t>GPS.</t>
    <t>PeerSim.</t>
    <t>P2PSim.</t>
    <t>OverSim.</t>
    <t>DHTSim.</t>
    <t>PlanetSim.</t>
    <t>VPDNS.</t>
    <t>Narses.</t>
    <t>Neurogrid.</t>
    <t>GnutellaSim.</t>
    <t>myNS --- we could probably drop this in favor of ns-3.</t>
    <t>Overlay Weaver.</t>
    <t>Query-cycle Sim.</t>
    <t>GTNetS <xref target="gtnets"/> --- seems to be abandoned.</t>
    <t>...</t>
   </list></t>

  </section> <!-- sec:simul-frameworks -->

  <section anchor="sec:security" title="Security Considerations">
   
   <t>This document does not introduce any new security considerations
   in p2p protocols.</t>

  </section> <!-- sec:security -->

  <section anchor="sec:iana" title="IANA Considerations">
  
   <t>This document does not require any IANA considerations.</t>

  </section> <!-- sec:iana -->

</middle>

<back>
 <references title='Normative References'>

   &rfc2119;

 </references>

 <references title="Informative References">

  <reference anchor="naicken">
   <front>
    <title>A Survey of Peer-to-Peer Network Simulators</title>
    <author initials="S." surname="Naicken" fullname="Stephen Naicken">
     <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <author initials="A." surname="Basu" fullname="Anirban Basu">
     <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <author initials="B." surname="Livingston" 
            fullname="Barnaby Livingston">
     <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <author initials="S." surname="Rodhetbhai" 
            fullname="Sethalat Rodhetbhai">
     <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <date year="2006"/> 
   </front>
   <seriesInfo name=""
               value="Proceedings of the Seventh Annual Postgraduate Symposium,
                      Liverpool, UK"/>   
  </reference>

  <reference anchor="protopeer">
   <front>
    <title>ProtoPeer: A p2p toolkit bridging the gap between
    simulation and live deployment</title>
    <author initials="W." surname="Galuba" fullname="Wojciech Galuba">
     <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <author initials="K." surname="Aberer" fullname="Karl Aberer">
     <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <author initials="Z." surname="Despotovic" 
            fullname="Zoran Despotovic">
     <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <author initials="W." surname="Kellerer" 
            fullname="Wolfgang Kellerer">
     <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <date year="2009"/> 
   </front>
   <seriesInfo name="" value="Proceedings of SIMUTools, Rome, Italy"/>
  </reference>

  <reference anchor="ns-3">
   <front>
    <title>The ns-3 network simulator</title>
    <author/>
   </front>
   <seriesInfo name="" value="http://www.nsnam.org"/>
  </reference>

  <reference anchor="gtnets">
   <front>
    <title>The Georgia Tech Network Simulator (GTNetS)</title>
    <author/>
   </front>
   <seriesInfo name="" 
               value="http://www.ece.gatech.edu/research/labs/MANIACS/GTNetS/"/>
  </reference>

 </references>

 <section title="Acknowledgments">

 </section> 

</back>

</rfc>
