<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
    <!ENTITY rfc2119 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml'>
    <!ENTITY rfc2560 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2560.xml'>
    <!ENTITY rfc3447 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3447.xml'>
    <!ENTITY rfc4250 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4250.xml'>
    <!ENTITY rfc4251 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4251.xml'>
    <!ENTITY rfc4252 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4252.xml'>
    <!ENTITY rfc4253 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4253.xml'>
    <!ENTITY rfc4432 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4432.xml'>
    <!ENTITY rfc4462 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4462.xml'>
    <!ENTITY rfc5280 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5280.xml'>
    <!ENTITY rfc5480 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5480.xml'>
    <!ENTITY rfc5656 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5656.xml'>
    <!ENTITY rfc5758 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5758.xml'>
    <!ENTITY rfc5759 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5759.xml'>
]>

<rfc category="std" ipr="trust200902" docName="draft-igoe-secsh-x509v3-03">

<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc iprnotified="no" ?>
<?rfc strict="no" ?>

    <front>

		<title abbrev="X.509v3 Certificates for SSH">X.509v3 Certificates for Secure Shell Authentication</title>

		<author initials="K.M." surname="Igoe" fullname="Kevin M. Igoe">
			<organization>National Security Agency</organization>
			<address>
				<postal>
					<street>NSA/CSS Commercial Solutions Center</street>
					<country>United States of America</country>
				</postal>
				<email>kmigoe@nsa.gov</email>
			</address>
		</author>
		<author initials="D." surname="Stebila" fullname="Douglas Stebila">
			<organization>Queensland&nbsp;University&nbsp;of&nbsp;Technology</organization>
			<address>
				<postal>
					<street>Information Security Institute</street>
					<street>Level 7, 126 Margaret St</street>
					<city>Brisbane</city> <region>Queensland</region>
					<code>4000</code>
					<country>Australia</country>
				</postal>
				<email>douglas@stebila.ca</email>
			</address>
		</author>

		<date month="April" day="15" year="2010" />

		<area>Security</area>
		<workgroup>Network Working Group</workgroup>
		<keyword>I-D</keyword>
		<keyword>Internet-Draft</keyword>
		<keyword>X.509v3 Certificates</keyword>
		<keyword>Public Key Authentication</keyword>
		<keyword>Secure Shell (SSH)</keyword>

		<abstract><t>X.509 public key certificates use a signature by a trusted certification authority to bind a given public key to a given digital identity.  This document specifies how to use X.509 version 3 public key certificates in public key algorithms in the Secure Shell protocol.</t></abstract>

    </front>

    <middle>

		<section anchor="intro" title="Introduction">

			<t>There are two Secure Shell (SSH) protocols that use public key cryptography for authentication.  The Transport Layer Protocol, described in <xref target="RFC4253"/>, requires that a digital signature algorithm (called the "public key algorithm") MUST be used to authenticate the server to the client.  Additionally, the User Authentication Protocol described in <xref target="RFC4252"/> allows for the use of a digital signature to authenticate the client to the server ("publickey" authentication).</t>

			<t>In both cases, the validity of the authentication depends upon the strength of the linkage between the public signing key and the identity of the signer.  Digital certificates, such as those in X.509 version 3 (X.509v3) format, use a chain of signatures by a trusted root certification authority and its intermediate certificate authorites to bind a given public signing key to a given digital identity.</t> 

			<t>The following public key authentication algorithms are presently available for use in SSH:</t>

			<texttable>
				<ttcol align="center">Algorithm</ttcol>
				<ttcol align="center">Reference</ttcol>
				<c>ssh-dss</c> <c><xref target="RFC4253" /></c>
				<c>ssh-rsa</c> <c><xref target="RFC4253" /></c>
				<c>pgp-sign-dss</c> <c><xref target="RFC4253" /></c>
				<c>pgp-sign-rsa</c> <c><xref target="RFC4253" /></c>
				<c>ecdsa-sha2-*</c> <c><xref target="RFC5656" /></c>
			</texttable>

			<t>Since PGP has its own method for binding a public key to a digital identity, this document focuses solely upon the non-PGP methods.  In particular, this document defines the following public key algorithms which differ from the above solely in their use of X.509v3 certificates to convey the signer's public key.</t>

			<texttable>
				<ttcol align="center">Algorithm</ttcol>
				<c>x509v3-ssh-dss</c>
				<c>x509v3-ssh-rsa</c>
				<c>x509v3-ecdsa-sha2-*</c>
			</texttable>

			<t>Public keys conveyed using the x509v3-ecdsa-sha2-* public key algorithm can be used with the ecmqv-sha2 key exchange method.</t>

			<t>Implementation of this specification requires familiarity with the Secure Shell protocol <xref target="RFC4251" /> <xref target="RFC4253" /> and X.509v3 certificates <xref target="RFC5280" />.</t>
			
			<t>This document is concerned with SSH implementation details; specification of the underlying cryptographic algorithms and the handling and structure of X.509v3 certificates is left to other standards documents.</t>

			<t>An earlier Internet-Draft for the use of X.509v3 certificates in the Secure Shell was proposed by O. Saarenmaa and J. Galbraith; while this document is informed in part by that Internet-Draft, it does not maintain strict compatibility. (NOTE TO RFC EDITOR: This paragraph should not appear in the final RFC. A note about the previous I-D also appears in the Acknowledgements.)</t>

			<t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED",  "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in RFC 2119 <xref target="RFC2119" />.</t>
			
		</section>

		<section anchor="x509v3" title="X.509 Version 3 Certificates">

			<t>The reader is referred to <xref target="RFC5280" /> for a general description of X.509 version 3 certificates.  For the purposes of this document, it suffices to know that in X.509 a chain or sequence of certificates (possibly of length one) allows a trusted root certificate authority and its intermediate certificate authorities to cryptographically bind a given public key to a given digital identity using public key signatures.</t>

			<t>For all of the public key algorithms specified in this document, the key format consists of a sequence of one or more X.509v3 certificates followed by a sequence of 0 or more Online Certificate Status Protocol (OCSP) responses as in Section 4.2 of <xref target="RFC2560" />.   Providing OCSP responses directly in this data structure can reduce the number of communication rounds required (saving the implementation from needing to perform OCSP checking out-of-band) and can also allow a client outside of a private network to receive OCSP responses from a server behind firewall.  As with any use of OCSP data, implementations SHOULD check that the production time of the OCSP response is acceptable.  It is RECOMMENDED, but not REQUIRED, that implementations reject certificates for which the certificate status is revoked.</t>

			<t>The key format has the following specific encoding:</t>

			<figure>
			<artwork>
  string  "x509v3-ssh-dss" / "x509v3-ssh-rsa" / "x509v3-ecdsa-sha2-*"
  uint32  certificate-count
  string  certificate[1..certificate-count]
  uint32  ocsp-response-count
  string  ocsp-response[0..ocsp-response-count]</artwork>
	 		</figure>
			
			<t>Each certificate and ocsp-response MUST be encoded as a string of octets using the DER encoding of Abstract Syntax Notation One (ASN.1) <xref target="ASN1" />.  An example of an SSH key exchange involving one of these public key algorithms is given in <xref target="example" />.</t>

			<t>Additionally, the following constraints apply:</t>
 
			<t>
			<list style="symbols">
			<t>The sender's certificate MUST be the first certificate and the public key conveyed by this certificate MUST be consistent with the public key algorithm being employed to authenticate the sender.</t>
			<t>Each following certificate MUST certify the one preceding it.</t>
			<t>The self-signed certificate specifying the root authority MAY be omitted.  All other intermediate certificates in the chain leading to a root authority MUST be included.</t>
			<t>To improve the chances that a peer can verify certificate chains and OCSP responses, individual certificates and OCSP responses SHOULD be signed using only signature algorithms corresponding to public key algorithms supported by the peer, as indicated in the server_host_key_algorithms field of the SSH_MSG_KEXINIT packet (see Section 7.1 of <xref target="RFC4253" />).  However, other algorithms MAY be used.  The choice of signature algorithm used by any given certificate or OCSP response is independent of the signature algorithms chosen by other elements in the chain.</t>
			<t>Verifiers MUST be prepared to receive certificate chains and OCSP responses that use algorithms not listed in the server_host_key_algorithms field of the SSH_MSG_KEXINIT packet, including algorithms which potentially have no Secure Shell equivalent.  However, peers sending such chains should recognize that such chains are more likely to be unverifiable than chains which use only algorithms listed in the server_host_key_algorithms field.</t>
			<t>There is no requirement on the ordering or number of OCSP responses.</t>
			</list>
			</t>

			<t>Upon receipt of a certificate chain, implementations MUST verify the certificate chain according to Section 6.1 of <xref target="RFC5280" /> based on a root of trust configured by the system administrator or user.</t>
 
			<t>Issues associated with the use of certificates (such as expiration of certificates and revocation of compromised certificates) are addressed in <xref target="RFC5280" /> and are outside the scope of this document.  However, compliant implementations MUST comply with <xref target="RFC5280" />.  Implementations providing and processing OCSP responses MUST comply with <xref target="RFC2560" />.</t>
 
			<t><xref target="RFC5480" /> and <xref target="RFC5758" /> describes the structure of X.509v3 certificates to be used with ECDSA public keys.  <xref target="RFC5280" /> describes the structure of X.509v3 certificates to be used with RSA and DSA public keys.  <xref target="RFC5759" /> provides additional guidance for ECDSA keys in Suite B X.509v3 certificate and certificate revocation list profiles.</t>

			<section anchor="x509v3-ext" title="Certificate Extensions">

				<section anchor="x509v3-ext-ku" title="KeyUsage">

					<t>The KeyUsage extension MAY be used to restrict a certificate's use.  In accordance with Section 4.2.1.3 of <xref target="RFC5280" />, if the KeyUsage extension is present, then the certificate MUST be used only for one of the purposes indicated.  There are two relevant keyUsage identifiers for the certificate corresponding to the public key algorithm in use:</t>
					<t>
					<list style="symbols">
					<t>The digitalSignature KeyUsage identifier MAY be used with certificates for x509v3-ssh-dss, x509v3-ssh-rsa, and x509v3-ecdsa-sha2-* public key algorithms.</t>
					<t>The keyAgreement KeyUsage identifier MAY be used for certificates with convey keys for use with the ecmqv-sha2 key exchange method.</t>
					</list>
					</t>

					<t>For the remaining certificates in the certificate chain, implementations MUST comply with existing conventions on KeyUsage identifiers and certificates as in Section 4.2.1.3 on <xref target="RFC5280" />.</t>
					
				</section>

				<section anchor="x509v3-ext-eku" title="ExtendedKeyUsage">

					<t>This document defines two ExtendedKeyUsage key purpose IDs that MAY be used to restrict a certificate's use: id-kp-secureShellClient, which indicates that the key can be used for a Secure Shell client, and id-kp-secureShellServer, which indicates that the key can be used for a Secure Shell server.  In accordance with Section 4.2.1.12 of <xref target="RFC5280" />, if the ExtendedKeyUsage extension is present, then the certificate MUST be used only for one of the purposes indicated.  The object identifiers of the two key purpose IDs defined in this document are as follows:</t>

					<t>
					<list style="symbols">
					<t>id-pkix OBJECT IDENTIFIER ::= { iso(1) identified-organization(3) dod(6) internet(1) security(5) mechanisms(5) pkix(7) }</t>
					<t>id-kp   OBJECT IDENTIFIER ::= { id-pkix 3 }    -- extended key purpose identifiers</t>
					<t>id-kp-secureShellClient        OBJECT IDENTIFIER ::= { id-kp 21 }</t>
					<t>id-kp-secureShellServer        OBJECT IDENTIFIER ::= { id-kp 22 }</t>
					</list>
					</t>

				</section>

			</section>

		</section>

		<section anchor="sigencoding" title="Signature Encoding">

			<t>Signing and verifying using the X.509v3-based public key algorithms specified in this document (x509v3-ssh-dss, x509v3-ssh-rsa, x509v3-ecdsa-sha2-*) is done in the analogous way for the corresponding non-X.509v3-based public key algorithms (ssh-dss, ssh-rsa, ecdsa-sha2-*, respectively).  For concreteness, we specify this explicitly below.</t>

			<section anchor="sigencoding-dss" title="x509v3-ssh-dss">

				<t>Signing and verifying using the x509v3-ssh-dss key format is done according to the Digital Signature Standard <xref target="FIPS-186-3" /> using the SHA-1 hash <xref target="FIPS-180-2" />.</t>

				<t>The resulting signature is encoded as follows:</t>
				<figure>
				<artwork>
  string  "ssh-dss"
  string  dss_signature_blob</artwork>
				</figure>

				<t>The value for dss_signature_blob is encoded as a string containing r, followed by s (which are fixed-length 160-bit integers, without lengths or padding, unsigned, and in network byte order).</t>

				<t>This format is the same as for ssh-dss signatures in Section 6.6 of <xref target="RFC4253" />.</t>

			</section>

			<section anchor="sigencoding-rsa" title="x509v3-ssh-rsa">

				<t>Signing and verifying using the x509v3-ssh-rsa key format is performed according to the RSASSA-PKCS1-v1_5 scheme in <xref target="RFC3447" /> using the SHA-1 hash <xref target="FIPS-180-2" />.</t>

				<t>The resulting signature is encoded as follows:</t>
				<figure>
				<artwork>
  string  "ssh-rsa"
  string  rsa_signature_blob</artwork>
				</figure>

				<t>The value for rsa_signature_blob is encoded as a string containing s (which is an integer, without lengths or padding, unsigned, and in network byte order).</t>

				<t>This format is the same as for ssh-rsa signatures in Section 6.6 of <xref target="RFC4253" />.</t>

			</section>

			<section anchor="sigencoding-ecdsa" title="x509v3-ecdsa-sha2-*">

				<t>Signing and verifying using the x509v3-ecdsa-sha2-* key formats is performed according to the ECDSA algorithm in <xref target="FIPS-186-3" /> using the SHA2 hash function family <xref target="FIPS-180-3" />.  The choice of hash function from the SHA2 hash function family is based on the key size of the ECDSA key as specified in Section 6.2.1 of <xref target="RFC5656" />.</t>

				<t>The resulting signature is encoded as follows:</t>
				<figure>
				<artwork>
  string  "ecdsa-sha2-[identifier]"
  string  ecdsa_signature_blob</artwork>
				</figure>

				<t>The string [identifier] is the identifier of the elliptic curve domain parameters. The format of this string is specified in Section 6.1 of <xref target="RFC5656" />.</t>

				<t>The ecdsa_signature_blob value has the following specific encoding:</t>
				<figure>
				<artwork>
  mpint   r
  mpint   s</artwork>
				</figure>

				<t>The integers r and s are the output of the ECDSA algorithm.</t>

				<t>This format is the same as for ecdsa-sha2-* signatures in Section 3.1.2 of <xref target="RFC5656" />.</t>

			</section>

		</section>

		<section anchor="publickey" title="Use in public key algorithms">

			<t>The public key algorithms and encodings defined in this document SHOULD be accepted anyplace in the Secure Shell protocol suite where public keys are used, including, but not limited to, the following protocol messages for server authentication and user authentication:</t>

			<t>
			<list style="symbols">
			<t>in the SSH_MSG_USERAUTH_REQUEST message when "publickey" authentication is used <xref target="RFC4252" /></t>
			<t>in the SSH_MSG_USERAUTH_REQUEST message when "hostbased" authentication is used <xref target="RFC4252" /></t>
			<t>in the SSH_MSG_KEXDH_REPLY message <xref target="RFC4253" /></t>
			<t>in the SSH_MSG_KEXRSA_PUBKEY message <xref target="RFC4432" /></t>
			<t>in the SSH_MSG_KEXGSS_HOSTKEY message <xref target="RFC4462" /></t>
			<t>in the SSH_MSG_KEX_ECDH_REPLY message <xref target="RFC5656" /></t>
			<t>in the SSH_MSG_KEX_ECMQV_REPLY message <xref target="RFC5656" /></t>
			</list>
			</t>
			
			<t>When a public key from this specification is included in the input to a hash algorithm, the exact bytes that are transmitted on the wire must be used as input to the hash functions.  In particular, implementations MUST NOT omit any of the chain certificates or OCSP responses that were included on the wire, nor change encoding of the certificate or OCSP data.  Otherwise hashes that are meant to be computed in parallel by both peers will have differing values.</t>

			<t>For the purposes of server authentication, the mapping between certificates and host names is left as an implementation and configuration issue for implementers and system administrators.</t>

			<t>For the purposes of user authentication, the mapping between certificates and user names is left as an implementation and configuration issue for implementers and system administrators.</t>

		</section>

		<section anchor="security" title="Security Considerations">

			<t>This document provides new public key algorithms for the Secure Shell protocol that convey public keys using X.509v3 certificates.  For the most part, the security considerations involved in using the Secure Shell protocol apply, since all of the public key algorithms introduced in this document are based on existing algorithms in the Secure Shell protocol.  However, implementers should be aware of security considerations specific to the use of X.509v3 certificates in a public key infrastructure, including considerations related to expired certificates and certificate revocation lists.</t>

			<t>The reader is directed to the security considerations sections of <xref target="RFC5280" /> for the use of X.509v3 certificates, <xref target="RFC2560" /> for the use of OCSP response, <xref target="RFC4253" /> for server authentication, and <xref target="RFC4252" /> for user authentication.  The use of revoked certificates, while not RECOMMENDED, is allowed; as certificates may be revoked for a variety of reasons -- including the compromise of the private key or the issuance of a certificate to a wrong party -- authentication properties may not longer hold when revoked certificates are not rejected.</t>

		</section>

		<section anchor="iana" title="IANA Considerations">

			<t>Consistent with Section 8 of <xref target="RFC4251" /> and Section 4.6 of <xref target="RFC4250" />, this document makes the following registrations:</t>

			<t>In the Public Key Algorithm Names registry:</t>
			
			<t>
			<list style="symbols">
			<t>The SSH public key algorithm "x509v3-ssh-dss".</t>
			<t>The SSH public key algorithm "x509v3-ssh-rsa".</t>
			<t>The family of SSH public key algorithm names beginning with "x509v3-ecdsa-sha2-" and not containing the at-sign ('@').</t>
			</list>
			</t>

			<t>This document creates no new registries.</t>

			<t>The two object identifiers used in <xref target="x509v3-ext-eku" /> were assigned from an arc delegated by IANA to the PKIX Working Group. No further action by IANA is necessary for this document.</t>

		</section>

    </middle>

    <back>

		<references title="Normative References">

			<reference anchor="ASN1">
				<front>
					<title>Abstract Syntax Notation One (ASN.1): Specification of basic notation</title>
					<author>
						<organization>International Telecommunications Union</organization>
					</author>
					<date month="July" year="2002" />
				</front>
				<seriesInfo name="" value="X.680" />
			</reference>

			<reference anchor="FIPS-180-2">
				<front>
					<title>Secure Hash Standard</title>
					<author>
						<organization>National Institute of Standards and Technology</organization>
					</author>
					<date month="August" year="2002" />
				</front>
				<seriesInfo name="FIPS" value="180-2" />
			</reference>

			<reference anchor="FIPS-180-3">
				<front>
					<title>Secure Hash Standard</title>
					<author>
						<organization>National Institute of Standards and Technology</organization>
					</author>
					<date month="October" year="2008" />
				</front>
				<seriesInfo name="FIPS" value="180-3" />
			</reference>

			<reference anchor="FIPS-186-3">
				<front>
					<title>Digital Signature Standard (DSS)</title>
					<author>
						<organization>National Institute of Standards and Technology</organization>
					</author>
					<date month="June" year="2009" />
				</front>
				<seriesInfo name="FIPS" value="186-3" />
			</reference>

			&rfc2119;
			&rfc2560;
			&rfc3447;
			&rfc4250;
			&rfc4251;
			&rfc4252;
			&rfc4253;
			&rfc5280;
			&rfc5480;
			&rfc5656;
			&rfc5758;

		</references>

		<references title="Informative References">

			&rfc4432;
			&rfc4462;
			&rfc5759;

		</references>

		<section anchor="example" title="Example">

			<t>The following example illustrates the use of an X.509v3 certificate for a public key for the Digital Signature Algorithm when used in a Diffie-Hellman key exchange method.  In the example, there is a chain of certificates of length 2, and a single OCSP response is provided.</t>
			
			<figure>
			<artwork>
  byte    SSH_MSG_KEXDH_REPLY
  string  0x00 0x00 0xXX 0xXX  -- length of the remaining data in this string
          0x00 0x00 0x00 0x0D  -- length of string "x509v3-ssh-dss"
          "x509v3-ssh-dss"
          0x00 0x00 0x00 0x02  -- there are 2 certificates
          0x00 0x00 0xXX 0xXX  -- length of sender certificate
          DER-encoded sender certificate
          0x00 0x00 0xXX 0xXX  -- length of issuer certificate
          DER-encoded issuer certificate
          0x00 0x00 0x00 0x01  -- there is 1 OCSP response
          0x00 0x00 0xXX 0xXX  -- length of OCSP response
          DER-encoded OCSP response
  mpint   f
  string  signature of H</artwork>
			</figure>

		</section>

		<section anchor="ack" title="Acknowledgements">

			<t>The authors acknowledge helpful comments from Joseph Galbraith, Jeffrey Hutzelman, Jan Pechanec, Sean Turner, and Nicolas Williams.</t>

			<t>O. Saarenmaa and J. Galbraith previously prepared an Internet-Draft on a similar topic.</t>

		</section>

    </back>

</rfc>
