<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="no"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<rfc category="std" docName="draft-williams-avtcore-clksrc-00"
     ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="RTP Clock Source Signalling">RTP Clock Source
    Signalling</title>

    <author fullname="Aidan Williams" initials="A.M." surname="Williams">
      <organization>Audinate</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Level 1, 458 Wattle St</street>

          <city>Ultimo</city>

          <code>2007</code>

          <region>NSW</region>

          <country>Australia</country>
        </postal>

        <phone>+61 2 8090 1000</phone>

        <facsimile>+61 2 8090 1001</facsimile>

        <email>aidan.williams@audinate.com</email>

        <uri>http://www.audinate.com/</uri>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Ray van Brandenburg" initials="R."
            surname="van Brandenburg">
      <organization>TNO</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Brassersplein 2</street>

          <city>Delft</city>

          <region></region>

          <code></code>

          <country>The Netherlands</country>
        </postal>

        <phone>+31 88 86 63609</phone>

        <facsimile></facsimile>

        <email>ray.vanbrandenburg@tno.nl</email>

        <uri></uri>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Kevin Gross" initials="K." surname="Gross">
      <organization>AVA Networks</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>

          <city></city>

          <region></region>

          <code></code>

          <country></country>
        </postal>

        <phone></phone>

        <facsimile></facsimile>

        <email></email>

        <uri></uri>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date day="28" month="February" year="2012" />

    <area>Real-time Applications and Infrastructure</area>

    <workgroup>Audio/Video Transport Core Maintenance</workgroup>

    <keyword>Clock</keyword>

    <keyword>Source</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>NTP timestamps are used by several RTP protocols for synchronisation
      and statistical measurement. This memo specificies SDP signalling
      identifying NTP timestamp clock sources and SDP signalling identifying
      the media clock sources in a multimedia session.</t>
    </abstract>

    <note title="Requirements Language">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
      document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
      target="RFC2119">RFC 2119</xref>.</t>
    </note>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>RTP protocols use NTP format timestamps to facilitate media stream
      synchronisation and for providing estimates of round trip time (RTT) and
      other statistical parameters.</t>

      <t>Information about media clock timing exchanged in NTP format
      timestamps may come from a clock which is synchronised to a global time
      reference, but this cannot be assumed nor is there a standardised
      mechanism available to indicate that timestamps are derived from a
      common reference clock. Therefore, RTP implementations typically assume
      that NTP timestamps are taken using unsynchronised clocks and must
      compensate for absolute time differences and rate differences. Without a
      shared reference clock, RTP can time align flows from the same source at
      a given receiver using relative timing, however tight synchronisation
      between two or more different receivers (possibly with different network
      paths) or between two or more senders is not possible.</t>

      <t>High performance AV systems often use a reference media clock
      distributed to all devices in the system. The reference media clock is
      often distinct from the the reference clock used to provide timestamps.
      A reference media clock may be provided along with a audio or video
      signal interface, or via a dedicated clock signal (e.g. <eref
      target="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Genlock">genlock</eref> or <eref
      target="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Word_clock">audio word
      clock</eref>. If sending and receiving media clocks are known to be
      synchronised to a common reference clock, performance can improved by
      minimising buffering and avoiding rate conversion.</t>

      <t>This specification defines SDP signalling of timestamp clock sources
      and media reference clock sources.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Applications">
      <t>Timestamp clock source and reference media clock signalling benefit
      applications requiring synchronised media capture or playout and low
      latency operation.</t>

      <t>Exmaples include, but are not limited to:</t>

      <t><list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="Social TV"><xref target="I-D.ietf-avtcore-idms">RTCP
          for inter-destination media synchronization</xref> defines social TV
          as the combination of media content consumption by two or more users
          at different devices and locations and real-time communication
          between those users. An example of Social TV, is when two or more
          users are watching the same television broadcast at different
          devices and locations, while communicating with each other using
          text, audio and/or video. A skew in the media play-out of the two or
          more users can have adverse effects on their experience. A
          well-known use case here is one friend experiencing a goal in a
          football match well before or after other friend(s).</t>

          <t hangText="Video Walls">A video wall consists of multiple computer
          monitors, video projectors, or television sets tiled together
          contiguously or overlapped in order to form one large screen. Each
          of the screens reproduces a portion of the larger picture. In some
          implementations, each screen may be individually connected to the
          network and receive its portion of the overall image from a
          network-connected video server or video scaler. Screens are
          refreshed at 60 hertz (every 16-2/3 milliseconds) or potentially
          faster. If the refresh is not synchronized, the effect of multiple
          screens acting as one is broken.</t>

          <t hangText="Netwoked Audio">Networked loudspeakers, amplifiers and
          analogue I/O devices transmitting or receiving audio signals via RTP
          can be connected to various parts of a building or campus network.
          Such situations can for example be found in large conference rooms,
          legislative chambers, classrooms (especially those supporting
          distance learning) and other large-scale environments such as
          stadiums. Since humans are more susceptible to differences in audio
          delay, this use case needs even more accuracy than the video wall
          use case. Depending on the exact application, the need for accuracy
          can then be <eref
          target="http://www.ieee802.org/1/files/public/docs2007/as-dolsen-time-accuracy-0407.pdf">in
          the range of microseconds</eref>.</t>

          <t hangText="Sensor Arrays">Sensor arrays contain many synchronised
          measurement elements producing signals which are then combined to
          form an overall measurement. Accurate capture of the phase
          relationships between the various signals arriving at each element
          of the array is critically important for proper operation. Examples
          include towed or fixed sonar arrays, seismic arrays and phased
          arrays.</t>
        </list></t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="definitions" title="Definitions">
      <t>The definitions of streams, sources and levels of information in SDP
      descriptions follow the definitions found in <xref
      target="RFC5576">Source-Specific Media Attributes in the Session
      Description Protocol (SDP)</xref>.<list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="multimedia session">A set of multimedia senders and
          receivers as well as the data streams flowing from senders to
          receivers. The <xref target="RFC4566">Session Description Protocol
          (SDP)</xref> describes multimedia sessions.</t>

          <t hangText="media stream">An RTP session potentially containing
          more than one RTP source. SDP media descriptions beginning with an
          "m"-line define the parameters of a media stream.</t>

          <t hangText="media source">A media source is single stream of RTP
          packets, identified by an RTP SSRC.</t>

          <t hangText="session-level">Session-level information applies to an
          entire multimedia session. In an SDP description, session-level
          information appears before the first "m"-line.</t>

          <t hangText="media-level">Media-level information applies to a
          single media stream (RTP session). In an SDP description,
          media-level information appears after each "m"-line.</t>

          <t hangText="source-level">Source-level information applies to a
          single stream of RTP packets, identified by an RTP SSRC <xref
          target="RFC5576">Source-Specific Media Attributes in the Session
          Description Protocol (SDP)</xref> defines how source-level
          information is included into an SDP session description.</t>

          <t hangText="traceable time">A clock is considered to provide
          traceable time if it can be proven to be synchronised to a global
          time reference. GPS XXX is commonly used to provide a traceable time
          reference. Some network time synchronisation protocols (e.g. XXX
          PTP) can explicitly indicate that the master clock is providing a
          traceable time reference over the network.</t>
        </list></t>
    </section>

    <section title="Timestamp Reference Clock Source Signalling">
      <t>The NTP timestamps used by RTP are taking by reading a local clock at
      the sender or receiver. This local clock may be synchronised to another
      clock (time source) by some means or it may be unsynchronised. A variety
      of methods are available to synchronise local clocks to a reference time
      source, including network time protocols (e.g. <xref
      target="RFC5905">NTP</xref>) and radio clocks like GPS [XXX].</t>

      <t>The following sections describe and define SDP signalling indicating
      whether and how the local timestamping clock in an RTP sender/receiver
      is synchronised to a reference clock.</t>

      <section title="Equivalent Timestamp Clocks">
        <t>Two or more local clocks that are sufficiently synchronised will
        produce timestamps for a given event which are effectively identical
        for the purposes of RTP. A local clock in one RTP sender/receiver can
        be considered equivalent to a local clock in another RTP
        sender/receiver providing they are sufficiently synchronised such that
        timestamps produced by one clock are indistinguishable from timestamps
        produced by the other. The timestamps produced by equivalent local
        clocks in two or more RTP senders/receivers receivers can be directly
        compared.</t>

        <t>One or more local clocks are equivalent if they are synchronised to
        a single master clock via a network time protocol (e.g. XXX NTP,
        802.1AS, IEEE1588v2).</t>

        <t>One or more local clocks are equivalent if they are synchronised to
        any member of a set of master clocks provided that the set of master
        clocks are synchronised.</t>

        <t>One or more local clocks are equivalent if they are synchronised to
        a clock master providing a global time reference (e.g. XXX GPS,
        Gallileo). Some network time protocols (e.g. XXX PTP) may allow master
        clocks to explicitly indicate that they are "traceable" back to a
        global time reference.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Identifying NTP Reference Clocks">
        <t>A single NTP server is identified by identified by hostname (or IP
        address) and an optional port number. If the port number is not
        indicated, it is assumed to be the standard NTP port (123) XXX.</t>

        <t>Two or more NTP servers may be listed to indicate that they are
        interchangeable. RTP senders/receivers can use any of the listed NTP
        servers to govern a local clock that is equivalent to a local clock
        slaved to a difference server.</t>

        <t>XXX Question: Does NTP carry traceability information? Or is this
        implicit somehow in the stratum? Apparently there are some bits in the
        leap seconds functionality which talk about "tracking"..</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Identifying PTP Reference Clocks">
        <t>The IEEE1588 Precision Time Protocol (PTP) family of clock
        synchronisation protocols provide a shared reference clock in an
        network - typically a LAN. IEEE1588 provides sub-microsecond
        synchronisation between devices on a LAN and typically locks within
        seconds at startup. With support from Ethernet switches, IEEE1588
        protocols can achieve nanosecond timing accuracy in LANs. Network
        interface chips and cards supporting hardware time-stamping of timing
        critical protocol messages are also available.</t>

        <t>When using IEEE1588 clock synchronisation, networked AV systems can
        achieve sub 1 microsecond time alignment accuracy when rendering AV
        signals and can support latencies less than 1ms through a gigabit
        LAN.</t>

        <t>Three flavours of IEEE1588 are in use today:<list style="symbols">
            <t><xref target="IEEE1588-2002">IEEE 1588-2002</xref>: the
            original "Standard for a Precision Clock Synchronization Protocol
            for Networked Measurement and Control Systems". This is often
            called IEEE1588v1 or PTPv1.</t>

            <t><xref target="IEEE1588-2008">IEEE 1588-2008</xref>: the second
            version of the "Standard for a Precision Clock Synchronization
            Protocol for Networked Measurement and Control Systems". This is a
            revised version of the original IEEE1588-2002 standard and is
            often called IEEE1588v2 or PTPv2.</t>

            <t><xref target="IEEE802.1AS-2011">IEEE 802.1AS</xref>: "Timing
            and Synchronization for Time Sensitive Applications in Bridged
            Local Area Networks". This is a Layer-2 only profile of IEEE
            1588-2008 for use in Audio/Video Bridged LANs.</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>Each IEEE1588 clock is identified by a globally unique EUI-64
        called a "ClockIdentity". A slave clock using one of the IEEE1588
        family of network time protocols acquires the ClockIdentity/EUI-64 of
        the grandmaster clock that is the ultimate source of timing
        information. A master clock which is itself slaved to another master
        clock passes the grand master clock identity through to its
        slaves.</t>

        <t>Several instances of the IEEE1588v1/v2 protocol may operate
        independently on a single network, forming distinct PTP network
        protocol domains each of which may have a different master clock. As
        the IEEE1588 standards have developed, the definition of PTP domains
        has changed. IEEE1588v1 identifies protocol subdomains by a textual
        name and IEEE1588v2 identifies protocol domains using a numeric domain
        number. 802.1AS is a Layer2 profile of IEEE1588v2 supporting a single
        numeric clock domain (0). This specification assumes that an IEEE1588
        clock master for multiple domains will provide the same timing
        information to all domains or that each clock domain has a different
        master. In other words, this specification assumes that a timing
        domain can be uniquely identified using the ClockIdentity of the
        grandmaster clock alone.</t>

        <t>The PTP family of protocols employ a distributed election protocol
        called the "Best Master Clock Algorithm (BMCA) to determine the active
        clock master. The clock master choices available to BMCA can be
        restricted or favourably biased by setting stratum values, preffered
        master clock bits, or other parameters to influence the election
        process. In some systems it may be desirable to limit the number of
        possible PTP clock masters to avoid re-signalling timestamp clock
        sources when the clock master changes.</t>

        <!--### what about transition from master->backup master clock?
Is the backup master identify known by all devices in the network?
If so, signalling can provide both the primary and backup master gmIds

### New clock gmID can be re-signalled without tearing down the stream if using SIP.
If not capable of re-signalling, should specify all possible gmIDs.
Might want to make use of the preferred master mechanism,
or stratum to limit the number of candidate master clocks.

### Can phase continuity during master->backup master be relied upon?
What about with 802.1AS? Recall some discussion that time would be
allowed to step.. hence the "uncertain" stuff.

### See Kevin's comments. Use multiple gmIds, just like multiple IP addresses are used for NTP servers.
Discovering them would not be part of this specification.
There are manual configuration methods which can also be used - preferred master, stratum, etc
to limit the potential gms to a smaller list.

### General issue about re-signalling.
Change of clock master for a sender could happily be re-signalled.
If the media packets had the "timestamp uncertain" bit set,
then the receiver would know not to update NTP->rtp timestamp
information from the incoming timestamps until clocks had settled
and resignalling had occurred.
-->
      </section>

      <section title="Identifying Global Reference Clocks">
        <t>Global reference clocks provide a source of tracable time,
        typically via a hardware radio receiver interface. Examples include
        GPS and Gallileo. Apart from the name of the reference clock system,
        no further identification is required.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Other Reference Clocks">
        <t>At the time of writing, it is common for RTP senders/receivers not
        to synchronise their local timestamp clock to a master. An
        unsynchronised clock such as a quartz oscillator is identified as a
        "local" reference clock.</t>

        <t>In some systems, all RTP senders/receivers may use a timetsamp
        clock synchronised to a reference clock that is not provided by one of
        the methods listed above. Examples may include the reference time
        information provided by digital television or cellular services. These
        sources are identified as "private" reference clocks. All RTP
        senders/receivers in a session using a private reference clock are
        assumed to have a mechanism outside this specification confirming that
        their local timestamp clocks are equivalent.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Traceable Reference Clocks">
        <t>A timestamp clock source may be labelled "traceable" if it is known
        to be sourced from a global time reference such as TAI or UTC XXX.
        Providing adjustments are made for differing time bases, timestamps
        taken using a clocks synchronised to a traceable time source can be
        directly compared even if the clocks are synchronised to different
        servers or via different mechanisms. Any traceable timestamp clock
        source can be considered equivalent to another traceable timestamp
        clock source and the timestamps may be directly compared.</t>

        <t>Since any NTP or PTP server providing traceable time can be
        considered equivalent, it is not necessary to identify traceable time
        servers by protocol address.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Synchronisation Confidence">
        <t>Network time protocols periodically exchange timestamped messages
        between servers and clients. Assuming RTP sender/receiver clocks are
        based on commonly available quartz crystal hardware, tight
        synchronisation requires frequent exchange of synchronisation
        messages.</t>

        <t>Unfortunately, in some implementations, it is not possible to
        control the frequency of synchronisation messages nor is it possible
        to discover when the last sychronisation message occured. In order to
        provide a measure of confidence that the timestamp clock is
        sufficiently synchronised, an optional timestamp may be included in
        the SDP clock source signalling. In addition, the frequency of
        synchronisation message may also optionally be provided.</t>

        <t>The optional timestamp and synchronisation frequency parameters
        provide an indication of synchronisation quality to the receiver of
        those parameters. If the synchronisation confidence timestamp is far
        from the timestamp clock at the receiver of the parameters, it can be
        assumed that synchronisation has not occured recently or the timestamp
        reference clock source is wrongly configured or cannot be contacted.
        In this case, the receiver can take action to prevent unsynchronised
        playout or may fall back to assuming that the timestamp clocks are not
        synchronised.</t>

        <t>Synchronisation frequency is expressed as an <eref
        target="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Signed_number_representations#Excess-K">8-bit
        excess-127 field</eref> which is the base 2 logarithm of the frequency
        in HZ. The synchronisation frequencies represented by this field range
        from 2^-127 Hz to 2^+128 Hz. The field value of 127 corresponds to an
        update frequency of 1 Hz.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="SDP Signalling of Timestamp Clock Source">
        <t>Specification of the timestamp reference clock source may at all
        levels of an SDP description (see <xref target="definitions">level
        definitions</xref> earlier in this document for more information).</t>

        <t>Timestamp clock source signalling included at session-level
        provides default parameters for all RTP sessions and sources in the
        session description. More specific signalling included at the
        media-level overrides default session-level signalling. Further,
        source-level signalling overrides timestamp clock source signalling at
        the enclosing media-level and session-level.</t>

        <t>If timestamp clock source signalling is included anywhere in an SDP
        description, it must be properly defined for all levels in the
        description. This may simply be achieved by providing default
        signalling at the session level.</t>

        <t>Timestamp reference clock parameters may be repeated at a given
        level (i.e. for a session or source) to provide information about
        additional servers or clock sources. If the attribute is repeated at a
        given level, all clocks described at that level are assumed to be
        equivalent. Traceable clock sources MUST NOT be mixed with clock
        sources having explicit addresses for a given source or session.
        Unless synchronisation confidence information is available for each of
        the reference clocks listed at a given level, it SHOULD only be
        included with the first reference clock source attribute at that
        level.</t>

        <t>Note that clock source parameters may change from time to time, for
        example, as a result of a PTP clock master election. The SIP XXX
        protocol supports re-signalling of updated SDP information, however
        other protocols may require additional notification mechanisms.</t>

        <figure align="center" anchor="ebnf-ts-refclk"
                title="Timestamp Reference Clock Source Signalling">
          <artwork><![CDATA[
timestamp-refclk = "a=ts-refclk:" clksrc SP [sync-confidence] CRLF

clksrc = ntp / ptp / gps / gal / local / private

ntp             =  "ntp=" ntp-server-addr
ntp-server-addr =  host [ ":" port ]
ntp-server-addr =/ "traceable" )

ptp             =  "ptp=" ptp-version ":" ptp-gmid
ptp-version     =  "IEEE1588-2002"
ptp-version     =/ "IEEE1588-2008"
ptp-version     =/ "IEEE802.1AS-2011"
ptp-gmid        =  EUI64
ptp-gmid        =/ "traceable"

gps      =  "gps"
gal      =  "gal"
local    =  "local"
private  =  "private" [ ":" "traceable" ]


sync-confidence = sync-timestamp [SP sync-frequency]

sync-timestamp  = sync-date SP sync-time SP sync-UTCoffset

sync-date       = 4DIGIT "-" 2DIGIT "-" 2DIGIT
                  ; yyyy-mm-dd (e.g., 1982-12-02)

sync-time       = 2DIGIT ":" 2DIGIT ":" 2DIGIT "." 3DIGIT
                  ; 00:00:00.000 - 23:59:59.999

sync-UTCoffset  = ( "+" / "-" ) 2DIGIT ":" 2DIGIT
                  ; +HH:MM or -HH:MM

sync-frequency  = 2HEXDIG
                  ; If N is the field value, HZ=2^(N-127)


host          = hostname / IPv4address / IPv6reference

hostname      =  *( domainlabel "." ) toplabel [ "." ]
toplabel      =  ALPHA / ALPHA *( alphanum / "-" ) alphanum
domainlabel   =  alphanum
              =/ alphanum *( alphanum / "-" ) alphanum

IPv4address   =  1*3DIGIT "." 1*3DIGIT "." 1*3DIGIT "." 1*3DIGIT
IPv6reference =  "[" IPv6address "]"
IPv6address   =  hexpart [ ":" IPv4address ]
hexpart       =  hexseq / hexseq "::" [ hexseq ] / "::" [ hexseq ]
hexseq        =  hex4 *( ":" hex4)
hex4          =  1*4HEXDIG

port = 1*DIGIT

EUI-64 = 7(HEXDIG "-") 2HEXDIG

]]></artwork>
        </figure>

        <section title="Examples">
          <t><xref target="example-session-level"></xref> shows an example SDP
          description with a timestamp reference clock source defined at the
          session-level.</t>

          <figure align="center" anchor="example-session-level"
                  title="Timestamp reference clock defintion at the session level">
            <artwork><![CDATA[
v=0
o=jdoe 2890844526 2890842807 IN IP4 10.47.16.5
s=SDP Seminar
i=A Seminar on the session description protocol
u=http://www.example.com/seminars/sdp.pdf
e=j.doe@example.com (Jane Doe)
c=IN IP4 224.2.17.12/127
t=2873397496 2873404696
a=recvonly
a=ts-refclk:ntp=traceable
m=audio 49170 RTP/AVP 0
m=video 51372 RTP/AVP 99
a=rtpmap:99 h263-1998/90000
]]></artwork>
          </figure>

          <t></t>

          <t><xref target="example-media-level"></xref> shows an example SDP
          description with timestamp reference clock definitions at the
          media-level overriding the session-level defaults. Note that the
          synchronisation confidence timestamp appears on the first attribute
          at the media-level only.</t>

          <figure align="center" anchor="example-media-level"
                  title="Timestamp reference clock definition at the media-level">
            <artwork><![CDATA[
v=0
o=jdoe 2890844526 2890842807 IN IP4 10.47.16.5
s=SDP Seminar
i=A Seminar on the session description protocol
u=http://www.example.com/seminars/sdp.pdf
e=j.doe@example.com (Jane Doe)
c=IN IP4 224.2.17.12/127
t=2873397496 2873404696
a=recvonly
a=ts-refclk:local
m=audio 49170 RTP/AVP 0
a=ts-refclk:ntp=203.0.113.10 2011-02-19 21:03:20.345+01:00
a=ts-refclk:ntp=198.51.100.22
m=video 51372 RTP/AVP 99
a=rtpmap:99 h263-1998/90000
a=ts-refclk:ptp=IEEE802.1AS-2011:39-A7-94-FF-FE-07-CB-D0
]]></artwork>
          </figure>

          <t></t>

          <t><xref target="example-source-level"></xref> shows an example SDP
          description with a timestamp reference clock definition at the
          source-level overriding the session-level default.</t>

          <figure align="center" anchor="example-source-level"
                  title="Timestamp reference clock signalling at the source level">
            <artwork><![CDATA[
v=0
o=jdoe 2890844526 2890842807 IN IP4 10.47.16.5
s=SDP Seminar
i=A Seminar on the session description protocol
u=http://www.example.com/seminars/sdp.pdf
e=j.doe@example.com (Jane Doe)
c=IN IP4 224.2.17.12/127
t=2873397496 2873404696
a=recvonly
a=ts-refclk:local
m=audio 49170 RTP/AVP 0
m=video 51372 RTP/AVP 99
a=rtpmap:99 h263-1998/90000
a=ssrc:12345 ts-refclk:ptp=IEEE802.1AS-2011:39-A7-94-FF-FE-07-CB-D0
]]></artwork>
          </figure>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Timescales, UTC TAI and leap seconds">
      <t>RTP implementation is simplified by using a clock reference with a
      timescale which does not include leap seconds. IEEE 1588, GPS and other
      TAI (Inernational Atomic Time) references do not include leap seconds.
      NTP time, operating system clocks and other UTC (Coordinated Universal
      Time) references include leap seconds (though the ITU is studying a
      proposal which could eventually eliminate leap seconds from UTC).</t>

      <t>Leap seconds are potentially scheduled at the end of the last day of
      December and June each year. NTP inserts a leap second at the beginning
      of the last second of the day. This results in the clock freezing for
      one second immediately prior to the last second of the affected day.
      Most system clocks insert the leap second at the end of the last second.
      This results in repetition of the last second of the day. Generating or
      using timestamps during the entire last second of a day on which a leap
      second has been scheduled should therefore be avoided. Note that the
      period to be avoided has a real-time duration of two seconds.</t>

      <t>It is also important that all participants correctly implement leap
      seconds and have a working communications channel to receive
      notification of leap second scheduling. Without prior knowledge of leap
      second schedule, NTP servers and clients may be offset by exactly one
      second with respect to their UTC reference. This potential discrepancy
      begins when a leap second occurs and ends when all participants receive
      a time update from a server or peer (which, depending on the operating
      system and/or implementation, could be anywhere from a few minutes to a
      week). Such a long-lived discrepancy can be particularly disruptive to
      RTP operation.</t>

      <t>Apart from the long-lived discrepancy due to dependence on both
      timing (e.g. NTP) updates and leap seconds scheduling updates, there is
      also the potential for a short-lived timing discontinuity having an
      effect on RTP playout timing (even though leap seconds are quite
      rare).</t>

      <t>If a timescale with leap seconds is used for RTP:</t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>RTP Senders using a leap-second-bearing reference must not
          generate sender reports (SR) containing an originating NTP timestamp
          in the vicinity of a leap second. Receivers should ignore timestamps
          in any such reports inadvertently generated.</t>

          <t>Receivers working to a leap-second-bearing reference must be
          careful to take leap seconds into account if a leap second occurs
          between the time a RTP packet is originated and when it is to be
          presented.</t>
        </list></t>
    </section>

    <section title="Media Clock Source Signalling">
      <t>A timestamp clock source (ie media clock is locked to a reference
      clock like NTP, GPS, etc) Reference clock source..</t>

      <t>An RTP session.. This should be an SSRC within an RTP session.
      Include IP address and port.</t>

      <t>An IEEE 1722 stream, identified by a Stream ID.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>The SDP attribute "ts-clksrc" defined by this document is registered
      with the IANA registry of SDP Parameters as follows:</t>

      <figure>
        <artwork><![CDATA[
SDP Attribute ("att-field"):

  Attribute name:     ts-refclk

  Long form:          Timestamp reference clock source

  Type of name:       att-field

  Type of attribute:  session, media and source level

  Subject to charset: no

  Purpose:            See sections 1-4 of this document

  Reference:          This document

  Values:             see this document and registrations below

]]></artwork>

        <postamble>The attribute has an extensible parameter field and
        therefore a registry for these parameters is required. This document
        creates an IANA registry called the Timestamp Reference Clock Source
        Parameters Registry. It contains the six parameters defined in <xref
        target="ebnf-ts-refclk"></xref>: "ntp", "ptp", "gps", "gal", "local",
        "private".</postamble>
      </figure>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">
      <t></t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4566"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5576"?>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5905"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.I-D.ietf-avtcore-idms"?>

      <reference anchor="IEEE1588-2002"
                 target="http://standards.ieee.org/findstds/standard/1588-2002.html">
        <front>
          <title>1588-2002 - IEEE Standard for a Precision Clock
          Synchronization Protocol for Networked Measurement and Control
          Systems</title>

          <author>
            <organization>Institute of Electrical and Electronics
            Engineers</organization>
          </author>

          <date year="2002" />
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="" value="IEEE Std 1588-2002" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="IEEE1588-2008"
                 target="http://standards.ieee.org/findstds/standard/1588-2008.html">
        <front>
          <title>1588-2008 - IEEE Standard for a Precision Clock
          Synchronization Protocol for Networked Measurement and Control
          Systems</title>

          <author>
            <organization>Institute of Electrical and Electronics
            Engineers</organization>
          </author>

          <date year="2008" />
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="" value="IEEE Std 1588-2008" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="IEEE802.1AS-2011"
                 target="http://standards.ieee.org/findstds/standard/802.1AS-2011.html">
        <front>
          <title>Timing and Synchronization for Time-Sensitive Applications in
          Bridged Local Area Networks</title>

          <author>
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date />
        </front>
      </reference>
    </references>

    <section title="An Appendix">
      <t></t>
    </section>
  </back>
</rfc>
