<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc strict="yes"?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<rfc ipr="trust200902" category="std">
  <front>
    <title>Overlay Path Option for IP and TCP</title>
    <author initials="B." surname="Williams" fullname="Brandon Williams">
      <organization>Akamai, Inc.</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>
          <city>Cambridge</city>
          <region>MA</region>
          <code></code>
          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>
        <email>brandon.williams@akamai.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date month="September" year=" 2012" />
    <abstract>
      <t>Data transport through overlay networks often uses either connection
      termination or network address translation (NAT) in such a way that the
      public IP addresses of the true endpoint machines involved in the data
      transport are invisible to each other. This document describes IPv4,
      IPv6, and TCP options for communicating this information from the
      overlay network to the endpoint machines.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section anchor="intro" title="Introduction">
      <t>An overlay network is a network of machines distributed throughout
        multiple autonomous systems within the public Internet that can be
        used to improve the performance of data transport. IP packets from the
        sender are delivered first to one of the machines that make up the
        overlay network. That machine will relay the IP packets via one or
        more other machines in the overlay network, applying various
        performance enhancement methods and eventually delivering the packets
        to the real intended receiver. Such overlay networks are used to
        improve the performance of content delivery 
        <xref target="IEEE1344002" />.  Overlay networks are also used for
        peer-to-peer data transport <xref target="RFC5694" />, and they have
        been suggested for use in improved scalability for the internet
        routing infrastructure <xref target="RFC6179" />.</t>

      <t>Data transport through such an overlay network will often use network
        address translation for the source (SNAT) or destination (DNAT)
        addresses <xref target="RFC2663" /> in such a way that the public IP
        addresses of the true endpoint machines involved in the data
        transport are invisible to each other. For example, the actual sender
        and receiver may use two completely different pairs of source and
        destination addresses to identify the connection on the sending and
        receiving networks.</t>

      <figure anchor="intro_figure">
        <artwork>
---------------------------------------------------------------------

          ip hdr contains:               ip hdr contains:
SENDER -> src = sender   --> OVERLAY --> src = overlay2  --> RECEIVER 
          dst = overlay1                 dst = receiver  

---------------------------------------------------------------------
        </artwork>
      </figure>

      <t>This can be problematic for network security and diagnostics, since
        the source and destination IP addresses used by the sender are not
        accessible by the receiver.</t> 

      <t>Some application layer protocols provide functionality that allows
        the overlay network to communicate the sender's public IP address to
        the receiver, such as the HTTP X-FORWARDED-FOR header field. However,
        use of such application specific options requires both the overlay
        network and the receiver to perform application layer processing with
        associated overhead.  It also requires separate implementations for
        each supported application type.</t>
  
      <t>Some proprietary implementations use IP-in-IP or UDP tunneling in
        order to communicate the information in question, but these solutions
        require continuous network overhead throughout the life of the
        connection.</t>
  
      <t>In order to limit the network and processing overhead associated with
        the other commonly used approaches, the mechanism described herein
        uses an internet or transport layer protocol option to communication
        the required address(es).</t>

      <t>Theoretically, the existing IP Record Route option could be used to
        provide the required information, but there are a few problems
        associated with this approach. First, this use would be a re-purposing
        of the option, and thus existing implementations of support for the
        option would quite possibly conflict with this new use. More
        importantly, many IP-layer devices are configured to drop packets that
        include IP protocol options. Allowing the information to be
        transmitted at either the internet layer or the transport layer allows
        for more reliable packet delivery in a broad range of network
        configurations.</t>

      <t>This document describes <xref target="RFC0791">IPv4</xref>,
        <xref target="RFC2460">IPv6</xref>, and
        <xref target="RFC0793">TCP</xref> options for communicating this
        information from the overlay to the destination network/machine.  The
        list of addresses specified in the option may include any addresses
        that might be useful to the eventual receiver for security and/or
        diagnostic purposes, including but not limited to the source and
        destination addresses as seen by the sender.</t>

      <t>The IPv4 and TCP protocol options described herein provide limited
        support for IPv6 addresses. It should be noted that inclusion of even
        a single IPv6 address would require the option to consume nearly half
        of the total option space provided by TCP and IPv4, which means that
        the entire TCP option space would be consumed for SYN packets that
        include the most commonly used options (i.e. MSS, WSOPT, SACK
        permitted, and TSOPT). This may prevent effective use of the IPv4 and
        TCP protocol options for communicating IPv6 addresses in some
        circumstances.</t>

    </section>

    <section anchor="use_case" title="Detailed Use Case">
      <t>An example use case that is satisfied by this design is as
        follows.

        <list style="numbers">
          <t>The sending endpoint host performs a DNS lookup that returns the
            IP address of a machine on the overlay network. The sending
            endpoint addresses its packets with its own public IP address as
            the source and the provided overlay IP address as the
            destination.</t>

          <t>The overlay ingress host receives the packet on its public IP
            address, and forwards the packet through the overlay to the egress
            host.  The overlay egress host performs SNAT, replacing the source
            IP address of the sending endpoint with its own IP address in
            order to ensure that return traffic will also use the overlay
            network. This use of SNAT hides the client's public IP address for
            the receiving network.</t>

          <t>For load balancing and diagnostic purposes, it is important for
            one or more machines on the receiver's network to be able to
            determine the public IP address associated with the sending host
            (i.e. the address that was hidden due to the use of SNAT by the
            overlay).</t>

          <t>The overlay egress host is located on the receiver's network,
            which means there is a relatively small set of addresses for
            machines that may be producing packets that include the overlay
            path option.</t>
        </list>
      </t>

      <t>Under these circumstances, the overlay path option will contain a
        single IP address: the public IP address of the sending host. If the
        receiving network must use the IP address included in the option for a
        purpose that requires trust, the fact that the overlay egress host is
        under the receiver's administrative control allows the receiver to
        apply the necessary limitations to the network configuration. For
        example, under these circumstances, the receiver's firewall device
        could be configured to drop packets from external hosts if they
        contain the overlay path option.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="format" title="Option Format">
      <t>Some implementations already exist for version 1 of the overlay path
        option.  However, version 1 of the option does not provide support for
        communicating IPv6 addresses in either the IPv4 or TCP option. Both
        version 1 and version 2 of the option are described here in order to
        reflect the requirements of current and future implementors.</t>
  
      <t>It is up to the implementor whether version 1 is supported or both
        versions are supported. A receiving implementation that supports
        version 2 MUST also support version 1. The format changes defined for
        version 2 directly support the required backward compatibility.</t>
  
      <t>When a receiving implementation encounters the overlay path option
        with an unsupported version number, the receiver MAY either ignore the
        option or drop the packet. The appropriate response will be dependent
        upon how the overlay path option's value is used by the receiver.</t>

      <section anchor="format_v1" title="Version 1">

        <t>Version 1 of the option supports only IPv4 addresses. The option
          format for both IPv4 and TCP is identical.</t>

        <figure anchor="layout_v1">
          <artwork>
+---------+---------+---------+--------------------------------+ 
|Type/Kind| Length  | Version | Addresses ...
+---------+---------+---------+--------------------------------+ 
     1         1         1            4 x Address Count
----------------------------------------------------------------
          </artwork>
        </figure>

        <t><list style="hanging">

            <t hangText="IPv4 Type:">The type value for IPv4 is TBD-IP4-FULL
              (see also <xref target="iana">IANA Considerations</xref>).
              <list style="hanging">
                <t hangText="Copied flag:">  1 (All fragments must carry the
                  option.)</t>
                <t hangText="Option class:"> 2 (debugging/measurement)</t>
                <t hangText="Option number:">TBD-IP4 (decimal)</t>
              </list>
            </t>

            <t hangText="TCP Kind:">The option kind value for TCP is TBD-TCP
              (see also <xref target="iana">IANA Considerations</xref>).</t>

            <t hangText="Length:">The length of the option is variable, based
              on the number of addresses provided. The minimum value is 7 (3
              1-octet fields plus one 4-octet address). The option MUST be
              ignored if the length value cannot represent 3 octets plus a
              list of 4-octet address value.</t>

            <t hangText="Version:">The version number is 1.</t>

            <t hangText="Addresses:">Version 1 of the option supports only IPv4
              addresses.  The remainder of the option space is filled with
              standard 32-bit IPv4 addresses. In practice, the first address
              will be the public source address used by the sender and the
              second address (if present) will be the public destination
              address used by the sender.  However, the nature of the
              addresses provided may vary depending on the nature of the
              overlay network in question and is not required to include every
              IP address used for the connection. The list of IP addresses
              MUST be provided in order of traversal from sender to
              receiver.</t>
        </list></t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="format_v2" title="Version 2">
        <t>Version 2 of the options supports either IPv4 addresses or IPv6
          addresses, but it does not support a mix of IPv4 and IPv6 options
          within the same option value. Version 2 provides not only IPv4 and
          TCP options, but also an IPv6 option for inclusion in the IPv6
          Hop-by-hop Options header. When IPv6 address support is required,
          the implementation SHOULD use the IPv6 header option whenever
          possible in order to avoid exhaustion of the TCP option space. The
          option format for all three protocols is identical.</t>

        <figure anchor="layout_v2_ipv6">
          <artwork>
+---------------+---------------+---------------+-------------------\ 
|   Type/Kind   |    Length     |Fmly| Version  |  Addresses ...
+---------------+---------------+---------------+-------------------\
       8b              8b       | 3b     5b     |
                                -----------------
        1               1              1          Addr Size x Count
---------------------------------------------------------------------
          </artwork>
        </figure>

        <t><list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="IPv4 Type:">Identical to Version 1.</t>

            <t hangText="TCP Kind:">Identical to Version 1.</t>

            <t hangText="IPv6 Type:">The Type value for IPv6 is TBD-IP6
              (see also <xref target="iana">IANA Considerations</xref>).
              <list style="hanging">
                <t hangText="act flag:">00 (skip over option)</t>
                <t hangText="chg flag:"> 0 (option data does not change
                  en-route)</t>
                <t hangText="rest:">   TBD-IP6 (decimal)</t>
              </list>
            </t>

            <t hangText="Length:">The length of the option is variable, based
              on the address family and the number of addresses provided. The
              minimum value is 7 (3 1-octet fields plus one 4-octet IPv4
              address). The option MUST be ignored if the length value cannot
              represent 3 octets plus a list of addresses of the correct
              address family.</t>

            <t hangText="Family/Version:">The third octet is comprised of two
              fields: family and version.Note that the possible family values
              have been selected to support backward compatibility with the
              8-bit version field in version 1 of the option format.</t>

            <t hangText="Family:">The high order 3 bits of the third octet
              indicate the address family for all IP addresses represented in
              the variable-length Addresses field. The allowed values are:
              <list style="hanging">
                <t hangText="0:">Address family is IPv4.</t>
                <t hangText="1:">Address family is IPv6.</t>
              </list>
            </t>

            <t hangText="Version:">The low order 5 bits of the third octet
              indicate the protocol version number. The version number is
              2.</t>

            <t hangText="Addresses:">The remainder of the option space is
              filled with either 32-bit IPv4 or 128-bit IPv6 addresses, as
              indicated by the Family field. In practice, the first address
              will be the public source address used by the sender and the
              second address (if present) will be the public destination
              address used by the sender.  However, the nature of the
              addresses provided may vary depending on the nature of the
              overlay network in question and is not required to include every
              IP address used for the connection. The list of IP addresses
              MUST be provided in order of traversal from sender to
              receiver.</t>
        </list></t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="net_traversal" title="Network Traversal">

      <figure anchor="net_traversal_figure">
        <preamble>
	  The following block diagram illustrates the use of addresses in the
          IPv4 header and the overlay path option as a packet traverses the
          network from sender to receiver. The diagram assumes that the
          overlay network uses separate addresses (overlay1 and overlay2) for
          ingress and egress.
        </preamble>
        <artwork>
-----------------------------------------------------------------

                             SENDER
                               |
                               V
                       +----------------+
                       |                |
                       | src: sender    |
                       | dst: overlay1  |
                       | opt: none      |
                       |                |
                       +----------------+
                               |
                               V
                            OVERLAY
                            NETWORK
                               |
                               V
                       +----------------+
                       |                |
                       | src: overlay2  |
                       | dst: receiver  |
                       | opt: sender    |
                       |                |
                       +----------------+
                               |
                               V
                            RECEIVER

-----------------------------------------------------------------
        </artwork>
      </figure>
    </section>

    <section anchor="option_use" title="Option Use">
      <t>Use of the TCP option allows an implementation to minimize the impact
        of this option on bandwidth utilization. Due to the
        connection-oriented nature of TCP, the addresses used by the overlay
        network cannot change throughout the life of the connection. For this
        reason, it is not necessary for the overlay network to include the
        overlay path option on every packet. On the other hand, it is not
        enough for the option to be provided exclusively in the TCP SYN packet
        because the use of SYN cookies, for example, would mean that
        connection state is not stored until completion of the three-way
        handshake. For this reason, the overlay network MUST include the TCP
        overlay path option in every outgoing packet until the receiver has
        either acknowledged or transmitted at least one byte of real data. The
        overlay network SHOULD discontinue inclusion of the TCP overlay path
        option after the first byte is either received or acknowledged. The
        receiver MAY ignore the TCP overlay path option on subsequent packets
        after successfully processing one instance of the option attached to a
        single in-order TCP packet.</t>

      <t>IP is not connection oriented, which means that the above described
        optimization is not possible. In order to make effective use of the
        TCP optimization, an overlay network SHOULD only send the IP option on
        packets that do not use TCP as the transport layer protocol. When the
        IP option is in use, the overlay network MUST transmit the option with
        every packet. The receiver MUST NOT assume that that addresses in the
        IP overlay path option will remain consistent, but instead MUST be
        prepared to handle address changes in an application appropriate
        way.</t>

      <t>Use of the IP option is dependent upon support for IP options in all
        routers between the overlay egress point and the packet receiver. If
        any router along the path is configured to drop packets with unknown
        IPv4 options (or any IP options, as is sometimes done as part of a DoS
        protection scheme), then use of the IP option will cause connections
        to simply fail. For this reason, the IP option SHOULD only be used in
        environments where the full path between the overlay egress machine
        and the packet receiver is under common administrative control.</t>

      <t>As explained above, the intention of both the TCP and IP options is
        to provide the receiver with public IP addresses that it would
        otherwise have seen if the overlay network were not in use. There are
        security implications associated with exposing a network's use of the
        private <xref target="RFC1918" /> address space to the public
        internet, and for this reason, the overlay path option SHOULD NOT be
        used to communicate RFC1918 addresses in packets that traverse the
        public internet.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>This specification provides no authentication/validity verification
        for the data contained in the address fields. For this reason, the
        data contained in the addresses field of the new option cannot itself
        be considered inherently secure. In other words, confidence in the
        validity of the source address of the IPv4/IPv6 packet does not
        translate into confidence in the validity of the addresses in the
        overlay path option. With this exception, this specification does not
        alter the inherent security of IPv4, IPv6, or TCP.</t>

      <t>The addresses provided in the option SHOULD NOT be used for purposes
        that require a trust relationship between the overlay network and the
        receiver (e.g. billing and/or intrusion prevention) unless a mechanism
        outside the scope of this specification is used to ensure the
        necessary level of trust.  As noted above, one possible example of
        such a mechanism would be to place the overlay egress host on the
        receiver's own network and to configure the receiver's firewall to
        drop any packets from external hosts that provide the overlay path
        option. When the receiving network uses the values provided by the
        option in a way that does not require trust (e.g. maintaining session
        affinity in a load-balancing system), then use of a mechanism to
        enforce the trust relationship may not be required.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="fwd_compat" title="Forward Compatibility Support">
      <t>The most common use of this option on the internet today will require
        recording IP addresses for a single address family only. However, it
        may be important in the future to be able to record a mix of IPv4 and
        IPv6 addresses. Alternatively, future security requirements may demand
        the use of, for example, a keyed hash for data integrity and
        authentication purposes and/or inclusion of additional information
        specific to the sender's connection.</t>

      <t>To balance current-day performance and efficiency against the need
        for future extensibility, the option includes a version field, so that
        future requirements can be met without the need to consume a new
        option number.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="iana" title="IANA Considerations">

      <t>[Paragraphs below in braces should be removed by the RFC Editor upon
        publication]</t>

      <t>[The TCP Overlay Path Option requires that IANA allocate a value from
        the TCP option kind namespace, to be replaced for TBD-TCP throughout
        this document.]</t>

      <t>[The IPv4 Overlay Path Option requires that IANA allocate a value
        from the IP option number namespace. The copy flag for this option is
        1 and the class for this option is 2. The assigned number will replace
        TBD-IP4 throughout this document, and the full type value
        (representing copy, class, and number) will replace TBD-IP4-FULL
        throughout the document.]</t>

      <t>[The IPv6 Overlay Path Option requires that IANA allocate a value
        from the IPv6 parameters: hop-by-hop options namespace. The action for
        this option is 00 and the change flag for this option is 0. The
        assigned number will replace TBD-IP6 throughout this document.]</t>

      <t>This document defines the TCP Overlay Path option, described in <xref
        target="format_v1" /> and <xref target="format_v2" />. This option
        has been assigned the option number TBD-TCP by IANA action.</t>

      <t>This document also defines the IPv4 Overlay Path option, described in
        <xref target="format_v1" /> and <xref target="format_v2" />. This
        option has been assigned the option number TBD-IP4-FULL by IANA
        action.</t>

      <t>This document also defines the IPv6 Overlay Path hop-by-hop option,
        described in <xref target="format_v2" />. This option has been
        assigned the option number TBD-IP6 by IANA action.</t>

      <t>This document defines no new namespaces.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Informative References">
      <reference anchor="RFC0791">
        <front>
          <title>Internet Protocol</title>
          <author initials="J." surname="Postel" fullname="Jon Postel">
            <organization abbrev="ISI">
              USC/Information Sciences Institute
            </organization>
          </author>
          <date month="September" year="1981" />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="791" />
        <seriesInfo name="STD" value="5" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RFC0793">
        <front>
          <title>Transmission Control Protocol</title>
          <author initials="J." surname="Postel" fullname="Jon Postel">
            <organization abbrev="ISI">
              USC/Information Sciences Institute
            </organization>
          </author>
          <date month="September" year="1981" />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="793" />
        <seriesInfo name="STD" value="7" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RFC1918">
        <front>
          <title>Address Allocation for Private Internets</title>
          <author initials="Y." surname="Rekhter" fullname="Yakov Rekhter">
            <organization>Cisco Systems</organization>
          </author>
          <author initials="B." surname="Moskowitz" fullname="Robert G. Moskowitz">
            <organization abbrev="Chrysler Corp.">Chrysler Corporation</organization>
          </author>
          <author initials="D." surname="Karrenberg" fullname="Daniel Karrenberg">
            <organization abbrev="RIPE NCC">
              RIPE Networking Coordination Center
            </organization>
          </author>
          <author initials="G.J." surname="de Groot" fullname="Geert Jan de Groot">
            <organization abbrev="RIPE NCC">
              RIPE Networking Coordination Center
            </organization>
          </author>
          <author initials="E." surname="Lear" fullname="Eliot Lear">
            <organization>Silicon Graphics, Inc.</organization>
          </author>
          <date month="February" year="1996" />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="1918" />
        <seriesInfo name="BCP" value="5" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RFC2460">
        <front>
          <title>Internet Protocol, Version 6 (IPv6)</title>
          <author initials="S." surname="Deering" fullname="Stephen E. Deering">
            <organization abbrev="Cisco">Cisco Systems, Inc.</organization>
          </author>
          <author initials="R." surname="Hinden" fullname="Robert M. Hinden">
            <organization>Nokia</organization>
          </author>
          <date month="December" year="1998" />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="2460" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RFC2663">
        <front>
          <title>IP Network Address Translator (NAT) Terminology and
            Considerations</title>
          <author initials="P." surname="Srisuresh" fullname="Pyda Srisuresh">
            <organization>Lucent Technologies</organization>
          </author>
          <author initials="M." surname="Holdrege" fullname="Matt Holdrege">
            <organization>Lucent Technologies</organization>
          </author>
          <date month="August" year="1999" />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="2663" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RFC5694">
        <front>
          <title>Peer-to-Peer (P2P) Architecture: Definition, Taxonomies,
            Examples, and Applicability</title>
          <author initials="G." surname="Camarillo" fullname="Gonzalo Camaillo">
            <organization abbrev="IAB">Internet Architecture Board</organization>
          </author>
          <date month="November" year="2009" />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="5694" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RFC6179">
        <front>
          <title>The Internet Routing Overlay Network (IRON)</title>
          <author initials="F." surname="Templin" fullname="Fred L. Templin">
            <organization>Boeing Research &amp; Technology</organization>
          </author>
          <date month="March" year="2011" />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="6179" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="IEEE1344002">
        <front>
          <title abbrev="Informed content delivery">Informed content delivery
            across adaptive overlay networks: IEEE/ACM Transactions on
            Networking, Vol 12, Issue 5, ppg 767-780</title>
          <author initials="J.W." surname="Byers" fullname="John Byers">
            <organization abbrev="Boston University">
              Boston University, Dept. of Computer Science
            </organization>
          </author>
          <author initials="J." surname="Considine" fullname="Jeffrey Considine">
            <organization abbrev="Boston University">
              Boston University, Dept. of Computer Science
            </organization>
          </author>
          <author initials="M." surname="Mitzenmacher" fullname="Michael Mitzenmacher">
            <organization abbrev="Harvard University">
              Harvard University, EECS
            </organization>
          </author>
          <author initials="S." surname="Rost" fullname="Stanislav Rost">
            <organization abbrev="MIT">
              MIT Laboratory for Computer Science
            </organization>
          </author>
          <date month="October" year="2004" />
        </front>
      </reference>
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
