<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- edited with XMLSPY v5 rel. 3 U (http://www.xmlspy.com)
     by Daniel M Kohn (private) -->
<!-- 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml' -->

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY rfc2119 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml'>
<!ENTITY rfc2818 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2818.xml'>
<!ENTITY rfc2660 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2660.xml'>
<!ENTITY rfc2743 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2743.xml'>
<!ENTITY rfc4422 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4422.xml'>
<!ENTITY rfc4511 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4511.xml'>
<!ENTITY rfc4647 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4647.xml'>
<!ENTITY rfc5056 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5056.xml'>
<!ENTITY rfc5246 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5246.xml'>
<!ENTITY rfc5646 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5646.xml'>
<!ENTITY rfc5746 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5746.xml'>
<!ENTITY rfc5801 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5801.xml'>
<!ENTITY rfc5929 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5929.xml'>
]>

<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>

<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc tocindent="no" ?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc iprnotified="no" ?>
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>

<rfc category="std" ipr="trust200902" docName="draft-williams-tls-app-sasl-opt-04.txt">
    <front>
	<title abbrev="TLS/SA">TLS Extension for Optimizing Application Protocols, Specifically SASL with GSS-API mechanisms</title>
        <author initials='N.' surname="Williams" fullname='Nicolas
            Williams'>
            <organization>Oracle</organization>
            <address>
                <postal>
                    <street>5300 Riata Trace Ct</street>
                    <city>Austin</city> <region>TX</region>
                    <code>78727</code> <country>US</country>
                </postal>
                <email>Nicolas.Williams@oracle.com</email>
            </address>
        </author>
        <date year="2010"/>
        <area>Security</area>
        <keyword>Internet-Draft</keyword>
	<abstract>
	    
	    <t>This document specifies Hello extensions to Transport
		Layer Security (TLS).  One extension is used for
		carrying application data which is suitable for delayed
		integrity protection and does not require privacy
		protection.  Another extension is used to negotiate an
		early start to the application data protocol in the case
		of initial TLS connections (i.e., which do not resume
		sessions).</t>

	    <t>We describe how to use these extensions to reduce the
		number of round trips needed for application-layer
		authentication, by piggy-backing Simple Authentication
		(SASL) mechanism negotiation on the first leg of a TLS
		handshake and the first round of SASL authentication
		messages on the second leg of the same TLS handshake.
		Through SASL we get support for Generic Security
		Services (GSS-API) mechanisms.  Channel binding is used
		from SASL authentication to the TLS channel.  This
		results in a two round-trip optimization for
		applications that use SASL on top of TLS.</t>

	    <t>We also provide generic framing for SASL authentication
		messages which, combined with the use of these
		extensions, will be referred to as "TLS/SA".  These
		extensions can also be used to optimize application
		protocols separately from SASL.</t>

        </abstract>
    </front>

    <middle>

	<section title="Introduction">

	    <t>Many applications use TLS <xref target='RFC5246'/> and
		then Simple Authentication and Security Layers (SASL)
		<xref target='RFC4422'/> on top of TLS.  This requires
		at least two round trips for TLS, then one round trip
		for SASL mechanism negotiation, then as many round trips
		as the negotiated SASL mechanism requires.  The TLS
		Hello exchanges can can carry extensions bearing
		application data.  We could also define additional
		non-Hello Handshake extensions to carry application
		data, but it suffices to be able to start using TLS
		application records as soon as the client's Finished
		message is sent, without waiting for a server reply (in
		the new TLS session case).  Here we describe how to use
		such TLS extensions to reduce the number of round trips
		needed for SASL mechanism negotiation and
		authentication.</t>

	    <t>We define a TLS extension for use in Hello messages.
		This extension will carry typed application data.  We
		also define a TLS Hello extension for negotiating an
		early start for the TLS application record protocol.</t>

	    <t>Through the new SASL to GSS-API mechanism bridge, GS2
		<xref target='RFC5801'/>, we obtain support for use of
		GSS-API <xref target='RFC2743'/> security mechanisms.
		Altogether we achieve up to a two round-trip reduction
		for applications using SASL over TLS.</t>

	    <t>We use the first TLS round trip to optimize the SASL
		mechanism negotiation by piggybacking the mechanism
		negotiation on TLS Hello messages.  By negotiating an
		early start to the TLS application record protocol we
		can send the first authentication message of the
		selected SASL mechanism in the second leg of the TLS
		handshake, immediately after the client's Finished
		message is sent.  Note that the TLS channel binding
		<xref target='RFC5929'/> is available just in time to
		start the SASL authentication at that time, thus no
		special considerations apply to how channel binding is
		done.  Use of channel binding protects against
		man-in-the-middle attacks as well as downgrade attacks
		on mechanism negotiation.</t>

	    <t>These extensions are motivated by:

		<list style='symbols'>

		    <t>a desire to reduce the number of round trips
			needed by SASL and GSS-API applications running
			over TLS;</t>

		    <t>a desire to replace an earlier proposal for
			"TLS/GSS" with one that passes muster at the TLS
			implementor community;</t>

		    <t>a desire to provide a profile that new
			applications may use for TLS with SASL and/or
			GSS-API for user authentication.</t>

		</list>

	    </t>

	    <t>The use of these extensions to optimize SASL/GSS-API
		authentication is hereby termed "Transport Layer
		Security with Simple Authentication", or "TLS/SA" for
		short.</t>

	    <section title="Conventions used in this document">

		<t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED",
		    "SHALL", "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT",
		    "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
		    document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
			target="RFC2119"/>.</t>

	    </section>

	</section>

	<section anchor='ext' title="TLS Extensions for Optimization of
	    Application protocols">

	    <t>When a client application wishes to exchange one or more
		application messages prior to the conclusion of a TLS
		exchange it uses TLS client Hello message extensions to
		a) request permission to start the application record
		protocol early, and b) optionally send the first
		application message to the server.  Such application data
		MUST NOT require privacy or integrity protection, unless
		either a) the current TLS handshake is part of a renegotiation
		<xref target='RFC5746'/> where the previous negotiation
		established cipher suites that provide the required
		protection or b) deferred integrity protection is
		sufficient.</t>

	    <t>When an application data bearing Hello message is
		received the server will either ignore the extension or
		pass it to the application, which then may respond to
		that application data via the server's Hello message.
		If the server or server application ignores the client's
		Hello extension then the client will discover that the
		server does not support this extension when the client
		receives the server's Hello.</t>

	    <t>The extension contents are defined by the application.
		In order to save the application having to encode
		application "type" information we define application
		data extension types and we allow the Client Hello to
		carry one of each of these extensions:

		<list style='symbols'>

		    <t>app_hello (&lt;TBD&gt;)</t>
		    <t>sasl_sml (&lt;TBD&gt;)</t>
		    <t>early_start (&lt;TBD&gt;)</t>

		</list>

	    </t>

	    <t>It is the application's responsibility to define the
		contents of the app_hello Hello extension.</t>

	    <t>The sasl_sml Hello extension represents a SASL server
		mechanism list request.  The server returns this list,
		if it can, via the same Hello extension in its Hello.
		The client's sasl_sml MUST be have an empty value.  The
		client will use this server's SASL mechanism list to
		pick a suitable SASL mechanism.  See <xref
		    target='mech_nego'/> for details of the encoding of
		the server's SASL mechanism list.</t>

	    <t>The early_start extension requests permission to
		start the application data record protocol on the
		client-side immediately after sending the client's
		Finished message (which, in the case of initial TLS
		connections, is sent before receiving the server's
		Finished message).  Servers that supports this
		extension MUST include the same extension in its Hello
		message with the same value.  The value of early_start
		consists of an encoded enum (EarlyStartProto) that
		indicates the kind of application data that will be sent
		early:</t>

	    <figure anchor='EarlyStartProto' title="EarlyStartProto TLS Hello extension">
		<artwork>
      enum { app_protocol (0), generic_sasl(1), (255)
      } EarlyStartProto;
		</artwork>
	    </figure>

	    <t>If the value of early_start is app_protocol (0), then the
		contents of format of the early start application data
		is defined by the application; see <xref
		    target='existing_sasl_apps'/> and <xref
		    target='non_sasl_apps'/>.  If the value of
		early_start is generic_sasl(1) then the application is
		said to be a "TLS/SA" application, and SASL messages
		will be exchanged as application records, with generic
		framing described in <xref target='generic-sasl'/>,
		until authentication succeeds or fails, at which point
		the actual application protocol will take over the TLS
		application records.</t>

	    <t>A generic application protocol using these TLS extensions
		might look like:</t>

	    <figure anchor='tlssa_init' title="Message flow for initial TLS connections with SASL mechanism negotiation and SASL authentication">
		<artwork>
		    <![CDATA[
   Client                                               Server

   ClientHello w/ sasl_sml
               early_start     -------->
                                                ServerHello w/
                                                      sasl_sml
                                                   early_start
                                                  Certificate*
                                            ServerKeyExchange*
                                           CertificateRequest*
                                <--------      ServerHelloDone
   Certificate*
   ClientKeyExchange
   CertificateVerify*
   [ChangeCipherSpec]
   Finished
   SASL auth message as data    -------->   
                                            [ChangeCipherSpec]
                                                      Finished
                                <--------    SASL auth message
   SASL auth messages           <------->   SASL auth messages
                                <--------      Outcome of SASL
                                                authentication
   Application Data             <------->     Application Data
		    ]]>
		</artwork>
	    </figure>

	    <figure anchor='tlssa_resume' title="Message flow for resumed TLS connections with SASL mechanism negotiation and SASL authentication">
		<artwork>
		    <![CDATA[
   Client                                               Server

   ClientHello w/ sasl_sml
               early_start     -------->
                                                ServerHello w/
                                                      sasl_sml
                                                   early_start
                                            [ChangeCipherSpec]
                                <--------             Finished
   [ChangeCipherSpec]
   Finished
   SASL auth message as data    -------->   
                                <--------    SASL auth message
   SASL auth messages           <------->   SASL auth messages
                                <--------      Outcome of SASL
                                                authentication
   Application Data             <------->     Application Data
		    ]]>
		</artwork>
	    </figure>

	</section>

	<section title="Sending Application Data in TLS Hello Messages">

	    <t>The app_hello client Hello message extension can be used
		to send arbitrary application-specific messages in the
		client Hello.  The application MUST NOT use this
		extension unless both of these requirements are met:
		
		<list style='numbers'>
		
		    <t>the application data being sent in the app_hello
			and the reply expected in the app_hello reply
			MUST NOT require privacy protection unless
			either the TLS connection is part of a
			renegotiation of another that provides the
			required protection and/or deferred integrity
			protetion is sufficient;</t>

		    <t>the application on the server side knows
			unambiguously what data to expect in an
			app_hello.</t>
		</list>

	    </t>

	    <t>For example, SMTP could use the app_hello extension to
		send its EHLO before the TLS handshake completes.</t>
	    
	    <t>The app_hello extension data and early-start application
		records are ultimately integrity-protected once the TLS
		Finished message exchange completes, if the TLS
		connection uses a non-null TLS ciphersuite.</t>

	    <section anchor='mech_nego' title="Optimizing SASL Mechanism Negotiation">

		<t>A client wishing to optimize SASL mechanism
		    negotiation MUST send a sasl_sml extension in
		    the client's TLS Hello message.  The client MUST NOT
		    send a payload in its sasl_sml client hello
		    extension.</t>
		
		<t>If the server supports SASL mechanism negotiation
		    optimization and the server's mechanism list is
		    shorter than 2^16 - 1 bytes then the server MUST
		    include a sasl_sml Hello extension in its reply to the
		    client.  The payload of the server's sasl_sml MUST
		    be a string of ASCII characters representing a
		    comma-separated list of SASL mechanism names (note:
		    servers SHOULD NOT send a NUL string terminator is
		    needed, but if present the client MUST ignore the
		    NUL).</t>

	    </section>

	</section>

	<section anchor='early_start' title="Application Data Protocol Early Start">

	    <t>Applications may request that the TLS application data
		record protocol commence immediately after the client's
		Finished message is sent (which can be before the
		server's Finished message is received in the case of
		initial TLS connections).  To do this the client
		includes the client Hello extension 'early_start' in
		its Hello message.  If the server responds with the same
		extension and extension value in its server Hello
		message then the server will allow the early start of
		the TLS application data record protocol.</t>

	    <t>This extension MUST NOT be used if the nature of the
		application data to be sent early is such that the
		server must be authenticated to the client before
		sending the data.  For example, passwords MUST NOT be
		sent early.</t>

	    <t>Note that in the case of TLS session resumption the
		early_start feature has no effect as in that case the
		TLS handshake is already abbreviated.  Because the
		decision to abbreviate a TLS handshake depends on client
		and server choices, clients that want an early start of
		the application record protocol should use the
		early_start extension even when requesting TLS session
		resumption.</t>

	</section>

	<section title="Use with StartTLS-like Protocols">

	    <t>These extensions can be used in "raw TLS" and "StartTLS"
		application protocols both.  This section gives
		INFORMATIVE guidance to application protocol developers
		regarding how to integrate TLS/SA into their
		applications.</t>

	    <t>For example, the HyperText Transfer Protocol over TLS
		(HTTPS) <xref target='RFC2818'/> is a "raw TLS"
		application protocol: clients initiate TCP connections
		to servers, then they initiate TLS connections
		immediately, then they run the application protocol
		(HTTP in this case) over TLS.  Whereas the Secure
		HyperText Transfer Protocol (S-HTTP) <xref
		    target='RFC2660'/> allows TLS to be "started" from
		within HTTP, at which point the application protocol
		(HTTP) is run over TLS-over-HTTP.  The latter is
		commonly known as the "StartTLS" pattern.  Other
		examples of application protocols using raw TLS and
		StartTLS include LDAP <xref target='RFC4511'/>, IMAP4
		[add ref], SMTP [add ref], etcetera.</t>

	    <t>Raw TLS applications need only use these optimizations to
		negotiate and optimize SASL authentication, and as soon
		as SASL authentication is complete they can begin the
		application protocol.  We can call these "raw TLS/SA"
		applications.</t>

	    <t>StartTLS applications might have performed SASL
		authentication before starting TLS, in which case they
		have to redo SASL authentication.</t>

	    <t>StartTLS applications should treat the TLS handshake
		messages and any subsequent SASL authentication messages
		as a TLS handshake messages and frame them accordingly.
		When the TLS/SA authentication completes the application
		should then consider the TLS handshake complete, and the
		application may then start using the TLS record protocol
		for the application protocol's needs.</t>

	</section>

	<section title="Using TLS with the GSS-API">

	    <t>By using the SASL framework known as "GS2" <xref
		    target='RFC5801'/>, applications can use GSS-API
		mechanisms as SASL mechanisms.</t>

	</section>

	<section anchor='existing_sasl_apps' title="Using these Extensions with Existing SASL Applications">

	    <t>Applications that already use TLS and SASL can be
		trivially updated to use the sasl_sml and early_start
		extensions as follows: a) optimize the SASL mechanism
		negotiation as described in <xref target='mech_nego'/>,
		b) start the application data protocol early as
		described in <xref target='early_start'/>.  Having
		listed the server's SASL mechanism list early the
		application can then immediately begin authentication
		using its preferred SASL mechanism.</t>

	    <t>Application protocol designers SHOULD, however, opt for
		the "TLS/SA" profile of TLS and SASL described in <xref
		    target='generic-sasl'/>.  The rationale for this
		SHOULD is that the fewer ways to combine TLS and SASL,
		the more likely it is that developer frameworks will be
		produced to abstract the combination for
		programmers.</t>

	    <t>Non-TLS/SA applications MUST NOT use any SASL mechanism
		that might send credentials (passwords) in cleartext or
		cleartext-equivalent ways before the TLS handshake
		completes (i.e., before the server's Finished message is
		received and validated) unless the server has already
		been authenticated by the TLS connection being
		renegotiated.  It is RECOMMENDED that non-TLS/SA
		applications use only SASL/GS2 <xref target='RFC5801'/>
		mechanisms using channel binding to TLS.  Channel
		binding to TLS is RECOMMENDED.</t>

	</section>

	<section anchor='generic-sasl' title="TLS/SA (TLS + SASL with generic framing of SASL authentication messages)">

	    <t>Application protocols can use the sasl_sml and
		early_start extensions to optimize SASL authentication.
		Each application would have to provide the details of
		how to request SASL authentication start, how to frame
		SASL authentication messages, and how to convey the
		outcome of authentication to the client.  A generic
		profile of TLS and the sasl_sml and early_start
		extensions would allow many applications to share a
		single TLS + SASL sub-protocol.</t>

	    <t>In this section we describe a generic profile of TLS and
		SASL <xref target='RFC4422'/>, using GS2 <xref
		    target='RFC5801'/> mechanisms in TLS applications in
		a round trip optimized manner.  We call this generic
		profile "TLS/SA", or "Transport Layer Security with
		Simple Authentication".  TLS/SA defines those parts of
		the SASL authentication process which SASL <xref
		    target='RFC4422'/> leaves to applications.</t>
	    
	    <t>Existing SASL applications may, but need not use TLS/SA.
		New application protocols that would otherwise use TLS
		and/or SASL SHOULD use TLS/SA.</t>

	    <t>TLS/SA defines the framing of SASL authentication
		request, SASL mechanism and SASL outcome of
		authentication messages.</t>

	    <t>SASL mechanism negotiation in TLS/SA is done as described
		in <xref target='mech_nego'/>.  Channel binding to TLS
		is REQUIRED.  The channel binding type MUST be
		'tls-unique'.  Note that as of today there exist no SASL
		mechanisms that support channel binding but which are
		not SASL/GS2 mechanisms.</t>

	    <section title="TLS/SA Exchanges">

		<t>A client wishing to optimize a SASL/GS2 mechanism
		    MUST: a) negotiate a SASL mechanism to use using the
		    method described in <xref target='mech_nego'/>, b)
		    begin the SASL mechanism authentication message
		    exchange immediately after the client's Finished
		    message as application data without waiting for the
		    server's Finished message, and using the TLS
		    connection's channel binding data for channel
		    binding.</t>

		<t>The first SASL mechanism authentication message
		    (always sent by the client in the case of SASL/GS2
		    mechanisms) MUST be prefixed with, and in the
		    following order:
		    
		    <list style='numbers'>

			<t>the SASL name of the mechanism,
			    NUL-terminated;</t>

			<t>a NUL-terminated, possibly-empty
			    comma-separated list of language tags <xref
				target='RFC5646'/>;</t>

			<t>a four octet, network byte order binary
			    message length.</t>
			
		    </list>

		</t>

		<t>Subsequent SASL mechanism authentication messages are
		    sent prefixed with a four octet, network byte order
		    binary message length.</t>
		    
		<t>Authentication messages MUST NOT be longer
		    than 2^24 octets (i.e., the 8 most significant bits
		    of the message length MUST be zeros); if SASL
		    produces such messages then authentication MUST
		    FAIL.</t>

		<t>The server's "outcome of authentication exchange"
		    message MUST consist of a UTF-8 string containing
		    supplementary information prefixed with a network
		    byte order four byte unsigned binary length of of
		    that string, with the most significant bit of the
		    length set to 1.  The next most significant bit MUST
		    be 1 to indicate success, 0 to indicate failure.
		    The next most significant bit MUST be 1 to indicate
		    that authentication can be re-tried, otherwise it
		    must be set to 0, and MUST be 0 in the case of
		    authentication success.  The supplementary
		    information MUST NOT be longer than 2^16-1 bytes.
		    The supplementary information SHOULD be a
		    human-readable message localized to a language
		    selected from the client's language tags selected
		    according to <xref target='RFC4647'/>, or to one of
		    the server's choice if the client sent no language
		    tags or the server did not support localizations to
		    any of them.  [Question: should this message also
		    include the language tag chosen by the server?  That
		    could be done using UTF-8 language tag codepoints,
		    but IIRC those are deprecated and hard to use.]</t>

		<t>Where empty messages are required by SASL the
		    application should send an empty message with
		    correspondingly set length octets.</t>

		<t>If the last SASL mechanism authentication message is
		    to be sent by the server then the server's outcome
		    of authentication message MUST immediately follow
		    the last mechanism message.  That is: there is no
		    need for the client to send an empty message in
		    response to the last mechanism message just to get
		    the outcome of authentication message.  This saves
		    another round trip.</t>

		<t>If authentication fails then the client MAY retry
		    authentication, and indicates this by sending four
		    octets with all bits set, followed by the first SASL
		    authentication message of the next exchange.
		    Otherwise, the client MUST send four octets with all
		    bits cleared prior to commencing the application
		    protocol.  The server MAY abort the TLS connection
		    on authentication failure and/or
		    re-authentication.</t>

		<t>If authentication succeeds then the application
		    protocol takes over the TLS record protocol
		    contents.</t>

		<figure anchor='tlssa_1rt' title="Message flow for initial TLS connections with a one-round-trip SASL mechanism for authentication">
		    <artwork>
			<![CDATA[
   Client                                               Server

   ClientHello w/ sasl_sml
               early_start      -------->
                                                ServerHello w/
                                                   early_start
                                                      sasl_sml
                                                  Certificate*
                                            ServerKeyExchange*
                                           CertificateRequest*
                                <--------      ServerHelloDone
   Certificate*
   ClientKeyExchange
   CertificateVerify*
   [ChangeCipherSpec]
   Finished
   SASL auth message as data    -------->   
                                            [ChangeCipherSpec]
                                                      Finished
                                             SASL auth message
                                <--------      Outcome of SASL
                                                authentication
   Application Data             <------->     Application Data
			]]>
		    </artwork>
		</figure>

		<figure anchor='tlssa_resume_1rt' title="Message flow for session resumption TLS connections with a one-round-trip SASL mechanism for authentication">
		    <artwork>
			<![CDATA[
   Client                                               Server

   ClientHello w/ sasl_sml
               early_start      -------->
                                                ServerHello w/
                                                   early_start
                                                      sasl_sml
                                            [ChangeCipherSpec]
                                <--------             Finished
   Certificate*
   ClientKeyExchange
   CertificateVerify*
   [ChangeCipherSpec]
   Finished
   SASL auth message as data    -------->   
                                             SASL auth message
                                <--------      Outcome of SASL
                                                authentication
   Application Data             <------->     Application Data
			]]>
		    </artwork>
		</figure>

		<figure anchor='tlssa_1.5rt' title="Message flow for initial TLS connections with one and a half round-trip SASL mechanisms for authentication">
		    <artwork>
			<![CDATA[
   Client                                               Server

   ClientHello w/ sasl_sml
               early_start      -------->
                                                ServerHello w/
                                                   early_start
                                                      sasl_sml
                                                  Certificate*
                                            ServerKeyExchange*
                                           CertificateRequest*
                                <--------      ServerHelloDone
   Certificate*
   ClientKeyExchange
   CertificateVerify*
   [ChangeCipherSpec]
   Finished
   SASL auth message as data    -------->   
                                            [ChangeCipherSpec]
                                                      Finished
                                <--------    SASL auth message
   SASL auth message            -------->   
                                <--------      Outcome of SASL
                                                authentication
   Application Data             <------->     Application Data
			]]>
		    </artwork>
		</figure>

		<t>And with a two round trip mechanism the protocol
		    looks like:</t>

		<figure anchor='tlssa_2rt' title="Message flow for initial TLS connections with two round-trip SASL mechanisms for authentication">
		    <artwork>
			<![CDATA[
   Client                                               Server

   ClientHello w/ sasl_sml
               early_start      -------->
                                                ServerHello w/
                                                   early_start
                                                      sasl_sml
                                                  Certificate*
                                            ServerKeyExchange*
                                           CertificateRequest*
                                <--------      ServerHelloDone
   Certificate*
   ClientKeyExchange
   CertificateVerify*
   [ChangeCipherSpec]
   Finished
   SASL auth message as data    -------->   
                                            [ChangeCipherSpec]
                                                      Finished
                                <--------    SASL auth message
   SASL auth message            -------->   
                                             SASL auth message
                                <--------      Outcome of SASL
                                                authentication
   Application Data             <------->     Application Data
			]]>
		    </artwork>
		</figure>

		<t>The reader can figure out what the protocol looks
		    like for SASL mechanisms with more than two
		    round trips from the above..</t>

	    </section>

	</section>

	<section anchor='cbinding' title="Channel Binding">

	    <t>Existing TLS channel binding types that are suitable for
		use with SASL in this facility are:

		<list style='symbols'>

		    <t>tls-server-end-point <xref target='RFC5929'/></t>

		    <t>tls-unique <xref target='RFC5929'/></t>

		</list>

	    </t>

	    <t>See <xref target='RFC5929'/> and the IANA channel binding
		type registry for more information about these channel
		binding types.  TLS/SA applications MUST use the
		'tls-unique' channel binding type.</t>

	</section>

	<section anchor='applicability' title="Application Control of
	    Authentication and Applicability of TLS/SA">

	    <t>Applications that should best be able to make use of
		these extensions to optimize authentication are those
		where clients can be expected to know a priori that
		authentication will be required.  For example: LDAP,
		SMTP, IMAP4, XMPP and non-browser HTTP applications.</t>

	    <t>TLS/SA is inapplicable to applications where decisions
		about when authentication is required are made in
		context-specific manners by the application, rather than
		by the TLS layer.  Web browser-based HTTP applications
		are a good example of this.  For such applications
		TLS/SA will not be usable, either at all or without HTTP
		extensions that allow the server application to indicate
		that authentication is required, letting the client
		re-try.  Moreover, for applications that make multiple
		short-lived TLS connections there is the need to bind
		each TLS connection in an "application session" to the
		initial authentication, and we do not provide a method
		for doing this other than to authenticate each TLS
		connection.  Different methods of applying SASL/GSS-API
		authentication mechanisms will be needed for web
		applications.</t>

	    <t>Even where full TLS/SA is not applicable, the sasl_sml
		extension can be used to pre-negotiate SASL mechanisms
		in case that the application later decides that SASL
		authentication is required.</t>

	</section>

	<!--
	<section title="Using this Extension with Existing Application Protocols">

	    <t>[This section's sub-sections need to be separate I-Ds,
		though each should be so small as to make that seem like
		overkill.]</t>

	    <t>In this section and its sub-sections we NORMATIVELY
		describe how a number of existing TLS and SASL
		application protocols are modified to make use of this
		extension.</t>

	</section>
	-->

	<section anchor='non_sasl_apps' title="Contrived Examples of Non-SASL Optimizations of Existing Application Protocols">

	    <t>In this section and its sub-sections we INFORMATIVELY
		describe how a number of existing TLS application
		protocols might be modified to take advantage of the
		application data extension for optimization of the
		application protocol.  Implementors MUST NOT implement
		anything described in this section, except for
		experimental purposes only.</t>

	    <t>It is crucial that clients only use the app_hello Hello
		extension for operations that do not require that the
		user already be authenticated (the server application
		MUST reject such uses of app_hello) or that require
		privacy protection.  There are likely no operations in
		IMAP and POP3, for example, which are suitable for
		optimization via app_hello, but there are for SMTP and
		LDAP.  That's because IMAP and POP3 deal exclusively
		with user data, while SMTP and LDAP have some operations
		or objects which can be executed publicly and without
		user authentication (see below).</t>

	    <t>By starting the application protocol early these
		applications can obtain a similar round-trip
		optimization as for SASL in the TLS/SA case.</t>

	    <section title="Contrived Example: LDAP">

		<t>In the case of LDAP the app_hello extension could be
		    used to send a single LDAP message, typically a
		    search for the root DSE object.  If the server
		    supports this extension then the server's app_hello
		    Hello extension can be used to return the result.
		    If the server does not support this extension then
		    the client can repeat its search after the TLS
		    handshake is completed.</t>

		<t>LDAP applications could also use an early_start
		    request with value app_protocol and begin the LDAP
		    protocol early.  If the first operation performed
		    were an LDAP Bind then the application will obtain
		    the same round-trip optimization that we get for
		    SASL using TLS/SA.</t>

	    </section>

	    <section title="Contrived Example: SMTP">

		<t>Clients could use the app_hello Hello extension to
		    send a EHLO SMTP command to the server, and the
		    server may send the SMTP reply to it in a app_hello
		    Hello extension.</t>

	    </section>

	</section>

	<section title="Impact on TLS Concentrators">

	    <t>This protocol is designed to have minimal impact on TLS
		server-side proxies (a.k.a. concentrators).</t>

	    <t>The minimal changes to make to TLS concentrators in order
		to support this protocol are:

		<list style='symbols'>

		    <t>Add a configuration parameter through which the
			administrator may list the SASL mechanisms
			available to the application servers behind the
			concentrator;</t>

		    <t>Add support for sasl_sml Hello extension,
			using the server SASL mechanism list from the
			configuration parameter mentioned in the
			previous item;</t>

		    <t>Add a configuration parameter through which the
			administrator may indicate whether the
			application supports the 'generic-sasl' framing
			defined in <xref target='generic-sasl'/>.</t>

		    <t>Add support for early_start, which means that
			the concentrator MUST NOT consider it an error
			to receive TLS application data record messages
			prior to sending the concentrator's Finished
			message.</t>

		</list>

	    </t>

	    <t>Implementors may also want to add support for unique
		channel binding types, such as the 'tls-unique' channel
		binding type.  This requires being able to communicate
		to the application server the tls-unique channel binding
		for each TLS connection, probably via an out of band
		mechanism (though if the application protocol is HTTP
		then perhaps the concentrator could use an HTTP request
		header to do this).</t>

	    <t>Implementors may also add a way to communicate
		app_hello Hello extension to the application.</t>

	</section>

        <section title="IANA Considerations">

	    <t>By the time this document is published, the values for
		the 'sasl_sml' and 'early_start' TLS Hello extensions
		will be assined by the IANA.  The ExtensionType registry
		will have to be updated to reflect these assignments.
		(These registries require IETF Consensus.)</t>

        </section>

        <section title="Security Considerations">

	    <t>The security considerations of <xref target='RFC4422'/>,
		<xref target="RFC5246"/> and <xref target="RFC5056"/>
		apply, as do those of <xref target='RFC2743'/> when used
		via the SASL/GS2 bridge <xref target='RFC5801'/>.
		Additionally, this document has security consideration
		information throughout.</t>

	    <t>Needless to say, TLS applications that make use of TLS
		renegotiation should ensure that they use the TLS
		renegotiation indication extension <xref
		    target='RFC5746'/>.</t>

	    <t>The initial SASL authentication message should not be
		considered protected by TLS until the TLS handshake
		completes.  If a TLS cipher suite is used that does not
		authenticate the server, but a SASL mechanism is used
		that does authenticate the server, then the SASL
		exchanges should not be considered protected until
		authentication completes and succeeds.  Channel binding
		MUST be used in the optimized authentication case (but
		then, channel binding should always be used when SASL is
		used over TLS).</t>

	    <t>Non-SASL early_start application data should not be
		considered protected by TLS until the TLS handshake
		completes.</t>

	    <t>The SASL mechanism negotiation and app_hello data should
		not be considered protected by TLS until the TLS
		handshake completes, and, if the application uses SASL,
		should not be considered protected until SASL
		authentication completes successfully.</t>

        </section>

    </middle>

    <back>
        <references
	    title="Normative References">
	    &rfc2119;&rfc4422;&rfc4647;&rfc5056;&rfc5246;&rfc5646;
	    &rfc5746;
	    &rfc5801;
	    &rfc5929;
	</references>
	<references title="Informative References">
	    &rfc2660;
	    &rfc2743;
	    &rfc2818;
	    &rfc4511;
	</references>
    </back>

</rfc>
