<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY __reference.I-D.ietf-fecframe-framework SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-fecframe-framework.xml">
<!ENTITY __reference.I-D.ietf-fecframe-sdp-elements SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-fecframe-sdp-elements.xml">
<!ENTITY __reference.I-D.ietf-mmusic-rfc4756bis SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-mmusic-rfc4756bis.xml">
<!ENTITY __reference.I-D.ietf-rmt-bb-fec-raptorq SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-rmt-bb-fec-raptorq.xml">
<!ENTITY __reference.RFC.2119 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
<!ENTITY __reference.RFC.4566 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4566.xml">
<!ENTITY __reference.RFC.5052 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5052.xml">
<!ENTITY __reference.RFC.5053 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5053.xml">
]>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc iprnotified="yes" ?>
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="no" ?>
<?rfc colonspace='yes' ?>
<?rfc tocindent='yes' ?>
<rfc category="std" docName="draft-ietf-fecframe-raptor-02" ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="Raptor FEC Scheme">Raptor FEC Schemes for FECFRAME</title>

    <author fullname="Mark Watson" initials="M." surname="Watson">
      <organization>Qualcomm, Inc.</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>3165 Kifer Road</street>

          <city>Santa Clara</city>

          <region>CA</region>

          <code>95051</code>

          <country>U.S.A.</country>
        </postal>

        <email>watson@qualcomm.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date day="5" month="March" year="2010" />

    <area>Transport</area>

    <workgroup>FEC Framework</workgroup>

    <abstract>
      <t>This document describes Fully-Specified Forward Error Correction
      (FEC) Schemes for the Raptor and RaptorQ codes and their application to
      reliable delivery of media streams in the context of FEC Framework. The
      Raptor and RaptorQ codes are systematic codes, where a number of repair
      symbols are generated from a set of source symbols and sent in one or
      more repair flows in addition to the source symbols that are sent to the
      receiver(s) within a source flow. The Raptor and RaptorQ codes offer
      close to optimal protection against arbitrary packet losses at a low
      computational complexity. Six FEC Schemes are defined, two for
      protection of arbitrary packet flows, two that are optimised for small
      source blocks and another two for protection of a single flow that
      already contains a sequence number. Repair data may be sent over
      arbitrary datagram transport (e.g. UDP) or using RTP.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>The FEC Framework <xref target="I-D.ietf-fecframe-framework"> </xref>
      describes a framework for the application of Forward Error Correction to
      arbitrary packet flows. Modelled after the FEC Building Block developed
      by the IETF Reliable Multicast Transport working group <xref
      target="RFC5052"></xref>, the FEC Framework defines the concept of FEC
      Schemes which provide specific Forward Error Correction schemes. This
      document describes six FEC Schemes which make use of the Raptor and
      RaptorQ FEC codes as defined in <xref target="RFC5053"></xref> and <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-rmt-bb-fec-raptorq"></xref>.</t>

      <t>The FEC protection mechanism is independent of the type of the source
      data, which can be an arbitrary sequence of packets, including for
      example audio or video data. In general, the operation of the protection
      mechanism is as follows:</t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>The sender determines a set of source packets (a source block) to
          be protected together based on the FEC Framework Configuration
          Information.</t>

          <t>The sender arranges the source packets into a set of source
          symbols, each of which is the same size.</t>

          <t>The sender applies the Raptor protection operation on the source
          symbols to generate the required number of repair symbols.</t>

          <t>The sender packetizes the repair symbols and sends the repair
          packet(s) along with the source packets to the receiver(s).</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>Per the FEC Framework requirements, the sender MUST transmit the
      source and repair packets in different source and repair flows, or in
      the case RTP transport is used for Repair packets, in different RTP
      streams. At the receiver side, if all of the source packets are
      successfully received, there is no need for FEC recovery and the repair
      packets are discarded. However, if there are missing source packets, the
      repair packets can be used to recover the missing information.</t>

      <t>The operation of the FEC mechanism requires that the receiver can
      identify the relationships between received source packets and repair
      packets and in particular which source packets are missing. In many
      cases, data already exists in the source packets which can be used to
      refer to source packets and to identify which packets are missing. In
      this case we assume it is possible to derive a "sequence number"
      directly or indirectly from the source packets and this sequence number
      can be used within the FEC Scheme. This case is referred to as a "single
      sequenced flow". In this case the FEC Source Payload ID defined in <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-fecframe-framework"></xref> is empty and the source
      packets are not modified by the application of FEC, with obvious
      backwards compatibility advantages.</t>

      <t>Otherwise, it is necessary to add data to the source packets for FEC
      purposes in the form of a non-empty FEC Source Payload ID. This case if
      referred to as the "arbitrary packet flow" case. Accordingly, this
      document defines two FEC Schemes, one for the case of a single sequenced
      flow and another for the case of arbitrary packet flows.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Document Outline">
      <t>This document is organised as follows: <list>
          <t><xref target="GeneralProcedures"> </xref> defines general
          procedures applicable to the use of the Raptor and RaptorQ codes in
          the context of the FEC Framework.</t>

          <t><xref target="ArbitraryFlowScheme"></xref>defines an FEC Scheme
          for the case of arbitrary source flows and follows the format
          defined for FEC Schemes in <xref
          target="I-D.ietf-fecframe-framework"></xref>. When used with Raptor
          codes, this scheme is equivalent to that defined in <xref
          target="MBMSTS"></xref>.</t>

          <t><xref target="OptimisedArbitraryFlowScheme"></xref> defines an
          FEC Scheme similar to that defined in <xref
          target="ArbitraryFlowScheme"> </xref>but with optimisations for the
          case where only limited source block sizes are required. When used
          with Raptor codes, this scheme is equivalent to that defined in
          <xref target="dvbts"></xref> for arbitrary packet flows.</t>

          <t><xref target="SingleFlowScheme"></xref> defines an FEC Scheme for
          the case of a single flow which is already provided with a source
          packet sequence number. When used with Raptor codes, this scheme is
          equivalent to that defined in <xref target="dvbts"></xref> for the
          case of a single sequenced flow.</t>
        </list></t>
    </section>

    <section title="Requirements Notation">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
      document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
      target="RFC2119"></xref>.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Definitions and Abbreviations">
      <t>The definitions, notations and abbreviations commonly used in this
      document are summarized in this section.</t>

      <section title="Definitions">
        <t>This document uses the following definitions. For further
        definitions that apply to FEC Framework in general, see <xref
        target="I-D.ietf-fecframe-framework"></xref>.</t>

        <t>Source Flow: The packet flow(s) or stream(s) carrying the source
        data and to which FEC protection is to be applied.</t>

        <t>Repair Flow: The packet flow(s) or stream(s) carrying the repair
        data.</t>

        <t>Symbol: A unit of data. Its size, in bytes, is referred to as the
        symbol size.</t>

        <t>Source Symbol: The smallest unit of data used during the encoding
        process.</t>

        <t>Repair Symbol: Repair symbols are generated from the source
        symbols.</t>

        <t>Source Packet: Data packets that contain only source symbols.</t>

        <t>Repair Packet: Data packets that contain only repair symbols.</t>

        <t>Source Block: A block of source symbols that are considered
        together in the encoding process.</t>

        <t>FEC Framework Configuration Information: Information that controls
        the operation of the FEC Framework. Each FEC Framework instance has
        its own configuration information.</t>

        <t>FEC Payload ID: Information that identifies the contents of a
        packet with respect to the FEC scheme.</t>

        <t>Source FEC Payload ID: An FEC Payload ID specifically used with
        source packets.</t>

        <t>Repair FEC Payload ID: An FEC Payload ID specifically used with
        repair packets.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Abbreviations">
        <t><list style="symbols">
            <t>FSSI: FEC-Scheme-Specific Information.</t>

            <t>SS-FSSI: Sender-Side FEC-Scheme-Specific Information.</t>

            <t>RS-FSSI: Receiver-Side FEC-Scheme-Specific Information.</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="GeneralProcedures"
             title="General procedures for Raptor FEC Schemes">
      <t>This section specifies general procedures which apply to all Raptor
      and RaptorQ FEC Schemes, specifically the construction of source symbols
      from a set of source transport payloads. As described in <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-fecframe-framework"> </xref> for each Application Data
      Unit in a source block, the FEC Scheme is provided with:</t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>A description of the source data flow with which the Application
          Data Unit is associated and an integer identifier associated with
          that flow.</t>

          <t>The Application Data Unit itself.</t>

          <t>The length of the Application Data Unit.</t>
        </list>For each Application Data Unit, we define the Application Data
      Unit Information (ADUI) as follows:</t>

      <t>Let</t>

      <t><list>
          <t>n be the number of Application Data Units in the source
          block.</t>

          <t>T be the source symbol size in bytes. Note: this information is
          provided by the FEC Scheme as defined below.</t>

          <t>i the index to the (i+1)-th Application Data Unit to be added to
          the source block, 0 &lt;= i &lt; n.</t>

          <t>R[i] denote the number of octets in the (i+1)-th Application Data
          Unit.</t>

          <t>l[i] be a length indication associated with the i-th Application
          Data Unit &ndash; the nature of the length indication is defined by
          the FEC Scheme.</t>

          <t>L[i] denote two octets representing the value of l[i] in network
          byte order (high order octet first) of the i-th Application Data
          Unit.</t>

          <t>f[i] denote the integer identifier associated with the source
          data flow from which the i-th Application Data Unit was taken.</t>

          <t>F[i] denote a single octet representing the value of f[i].</t>

          <t>s[i] be the smallest integer such that s[i]*T &gt;= (l[i]+3).
          Note s[i] is the length of SPI[i] in units of symbols of size T
          bytes.</t>

          <t>P[i] denote s[i]*T-(l[i]+3) zero octets. Note: P[i] are padding
          octets to align the start of each UDP packet with the start of a
          symbol.</t>

          <t>ADUI[i] be the concatenation of F[i] ,L[i], R[i] and P[i].</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>Then, a source data block is constructed by concatenating ADUI[i] for
      i = 0, 1, 2, ... n-1. The source data block size, S, is then given by
      sum {s[i]*T, i=0, ..., n-1}. Symbols are allocated integer Encoding
      Symbol IDs consecutively starting from zero within the source block.
      Each Application Data Unit is associated with the Encoding Symbol ID of
      the first symbol containing SPI for that packet. Thus, the Encoding
      Symbol ID value associated with the j-th source packet, ESI[j], is given
      by ESI[j] = 0, for j=0 and ESI[j] = sum{s[i], i=0,...,(j-1)}, for 0 &lt;
      j &lt; n.</t>

      <t>Source blocks are identified by integer Source Block Numbers. This
      specification does not specify how Source Block Numbers are allocated to
      source blocks. The Source FEC Packet Identification Information consists
      of the identity of the source block and the Encoding Symbol ID
      associated with the packet.</t>

      <t></t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="ArbitraryFlowScheme"
             title="Raptor FEC Schemes for arbitrary packet flows">
      <section title="Introduction">
        <t>This section specifies an FEC Scheme for the application of the
        Raptor and RaptorQ codes to arbitary packet flows. This scheme is
        recommended in scenarios where maximal generality is required.</t>

        <t>When used with Raptor codes, this scheme is equivalent to that
        specified in <xref target="MBMSTS"></xref>.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Formats and Codes">
        <section title="FEC Framework Configuration Information">
          <section title="FEC Scheme ID">
            <t>The value of the FEC Scheme ID for the fully-specified FEC
            scheme defined in this section is XXX when <xref
            target="RFC5053"></xref> is used and YYY when <xref
            target="I-D.ietf-rmt-bb-fec-raptorq"></xref> is used, as assigned
            by IANA.</t>
          </section>

          <section anchor="ArbitraryFSSISection"
                   title="Scheme-Specific Elements">
            <t>The scheme-specific elements of the FEC Framework Configuration
            information for this scheme are as follows:</t>

            <t><list style="hanging">
                <t hangText="Maximum Source Block Length">Name: <spanx
                style="verb">Kmax</spanx>, Value range: A decimal non-negative
                integer less than 8192 (for Raptor) or 56405 (for RaptorQ), in
                units of symbols</t>

                <t hangText="Encoding Symbol Size">Name: <spanx style="verb">T</spanx>,
                Value range: A decimal non-negative integer less than 65536,
                in units of bytes</t>

                <t hangText="Payload ID Format">Name: <spanx style="verb">P</spanx>,
                Value range: "A" or "B"</t>
              </list></t>

            <t>An encoding format for The Maximum Source Block Length and
            Encoding Symbol Size is defined below.</t>

            <t><figure anchor="ArbitraryFSSI"
                title="FEC Scheme Specific Information">
                <preamble></preamble>

                <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
                         1                   2                   3
     0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
    |       Symbol Size (T)         |Max. Source Block Length (Kmax)|
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
    |P|  Reserved   |
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
    ]]></artwork>

                <postamble></postamble>
              </figure>The P bit shall be set to zero to indicate Format A or
            to 1 to indicate Format B. The last octet of the above encoding
            may be omitted, in which case Format A shall be assumed.</t>

            <t>The Payload ID Format identifier defines which of the Source
            FEC Payload ID and Repair FEC Payload ID formats defined below
            shall be used. Payload ID Format B SHALL NOT be used when<xref
            target="RFC5053"></xref> is used.</t>
          </section>
        </section>

        <section anchor="SourceFECPayloadID" title="Source FEC Payload ID">
          <t>This scheme makes use of an Explicit Source FEC Payload ID, which
          is appended to the end of the source packets. Two formats are
          defined for the Source FEC Payload ID, format A and format B. The
          format that is used is signalled as part of the FEC Framework
          Configuration Information</t>

          <t><figure anchor="SourceFECPayloadIDFigureA"
              title="Source FEC Payload ID - Format A">
              <preamble></preamble>

              <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
                     1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|   Source Block Number (SBN)   |   Encoding Symbol ID (ESI)    |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
]]></artwork>

              <postamble></postamble>
            </figure></t>

          <t>Source Block Number (SBN), (16 bits): An integer identifier for
          the source block that the source data within the packet relates
          to.</t>

          <t>Encoding Symbol ID (ESI), (16 bits): The starting symbol index of
          the source packet in the source block.</t>

          <t><figure anchor="SourceFECPayloadIDFigureB"
              title="Source FEC Payload ID - Format B">
              <preamble></preamble>

              <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
                     1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|      SBN      |            Encoding Symbol ID (ESI)           |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
]]></artwork>

              <postamble></postamble>
            </figure></t>

          <t>Source Block Number (SBN), (8 bits): An integer identifier for
          the source block that the source data within the packet relates
          to.</t>

          <t>Encoding Symbol ID (ESI), (24 bits): The starting symbol index of
          the source packet in the source block</t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="RepairFECPayloadID" title="Repair FEC Payload ID">
          <t>Two formats for the Repair FEC Payload ID, Format A and Format B
          are defined below:</t>

          <t><figure title="Repair FEC Payload ID - Format A">
              <preamble></preamble>

              <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
                     1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|   Source Block Number (SBN)   |   Encoding Symbol ID (ESI)    |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|   Source Block Length (SBL)   |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
]]></artwork>

              <postamble></postamble>
            </figure></t>

          <t><figure title="Repair FEC Payload ID - Format B">
              <preamble></preamble>

              <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
                     1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|      SBN      |            Encoding Symbol ID (ESI)           |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|   Source Block Length (SBL)   |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
]]></artwork>

              <postamble></postamble>
            </figure></t>

          <t><list style="hanging">
              <t hangText="Source Block Number (SBN), (16 bits)">An integer
              identifier for the source block that the repair symbols within
              the packet relate to.</t>

              <t hangText="Encoding Symbol ID (ESI), (16 bits)">Integer
              identifier for the encoding symbols within the packet.</t>

              <t hangText="Source Block Length (SBL), (16 bits)">The number of
              source symbols in the source block.</t>
            </list></t>

          <t>The interpretation of the Source Block Number, Encoding Symbol
          Identifier and Source Block Length is defined by the FEC Code
          Specification.</t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section title="Procedures">
        <section anchor="SourceSymbolSection"
                 title="Source symbol construction">
          <t>This FEC Scheme uses the procedures defined in <xref
          target="GeneralProcedures"></xref> to construct a set of source
          symbols to which the FEC code can be applied. The sender MUST
          allocate Source Block Numbers to source blocks sequentially,
          wrapping around to zero after Source Block Number 65535 (Format A)
          or 255 (Format B).</t>

          <t>During the construction of the source block:</t>

          <t><list style="symbols">
              <t>the length indication, l[i], included in the Source Packet
              Information for each packet shall be the transport payload
              length.</t>

              <t>the value of s[i] in the construction of the Source Packet
              Information for each packet shall be the smallest integer such
              that s[i]*T &gt;= (l[i]+3).</t>
            </list></t>
        </section>

        <section title="Repair packet construction">
          <t>The number of repair symbols contained within a repair packet is
          computed from the packet length. The ESI value placed into a repair
          packet is given by the following formula:</t>

          <t>ESI_repair = I_repair + SBL,</t>

          <t>where I_repair is the index of the repair symbol in the sequence
          of repair symbols generated according to <xref
          target="FECSpecificationSection"></xref>, where the first repair
          symbol has index 0, the second index 1 etc. and SBL is the Source
          Block Length. The Source Block Length field of the Repair FEC
          Payload ID field SHALL be set to the number of symbols included in
          the Source Packet Information of packets associated with the source
          block.</t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section anchor="FECSpecificationSection" title="FEC Code Specification">
        <t>The Raptor FEC encoder defined in <xref target="RFC5053"></xref> or
        <xref target="I-D.ietf-rmt-bb-fec-raptorq"></xref> SHALL be used. The
        source symbols passed to the Raptor FEC encoder SHALL consist of the
        source symbols constructed according to <xref
        target="SourceSymbolSection"></xref>. Thus the value of the parameter
        K used by the FEC encoder (equal to the Source Block Length) may vary
        amongst the blocks of the stream but SHALL NOT exceed the Maximum
        Source Block Length signalled in the FEC Scheme-specific information.
        The symbol size, T, to be used for source block construction and the
        repair symbol construction is equal to the Encoding Symbol Size
        signaled in the FEC Scheme Specific Information.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="OptimisedArbitraryFlowScheme"
             title="Optimised Raptor FEC Scheme for arbitrary packet flows">
      <section title="Introduction">
        <t>This section specifies a slightly modified version of the FEC
        Scheme specified in <xref target="ArbitraryFlowScheme"></xref> which
        is applicable to scenarios in which only relatively small block sizes
        will be used. These modifications admit substantial optimisations to
        both sender and receiver implementations.</t>

        <t>In outline, the modifications are:</t>

        <t><list style="empty">
            <t>All source blocks within a stream are encoded using the same
            source block size. Code shortening is used to encode blocks of
            different sizes. This is achieved by padding every block to the
            required size using zero symbols before encoding. The zero symbols
            are then discarded after decoding. The source block size to be
            used for a stream is signalled in the Maximum Source Block Size
            field of the scheme-specific information. This allows for
            efficient parallel encoding of multiple streams.</t>

            <t>A restricted set of possible source block sizes is specified.
            This allows explicit operation sequences for encoding the
            restricted set of block sizes to be pre-calculated and embedded in
            software or handware.</t>
          </list> This scheme is equivalent to that specified in <xref
        target="dvbts"></xref> for arbitrary packet flows.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Formats and Codes">
        <section title="FEC Framework Configuration Information">
          <section title="FEC Scheme ID">
            <t>The value of the FEC Scheme ID for the fully-specified FEC
            scheme defined in this section is XXX when <xref
            target="RFC5053"></xref> is used and YYY when <xref
            target="I-D.ietf-rmt-bb-fec-raptorq"></xref> is used, as assigned
            by IANA.</t>
          </section>

          <section title="FEC Scheme specific information">
            <t>See <xref target="ArbitraryFSSISection">.</xref></t>
          </section>
        </section>

        <section title="Source FEC Payload ID">
          <t>See <xref target="SourceFECPayloadID">.</xref></t>
        </section>

        <section title="Repair FEC Payload ID">
          <t>See<xref target="RepairFECPayloadID"> </xref></t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section title="Procedures">
        <section title="Source symbol construction">
          <t>See <xref target="SourceSymbolSection"></xref></t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="OptimisedRepairPacketSection"
                 title="Repair packet construction">
          <t>The number of repair symbols contained within a repair packet is
          computed from the packet length. The ESI value placed into a repair
          packet is given by the following formula:</t>

          <t>ESI_repair = I_repair + MSBL</t>

          <t>Where I_repair is the index of the repair symbol in the sequence
          of repair symbols generated according to <xref
          target="FECSpecificationSection"></xref>, where the first repair
          symbol has index 0, the second index 1 etc. and MSBL is the Maximum
          Source Block Length signalled in the FEC Scheme Specific
          Information. The Source Block Length field of the Repair FEC Payload
          ID field SHALL be set to the number of symbols included in the
          Source Packet Information of packets associated with the source
          block.</t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section anchor="OptimisedFECSpecificationSection"
               title="FEC Code Specification">
        <t>The Raptor FEC encoder defined in <xref target="RFC5053"></xref> or
        <xref target="I-D.ietf-rmt-bb-fec-raptorq"></xref> SHALL be used. The
        source symbols passed to the Raptor FEC encoder SHALL consist of the
        source symbols constructed according to <xref
        target="SourceSymbolSection"></xref> extended with zero or more
        padding symbols such that the total number of symbols in the source
        block is equal to the Maximum Source Block Length signaled in the FEC
        Scheme Specific Information. Thus the value of the parameter K used by
        the FEC encoded is equal to the Maximum Source Block Length for all
        blocks of the stream. Padding symbols shall consist entirely of bytes
        set to the value zero. The symbol size, T, to be used for source block
        construction and the repair symbol construction is equal to the
        Encoding Symbol Size signaled in the FEC Scheme Specific
        Information.</t>

        <t>When <xref target="RFC5053"></xref> is used, the parameter T SHALL
        be set such that the number of source symbols in any source block is
        at most 8192. The Maximum Source Block Length parameter &ndash; and
        hence the number of symbols used in the FEC Encoding and Decoding
        operations - SHALL be set to one of the following values:</t>

        <t><list>
            <t>101, 120, 148, 164, 212, 237, 297, 371, 450, 560, 680, 842,
            1031, 1139, 1281</t>
          </list>When <xref target="I-D.ietf-rmt-bb-fec-raptorq"></xref> is
        used, the parameter T SHALL be set such that the number of source
        symbols in any source block is less than 56404. The Maximum Source
        Block Length parameter SHALL be set to one of the supported vaoues for
        K' defined in Section 5.6 of <xref
        target="I-D.ietf-rmt-bb-fec-raptorq"></xref>.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="SingleFlowScheme"
             title="Raptor FEC Scheme for a single sequenced flow">
      <section title="Formats and codes">
        <section title="FEC Framework Configuration Information">
          <section title="FEC Scheme ID">
            <t>The value of the FEC Scheme ID for the fully-specified FEC
            scheme defined in this section is XXX when <xref
            target="RFC5053"></xref> is used and YYY when <xref
            target="I-D.ietf-rmt-bb-fec-raptorq"></xref> is used, as assigned
            by IANA.</t>
          </section>

          <section title="Scheme-specific elements">
            <t>See <xref target="ArbitraryFSSISection"></xref></t>
          </section>
        </section>

        <section title="Source FEC Payload ID">
          <t>The Source FEC Payload ID field is not used by this FEC Scheme.
          Source packets are not modified by this FEC Scheme.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Repair FEC Payload ID">
          <t>Two formats for the Repair FEC Payload ID are defined, Format A
          and Format B.</t>

          <t><figure anchor="RepairFECPayloadID2A"
              title="Repair FEC Payload ID - Format A">
              <preamble></preamble>

              <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[                     1                   2                   3   
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|    Initial Sequence Number    |      Encoding Symbol ID       |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|      Source Block Length      |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
]]></artwork>

              <postamble></postamble>
            </figure><list style="hanging">
              <t
              hangText="Initial Sequence Number (Flow i ISN) &ndash; 16 bits">This
              field specifies the lowest 16 bits of the sequence number of the
              first packet to be included in this sub-block. If the sequence
              numbers are shorter than 16 bits then the received Sequence
              Number SHALL be logically padded with zero bits to become 16
              bits in length respectively.</t>

              <t hangText="Encoding Symbol ID (ESI) &ndash; 16 bits">This
              field indicates which repair symbols are contained within this
              repair packet. The ESI provided is the ESI of the first repair
              symbol in the packet.</t>

              <t hangText="Source Block Length (SBL) &ndash; 16 bits">This
              field specifies the length of the source block in symbols.</t>
            </list><figure anchor="RepairFECPayloadID2B"
              title="Repair FEC Payload ID - Format B">
              <preamble></preamble>

              <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[                     1                   2                   3   
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|    Initial Sequence Number    |      Source Block Length      |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                 Encoding Symbol ID            |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
]]></artwork>

              <postamble></postamble>
            </figure><list style="hanging">
              <t
              hangText="Initial Sequence Number (Flow i ISN) &ndash; 16 bits">This
              field specifies the lowest 16 bits of the sequence number of the
              first packet to be included in this sub-block. If the sequence
              numbers are shorter than 16 bits then the received Sequence
              Number SHALL be logically padded with zero bits to become 16
              bits in length respectively.</t>

              <t hangText="Encoding Symbol ID (ESI) &ndash; 16 bits">This
              field indicates which repair symbols are contained within this
              repair packet. The ESI provided is the ESI of the first repair
              symbol in the packet.</t>

              <t hangText="Source Block Length (SBL) &ndash; 16 bits">This
              field specifies the length of the source block in symbols.</t>
            </list></t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section title="Procedures">
        <section title="Source symbol construction">
          <t>This FEC Scheme uses the procedures defined in <xref
          target="GeneralProcedures"></xref> to construct a set of source
          symbols to which the FEC code can be applied. The sender MUST
          allocate Source Block Numbers to source blocks sequentially,
          wrapping around to zero after Source Block Number 65535 in the case
          Format A is used for FEC Payload IDs and 255 in the case Format B is
          used for FEC Payload IDs.</t>

          <t>During the construction of the source block:</t>

          <t><list style="symbols">
              <t>the length indication, l[i], included in the Source Packet
              Information for each packet shall be dependent on the protocol
              carried within the transport payload. Rules for RTP are
              specified below.</t>

              <t>the value of s[i] in the construction of the Source Packet
              Information for each packet shall be the smallest integer such
              that s[i]*T &gt;= (l[i]+3)</t>
            </list></t>
        </section>

        <section title="Derivation of Source FEC Packet Identification Information">
          <t>The Source FEC Packet Identification Information for a source
          packet is derived from the sequence number of the packet and
          information received in any Repair FEC packet belonging to this
          Source Block. Source blocks are identified by the sequence number of
          the first source packet in the block. This information is signaled
          in all Repair FEC packets associated with the source block in the
          Initial Sequence Number field.</t>

          <t>The length of the Source Packet Information (in bytes) for source
          packets within a source block is equal to length of the payload
          containing encoding symbols of the repair packets (i.e. not
          including the Repair FEC Payload ID) for that block, which MUST be
          the same for all repair packets. The Application Data Unit
          Information Length (ADUIL) in symbols is equal to this length
          divided by the Encoding Symbol Size (which is signaled in the FEC
          Framework Configuration Information). The set of source packets
          which are included in the source block is determined from the
          Initial Sequence Number (ISN) and Source Block Length (SBL) as
          follows:</t>

          <t>Let,</t>

          <t><list style="empty">
              <t>I be the Initial Sequence Number of the source block</t>

              <t>LP be the Source Packet Information Length in symbols</t>

              <t>LB be the Source Block Length in symbols</t>
            </list>Then, source packets with sequence numbers from I to I
          +LB/LP-1 inclusive are included in the source block.</t>

          <t>Note that if no FEC Repair packets are received then no FEC
          decoding is possible and it is unnecessary for the receiver to
          identify the Source FEC Packet Identification Information for the
          source packets.</t>

          <t>The Encoding Symbol ID for a packet is derived from the following
          information:</t>

          <t><list>
              <t>The sequence number, Ns, of the packet</t>

              <t>The Source Packet Information Length for the source block,
              LP</t>

              <t>The Initial Sequence Number of the source block, I</t>
            </list>Then the Encoding Symbol ID for packet with sequence number
          Ns is determined by the following formula:</t>

          <t><list>
              <t>ESI = ( Ns - I ) * LP</t>
            </list>Note that all repair packet associated to a given Source
          Block MUST contain the same Source Block Length and Initial Sequence
          Number.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Repair packet construction">
          <t>See <xref target="OptimisedRepairPacketSection"></xref></t>
        </section>

        <section title="Procedures for RTP source flows">
          <t>In the specific case of RTP source packet flows, then the RTP
          Sequence Number field SHALL be used as the sequence number in the
          procedures described above. The length indication included in the
          Application Data Unit Information SHALL be the RTP payload length
          plus the length of the CSRCs, if any, the RTP Header Extension, if
          present, and the RTP padding bytes, if any. Note that this length is
          always equal to the UDP payload length of the packet minus 12.</t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section title="FEC Code Specification">
        <t>See <xref target="OptimisedFECSpecificationSection"></xref></t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="SecuritySection" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>For the general security considerations related to the use of FEC,
      refer to <xref target="I-D.ietf-fecframe-framework"></xref>. No security
      considerations specific to this document have been identified.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Session Description Protocol (SDP) Signaling">
      <t>This section provides an SDP <xref target="RFC4566"></xref> example.
      The following example uses the SDP elements for FEC Framework, which
      were introduced in <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-fecframe-sdp-elements"></xref>, and the FEC grouping
      semantics <xref target="I-D.ietf-mmusic-rfc4756bis"></xref>.</t>

      <t>In this example, we have one source video stream (mid:S1) and one FEC
      repair stream (mid:R1). We form one FEC group with the "a=group:FEC S1
      R1" line. The source and repair streams are sent to the same port on
      different multicast groups. The repair window is set to 200 ms.</t>

      <t><figure>
          <preamble></preamble>

          <artwork><![CDATA[     v=0
     o=ali 1122334455 1122334466 IN IP4 fec.example.com
     s=Raptor FEC Example
     t=0 0
     a=group:FEC S1 R1
     m=video 30000 RTP/AVP 100
     c=IN IP4 233.252.0.1/127
     a=rtpmap:100 MP2T/90000
     a=fec-source-flow: id=0; tag-len=4
     a=mid:S1
     m=application 30000 udp/fec
     c=IN IP4 233.252.0.2/127
     a=fec-repair-flow: encoding-id=0; fssi=Kmax:8192,T:128,P:A
     a=repair-window:200
     a=mid:R1
]]></artwork>
        </figure></t>
    </section>

    <section title="Congestion Control Considerations">
      <t>For the general congestion control considerations related to the use
      of FEC, refer to <xref target="I-D.ietf-fecframe-framework"></xref>.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="IANASection" title="IANA Considerations">
      <section title="Registration of FEC Scheme IDs">
        <t>The value of FEC Scheme IDs is subject to IANA registration. For
        general guidelines on IANA considerations as they apply to this
        document, refer to <xref
        target="I-D.ietf-fecframe-framework"></xref>.</t>

        <t>This document registers three values in the FEC Framework
        (FECFRAME) FEC Encoding IDs registry as follows:</t>

        <t><list style="symbols">
            <t>XXX for the Raptor FEC Scheme for Arbitrary Packet Flows (<xref
            target="ArbitraryFlowScheme"></xref> using Raptor <xref
            target="RFC5053"></xref>.</t>

            <t>XXX for the Raptor FEC Scheme for Arbitrary Packet Flows (<xref
            target="ArbitraryFlowScheme"></xref> using RaptorQ <xref
            target="I-D.ietf-rmt-bb-fec-raptorq"></xref>.</t>

            <t>XXX for the Optimised Raptor FEC Scheme for Arbitrary Packet
            Flows (<xref target="OptimisedArbitraryFlowScheme"></xref>) using
            Raptor <xref target="RFC5053"></xref>.</t>

            <t>XXX for the Optimised Raptor FEC Scheme for Arbitrary Packet
            Flows (<xref target="OptimisedArbitraryFlowScheme"></xref>) using
            RaptorQ <xref target="I-D.ietf-rmt-bb-fec-raptorq"></xref>.</t>

            <t>XXX for the Raptor FEC Scheme for a single sequence flow (<xref
            target="SingleFlowScheme"></xref>) using Raptor <xref
            target="RFC5053"></xref>.</t>

            <t>XXX for the Raptor FEC Scheme for a single sequence flow (<xref
            target="SingleFlowScheme"></xref>) using RaptorQ <xref
            target="I-D.ietf-rmt-bb-fec-raptorq"></xref>.</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      &__reference.I-D.ietf-fecframe-framework;

      &__reference.I-D.ietf-fecframe-sdp-elements;

      &__reference.RFC.5052;

      &__reference.RFC.5053;

      &__reference.RFC.2119;

      &__reference.RFC.4566;

      &__reference.I-D.ietf-mmusic-rfc4756bis;

      &__reference.I-D.ietf-rmt-bb-fec-raptorq;

      <reference anchor="dvbts">
        <front>
          <title>ETSI TS 102 034 - Digital Video Broadcasting (DVB); Transport
          of MPEG-2 Based DVB Services over IP Based Networks</title>

          <author>
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date day="1" month="March" year="2005" />
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="MBMSTS">
        <front>
          <title>Multimedia Broadcast/Multicast Service (MBMS); Protocols and
          codecs</title>

          <author>
            <organization>3GPP</organization>
          </author>

          <date day="01" month="April" year="2005" />
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="3GPP TS" value="26.346" />

        <format target="http://www.3gpp.org/ftp/Specs/html-info/26346.htm"
                type="HTML" />
      </reference>
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
