<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='http://xml.resource.org/authoring/rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY rfc2119 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc2250 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2250.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc3611 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3611.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc3357 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3357.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc3550 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3550.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc4566 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4566.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc5216 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5216.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc5234 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5234.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc5296 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5296.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc5247 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5247.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.ietf-avt-rapid-rtp-sync PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-avt-rapid-rtp-sync.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.ietf-pmol-metrics-framework PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-pmol-metrics-framework.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.hunt-avt-monarch PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.hunt-avt-monarch.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.ietf-avt-rtp-svc PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-avt-rtp-svc.xml">
]>
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="yes" ?>
<rfc category="std" docName="draft-ietf-xrblock-rtcp-xr-synchronization-07"
     ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="SDO Report Blocks">RTP Control Protocol (RTCP) Extended
    Report (XR) Blocks for Synchronization Delay and Offset Metrics
    Reporting</title>

    <author fullname="Hitoshi Asaeda" initials="H" surname="Asaeda">
      <organization abbrev="NICT">National Institute of Information and
      Communications Technology</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>4-2-1 Nukui-Kitamachi</street>

          <city>Koganei</city>

          <region>Tokyo</region>

          <code>184-8795</code>

          <country>Japan</country>
        </postal>

        <email>asaeda@nict.go.jp</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Qin Wu" initials="Q" surname="Wu">
      <organization abbrev="Huawei">Huawei Technologies Co.,
      Ltd.</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>101 Software Avenue, Yuhua District</street>

          <city>Nanjing</city>

          <region>Jiangsu</region>

          <code>210012</code>

          <country>China</country>
        </postal>

        <email>sunseawq@huawei.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Rachel Huang" initials="R" surname="Huang">
      <organization abbrev="Huawei">Huawei Technologies Co.,
      Ltd.</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>101 Software Avenue, Yuhua District</street>

          <city>Nanjing</city>

          <region>Jiangsu</region>

          <code>210012</code>

          <country>China</country>
        </postal>

        <email>Rachel@huawei.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date year="2013" />

    <abstract>
      <t>This document defines two RTP Control Protocol (RTCP) Extended Report
      (XR) Blocks that allow the reporting of synchronization delay and offset
      metrics for use in a range of RTP applications.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <section title="Synchronization Delay and Offset Metrics Reporting Blocks">
        <t>This document defines two new block types to augment those defined
        in <xref target="RFC3611"></xref>, for use in a range of RTP
        applications.</t>

        <t>The first new block type supports reporting of Initial
        Synchronization Delay to establish multimedia session. Information is
        recorded about time difference between the start of RTP sessions and
        the time the RTP receiver acquires all components of RTP sessions in
        the multimedia session <xref target="RFC6051"></xref>.</t>

        <t>The second new block type supports reporting of the relative
        synchronization offset time of two arbitrary streams (e.g., between
        audio and video streams), with the same RTCP CNAME included in RTCP
        SDES packets <xref target="RFC3550"></xref>.</t>

        <t>These metrics belong to the class of transport level metrics
        defined in <xref target="RFC6792"></xref>.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="RTCP and RTCP XR Reports">
        <t>The use of RTCP for reporting is defined in <xref
        target="RFC3550"></xref>. <xref target="RFC3611"></xref> defined an
        extensible structure for reporting using an RTCP Extended Report (XR).
        This document defines a new Extended Report block for use with <xref
        target="RFC3550"></xref> and <xref target="RFC3611"></xref>.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Performance Metrics Framework">
        <t>The RTP Monitoring Architectures <xref target="RFC6792"></xref>
        provides guideline for reporting block format using RTCP XR. The new
        report block described in this memo is in compliance with the
        monitoring architecture specified in <xref
        target="RFC6792"></xref>.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Applicability">
        <t>When joining each session in layered video sessions <xref
        target="RFC6190"></xref> or the multimedia session, a receiver may not
        synchronize playout across the multimedia session or layered video
        session until RTCP SR packets have been received on all components of
        RTP sessions. The component RTP session are referred to as each RTP
        session for each media type in multimedia session or separate RTP
        session for each layer in the layered video session. For multicast
        session, the initial synchronization delay metric varies with the
        session bandwidth, the number of members, and the number of senders in
        the session. The RTP flow Initial synchronization delay block defined
        in this document can be used to report such metric, i.e., the initial
        synchronization delay to receive all the RTP streams belonging to the
        same multimedia session or layered video session. In the absence of
        packet loss, the initial synchronization delay equals to the average
        time taken to receive the first RTCP packet in the RTP session with
        the longest RTCP reporting interval. In the presence of packet loss,
        the media synchronization should rely on the in-band mapping of RTP
        and NTP-format timestamps <xref target="RFC6051"></xref> or wait until
        the reporting interval has passed, and the next RTCP SR packet is
        sent.</t>

        <t>Receivers of the RTP flow initial synchronization delay block could
        use this metric to compare with targets (i.e., Service Level Agreement
        or thresholds of the system) to help ensure the quality of real-time
        application performance.</t>

        <t>In an RTP multimedia session, there can be an arbitrary number of
        streams carried in different RTP sessions, with the same RTCP CNAME.
        These streams may be not synchronized with each other. For example,
        one audio stream and one video stream belong to the same session, and
        the audio stream is transmitted lagging behind video stream for
        multiple tens of milliseconds <xref target="TR-126"></xref>. The RTP
        Flows Synchronization Offset block can be used to report such
        synchronization offset between video stream and audio stream. This
        block is also applied to the case where an RTP session can contain
        media streams with media from multiple media types. The metrics
        defined in the RTP flows synchronization Offset block can be used by
        network manager for trouble shooting and dealing with user experience
        issues.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Terminology">
      <section title="Standards Language">
        <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
        "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
        document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
        target="RFC2119">RFC 2119</xref>.</t>

        <t>In addition, the following terms are defined:</t>

        <t><list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="Initial Synchronization Delay:"><vspace
            blankLines="1" />A multimedia session comprises a set of
            concurrent RTP sessions among a common group of participants,
            using one RTP session for each media type. The initial
            synchronization Delay is the average time for receiver to
            synchronize all components of a multimedia session <xref
            target="RFC6051"></xref>.<vspace blankLines="1" /></t>

            <t hangText="Synchronization Offset:"><vspace
            blankLines="1" />Synchronization between two media streams must be
            maintained to ensure satisfactory QoE. Two media streams can be of
            the same or different media type belonging to one RTP session or
            in different media types belonging to one multimedia session. The
            Synchronization Offset is the relative time difference of the two
            media streams that need to be synchronized. <vspace
            blankLines="1" /></t>
          </list></t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="RFISD"
             title="RTP Flows Initial Synchronization Delay Report Block">
      <t>This block is sent by RTP receivers and reports Initial
      synchronization delay beyond the information carried in the standard
      RTCP packet format. Information is recorded about time difference
      between the start of multimedia session and the time when the RTP
      receiver acquires all components of RTP sessions <xref
      target="RFC6051"></xref> measured at the receiving end of RTP
      stream.</t>

      <t>This block needs only be exchanged occasionally, for example sent
      once at the start of RTP session.</t>

      <section title="Metric Block Structure">
        <t>The RTP Flows Initial Synchronization Delay Report Block has the
        following format: <figure>
            <artwork>
    0                   1                   2                   3
    0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |    BT=RFISD   |   Reserved    |         Block length=2        |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |                      SSRC of Source                           |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |               Initial Synchronization Delay                   |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
</artwork>
          </figure></t>
      </section>

      <section title="Definition of Fields in RTP Flow Initial Synchronization Delay Metrics Block">
        <t><list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="Block type (BT): 8 bits"><vspace blankLines="1" />The
            RTP Flows Initial Synchronization Delay Report Block is identified
            by the constant &lt;RFISD&gt;. <vspace blankLines="1" /> [Note to
            RFC Editor: please replace RFISD with the IANA provided RTCP XR
            block type for this block.] <vspace blankLines="1" /></t>

            <t hangText="Reserved: 8 bits"><vspace blankLines="1" />This field
            is reserved for future definition. In the absence of such a
            definition, the bits in this field MUST be set to zero and ignored
            by the receiver. <vspace blankLines="1" /></t>

            <t hangText="Block length: 16 bits"><vspace blankLines="1" />The
            constant 2, in accordance with the definition of this field in
            Section 3 of <xref target="RFC3611">RFC 3611</xref>. <vspace
            blankLines="1" /></t>

            <t hangText="SSRC of source: 32 bits"><vspace blankLines="1" />The
            SSRC of the media source SHALL be set to the value of the SSRC
            identifier carried in any arbitrary component of RTP sessions
            belonging to the same multimedia session. <vspace
            blankLines="1" /></t>

            <t hangText="Initial Synchronization Delay: 32 bits"><vspace
            blankLines="1" />The average delay, expressed in units of 1/65536
            seconds, from the beginning of multimedia session <xref
            target="RFC6051"></xref> to the time when RTCP packets are
            received on all of the components RTP sessions. It is recommended
            that the beginning of multimedia session is chosen as the time
            when the receiver has joined the first RTP session of the
            multimedia session. The value of the initial synchronization delay
            is calculated based on received RTCP SR packets or the RTP header
            extension containing in-band mapping of RTP and NTP-format
            timestamps <xref target="RFC6051"></xref>. If there is no packet
            loss, the initial synchronization delay is expected to be equal to
            the average time taken to receive the first RTCP packet in the RTP
            session with the longest RTCP reporting interval or the average
            time taken to receive the first RTP header extension containing
            in-band mapping of RTP and NTP-format timestamps. <vspace
            blankLines="1" />If the measurement is unavailable, the value of
            this field with all bits set to 1 MUST be reported.</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="RFSO"
             title="RTP Flows Synchronization Offset Metrics Block">
      <t>In the RTP multimedia sessions or one RTP session, there can be an
      arbitrary number of Media streams and each media stream (e.g., audio
      stream or video stream) is sent in a separate RTP stream. In case of one
      RTP session, each media stream or each medium uses different SSRC. The
      receiver associates RTP streams to be synchronized by means of RTCP
      CNAME contained in the RTCP Source Description (SDES) packets <xref
      target="RFC3550"></xref>.</t>

      <t>This block is sent by RTP receivers and reports synchronization
      offset of two arbitrary RTP streams that needs to be synchronized in the
      RTP multimedia session. Information is recorded about the relative
      average time difference between two arbitrary RTP streams (one is
      reporting stream, the other is reference stream) with the same CNAME and
      measured at the receiving end of RTP stream. In order to tell what the
      offset of reporting stream is relative to, the block for reference
      stream with synchronization offset of zero should be reported.</t>

      <t>Instances of this Block refer by Synchronization source (SSRC) to the
      separate auxiliary Measurement Information block <xref
      target="RFC6776"></xref> which describes measurement periods in use (see
      <xref target="RFC6776"></xref> section 4.2). This metrics block relies
      on the measurement period in the Measurement Information block
      indicating the span of the report and SHOULD be sent in the same
      compound RTCP packet as the measurement information block. If the
      measurement period is not received in the same compound RTCP packet as
      this Block, this Block MUST be discarded.</t>

      <section title="Metric Block Structure">
        <t>The RTP Flow General Synchronization Offset Report Block has the
        following format: <figure>
            <artwork>   
    0                   1                   2                   3
    0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |    BT=RFSO    | I | Reserved  |         Block length=3        |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |                        SSRC of source                         |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |         Synchronization Offset, most significant word         |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |         Synchronization Offset, least significant word        |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
</artwork>
          </figure></t>
      </section>

      <section title="Definition of Fields in RTP Flow General Synchronization Offset Metrics Block">
        <t><list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="Block type (BT): 8 bits"><vspace blankLines="1" />The
            RTP Flow General Synchronization Offset Report Block is identified
            by the constant &lt;RFSO&gt;. <vspace blankLines="1" /> [Note to
            RFC Editor: please replace RFSO with the IANA provided RTCP XR
            block type for this block.] <vspace blankLines="1" /></t>

            <t hangText="Interval Metric Flag (I): 2 bits"><vspace
            blankLines="1" />This field is used to indicate whether the
            Burst/Gap Discard Summary Statistics metrics are Sampled, Interval
            or Cumulative metrics: <vspace blankLines="1" /><list>
                <t>I=10: Interval Duration - the reported value applies to the
                most recent measurement interval duration between successive
                metrics reports.</t>

                <t>I=11: Cumulative Duration - the reported value applies to
                the accumulation period characteristic of cumulative
                measurements.</t>

                <t>I=01: Sampled Value - the reported value is a sampled
                instantaneous value.</t>
              </list><vspace blankLines="1" /><vspace blankLines="1" />In this
            document, the value I=00 is the reserved value and MUST NOT be
            used.<vspace blankLines="1" /></t>

            <t hangText="Reserved: 6 bits"><vspace blankLines="1" />This field
            is reserved for future definition. In the absence of such a
            definition, the bits in this field MUST be set to zero and MUST be
            ignored by the receiver. <vspace blankLines="1" /></t>

            <!--            <t hangText="Rsd.: 8 bits"><vspace blankLines="1" /> This field is
            reserved for future definition. In the absence of such a
            definition, the bits in this field MUST be set to zero and MUST be
            ignored by the receiver.
     <vspace blankLines="1" /></t>-->

            <t hangText="Block length: 16 bits"><vspace blankLines="1" />The
            constant 3, in accordance with the definition of this field in
            Section 3 of <xref target="RFC3611">RFC 3611</xref>. <vspace
            blankLines="1" /></t>

            <t hangText="SSRC of Source: 32 bits"><vspace blankLines="1" />The
            SSRC of the media source SHALL be set to the value of the SSRC
            identifier of the reporting RTP stream to which the XR relates.
            <vspace blankLines="1" /></t>

            <t hangText="Synchronization Offset: 64 bits"><vspace
            blankLines="1" />The synchronization offset of the reporting RTP
            stream relative to the reference stream with the same CNAME. The
            calculation of Synchronization Offset is similar to Difference D
            calculation in the RFC3550. That is to say, if Si is the NTP
            timestamp from the reporting RTP packet i, and Ri is the time of
            arrival in NTP timestamp units for reporting RTP packet i, Sj is
            the NTP timestamp from the reference RTP packet j, and Rj is the
            time of arrival in NTP timestamp units for reference RTP packet j,
            then the value of the synchronization offset D may be expressed as
            <vspace blankLines="1" /><list>
                <t>D(i,j) = (Rj - Ri) - (Sj - Si) = (Rj - Sj) - (Ri -
                Si)<vspace blankLines="1" /></t>
              </list>If in-band delivery of NTP-format timestamps is supported
            <xref target="RFC6051"></xref>, Si and Sj should be obtained
            directly from the RTP packets where NTP timestamps are available.
            If not, Si and Sj should be calculated from their corresponding
            RTP timestamps. The value of the synchronization offset is
            represented using a 64-bit signed NTP-format timestamp as defined
            in <xref target="RFC5905"></xref>, which is 64-bit signed
            fixed-point number with the integer part in the first 32 bits and
            the fractional part in the last 32 bits. A positive value of the
            synchronization offset means that the reporting stream leads
            before the reference stream, while a negative one means the
            reporting stream lags behind the reference stream. The
            synchronization offset of zero means the stream is the reference
            stream.<vspace blankLines="1" />If the measurement is unavailable,
            the value of this field with all bits set to 1 MUST be
            reported.</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="SDP Signaling">
      <t><xref target="RFC3611"></xref> defines the use of SDP (Session
      Description Protocol) <xref target="RFC4566"></xref> for signaling the
      use of XR blocks. XR blocks MAY be used without prior signaling.</t>

      <section title="SDP rtcp-xr-attrib Attribute Extension">
        <t>Two new parameters are defined for the two report blocks defined in
        this document to be used with Session Description Protocol (SDP) <xref
        target="RFC4566"></xref> using the Augmented Backus-Naur Form (ABNF)
        <xref target="RFC5234"></xref>. They have the following syntax within
        the "rtcp-xr" attribute <xref target="RFC3611"></xref>: <figure
            align="left">
            <artwork>
xr-format = xr-rfisd-block
          / xr-rfso-block

xr-rfisd-block = "rtp-flow-init-syn-delay"
xr-rfso-block = "rtp-flow-syn-offset"
</artwork>
          </figure> Refer to Section 5.1 of <xref target="RFC3611">RFC
        3611</xref> for a detailed description and the full syntax of the
        "rtcp-xr" attribute.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Offer/Answer Usage">
        <t>When SDP is used in offer-answer context, the SDP Offer/Answer
        usage defined in <xref target="RFC3611"></xref> applies.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>New report block types for RTCP XR are subject to IANA registration.
      For general guidelines on IANA allocations for RTCP XR, refer to <xref
      target="RFC3611">Section 6.2 of</xref>.</t>

      <t>This document assigns two new block type values in the RTCP XR Block
      Type Registry: <list>
          <t><list hangIndent="12" style="hanging">
              <t hangText="Name:">RFISD<vspace blankLines="0" /></t>

              <t hangText="Long Name:">RTP Flows Initial Synchronization
              Delay<vspace blankLines="0" /></t>

              <t hangText="Value">&lt;RFISD&gt;<vspace blankLines="0" /></t>

              <t hangText="Reference:"><xref target="RFISD"></xref><vspace
              blankLines="1" /></t>

              <t hangText="Name:">RFSO<vspace blankLines="0" /></t>

              <t hangText="Long Name:">RTP Flows Synchronization Offset
              Metrics Block<vspace blankLines="0" /></t>

              <t hangText="Value">&lt;RFSO&gt;<vspace blankLines="0" /></t>

              <t hangText="Reference:"><xref target="RFSO"></xref><vspace
              blankLines="1" /></t>
            </list></t>
        </list></t>

      <t>This document also registers two new SDP <xref
      target="RFC4566"></xref> parameters for the "rtcp-xr" attribute in the
      RTCP XR SDP Parameters Registry: <list>
          <t><list style="symbols">
              <t>"rtp-flow-init-syn-delay "</t>

              <t>"rtp-flow-syn-offset"</t>
            </list></t>
        </list></t>

      <t>The contact information for the registrations is: <list>
          <t><list style="hanging">
              <t>Qin Wu</t>

              <t>sunseawq@huawei.com</t>

              <t>101 Software Avenue, Yuhua District</t>

              <t>Nanjing, Jiangsu 210012, China</t>
            </list></t>
        </list></t>
    </section>

    <section title="Security Considerations">
      <t>The new RTCP XR report blocks proposed in this document introduces no
      new security considerations beyond those described in <xref
      target="RFC3611"></xref>.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>The authors would like to thank Bill Ver Steeg, David R Oran, Ali
      Begen, Colin Perkins, Roni Even, Kevin Gross, Jing Zhao, Fernando
      Boronat Seguí, Mario Montagud Climent, Youqing Yang, Wenxiao Yu and
      Yinliang Hu,Jonathan Lennox for their valuable comments and suggestions
      on this document.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <reference anchor="RFC6190">
        <front>
          <title>RTP Payload Format for Scalable Video Coding</title>

          <author fullname="Stephan Wenger" initials="S" surname="Wenger">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="Ye-Kui Wang" initials="Y" surname="Wang">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="Thomas Schierl" initials="T" surname="Schierl">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="Alex Eleftheriadis" initials="A"
                  surname="Eleftheriadis">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date month="May" year="2011" />

          <abstract>
            <t>This memo describes an RTP payload format for Scalable Video
            Coding (SVC) as defined in Annex G of ITU-T Recommendation H.264,
            which is technically identical to Amendment 3 of ISO/IEC
            International Standard 14496-10. The RTP payload format allows for
            packetization of one or more Network Abstraction Layer (NAL) units
            in each RTP packet payload, as well as fragmentation of a NAL unit
            in multiple RTP packets. Furthermore, it supports transmission of
            an SVC stream over a single as well as multiple RTP sessions. The
            payload format defines a new media subtype name "H264-SVC", but is
            still backwards compatible to [I-D.ietf-avt-rtp-rfc3984bis] since
            the base layer, when encapsulated in its own RTP stream, must use
            the H.264 media subtype name ("H264") and the packetization method
            specified in [I- D.ietf-avt-rtp-rfc3984bis]. The payload format
            has wide applicability in videoconferencing, Internet video
            streaming, and high bit-rate entertainment-quality video, among
            others.Table of Contents</t>
          </abstract>
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="6190" />

        <format octets="34293"
                target="http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc6190.txt" type="TXT" />
      </reference>

      &rfc3611;

      &rfc2119;

      &rfc4566;

      &rfc5234;

      &rfc3550;

      <reference anchor="RFC6051">
        <front>
          <title>Rapid Synchronisation of RTP Flows</title>

          <author fullname="Colin Perkins" initials="C." surname="Perkins">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="Thomas Schierl" initials="T" surname="Schierl">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date day="10" month="November" year="2010" />

          <abstract>
            <t>This memo outlines how RTP sessions are synchronized, and
            discusses how rapidly such synchronisation can occur. We show that
            most RTP sessions can be synchronized immediately, but that the
            use of video switching multipoint conference units (MCUs) or large
            source specific multicast (SSM) groups can greatly increase the
            synchronisation delay. This increase in delay can be unacceptable
            to some applications that use layered and/or multi-description
            codecs. This memo introduces three mechanisms to reduce the
            synchronisation delay for such sessions. First, it updates the RTP
            Control Protocol (RTCP) timing rules to reduce the initial
            synchronisation delay for SSM sessions. Second, a new feedback
            packet is defined for use with the Extended RTP Profile for
            RTCP-based Feedback (RTP/AVPF), allowing video switching MCUs to
            rapidly request resynchronisation. Finally, new RTP header
            extensions are defined to allow rapid synchronisation of late
            joiners, and guarantee correct timestamp based decoding order
            recovery for layered codecs in the presence of clock skew.</t>
          </abstract>
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="6051" />

        <format target="http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc6051" type="TXT" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RFC5905">
        <front>
          <title>Network Time Protocol Version 4: Protocol and Algorithms
          Specification</title>

          <author fullname="D.Mills" initials="D." surname="Mills">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="J.Martin" initials="J." surname="Martin">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="J.Burbank" initials="J." surname="Burbank">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="W. Kasch" initials="W." surname="Kasch">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date month="June" year="2010" />
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="5905" />

        <format type="TXT" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RFC6776">
        <front>
          <title>Measurement Identity and information Reporting using SDES
          item and XR Block</title>

          <author fullname="Qin Wu" initials="Q." surname="Wu">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date month="August" year="2012" />
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="6776" />

        <format type="TXT" />
      </reference>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <reference anchor="RFC6792">
        <front>
          <title>Guidelines for Use of the RTP Monitoring Framework</title>

          <author fullname="Qin Wu" initials="Q." surname="Wu">
            <organization>Huawei</organization>
          </author>

          <date month="November" year="2012" />
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="6792" />

        <format type="TXT" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="Y.1540">
        <front>
          <title>ITU-T Rec. Y.1540, IP packet transfer and availability
          performance parameters</title>

          <author fullname="" initials="" surname="">
            <organization>ITU-T</organization>
          </author>

          <date month="November" year="2007" />
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RFC6390">
        <front>
          <title>Guidelines for Considering New Performance Metric
          Development</title>

          <author fullname="A.Clark" initials="A." surname="Clark">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="B. Claise" initials="B." surname="Claise">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date month="October" year="2011" />
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="6390" />

        <format type="TXT" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="TR-126">
        <front>
          <title>Triple-play Services Quality of Experience (QoE)
          Requirements</title>

          <author>
            <organization>BBF Forum</organization>
          </author>

          <date month="December" year="2006" />
        </front>
      </reference>
    </references>

    <section title="Metrics represented using RFC6390 Template">
      <t>RFC EDITOR NOTE: please change XXXX in [RFCXXXX] by the new RFC
      number, when assigned.</t>

      <t><list style="letters">
          <t>Initial Synchronization Delay Metric<vspace
          blankLines="1" /><list style="symbols">
              <t>Metric Name: RTP Initial Synchronization Delay<vspace
              blankLines="1" /></t>

              <t>Metric Description: See Section 2.1,Initial Synchronization
              Delay term [RFCXXXX].<vspace blankLines="1" /></t>

              <t>Method of Measurement or Calculation: See section 3.2,
              Initial Synchronization Delay definition [RFCXXXX].<vspace
              blankLines="1" /></t>

              <t>Units of Measurement: See section 3.2, Initial
              Synchronization Delay definition [RFCXXXX].<vspace
              blankLines="1" /></t>

              <t>Measurement Point(s) with Potential Measurement Domain: See
              section 3, 1st paragraph [RFCXXXX]. <vspace
              blankLines="1" /></t>

              <t>Measurement Timing: See section 3, 2nd paragraph [RFCXXXX]
              for measurement timing. <vspace blankLines="1" /></t>

              <t>Use and applications: See section 1.4 [RFCXXXX].<vspace
              blankLines="1" /></t>

              <t>Reporting model: See RFC3611.<vspace blankLines="1" /></t>
            </list></t>

          <t>Synchronization Offset Metric<vspace blankLines="1" /><list
              style="symbols">
              <t>Metric Name: RTP Synchronization Offset Delay<vspace
              blankLines="1" /></t>

              <t>Metric Description: See Section 2.1, Synchronization Offset
              term [RFCXXXX].<vspace blankLines="1" /></t>

              <t>Method of Measurement or Calculation: See section 4.2,
              Initial Synchronization Delay definition [RFCXXXX].<vspace
              blankLines="1" /></t>

              <t>Units of Measurement: See section 4.2, Initial
              Synchronization Delay definition [RFCXXXX].<vspace
              blankLines="1" /></t>

              <t>Measurement Point(s) with Potential Measurement Domain: See
              section 4, 2nd paragraph [RFCXXXX]. <vspace
              blankLines="1" /></t>

              <t>Measurement Timing: See section 4, 3rd paragraph [RFCXXXX]
              for measurement timing and section 4.2 [RFCXXXX] for Interval
              Metric flag.<vspace blankLines="1" /></t>

              <t>Use and applications: See section 1.4 [RFCXXXX].<vspace
              blankLines="1" /></t>

              <t>Reporting model: See RFC3611.<vspace blankLines="1" /></t>
            </list></t>
        </list></t>
    </section>

    <section title="Change Log">
      <t>Note to the RFC-Editor: please remove this section prior to
      publication as an RFC.</t>

      <section title="draft-ietf-xrblock-rtcp-xr-syncronization-07">
        <t>The following are the major changes compared to previous
        version:<vspace blankLines="1" /><list>
            <t>Minor Editorial changes.</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>

      <section title="draft-ietf-xrblock-rtcp-xr-syncronization-06">
        <t>The following are the major changes compared to previous
        version:<vspace blankLines="1" /><list>
            <t>Some Editorial changes.</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>

      <section title="draft-ietf-xrblock-rtcp-xr-syncronization-05">
        <t>The following are the major changes compared to previous
        version:<vspace blankLines="1" /><list>
            <t>Editorial changes and typo fixed.</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>

      <section title="draft-ietf-xrblock-rtcp-xr-syncronization-04">
        <t>The following are the major changes compared to previous
        version:<vspace blankLines="1" /><list>
            <t>Additional text to clarify on how to distinguish report stream
            from reference stream.</t>

            <t>Other Editorial changes.</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>

      <section title="draft-ietf-xrblock-rtcp-xr-syncronization-03">
        <t>The following are the major changes compared to previous
        version:<vspace blankLines="1" /><list>
            <t>Remove the need to signal the reference source in the
            synchronisation offset metrics RTCP XR report.</t>

            <t>Apply RFC6390 template to metrics in the appendix.</t>

            <t>Other editorial changes to get inline with other XRBLOCK
            drafts.</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>

      <section title="draft-ietf-xrblock-rtcp-xr-syncronization-02">
        <t>The following are the major changes compared to previous
        version:<vspace blankLines="1" /><list>
            <t>Editorial change based on comments raised on the list and in
            the IETF85 meeting</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>
    </section>
  </back>
</rfc>
