<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<rfc category="info" docName="draft-tripathi-roll-reactive-applicability-01"
     ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="Reactive Protocol Evaluation in LLNs">Why Reactive
    Protocols are Ill-Suited for LLNs</title>

    <author fullname="Joydeep Tripathi" initials="J." role="editor"
            surname="Tripathi">
      <organization>Drexel University</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>3141 Chestnut Street 7-313</street>

          <city>Philadelphia</city>

          <code>19104</code>

          <region>PA</region>

          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>

        <email>jt369@drexel.edu</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Jaudelice C. de Oliveira" initials="J. C." role="editor"
            surname="de Oliveira">
      <organization>Drexel University</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>3141 Chestnut Street 7-313</street>

          <city>Philadelphia</city>

          <code>19104</code>

          <region>PA</region>

          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>

        <email>jau@coe.drexel.edu</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="C. Chauvenet" initials="C." role="editor"
            surname="Chauvenet">
      <organization>Watteco.</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street> 1766, Chemin de la Planquette</street>

          <city>La Garde.</city>

          <code>83130</code>

          <region/>

          <country>France</country>
        </postal>

        <email>c.chauvenet@watteco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="JP Vasseur" initials="JP" role="editor"
            surname="Vasseur">
      <organization>Cisco Systems, Inc.</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>11, Rue Camille Desmoulins</street>

          <city>Issy Les Moulineaux</city>

          <code>92782</code>

          <region/>

          <country>France</country>
        </postal>

        <email>jpv@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date day="3" month="July" year="2013"/>

    <area>Routing Area</area>

    <workgroup>Networking Working Group</workgroup>

    <keyword>Reactive Protocol</keyword>

    <keyword>LLN</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>This document describes serious issues and shortcomings regarding the
      use of reactive routing protocols in low power and lossy networks
      (LLNs). Routing requirements for various LLN deployments are discussed
      in order to judge how reactive routing may or may not adhere to the
      necessary criteria.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>In 2008, the IETF chartered a Working Group called ROLL (Routing Over
      Low power and Lossy networks) with the objective of specifying routing
      requirements of Low power and Lossy Networks (LLN), and then either
      select an existing routing protocol or specify and design a new routing
      protocol in light of the unique requirements of these networks. This led
      to the specification of a new routing protocol called RPL (see <xref
      target="RFC6550"/>) along with other specifications related to RPL.</t>

      <t>Despite the existence of a standard track routing protocol for LLN,
      discussions have been taken place as to whether other routing approaches
      could be suitable, such as deploying reactive routing protocols in LLNs,
      such as in smart metering networks, industrial automation, water
      management networks, etc.. The aim of this document is not to discuss a
      specific reactive routing protocol but why reactive routing protocols in
      general are ill-suited for LLNs. For the sake of illustration, we will
      refer to a reactive protocol called LOADng (<xref
      target="I-D.clausen-lln-loadng"/>) which was introduced at the IETF,
      with results seeming to indicate performance improvement over the
      standard AODV protocol in the context of LLNs (<xref
      target="clausen-load-vtc"/>). The aim of this document is to highlight
      the number of shortcomings and technical issues in using reactive
      routing in such networks. Note that reactive protocols are perfectly
      applicable to several types of mobile ad-hoc networks (MANETs), which
      are not LLNs. Specifically, LLNs exhibit constrained characteristics
      such as very low data rate (a few Kbps), lossy physical links where the
      packet delivery ratio can be poor (below 50%) and the links exhibit
      highly dynamic properties (high variation of Packet Delivery Ratio (PDR)
      with respect to time).</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Terminology">
      <t>Please refer to <xref target="ROLL-TERMS"/> for terminology.
      Additionally, the following terms are used throughout the document.</t>

      <t><list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="U-LLN:">Urban Low-Power Lossy Network.</t>

          <t hangText="PDR:">Packet Delivery Ratio.</t>

          <t hangText="RREQ">Route Request.</t>

          <t hangText="RREP">Route Reply.</t>

          <t hangText="AMI">Advanced Metering Infrastructure.</t>
        </list></t>
    </section>

    <section title="Non-compliance with routing requirements in LLNs">
      <t/>

      <section title="Inability to support P2MP traffic pattern">
        <t>An LLN often has a more demanding traffic pattern than simple
        traffic between two peer nodes (P2P traffic). The nature of
        deployments and applications running over an LLN often requires a given
        node to send the same data to multiple recipients, requiring
        multicasting or point-to-multipoint (P2MP) support from the routing
        protocol. These destinations may be several hops away, therefore
        necessitating an efficient dissemination method. Examples of such
        traffic include:</t>

        <t><list style="symbols">
            <t>management information multicasted to all nodes belonging to a
            certain region in a landscape, certain part of the manufacturing
            pipeline in an industrial automation setting, upgrade of a new
            firmware,</t>

            <t>new tariff notification to a group of users in a smart grid
            deployment,</t>

            <t>a single node providing sensed data to multiple servers.</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>Indeed, <xref target="RFC5548"/> necessitates the support of P2MP
        traffic for a protocol to be suitable for U-LLN deployment. It
        describes - "Thus, the protocol(s) should be optimized to support a
        large number of unicast flows from the sensing nodes or sensing
        clusters towards a LBR, or highly directed multicast or anycast flows
        from the nodes towards multiple LBRs." and "A U-LLN may also need to
        support efficient large-scale messaging to groups of actuators.",
        which represents a massive critical need for a reliable P2MP
        mechanism. This requirement also necessitates a valid MP2P traffic
        support as well, which will be described in the next section.</t>

        <t>While a reactive routing protocol may be altered to support an
        on-demand bi-directional route between any two nodes in the network as
        provided by LOADng (see <xref target="I-D.clausen-lln-loadng"/>), the
        protocol does not define a way to build and maintain an always usable
        multicast topology. It is worth mentioning here that the AODV protocol
        in <xref target="RFC3561"/> mentions provision for nodes to join a
        multicast tree and RREQs to use multicast IP address as their
        destination address. However, no such methods or provisions are
        available in the lightweight versions of the AODV protocol, namely
        AODVv2 <xref target="I-D.Perkins-AODVv2"/> or LOADng (<xref
        target="I-D.clausen-lln-loadng"/>). A naive and very costly solution
        would be to create a copy of the same message/application data to send
        for each destination. Also, to find the route to each destination, the
        node may have to create separate route request (RREQ) messages and
        broadcast them. This broadcast event creates a huge control overhead.
        Number of intended destinations for this P2MP traffic can reach an
        order of hundreds or thousands, which is very common in an LLN deployed
        in urban area, or for a number of Advanced Metering Infrastructure
        (AMI) meters in a particular region in a smart grid deployment. If
        such is the case, the protocol does not scale well with the network
        size in terms of control overhead. Hence, reactive routing protocols
        in general may become unsuitable to be deployed in a large scale LLN
        such as a U-LLN where P2MP traffic needs to be supported and be
        maintained, even if for 1-2 times a day.</t>

        <t>Simulation studies, such as the on in <xref
        target="Tripathi-CISS"/>have verified that a reactive protocol suffers
        from high (over hundred seconds) end-to-end delay and large control
        overhead when P2MP traffic exists in the network.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Inability to support MP2P traffic pattern">
        <t>Likewise P2MP traffic, MP2P traffic needs to be supported by a
        routing protocol intended for an LLN. This traffic pattern arises when
        multiple nodes may try to send data to a single sink at the same time.
        As <xref target="RFC5548"/> describes, "A U-LLN should support
        occasional large-scale traffic flows from sensing nodes through LBRs
        (to nodes outside the U-LLN), such as system-wide alerts." By nature,
        this kind of traffic may be time-critical, and the alerts may need to
        be delivered within a small time-frame. Similar traffic may include
        critical scenarios in an industrial automation LLN deployment, where
        all nodes in one area may need to report malfunction, fire, or other
        emergency in that part of the manufacturing plant.</t>

        <t>Since, by default, reactive routing does not provide any efficient
        MP2P routing paradigm, all nodes will create their own route request
        (RREQ) in order to find the route to the LBR or server, if the route
        is expired or not cached. This situation will create separate
        broadcast control messages from each node, which may lead to a
        broadcast storm in the network, similar to the P2MP traffic scenario.
        The broadcast storm may result in individual RREPs reaching the
        initiator node much later, yielding a high delay for the time-critical
        alert packets.</t>

        <t>Routing for MP2P traffic is therefore not efficient or optimized,
        and does not follow an aggregation tree neither any such hierarchy is
        maintained in reactive protocols. As a result, it is difficult to
        devise a data aggregation algorithm compatible to AODV or any of its
        derivatives.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Dependency of control overhead on application module">
      <t>An LLN that is provisioned to be used for data gathering purpose today
      may include additional application layer modules in the future. Smart
      grid deployments may need to implement new modules of management traffic
      from the base stations to AMI meters, in addition to what is envisioned
      at present. LLNs are evolving and therefore it is expected that new
      applications and requirements will be part of its future (an LLN may also
      be re-purposed).</t>

      <t>Reactive protocols discover route to destination on an on-demand
      basis. If communication between same source-destination pair are spaced
      far apart in time, the protocol tends to discover the routes every time
      communication is requested by the application layer. With reactive
      routing protocols, adding a new application module which requires more
      data communication in between the existing data traffic pattern will
      incur control overhead. Hence, if a network is designed to operate
      within bounds in terms of maximum control overhead load, adding new
      application modules may well force the control overhead to surpass the
      designed maximum limit. For example, a deployment requiring both MP2P
      and P2P application may incur more overhead than a deployment which is
      currently working with only data aggregation. Since LLNs will
      undoubtedly require more application modules and management modules to
      be augmented in future, a suitable routing protocol should be able to
      cope with the added traffic. For the sake of illustration, many smart
      grid networks, which were originally designed for the purpose of
      advanced metering, now require a multi-service networks in support of a
      variety of applications including meter reading, use of meters of
      alarms, distribution automation and electric vehicles, leading to a
      variety of traffic patterns each with different quality of service
      requirements.</t>

      <t>As we observed in <xref target="Tripathi-CISS"/>, even for a smaller
      network with less than 100 nodes, if the application data rate is
      increased from once in 12 hours to once an hour, the control overhead
      for a reactive protocol such as LOADng gets magnified by about 10
      times.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Flooding issues in LLNs">
      <t>A reactive protocol is well-suited for a traffic pattern where data
      transfer is not very frequent. However, if the traffic pattern includes
      periodic data reporting, even as low as a few times in a day, the
      traffic pattern will induce periodic broadcast of route request
      throughout the network. A simple example scenario can clarify this:
      assume an application in a U-LLN requires periodic data reporting every
      6 hours or 4 times in a day - morning, noon, evening and night. If the
      network consists of 2000 nodes, which is a very conservative number in a
      typical U-LLN, the application alone will create a route request
      broadcast for each sensor node every 11 seconds, on average. Thus, over
      the life of the sensor network, a reactive protocol will use more
      control overhead than a proactive protocol.</t>

      <t>The amount of flooding to discover routes may also be controlled via
      tweaking the route expiry time or route validity time. If a route is
      active, nodes should not waste network resources trying to find out the
      route to the same destination. Keeping a high expiry time for the
      routes, on the other hand may prevent flooding the next time data is
      generated for the same destination. However, the path may well have been
      invalid by the route expiry time. Considering LLN link characteristics,
      link flapping is a very frequent event. Hence, high route expiry time
      may lead a node to find out invalidity of a path, thus forcing to flood
      the network again for route discovery. Thus, increasing route expiry
      time or route validity time for an AODV-based reactive protocol may not
      prove to control flooding in LLN. Proactively choosing a back-up path
      proves to be an effective way to ensure valid routing path in presence
      of link flaps, whereas reactive routing approaches are not able to cope
      with link dynamics, thus preventing its usage for LLNs. Furthermore,
      if traffic is sent along a broken path, a new request would consequently
      be generated, thus increasing the control traffic load, in addition to
      incurring additional delays for the user data.</t>

      <section title="Impact of flooding in battery operated nodes">
        <t>Note that there is a lot of experimental evidence supporting the
        claim that using flooding or scoped flooding to discover routes is
        ill-suited to low-power and lossy networks (LLNs). This is due to the
        low-power requirement. In low-power wireless networks, broadcast
        packets usually cost much more energy by the hardware to transmit than unicast ones. However, at this point, we would exclude consideration of such hardware dependent energy expense from our discussion.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Impact on memory">
      <t>Reactive routing protocols usually rely on route caching for
      discovered destination. Hence, if any node participates in multiple
      active flows in the network, the node needs to store next hop (and
      validity) information for each source and destination node in the
      network. Thus, depending on the user traffic, some nodes tend to
      increase their routing table size proportional to the number of flows
      passing through themselves. Hence, the nodes require more memory storage
      to operate successfully in these networks, depending on the traffic
      pattern. However, characteristics of LLNs never guarantee enough storage
      space in any node for storing routing tables. In LLNs, thus it is always
      advantageous to store route to a subset of nodes and still be able to
      find a path to any destination in the network. Reactive routing
      protocols, in their current specification or any variant, fail to
      achieve low memory requirement in nodes in the context of large scale
      LLNs.</t>

      <t>Destination oriented flooding in LLN, tends to worsen this situation.
      Multiple route requests may reach the same node at the same time for
      different destinations. Even though the destination may never be reached
      through the concerned node, the node still has to process and
      re-broadcast each request, along with its neighbors. Vital memory is
      consumed in RREQ/RREP processing and buffering in this method.</t>

      <t>As we observed during simulation study and in <xref
      target="Tripathi-CISS"/>, the memory requirement in a reactive protocol
      such as LOADng grows with the network scale considerably. More
      specifically, they depend on number of active flows through a node, or
      number of destinations a node serves for which the routes have not
      expired yet. For a large network of over 2000 nodes, the total memory
      occupancy for a node, including route tables and buffered packets, for a
      reactive protocol may reach over 200 KB, as observed during
      simulation. Even for a small home automation network, the authors in <xref target="Malisa-WCNC"/> pointed out, that the number of route entries and thus memory consumption depends on route expiry time for a reactive protocol. With increase in the route expiry time or route hold time, average number of route entries in a node increases. If the route expiry time is higher, the number of entries increases more sharply with increase in network size. However, at the same time, the study in <xref target="Malisa-WCNC"/> agrees with the study conducted in <xref target="Tripathi-CISS"/> that with decrease in route expiry time in order to save memory, control overhead increases as predicted in section 5.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Lack of support for routing based on node capability">
      <t>Apart from providing a route between any two nodes in the network, a
      routing protocol suitable for LLN should be able to handle additional
      constraints. An LLN mainly consists of constrained devices, both
      functionality and memory-wise, and inherently heterogeneous in nature.
      Hence, any routing protocol suitable for LLNs should support node
      constraint based routing. This requirement is mandated in <xref
      target="RFC5548"/> as follows: " the routing protocol MUST be able to
      advertise node capabilities that will be exclusively used by the routing
      protocol engine for routing decision". For example, the routing protocol
      should avoid a node with less battery power while routing to reach a
      server. Similarly, for industrial automation requirements, <xref
      target="RFC5673"/> also needs a routing protocol to provide device-aware
      routing, as it describes "The routing algorithm MUST support
      node-constrained routing (e.g., taking into account the existing energy
      state as a node constraint). Node constraints include power and memory,
      as well as constraints placed on the device by the user, such as battery
      life". For home routing automation, <xref target="RFC5826"/> specifies,
      "The routing protocol SHOULD route via mains-powered nodes if possible.
      The routing protocol MUST support constraint-based routing taking into
      account node properties (CPU, memory, level of energy, sleep intervals,
      safety/convenience of changing battery)".</t>

      <t>Clearly, recognizing a node's capability and routing accordingly is
      an important aspect for any routing protocol designed to be suitable for
      LLNs. However, any AODV-based protocol (such as DYMO <xref
      target="I-D.DYMO"/>and LOADng), in their current specification, fail to
      provide routes based on any such constraint. Currently known reactive
      routing protocols do not have any provision to determine whether the
      next-hop node in a route has enough battery power to sustain the route,
      or whether the next-hop node is main powered or provides a particular
      functionality. Thus, these protocols fail to provide requirements
      mandated by <xref target="RFC5548"/>, <xref target="RFC5673"/> and <xref
      target="RFC5826"/> for routing in an LLN.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="High delay for emergency traffic">
      <t>Some data in an LLN are delay sensitive by nature. While data
      generated for periodic reporting can be delivered even up to few seconds
      later, emergency alarms, fault notification and alert packets need to be
      delivered as quickly as possible. According to <xref target="RFC5673"/>,
      in an industrial automation setting, "Non-critical closed-loop
      applications have a latency requirement that can be as low as 100
      milliseconds but many control loops are tolerant of latencies above 1
      second". Clearly, these types of alert packets need a path to the
      destination beforehand as soon as they are generated. However, reactive
      protocols depend on finding a path when data is generated. Since the
      receipt of an RREP packet can take up to the network traversal time, for
      large networks the delivery of an emergency packet may take more than
      few hundred milliseconds. Also, if this emergency situation initiates a
      system wide alert from all nodes in the region to one or multiple
      servers outside the LLN, each node will create their own broadcast to
      reach the destination. Similar to the condition in section 3, the
      broadcast storm may lead to huge delay in receipt of RREP packets, and
      thus delay in delivering the emergency packet. The broadcast will lead
      to high control overhead, clogging the network, as well as loss of some
      RREQ/RREP packets.</t>

      <t>Indeed, reactive protocols provide a very high unreliability in delay
      bound for any number of hop distance to the destination. The delay is
      small when an active path is available, but high when the source has to
      issue a route request. The delay is a few magnitudes larger when
      multiple route requests/replies are simultaneously active. As observed
      during simulation and in <xref target="Tripathi-CISS"/>, a reactive
      protocol as LOADng may take from tens of seconds to hundreds of seconds to
      deliver the data, depending on the network size and whether multiple
      RREQs/RREPs are active. Unreliability in delay bound has been found to
      be as high as 95% confidence interval in average end-to-end delay for
      the data packets. Also in <xref target="Malisa-WCNC"/>, the authors pointed out how reactive protocols, even for a small home automation network presents large delay in order of a few seconds which increases with decrease in route expiry time. </t>
    </section>

    <section title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>TBD</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Informative References">
      <!-- draft-ietf-roll-terminology (Expired) -->

      <reference anchor="ROLL-TERMS">
        <front>
          <title>Terminology in Low power And Lossy Networks</title>

          <author fullname="JP Vasseur" initials="JP" surname="Vasseur"/>

          <date month="September" year="2011"/>
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="Work in" value="Progress"/>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="clausen-load-vtc">
        <front>
          <title>LOADng: Towards AODV Version 2</title>

          <author fullname="T. Clausen" initials="T." role="editor"
                  surname="Clausen">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <author fullname="Jiazi Yi" initials="J." role="editor" surname="Yi">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <author fullname="Axel Colin" initials="A." role="editor"
                  surname="de Verdiere">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <date month="September" year="2012"/>
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="Vehicular Technology Conference (VTC Fall),"
                    value=" 2012 IEEE"/>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="Tripathi-CISS">
        <front>
          <title>Proactive versus Reactive Revisited: IPv6 Routing for Low
          Power Lossy Networks</title>

          <author fullname="J. Tripathi" initials="J." role="editor"
                  surname="Tripathi">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <author fullname="J. C. de Oliveira" initials="J.C." role="editor"
                  surname="de Oliveira">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <date month="March" year="2013"/>
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="47th Annual Conference on Information Science and Systems (CISS),"
                    value=" 2013"/>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="Malisa-WCNC">
        <front>
          <title>Performance Comparison of the RPL and LOADng Routing Protocols in a Home Automation Scenario</title>

          <author fullname="M. Vucinic" initials="M." role="editor"
                  surname="Vucinic">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <author fullname="B. Tourancheau" initials="B." role="editor"
                  surname="Tourancheau">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <author fullname="A. Duda" initials="A." role="editor"
                  surname="Duda">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <date month="June" year="2013"/>
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="IEEE WCNC - Wireless Communications and Networking Conference 2013"
                    value=" 2013"/>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RFC5548">
        <front>
          <title>Routing Requirements for Urban Low-Power and Lossy
          Networks</title>

          <author fullname="M. Dohler" initials="M." role="editor"
                  surname="Dohler">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <author fullname="T. Watteyne" initials="T." role="editor"
                  surname="Watteyne">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <author fullname="T. Winter" initials="T." role="editor"
                  surname="Winter">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <author fullname="D. Barthel" initials="D." role="editor"
                  surname="Barthel">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <date month="May" year="2009"/>
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="5548"/>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RFC5673">
        <front>
          <title>Industrial Routing Requirements in Low-Power and Lossy
          Networks</title>

          <author fullname="K. Pister" initials="K." role="editor"
                  surname="Pister">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <author fullname="P. Thubert" initials="P." role="editor"
                  surname="Thubert">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <author fullname="S. Dwars" initials="S." surname="Dwars">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <author fullname="T. Phinney" initials="T." surname="Phinney">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <date month="October" year="2009"/>
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="5673"/>
      </reference>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6550'?>

      <reference anchor="I-D.DYMO">
        <front>
          <title>Dynamic MANET On-demand (AODVv2) Routing</title>

          <author fullname="C. Perkins" initials="C." role="editor"
                  surname="Perkins">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <author fullname="S. Ratliff" initials="S." role="editor"
                  surname="Ratliff">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <author fullname="J. Dowdell" initials="J." role="editor"
                  surname="Dowdell">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <date month="February" year="2013"/>
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="Work in" value="Progress"/>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="I-D.Perkins-AODVv2">
        <front>
          <title>Dynamic MANET On-demand (AODVv2) Routing</title>

          <author fullname="C. Perkins" initials="C." role="editor"
                  surname="Perkins">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <author fullname="S. Ratliff" initials="S." role="editor"
                  surname="Ratliff">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <author fullname="J. Dowdell" initials="J." role="editor"
                  surname="Dowdell">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <date month="March" year="2013"/>
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="Work in" value="Progress"/>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="I-D.clausen-lln-loadng">
        <front>
          <title>The Lightweight On-demand Ad hoc Distance-vector Routing
          Protocol - Next Generation (LOADng)</title>

          <author fullname="T. Clausen" initials="T." role="editor"
                  surname="Clausen">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <author fullname="J. Yi" initials="J." role="editor" surname="Yi">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <author fullname="A. Niktash" initials="A." role="editor"
                  surname="Niktash">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <author fullname="Y. Igarashi" initials="Y." role="editor"
                  surname="Igarashi">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <author fullname="H. Satoh" initials="H." role="editor"
                  surname="Satoh">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <author fullname="U. Herberg" initials="U." role="editor"
                  surname="Herberg">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <author fullname="C. Lavenu" initials="C." role="editor"
                  surname="Lavenu">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <author fullname="T. Lys" initials="T." role="editor" surname="Lys">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <author fullname="C. Perkins" initials="C." role="editor"
                  surname="Perkins">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <author fullname="J. Dean" initials="J." role="editor"
                  surname="Dean">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <date month="January" year="2013"/>
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="Work in" value="Progress"/>
      </reference>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.5826'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.3561'?>

      <reference anchor="RFC5867">
        <front>
          <title>Building Automation Routing Requirements in Low-Power and
          Lossy Networks</title>

          <author fullname="J. Martocci" initials="J." role="editor"
                  surname="Martocci">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <author fullname="P. De Mil" initials="P." surname="De Mil">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <author fullname="N. Riou" initials="N." surname="Riou">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <author fullname="W. Vermeylen" initials="W." surname="Vermeylen">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <date month="June" year="2010"/>
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="5867"/>
      </reference>
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
