<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<rfc category="info" docName="draft-tripathi-rpl-simulation-00" ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="draft-tripathi-rpl-simulation-00">Performance Evaluation of
    Routing Protocol for Low Power and Lossy Networks (RPL)</title>

    <author fullname="Joydeep Tripathi" initials="J.T." role="editor"
            surname="Tripathi">
      <organization>Drexel University</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>3141 Chestnut Street 7-313</street>

          <city>Philadelphia</city>

          <code>19104</code>

          <region>PA</region>

          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>

        <email>jt369@drexel.edu</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Jaudelice C. de Oliveira" initials="J. O." role="editor"
            surname="de Oliveira">
      <organization>Drexel University</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>3141 Chestnut Street 7-313</street>

          <city>Philadelphia</city>

          <code>19104</code>

          <region>PA</region>

          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>

        <email>jau@ece.drexel.edu</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="JP Vasseur" initials="JP" role="editor"
            surname="Vasseur">
      <organization>Cisco Systems, Inc.</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>1414 Massachusetts Avenue</street>

          <city>Boxborough</city>

          <code>01719</code>

          <region>MA</region>

          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>

        <email>jpv@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date day="19" month="October" year="2009" />

    <area>Routing Area</area>

    <workgroup>Networking Working Group</workgroup>

    <keyword></keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>This document presents a performance evaluation of RPL in a single
      DAG scenario, and comparison of the same with shortest path routing in a
      LLN. Metrics to capture the significant performance aspects are
      identified and detailed simulations are carried out on a set of
      real-life scenarios.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Terminology">
      <t><list>
          <t>DAG - Directed Acyclic Graph.</t>

          <t>LBR - Low power and lossy network Border Router</t>

          <t>RA-DIO - Router Advertisement DAG Information Option message</t>

          <t>DAO - Destination Advertisement Option</t>

          <t>PDR - Packet Delivery Ratio</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>Please refer to additional terminology in <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-roll-terminology"></xref>.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>Designing routing in low power devices and lossy link networks
      imposes great challenges, mainly due to low data rates, high probability
      of packet delivery failure, and strict energy constraint in nodes. The
      IETF ROLL Working Group has specified RPL in <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-roll-rpl"></xref>.</t>

      <t>RPL is designed to meet the core requirements specified in <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-roll-home-routing-reqs"></xref>,<xref
      target="I-D.ietf-roll-building-routing-reqs"></xref>,<xref
      target="I-D.ietf-roll-indus-routing-reqs"> </xref> and <xref
      target="RFC5548"></xref>.</t>

      <t>This document&rsquo;s contributions are:</t>

      <t>* To provide a simulation study of RPL in various real-life
      deployment scenarios;</t>

      <t>* To include preliminary evaluation metrics that will be enriched in
      further revision. Metrics of interest will be of various nature: Path
      quality metrics; Control place overhead; Ability to cope with unstable
      situations (link churns, node dying); Required resource constraints on
      nodes (routing table size, etc.).</t>

      <t>It is to be noted that while simulation cannot prove formally that a
      protocol operates properly in all situations, it could give a good level
      of confidence in protocol behavior in highly stressful conditions, if
      and only if real data are used, as opposed to theoretical models that
      may not be applicable to such networks/scenarios. Therefore, we used
      real deployed network data to create our link model.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Method">
      <t>RPL was simulated using OMNET++, a well known event based simulator
      written in C++ and NED. We also used the Castalia-2.2 Wireless Sensor
      Network Simulator framework within OMNET++. OMNET++ is freely available
      for academic research use. The output and events in the simulating are
      visualized with the help of the Network AniMator or NAM, which is
      distributed with NS(Network Simulator). Note that NS or any of its
      versions were not used in this simulation study. Only the visualization
      tool was borrowed for verification purposes. As noted, real link layer
      data gathered from networks deployed on the field were used to compute
      the PDR (Packet Delivery Ratio) for each of the links in the network. We
      do not use theoretical models but real-life data for two aspects of the
      simulations:</t>

      <t>* Link failure model: Time varying real network traces containing
      packet delivery probability for each link and over all channels for both
      indoor network deployment and outdoor network deployment were used.
      Thus, different types of link characteristics are used in the study.</t>

      <t>* Topology: The topologies are gathered from real-life deployment
      (traces mentioned above) as opposed to random topology simulations. are
      repeated here:</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Simulation Set-up ">
      <t>We simulate RPL for a given 23 node topology, shown in Figure 1. This
      topology is here repeated for the sake of completeness. It is the
      topology shown in Figure 8 in Appendix B of <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-roll-rpl"></xref>.</t>

      <figure>
        <preamble></preamble>

        <artwork>
                                     (LBR)
                                     / | \
                                .---`  |  `----.
                               /       |        \
                            (11)------(12)------(13)
                             | \       | \       | \
                             |  `----. |  `----. |  `----.
                             |        \|        \|        \
                            (21)------(22)------(23)      (24)
                             |        /|        /|         |
                             |  .----` |  .----` |         |
                             | /       | /       |         |
                            (31)------(32)------(33)------(34)
                             |        /| \       | \       | \
                             |  .----` |  `----. |  `----. |  `----.
                             | /       |        \|        \|        \
                   .--------(41)      (42)      (43)------(44)------(45)
                  /         /         /| \       | \
            .----`    .----`    .----` |  `----. |  `----.
           /         /         /       |        \|        \
        (51)------(52)------(53)------(54)------(55)------(56)</artwork>

        <postamble>Figure 1: Network topology for preliminary simulation
        results.</postamble>
      </figure>

      <t></t>

      <t>Note that this is just a start to validate the simulation before
      using large scale networks.</t>

      <t>A database of time varying link quality data, gathered from real
      network deployment, was created. Each link in the topology randomly
      'picks up' a link model from the database, and the link&rsquo;s PDR
      varies according to the gathered data. Packets are dropped randomly from
      that link with probability (1 - PDR).</t>

      <t>In simulating RPL, the LBR first initiates sending out RA-DIO, and
      gradually the DAG is constructed. The trickle time interval for emitting
      the RA-DIO assumes the initial value of 1s, and then changes over
      simulation time as mentioned in the draft <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-roll-rpl"></xref>.</t>

      <t>I_max and I_doubling are initially taken as 1 second and 6 seconds,
      respectively, so that maximum time between two consecutive RA-DIO
      emissions by a node (under a steady network condition) is 1 minute.
      Another objective of this study is to give insight to the network
      administrator on how to tweak the trickle values. We plan to run
      simulations for large scale networks with varied parameters and show how
      quickly the network will stabilize, comparing data/control traffic and
      studying the tradeoff between reactivity and lifetime.</t>

      <t>Each node in the network, other than the LBR, also emits NA-DAO, to
      initially set up the routing table for all the nodes in the network. We
      assume that each node is capable of storing route information for other
      nodes in the network. In the next revision we will incorporate nodes
      without storage capability and see the influence of extra states on the
      nodes and the additional control plane overhead to propagate the route
      records.</t>

      <t></t>

      <t>In this simulation study, RPL is compared to an ideal shortest path
      routing, where each node has the forwarding information for every
      destination in the network. The shortest path refers to a path where
      either the number of hops or ETX of packet delivery (depending on the
      OCP used) along the path is minimum for any given source and destination
      pair. To be noted, this comparison aims at giving an insight on how
      worse the Point-to-Point path may be compared to the ideal path.</t>

      <t>For nodes implementing RPL, the routing table memory requirement
      varies depending on the position in the DAG. We make the worst-case
      assumption that there is no route summarization in the network. Thus a
      node closer to the DAG will have to store more routing entries. Further
      revision of this document will explore the influence of performing route
      summarization along the DAG, which could be performed thanks to a newly
      defined Objective Function. Also, initially we assume that all nodes
      have equal capacity to store the routing states of nodes in its
      sub-DAG.</t>

      <t>Each node also periodically (a few packets per hour)sends CBR
      (Constant Bit Rate) traffic to all other nodes in the network over the
      simulation period.</t>

      <t>The packets are routed through the DAG as mentioned in <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-roll-rpl"></xref>.</t>

      <t>We do not make any assumption on the link layer, thus potential gains
      in terms of header compression provided by 6loWPAN is not under
      consideration <xref target="draft-iphc"></xref>.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Metrics to evaluate RPL">
      <t>Routing Table Size: As the NA-DAO messages help to construct the
      routing table in the node, we record the routing table size for each
      node in the network. Currently, the routing table size is not in exact
      Kb of memory usage, but we measure it in terms of number of entries for
      each node. Each entry has next hop node and distance associated with the
      destination node. In further revision we will use a single full 128-bit
      address per leaf plus a few bits to store other information and
      flags.</t>

      <t>Hops to destination: We record the number of hops each packet
      travels. The aim of this metric is to determine how optimal is the path
      computed by the DAG compared to an optimal path computed by an
      &ldquo;ideal&rdquo; shortest path routing protocol. This allows for
      evaluating if the path cost is good enough, in particular for
      applications involving point-to-point traffic.</t>

      <t>Although simulations have been run on different and realistic
      topologies showing consistent results, the metrics discussed here may
      vary with the network topology.</t>

      <section title="Simulation Results">
        <t>Routing Table Size :</t>

        <t>Number of Hops:</t>

        <t>We currently concentrate on hop counts, but further revision will
        address several metrics as in <xref
        target="I-D.ietf-roll-routing-metrics"></xref>, such as reliability,
        energy, etc., with the objective of evaluating RPL&rsquo;s path
        quality for new metrics, combination of metrics and constraints.</t>
      </section>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.2119'?>

      <?rfc ?>

      <?rfc ?>

      <?rfc ?>

      <?rfc ?>

      <?rfc ?>

      <?rfc ?>

      <?rfc ?>

      <?rfc ?>

      <?rfc ?>

      <?rfc ?>

      <?rfc ?>

      <?rfc ?>

      <?rfc ?>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <reference anchor="I-D.ietf-roll-building-routing-reqs">
        <front>
          <title>Building Automation Routing Requirements in Low Power and
          Lossy Networks, draft-ietf-roll-building-routing-reqs-07 (work in
          progress)</title>

          <author fullname="" initials=""
                  surname="Martocci, J., Riou, N., Mil, P., and W. Vermeylen">
            <organization>draft-ietf-roll-building-routing-reqs-05</organization>
          </author>

          <date month="" year="September 2009" />
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="I-D.ietf-roll-rpl">
        <front>
          <title>RPL: Routing Protocol for Low Power and Lossy Networks,
          draft-ietf-roll-rpl-03 (work in progress)</title>

          <author surname="Winter, T., Thubert, P., et al.">
            <organization>draft-ietf-roll-rpl-03</organization>
          </author>

          <date year="October 2009" />
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="I-D.ietf-roll-home-routing-reqs">
        <front>
          <title>Home Automation Routing Requirements in Low Power and Lossy
          Networks, draft-ietf-roll-home-routing-reqs-08 (work in
          progress)</title>

          <author fullname="" initials=""
                  surname="Brandt, A., Buron, J., and G. Porcu">
            <organization>draft-ietf-roll-home-routing-reqs-08</organization>
          </author>

          <date month="" year="September 2009" />
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="I-D.ietf-roll-indus-routing-reqs">
        <front>
          <title>Industrial Routing Requirements in Low Power and Lossy
          Networks, draft-ietf-roll-indus-routing-reqs-06 (work in
          progress)</title>

          <author fullname="" initials=""
                  surname="Pister, K., Thubert, P.,  Dwars, S., Phinney, T.">
            <organization>draft-ietf-roll-indus-routing-reqs-06</organization>
          </author>

          <date month="" year="June 2009" />
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="I-D.ietf-roll-routing-metrics">
        <front>
          <title>Routing Metrics used for Path Calculation in Low Power and
          Lossy Networks, draft-ietf-roll-routing-metrics-00 (work in
          progress)</title>

          <author surname="">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date year="April 2009" />
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="I-D.ietf-roll-terminology">
        <front>
          <title>Terminology in Low power And Lossy Networks,
          draft-ietf-roll-terminology-02 (work in progress)</title>

          <author surname="JP Vasseur">
            <organization>draft-ietf-roll-terminology-02.txt</organization>
          </author>

          <date year="May 2009" />
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="draft-iphc">
        <front>
          <title>Limited IP Header Compression over PPP,
          draft-jurski-pppext-iphc-02.txt (work in progress)</title>

          <author surname="J. Jurski">
            <organization>draft-jurski-pppext-iphc-02.txt</organization>
          </author>

          <date year="March 2007" />
        </front>
      </reference>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.5548'?>

      <?rfc ?>

      <?rfc ?>

      <?rfc ?>

      <?rfc ?>
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
