<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<rfc category="exp" docName="draft-herberg-manet-nhdp-sec-01" ipr="trust200902">
	<front>
		<title abbrev="Cryptographical Signatures in NHDP">Cryptographical Signatures in NHDP</title>
		<author fullname="Ulrich Herberg" initials="U" surname="Herberg">
			<organization>LIX, Ecole Polytechnique</organization>
			<address>
				<postal>
					<street/>
					<city>91128 Palaiseau Cedex</city>
					<region/>
					<country>France</country>
				</postal>
				<email>ulrich@herberg.name</email>
				<uri>http://www.herberg.name/</uri>
			</address>
		</author>
		<author fullname="Thomas Heide Clausen" initials="T" surname="Clausen">
			<organization>LIX, Ecole Polytechnique</organization>
			<address>
				<postal>
					<street/>
					<city>91128 Palaiseau Cedex</city>
					<region/>
					<country>France</country>
				</postal>
				<phone>+33 6 6058 9349</phone>
				<email>T.Clausen@computer.org</email>
				<uri>http://www.thomasclausen.org/</uri>
			</address>
		</author>
		<date year="2011"/>
		<area/>
		<workgroup>Mobile Ad hoc Networking (MANET)</workgroup>
		<keyword>MANET</keyword>
		<keyword>Draft</keyword>
		<abstract>
			<t>This document specifies an extension to the Neighbor Discovery Protocol (NHDP) which uses cryptographic signatures in HELLO messages to encounter a selection of security threats to NHDP.</t>
		</abstract>
	</front>
	<middle>
	
		<section title="Introduction">
			<t>This document describes how to use cryptographic signatures for countering a selection of the security threats analyzed in <xref target="NHDP-sec-threats"/>. It specifies the use of such signatures for validating the identity of the originator of a HELLO message, the validity of the content (i.e. links being advertised) of a HELLO message, and the message integrity. The protection so offered against the threats in <xref target="NHDP-sec-threats"/> is evaluated.</t>
			
			<t>This document specifies TLVs for carrying cryptographic signatures in HELLO messages using <xref target="RFC5444"/>, and specifies extensions (as enabled by <xref target="NHDP"/>) to the HELLO message processing in <xref target="NHDP"/>.</t>
		</section>
		
		
		<section title="Terminology">
			<t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in <xref target="RFC2119">RFC 2119</xref>.</t>
			<t>Additionally, this document uses the terminology of <xref target="RFC5444"/>,  <xref target="packetbb-sec"/>, <xref target="NHDP"/> and <xref target="NHDP-sec-threats"/>.</t>
		</section>
		
		
		<section title="Applicability Statement">
			<!--<t>The signature extension proposed in this document applies to the neighborhood discovery protocol (<xref target="NHDP"/>) for mobile ad hoc networks (MANET). A MANET router running NHDP uses an exchange of HELLO messages in order to determine the presence and status of its 1-hop and symmetric 2-hop neighbors. Messages are defined as specified in the generalized MANET packet/message format <xref target="RFC5444"/>.

			This document is applicable for use in untrusted environments where routers may be malicious and intend to harm the neighbor discovery process.</t>-->
			<t>
				<list style="symbols">
					<t><xref target="NHDP"/> enables extensions to recognize additional reasons for rejecting a message as malformed, and mentions security as an explicit example.</t>
					<t>This document, therefore, elaborates on how this in details can be done, providing a framework for signing and validating messages in NHDP.</t>
					<t>Note that there is no "no one-size-fits-all", therefore this document uses the containers for carrying signatures and registries for cryptographic code-points as specified in <xref target="packetbb-sec"/>. The specification should therefore be generally be applicable where cryptographic signatures are thought an appropriate security solution. Note that the the choice of the cryptographic algorithm are to be made for each given deployment, and that the choice of such is out of scope for this document.</t>	
					<t>This document does not specify how to distribute cryptographic keys, shared secrets, parameters for signature algorithms, etc.</t>
					<t>Note also that this document assumes that a router which is able to sign messages correctly (e.g. having valid cryptographic keys), is considered trusted. This document does not handle compromised routers with valid keys (e.g. a router that is compromised by a computer virus).</t>
				</list>
				Therefore:
				<list style="symbols">
					<t>This document is generally applicable when <xref target="NHDP"/> is used, and uses the <xref target="RFC5444"/> extension specified in <xref target="packetbb-sec"/>.</t>
				</list>
			</t>
					
		</section>
		
		
		<section title="Protocol Overview and Functioning">
			<!--<t>This document does not specify a protocol itself, but an extension to <xref target="NHDP"/> that allows for signing and validating HELLO messages using cryptographic signatures as defined in <xref target="packetbb-sec"/> in order to:	
			<list style="symbols"><t>let only trusted routers (i.e. routers with a valid key) participate in the MANET,</t><t>limit the possibility of relay and replay attacks,</t><t>assure that an incoming HELLO message really originates from the router that the originator address claims,</t><t>prevent wrong link injection by untrusted routers.</t></list>
          
		<vspace blankLines="1"/>
         These objectives are achieved by every router being able to:
        <list style="symbols"><t>digitally sign messages using cryptographic keys.</t><t>validate (or reject) incoming signed messages.</t></list>

		<vspace blankLines="1"/>
        This specification defines, in turn:
        <list style="symbols"><t>The process of signing generated HELLO messages.</t><t>The process of validating incoming HELLO messages.</t><t>The security issues that are counteracted by using this extension of NHDP.</t></list>
      </t>-->
      		<t>The framework presented in this document provides two functionalities:
      		<list style="symbols">
      			<t>Signing a HELLO message, and</t>
      			<t>Checking whether a signed incoming HELLO message is valid.</t>
      		</list>
      		
      		When a router running NHDP is about to transmit a HELLO message on an interface, this extension:
      		
      		<list style="symbols">
      			<t>Specifies to calculate a digital signature of the message, and</t>
      			<t>Specifies how to add that signature to a message for transmission, by way of a SIGNATURE TLV.</t>
      		</list>
      		The framework allows to add several signatures with different hash and cryptographic functions.</t>
      		
      		<t><xref target="NHDP"/> allows to reject incoming HELLO messages prior to processing by NHDP for reasons such as invalid signatures. This extension specifies that for each SIGNATURE TLV in the Message TLV Block of that incoming message, the value of that TLV (i.e. the contained signature) is verified.</t>
		</section>
			
		
		<section title="Transmitting a Message in NHDP">
			<t>HELLO messages are generated as specified in <xref target="NHDP"/>. In addition, each HELLO message MUST set the &lt;msg-orig-addr&gt; as well as the &lt;msg-seq-num&gt; field as specified in <xref target="RFC5444"/>. Before transmission of a message, it is signed as described in <xref target="sign"/>.
        	</t>
		</section>
		
		
		
		<section title="Signing a Message" anchor="sign">
			<t>This section specifies how to sign a message. Note that a message may be signed several times using different signature algorithms. The following constraints MUST be respected when signing a message:
      		<list style="symbols">
      			<t>The originator address of the message MUST be included. </t>
      			<t>The sequence number of the message MUST be included.</t>
      		</list>
      
      		Optionally:
			<list style="symbols">
				<t>A TIMESTAMP TLV (as defined in <xref target="packetbb-sec"/>) MAY be added to the message if no such TLV is already included in the message TLV block of that message. The value of the TIMESTAMP TLV is the current POSIX timestamp (32-bit) of the router, and the type extension is 1 (one).</t>
			</list>

      		For each signature algorithm that is used to sign the message:
        	<list style="numbers">
        		<t>All TLVs of type SIGNATURE are temporarily removed from the message and stored in temporary variables. The message size is recalculated accordingly, i.e. to the size of the message without the SIGNATURE TLVs.</t>
        		<t>The signature value is calculated over the whole message (as resulting after step 1) according to the chosen signature algorithm.</t>
        		<t>A TLV of type SIGNATURE is added in the message TLV block. The TLV value is set to the signature calculated in step 2 as well as the chosen hash and cryptographic algorithms.</t>
        		<t>All other SIGNATURE TLVs that have been temporary removed, are restored.</t>
        		<t>The message size is recalculated.</t>
        	</list>
      		</t>
		</section>
		
		<section title="Processing a Message">
			<t>NHDP specifies that 
      			<list style="hanging">
      				<t>"On receiving a HELLO message, a router MUST first check if the message is invalid for processing by this router"</t>
      			</list>
   			and gives a number of conditions that will lead to a rejection of the HELLO message if any of these conditions is true. The extension to NHDP, specified in this document, adds the following conditions for rejecting a message:
     		<list style="symbols">
     			<t>The message does not include the &lt;msg-orig-addr&gt; or the &lt;msg-seq-num&gt; field.</t>
     			<t>The message contains more than one TIMESTAMP TLV.</t>
     			<t>Any signature of the message is invalid as specified in <xref target="validate"/>.</t>
     			<t>The timestamp of the message is invalid as specified in <xref target="validate_timestamp"/>.</t>
     		</list>
      		</t>
		</section>
		
		<section title="Validating a Timestamp" anchor="validate_timestamp">
			<t>This section specifies how to validate a message timestamp.
       		<list style="numbers">
       			<t>If the message includes a TIMESTAMP Message TLV, and the value of the TIMESTAMP TLV differs from the current POSIX time of more than MAX_TIMESTAMP_DIFF, the message MUST be discarded.</t>
          	</list>  
      		</t>
		</section>
		
		
		<section title="Validating a Signature" anchor="validate">
			<t>This section specifies how to validate a message signature.
       		<list style="numbers">
       			<t>For all SIGNATURE Message TLVs:
           			<list style="letters">
           				<t>If the hash function and the cryptographic function defined in that TLV are known to the router: goto step 2.</t>
           				<t>Otherwise goto step 1</t>
           			</list>
          		</t>
          		<t>If no signature algorithm has been recognized in step 1, the message MUST be discarded.</t>
          		<t>All SIGNATURE TLVs are removed from the message, and the message size is recalculated.</t>
          		<t>The signature is recalculated using the same hash function and cryptographic function as indicated in the TLV, and compared with the signature from the SIGNATURE TLV that has been removed in step 3.</t>
          		<t>If the verification fails, the message MUST be discarded.</t>
          		<t>Otherwise:
            		<list style="letters">
            			<t>All SIGNATURE TLVs are restored.</t>
            			<t>The message size is restored.</t>
            		</list>
          		</t>
          		<t>The message can now be processed according to <xref target="NHDP"/>.</t>
          	</list>  
      		</t>
		</section>
		
		
		<section title="Parameters and Constants">
			<t>This document specifies the following parameters and constants:
			<list style="symbols">
				<t>MAX_TIMESTAMP_DIFF - The maximum age a message that is to be validated may have. If the current POSIX time of the router validating the message minus the timestamp indicated in the TIMESTAMP TLV of the message is greater than MAX_TIMESTAMP_DIFF, the message will be discarded.</t>
			</list>
			
			The following constraints apply to these parameters:
			<list style="symbols">
				<t>MAX_TIMESTAMP_DIFF &gt; 0</t>
			</list>
			</t>
		</section>
		
		
		<section title="Preconditions">
			<t>Before a router is able to sign or validate messages, it must initially parameterize some security settings. In particular, it MUST acquire the cryptographic key(s) and any parameters of the cryptographic algorithm from all other routers that are to participate in the network. This document does not specify how a router acquires the cryptographic keys and parameters used in the MANET. 
        	</t>
		</section>
		
		
		<section title="Summary of NHDP Interaction">
			<t>When the security mechanism as specified in this document is used, the following MUST be observed:
			<list style="symbols">
				<t>NHDP must generate HELLO messages as usual.</t>
				<t>NHDP MUST allow this security mechanism access to the HELLO message after its generation and prior to transmission, in order that a SIGNATURE TLV can be generated and inserted, as allowed by Section 16 in <xref target="NHDP"/>.</t>
				<t>Any other NHDP extension which adds information to a HELLO message and which wishes this added information to be included when calculating the cryptographic signature MUST do so prior to the HELLO message being handed off for signature generation.</t>
				<t>An incoming HELLO message MUST be processed according to this specification prior to processing by <xref target="NHDP"/> as allowed in Section 16 in <xref target="NHDP"/>.</t>
				<t>Any other NHDP extension, which has added information to a HELLO message and which wishes that the HELLO message is rejected if a cryptographic signature is not valid, MUST likewise process the HELLO message only after its processing according to this specification.</t>
			</list>
			</t>
		</section>
		
		
		<section title="Security Threats Alleviation Analysis">
			<t>This section analyzes which of the security threats that are detailed in <xref target="NHDP-sec-threats"/> are alleviated by the framework presented in this document.</t>
			
			<section title="Jamming">
				<t>Since jamming is a physical layer issue, it cannot be alleviated by protocols on the routing layer. This framework does not counteract jamming attacks, therefore.</t>
			</section>
			
			<section anchor="identity_spoofing" title="Identity Spoofing">
				<t>As only routers possessing valid cryptographic keys are able to correctly sig  HELLO messages, identity spoofing is counteracted. If a router does not have access to valid keys or does not sign messages at all, it is not able to create HELLOs that are processed by neighbor routers. Such wrongly signed or unsigned messages are rejected by receiving routers as described in <xref target="validate"/>.</t>
			</section>
			
			<section title="Link Spoofing">
				<t>Link spoofing is counteracted by the framework specified in this document, with the same argument as in <xref target="identity_spoofing"/>. A router without access to valid cryptographic keys cannot sign the message correctly, and therefore the message will be rejected by any receiving routers. Hence, all links postulated by an attacker are ignored.</t>
			</section>
			
			<section title="Replay Attack">
				<t>Replay attacks are only counteracted if TIMESTAMP TLVs are included in HELLO messages. This is optional, and depends on synchronized clocks of all routers in the MANET. An attacker which records messages to replay them later can only do so in the time interval between the timestamp that is contained in the TIMESTAMP TLV and MAX_TIMESTAMP_DIFF seconds later. As an attacker cannot modify the content of the TIMESTAMP TLV (since it does not possess the valid cryptographic keys), it cannot replay messages after this time interval. Within this time interval, however, it is still possible to replay attacks.</t>
			</section>
		</section>
		
		
		<section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
			<t>This document has no actions for IANA.</t>
		</section>
		
		
		<section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
			<t>This document specifies a protocol extension to NHDP which allows to alleviate some of the security threats of NHDP analyzed in <xref target="NHDP-sec-threats"/>.</t>
			
			<t>If no synchronized clocks are available in the MANET, replay attacks cannot be counteracted by this framework.</t>
			
			<t>This framework does not avoid or detect security attacks by routers possessing the cryptographic keys that is used to sign messages.</t>
			
			<t>This specification depends on the quality of the used signature algorithm and provides as such the same security considerations as the hash function and the cipher algorithm.</t>
			
			<t>This specification relies on an out-of-band protocol to distribute keys and parameters. The security considerations of that protocol apply.</t>
			
			<t>This specification does not provide a key revocation mechanism.</t>
		</section>
		
	</middle>
	
	
	
	<back>
		<references title="Normative References">
			<reference anchor="packetbb-sec">
				<front>
					<title abbrev="MANET Cryptographical Signature TLV">MANET Cryptographical Signature TLV Definition</title>
					<author fullname="Ulrich Herberg" initials="U" surname="Herberg">
						<organization>LIX, Ecole Polytechnique</organization>
					</author>
					<author fullname="Thomas Heide Clausen" initials="T" surname="Clausen">
						<organization>LIX, Ecole Polytechnique</organization>
					</author>
					<date year="2011" month="March"/>
				</front>
				<seriesInfo name="work in progress" value="draft-ietf-manet-packetbb-sec-03.txt"/>
			</reference>
			
			
			<reference anchor="RFC2119">
				<front>
					<title abbrev="RFC Key Words">Key words for use in RFCs to Indicate Requirement Levels</title>
					<author initials="S." surname="Bradner" fullname="Scott Bradner">
						<organization>Harvard University</organization>
					</author>
					<date year="1997" month="March"/>
				</front>
				<seriesInfo name="BCP" value="14"/>
				<seriesInfo name="RFC" value="2119"/>
				<format type="TXT" octets="4723" target="ftp://ftp.isi.edu/in-notes/rfc2119.txt"/>
				<format type="HTML" octets="17491" target="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/html/rfc2119.html"/>
				<format type="XML" octets="5777" target="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/xml/rfc2119.xml"/>
			</reference>
			
			
			<reference anchor="NHDP">
				<front>
					<title>Mobile Ad Hoc Network (MANET) Neighborhood Discovery Protocol (NHDP)</title>
					<author initials="T." surname="Clausen" fullname="Thomas Heide Clausen">
						<organization abbrev="X">LIX, Ecole Polytechnique</organization>
					</author>
					<author initials="C." surname="Dearlove" fullname="Christopher Dearlove">
						<organization>BAE Systems ATC</organization>
					</author>
					<author initials="J." surname="Dean" fullname="Justin W. Dean">
						<organization abbrev="NRL">Naval Research Laboratory</organization>
					</author>
					<date month="March" year="2011"/>
				</front>
				<seriesInfo name="RFC" value="6130"/>
			</reference>
			
			<reference anchor="NHDP-sec-threats">
				<front>
					<title>Security Threats for NHDP</title>
					<author initials="U." surname="Herberg" fullname="Ulrich Herberg">
						<organization abbrev="NRL">Ecole Polytechnique, France</organization>
					</author>
					<author initials="T.H." surname="Clausen" fullname="Thomas Heide Clausen">
						<organization abbrev="X">Ecole Polytechnique, France</organization>
					</author>
					<date month="November" year="2009"/>
				</front>
				<seriesInfo name="work in progress" value="draft-herberg-manet-nhdp-sec-threats-00.txt"/>
			</reference>
			
			
			<reference anchor="RFC5444">
				<front>
					<title abbrev="RFC5444">Generalized MANET Packet/Message Format</title>
					<author initials="T.H." surname="Clausen" fullname="Thomas Heide Clausen">
						<organization abbrev="X">Ecole Polytechnique, France</organization>
					</author>
					<author initials="C.M." surname="Dearlove" fullname="Christopher Dearlove">
						<organization abbrev="BAE">BAE Systems Advanced Technology Centre, UK</organization>
					</author>
					<author initials="J.W." surname="Dean" fullname="Justin W. Dean">
						<organization abbrev="NRL">Naval Research Laboratory, USA</organization>
					</author>
					<author initials="C." surname="Adjih" fullname="Cedric Adjih">
						<organization>INRIA Rocquencourt</organization>
					</author>
					<date month="February" year="2009"/>
				</front>
				<seriesInfo name="RFC" value="5444"/>
			</reference>
		</references>
	
		<!-- references title="Informative References">
    	</references-->
		
		<!--
    	<section title="Appendix">
      		<t></t>
    	</section>
    	-->
	</back>
</rfc>
