<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">

<rfc category='bcp' ipr='trust200902'
     docName='draft-ivov-xmpp-cusax-00'>

<?rfc toc='yes' ?>
<?rfc symrefs='yes' ?>
<?rfc sortrefs='yes'?>
<?rfc iprnotified='no' ?>
<?rfc strict='yes' ?>
<?rfc compact='yes' ?>
  <front>

    <title abbrev='Combined Use of SIP and XMPP'>
      Combined Use of the Session Initiation Protocol (SIP) and the 
      eXtensible Messaging and Presence Protocol (CUSAX) 
    </title>
    <author initials='E.' surname='Ivov' fullname='Emil Ivov'>
      <organization abbrev='Jitsi'>Jitsi</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>
          <city>Strasbourg</city>
          <code>67000</code>
          <country>France</country>
        </postal>
        <email>emcho@jitsi.org</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author initials='E.' surname='Marocco' fullname='Enrico Marocco'>
      <organization>Telecom Italia</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Via G. Reiss Romoli, 274</street>
          <city>Turin</city>
          <code>10148</code>
          <country>Italy</country>
        </postal>
        <email>enrico.marocco@telecomitalia.it</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date />
    <abstract>
      <t>
        This document describes current practices for combined use of 
        the Session Initiation Protocol (SIP) and the eXtensible 
        Messaging and Presence Protocol (XMPP). Such practices aim to
        provide a single fully featured real-time communication service
        by using complimenting subsets of features from each of the 
        protocols. Typically such subsets would include telephony
        oriented ones from SIP and instant messaging and presence 
        capabilities from XMPP. This specification does not define any 
        new protocols or syntax for neither SIP nor XMPP. However, 
        implementing it may require modifying or at least reconfiguring 
        existing client and server-side software. Also, it is not the 
        purpose of this document to make recommendations as to whether 
        or not such combined use should be preferred to the mechanisms 
        provided natively by each protocol like for example SIP's SIMPLE
        or XMPP's Jingle. It merely aims to provide guidance to those 
        who are interested in such a combined use.
      </t>
    </abstract>
  </front>
  <middle>
    <section title='Introduction'>
      <t>
        Historically <xref target="RFC3261">SIP</xref> and 
        <xref target="RFC6120">XMPP</xref> have often been implemented 
        and deployed with different purposes: from its very start SIP's 
        primary goal has been to provide a means of conducting "Internet 
        telephone calls". XMPP on the other hand, has from its Jabber 
        days been mostly used for its instant messaging and presence 
        capabilities. 
      </t>
      <t>
        For various reasons, these trends have continued through the 
        years even after each of the protocols had been equipped to 
        provide the features it was initially lacking.
      </t>
      <t>
        Today, in the context of the SIMPLE working group, the IETF has 
        defined a number of protocols and protocol extensions that not
        only allow for SIP to be used for regular instant messaging and
        presence but that also provide mechanisms for elaborated 
        features such as multi-user chats, server-stored contact lists,
        file transfer and others.
      </t>
      <t>
        Similarly, the XMPP community and the XMPP Standards Foundation
        have worked on defining a number of XMPP Extension Protocols
        (XEPs) that provide XMPP implementations with the means of 
        establishing end-to-end sessions. These extensions are often 
        jointly referred to as Jingle and their arguably most popular
        use case are audio and video calls.  
      </t>
      <t>
        Yet, despite these advances SIP remains the protocol of choice
        for telephony-like services, especially in enterprises where 
        users are accustomed to features such as voice mail, call park,
        call queues, conference bridges and many others that are rarely
        (if at all) available in Jingle servers. XMPP implementations on 
        the other hand, greatly outnumber and outperform those available
        for protocols recommended by SIMPLE, such as [MSRP] and [XCAP].  
      </t>
      <t>
        For these reasons in a number of cases, adopters may find 
        themselves needing a set of features that are not offered by any 
        single-protocol solution but that separately exist in SIP and 
        XMPP products. The idea of seamlessly using both protocols 
        together would hence often appeal to service providers.      
      </t>
      <t>
        Most often such combined use would employ SIP exclusively for 
        audio, video and telephony services and it would rely on XMPP 
        for anything else varying from chat, roster management and 
        presence to exchanging files.
      </t>
      <t>
        This document explains how the above could be achieved with a
        minimum amount of modifications on existing software while 
        providing an optimal user experience. It tries to cover points 
        such as server discovery, determining a SIP AOR while using 
        XMPP and an XMPP JID from incoming SIP requests. Most of the 
        text here pertains to client behavior but it also recommends 
        certain server-side configurations.
      </t>
    </section>
    <section title="Terminology">
      <t>
        The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL
        NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and
        "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described
        in <xref target="RFC2119"/>.
      </t>
    </section>
    <section title='Client Bootstrap'>
      <t>
        One of the main problems of using two distinct protocols when
        providing one service is how it affects usability. E-mail 
        services for example have long been affected by the mixed use of 
        SMTP on for outgoing mail and POP3 and IMAP for incoming, making 
        it rather complicated for inexperienced users to configure a 
        mail client and start using it with a new service. As a result 
        mailing list services often need to provide configuration 
        instructions for various mail clients. Client developers and
        communications device manufacturers on the other hand often ship
        with a number of wizards that allow to easily set up a new 
        account for a number of popular e-mail services. While this may 
        improve the situation to some extent, user experience is still 
        clearly sub-optimal.
      </t>
      <t>
        While it should be possible for CUSAX users to manually 
        configure their separate SIP and XMPP accounts, it is 
        RECOMMENDED that dual stack SIP/XMPP clients provide means of 
        online provisioning. While the specifics of such mechanisms are 
        not in the scope of this specification, they should make it 
        possible for service providers to remotely configure the clients
        based on minimal user input (e.g. user id and password).
      </t>
      <t>
        Given that many of the features that CUSAX would privilege in
        one protocol would also be available in the other, clients 
        should make it possible for such features to be disabled for a 
        specific account. Specifically it is RECOMMENDED that clients
        allow for audio/video calling features to be disabled for XMPP
        accounts. Additionally instant messaging and presence features 
        MAY also be made optional for SIP accounts.
      </t>
      <t>
        The main advantage of the above would be that clients would be
        able to continue to function properly and use the complete 
        feature set of stand-alone SIP and XMPP accounts. 
      </t>
      <t>
        Once client bootstrap has completed, clients SHOULD log 
        independently to the SIP and XMPP accounts that make up the 
        CUSAX service and should maintain both these connections. In 
        order to improve user experience, when reporting connection 
        status clients may also wish to present the CUSAX XMPP 
        connection as an "instant messaging" or a "chat" account. 
        Similarly they could also depict the SIP CUSAX connection as a
        "Voice and Video" or a "Telephony" connection. The exact naming
        is of course entirely up to implementors. The point is that such
        presentation  could help users better understand why they are 
        being shown two different connections for a single service. It
        could even alleviate especially situations where one of these 
        connections is disrupted while the other one is successfully 
        maintained.
      </t>
    </section>
    <section title='Operation'>
      <t>
        Once a CUSAX client has been provisioned/configured to connect
        to the corresponding SIP and XMPP services it would proceed by 
        retrieving its XMPP roster. In order for CUSAX to function 
        properly, XMPP service administrators should make sure that at 
        least one of the [VCARD] "tel" fields for each contact is 
        properly populated with a SIP URI or  a phone number. There are 
        no limitations as to the form of that number (e.g. it does not 
        need to respect any equivalence with the XMPP JID). It SHOULD
        however be reachable through the SIP counterpart of this CUSAX
        service.
      </t>
      <t>
        In order to make sure that the above is always respected, 
        service maintainers MAY prevent clients (and hence users) from
        modifying the VCARD "tel" fields or they MAY apply some form of
        validation before recording changes.
      </t>
      <t>  
        When rendering the XMPP roaster CUSAX clients should make sure
        that users are presented with a "Call" option for each roster 
        entry that has a properly set "tel" field even if calling has
        been disabled for that particular XMPP account. The usefulness 
        of such a feature is not limited to CUSAX. After all, numbers
        are entered in VCARDs in order to be dialed and called. Hence, 
        as long as an XMPP client is equipped with accounts that have 
        calling features it may wish to present the user with the
        option of using these accounts to reach numbers from an XMPP 
        VCARD. In order to improve usability, in cases where clients are 
        provisioned with only a single telephony capable account they 
        SHOULD do so immediately upon user request without asking for 
        confirmation. This way CUSAX users whose only account with 
        calling capabilities would often be the SIP part of their 
        service would be having better user experience. If on the other 
        hand, the CUSAX client is aware of multiple telephony-capable 
        accounts, it SHOULD present the user with the choice of reaching 
        the phone number through any of them (including the source XMPP 
        account where the VCARD was obtained) in order to guarantee 
        proper operation for XMPP accounts that are not part of a CUSAX 
        deployment.
      </t>
      <t> 
        The client should use XMPP for all other forms of communication 
        with the contacts from its roster so it should and this should 
        occur naturally given that they were retrieved through XMPP. 
      </t>
      <t>
        When receiving SIP calls, clients may wish to determine the 
        identity of the caller and bind it to a roster entry so that 
        users could revert to chatting or other forms of communication
        that require XMPP. To do so clients could search their roster
        for an entry whose VCARD has a "tel" field matching the 
        originator of the call.
      </t>
      <t>
        An alternate mechanism would be for CUSAX clients to add to 
        their SIP invite requests a contact header containing their 
        XMPP JID, but at this point we are not really sure if that's '
        such a good idea. (After all Contact headers carry URIs and 
        JIDs are not URIs).
      </t>
    </section>
    <section title='Security Considerations'>
      <t>
        TBD
      </t>
    </section>
    <section title='Acknowledgements'>
      <t>
        This draft is inspired by work from Markus Isomaki and Simo
        Veikkolainen.
      </t>
    </section>
  </middle>
  <back>
    <references title='Normative References'>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119"?>
    </references>
    <references title='Informative References'>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3261"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6120"?>
      
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3264"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3489"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3711"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4474"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4566"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4787"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5245"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5389"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5751"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5766"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5853"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6189"?>
      <reference anchor="XEP-0177">
        <front>
        <title>XEP-0177: Jingle Raw UDP Transport Method</title>
        <author initials='J.' surname='Beda'
                    fullname='Joe Beda'>
                <organization abbrev='Google'>
                Google
                </organization>
        </author>
        <author initials='P.' surname='Saint-Andre'
                    fullname='Peter Saint-Andre'>
                <organization abbrev='Cisco'>
                Cisco
                </organization>
        </author>
        <author initials='J.' surname='Hildebrand'
                    fullname='J. Hildebrand'>
                <organization abbrev='Cisco'>
                Cisco
                </organization>
        </author>
        <author initials='S.' surname='Egan'
                    fullname='Sean Egan'>
                <organization abbrev='Google'>
                Google
                </organization>
        </author>
        <date month="December" year="2009" />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="XEP" value="XEP-0177" />
      </reference>
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
