<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!-- This template is for creating an Internet Draft using xml2rfc,
     which is available here: http://xml.resource.org. -->
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!-- One method to get references from the online citation libraries.
     There has to be one entity for each item to be referenced. 
     An alternate method (rfc include) is described in the references. -->

<!ENTITY RFC2119 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC2629 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2629.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3552 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3552.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.narten-iana-considerations-rfc2434bis SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.narten-iana-considerations-rfc2434bis.xml">
]>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<!-- used by XSLT processors -->
<!-- For a complete list and description of processing instructions (PIs), 
     please see http://xml.resource.org/authoring/README.html. -->
<!-- Below are generally applicable Processing Instructions (PIs) that most I-Ds might want to use.
     (Here they are set differently than their defaults in xml2rfc v1.32) -->
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<!-- give errors regarding ID-nits and DTD validation -->
<!-- control the table of contents (ToC) -->
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<!-- generate a ToC -->
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<!-- the number of levels of subsections in ToC. default: 3 -->
<!-- control references -->
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<!-- use symbolic references tags, i.e, [RFC2119] instead of [1] -->
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<!-- sort the reference entries alphabetically -->
<!-- control vertical white space 
     (using these PIs as follows is recommended by the RFC Editor) -->
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<!-- do not start each main section on a new page -->
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<!-- keep one blank line between list items -->
<!-- end of list of popular I-D processing instructions -->
<rfc category='info' docName='draft-geib-tsvwg-diffserv-intercon-04' ipr='trust200902'>
  <!-- category values: std, bcp, info, exp, and historic
     ipr values: noModificationTrust200902, noDerivativesTrust200902, pre5378Trust200902
     you can add the attributes updates="NNNN" and obsoletes="NNNN" 
     they will automatically be output with "(if approved)" -->

  <!-- ***** FRONT MATTER ***** -->

  <front>
    <!-- The abbreviated title is used in the page header - it is only necessary if the 
         full title is longer than 39 characters -->

    <title abbrev="Abbreviated Title">DiffServ interconnection classes and practice</title>

    <!-- add 'role="editor"' below for the editors if appropriate -->

    <!-- Another author who claims to be an editor -->

    <author fullname="Ruediger Geib" initials="R." role="editor"
            surname="Geib">
      <organization>Deutsche Telekom</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Heinrich Hertz Str. 3-7</street>

          <!-- Reorder these if your country does things differently -->

          <code>64295</code>
          
          <city>Darmstadt</city>

          <region></region>

          <country>Germany</country>
        </postal>

        <phone>+49 6151 5812747</phone>

        <email>Ruediger.Geib@telekom.de</email>

        <!-- uri and facsimile elements may also be added -->
      </address>
    </author>

    <date month="October" year="2013" />

    <!-- If the month and year are both specified and are the current ones, xml2rfc will fill 
         in the current day for you. If only the current year is specified, xml2rfc will fill 
	 in the current day and month for you. If the year is not the current one, it is 
	 necessary to specify at least a month (xml2rfc assumes day="1" if not specified for the 
	 purpose of calculating the expiry date).  With drafts it is normally sufficient to 
	 specify just the year. -->

    <!-- Meta-data Declarations -->

    <area>Transport</area>

    <workgroup>TSVWG</workgroup>

    <!-- WG name at the upperleft corner of the doc,
         IETF is fine for individual submissions.  
	 If this element is not present, the default is "Network Working Group",
         which is used by the RFC Editor as a nod to the history of the IETF. -->

    <keyword>RFC5127, DiffServ, Interconnection</keyword>

    <!-- Keywords will be incorporated into HTML output
         files in a meta tag but they have no effect on text or nroff
         output. If you submit your draft to the RFC Editor, the
         keywords will be used for the search engine. -->

    <abstract>
      <t>This document proposes a limited set of interconnection QoS PHBs and 
      PHB groups. It further introduces some DiffServ deployment aspects. The proposals 
      made here should be integrated into a revised version of RFC5127.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>

    <section title="Introduction">

      <t>This draft proposes a DiffServ interconnection class and 
      codepoint scheme. At least one party of an interconnection often is a 
      network provider. Many network providers operate Aggregated DiffServ 
      classes. This draft contains concepts and current 
      practice relevant for a revised version of <xref target="RFC5127">RFC5127</xref>. 
      Its main purpose is to be considered as an input for the latter task.</t>

      <t>DiffServ sees deployment in many networks for the time being. As 
      described in the introduction of the <xref target="I-D.polk-tsvwg-diffserv-stds-problem-statement">
      draft DiffServ problem statement</xref>, remarking of packets at domain 
      boundaries is a DiffServ feature. This draft proposes a set of standard 
      QoS classes and codepoints at interconnection points to which and from 
      which locally used classes and codepoints should be mapped. Such a scheme 
      simplifies interconnection negotiations and ensures that end to end class 
      properties remain roughly the same while codepoints may change.</t>

      <t>The proposed Interconnection class and codepoint scheme tries to 
      reflect and consolidate related DiffServ and QoS standardisation efforts 
      outside of the IETF, namely MEF, GSMA and ITU.</t>

      <t>IP Precedence has been deprecated when DiffServ was standardised. It 
       is common practice today however to copy the DSCPs Bits 0-2 (called 
       DSCP Precedence Prefix in the following) into MPLS TC or Ethernet P-Bits. 
       This is also reflected by the DiffServ codepoint 
       definitions of AF and EF.  Class based PHBs may be applied 
       in core network sections rather than then DSCP based PHBs.</t>

      <t>The set of available router and traffic 
      management tools to configure and operate DiffServ classes is limited. 
      This should be reflected by class definitions. These may in the end be  
      more related to transport properties than to application requirements. 
      Please interpret transport properties as "congestion aware" and "not 
      congestion aware" rather then TCP or UDP.</t>

      <t>Finally, this draft proposes to leave some lass Selector Codepoint and 
      by that MPLS TC codepoint space to allow for future DiffServ extensions like ECN/PCN 
      and domain internal classes. An example for an internal PHB may be CS6.  
      Some operators protect their network internal routing and / or management 
      traffic by CS6. This PHB is possibly not available to transport customer 
      or interconnection partner signaling and management traffic.</t>

      <t>In addition to the standardisation activities which triggered this work, 
      other authors published RFCs or drafts which may benefit from an interconnection 
      class- and codepoint scheme. RFC 5160 suggests Meta-QoS-Classes to enable 
      deployment of standardised end to end QoS <xref target="RFC5160">classes</xref>. The authors agree that the 
      proposed interconnection class- and codepoint scheme as well as the idea of 
      standardised end to end classes would complement their own work.
      Work on signaling Class of Service at interconnection interfaces by <xref target="I-D.knoll-idr-cos-interconnect">BGP</xref>, <xref target="ID.idr-sla"> </xref> 
      is beyond the scope of this draft. Should the basic transport 
      and class properties be standardised as proposed here, signaled 
      access to QoS classes may be of interest. The current BGP drafts focus on 
      exchanging SLA and traffic conditioning parameters. They seem to assume that 
      common interpretation of the PHB properties identified by DSCPs has been 
      established prior to exchanging further details by BGP signaling.</t>

      <section title="Requirements Language">
        <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
        "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
        document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
        target="RFC2119">RFC 2119</xref>.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Terminology">
      
      <t>This draft re-uses existing terminology.</t>

     <t><list hangIndent="8" style="hanging">

         <t hangText="DSCP Precedence Prefix">The bits 0-2 of the DSCP (marked "x" in this 
             generic DSCP field: xxxddd) are called the <xref target="RFC2474">DSCP Precedence Prefix</xref> in the following.
             By ignoring the value of bits 3-6 ( d stands for don' care), a simple 
             aggregation of PHBs differed by DSCP is possible in IP and MPLS backbones, 
             but also if Ethernet transport is applied. This is discussed in more detail below.</t> 
  
         <t hangText="Class"> A class is a set of one or more PHBs utilising the same 
             PHB if classified by a single identical DSCP Precedence Prefix (<xref target="RFC2597">e.g. an AF class</xref>). 
             It is <xref target="RFC3260"> a PHB Scheduling Class</xref> or an Ordered Aggregate.  
             A class is a <xref target="RFC2575">PHB group</xref>. Different classes must 
             not be aggregated.</t>

         <t hangText="PHB">On IP layer, a single DSCP identifies a single PHB. In 
             addition, this document proposes an MPLS like classification of traffic for 
             a single PHB based on the DSCP Precedence Prefix (<xref target="RFC3270">see</xref>).</t>

          </list></t>

      <t>The above references may be incomplete and mostly refer to the early 
      DiffServ RFCs only.</t>

      <t>To gain clarity, "DSCP based PHB selection" is only meant if expressed exactly that 
      way in the remaining document. "PHB" here relates to DSCP Precedence Prefix based PHB 
      selection.</t>


      <t>The following current practice issues relate to the concept of the DiffServ 
      interconnection class proposal rather than to terminology. They serve as
      additional motivation of this activity:</t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>Abstract class names like "EF" are preferential over those 
          being close to an application, like "Voice". Unfortunately, 
          non QoS experts can't handle abstract class names. Hence and usually 
          sooner than later, classes are named for applications or groups 
          of them. One consequence however is, that people tend to combine 
          application group class names and SLA parameters. Based on an application 
          specific name and some worst case performance numbers on a paper, 
          they often decide that their application needs a separate new 
          QoS class.</t>

          <t>Worse than that, but very present in practice, is the class 
          abstraction level which is preferred by those dealing with QoS 
          (as experts or non experts): the DSCPs or the DSCP Precedence Prefix values. 
          These are the commodity abstractions applied for QoS classes. Most 
          of these persons have fixed class to codepoint mappings in their 
          minds, which they can't easily adapt on per customer or per
          interconnection partner basis. </t>
      </list></t> 
      
      <t>While these issues aren't to be solved by IETF (QoS experts 
      could and should of course teach staff to use proper Diffserv 
      terminology and concepts), a simple and comprehensible QoS interconnection 
      class scheme also is helpful in this area.</t>
    </section>
      
    <section title="Aggregating PHBs of a class by a DSCP Precedence Prefix">
      
      <t>Operation of IP and MPLS networks and router configuration is simplified, 
       if DSCP based PHBs can be aggregated into a single class by simply 
       classifying them by their DSCP Precedence Prefix. As specified above, 
       the DSCP Precedence Prefix are the bits 0-2 od the DSCP. If classification 
       based on DSCP Precedence Prefix is applied in an MPLS domain, the DSCP 
       Precedence Prefix my simply be copied into the MPLS TC field. This is 
       very useful in domains operating Pen-ultimate hop popping. Also in this 
       case, operation and configuration of routers can be simplified 
       significantly as compared to aggregation schemes based on configuring 
       individual DSCPs.</t>

      <t>A network provider applying DSCP Precedence Prefix based aggregation MAY 
       remark incoming DSCPs so that they can be aggregated by their DSCP Precedence 
       Prefix. To allow for simple carrier interconnection agreements, carriers 
       sending traffic belonging to the same class but marked by DSCPs with differing 
       DSCP Precedence Prefixes SHOULD apply the interconnection marking and codepoint 
       scheme specified below, if they interconnect to a carrier applying DSCP 
       Precedence Prefix based traffic aggregation. An example where this may be 
       required is the <xref target="IR.34">Interactive Class of GSMA IR.34</xref>  (note that 
       the author of this draft believes that the GSMA specification is breaking RFC 2597). 
       Another option is to negotiate a customised interconnection agreement of course.</t>

     <t>A node forwarding traffic based the DSCP Precedence Prefix MUST classify this traffic
      by the DSCP bits 0-2 and it MUST ignore the bits 4-6 of DSCP for classification. 
      Classification by DSCP Precedence Prefix is useful for links aggregating DiffServ 
      traffic. DSCP Precedence Prefix based classification is not recommended as a general 
      mode of operation. Edge systems, QoS policy enforcement nodes, service areas and hosts 
      benefit from fine grained DSCP based classification and should continue to do so.</t>

     <t>RFC 2474 specifies the <xref target="RFC2474">Class Selector Codepoints</xref>. These 
      offer a similar concept, but they are strictly limited to xxx000 DSCPs. The Class 
      Selector Codepoints don't offer aggregation, they just simplify classification. This draft 
      intents to aggregate several PHBs of a single class by a DSCP Precedence Prefix, which 
      a different concept than that of the Class Selector Codepoints.</t>

    </section>

    <section title="An Interconnection class and codepoint scheme">
      
      <t>DiffServ deployments mostly follow loose class specification schemes 
      (often one or two AF classes, EF and Best Effort). Especially 
      DSCP assignment for the AF classes varies between deployments.  
      Basic AF class property definitions are often similar however. Applying 
      provider specific DSCPs is in line with the DiffServ architecture. This 
      document doesn't propose to change that.</t>

      <t>Interconnecting parties face the problem of matching classes 
      to be interconnected and then to agree on codepoint mapping. As stated 
      by <xref target="I-D.polk-tsvwg-diffserv-stds-problem-statement">
      draft DiffServ problem statement</xref>, remarking is a standard 
      behaviour at interconnection interfaces. This draft proposes a 
      standard interconnection set of 4 QoS classes with well defined 
      DSCP and DSCP Precedence Prefix values. A sending party remarks DSCPs 
      from internal schemes to the Interconnection codepoints. The 
      receiving party remarks DSCP Precedence Prefixes and / or DSCPs to her internal 
      scheme. Thus the interconnection codepoint scheme fully complies with 
      the DiffServ architecture. An interconnection class and codepoint 
      scheme was introduced by <xref target="Y.1566">ITU-T</xref> (there also 
      includíng Ethernet). It is specified to a higher level of detail in 
      this document.</t>

      <t>At first glance, this looks like an additional effort. But there are 
      obvious benefits: each party sending or receiving traffic has to 
      specify the mapping from or to the interconnection class and codepoint 
      scheme only once. Without it, this is to be negotiated per 
      interconnection party individually. Further, end-to-end QoS in terms 
      of traffic being classified for the same class in all passed domains 
      is likely to result if an interconnection codepoint scheme is used. It 
      is not necessarily resulting from individual per network mapping 
      negotiations.</t>

      <t>The standards and deployments known to the author of this 
      draft are limited to 4 DiffServ classes at interconnection points (or 
      less).<xref target="I-D.polk-tsvwg-rfc4594-update">
      Draft RFC 4597 update </xref>doesn't seem to generally contradict 
      to this, as it proposes to standardise "many services classes, not all 
      will be used in each network at any period of time." Some reasons favour
      working with 4 DiffServ interconnection classes:</t>
      
      <t><list style="symbols">

         <t>There should be a coding reserve for interconnection classes. This leaves 
         space for future standards, for private bilateral agreements and for provider 
         internal classes.</t>

         <t>MPLS and Ethernet support only 8 PHBs, classes or ECN indications. 
         Assignment of 3 bit codepoints for whatever purpose must be well thought through. 
         Limiting interconnection QoS to four classes is MPLS and Ethernet friendly 
         in that sense.</t>

         <t>Migrations from one codepoint scheme to another may require spare 
         QoS codepoints.</t>

      </list></t>

      <t>The proposed class and codepoint scheme is designed for point to point IP 
      layer interconnections. Other types of interconnections are out of scope of 
      this document. The basic class and codepoint scheme is applicable on Ethernet 
      layer too.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Consolidation of QoS standards by the interconnection codepoint scheme">
      
      <t>The interconnection class and codepoint scheme proposed by Y.1566 also 
      tries to consolidate related DiffServ and QoS standardisation efforts 
      outside of <xref target="Y.1566"> the IETF</xref>. The interconnection class and 
      codepoint scheme may be a suitable approach to consolidate these standards.
      MEF 23.1 specifies 3 aggregated classes, consuming up to 5 codepoints on 
      Ethernet layer (EF, AF3, AF1 and Best Effort) 
      and <xref target="MEF23.1"> 5 PHBs </xref>. MEF aggregates AF1 and Default 
      PHB in a single class. This is not recommended for interconnection, 
      as it is not in line with RFC 2597 (which requires separate forwarding 
      resources for each AF class and doesn't foresee aggregation of Default PHB 
      and an AF class).</t> 

     <t>GSMA IR.34 proposes four classes, EF, AF4, another AF class and 
      Best Effort with <xref target="IR.34"> 7 PHBs in sum</xref>. IR.34 specifies 
      an "Interactive" class consisting of 3 PHBs with different priorities.
      IR.34 assigns the PHBS AF31, AF21 and AF11 to this Interactive class. 
      This breaks RFC 2597. The proposed interconnection class and codepoint scheme 
      supports an GSMA Interactive like class but assigns AF3 with PHBs AF31, AF32 and 
      AF33.</t>

     <t>If IETF picks up this draft, it may be a good idea to inform MEF and GSMA about
     conflicts of their standards with DiffServ and suggest joint activities to improve 
     the situation. Information on interworking with MEF 23 and GSMA IR.34 with the 
     interconnection QoS scheme could be given by a later version of this draft.</t>

     <t>The classes to be supported at interconnection interfaces are specified by 
      Y.1566 as:</t>

     <t><list hangIndent="8" style="hanging">

          <t hangText="Class Priority:">EF, expecting the figures of merit describing 
          the PHB to be in the range of low single digit milliseconds. <xref target="RFC3246">See</xref>.</t>

          <t hangText="Bulk inelastic:">Optimised for low loss, low delay, low jitter at high bandwidth.
          Traffic load in this class must be controlled, e.g. by application servers. 
          One example could be flow admission control. There may be infrequent 
          retransmissions requested by the application layer to mitigate low levels 
          of packet losses. Discard of packets through active queue management should 
          be avoided in this class. Congestion in this class may result in bursty packet 
          loss. If used to carry multimedia traffic, it is recommended to carry audio 
          and video traffic in a single PHB. All of these properties influence the 
          buffer design.</t>

          <t hangText="Assured:">This class may be optimised to transport traffic without bandwidth requirements. 
          It aims on Very low loss at high bandwidths. Retransmissions after losses characterise 
          the class and influence the buffer design. Active queue management with probabilistic 
          dropping may be deployed.</t>

          <t hangText="Default:">Default. This class may be optimised to transport traffic without bandwidth requirements. 
           Retransmissions after losses characterise the class and influence the buffer design. 
           Active queue management with probabilistic dropping may be deployed.</t>

      </list></t>

      <t>Note that other DiffServ related standards trim down class requirements to SLA parameters. 
      To quote e.g. RFC 4594-update, "A "service class" represents a similar set of traffic 
      characteristics for delay, loss, and jitter as packets traverse routers in a network." This 
      draft adds traffic PHB properties corresponding to expected transport layer 
      characteristics as a key factor to a class definition: the desired class performance like 
      delay, jitter and worst case loss are met only if PHB and transport properties 
      meet the ones described by the class definition.
      This is not to say, the other standards ignore PHB properties. They are e.g. a core part 
      of RFC 4594-update. They do not directly refer to transport protocol properties, as most 
      existing QoS standards prefer the approach of assigning QoS classes to applications or 
      application sets. This may result in undesirable class mappings, if an e.g. IP TV application
      demanding low loss is matched to a class whose low loss guarantees depend on AQM mechanisms.</t>  

      <t>Y.1566 does not define a complete set of DSCP based PHBs to be supported at an interconnection 
      interface. This information is added by this draft. At interconnection points, 
      the following DSCP based PHBs should be accepted between interconnected parties:</t>

      <t><list hangIndent="8" style="hanging">
      
	  <t hangText="Class:">PHB (one or more)</t>

          <t hangText="Class Priority:">EF</t>

          <t hangText="Bulk inelastic:">AF41 (AF42 and AF43 are reserved for extension)</t>

          <t hangText="Assured:">AF31, AF32 and AF33</t>

          <t hangText="Default:">Default (i.e. Best Effort)</t>
      
      </list></t>


      <t>Class names (and property specification) have been picked from Y.1566 above.</t>

  </section>

    <section title="Treatment of Network Control traffic at carrier interconnection interfaces">

      <t>As specified by RFC4594, section 3.2, Network Control (NC) traffic
       marked by CS6 is to be expected at interconnection interfaces. This
       document does not change NC specifications of RFC4594. The latter
       specification is detailed on domain internal NC traffic and on traffic
       exchanged between peering points. Further, it recommends not to
       forward CS6 marked traffic originating from user-controlled end points
       by the NC class of a provider domain.</t>

      <t>As a minor clarification to RFC4594, "peering" shouldn't be interpreted 
      in a commercial sense. The NC PHB is applicable also in the case of a 
      purchased network service based on a transit agreement with an upstream 
      provider. RFC4594 recommendations on NC traffic are applicable for 
      IP carrier interconnections in general.</t> 

      <t>Some CS6 traffic exchanged accross carrier interconnections will 
      terminate at the domain ingress node (e.g., if BGP is running between 
      the two routers on opposite ends of the interconnection link).</t>

      <t>An IP carrier MAY limit access to the NC PHB for traffic which is 
      recognised as network control traffic relevant to the own domain.  
      Interconnecting carriers SHOULD specify treatment of CS6 marked 
      traffic received at a carrier interconnection which is to be 
      forwarded beyond the ingress node. An SLA covering the following 
      cases is recommended, if a carrier wishes to send CS6 marked 
      traffic accross an interconnection link which isn't terminating 
      at the interconnected ingress node:</t>
      
      <t><list style="symbols">
 
     <t>classification of traffic which is network control traffic for 
     both domains. This traffic SHOULD be classified for the NC PHB.</t>

     <t>classification of traffic which is network control traffic for 
     the sending domain only. This traffic SHOULD be classified for 
     a PHB offering similar properties as the NC class (e.g. AF31 
     as specified by this document).</t>

     <t>any other CS6 marked traffic SHOULD be remarked or dropped.</t>
      
     </list></t>


</section>

    <section title="MPLS, Ethernet and DSCP Precedence Prefixes for aggregated classes">      

      <t> Ethernet and MPLS support 3 bit codepoint fields to differentiate service 
      quality. Mapping of the DSCP Precedence Prefix to these 3 Bit fields has been 
      a configuration restriction in the early days of DiffServ. The concept
      of classifying DiffServ traffic classes by the bits 0-2 of a DSCP has 
      however been part of Diffserv from start on. EF's DSCP Precedence Prefix is 5, 
      that of AF4 is 4 and so on. The interconnection class and codepoint 
      scheme respects properties and limits of a 3 bit PHB coding space in different 
      ways:</t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>it allows to classify four interconnection classes based on Class 
          Selector Codepoints.</t>

          <t>it supports a single PHB group (AF3), whose DSCP based PHBs may 
          be mapped to up to three different MPLS TC's or Ethernet P-Bits. 
          Note that this draft doesn's favour or recommend doing that, but 
          it is possible. 
          The author isn't aware of deployed service offers with 3 different 
          drop levels in a single class.</t>
      </list> </t>


      <t>The above statement is no requirement to depricate any DSCP to MPLS TC 
      or Ethernet P-Bit mapping functionality. In the opposite, by limiting the 
      interconnection scheme to 7 DSCP based PHBs, each PHB may be mapped to a 
      3 Bit based PHB scheme.</t>
     </section>

     <section title="QoS class name selection">   

      <t>This is more of an informational discussion, proposed best practice, and 
      mainly relates to human behaviour (including QoS experts) rather than 
      technical issues. Above the human preference for conceivable class names 
      has been mentioned. Network engineers (including the former Diffserv WG 
      authors) recommend avoiding application related QoS class names. Focus 
      should be put on class properties. These can be irritating again. 
      Just looking at SLA parameters like Delay, Jitter and packet loss doesn't 
      tell the reader, which transport properties guided 
      the related scheduler engineering of a PHB. A router produces QoS with a 
      scheduling mechanism, a settable queue depth and optional active queue 
      management (including ECN), and may be a policer. Some kind of resource 
      management may be present (also in Diffserv domains). It's beyond the 
      imagination of the author how one would engineer more than half a dozen 
      classes with distinguishable properties using this set of tools.</t>

      <t>There's no perfect solution to the problem, as PHB configurations 
      are not comprehensible to most readers, even if they were communicated 
      (they are operational secrets of course). There are (or should be) 
      engineering assumptions, when designing QoS PHBs. They closer 
      relate to layer 3 or layer 4 level properties than to specific 
      applications. In most cases, an application responds to congestion by 
      reducing traffic, or it ignores congestion. Active queue management 
      doesn't help to avoid congestion in the latter case, only resource 
      management does. EF may be a special case. If the EF traffic is not 
      responsive to congestion, and packets are assumed to be short, rather 
      small jitter values can be reached if engineering ensures that the 
      packet arrival rate never exceeds the transmission rate of that queue 
      (see <xref target="RFC3246">RFC 3246</xref>). There's other non congestion-responsive traffic, for 
      which the EF engineering assumptions may not fit. So support of a PHB 
      like bulk inelastic is reasonable.</t>

      <t>Active queue management may be deployed for QoS classes 
      designed to transport traffic responding to congestion by 
      traffic reduction.</t>

      <t>The class names of this document follow Y.1566. TCP_optimised 
      and especially UDP_optimised are inappropriate class names, as some 
      UDP based applications are or may be expected to become TCP friendly.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Allow for DiffServ extendibility on MPLS and Ethernet level">   

      <t>Any aggregated Diffserv deployment faces codepoint depletion issues 
      rather soon, if deployed on MPLS or Ethernet. Coding space should be 
      left for new features, like ECN, PCN or Conex. In addition to carrying 
      customer traffic, internal routing and network management 
      traffic may be protected by using a separate class. Offering 
      interconnection with up to four classes and 4 - 6 MPLS TC's (or 
      Ethernet P-bits) to that respect is probably at least a 
      fair compromise. </t> 
    </section>

    <section title="Acknowledgements">  
      <t>David Black gave many helpful comments to this work. Al Morton and 
      Sebastien Jobert provided feedback on many aspects during private discussions.
      Brian Carpenter, Mohamed Boucadair and Thomas Knoll helped adding awareness 
      of further potentially related work.</t> 
    </section>


    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>This memo includes no request to IANA.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>This document does not introduce new features, it 
      describes how to use existing ones. The security section of 
      <xref target="RFC4597">RFC 4597</xref> applies.</t>
     </section>

  </middle>

  <!--  *****BACK MATTER ***** -->

  <back>
    <!-- References split into informative and normative -->

    <!-- There are 2 ways to insert reference entries from the citation libraries:
     1. define an ENTITY at the top, and use "ampersand character"RFC2629; here (as shown)
     2. simply use a PI "less than character"?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119.xml"?> here
        (for I-Ds: include="reference.I-D.narten-iana-considerations-rfc2434bis.xml")

     Both are cited textually in the same manner: by using xref elements.
     If you use the PI option, xml2rfc will, by default, try to find included files in the same
     directory as the including file. You can also define the XML_LIBRARY environment variable
     with a value containing a set of directories to search.  These can be either in the local
     filing system or remote ones accessed by http (http://domain/dir/... ).-->

    <references title="Normative References">
      <!--?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"?-->
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.2474'?>
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.2575'?>
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.2597'?>
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.3246'?> 
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.3260'?>
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.3270'?>
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.2119'?>
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.5462'?>

      <reference anchor="min_ref">
        <!-- the following is the minimum to make xml2rfc happy -->

        <front>
          <title>Minimal Reference</title>

          <author initials="authInitials" surname="authSurName">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date year="2006" />
        </front>
      </reference>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <!-- Here we use entities that we defined at the beginning. -->


      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.5160'?>
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.5127'?>
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.4597'?>
      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.polk-tsvwg-diffserv-stds-problem-statement'?>
      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.polk-tsvwg-rfc4594-update'?>
      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.knoll-idr-cos-interconnect'?>


      <!-- A reference written by by an organization not a person. -->

      <reference anchor="ID.idr-sla">
        <front>
          <title>Inter-domain SLA Exchange
          </title>

          <author>
            <organization>IETF</organization>
          </author>
          <date year="2013"/>
        </front>
      <seriesInfo name="IETF, "  value="http://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/draft-ietf-idr-sla-exchange/"/>
      </reference>             

     <reference anchor="IR.34">
        <front>
          <title>IR.34 Inter-Service Provider IP Backbone Guidelines Version 7.0
          </title>

          <author>
            <organization>GSMA Association</organization>
          </author>
          <date year="2012" />
        </front>
      <seriesInfo name="GSMA, "  value="GSMA IR.34 http://www.gsma.com/newsroom/wp-content/uploads/2012/03/ir.34.pdf"/>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="MEF23.1">
        <front>
          <title>Implementation Agreement MEF 23.1 Carrier Ethernet Class of Service Phase 2
          </title>

          <author>
            <organization>MEF</organization>
          </author>
          <date year="2012"/>
        </front>
      <seriesInfo name="MEF, " value="MEF23.1 http://metroethernetforum.org/PDF_Documents/technical-specifications/MEF_23.1.pdf"/>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="Y.1566">
        <front>
          <title>Quality of service mapping and interconnection between Ethernet, IP and multiprotocol label switching networks
          </title>

          <author>
            <organization>ITU-T</organization>
          </author>
          <date year="2012"/>
        </front>
      <seriesInfo name="ITU, "  value="http://www.itu.int/rec/T-REC-Y.1566-201207-I/en"/>

      </reference>


    </references>

    <section anchor="app-additional" title="Change log">
    
    <t><list hangIndent="8" style="hanging">
    
      <t hangText="00 to 01">Added terminology and references. Added details and
      information to interconnection class and codepoint scheme. Editorial changes.</t>
      <t hangText="01 to 02">Added some references regarding related work. 
      Clarified class definitions. Further editorial improvements.</t>
      <t hangText="02 to 03">Consistent terminology. Discussion of Network Management 
      PHB at interconnection interfaces. Editorial review.</t>
      <t hangText="03 to 04">Again improved terminology. Better wording of Network Control 
      PHB at interconnection interfaces.</t>


    </list></t>
    </section>

    <!-- Change Log

v00 2012-10-26  RG   Initial version

v01 2013-02-20  RG   Added material see change log and editorial changes

v02 2013-02-25  RG   Added some references promised for -01 but forgotten there

v03 2013-06-14  RG   Clarified Traffic Class definition and Network Management treatment and some other issues.

v04 2013-10-18  RG   Clarified DSCP Precedence Prefix specification and Network Control treatment.
  -->
  </back>
</rfc>
