<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
  <!ENTITY RFC2119 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
  <!ENTITY RFC3209 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3209.xml">
  <!ENTITY RFC3630 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3630.xml">
  <!ENTITY RFC4090 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4090.xml">
  <!ENTITY RFC5305 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5305.xml">
  <!ENTITY RFC5420 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5420.xml">
  <!ENTITY RFC5786 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5786.xml">
  ]>

<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>

<rfc category="std" docName="draft-dong-mpls-frr-resource-class-00"
     ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="MPLS TE FRR Resource Classification">
      MPLS-TE Fast Reroute Resource Classification
    </title>

    <author fullname="Jie Dong" initials="J." surname="Dong">
      <organization>Huawei Technologies</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Huawei Building, No.3 Xinxi Rd</street>

          <city>Beijing</city>

          <code>100085</code>

          <country>China</country>
        </postal>

        <email>jie.dong@huawei.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Mach Chen" initials="M." surname="Chen">
      <organization>Huawei Technologies</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Huawei Building, No.3 Xinxi Rd</street>

          <city>Beijing</city>

          <code>100085</code>

          <country>China</country>
        </postal>

        <email>mach.chen@huawei.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Curtis Villamizar" initials="C. " surname="Villamizar">
      <organization>OCCNC, LLC</organization>

      <address>
        <email>curtis@occnc.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date day="24" month="October" year="2011" />

    <abstract>
      <t>This document describes simple and backward compatible
      extensions to Fast-Reroute (FRR) MPLS Traffic Engineering (TE).
      The purpose of these extensions include the following. These
      extensions provide a classification of SRLG to support LSP with
      differing protection requirements.  These extensions allow
      highly reliable nodes or links, typically resources with
      redundancy at a lower layer, to be identified to allow LSP to
      optionally not consider these resources as potential points of
      failure.</t>
    </abstract>

    <note title="Requirements Language">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
      document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
      target="RFC2119" />.</t>
    </note>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>MPLS Traffic Engineering (TE) Fast Reroute (FRR) <xref
      target="RFC4090" /> is widely used for protecting MPLS-TE
      LSPs from local failures. TE FRR implementations today can
      consistently achieve redirection of traffic from a single
      resource failure to other local resources in 10s of
      milliseconds.  TE FRR can therefore provide high availability
      for service carried on the TE LSP.</t>

      <t> The existing TE FRR defines several protection and switching
      modes which are designed to apply to a all protected LSP
      regardless of what kind of availability is required by the
      service. Protection must accomodate the most strict protection
      requirements of any service carried, even though protection of
      low probability failures are not appropriate for other services.
      Where this occurs, the result can be greater requirements for
      network resources and higher network costs.</t>

      <t>This document first describes the flexibility limitations in
      existing TE FRR that are addressed and then proposes a flexible
      TE FRR mechanism to address them.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Problem Statement">
      <t>MPLS-TE LSPs may be used to carry services which require different
      levels of availability. MPLS-TE FRR mechanism defined in [RFC4090] can
      only provide the same local protection level for LSPs regardless of the
      availability requirement of the services.</t>

      <t>In some cases network nodes with sufficient internal
      redundancy mechanisms could be considered sufficiently immune to
      node failures for most services. Similarly, some links could
      also be considered sufficiently redundant for most services.
      Examples of reliable links are link bundle and multipath links
      that do not use common media, such as parallel physical links
      deployed within a provider facility. Thus for most services such
      nodes and links could be considered sufficiently reliable that
      they do not need be protected at LSP level.</t>

      <t>A subset of LSP may require extremely high availability.
      Commonly cited examples include communications among emergency
      first responders (police, fire, etc) and application for which
      loss of connectivity may result in large financial losses
      (financial services, e-commerce, trading).  These services may
      require protection against Shared Risk Link Group (SRLG) which
      would be expected to cause failure in extremely rare
      circumstances. This same high level of protection is unnecessary
      for most services.</t>

      <t>In order to provide different levels of local protection for
      different kinds of services, a more flexible TE FRR mechanism is
      required.  Resource classes and resource class affinity are
      proposed to address this.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="TE FRR Resource Class Overview">

      <t>To support different levels of local protection, a
      classification of node and link reliability is defined.  This
      information is carried in the TE link state database (TED).  A
      classification may be associated with a node, a link, or an
      SRLG.  Extensions are defined for OSPF-TE and ISIS-TE.</t>

      <t>To support a decision at the point of local repair (PLR), an
      extension is defined for RSVP-TE.  The requirements of a
      specific LSP is defined in the RSVP-TE PATH message.  The
      requirements are expressed as changes from a default
      behavior.</t>

      <section title="Setting Default Behavior">

	<t>Signaling can be reduced by configuring a default behavior
	at potential PLR.  If the majority of services do not
	requirement protection from relatively reliable nodes and/or
	links, setting configured defaults to this behavior allows a
	small reduction in the size of RSVP-TE PATH messages.</t>

	<t>Using a new TLV to define SRLG which are disabled by
	default can improve backward compatibility with respect to
	legacy PLR in cases where it is preferred that these legacy
	PLR ignore these low probability SRLG for all LSP.  Using the
	SRLG extensions understood by the legacy PLR allows these PLR
	to consider low probability SRLG for all LSP, with extension
	affecting only the PLR implementing this specification.</t>

      </section>

      <section title="Backwards Compatibility with Legacy PLR">

	<t>Legacy PLR will ignore distinctions between relatively
	reliable nodes or links and low probability SRLG and those
	which are relatively unreliable.  These PLR may choose
	protection paths which error on the side of providing more
	protection for some services than is required.  At worst, this
	has an impact on network cost, but still would represent a
	lower cost than if the extensions were unavailable at all
	nodes.</t>

	<t>SRLG can be defined such that legacy PLR either always
	consider the SRLG or always ignore the SRLG.  Only the PLR
	implementing this specification will be able to selectively
	apply classes of SRLG on a per LSP basis.</t>

      </section>

      <section title="Backwards Compatibility with Legacy Ingress">

	<t>Legacy Ingress will not provide any extensions which allow
	LSP to be treated differently from the default.  In a
	brownfield installation the defaults can be set to provide the
	level of protection that had been available.  Extensions can
	then be used by LSR implementing this specification to
	indicate LSP which require some protection, but less than this
	default, or more protection than this default.</t>

      </section>

    </section>

    <section title="TE FRR Resource Class Protocol Extensions">

        <t>This document defines the following extensions.
	<list style="numbers">
	  <t>new TLVs in OSPF and IS-IS to provide a means of host or
	  link reliability classification.</t>
	  <t>new TLVs in OSPF and IS-IS to provide SRLG
	  classification.</t>
	  <t>a new alternate SRLG TLV for OSPF and IS-IS to allow
	  definition of SRLG that will be ignored by legacy PLR.</t>
	  <t>an extension to RSVP-TE to allow per LSP deviations from
	  default protection to be specified.</t>
	</list>
	</t>

      </section>

      <section title="IGP Extensions">

        <section anchor="sect.ospf-nr-tlv"
		 title="OSPF Node Reliability sub-TLV">

          <t>The reliability of a node is specified using a Node
          Reliability sub-TLV of the Node Attribute TLV <xref
          target="RFC5786" />.  Length of this sub-TLV is variable.
          The format is as follows:</t>

          <t><figure>
	    <artwork align="center">
<![CDATA[    0                   1                   2                   3
    0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |              TBD              |             Length            |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |    Flags      |          Node Classification Bit Map          |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |                       Zero or more SRNG                       |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+]]>
	    </artwork>
	  </figure></t>

          <t>The type code is TBA for Node Reliability sub-TLV.</t>

          <t>The length field is set to four plus the number of SRNG
          included time the size of an SRNG.</t>

          <t>The Flags field is reserved for future use.</t>

          <t>The 3 octet Node Classification Bit Map is a bit map
          which may be used by operator to specify inclusion of the
          node in a set of operator defined classifications.</t>

	  <t>The format of SRNG is common to OSPF and ISIS and is
	  defined in <xref target="sect.SRNG" /></t>

        </section>

        <section anchor="sect.ospf-lr-tlv"
		 title="OSPF Link Reliability sub-TLV">

          <t>The reliability of link is specified using a Link Reliability
          sub-TLV of the Link TLV <xref target="RFC3630" />. Length of
          this sub-TLV is variable. The format is as follow:</t>

          <t><figure>
	    <artwork align="center">
<![CDATA[    0                   1                   2                   3
    0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |    Flags      |          Link Classification Bit Map          |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |                  Zero or more Extended SRLG                   |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+]]>
	    </artwork>
	  </figure></t>

          <t>The Flags field is reserved for future use.</t>

          <t>The 3 octet Link Classification Bit Map is a bit map
          which may be used by operator to specify inclusion of the
          link in a set of operator defined classifications.</t>

	  <t>The format of Extended SRLG is common to OSPF and ISIS
	  and is defined in <xref target="sect.SRNG" /></t>

        </section>

        <section anchor="sect.isis-nr-tlv"
		 title="IS-IS Node Reliability TLV">

          <t>The reliability of node is specified using a Node
          Reliability TLV with TLV Type TBA. Length of this TLV is
          variable. The format is as follows:</t>

          <t><figure>
	    <artwork align="center">
<![CDATA[    0                   1                   2                   3
    0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |              TBD              |             Length            |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |    Flags      |          Node Classification Bit Map          |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |                       Zero or more SRNG                       |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+]]>
	    </artwork>
	  </figure></t>

          <t>The Flags field is reserved for future use.</t>

          <t>The 3 octet Node Classification Bit Map is a bit map
          which may be used by operator to specify inclusion of the
          node in a set of operator defined classifications.</t>

	  <t>The format of SRNG is common to OSPF and ISIS and is
	  defined in <xref target="sect.SRNG" /></t>

        </section>

        <section anchor="sect.isis-lr-tlv"
		 title="IS-IS Link Reliability TLV">

          <t>The reliability of link is specified using a Link
          Reliability sub-TLV of the TLV 22 <xref target="RFC5305"
          />. Length of this sub-TLV is variable. The format is as
          follow:</t>

          <t><figure>
	    <artwork align="center">
<![CDATA[    0                   1                   2                   3
    0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |    Flags      |          Link Classification Bit Map          |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |                  Zero or more Extended SRLG                   |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+]]>
	    </artwork>
	  </figure></t>

          <t>The Flags field is reserved for future use.</t>

          <t>The 3 octet Link Classification Bit Map is a bit map
          which may be used by operator to specify inclusion of the
          link in a set of operator defined classifications.</t>

	  <t>The format of Extended SRLG is common to OSPF and ISIS
	  and is defined in <xref target="sect.SRNG" /></t>

        </section>

	<section anchor="sect.SRNG" title="Shared Risk Node Group">

	  <t>The Shared Risk Node Group (SRNG) is carried within
	  either the OSPF Node Reliability sub-TLV (see <xref
	  target="sect.ospf-nr-tlv" />) or the IS-IS Node Reliability
	  TLV (see <xref target="sect.isis-nr-tlv" />).  The SRNG is 8
	  bytes. The format is as follow:</t>

          <t><figure>
	    <artwork align="center">
<![CDATA[    0                   1                   2                   3
    0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |               Shared Risk Node Group Number                   |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |    Flags      |         SRNG Classification Bit Map           |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+]]>
	    </artwork>
	  </figure></t>

	  <t>The Shared Risk Node Group Number (SRLG) is a 32 bit
	  number used to specify the inclusion of the node within a
	  set of nodes which share a common resource that therefore
	  can be expected to fail simultaneously if that resource
	  becomes unavailable.  The SRLG is a operator assigned number
	  which identified the resource.</t>

          <t>The Flags field is reserved for future use.</t>

          <t>The 3 octet SRNG Classification Bit Map is a bit map
          which may be used by operator to specify inclusion of the
          SRNG in a set of operator defined classifications.</t>

	</section>

	<section anchor="sect.SRLG" title="Extended Shared Risk Link Group">

	  <t>The Extended Shared Risk Link Group (ESRLG) is carried
	  within either the OSPF Link Reliability sub-TLV (see <xref
	  target="sect.ospf-lr-tlv" />) or the IS-IS Link Reliability
	  TLV (see <xref target="sect.isis-lr-tlv" />).  The ESRLG is
	  8 bytes. The format is as follow:</t>

          <t><figure>
	    <artwork align="center">
<![CDATA[    0                   1                   2                   3
    0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |           Extended Shared Risk Link Group Number              |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |    Flags      |         SRLG Classification Bit Map           |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+]]>
	    </artwork>
	  </figure></t>

	  <t>The Extended Shared Risk Link Group Number (ESRLG) is a
	  32 bit number used to specify the inclusion of the link
	  within a set of links which share a common resource that
	  therefore can be expected to fail simultaneously if that
	  resource becomes unavailable.  The SRLG is a operator
	  assigned number which identified the resource.</t>

          <t>The Flags field is reserved for future use.</t>

          <t>The 3 octet SRLG Classification Bit Map is a bit map
          which may be used by operator to specify inclusion of the
          SRLG in a set of operator defined classifications.</t>

	  <t>The Extended Shared Risk Link Group Number (ESRLG) may be
	  given the same number as an advertised SRLG when the desired
	  behavior for legacy PLR is to have the legacy PLR always
	  protect against failure of the ESRLG.  If the desired
	  behavior for legacy PLR is to have the legacy PLR never
	  protect against failure of the ESRLG, then the ESRLG number
	  must not conflict with an SRLG number.</t>

	</section>

      </section>

      <section title="RSVP-TE Extensions">

      <section title="Resource Attribute Bit Mask">

        <t>The Resource Attribute Bit Mask is defined in
        LSP_ATRTRIBUTE Object.  The LSP_ATRTRIBUTE is defined in <xref
        target="RFC3209" /> and updated in <xref target="RFC5420"
        />. The format of the Resource Attribute Bit Mask is as
        follows:</t>

        <t><figure>
	  <artwork>
<![CDATA[    0                   1                   2                   3
    0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   | OP| Ap| Resv  |         Resource Attribute Bit Mask           |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+]]>
	  </artwork>
	</figure></t>

	<t>The 2 bit Operation field (OP) specifies one of the
	following operations.  The following values are defined for
	the Operation field.
	<list style="hanging" hangIndent="4">
	  <t hangText="00">Include if any set</t>
	  <t hangText="01">Include if all set</t>
	  <t hangText="10">Exclude if any set</t>
	  <t hangText="11">Exclude if all set</t>
	</list>
	</t>

	<t>The 2 bit Apply field (Ap) is a bit map which indicates
	which context the bit mask is applied to.  The following
	values are defined for the Apply field.
	<list style="hanging" hangIndent="4">
	  <t hangText="00">Applu the mask to Node Reliability values</t>
	  <t hangText="01">Applu the mask to Link Reliability values</t>
	  <t hangText="10">Applu the mask to SRNG Reliability values</t>
	  <t hangText="11">Applu the mask to ESRLG Reliability values</t>
	</list>
	</t>

	<t>The 3 octet Resource Attribute Bit Mask is a bit mask
	applied to the 2 octet resource classifications specified for
	nodes, links, SRNG, or ESRLG.  The Apply field indicates which
	type of resource classification to apply the mask to.  The
	Operation field indicates what action to take as a result of
	the mask operation.</t>

      </section>

    </section>

    <section title="Protocol Actions">

      <t>The Node Reliability (see ) and Link Reliability (see ) are
      assigned to nodes and links according to configuration on the
      LSR advertising the containing TLV.  The Resource Attribute Bit
      Mask is assigned according to configuration on the ingress
      LSR for a given LSP.</t>

      <t>The action taken at a PLR for a given LSP are as follows.</t>

      <t>If no protection is required, as indicated by the "protection
      desired" bit in the RSVP-TE Flags SESSION_ATTRIBUTE <xref
      target="RFC3209" /> not being set, then no protection path is
      created at a potential PLR.  This behavior is unchanged.</t>

      <t>If link disjoint protection if required, as indicated by the
      "protection desired" bit set and the "Node protection desired"
      bit not set <xref target="RFC4090" />, then the protection path
      must be disjoint with respect to all links and SRLG, except
      those ESRLG added or links or SRLG removed as a result of
      applying the Resource Attribute Bit Masks for the LSP.</t>

      <t>If node disjoint protection if required, as indicated by the
      "protection desired" bit set and the "Node protection desired"
      bit set, then the protection path must be disjoint with respect
      to all nodes, links, and SRLG, except SRNG or ESRLG added or
      nodes, links or SRLG removed as a result of applying the
      Resource Attribute Bit Masks for the LSP.</t>

      <t>The action taken in the absense of any Resource Attribute Bit
      Masks in all cases is identical to the action that would be
      taken by a legacy PLR.  Inclusion of one or more Resource
      Attribute Bit Mask modifies this behavior.</t>

    </section>

    <section title="To Be Completed">

      <t>An LSP may have many Resource Attribute Bit Masks.  It may be
      more efficient to define a container for the Resource Attribute
      Bit Masks and include that container in the LSP_ATTRIBUTES.
      Whether to use such a container rather than include multiple
      Resource Attribute Bit Masks directly in the LSP_ATTRIBUTES is
      up for discussion.</t>

    </section>

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">

      <section title="OSPF">

        <t>The registry for the Node Attribute TLV is defined in <xref
        target="RFC5786" />. IANA is requested to assign a new sub-TLV
        codepoint for the Node Reliability sub-TLV carried in the Node
        Attribute TLV.</t>

        <t><figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[Value     Sub-TLV                    Reference
-----     -------                    ---------
 TBA      Node Reliability sub-TLV   this document]]></artwork>
          </figure></t>

        <t>The registry for the Link TLV is defined in <xref
        target="RFC3630" />. IANA is requested to assign a new sub-TLV
        codepoint for the Link Reliability sub-TLV carried in the Link
        TLV.</t>

        <t><figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[Value     Sub-TLV                    Reference
-----     -------                    ---------
 TBA      Link Reliability sub-TLV   this document]]></artwork>
          </figure></t>

      </section>

      <section title="IS-IS">

        <t>IANA is requested to assign a new TLV codepoint for Node
        Reliability TLV.</t>

        <t><figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[Type     TLV                         Reference
-----    -------                     ---------
 TBA     Node Reliability sub-TLV    this document]]></artwork>
          </figure></t>

        <t>The registry for TLV 22 is defined in <xref
        target="RFC5305" />. IANA is requested to assign a new sub-TLV
        codepoint for the Link Reliability sub-TLV which is carried in TLV
        22.</t>

        <t><figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[Value     Sub-TLV                    Reference
-----     -------                    ---------
 TBA      Link Reliability sub-TLV   this document]]></artwork>
          </figure></t>

      </section>

      <section title="RSVP-TE">

        <t>IANA is requested to assign a new type codepoint for the "Resource Attribute Bit Mask" TLV in the Attribute TLV Space. It is
        carried in the LSP_ATTRIBUTES object (class = 197, C-Type = 1).</t>

        <t><figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[    Type:  TBA
    Name:  Resource Attribute Bit Mask
    Allowed on LSP_ATTRIBUTES:  Yes
    Allowed on LSP_REQUIRED_ATTRIBUTES:  No]]></artwork>
          </figure></t>

      </section>

    </section>

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">

      <t>The function described in this document does not create any
      new security issues for the OSPF and IS-IS protocols and does
      not introduce any new security issues above those identified in
      [RFC3209] and [RFC4090].</t>

    </section>

    <section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">

      <t>TBD</t>

    </section>

  </middle>

  <back>

    <references title="Normative References">

      &RFC2119;
      &RFC3209;
      &RFC3630;
      &RFC4090;
      &RFC5305;
      &RFC5420;
      &RFC5786;

    </references>

  </back>

</rfc>
