<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!-- This template is for creating an Internet Draft using xml2rfc,
     which is available here: http://xml.resource.org. -->

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
  <!ENTITY RFC4787 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4787.xml">
  <!ENTITY RFC5382 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5382.xml">
  <!ENTITY RFC6056 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6056.xml">
  <!ENTITY RFC6269 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6269.xml">
  <!ENTITY RFC6888 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6888.xml">
]>

<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<!-- used by XSLT processors -->
<!-- For a complete list and description of processing instructions (PIs), 
     please see http://xml.resource.org/authoring/README.html. -->
<!-- Below are generally applicable Processing Instructions (PIs) that most I-
Ds might want to use.
     (Here they are set differently than their defaults in xml2rfc v1.32) -->
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<!-- give errors regarding ID-nits and DTD validation -->
<!-- control the table of contents (ToC) -->
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<!-- generate a ToC -->
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<!-- the number of levels of subsections in ToC. default: 3 -->
<!-- control references -->
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<!-- use symbolic references tags, i.e, [RFC2119] instead of [1] -->
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<!-- sort the reference entries alphabetically -->
<!-- control vertical white space 
     (using these PIs as follows is recommended by the RFC Editor) -->
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<!-- do not start each main section on a new page -->
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<!-- keep one blank line between list items -->
<!-- end of list of popular I-D processing instructions -->


<rfc category="info" docName="draft-tsou-behave-natx4-log-reduction-04"
     ipr="trust200902">
  <!-- category values: std, bcp, info, exp, and historic
     ipr values: trust200902, noModificationTrust200902,
noDerivativesTrust200902,
        or pre5378Trust200902
     you can add the attributes updates="NNNN" and obsoletes="NNNN" 
     they will automatically be output with "(if approved)" -->

  <!-- ***** FRONT MATTER ***** -->

  <front>
    <!-- The abbreviated title is used in the page header - it is only
necessary if the 
         full title is longer than 39 characters -->

    <title abbrev="NATx4 Log Reduction">Port Management To Reduce Logging In
       Large-Scale NATs</title>

    <author fullname="Tina Tsou" initials="T." surname="Tsou">
      <organization>Huawei Technologies (USA)</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>2330 Central Expressway</street>

          <city>Santa Clara</city>

          <region>CA</region>

          <code>95050</code>

          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>

        <phone>+1 408 330 4424</phone>

        <email>tina.tsou.zouting@huawei.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

     <author fullname="Weibo Li" initials="W." surname="Li">
      <organization>China Telecom</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>109, Zhongshan Ave. West, Tianhe District</street>

          <!-- Reorder these if your country does things differently -->

          <city>Guangzhou</city>

          <code>510630</code>

          <country>P.R. China</country>
        </postal>

        <phone></phone>

        <email>mweiboli@gmail.com</email>

        <!-- uri and facsimile elements may also be added -->
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Tom Taylor" initials="T." surname="Taylor">
      <organization>Huawei Technologies</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>

          <!-- Reorder these if your country does things differently -->

          <city>Ottawa</city>

          <code></code>

          <country>Canada</country>
        </postal>

        <phone></phone>

        <email>tom.taylor.stds@gmail.com</email>

        <!-- uri and facsimile elements may also be added -->
      </address>
    </author>
    
    <author fullname="James Huang" initials="J." 
            surname="Huang">
      <organization>Huawei Technologies</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Bantian, Longgang District</street>

          <!-- Reorder these if your country does things differently -->

          <city>Shenzhen</city>

          <code>518129</code>

          <country>P.R. China</country>
        </postal>

        <phone></phone>

        <email>James.huang@huawei.com</email>

        <!-- uri and facsimile elements may also be added -->
      </address>
    </author>
    
    <date year="2013" />

    <!-- If the month and year are both specified and are the current ones,
xml2rfc will fill in the current day for you. If only the current year is
specified, xml2rfc will fill in the current day and month for you. If the year
is not the current one, it is necessary to specify at least a month (xml2rfc
assumes day="1" if not specified for the purpose of calculating the expiry
date).  With drafts it is normally sufficient to specify just the year. -->

    <!-- Meta-data Declarations -->

    <area>Transport</area>

    <workgroup>Behavior Engineering for Hindrance Avoidance</workgroup>


    <keyword>NAT logging</keyword>

    <!-- Keywords will be incorporated into HTML output
         files in a meta tag but they have no effect on text or nroff
         output. If you submit your draft to the RFC Editor, the
         keywords will be used for the search engine. -->

    <abstract>
      <t>
        Various IPv6 transition strategies require the introduction of 
        large-scale NATs (e.g. AFTR, NAT64) to share the limited supply of IPv4
        addresses available in the network until transition is complete. There
        has recently been debate over how to manage the sharing of ports
        between different subscribers sharing the same IPv4 address. One
        factor in the discussion is the operational requirement to log the
        assignment of transport addresses to subscribers. It has been argued
        that dynamic assignment of individual ports between subscribers
        requires the generation of an excessive volume of logs. This document
        suggests a way to achieve dynamic port sharing while keeping log
        volumes low.
      </t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>
       During the IPv6 transition period, some large-scale NAT devices may be
       introduced, e.g. DS-Lite AFTR, NAT64. When a NAT device needs to set
       up a new connection for a given internal address behind the NAT, it
       needs to create a new mapping entry for the new connection, which will
       contain source IP address, source port or ICMP identifier, converted
       source IP address, converted source port, protocol (TCP/UDP), etc. 
      </t>

      <t>
        For various reasons it is necessary to log these mappings. Some high
        performance NAT devices may need to create a large amount of new
        sessions per second. If logs are generated for each mapping entry, the
        log traffic could reach tens of megabytes per second or more, which
        would be a problem for log generation, transmission and storage. 
      </t>

      <t>
        <xref target="RFC6888"/>, REQ-13, REQ-14, and 
        REQ-15 deal explicitly with port allocation schemes. However, it is
        recognized that these are conflicting requirements, requiring a
        tradeoff between the efficiency with which ports are used and the rate
        of generation of log records.
      </t>

      <section title="Requirements Language">
        <t>This draft includes no requirements language.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="proposal" title="A Suggested Solution">

      <t>   
        This document proposes a solution that allows dynamic sharing of port
        ranges between users while minimizing the number of logs that have to be
        generated. Briefly, ports are allocated to the user in blocks. Logs are
        generated only when blocks are allocated or deallocated. This provides
        the necessary traceability while reducing log generation by a factor
        equal to the block size, as compared with fully dynamic port allocation. 
      </t>

      <t> 
        Here is how the proposal would work in greater detail. When the user
        sends out the first packet, a port resource pool is allocated for the
        user, e.g., assigning ports 2001~2300 of a public IP address to the user's
        resource pool. Only one log should be generated for this port block.
        When the NAT needs to set up a new mapping entry for the user, it can
        use a port in the user's resource pool and the corresponding public IP
        address. If the user needs more port resources, the NAT can allocate
        another port block, e.g., ports 3501~3800, to the user's resource pool.
        Again, just one log needs to be generated for this port block.   
      </t>

      <t> 
        <xref target="I-D.bajko-pripaddrassign"/> takes this idea further by
        allocating non-contiguous sets of ports using a pseudorandom function.
        Scattering the allocated ports in this way provides a modest barrier to
        port guessing attacks. The use of randomization is discussed further in
        <xref target="Security"/>. 
      </t>

      <t>
        Suppose now that a given internal address has been assigned more than
        one block of ports. The individual sessions using ports within a port
        block will start and end at different times. If no ports in some port
        block are used for some configurable time, the NAT can remove the port
        block from the resource pool allocated to a given internal address, and
        make it available for other users. In theory, it is unnecessary to log
        deallocations of blocks of ports, because the ports in deallocated
        blocks will not be used again until the blocks are reallocated. However,
        the deallocation may be logged when it occurs add robustness to
        troubleshooting or other procedures. 
      </t>

      <t> 
        The deallocation procedure presents a number of difficulties in
        practice. The first problem is the choice of timeout value for the
        block. If idle timers are applied for the individual mappings
        (sessions) within the block, and these conform to the recommendations
        for NAT behaviour for the protocol concerned, then the additional time
        that might be configured as a guard for the block as a whole need not
        be more than a few minutes. The block timer in this case serves only
        as a slightly more conservative extension of the individual session
        idle timers. If, instead, a single idle timer is used for the whole
        block, it must itself conform to the recommendations for the protocol
        with which that block of ports is associated. For example, REQ-5 of
        <xref target="RFC5382" /> requires an idle timer expiry duration of at
        least 2 hours and 4 minutes for TCP. 
      </t>
       
      <t>
        The next issue with port block deallocation is the conflict between
        the desire to randomize port allocation and the desire to make unused
        resources available to other internal addresses. As mentioned above,
        ideally port selection will take place over the entire set of blocks
        allocated to the internal address. However, taken to its fullest
        extent, such a policy will minimize the probability that all ports in
        any given block are idle long enough for it to be released. 
      </t>
      
      <t>
        As an alternative, it is suggested that when choosing which block to
        select a port from, the NAT should omit from its range of choice the
        block that has been idle the longest, unless no ports are available in
        any of the other blocks. The expression "block that has been idle the
        longest" designates the block in which the time since the last packet
        was observed in any of its sessions, in either direction, is earlier
        than the corresponding time in any of the other blocks assigned to
        that internal address. As <xref target="RFC6269"/> points out, port
        randomization is just one security measure of several, and the loss of
        randomness incurred by the suggested procedure is justified by the
        increased utilization of port resources it allows.
      </t>

    </section><!-- proposal -->

    <section anchor="trac" title="Issues Of Traceability">   

      <t>
        Section 11 of <xref target="RFC6269"/> provides a good discussion of
        the traceability issue. Complete traceability given the NAT logging
        practices proposed in this draft requires that the remote destination
        record the source port of a request along with the source address (and
        presumably protocol, if not implicit). In addition, the logs at each
        end must be timestamped, and the clocks must be synchronized within a
        certain degree of accuracy. Here is one reason for the guard timing on
        block release, to increase the tolerable level of clock skew between
        the two ends.
      </t>

      <t> The ability to configure various server applications to record
        source ports has been investigated, with the following results:
        <list style="symbols">
          <t> Source port recording can be configured in Apache, Postfix,
          sendmail and sshd. Please refer to the appendix for configuration
          guide.</t>
          <t> Source port recording is not supported by IIS, Cyrus IMAP and UW
          IMAP. But it should not be too difficult to get Cyrus IMAP and UW IMAP
          to support it by modifying the source code.</t>
        </list>
        Where source port logging can be enabled, this memo strongly urges the
        operators to do so. Similarly, intrusion detection systems should
        capture source port as well as source address of suspect packets.
      </t>

      <t>
        In some cases <xref target="RFC6269"/>, a server may not record the
        source port of a connection. To allow traceability, the NAT device
        needs to record the destination IP address of a connection. As <xref
        target="RFC6269"/> points out, this will provide an incomplete
        solution to the issue of traceability because multiple users of the
        same shared public IP address may access the service at the same time.
        From the point of view of this draft, in such situations the game is
        lost, so to speak, and port allocation at the NAT might as well be
        completely dynamic.
      </t>

      <t> 
        The final possibility to consider is where the NAT does not do per-
        session logging even given the possibility that the remote end is
        failing to capture source ports. In that case, the port allocation
        policy proposed in this draft can be used. The impact on traceability is
        that analysis of the logs would yield only the list of all internal
        addresses mapped to a given public address during the period of time
        concerned. This has an impact on privacy as well as traceability,
        depending on the follow-up actions taken. 
      </t>

    </section><!-- trac -->

    <section title="Other Considerations">

      <t>
        <xref target="RFC6269"/> notes several issues introduced by the use
        of dynamic as opposed to static port assignment. For example, Section
        12.2 of that document notes the effect on authentication procedures.
        These issues must be resolved, but are not specific to the port
        allocation policy described in this document.
       </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>This memo includes no request to IANA.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>
        The discussion which follows addresses an issue that is particularly
        relevant to the proposal made in this document. The security
        considerations applicable to NAT operation for various protocols as
        documented in, for example, <xref target="RFC4787"/> and <xref
        target="RFC5382"/> also apply to this proposal. 
      </t>
      
        <t>
          <xref target="RFC6056"/> summarizes the TCP port-guessing attack, by
          means of which an attacker can hijack one end of a TCP connection. One
          mitigating measure is to make the source port number used for a TCP
          connection less predictable. <xref target="RFC6056"/> provides various
          algorithms for this purpose.
        </t>
        
        <t>
          As Section 3.1 of that RFC notes:
            &quot;...provided adequate algorithms are in use, the larger the
            range from which ephemeral ports are selected, the smaller the
            chances of an attacker are to guess the selected port
            number.&quot; 
          Conversely, the reduced range sizes proposed by the present
          document increase the attacker's chances of guessing correctly. This
          result cannot be totally avoided. However, mitigating measures to
          improve this situation can be taken both at port block assignment time
          and when selecting individual ports from the blocks that have been
          allocated to a given user. 
        </t>
        
        <t>
          At assignment time, one possibility is to assign ports as 
          non-contiguous sets of values as proposed in 
          <xref target="I-D.bajko-pripaddrassign"/>. However, this approach
          creates a lot of complexity for operations, and the pseudo
          randomization can create uncertainty when the accuracy of logs is
          important to protect someone's life or liberty. 
        </t>
        
        <t>
          Alternatively, the NAT can assign blocks of contiguous ports. However,
          at assignment time the NAT could attempt to randomize its choice of
          which of the available idle blocks it would assign to a given user.
          This strategy has to be traded off against the desirability of
          minimizing the chance of conflict between what <xref
          target="RFC6056"/> calls "transport protocol instances" by assigning
          the most-idle block, as suggested in <xref target="proposal"/>. A
          compromise policy might be to assign blocks only if they have been
          idle for a certain amount of time whenever possible, and select
          pseudorandomly between the blocks available according to this
          criterion. In this case it is suggested that the time value used be
          greater than the guard timing mentioned in <xref target="proposal"/>,
          and that no block should ever be reassigned until it has been idle at
          least for the duration given by the guard timer. 
        </t>
        
        <t>
          While the block assignment strategy can provide some mitigation of the
          port guessing attack, the largest contribution will come from pseudo
          randomization at port selection time. <xref target="RFC6056"/>
          provides a number of algoriths for achieving this pseudorandomization.
          When the available ports are contained in blocks which are not in
          general consecutive, the algorithms clearly need some adaptation. The
          task is complicated by the fact that the number of blocks allocated to
          the user may vary over time. Adaptation is left as an exercise for the
          implementor. 
        </t>

    </section>

    <section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>
        Mohamed Boucadair reviewed the initial document and provided useful
        comments to improve it. Reinaldo Penno, Joel Jaeggli, and Dan Wing
        provided comments on the subsequent version that resulted in major
        revisions. Serafim Petsis provided encouragement to publication after
        a hiatus of two years.
      </t>
      
      <t>
        The authors are grateful to Dan Wing for his help in moving this
        document forward, and in particular for his helpful comments on its
        content. 
      </t>
    </section>
    
    <section  title="Appendix A: Configure Server Software to Log Source Port">
      <section title="Apache">
        <t>The user can use LogFormat command to define a customized log
        format and use CustomLog command to apply that log format. "%a" and
        "%{remote}p" can be used in the format string to require logging the
        client's IP address and source port respectively. This feature is
        available since Apache version 2.1.</t>
        
        <t>A detailed configuration guide can be found at <xref
        target="APACHE_LOG_CONFIG"/>.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Postfix">
        <t> In order to log the client source port, macro
        smtpd_client_port_logging should be set to "yes" in the configuration
        file. <xref target="POSTFIX_LOG_CONFIG"/></t>
        <t>This feature is available since Postfix version 2.5.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Sendmail">
        <t> Sendmail has a macro ${client_port} storing the client port. To
        log the source port, the user can define some check rules. Here is an
        example which should be in the .mc configuration macro <xref
        target="SENDMAIL_LOG_CONFIG"/>:</t>
        <figure>
          <artwork>
LOCAL_CONFIG
Klog syslog

LOCAL_RULESETS
SLocal_check_mail
R $* $@ $(log Port_Stat $&amp;{client_addr} $&amp;{client_port} $)
          </artwork>
        </figure>
        <t>This feature is available since version 8.10.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="sshd">
      
        <t>SSHD_CONFIG(5)            OpenBSD Programmer's Manual           SSHD_CONFIG(5)

NAME
     sshd_config - OpenSSH SSH daemon configuration file
     LogLevel
             Gives the verbosity level that is used when logging messages from
             sshd(8).  The possible values are: QUIET, FATAL, ERROR, INFO,
             VERBOSE, DEBUG, DEBUG1, DEBUG2, and DEBUG3.  The default is INFO.
             DEBUG and DEBUG1 are equivalent.  DEBUG2 and DEBUG3 each specify
             higher levels of debugging output.  Logging with a DEBUG level
             violates the privacy of users and is not recommended.
     SyslogFacility
             Gives the facility code that is used when logging messages from
             sshd(8).  The possible values are: DAEMON, USER, AUTH, LOCAL0,
             LOCAL1, LOCAL2, LOCAL3, LOCAL4, LOCAL5, LOCAL6, LOCAL7.  The
             default is AUTH.
</t>
        <t>sshd supports logging the client IP address and client port when a 
        client starts connection since version 1.2.2, here is the source code
        in sshd.c:</t>
        <figure>
          <artwork>
...
verbose("Connection from %.500s port %d", remote_ip, remote_port);
...
          </artwork>
        </figure>
        <t>sshd supports logging the client IP address when a client
        disconnects, from version 1.2.2 to version 5.0. Since version 5.1 sshd
        supports logging the client IP address and source port. Here is the
        source code in sshd.c:</t>
        <figure>
          <artwork>
...
/* from version 1.2.2 to 5.0*/
verbose("Closing connection to %.100s", remote_ip);
...

/* since version 5.1*/
verbose("Closing connection to %.500s port %d", 
remote_ip, remote_port);
          </artwork>
        </figure>

        <t> In order to log the source port, the LogLevel should be set to VERBOSE
        <xref target="SSHD_LOG_CONFIG"/>
         in the configuration file:</t>

        <figure>
          <artwork>
LogLevel    VERBOSE
          </artwork>
        </figure>

      </section>

      <section title="Cyrus IMAP and UW IMAP">
        <t>
          Cyrus IMAP and UW IMAP do not support logging the source port for 
          the time being. Both software use syslog to create logs; it should not
          be too difficult to get it supported by adding some new code.
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>

  </middle>

  <!--  *****BACK MATTER ***** -->

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">

      &RFC6269;
      &RFC6056;

    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
    
      &RFC4787;
      &RFC5382;
      &RFC6888;
      
      <reference anchor="I-D.bajko-pripaddrassign">
        <front>
          <title>Port Restricted IP Address Assignment (Work in progress)</title>
  
          <author initials="G." surname="Bajko">
            <organization>Nokia</organization>
          </author>
  
          <author initials="T." surname="Savolainen">
            <organization>Nokia</organization>
          </author>
  
          <author initials="M." surname="Boucadair">
            <organization>France Telecom</organization>
          </author>
  
          <author initials="P." surname="Levis">
            <organization>France Telecom</organization>
          </author>
  
          <date month="April" year="2012" />
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="APACHE_LOG_CONFIG">
        <front>
          <title> http://httpd.apache.org/docs/2.4/mod/mod_log_config.html </title>
          <author><organization>The Apache Software Foundation</organization></author>
          <date year="2013"/>
        </front>
      </reference>
      
      <reference anchor="POSTFIX_LOG_CONFIG">
        <front>
          <title> http://www.postfix.org/postconf.5.html </title>
          <author><organization></organization></author>
          <date year="2013"/>
        </front>
      </reference>
      
      <reference anchor="SENDMAIL_LOG_CONFIG">
        <front>
          <title> Sendmail, 3rd Edition, Page 798</title>
          <author fullname="Bryan Costales">
            <organization>O'Reilly</organization>
          </author>
          <date month="December" year="2002"/>
        </front>
      </reference>
      
      <reference anchor="SSHD_LOG_CONFIG">
        <front>
          <title>http://www.openbsd.org/cgi-bin/man.cgi?query=sshd_config&amp;sektion=5</title>
          <author><organization></organization></author>
          <date month="April" year="2013"/>
        </front>
      </reference>

    </references>

  </back>
</rfc>
