<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!-- This template is for creating an Internet Draft using xml2rfc,
     which is available here: http://xml.resource.org. -->
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!-- One method to get references from the online citation libraries.
     There has to be one entity for each item to be referenced. 
     An alternate method (rfc include) is described in the references. -->
<!ENTITY RFC3261 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3261.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4078 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4078.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4566 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4566.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5245 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5245.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6052 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6052.xml">
]>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<!-- used by XSLT processors -->
<!-- For a complete list and description of processing instructions (PIs), 
     please see http://xml.resource.org/authoring/README.html. -->
<!-- Below are generally applicable Processing Instructions (PIs) that most I-Ds might want to use.
     (Here they are set differently than their defaults in xml2rfc v1.32) -->
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<!-- give errors regarding ID-nits and DTD validation -->
<!-- control the table of contents (ToC) -->
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<!-- generate a ToC -->
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<!-- the number of levels of subsections in ToC. default: 3 -->
<!-- control references -->
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<!-- use symbolic references tags, i.e, [RFC2119] instead of [1] -->
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<!-- sort the reference entries alphabetically -->
<!-- control vertical white space 
     (using these PIs as follows is recommended by the RFC Editor) -->
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<!-- do not start each main section on a new page -->
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<!-- keep one blank line between list items -->
<!-- end of list of popular I-D processing instructions -->

<rfc category="info" docName="draft-tsou-mboned-multrans-addr-acquisition-00"
  ipr="trust200902">
  <!-- category values: std, bcp, info, exp, and historic
     ipr values: trust200902, noModificationTrust200902, noDerivativesTrust200902
     pre5378Trust200902
     you can add the attributes updates="NNNN" and obsoletes="NNNN" 
     they will automatically be output with "(if approved)" -->

  <!-- ***** FRONT MATTER ***** -->

  <front>
    <!-- The abbreviated title is used in the page header - it is only necessary if the 
         full title is longer than 39 characters -->

    <title abbrev="Multicast Address Acquisition">Address Acquisition For Multicast Content When Source and Receiver Support Differing IP Versions</title>

    <!-- add 'role="editor"' below for the editors if appropriate -->

    <author fullname="Tina Tsou" initials="T." surname="Tsou">
      <organization>Huawei Technologies (USA)</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>2330 Central Expressway</street>

          <city>Santa Clara</city>

          <region>CA</region>

          <code>95050</code>

          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>

        <phone>+1 408 330 4424</phone>

        <email>Tina.Tsou.Zouting@huawei.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    
    <author initials="A." surname="Clauberg" fullname="Axel Clauberg">
   	  <organization>Deutsche Telekom</organization>
      <address>
  	    <postal>
  	      <street>Deutsche Telekom AG, GTN-FM4</street>
  	      <street>Landgrabenweg 151</street>
          <code>53227</code>
          <city>Bonn</city>
          <region></region>
          <country>Germany</country>
        </postal>
        <phone>+4922893618546</phone>
        <email>axel.clauberg@telekom.de</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    
    <author initials="M." surname="Boucadair" fullname="Mohamed Boucadair">
   	  <organization>France Telecom</organization>
      <address>
  	    <postal>
  	      <street></street>
          <city>Rennes</city>
          <region></region>
          <code>35000</code>
          <country>France</country>
        </postal>
        <phone></phone>
        <email>mohamed.boucadair@orange.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    
  <author initials="S." surname="Venaas" fullname="Stig Venaas">
    <organization>Cisco Systems</organization>
    <address>
      <postal>
        <street>Tasman Drive</street>
        <city>San Jose</city>
        <region>CA</region>
        <code>95134</code>
        <country>USA</country>
      </postal>
      <phone></phone>
      <email>stig@cisco.com</email>
    </address>
  </author>
    
    <author initials="Q." surname="Sun" fullname="Qiong Sun">
   	  <organization>China Telecom</organization>
      <address>
  	    <postal>
  	      <street>Room 708, No.118, Xizhimennei Street</street>
          <city>Beijing</city>
          <region></region>
          <code>100035</code>
          <country>P.R.China</country>
        </postal>
        <phone>+86-10-58552936</phone>
        <email>sunqiong@ctbri.com.cn</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    
    <date year="2012" />

    <!-- If the month and year are both specified and are the current ones,
    xml2rfc will fill in the current day for you. If only the current year is
    specified, xml2rfc will fill in the current day and month for you. If the
    year is not the current one, it is necessary to specify at least a month
    (xml2rfc assumes day="1" if not specified for the purpose of calculating
    the expiry date).  With drafts it is normally sufficient to specify just
    the year. -->

    <!-- Meta-data Declarations -->

    <area>General</area>

    <workgroup>Internet Engineering Task Force</workgroup>

    <!-- WG name at the upperleft corner of the doc,
         IETF is fine for individual submissions.  
	 If this element is not present, the default is "Network Working Group",
         which is used by the RFC Editor as a nod to the history of the IETF. -->

    <!-- Keywords will be incorporated into HTML output
         files in a meta tag but they have no effect on text or nroff
         output. If you submit your draft to the RFC Editor, the
         keywords will be used for the search engine. -->

    <abstract>
      <t>During the transition from IPv4 to IPv6, scenarios can occur where the
      IP version supported by the receiver differs from that supported by the
      source. This memo examines and evaluates alternative strategies for allowing
      the receiver to acquire multicast address information in such scenarios in
      the version it supports. </t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction" anchor="intro">
    
      <t>Discussion of the multicast transition problem has focussed on the case
      of unidirectional delivery of multicast content. Within this scenario, the
      operation of viewing a program follows a well-defined sequence.  For the 
      sake of reducing the zapping delay, the list of multicast addresses is 
      generally pre-provisioned to the receiver as part of the program guide 
      prior to requesting access to the multicast content. At some subsequent 
      time the user chooses to view a program, possibly by selecting it from a
      displayed program guide, or simply by selecting a channel. The receiver
      uses its pre-acquired information to signal to the network to receive 
      the desired content. In particular, the receiver initiates reception of
      multicast content using the multicast group address and possibly a unicast
      source address supplied within the program information.</t>
      
      <t>If the network, the source of the multicast content, and the receivers 
      all use IPv4, it is evident that the program information will only include
      IPv4 multicast group addresses (and optionally, IPv4 unicast source 
      addresses). Suppose now, as can occur in some transition scenarios, that
      IPv6-only receivers acquire program information containing these IPv4
      addresses. Then there will be a mismatch: the IPv6-only receivers will 
      be unable to use the addresses that are provided in the program information.
      This memo examines the possible strategies for remedying this mismatch,
      evaluating them in terms of their impact on receiver implementation and 
      network operation.  </t>

      <t>This document makes reference to some of the scenarios described in 
      Section 3 of <xref target="ID.jaclee-behave-v4v6-multicast-ps"/>. The remarks
      in Section 4.1 of <xref target="ID.jaclee-behave-v4v6-multicast-ps"/> are
      relevant to the problem considered here, but are more restricted in scope.</t>
      
    </section><!-- intro -->

    
    
    <section anchor="whichProb" title="Which Problem Are We Solving?">
   
   	  <t>In some transition scenarios, the source supports one IP version while 
   	  the receiver and the provider network support the other (e.g., the source
   	  supports IPv4, the receiver and the network to which it is attached support
   	  IPv6). In this case, the problem stated above can be expressed as follows:
   	  how does the receiver acquire addresses of the IP version it supports,
   	  possibly with the help of the provider network?</t>
   	  
   	  <t>In other transition scenarios, the source and provider network may support
   	  one IP version while the receiver supports another. In this case there are
   	  actually two problems: how the receiver acquires addresses that
   	  it supports (as already stated), and how to make those addresses usable
   	  in a network supporting a different version? This second problem is the 
   	  subject of a different memo and out of scope of the present one.</t>
   	  
   	  <t>There is also a third class of scenarios, where the source and receiver
   	  support the same IP version but the intervening network supports a 
   	  different one (e.g., the 4-6-4 scenario, Section 3.1 of 
   	  <xref target="ID.jaclee-behave-v4v6-multicast-ps"/>). In those scenarios,
   	  delivering addresses of the right IP version to the receiver within the 
   	  program guide is notionally a non-problem. The problem still can arise,
   	  if the intervening network intercepts and modifies the program guide to 
   	  be consistent with the IP version it supports. In this case, the problem
   	  can be re-stated as: how can such modification be avoided when it is not
   	  needed?</t>

    </section><!-- whichProb -->
   
    
    <section anchor="solutions" title="Possible Solutions">
   
   	  <t>This section explores three classes of solutions to the problem just 
   	  described:
   	  <list style="symbols">
   	    <t>reactive: the receiver recognizes that addresses it has received are
   	    in the wrong version and converts them through a request to a mapping
   	    function or using an in-built algorithm and accompanying configuration;</t>
   	    
   	    <t>dynamic modification: the network intercepts the access information
   	    and modifies it as necessary to meet the requirements of the receiver;</t>
   	    
   	 	  <t>administrative: the electronic program guide is modified in advance of
   	 	  its acquisition by the receiver to provide alternative address versions.
   	 	  Two variations on this strategy are identified.</t>
   	  </list>
   	  </t>
   	  
   	  
   	  <section anchor="react" title="The Reactive Strategy">
   	 
   	 	  <t>According to this strategy, an IPv6 receiver receiving IPv4 addresses,
   	 	  for example, would recognize that they were the wrong version. As one
   	 	  possibility, it would package the addresses into one or two requests to
   	 	  a mapping function, which would return corresponding IPv6 addresses. In
   	 	  the 6-4-4 scenario (IPv6 receiver, IPv4 network and source), the mapping
   	 	  function could be located in another node at the user site or located in
   	 	  a dual-stack element at the provider edge. In the 6-6-4 case (IPv6 
   	 	  receiver and network, IPv4 source) it would have to be part of the
   	 	  provider network, although not necessarily at its edge. </t>
   	 	  
   	 	  <t>This approach involves a fair amount of work to implement. Not
   	 	  only does the receiver need to recognize that addresses are the wrong
   	 	  version; it also has to implement a new protocol to the mapping function.
   	 	  It also has to discover that function. </t>
   	 	  
   	 	  <t>As an alternative, the receiver could implement an algorithm to perform
   	 	  the mapping itself, for example, synthesizing an IPv6 address given the 
   	 	  IPv4 address of the source using the approach described by 
   	 	  <xref target="ID.mboned-64-multicast-address-format"/> for multicast group
   	 	  addresses or <xref target="RFC6052"/> for unicast source addresses. In this
   	 	  case, the receiver must be configured with the IPv6 prefixes allocated for
   	 	  that purpose in the network to which the receiver is attached (e.g., using
   	 	  <xref target="ID.qin-softwire-multicast-prefix-option"/>). When 
   	 	  applicable, this approach clearly has advantages over an approach using
   	 	  an external mapping function. It still requires implementation effort
   	 	  in the receiver, but at more limited level.</t>
   	 
   	  </section><!-- react -->
   	  
   	   
   	  <section anchor="dynamic" title="Dynamic Modification">
   	  
   	  	<t>This strategy puts the entire burden of address adaptation on the 
   	  	provider network. It requires that an element in that network must intercept
   	  	program guide information destined to the receiver, locate the access
   	  	information, and map IP addresses to an alternate version as necessary 
   	  	to suit the receiver. If the problem identified in the last paragraph of 
   	  	<xref target="whichProb"/> is to be avoided, the intercepting element 
   	  	has to be aware of the version supported by each receiver.</t>
   	  	
   	  	<t>As noted in the description of the OMA architecture in 
   	  	<xref target="rcvrArt"/>, it is possible that such an adaptive function
   	  	is present, but not clear that its scope would extend to IP version
   	  	changes. The need to include IP version along with other receiver-related
   	  	information might or might not prove to be administratively demanding.
   	  	With the dynamic modification strategy the workload on the adaptation
   	  	function might be large enough to make it a bottleneck in the process 
   	  	of program acquisition. The mitigating factor is that program metadata
   	  	will typically be retrieved rather less often than program content. </t>
   	  	
   	  	<t>This strategy has the clear advantage that it requires no changes
   	  	in the receiver.</t>
   	  
   	  </section><!-- dynamic -->
   	  
   	   
   	  <section anchor="admin" title="Administrative Preparation">
   	  
   	  	<t>The basic idea with this strategy is that the access information 
   	  	in the program metadata is set up to provide the right address version
   	  	in advance of acquisition by any receiver. There are two basic
   	  	approaches:
   	  	<list style="symbols">
   	  	  <t>separate alternative versions of the access information are 
   	  	  prepared. The correct version is served up to the receiver when it
   	  	  requests it. Like the dynamic modification strategy, this approach
   	  	  assumes that it is administratively feasible for the program guide
   	  	  server to know the IP version of the requesting receiver. That may
   	  	  or may not be true in a given operator's context. Also as with the
   	  	  dynamic modification approach, no change is required in the receiver.
   	  	  The big advantage over dynamic modification is that there is no need
   	  	  for the complications of an intercepting adapting element.</t>
   	  	  
   	  	  <t>The same access information instance contains alternative IP 
   	  	  address versions. Where SDP is used, we can think of ICE or ICE-lite
   	  	  <xref target="RFC5245"/> or the proposed 'altc' mechanism 
   	  	  <xref target="ID.boucadair-altc"/>. This requires receiver 
   	  	  modification to recognize the alternative syntax and (in the case of
   	  	  ICE and potentially in the case of ICE-Lite) to take part in STUN 
   	  	  exchanges. However, it means that the same access information can be
   	  	  served up to all receivers in a backward-compatible manner.</t>
   	    </list>
   	    </t>
   	    
   	    <t>The administrative strategy requires that the network provider have 
   	    control over the translations used in the preparation of the alternative   	      versions of the access information. The network has to be aware of the
   	    translations used, so it can reuse them at other stages of the multicast
   	    acquisition process. Note networks owned by different operators are likely
   	    to have different mappings between IPv4 and IPv6 addresses, so if multiple
   	    receiving networks are downstream of the same source network, each of them
   	    may have to prepare and make available its own IPv6 version of the
   	    electronic program guide.</t>
   	    
   	  </section><!-- admin -->
   	   
    </section><!-- solutions -->
   

    
    <section anchor="conclusion" title="Conclusions">
   
   	  <t>To come.</t>
   
    </section><!-- conclusion -->
   

    <section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">
    
      <t>TBD</t>
      
    </section>

    <!-- Possibly a 'Contributors' section ... -->

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
    
      <t>This memo includes no request to IANA.</t>

    </section>

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
    
      <t>To come.</t>
      
    </section>
  </middle>

  <!--  *****BACK MATTER ***** -->

  <back>
  
   <!-- References split into informative and normative -->

    <references title="Informative References">
    
      &RFC3261;
      &RFC4078;
      &RFC4566;
      &RFC5245;
      &RFC6052;
      
      <reference anchor="ID.boucadair-altc">
     	  <front>
    	    <title>Session Description Protocol (SDP) Alternate Connectivity (ALTC) Attribute (Work in Progress)</title>
          <author initials="M." surname="Boucadair" fullname="M. Boucadair">
            <organization>France Telecom</organization>
          </author>
          <author initials="H." surname="Kaplan" fullname="H. Kaplan">
            <organization>Acme Packet</organization>
          </author>
          <author initials="R." surname="Gilman" fullname="R. Gilman">
            <organization>Independent</organization>
          </author>
          <author initials="S." surname="Veikkolainen" fullname="S. Veikkolainen">
            <organization>Nokia</organization>
          </author>
          <date month="November" year="2011"/>
        </front>
      </reference>
      
      <reference anchor="ID.jaclee-behave-v4v6-multicast-ps">
     	  <front>
    	    <title>IPv4-IPv6 Multicast: Problem Statement and Use Cases (Work in Progress)</title>
          <author initials="C." surname="Jacquenet" fullname="C. Jacquenet">
            <organization>France Telecom</organization>
          </author>
          <author initials="M." surname="Boucadair" fullname="M. Boucadair">
            <organization>France Telecom</organization>
          </author>
          <author initials="Y." surname="Lee" fullname="Y. Lee">
            <organization>Comcast</organization>
          </author>
          <author initials="J." surname="Qin" fullname="J. Qin">
            <organization>ZTE</organization>
          </author>
          <author initials="T." surname="Tsou" fullname="T. Tsou">
            <organization>Huawei Technologies (USA)</organization>
          </author>
          <date month="November" year="2011"/>
        </front>
      </reference>
      
      <reference anchor="ID.qin-softwire-multicast-prefix-option">
     	  <front>
    	    <title>DHCPv6 Options for IPv6 DS-Lite Multicast Prefix (Work in Progress)</title>
          <author initials="J." surname="Qin" fullname="J. Qin">
            <organization>ZTE</organization>
          </author>
          <author initials="M." surname="Boucadair" fullname="M. Boucadair">
            <organization>France Telecom</organization>
          </author>
          <author initials="T." surname="Tsou" fullname="T. Tsou">
            <organization>Huawei Technologies (USA)</organization>
          </author>
          <date month="October" year="2011"/>
        </front>
      </reference>
     
     
      <reference anchor="ID.mboned-64-multicast-address-format">
     	  <front>
    	    <title>IPv4-Embedded IPv6 Multicast Address Format (Work in Progress)</title>
          <author initials="M." surname="Boucadair" fullname="M. Boucadair">
            <organization>France Telecom</organization>
          </author>
          <author initials="J." surname="Qin" fullname="J. Qin">
            <organization>ZTE</organization>
          </author>
          <author initials="Y." surname="Lee" fullname="Y. Lee">
            <organization>Comcast</organization>
          </author>
          <author initials="S." surname="Venaas" fullname="S. Venaas">
            <organization>Cisco Systems</organization>
          </author>
          <author initials="X." surname="Li" fullname="X. Li">
            <organization>CERNET Center/Tsinghua University</organization>
          </author>
          <author initials="M." surname="Xu" fullname="M. Xu">
            <organization>Tsinghua University</organization>
          </author>
          <date month="February" year="2012"/>
        </front>
      </reference>
     
     
      <reference anchor="MPEG-7_DDL">
   	    <front>
  	      <title>ISO/IEC 15938-2 (2002): "Information technology - Multimedia content description interface - Part 2: Description definition language".</title>
          <author initials="" surname="" fullname="">
            <organization>ISO/IEC</organization>
          </author>
          <date year="2002"/>
        </front>
      </reference>
   
    
    </references>

      
    
    <section anchor="rcvrArt" title="Some Background On Program Guides">
   
   	  <t>Numerous organizations have been involved in the development of 
   	  specifications for IPTV. Those specifications and the requirements of 
   	  individual providers have influenced the development of existing 
   	  receivers. Any solution to the multicast transition problem described 
   	  in <xref target="intro"/> has to take account of the effort involved not
   	  only in the direct development of a new generation of receivers, but also
   	  in evolving the specifications on which those receivers are based. It is
   	  thus worthwhile to review the current situation as it affects
   	  multicast transition.</t>
   	  
   	  <t>The TV-Anytime forum (http://www.tv-anytime.org/) did early work in 
   	  the area, formally terminating in 2005. Their work focussed on the 
   	  description of program content, to facilitate the creation of such 
   	  descriptions and their navigation by the user. The results are documented
   	  in the ETSI TS 102 822 series of technical specifications.</t>
   	  
   	  <t>The content reference identifier (CRID) is a fundamental concept in
   	  the TV-Anytime data model. It refers to a specific piece of content or
   	  to other CRIDs, the latter thereby providing a method for grouping 
   	  related pieces of content. TV-Anytime registered the CRID: URL schema
   	  in <xref target="RFC4078"/>. Quoting from the abstract of that document:

      <list style="empty">
	      <t>The Uniform Resource Locator (URL) scheme "CRID:" has been devised to
	      allow references to current or future scheduled publications of
	      broadcast media content over television distribution platforms and
	      the Internet.</t>

        <t>The initial intended application is as an embedded link within
        scheduled programme description metadata that can be used by the home
        user or agent to associate a programme selection with the
        corresponding programme location information for subsequent automatic
        acquisition.</t>
      </list>
      </t>
      
      <t>The process of location resolution for the CRID: URL for an individual
      piece of content locates the content itself so that the user can access 
      it. TV-Anywhere left the details of that process unspecified.</t>
      
      <t>The Open IPTV Forum (http://www.oipf.tv) has focussed on defining the 
      user-to-network interface, particularly for fixed broadband access. The
      architecture is based on the ETSI NGN (Next Generation Networks) model.
      The receiver obtains the actual access information for a given program,
      including the multicast group address and possibly a unicast source 
      address, from XML-encoded program information following the Open IPTV 
      Forum schema. The receiver uses SIP (Session Initiation Protocol
      <xref target="RFC3261"/>) signalling to obtain authorization and resources
      for a session, before signalling at the multicast level to acquire the
      program. The SIP signalling conveys the multicast group address and the 
      unicast source address, if available, in the form of an SDP (Session 
      Description Protocol <xref target="RFC4566"/>) session description.</t>
      
      <t>Finally, the Open Mobile Alliance (OMA, http://www.openmobilealliance.org/)
      has defined a series of specifications relating to broadcast services over
      wireless networks. The source and multicast group addresses used to acquire
      a given program instance are provided in SDP fragments either directly
      embedded in the primary electronic program guide or pointed to by it. The
      OMA architecture provides functionality to adapt access information within
      the program guide to the requirements of the transport network to which the 
      user is attached, but this functionality appears to be primarily directed
      toward overcoming differences in technology rather than a general capability
      for modification. </t>
      
      <t>In conclusion, it appears that there are at least two extant sources of
      specifications for the receiver interface, each providing its own data 
      model, XML data schema, and detailed architecture. In the OMA case, the
      access information including the source and multicast group addresses is
      embedded as an SDP fragment within a larger set of XML-encoded
      program metadata. The OMA metadata can be supplied to the receiver in 
      multiple segments, through multiple channels. This complicates the task
      of intercepting that metadata and modifying it in a particular transport
      network. </t>
      
    </section><!-- rcvrArt -->
    
   </back>
</rfc>
