<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
]>

<rfc category="info" ipr="trust200902"
     docName="draft-venaas-pim-registry-01.txt">

<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>

<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc iprnotified="no" ?>
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>

<front>
  <title>A Registry for PIM Message Types</title>
  <author initials='S.' surname='Venaas' fullname='Stig Venaas'>
    <organization>cisco Systems</organization>
    <address><postal>
        <street>Tasman Drive</street>
	<city>San Jose</city> <region>CA</region>
	<code>95134</code>
	<country>USA</country>
      </postal>
      <email>stig@cisco.com</email></address>
  </author>
  <date/>
  <abstract>
    <t>This document provides instructions to IANA for the creation of
      a registry for PIM message types. It specifies initial content of
      the registry based on existing RFCs specifying PIM message types.
      It also specifies a procedure for registering new types.</t>
    <t>In addition to this, one message type is reserved, and may be
      used for a future extension of the message type space.</t>
  </abstract>
</front>

<middle>
  <section title="Introduction">
    <t>Apart from this document, there is no existing document
specifying a registry for PIM message types. PIM version 1 made use of IGMP
<xref target="RFC1112"/> and there is an IGMP registry <xref target="IGMPREG"/>
listing the message types used by PIM version 1. PIM version 2 however is not
based on IGMP, and a separate PIM message type registry is needed. There are
currently several RFCs specifying new PIM version 2 message types that should
be in this new registry. They are the RFCs for PIM Dense Mode
<xref target="RFC3973"/>, PIM Sparse Mode <xref target="RFC4601"/> and
Bidirectional PIM <xref target="RFC5015"/>.
</t><t>This document specifies the initial content of the new PIM message type
registry based on those existing RFCs. This document also specifies a
procedure for registering new PIM message types.</t>
<t>In addition to this, this document reserves one message type. This type
may be used for a future extension of the message type space. How
exactly the extension should be done is left to a future document.</t>
  </section>
  <section title="Security Considerations">
    <t>This document only creates an IANA registry. There may be a
security benefit in a well-known place for finding information on which
PIM message types are valid and what they mean. Apart from that there are
no security considerations.</t>
  </section>
  <section title="IANA Considerations">
    <t>This document requests IANA to create a PIM message type
registry. This should be placed in the "Protocol Independent Multicast (PIM)"
branch of the tree. Each entry in the registry consists of message type,
message name and references to the documents defining the type.</t>
    <section title="Initial registry">
      <t>The initial content of the registry should be as follows.
        <figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[
Type   Name                                      Reference
----  ----------------------------------------  ---------------------
  0    Hello                                     [RFC3973] [RFC4601]
  1    Register                                  [RFC4601]
  2    Register Stop                             [RFC4601]
  3    Join/Prune                                [RFC3973] [RFC4601]
  4    Bootstrap                                 [RFC4601]
  5    Assert                                    [RFC3973] [RFC4601]
  6    Graft                                     [RFC3973]
  7    Graft-Ack                                 [RFC3973]
  8    Candidate RP Advertisement                [RFC4601]
  9    State Refresh                             [RFC3973]
 10    DF Election                               [RFC5015]
 15    Reserved (for extension of type space)    [this document]
          ]]></artwork>
        </figure>
      </t>
    </section>
    <section title="Assignment of new message types">
<t>Assignment of new message types is done according to the "IETF Review"
model, see [RFC5226].</t>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section title="Acknowledgements">
    <t>Thanks to Toerless Eckert for his suggestion to reserve a type
    for future message type space extension.</t>
  </section>
</middle>
<back>
  <references title='Normative References'>
    <?rfc include='reference.RFC.3973' ?>
    <?rfc include='reference.RFC.4601' ?>
    <?rfc include='reference.RFC.5015' ?>
  </references>
      
  <references title='Informative References'>
    <?rfc include='reference.RFC.1112' ?>
    <reference anchor="IGMPREG">
      <front>
	<title>IGMP Type Numbers</title>
	<author surname="IANA">
	  <organization />
   	</author>
	<date month="June" year="2005" />
      </front>
      <seriesInfo name="IGMP TYPE NUMBERS - per RFC3228, BCP57"
		  value="http://www.iana.org/assignments/igmp-type-numbers" />
    </reference>
  </references>
</back>
</rfc>
