<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<rfc category="std" docName="draft-ietf-pcp-description-option-02"
     ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="PCP Description Option">PCP Description Option</title>

    <author fullname="Mohamed Boucadair" initials="M." surname="Boucadair">
      <organization>France Telecom</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>

          <city>Rennes</city>

          <region></region>

          <code>35000</code>

          <country>France</country>
        </postal>

        <email>mohamed.boucadair@orange.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Reinaldo Penno" initials="R." surname="Penno">
      <organization>Cisco</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>

          <city></city>

          <code></code>

          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>

        <email>repenno@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Dan Wing" initials="D." surname="Wing">
      <organization abbrev="Cisco">Cisco Systems, Inc.</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>170 West Tasman Drive</street>

          <city>San Jose</city>

          <region>California</region>

          <code>95134</code>

          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>

        <email>dwing@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date day="31" month="July" year="2013" />

    <workgroup>PCP Working Group</workgroup>

    <abstract>
      <t>This document extends Port Control Protocol (PCP) with the ability to
      associate a description with a PCP-instantiated mapping. It does so by
      defining a new DESCRIPTION option.</t>
    </abstract>

    <note title="Requirements Language">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
      document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
      target="RFC2119">RFC 2119</xref>.</t>
    </note>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section anchor="introduction" title="Introduction">
      <t>This document extends the <xref target="RFC6887">base PCP </xref>
      with the ability to associate a human-readable description with a
      PCP-instantiated mapping. It does so by defining a new DESCRIPTION
      option.</t>

      <t>This PCP option can be used in both simple scenarios with a PCP
      client and PCP server, as well as in more complex scenarios where an
      interworking function is used to proxy between a UPnP IGD Control Point
      and a PCP server <xref target="RFC6970"></xref>.</t>

      <t>Querying the PCP server to get the description text of an existing
      mapping is out of scope.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Format">
      <t>The format of the DESCRIPTION option is shown in <xref
      target="desc"></xref>.</t>

      <t><figure anchor="desc" title="Description Option">
          <preamble></preamble>

          <artwork><![CDATA[    0                   1                   2                   3
    0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   | DESCRIPTION   |  Reserved     |           Length              |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |                           Description                         |
   :                                                               :
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
      
     This Option:

      Option Name: Description Option (DESCRIPTION)
      Number: <to be assigned in the optional-to-process range>
      Purpose: Used to associate a text description with a mapping
      Valid for Opcodes: MAP, PEER
      Length: Variable
      May appear in: request. May appear in response only if it 
                     appeared in the associated request.
      Maximum occurrences: 1

]]></artwork>

          <postamble></postamble>
        </figure>The Description field MUST carry UTF-8 encoded <xref
      target="RFC3629"></xref> description text. The description text SHOULD
      NOT be null terminated.</t>

      <t>This option can be used by a user (or an application) to indicate a
      description associated with a given mapping such as "FTP server", "My
      remote access to my CP router", "Camera", "Network attached storage
      serve", etc.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Behavior">
      <t>The DESCRIPTION option is optional to be supported by PCP servers and
      PCP clients.</t>

      <t>This option (Code TBA, <xref target="desc"></xref>) MAY be included
      in a PCP MAP/PEER request to associate a description with the requested
      mapping.</t>

      <t>The PCP server MAY be configurable to accept the DESCRIPTION option.
      If the PCP server does not support the DESCRIPTION option or it is
      configured to ignore it, received DESCRIPTION options MUST be ignored by
      the PCP server and a DESCRIPTION option MUST NOT be included in the
      response. The PCP server MUST store the content of the DESCRIPTION
      option only if it supports the DESCRIPTION option and if it is
      configured to accept handling DESCRIPTION options it receives.</t>

      <t><!--If no indication is explicitly configured to the PCP server, the default behavior is to ignore any received DESCRIPTION option.-->If
      the PCP client does not receive a DESCRIPTION option in a response to a
      request enclosing a DESCRIPTION option, this means the PCP server does
      not support that Option. If the DESCRIPTION option is not included in
      the request, the PCP server MUST NOT include the DESCRIPTION option in
      the associated response.</t>

      <t>The maximum length SHOULD be configurable in the PCP server. The
      configured maximum length MUST NOT exceed 1016 octets. The suggested
      maximum length is 128 octets. If a PCP client includes a DESCRIPTION
      option with a length exceeding the maximum length supported by the PCP
      server, only the portion of the Description field fitting that maximum
      length is stored by the PCP server and returned to the PCP client in the
      response.</t>

      <t>If the PCP server receives a DESCRIPTION option having a length which
      does not exceed the maximum value configured, the PCP server MUST record
      the complete sequence of the description text and MUST send back to the
      PCP client the same DESCRIPTION option as the one included in the
      request. If the description text carried in the DESCRIPTION option is
      null terminated, the exact description text, including Null characters,
      MUST be returned by the PCP server.</t>

      <t>Invalid DESCRIPTION options (e.g., the content is not a legal UTF-8
      string) MUST be ignored by the PCP server.</t>

      <t>To update the description text of a mapping maintained by a PCP
      server, the PCP client generates a PCP MAP/PEER renewal request which
      includes a DESCRIPTION option carrying the new description text. Upon
      receipt of the PCP request, the PCP server proceeds to the same
      operations to validate a MAP/PEER request refreshing an existing
      mapping. If validation checks are successfully passed, the PCP server
      replaces the old description text with the new one included in the
      DESCRIPTION option, and the PCP server returns the updated description
      text in the response, truncated (if necessary) as described above.</t>

      <t>The PCP client uses empty DESCRIPTION option (i.e., Length set to 0)
      to erase the description text associated with a mapping. Upon receipt of
      a PCP renewal request which includes an empty DESCRIPTION option, the
      PCP server MUST clear the description text associated with a mapping it
      maintains. When sending a successful PCP response, the PCP server MUST
      return back the empty DESCRIPTION option in the response to confirm the
      deletion of the description text is successfully handled.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>PCP-related security considerations are discussed in <xref
      target="RFC6887"></xref>. In addition, administrators of PCP servers
      SHOULD configure a maximum description length which does not lead to
      exhausting storage resources in the PCP server.</t>

      <t>If the PCP client and the PCP server are not under the same
      administrative entity, the DESCRIPTION option SHOULD NOT be used to leak
      privacy-related information (for example, see Section 3.2 of <xref
      target="RFC6462"></xref>).</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="iana" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>The following PCP Option Codes are to be allocated in the
      optional-to-process range (the registry is maintained in
      http://www.iana.org/assignments/pcp-parameters/pcp-parameters.xml#option-rules):<list
          style="empty">
          <t>DESCRIPTION</t>
        </list></t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119"?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6887'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.3629'?>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6970'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6462'?>
    </references>

    <!--
-->
  </back>
</rfc>
