<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<rfc category="std" docName="draft-ietf-pcp-description-option-00"
     ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="PCP Description Option">PCP Description Option</title>

    <author fullname="Mohamed Boucadair" initials="M." surname="Boucadair">
      <organization>France Telecom</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>

          <city>Rennes</city>

          <region></region>

          <code>35000</code>

          <country>France</country>
        </postal>

        <email>mohamed.boucadair@orange.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Reinaldo Penno" initials="R." surname="Penno">
      <organization>Cisco</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>

          <city></city>

          <code></code>

          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>

        <email>repenno@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Dan Wing" initials="D." surname="Wing">
      <organization abbrev="Cisco">Cisco Systems, Inc.</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>170 West Tasman Drive</street>

          <city>San Jose</city>

          <region>California</region>

          <code>95134</code>

          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>

        <email>dwing@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date day="11" month="March" year="2013" />

    <workgroup>PCP Working Group</workgroup>

    <abstract>
      <t>This document extends Port Control Protocol (PCP) with the ability to
      associate a description with a PCP-instantiated mapping: DESCRIPTION
      Option.</t>
    </abstract>

    <note title="Requirements Language">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
      document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
      target="RFC2119">RFC 2119</xref>.</t>
    </note>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section anchor="introduction" title="Introduction">
      <t>This document extends the <xref target="I-D.ietf-pcp-base">base PCP
      </xref> with the ability to associate a description with a
      PCP-instantiated mapping: DESCRIPTION Option.</t>

      <t>This option can be used in the context of <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-pcp-upnp-igd-interworking"></xref>.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Format">
      <t>The format of DESCRIPTION Option is shown in <xref
      target="desc"></xref>.</t>

      <t><figure anchor="desc" title="Description Option">
          <preamble></preamble>

          <artwork><![CDATA[    0                   1                   2                   3
    0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   | DESCRIPTION   |  Reserved     |           Length              |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |                           Description                         |
   :                                                               :
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
      
     This Option:

      Option Name: Description Option (DESCRIPTION)
      Number: TBA in the optional-to-process range (IANA)
      Purpose: Used to associate a text description with a mapping
      Valid for Opcodes: MAP, PEER
      Length: Variable
      May appear in: both request and response
      Maximum occurrences: 1

]]></artwork>

          <postamble></postamble>
        </figure>Description field MUST carry UTF-8 encoded <xref
      target="RFC3629"></xref> description text. The description text SHOULD
      NOT be null terminated.</t>

      <t>This option can be used by a user (or an application) to indicate a
      description associated with a given mapping such as "FTP server", "My
      remote access to my CP router", "Camera", "Network attached storage
      serve", etc.</t>

      <t>Issues related to the usage of this field for troubleshooting or for
      any further usage are out of scope of this document.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Behaviour">
      <t>DESCRIPTION Option is optional to be supported by PCP Servers and PCP
      Clients.</t>

      <t>This option (Code TBA, <xref target="desc"></xref>) MAY be included
      in a PCP MAP/PEER request to associate a description with the requested
      mapping.</t>

      <t>The PCP Server MAY be configurable to accept the DESCRIPTION Option.
      If the PCP Server does not support the DESCRIPTION Option or it is
      configured to ignore it, received DESCRIPTION Options MUST be ignored by
      the PCP Server and no DESCRIPTION Option MUST be included in the
      response. The PCP Server MUST store the content of DESCRIPTION Option
      only if it supports the DESCRIPTION Option and if it is configured to
      accept handling DESCRIPTION Options it receives.</t>

      <t><!--If no indication is explicitly configured to the PCP Server, the default behavior is to ignore any received DESCRIPTION Option.-->If
      the PCP Client does not receive a DESCRIPTION Option in a response to a
      request enclosing a DESCRIPTION Option, this means the PCP Server does
      not support that Option. The PCP Client SHOULD avoid including the
      DESCRIPTION Option in any subsequent request to that PCP Server.</t>

      <t>If the DESCRIPTION Option is not included in the request, the PCP
      Server MUST NOT include the DESCRIPTION Option in the associated
      response.</t>

      <t>The PCP Client MUST NOT include empty DESCRIPTION Option (i.e.,
      Length set to 0) in a request. Empty DESCRIPTION Options MUST be ignored
      by the PCP Server.</t>

      <t>The maximum length SHOULD be configurable in the PCP Server. If a PCP
      Client includes a DESCRIPTION PCP Option with a length exceeding the
      maximum length supported by the PCP Server, only the portion of the
      Description field fitting that maximum length is stored by the PCP
      Server and returned to the PCP Client in the response.</t>

      <t>If the PCP Server receives a DESCRIPTION Option having a length which
      does not exceed the maximum value configured, the PCP Server MUST record
      the complete sequence of the description text and MUST send back to the
      PCP Client the same DESCRIPTION Option as the one included in the
      request. If the description text carried in the DESCRIPTION Option is
      null terminated, the exact description text, including Null characters,
      MUST be returned by the PCP Server.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>Security considerations discussed in <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-pcp-base"></xref> must be considered. In addition,
      administrators of PCP Servers SHOULD configure a maximum description
      length which does not lead to exhaust storage resources in the PCP
      Server.</t>

      <t>Within this document, the content of DESCRIPTION Option is not used
      as a hint to construct a mapping in the PCP Server. If future documents
      make use of this option to influence the PCP Server decisions, those
      document MUST elaborate on the associated security considerations.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="iana" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>The following PCP Option Codes are to be allocated in the
      optional-to-process range:<list style="empty">
          <t>DESCRIPTION</t>
        </list></t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119"?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-pcp-base'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.3629'?>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-pcp-upnp-igd-interworking'?>
    </references>

    <!--
-->
  </back>
</rfc>
