<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY RFC2119 PUBLIC ''
'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml'>
<!ENTITY RFC4861 PUBLIC ''
'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4861.xml'>
<!ENTITY RFC4862 PUBLIC ''
'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4862.xml'>
<!ENTITY RFC6275 PUBLIC ''
'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6275.xml'>
<!ENTITY RFC3776 PUBLIC ''
'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3776.xml'>
<!ENTITY RFC5213 PUBLIC ''
'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5213.xml'>
<!ENTITY RFC3963 PUBLIC ''
'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3963.xml'>
<!ENTITY RFC5380 PUBLIC ''
'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5380.xml'>
<!ENTITY RFC5555 PUBLIC ''
'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5555.xml'>
<!ENTITY RFC5568 PUBLIC ''
'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5568.xml'>
<!ENTITY RFC6088 PUBLIC ''
'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6088.xml'>
<!ENTITY RFC6089 PUBLIC ''
'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6089.xml'>
<!ENTITY RFC5014 PUBLIC ''
'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5014.xml'>
<!ENTITY RFC5142 PUBLIC ''
'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5142.xml'>
<!ENTITY RFC4433 PUBLIC ''
'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4433.xml'>
<!ENTITY LMAREDIR PUBLIC ''       'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-netext-redirect.xml'> 
<!ENTITY PMIPMIP PUBLIC ''       'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-netlmm-mip-interactions.xml'> 
<!ENTITY PMIPLR PUBLIC ''       'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-netext-pmip6-lr-ps.xml'> 


]>

<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc tocappendix="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<rfc category="info"
     docName="draft-patil-mext-dmm-approaches-02"
     ipr="trust200902"
>
  <front>
    <title abbrev="DMM with MIP6">Approaches to Distributed mobility
    management using Mobile IPv6 and its extensions</title> 
    
    <author role ="editor" fullname="Basavaraj Patil" initials="B" surname="Patil">
      <organization>Nokia</organization>
      <address>
         <postal>
            <street>6021 Connection drive</street>
            <city>Irving</city>
            <region>TX</region>
            <code>75039</code>
            <country>USA</country>
         </postal>
         <email>basavaraj.patil@nokia.com</email>
      </address>
      </author>


      <author initials="C" surname="Williams"
      fullname="Carl Williams">
	<organization>MCSR Labs</organization>
	<address>
          <postal>
            <street></street>
            <city>Palo Alto</city>
            <region>CA</region>
            <code>94306</code>
            <country>USA</country>
          </postal>
          <email>carlw@mcsr-labs.org</email>
	</address>
      </author>

      <author initials="J" surname="Korhonen"
      fullname="Jouni Korhonen">
         <organization>Nokia Siemens Networks</organization>
         <address>
            <postal>
               <street>Linnoitustie 6</street>
               <code>FI-02600 Espoo</code>
               <country>FINLAND</country>
            </postal>
            <email>jouni.nospam@gmail.com</email>
         </address>
      </author>


    <date year="2011" />

    <area>Internet</area>

    <workgroup>Individual Submission</workgroup>
    <keyword>Mobility</keyword>
    <keyword>Mobile IPv6</keyword>
    <keyword>Distributed Mobility</keyword>
    <keyword>HMIP</keyword>
    <keyword>Home Agent</keyword>

    <abstract>
     <t>
       Mobility solutions at the IP layer have been specified in the
       IETF for IPv4 and IPv6. These solutions include host and
       network based mobility. All of the mobility protocols enable IP
       session continuity by providing the mobile host with an IP
       address or prefix that remains constant even as the host moves
       and attaches to different access networks and points of
       attachment. Mobile hosts are anchored at a gateway via
       a tunnel and the address/prefix provided to the host via the
       gateway remains unchanged across mobility events. All IP
       sessions initiated or terminated at a mobile host are anchored
       via the gateway. A gateway centric approach raises certain
       concerns in terms of cost and efficiency. A mobility model
       wherein the mobility functions are 
       distributed is a way of alleviating the concerns of a gateway
       centric approach. This document considers ways to
       alleviate anchored mobility issues with approaches that could
       be considered in a deployment.
     </t>
   </abstract>
 </front>

 <middle>
   <section title="Introduction">
     <t>
       Mobility solutions at the IP layer have been specified in the
       IETF for IPv4 and IPv6. These solutions include host and
       network based mobility. All of the mobility protocols enable IP
       session continuity by providing the mobile host with an IP
       address or prefix that remains constant even as the host moves
       and attaches to different access networks and points of
       attachment. Mobile hosts are anchored at a gateway via
       a tunnel and the address/prefix provided to the host via the
       gateway remains unchanged across mobility events. All IP
       sessions initiated or terminated at a mobile host are anchored
       via the gateway. There are issues and concerns with such a
       mobility model which are discussed in this
       document. A mobility model wherein the mobility functions are
       distributed is a way of alleviating the concerns of a gateway
       centric approach. This document also considers ways to
       alleviate anchored mobility issues with approaches that could
       be considered in a deployment.
     </t>
     <t>
       Mobile IPv6 as specified in <xref target="RFC6275"/>
       <xref target="RFC3776"/> is a host 
       based mobility protocol. It requires the MN to be anchored at a
       home agent. The home agent assigns the MN an IPv6 address or
       prefix that is static for the duration of the registration
       period. Similarly Proxy Mobile IPv6 <xref target="RFC5213"/> is
       a network based mobility protocol in which the mobility access
       gateway (MAG) assigns the MN a prefix provided by the local
       mobility anchor (LMA) for the duration of a valid
       registration. This prefix does not change across mobility
       events. The home agent and LMA entities can be viewed as
       centralized gateways. These gateways generally serve a large
       number of mobile hosts. All traffic to/from mobile hosts
       associated with an HA/LMA is routed through these
       gateways and as a result raises concerns such as :
     </t>
       <t>
	 <list style="numbers">
	   <t> single point of failure, </t>
	   <t> backhauling traffic to the gateway, </t> 
	   <t> latency as a result of backhauling and additional
	     processing,</t>
	   <t> cost and complexity, etc. </t>
	 </list>
       </t>
       <t>
       These issues are discussed in further detail in the document. It should also be
       noted that in addition to mobility for hosts, there is also
       specifications that deal with networks that are mobile. Network
       mobility is specified in <xref target="RFC3963"/>
     </t>
     <t>
       The mobility working groups in the IETF have extended the basic
       protocols to address various issues and concerns. Hierarchical
       Mobile IP <xref target="RFC5380"/> and flow mobility
       <xref target="RFC6088"/>, <xref target="RFC6089"/> are just a
       few examples. Many of these extensions can be utilized in
       deployments to alleviate the issues that arise from an anchored
       mobility solution. A few approaches to how a distributed
       mobility model could be deployed using current protocols and
       extensions are also discussed in this document.
     </t>

   </section>

   <section title="Terminology">
     <t>
       <list style="hanging">
	 <t hangText="Distributed Mobility">
           <vspace blankLines="1"/>
	   The term distributed mobility refers to an architecture in
	   which the mobility function is distributed across multiple
	   levels in a deployment. The mobility function could be
	   provided by an access point or base-station or it could be
	   a part of the access network. Distributed mobility would
	   enable session continuity for hosts while not requiring
	   that they be anchored at a single gateway (home agent) all
	   the time. 
	 </t>
       </list>
     </t>
   </section>

   <section title="Problem statement">
     <t>
       The lack of support for mobility at the IP layer has been
       addressed in IPv6 with the specification of Mobile IPv6
       <xref target="RFC6275"/>. Various extensions to the protocol
       such as support for multiple care-of-addresses as well as the
       ability to operate while attached to an IPv4 network using
       Dual-stack Mobile IPv6 <xref target="RFC5555"/> have been
       specified. The protocol has not been widely implemented or
       deployed as of date for various reasons. 
     </t>
     <t>
       The Internet has evolved to support real-time applications such
       as voice, multimedia streaming etc. These applications require
       low latency as well as no (or minimal) interruptions when
       switching interfaces or networks. Current IP mobility solutions
       based on Mobile IPv6 are well suited for non-real-time
       applications which are able to handle the delay which is caused
       by a mobile node doing a handover between networks or switching
       interfaces. Optimizations to support real time applications
       have also been specified such as FMIPv6
       <xref target="RFC5568"/>. The centralized gateway approach of
       Mobile IPv6 has multiple issues and raises concerns that are
       captured in this document. One of the ideas is to move the
       mobility gateway closer to the actual point of attachment. This
       has benefits in terms of reduced latency but it also causes
       other issues such as the ability to support mobility when the
       MN moves to a different access network or the ability to do
       charging at a central node. Distributed mobility is an approach
       that has some merit and worth studying further. At the same
       time the issues that are driving the mobility solutions towards
       a different model can be addressed by existing protocols with
       various extensions. The problems of a centralized gateway
       approach and reasons for considering distributed mobility need
       to be deeply analyzed and understood before beginning work on
       entirely new protocols for solving IP mobility.
     </t>
     </section>

     <section title="Issues with current mobility models">
       <t>
	 Current mobility protocols have been designed with a stable
	 topologically correct anchoring gateway in mind.  
	 They just do not tolerate mid-session anchor relocation. HMIP6,
	 HA Switch, HA-reliability and LMA Redirect are attempts in that
	 direction but fail or fall short.
       </t>
       <t>
	 In addition, one of the key deployment considerations of Mobile IPv6 is the
	 location of each of the home agents or gateways, both initially
	 and over time.  Each operator has unique requirements;  
	 therefore, no single deployment model will suit all operators.  
	 The operator's own organizational structure could also influence
	 the mobility architecture.  Some operators have network OAM
	 responsibilities that are assigned geographically, while others use a 
	 more centralized model.  The deployment architecture that has
	 been traditionally put forth is to have  centralized gateway elements
	 where all mobility control and data traffic is routed through them.  
       </t>
   
  
  
  <section title="Backhauling all traffic to a centralized GW">
    <t>
    A centralized home agent/gateway approach leads to backhauling all
    traffic to the node which has unfavorable operational consequences.
   </t>
    <t>
      The sheer volume of the aggregated throughput traffic  to backhaul all user data
      from a local aggregation anchor to centralized data centers with
      home gateways can  be expensive in many scenarios.  With high
      density deployments, the centralized architecture leads to heavy
      backhaul utilization, and the inability to distribute load quickly
      manifests unfavorably.  In addition, local user traffic does not
      remain local. User traffic must travel all the way to the
      centralized gateway and back, even if the corresponding peer is
      topologically closer.   
     </t>
    
    <t>
      In addition, a centralized gateway model increases the cost of
      backhaul by preventing the off-loading of high-bandwidth
      services locally.  Instead high-bandwidth services have their
      traffic backhauled to a centralized gateway in a data
      center. This will increase the distances and possibly the
      capacity associated with any backhaul. 
      </t>
  
   </section>

    <section title="Latency Considerations">
      <t>
	While the support for Internet offload of user data can
	significantly reduce the core network backhaul, the mobility
	management element may be strategically positioned deeper in
	the network to efficiently set-up and process the signaling
	and control including optional policies.   Such a hybrid
	architecture can provide for supporting a mix of real-time and
	non-real-time broadband services.  Real-time applications can
	benefit from lower latencies by having data closer to the
	subscriber and peers and not backhauled.  Non-real-time
	applications (such as e-mail) derive no such performance
	benefit and may have a more centralized traffic approach.
      </t> 
     <t>
     Current mobility models handle offload cases poorly. 
      A consideration may be to clearly make a working toolbox for applications to select 
      a prefix with anchored mobility and a prefix without anchoring.
       </t>
    </section>
    <section title="Inefficient Routing and signaling overhead">
      <t>
        Inefficient routing mechanism of a completely centralized
        mobility deployment approach causes QoS deterioration and may
        lead to heavy network congestion in the core. 
      </t>
      <t>
        In the centralized approach only the HA and the CNs manage a
            nodes mobility. Mobility signaling occurs each time a
            mobile node changes its point-of-attachment regardless of
            the locality and amplitude of its movement. As a
            consequence, the same level of signaling load is
            introduced independently of the user's mobility pattern.
            For example,  if the HA and/or CNs are far from the MN,
            even if the MNs movement is small, the mobility signaling
            messages travel across several IP networks, the latencies
            of which reduce handover speed.  Furthermore, route
            optimization which supports direct routing from CNs to the
            mobile node, generates excessive mobility messages and
            adds a significant extra load to the network. 
      </t>
    </section>
    
    <section title="Scalability and cost">
      <t>
        In a completely centralized Mobile IPv6-based deployment
        approach, the home agent becomes a single point of failure.
        Also, a distributed deployment approach may provide better
        overall capacity and performance, but this must be weighed
        against the increase in capital costs for deployment of local
        distributed gateways.  In addition, a completely centralized
        deployment model makes it difficult to scale with a large
        number of mobile nodes.  Scalability costs are weighted from
        many perspectives such as the number of nodes in the overall
        system, the geographic distance of the traffic, the number of
        autonomous parties in the deployment approach and others.  
      </t>
    </section>
   
</section>

<section title="Enhancements to improve mobility">
  <t>
    Enhancements to the Mobile IPv6 protocol have been done to improve
   mobile communications in certain scenarios so that mobility
   operations are efficient and optimized..  A key area of
   enhancements is in reducing the delays 
   in the data path redirection operation that is defined in Mobile
   IPv6 operations. Mobile IPv6 has adopted route optimization and
   HMIPv6 to reduce the traversal of data traffic to the mobile nodes
   new location changes in its point of attachment.   Delays in data
   traffic redirection will depend upon the location of the anchor
   agent that performs the redirection. As such enhancements focus on
   moving these anchor agents closer to the mobile node.  
  </t>
  
  <section title="HMIPv6">
    <t>
      Using Mobile IPv6, a mobile node sends location updates to any
      node it corresponds with each time it changes its location, and
      at intermittent intervals otherwise.  This involves a lot of
      signaling and processing, and requires a lot of resources.
      Furthermore, although it is not necessary for external hosts to
      be updated when a mobile nodes moves locally, these updates
      occur for both local and global moves.  Hierarchical Mobile IPv6
      (HMIPv6)is designed to enhance mobility support in MIPv6 and
      micro-mobility management. The benefit of the HMIPv6
      enhancement is to reduce the amount of signaling required and to
      improve handoff speed. 
    </t>
    <t>
      The key concept behind HMIPv6 is to locally handle handovers by
      the usage of an entity called the Mobility Anchor Point (MAP)
      located at any level in a hierarchical network of routers.  The
      major issue on HMIPv6 is designing the MAP selection scheme that
      can reduce frequent handover mobility signaling and improve
      handover performance. 
    </t>
     </section>
  <section title="Dynamic assignment of HA">
    <t> 
      Dynamic assignment of HA is an enhancement to reduce both the
      signaling traffic and the data traffic to the home network.  The
      dynamic HA assignment may take into account the geographical
      proximity of the HA to the mobile node. It may also consider
      performance factors such as HA load-balancing or other criteria.   
    </t>
  </section>
  <section title="­­­Route Optimization">
    <t>
      Mobile IPv6 Route optimization is an enhancement to optimize the
      data path between two communicating nodes despite changes in
      the IP connectivity on the mobile node side.  The data
      path reduction between the communicating nodes helps to reduce
      one way packet delay when both nodes are under the same
      localized domain and the mobility gateway is far away.  The
      process of reducing data path is referred to as route
      optimization. Route optimization helps reduce the delay and
      thus important for real-time applications.  An enhanced version
      of route optimization may also enable continued communications
      during periods of temporary home-agent unavailability.  
    </t>
  </section>
</section>


<section title="Distributed mobility - What does it imply">
  
  <t>
    Mobility is a service that provides significant value to a network
    operator. The ability to offer connectivity and services that work
    seamlessly across mobility events such as the switching of an
    access network type etc. creates a much superior end-user
    experience and thereby a demand for such service. Cellular
    networks have offered mobility for voice and messaging (short
    message service) since the late 80s and  early 90s. These networks
    have been evolving and are now offering broadband data services
    and Internet connectivity. The network architectures are also
    using Internet protocols and technologies to a significant
    extent. Traditionally the architectures of these networks has been
    hierarchical in nature. While such an architecture served
    operators well in the past, it has limitations when it comes to
    offering data services and Internet connectivity. There is an
    effort to distribute functionality that generally has resided in
    centralized gateways much more closer to the edge of the
    network. The line between the access and core network is fading
    and hence a need to rethink how mobility service is affected in
    such an evolving architecture. 
  </t>
  <t>
    Distributed mobility is a way to deploy existing mobility
    solutions that do not require a mobile host to be anchored at a
    gateway all the time but instead be attached to different mobility
    agents/gateways in the network depending on the access, location
    and other factors. Session continuity via distributed mobility is
    expected to be on par with that provided by an anchored mobility
    solution. 
  </t>
  <t>
    Does it require an entirely new approach to mobility architectures
    that would be based on the goal of distributing mobility related
    functions? It is an easy option to consider redesigning on a clean
    sheet of paper. However this is not a pragmatic approach. It is
    much more optimal to consider what are the issues that are created
    as a result of a centralized gateway architecture and then develop
    extensions to the protocols and, deployment models, that can address
    those issues. The implications of distributed mobility
    architectures on access and core networks needs to be also
    considered in any design. 
    </t>
  
</section>

<section title="Approaches using current protocols for distributed mobility">
  <t>
    We believe that most of the needed basic protocol functionality
    for distributed mobility management is already there. What is
    missing seem to be related to general system level design and lack
    of mobility aware APIs for application developers. One of the
    simple approaches for distributed mobility management is to avoid
    traditional "anchored mobility" like Mobile IPv6 when possible and
    rather use local (care-of) addresses for the communication. Use of
    local addressing also implies less mobility related signaling load
    in the network. For example <xref target="RFC5014"/> already
    provides means for an application to explicitly request for a
    prefix that has mobility characteristics (IPV6_PREFER_SRC_HOME) or
    a prefix that is local to the current access network
    (IPV6_PREFER_SRC_COA). It is not guaranteed that the IP stack in
    the MN would always respect the suggestion received from the
    application. In general it is also important that possible
    solutions in distributed mobility management space requires
    minimal changes in mobile hosts. 
  </t>
  <t>Another aspect that is in interest of distributed mobility
  management concentrates on allocating mobility anchors that are
  topologically close to the MN. Existing protocols such as HMIPv6
  <xref target="RFC5380"/> provide a solution that is close what is
  needed. What might be needed in addition is a mechanism to "chain"
  multiple MAP-domain to extend the micro-mobility area, or provide
  another RFC5014 like prefix type (IPV6_PREFER_SRC_MAP). We could
  also consider Mobile IPv6 + Proxy Mobile IPv6 interactions Scenario
  A.1 in <xref target="I-D.ietf-netlmm-mip-interactions"/> a similar
  solution. Finally, yet another approach for exploiting locality are
  Proxy Mobile IPv6 localized routing solutions
  <xref target="I-D.ietf-netext-pmip6-lr-ps"/> which allows bypassing
  the remote central Local Mobility Anchor when ever possible and have
  a direct communication via closer to MNs Mobile Access Gateways. 
  </t>
  <t>Home Agent Switch <xref target="RFC5142"/> extension to Mobile
 IPv6, Runtime LMA assignment
 <xref target="I-D.ietf-netext-redirect"/> extension to Proxy Mobile
 IPv6 and Mobile IPv4 Dynamic HA Assignment <xref target="RFC4433"/>
 all provide solutions to dynamically assign a mobility anchor to the
 MN. What is missing from these solutions, is a protocol or rather a
 system level solution for a "seamless mobility anchor relocation"
 during an existing mobility session. However, that would be rather
 challenging due the fact that a mobility anchor relocation usually
 implies topological location chance in the network, which would also
 mean different prefixes/subnetworks for home addresses from the IP
 routing point of view. Within a reasonably small autonomous  
 system or otherwise restricted area maybe some kind of interior
 routing solution could be used to assist mobility anchor relocation. 
  </t>
   
</section>

<section title="Potential future work">
  <t>
    As the MEXT working group evolves and transitions to one that is
    focused on dealing with distributed mobility, there is a need to
    clearly understand the drivers for such an approach and whether
    these could be dealt with via a framework that uses existing
    mobility protocols and extensions and can be applied in a manner
    that deals with those concerns. 
    </t>
  <t>
    One of the key efforts could be in understanding the key concerns
    driving the need for a distributed mobility solution and
    identifying various approaches using existing protocols and
    extensions to overcome them. 
    </t>
    
   <t>

     <list style="numbers">
       <t> Work on the generic solution for anchor relocation. This 
	 might be a architecture describing work, rather than protocol
	 work. I believe we have most protocols already in place but not
	 glued together.</t>
       <t>Work on address selection beyond RFC 5014 (with coloring i.e. the
	 end host stack knows properties of the prefix it got) and rapid
	 deprecation/renumbering of prefixes (needed when CoAs change and
	 applications try to use CoA for something local). This could
	 potentially be new protocol work an containers for coloring
	 prefixes (RA and DHCPv6) and how to handle local prefix deprecation
	 during handovers.</t> 
       <t>Work on localized mobility that does not involve signaling with
	 gateways or "mobility signaling". This could lead to work below
	 the IP layer, e.g. intra-AS mobility is handled
	 using some interior routing protocol enhancement.</t>
     </list>
   </t>
    
    
    
</section>

<section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
  <t>
    This document has no requests to IANA.
  </t>
</section>

<section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
  <t>
    This document is a discussion of distributed mobility
    solutions. Some of the approaches that are considered for
    deployment do have security implications. However since the
    approaches being discussed are based on existing mobility
    specifications developed within the IETF, they have already been
    reviewed for security. This document does not raise any new
    security concerns. 
  </t>
</section>


<section anchor="Summary" title="Summary and Conclusion">
  <t>
    Distributed mobility is a way of deploying mobility protocols that
    minimise the issues that arise from a centralized gateway centric
    approach that comes from a hierarchical model. As the amount of
    traffic in a network grows, operators are less willing to
    transport all the traffic to a centralized gateway just for the
    sake of enabling mobility. The mobility models have to evolve to
    meet the changing environment of mobile networks and traffic
    patterns.  
  </t>
  <t>
    Using many of the extensions and protocols that have been defined
    for Mobile IPv6 it is possible to deploy a mobility solution that
    meets the criteria of distributed mobility architecture. The
    concerns fo a centralized gateway approach can be addressed using
    deployment techniques effectively. 
  </t>
</section>

</middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Informative References">
            &RFC6275;
	    &RFC3776;
	    &RFC5213;
	    &RFC3963;
	    &RFC5380;
	    &RFC5555;
	    &RFC5568;
	    &RFC6088;
	    &RFC6089;
	    &RFC5014;
	    &RFC5142;
	    &RFC4433;
	    &LMAREDIR;
	    &PMIPMIP;
	    &PMIPLR;
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
