<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="no" ?>
<rfc category="info" docName="draft-ietf-hybi-websocket-requirements-00" ipr="trust200811">

<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="rfc2629.xslt" ?>

<front>
    <title abbrev="HyBi WebSocket Requirements">
        HyBi WebSocket Requirements and Features
    </title>

    <author initials="G." surname="Wilkins" fullname="Greg Wilkins" role="editor">
      <organization>Webtide.com</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>644 Emerson Street,Suite 200</street>
          <code>94301</code> 
          <city>Palo Alto</city> 
          <country>USA</country>

        </postal>
        <email>gregw@webtide.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author initials="M." surname="Stachowiak" fullname="Maciej Stachowiak" role="editor">
      <organization>Apple</organization>
      <address>
        <email>mjs@apple.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>



        <date year="2010"/>
        <area>APP</area>
        <workgroup>HYBI</workgroup>
        <keyword>HTTP</keyword>
        <keyword>WebSocket</keyword>

	<abstract>
	<t>This document considers the requirements and resulting features needed for the design of the WebSocket Protocol.
           The goal of the document is to provide a stable base for protocol design and related discussion.
	</t>
        </abstract>
</front>


<middle>

<section title="Introduction"> 
<t>HTTP <xref target="RFC2616"/> is a client/server protocol, where the HTTP servers store the data and provide it when it is requested by clients. 
  When used to used to retrieve data from an HTTP server, the client sends HTTP requests to the server, and the server returns 
  the requested data in HTTP responses. So the client has to poll continuously the server in order to receive new data.</t>

<t>Recently techniques that enable bidirectional communication over HTTP have become more pervasive. Those techniques reduce
   the need to poll continuously the server thanks to the usage of HTTP hanging requests and multiple connections between the
   client and the server <xref target="I-D.loreto-http-bidirectional"/>.</t>

<t>The goal of HyBi is to provide an efficient and clean two-way communication channel between client and server.</t>
<t>The communication channel will: </t>

<t><list style="symbols">
<t>allow each side to, independently from the other, send data when is willing and ready to do it;</t>
</list></t>
<t><list style="symbols">
<t>rely on a single TCP connection for traffic in both the directions.</t>
</list></t>
<t><list style="symbols">
<t>reduce the high overhead produced by HTTP headers in each request/response.</t>
</list></t>

<t>The goal of this work is to provide the set of requirements the WebSocket Protocol MUST meet.</t>

<t>In the following sections we list and analyse the requirements from the perspective of clients and servers.</t>

</section>

<section title="Terminology">
<t>
In this document, the key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED",
"SHALL", "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT
RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" are to be interpreted as described
in BCP 14, <xref target="RFC2119">RFC 2119</xref> and indicate
requirement levels for compliant implementations.
</t>

<section title="HyBi Terminology">
<t>
   This document uses the following HyBi-related terms:</t>
   <t><list style="hanging">
   <t hangText="connection:">A transport layer virtual circuit established between a client and a server for the purpose of communication.</t><t></t>
   <t hangText="frame:">The basic unit of WebSocket communication, consisting of a structured sequence of octets matching the syntax defined in
      the actual protocol and transmitted on the established communication channel.</t><t></t>
   <t hangText="message:">user message: a block of related data with identified boundaries.</t><t></t>
   <t hangText="origin server:">The server on which a given resource resides or is to be created.</t><t></t>
   </list></t>
     


</section>
    

</section>


<section title="WebSocket Requirements"> 
<t>The following requirements fro WebSocket Protocol have been identified both in the HyBi wg input document <xref target="I-D.hixie-thewebsocketprotocol"/> 
   and in the HyBi mailing list dicussion.</t>
<t><list style="hanging">
<t hangText="REQ. 1:">The WebSocket Protocol MUST run directly on top of a transport protocol (e.g. TCP, UDP or SCTP, DCCP).</t><t></t>
<t hangText="REQ. 2:">The WebSocket Protocol MUST be able to handle (send and receive) messages on top of a TCP data stream connection.</t>
</list></t>
<t>Reason:  transfer data as message prevents the receiver to parse/handle partial content.
</t>
<t><list style="hanging">
<t hangText="REQ. 3:">It MUST be possible to sent a message when the total size is either unknown or exceeds a fixed buffer size.</t>
</list></t>
<t>Reason:  This will allow dynamic messages to be constructed  and sent without the need to buffer the entire message.</t>
<t><list style="hanging">
<t hangText="REQ. 4:">Textual data MUST be encoded as UTF-8.</t><t></t>
<t hangText="REQ. 5:">The protocol MUST be designed to support different frame types (e.g. binary).</t><t></t>
<t hangText="REQ. 6:">The WebSocket protocol MUST allow HTTP and WebSocket connections to be served from the same port. Consideration MUST be given:</t>
<t><list style="empty">
<t>* to provide WebSocket services via  modules that plug in to existing web infrastructure.</t><t></t>
<t>* to making it possible and practical to implement standalone implementations of the protocol  without requiring a fully conforming HTTP  implementation.</t>
</list></t>
<t></t>
</list></t>
<t>Reason: Some server developers would like to integrate WebSocket support into existing HTTP servers. In addition, the default HTTP and HTTPS ports are ofter 
favoured for traffic that has to go through a firewall, so service providers will likely want to be able to use WebSocket over ports 80 and 443, even when running a We server
on the same host. However there could be scenarios where it is not opportune or possible to setup a proxy on the same  HTTP server.
</t>
<t><list style="hanging">
<t hangText="REQ. 7:">When sharing host and "well known" port with HTTP, the WebSocket protocol MUST be HTTP compatible until both ends have established the WebSocket protocol.</t>
</list></t>
<t>Reason:  when operating on the standard HTTP ports, existing web infrastructure may handle according to existing standards prior to the establishment of the new protocol.
</t>
<t><list style="hanging">
<t hangText="REQ. 8:">The protocol SHOULD make it possible and practical to reuse existing HTTP components where appropriate.</t>
</list></t>
<t>Reason:  the re-usage of existing well-debugged software decreases the number of implementation errors as well as the possibility to introduce security holes especially and at the same time 
speed up the development especially when  the Web Socket server is implemented as modules that plug in to existing popular Web servers.
</t>

 

<section title="WebSocket Client Requirements"> 
<t><list style="hanging">
<t hangText="REQ. 9:">The WebSocket Client MUST be able to set up a communication channel sending to a WebSocket Server a well defined handshake.</t><t></t>
<t hangText="REQ. 10:">WebSocket Protocol MUST provide for graceful close of an active WebSocket connection on request from the user Application.</t>
</list></t>
<t>Reason: a clean shutdown signals that the other endpoint has definitely received all the messages sent prior the the close, so there is no protocol uncertainty 
   about what has been processed / what can be retried on another connection.</t>

<t><list style="hanging">
<t hangText="OPEN ISSUE:">WebSocket Protocol MUST also allow ungraceful close, either on request from the user application or as a result of a detected error condition.</t><t></t>
<t hangText="REQ. 11:">The WebSocket Client MUST be able to request the server, during the handshake, to use a specific WebSocket sub-protocol.</t><t></t>
<t hangText="REQ. 12:">The WebSocket Client MUST have the ability to send arbitrary text content to the server on the established communication channel, in the form of ordered discrete blocks.</t><t></t>
<t hangText="REQ. 13:">The WebSocket Client MUST have the ability to send arbitrary binary content to the server on the established communication channel, in the form of ordered discrete blocks.</t><t></t>
</list></t>
</section>


<section title="WebSocket Server Requirements"> 
<t><list style="hanging">
<t hangText="REQ. 14:">The WebSocket Server that accept to set up, with a WebSocket Client, a communication channel MUST send back to the WebSocket Client a well defined handshake.</t><t></t>
<t hangText="REQ. 15:">The WebSocket Server MUST have the ability to send arbitrary text content to the client on the established communication channel, in the form of ordered discrete blocks.</t><t></t>
<t hangText="REQ. 16:">The WebSocket Server MUST have the ability to send arbitrary binary content to the client on the established communication channel, in the form of ordered discrete blocks.</t><t></t>
</list></t>
</section>


<section title="WebSocket Proxies Requirements"> 
<t>Todo</t>
<t><list style="hanging">
</list></t>
</section>


<section title="WebSocket Security Requirements"> 
<t><list style="hanging">
<t hangText="REQ. 17:">The WebSocket Protocol MUST use the Origin-based security model commonly used by Web browsers to restrict which Web pages can contact
a WebSocket  sever when the WebSocket protocol is used from a Web page.</t><t></t>
<t hangText="REQ. 18:">When used directly (not from a Web page), the WebSocket Protocol MUST use an equivalent security model.</t><t></t>
<t hangText="REQ. 19:">WebSocket should be designed to be robust against cross-protocol attacks. The protocol design should consider and mitigate the risk presented by WebSocket clients to existing servers (including HTTP servers). 
It should also consider and mitigate the risk to WebSocket servers presented by clients for other protocols (including HTTP).</t>
</list></t>

<t>Reason: As the Web Socket protocol is expected to be mainly used in browsers, a careful design is necessary to mitigate the chances for hostile JavaScript to use WebSocket for a cross-protocol attack against vanilla HTTP resources or non-HTTP servers. More the design should prevent the possibility for cross-site XMLHttpRequest (using CORS or XDomainRequest) to be used for a cross-protocol attack against WebSocket resources, potentially violating integrity (though not confidentiality).</t>


</section>

</section>







<section title="Security Considerations">
<t>
</t>
</section>

<section title="IANA Considerations">
<t>This requirements document does not mandate any immediate IANA actions. However, such IANA considerations may arise from future
HyBi specification documents which try to meet the requirements given here.</t>
</section>


<section title="Acknowledgments">
<t>
The initial requirements were created by the HyBi chair Salvatore Loreto &lt;salvatore.loreto@ericsson.com&gt;.
</t>
</section>




</middle>


<back>

	<references title="Normative References">


		<?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119"?>
		<?rfc include="reference.RFC.2616"?>
                <?rfc include="reference.I-D.loreto-http-bidirectional"?>
                <?rfc include="reference.I-D.hixie-thewebsocketprotocol"?>

	</references>


</back>


</rfc>
