<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="6"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc autobreaks="no"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>

<rfc category="std" docName="draft-cui-netext-multihome-lr-00" ipr="trust200902">
    
<front>
  <title abbrev="Localized Routing for Multi-Home Mobile Node in PMIPv6">Localized Routing for Multi-Home Mobile Node in PMIPv6</title>

  <author fullname="Yong Cui" initials="Y." surname="Cui">
    <organization>Tsinghua University</organization>
    <address>
    <postal>
      <street>Department of Computer Science, Tsinghua University</street>
      <city>Beijing</city>
      <code>100084</code>
      <country>P.R.China</country>
    </postal>
    <phone>+86-10-6260-3059</phone>
    <email>yong@csnet1.cs.tsinghua.edu.cn</email>
    </address>
  </author>

  <author fullname="Xin Xu" initials="X." surname="Xu">
    <organization>Beijing University of Posts and Telecommunications</organization>
    <address>
    <postal>
      <street>Department of Computer Science, Tsinghua University</street>
      <city>Beijing</city>
      <code>100084</code>
      <country>P.R.China</country>
    </postal>
    <email>xuxin1988@gmail.com</email>
    </address>
  </author> 

  <author fullname="Wendong Wang" initials="WD" surname="Wang">
    <organization>Beijing University of Posts and Telecommunications</organization>
    <address>
    <postal>
      <street>Room 609, teaching building 3,BUPT</street>
      <city>Beijing</city>
      <code>100876</code>
      <country>P.R.China</country>
    </postal>
    <email>wdwang@bupt.edu.cn</email>
    </address>
  </author>
  
  <author fullname="GuoYan Liu" initials="GY." surname="Liu">
    <organization>ZTE Corporation</organization>
    <address>
    <postal>
      <street>No.68 Zijinghua Rd.,Yuhuatai District</street>
      <city>Nanjing</city>
      <code>210012</code>
      <country>P.R.China</country>
    </postal>
    <email>liu.guoyan@zte.com.cn</email>
    </address>
  </author> 
  
    <author fullname="ChunHui Zhu" initials="CH." surname="Zhu">
    <organization>ZTE Corporation</organization>
    <address>
    <postal>
      <street>No.68 Zijinghua Rd.,Yuhuatai District</street>
      <city>Nanjing</city>
      <code>210012</code>
      <country>P.R.China</country>
    </postal>
    <email>zhu.chunhui@zte.com.cn</email>
    </address>
  </author>
  
     <author fullname="Na Zhou" initials="N." surname="Zhou">
    <organization>ZTE Corporation</organization>
    <address>
    <postal>
      <street>No.68 Zijinghua Rd.,Yuhuatai District</street>
      <city>Nanjing</city>
      <code>210012</code>
      <country>P.R.China</country>
    </postal>
    <email>zhou.na@zte.com.cn</email>
    </address>
  </author>

  <date year="2013"/>

  <workgroup>NETEXT Working Group</workgroup>

  <abstract>
  <t>In basic PMIPv6<xref target="RFC5213"/>, Local Mobility Anchor (LMA) should forward all 
	 traffic for the registered MN. Localized Routing (LR) for PMIPv6 
	 proposed in [RFC6705] allows MN to exchange data directly by using 
	 localized forwarding or tunnel between the MAGs. But in some 
	 multi-access scenarios, it is apparently suboptimal. The present 
	 document proposes two localized routing mechanisms that are 
	 compatible with RFC 6705 for multi-access MNs which have some 
	 interfaces attached to the same MAGs.
  </t>
  </abstract>
</front>

<middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
	<t>With the development of internet access technologies and mobile 
	   terminal equipment, more and more hosts are operating in multiple 
	   network interfaces, the situation that a terminal access to 
	   multiple heterogeneous network domains simultaneously has become 
	   more widespread.
	</t>
	
	<t>PMIPv6 is a protocol to provide IP mobility without MN participation. 
	<xref target="RFC5213"/> proposes three kinds of Localized Routing schemes which allow 
	MNs to route traffic by using localized forwarding or creating a direct 
	tunnel between MAGs to improve routing and reduce the load of LMA. Those 
	three Localized Routing schemes are focus on Single-access scenario, 
	as for Multiple-access scenario those schemes may be suboptimal.
	</t>
	
	<t>This document develops the mechanisms of RFC6705, and proposes two 
	other localized routing mechanisms which are compatible with RFC 6705 
	for multi-access MNs Attached to the same MAGs with some interfaces. 
	The mentioned mechanisms optimize the traffic transport among the 
	interfaces attached to the same MAG; consequently, reduce transport 
	costs and traffic loads at the network side.
	</t>
    </section>

    <section title = "Requirements Language">   
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
      document are to be interpreted as described in <xref target="RFC2119">
      </xref>.</t>  
    </section>

    <section title="Scenario">
      <t>In this scenario, at least one of the two Mobile Nodes involved in 
	  communication has multiple interface access in PMIPv6 domain, and both 
	  of the two MNs have interfaces attached to the same MAG, as shown in 
	  Figure 1.  Both MN1 and MN2 access to PMIPv6 domain via two interfaces, 
	  both MN1-IF1 and MN2-IF1 are attached to MAG1. We assume MN implements 
	  logical interface as defined in<xref target="I-D.ietf-netext-logical-interface-support"/>, 
	  so that MN can adjust the uplink traffic sending interface according 
	  to the interface that the downlink traffic was received.</t>
	  
	     <figure anchor="table_ex0" title="">
        <artwork><![CDATA[

                          +----------+
                          |   LMA    |
		                  +----------+
			                   |
			                   |
                          +----------+
                          |  Router  |
			              +----------+
                          /    |    \
                         /     |     \
                        /      |      \
                       /       |       \
            +----------+  +---------+  +----------+
            |   MAG2   |  |   MAG1  |  |    MAG3  |
            +----------+  +---------+  +----------+
                  \          /   \           /
                   \        /     \         /
                    \      /       \       /
                 IF2 |    | IF1 IF1 |     | IF2
                 +-----------+     +-----------+
                 |    MN1    |     |    MN2    |
	             +-----------+     +-----------+

         ]]></artwork>
    </figure>
	  <section title="Case 1">
	  <t>The LMA initiates a localized routing session by detecting 
	  both of the transport interfaces attached to the MAG that not 
	  connect with Correspondent nodes. For example the traffic that is 
	  transported between MN1-IF2 and MN2-IF2 in Figure 1. The  
	  Localized Routing for Multiple-Access Mobile Node is illustrated 
	  in Figure 2
	  </t>
	  
	  <figure anchor="table_ex1" title="Case 1 - Signaling Call Flow">
        <artwork><![CDATA[

     +-----+   +-----+   +-- ---+  +------+   +------+    +------+
     | MN1 |   | MN2 |   | MAG1 |  | MAG2 |   | MAG3 |    | LMA  |
     +-----+   +-----+   +------+  +------+   +------+    +------+
     IF1 IF2   IF1 IF2       |         |          |            |
      |   |     |   |        |         |          |            |
	  |   |<------------data --------->|<--------data--------->|
	  |   |     |   |<------------data----------->|<---data--->|
	  |   |     |   |        |         |          |     +-----------+
	  |   |     |   |        |         |          |     |LR decision|
	  |   |     |   |        |         |          |     +-----------+
	  |   |     |   |        |<---------LRI(Opt1)--------------|
	  |   |     |   |        |         |<-----LRI(Opt2)--------|
	  |   |     |   |        |         |          |<-LRI(Opt3)-|
	  |   |     |   |        |----------LRA(Opt4)------------->|
	  |   |     |   |        |         |------LTA(Opt5)------->|
	  |   |     |   |        |         |          |-LRA(Opt6)->|
	  |   |--------------data--------->|          |            |
	  |   |     |<---data----|<--data--|          |            |
	  |   |     |   |------------data------------>|            |
	  |<----data-------------|<-----------data----|            |
	 +------+ +------+       |         |          |            |
	 |update| |update|       |         |          |            |
	 +------+ +------+       |         |          |            |
	  |   |     |<---data--->|         |          |            |
	  |<-----data----------->|         |          |            |
	  Opt1:MN1-ID, MN1-HNP1, MN1-HNP2, MN2-ID, MN2-HNP1, MN2-HNP2
	  Opt2:MN1-ID, MN1-HNP2, MAG1-IPv6-Address
	  Opt3:MN2-ID, MN2-HNP2, MAG1-IPv6-Address
      Opt4:U=0, MN1-ID, MN1-HNP1, MN1-HNP2, MN2-ID, MN2-HNP1, MN2-HNP2
	  Opt5:U=0, MN1-ID, MN1-HNP1, MAG1-IPv6-Address
	  Opt6:U=0, MN2-ID, MN2-HNP2, MAG1-IPv6-Address
         ]]></artwork>
    </figure>
	  
	  <t>LMA construct three LRI messages which are used to signal the 
	  intent of initiating localized routing. As for the two LRIs sent 
	  to the MAGs(MAG2, MAG3) connect with the interface that the session 
	  transports on. it contains the Home Network Prefix(HNP) and 
	  MN-Identifier(MN-ID) of the transport interfaces attached to the MAG, 
	  and Both LRIs contain the IP address of the objective MAG (MAG1) that 
	  both MNs attached to. As for the LRI sent to the objective MAG, it 
	  contains HNPs and MN-ID of the MNs involved.
	  </t>
	  
	  <t>After receiving the LRI message, MAG verifies the attachment status 
	  of the MNs by checking the binding cache. When MAG (MAG2 and MAG3) detects 
	  that the LRI contains MAG IP address option, it creates a local forwarding 
	  entry and forwards the session through a tunnel associated with the remote 
	  MAG. When the MAG detects that the LRI contains no MAG IP address option 
	  but MN-ID option and a HNP option, it just updates the local route policy 
	  and forwards the session to the associated MNs. For example MAG1 forwards the 
	  packets that its destination address Prefix contains MN1-HNP1 and MN1-HNP2 to 
	  MN1-IF1. When the local process is over, MAG sends an LRA message for responding 
	  the LRI. Then the packets sent from MN1 to MN2 will take the path of 
	  MN1-IF2->MAG2->MAG1->MN2-IF1, and the packets sent from MN2 to MN1 will take 
	  the path of MN2-IF2->MAG3->MAG1->MN1-IF1.
	  </t>
	  
	  <t>As MN received a session on a sub-interface different from the sub-interface 
	  that the session had sent, it treats this event as a flow mobility trigger 
	  signal from the network. Then MN updates the local router policy rules, so 
	  that the session's uplink was sent by the sub-interface that its downlink 
	  was received. So the transport path between MN1 and MN2 is MN1-IF1&#60;->MAG1&#60;->MN2-IF1.
	  </t>
	 </section>
	 
	 <section title="Case 2">
	 
	 	 <figure anchor="table_ex3" title="Case 2 - Signaling Call Flow">
        <artwork><![CDATA[

     +-----+  +-----+   +-- ---+   +------+    +------+    +------+
     | MN1 |  | MN2 |   | MAG1 |   | MAG2 |    | MAG3 |    | LMA  |
     +-----+  +-----+   +------+   +------+    +------+    +------+
     IF1 IF2  IF1 IF2       |          |           |           |
      |   |    |   |        |          |           |           |
	  |   |<---------- data ---------->|<---------data-------->|
	  |   |    |<---data--->|<-------------data--------------->|
	  |   |    |   |        |          |           |     +-----------+
	  |   |    |   |        |          |           |     |LR decision|
	  |   |    |   |        |          |           |     +-----------+
	  |   |    |   |        |<----------LRI(Opt1)--------------|
	  |   |    |   |        |-----------LRA(Opt2)------------->|
	  |   |------------ data---------->|----------data-------->|
	  |   |    |<--- data---|<-------------data----------------|
	  |   |    |----------->|          |           |           |
	  |<----data------------|          |           |           |
	 +------+  |   |        |          |           |           |
	 |update|  |   |        |          |           |           |
	 +------+  |   |        |          |           |           |
	  |   |    |<---data--->|          |           |           |
	  |<------data--------->|          |           |           |
	  Opt1:MN1-ID, MN1-HNP1, MN1-HNP2, MN2-ID, MN2-HNP1, MN2-HNP2
	  Opt2:U=0, MN1-ID, MN1-HNP1, MN1-HNP2, MN2-ID, MN2-HNP1, MN2-HNP2

         ]]></artwork>
    </figure>
	
	 <t> Assumed that there is a session between MN1-IF2 and MN2-IF1, after LMA 
	 decision, LMA just creates an LRI message to the objective MAG(MAG1) that 
	 both of MNs attached to as illustrated in Figure 3. The Options that included 
	 in this LRI are the same as the ones included in the LRI sent to objective 
	 MAG in case1.
	 </t>
	 
	 <t>When MAG1 receives the LRI, as in case1, MAG1 just updates the local route 
	 policy and forwards the packets to the associated MNs. the transport path 
	 from MN1 to MN2 remains unchanged, but the path from MN2 to MN1 changes, 
	 it directly forwards packets to the MNs by MAG1 without Traversing the LMA. 
	 It means that the transport from MN2 to MN will take the path of 
	 MN2-IF1->MAG1->MN1-IF1.
	 </t>
	 
	 <t>As case1, when MN1 identified the downlink session arriving on the sub-interface 
	 is changed, it updates the local router policy rules, and then the packets sent from 
	 MN1 to MN2 will take the path of MN1-IF1->MAG1->MN2-IF1.
	 </t>
	 
	 </section>
    </section>
	
	<section title="Security Considerations">
      <t>TBD</t>
    </section>
  
    <section title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>This document does not include an IANA request.</t>
    </section>
    


</middle>

<back>

  <references title="Normative References">
  	<?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119" ?>
     <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5213" ?>
     <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6705" ?>
	 <?rfc include="reference.I-D.ietf-netext-logical-interface-support" ?>
   
  </references>

</back>
</rfc>
