<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="rfc2629.xslt" ?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfcXXXX.dtd">

<rfc docName="draft-irtf-p2prg-alto-survey-01" category="info" ipr="trust200902">

<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc iprnotified="no" ?>
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?> 
<front>

  <title abbrev="ALTO Survey">
    A Survey on Research on the Application-Layer Traffic Optimization
    (ALTO) Problem
  </title>

  <author initials="I." surname="Rimac" fullname="Ivica Rimac">
    <organization>Bell Labs, Alcatel-Lucent</organization>
    <address>
      <email>rimac@bell-labs.com</email>
    </address>
  </author>

  <author initials="V." surname="Hilt" fullname="Volker Hilt">
    <organization>Bell Labs, Alcatel-Lucent</organization>
    <address>
      <email>volkerh@bell-labs.com</email>
    </address>
  </author>

  <author initials="M." surname="Tomsu" fullname="Marco Tomsu">
    <organization>Bell Labs, Alcatel-Lucent</organization>
    <address>
      <email>marco.tomsu@alcatel-lucent.com</email>
    </address>
  </author>

  <author initials="V." surname="Gurbani" fullname="Vijay K. Gurbani">
    <organization>Bell Labs, Alcatel-Lucent</organization>
    <address>
      <email>vkg@bell-labs.com</email>
    </address>
  </author>

  <author initials="E." surname="Marocco" fullname="Enrico Marocco">
    <organization>Telecom Italia</organization>
    <address>
      <email>enrico.marocco@telecomitalia.it</email>
    </address>
  </author>


  <date day="11" month="December" year="2009"/>

  <abstract>
    <t>
      A significant part of the Internet traffic today is generated by
      peer-to-peer (P2P) applications used traditionally for
      file-sharing, and more recently for real-time communications and
      live media streaming. Such applications discover a route to each
      other through an overlay network with little knowledge of the
      underlying network topology. As a result, they may choose peers
      based on information deduced from empirical measurements, which
      can lead to suboptimal choices. This document, a product of the
      P2P Research Group, presents a survey of existing literature on
      discovering and using network topology information for
      application-layer traffic optimization.
    </t>
  </abstract>

</front>

<middle>
  <section title="Introduction">
    <t>
      A significant part of today's Internet traffic is generated by
      peer-to-peer (P2P) applications, used originally for file
      sharing, and more recently for realtime multimedia
      communications and live media streaming.  P2P applications are
      posing serious challenges to the Internet infrastructure; by
      some estimates, P2P systems are so popular that they make up
      anywhere between 40% to 85% of the entire Internet traffic <xref
      target="Meeker"/>, <xref target="Karagiannis"/>, <xref
      target="LightReading"/>, <xref target="LinuxReviews"/>, <xref
      target="Parker"/>, <xref target="Glasner"/>.
    </t>
    <t>
      P2P systems ensure that popular content is replicated at
      multiple instances in the overlay.  But perhaps ironically, a
      peer searching for that content may ignore the topology of the
      latent overlay network and instead select among available
      instances based on information it deduces from empirical
      measurements, which, in some particular situations may lead to
      suboptimal choices.  For example, a shorter round-trip time
      estimation is not indicative of the bandwidth and reliability of
      the underlying links, which have more of an influence than delay
      for large file transfer P2P applications.
    </t>
    <t>
      Most distributed hash tables (DHT) -- the data structure that
      imposes a specific ordering for P2P overlays -- use greedy
      forwarding algorithms to reach their destination, making locally
      optimal decisions that may not turn to be globally optimized
      <xref target="Gummadi"/>.  This naturally leads to the
      Application-Layer Traffic Optimization (ALTO) problem <xref
      target="RFC5693"/>: how to best provide the topology of the
      underlying network while at the same time allowing the
      requesting node to use such information to effectively reach the
      node on which the content resides.  Thus, it would appear that
      P2P networks with their application layer routing strategies
      based on overlay topologies are in direct competition against
      the Internet routing and topology.
    </t>
    <t>
      One way to solve the ALTO problem is to build distributed
      application-level services for location and path selection <xref
      target="Francis"/>, <xref target="Ng"/>, <xref
      target="Dabek"/>, <xref target="Costa"/>, <xref
      target="Wong"/>, <xref target="Madhyastha"/>, in order to
      enable peers to estimate their position in the network and to
      efficiently select their neighbors.  Similar solutions have been
      embedded into P2P applications such as Azureus <xref
      target="Azureus"/>.  A slightly different approach is to have
      the Internet service provider (ISP) take a pro-active role in
      the routing of P2P application traffic; the means by which this
      can be achieved have been proposed <xref target="Aggarwal"/>,
      <xref target="Xie"/>, <xref target="Saucez"/>.
      There is an intrinsic struggle between the layers -- P2P overlay
      and network underlay -- when performing the same service
      (routing), however there are strategies to mitigate this
      dichotomy <xref target="Seetharaman"/>. 
    </t>
    <t>
      This document, initially intended as a complement to <xref
      target="RFC5693">RFC 5693</xref> and discussed during the
      creation of the IETF ALTO Working Group, has been completed and
      refined in the IRTF P2P Research Group.
    </t>
  </section>

  <section title="Survey of Existing Literature"
           anchor="survey">
    <t>
      Gummadi et al. <xref target="Gummadi"/> compare popular DHT
      algorithms and besides analyzing their resilience, provide an
      accurate evaluation of how well the logical overlay topology
      maps on the physical network layer.  In their paper, relying
      only on measurements independently performed by overlay nodes
      without the support of additional location information provided
      by external entities, they demonstrate that the most efficient
      algorithms in terms of resilience and proximity performance are
      those based on the simplest geometric concept (i.e. the ring
      geometry, rather than hypercubes, tree structures and butterfly
      networks).
    </t>
    <t>
      Regardless of the geometrical properties of the distributed data
      structures involved, interactions between application-layer
      overlays and the underlying networks are a rich area of
      investigation.  The available literature in this field can be
      taxonomixed in two categories (<xref target="taxonomy"/>): using
      application-level techniques to estimate topology and through
      some kind of layer cooperation.
    </t>

    <figure anchor="taxonomy">
      <artwork>

  Application-layer traffic optimization
    |
    +--> Application-level topology estimation
    |      |
    |      +--> Coordinates-based systems
    |      |      |
    |      |      +--> GNP
    |      |      |
    |      |      +--> Vivaldi
    |      |      |
    |      |      +--> PIC
    |      |
    |      +--> Path selection services
    |      |      |
    |      |      +--> IDMaps
    |      |      |
    |      |      +--> Meridian
    |      |      |
    |      |      +--> Ono
    |      |
    |      +--> Link-layer Internet maps
    |             |
    |             +--> iPlane
    |
    +--> Topology estimation through layer cooperation
           |
           +--> P4P: Provider portal for applications
           |
           +--> Oracle-based ISPs and P2P cooperation
           |
           +--> ISP-driven informed path selection

      </artwork>
      <postamble>
        Taxonomy of solutions for the application-layer traffic
        optimization problem.
      </postamble>
    </figure>

    <section title="Application-Level Topology Estimation"
             anchor="app-level">

      <t>
        Estimating network topology information on the application
        layer has been an area of active research. Early systems used
        triangulation techniques to bound the distance between two
        hosts using a common landmark host. In such a technique, given
        a cost function C, a set of vertexes V and their corresponding
        edges, the triangle inequality holds if for any triple {a, b,
        c} in V, C(a, c) is always less than or equal to C(a, g) +
        C(b, c). The cost function C could be expressed in terms of
        desirable metrics such as bandwidth or latency.
      </t>
      <t>
        We note that the techniques presented in this section are only
        representative of the sizable research in this area. Rather
        than trying to enumerate an exhaustive list, we have chosen
        certain techniques because they represent and advance in the
        area that further led to derivative works.
      </t>
      <t>
        Francis et al. proposed <xref
        target="Francis">IDMaps</xref>, a system where one or more
        special hosts called tracers are deployed near an autonomous
        system. The distance between hosts A and B is estimated as the
        cumulative distance between A and its nearest tracer Ta, plus
        the distance between B and its nearest tracer Tb, plus the
        shortest distance from Ta to Tb. To aid in scalability beyond
        that provided by the client-server design of IDMaps, Ng et
        al. proposed a P2P-based <xref target="Ng">global network
        positioning (GNP) architecture</xref>. GNP was a network
        coordinate system based on absolute coordinates computed from
        modeling the Internet as a geometric space. It proposed a
        two-part architecture: in the first part, a small set of
        finite distributed hosts called landmarks compute their own
        coordinates in a fixed geometric space. In the second part, a
        host wishing to participate computes its own coordinates
        relative to those of the landmark hosts. Thus, armed with the
        computed coordinates, hosts can then determine interhost
        distance as soon as they discover each other.
      </t>
      <t>
        Both IDMaps and GNP require fixed network infrastructure
        support in the form of tracers or landmark hosts; this often
        introduces a single point of failure and inhibits
        scalability. To combat this, new techniques were developed
        that embedded the network topology in a low-dimensional
        coordinate space to enable network distance estimation through
        vector analysis. Costa et al. introduced <xref
        target="Costa">Practical Internet Coordinates
        (PIC)</xref>. While PIC used the notion of landmark hosts, it
        did not require explicit network support to designate specific
        landmark hosts.  Any node whose coordinates have been computed
        could act as a landmark host.  When a node joined the system,
        it probed the network distance to some landmark hosts.  Then,
        it obtained the coordinates of each landmark host and computed
        its own coordinates relative to the landmark host, subject to
        the constraint of minimizing the error in the predicted
        distance and computed distance.
      </t>
      <t>
        Like PIC, <xref target="Dabek">Vivaldi</xref> proposed a
        fully distributed network coordinate systems without any
        distinguished hosts. Whenever a node A communicates with
        another node B, it measures the round trip time (RTT) to that
        node and learns that node's current coordinates.  A
        subsequently adjusts its coordinates such that it is closer
        to, or further from B by computing new coordinates that
        minimize the squared error.  A Vivaldi node is thus constantly
        adjusting it's position based on a simulation of
        interconnected mass springs.  Vivaldi is now being used in the
        popular P2P application Azureus and studies indicate that it
        scales well to very large networks <xref target="Ledlie"/>.
      </t>
      <t>
        Network coordinate systems require the embedding of the
        Internet topology into a coordinate system. This is not always
        possible without errors, which impacts the accuracy of
        distance estimations. In particular, it has proved to be
        difficult to embed the triangular inequalities found in
        Internet path distances <xref target="Ledlie"/>.  Thus,
        <xref target="Wong">Meridian</xref> abandons the generality
        of network coordinate systems and provides specific distance
        evaluation services.  In Meridian, each node keeps track of
        small fixed number of neighbors and organizes them in
        concentric rings, ordered by distance from the node.  Meridian
        locates the closest node by performing a multi-hop search
        where each hop exponentially reduces the distance to the
        target.  Although less general than virtual coordinates,
        Meridian incurs significantly less error for closest node
        discovery.
      </t>
      <t>
        The <xref target="Ono">Ono project</xref> takes a different
        approach and uses network measurements from
        content-distribution network (CDN) like Akamai to find nearby
        peers.  Used as a plugin to the Azureus BitTorrent client, Ono
        provides 31% average download rate improvement <xref
        target="Su"/>.
      </t>

      <texttable anchor="comptab">
        <preamble>
          Comparison of application-level topology estimation
          techniques, as reported in literature.  Results in terms of
          number of (D)imensions and (L)andmarks, 90th percentile
          relative error.
        </preamble>
        <ttcol>GNP vs. IDMaps(a) (7D, 15L)</ttcol>
        <ttcol>PIC(b) vs. GNP (8D, 16L)</ttcol>
        <ttcol>Vivaldi vs. GNP (2D, 32L)</ttcol>
        <ttcol>Meridian vs. GNP (8D, 15L)</ttcol>
        <c>GNP: 0.50, IDMaps: 0.97</c>
        <c>PIC: 0.38, GNP: 0.37</c>
        <c>Vivaldi: 0.65, GNP: 0.65</c>
        <c>Meridian: 0.78, GNP: 1.18</c>
        <postamble>
          (a) Does not use dimensions or landmarks. (b) Using results
          from the hybrid strategy for PIC.
        </postamble>
      </texttable>

      <t>
        <xref target="comptab"/> summarizes the application-level
        topology estimation techniques. The salient performance metric
        is the relative error. While all approaches define this metric
        a bit differently, it can be generalized as how close a
        predicted distance comes to the corresponding measured
        distance. A value of zero implies perfect prediction and a
        value of 1 implies that the predicted distance is in error by
        a factor of two.  PIC, Vivaldi, and Meridian compare their
        results with that of GNP, while GNP itself compares its
        results with a precursor technique, IDMaps. Because each of
        the techniques uses a different Internet topology and a
        varying number of landmarks and dimensions to interpret the
        data set, it is impossible to normalize the relative error
        across all techniques uniformly.  Thus we present the relative
        error data in pairs, as reported in the literature describing
        the specific technique. Readers are urged to compare the
        relative error performance in each column on its own and not
        draw any conclusions by comparing the data across columns.
      </t>



      <t>
        Most of the work on estimating topology information focuses on
        predicting network distance in terms of latency and does not
        provide estimates for other metrics such as throughput or
        packet loss rate.  However, for many P2P applications latency
        is not the most important performance metric and these
        applications could benefit from a richer information plane.
        Sophisticated methods of active network probing and passive
        traffic monitoring are generally very powerful and can
        generate network statistics indirectly related to performance
        measures of interest, such as delay and loss rate on
        link-level granularity.  Extraction of these hidden attributes
        can be achieved by applying statistical inference techniques
        developed in the field of inferential network monitoring or
        network tomography subsequent to sampling of the network
        state. Thus, network tomography enables the extraction of a
        richer set of topology information, but at the same time
        inherently increasing complexity of a potential information
        plane and introducing estimation errors.  For both active and
        passive methods statistical models for the measurement,
        process need to be developed and the spatial and temporal
        dependence of the measurements should be assessed.  Moreover,
        measurement methodology and statistical inference strategy
        must be considered jointly.  For a deeper discussion of
        network tomography and recent developments in the field we
        refer the reader to <xref target="Coates"/>.
      </t>
      <t>
        One system providing such a service is <xref
        target="Madhyastha">iPlane</xref>, which aims at creating a
        annotated atlas of the Internet that contains information
        about latency, bandwidth, capacity and loss rate.  To
        determine features of the Internet topology, iPlane bridges
        and builds upon different ideas, such as active probing based
        on packet dispersion techniques to infer available bandwidth
        along path segments.  These ideas are drawn from different
        fields, including network measurement as described by Dovrolis
        et al. in <xref target="Dovrolis"/> and <xref
        target="Coates">network tomography</xref>.
      </t>

    </section>
    <section title="Topology Estimation through Layer Cooperation">
      <t>
        Instead of estimating topology information on the application
        level through distributed measurements, this information could
        be provided by the entities running the physical networks --
        usually ISPs or network operators.  In fact, they have full
        knowledge of the topology of the networks they administer and,
        in order to avoid congestion on critical links, are interested
        in helping applications to optimize the traffic they generate.
        The remainder of this section briefly describes three recently
        proposed solutions that follow such an approach to address the
        ALTO problem.
      </t>
      <section title="P4P Architecture">
        <t>
          The architecture proposed by Xie et al. <xref
          target="Xie"/> have been adopted by the DCIA P4P working
          group <xref target="P4P"/>, an open group established by
          ISPs, P2P software distributors and technology researchers
          with the dual goal of defining mechanisms to accelerate
          content distribution and optimize utilization of network
          resources.
        </t>
        <t>
          The main role in the P4P architecture is played by servers
          called ``iTrackers'', deployed by network providers and
          accessed by P2P applications (or, in general, by elements of
          the P2P system) in order to make optimal decisions when
          selecting a peer to connect.  An iTracker may offer three
          interfaces:
          <list style="empty"><t></t></list>
          <list style="numbers">
            <t>
              Info: Allows P2P elements (e.g. peers or trackers) to
              get opaque information associated to an IP address.
              Such information is kept opaque to hide the actual
              network topology, but can be used to compute the network
              distance between IP addresses.
            </t>
            <t>
              Policy: Allows P2P elements to obtain policies and
              guidelines of the network, which specify how a network
              provider would like its networks to be utilized at a
              high level, regardless of P2P applications.
            </t>
            <t>
              Capability: Allows P2P elements to request network
              providers' capabilities.
            </t>
          </list>
        </t>
        <t>
          The P4P architecture is under evaluation with simulations,
          experiments on the PlanetLab distributed testbed and in
          field tests with real users.  Initial simulations and
          PlanetLab experiments results <xref target="P4P"/>
          indicate that improvements in BitTorrent download completion
          time and link utilization in the range of 50-70% are
          possible.  Results observed on Comcast's network during a
          field test trial conducted with a modified version of the
          software used by the Pando content delivery network
          (documented in <xref target="RFC5632">RFC 5632</xref>) show
          average improvements in download rate in different scenarios
          varying between 57% and 85%, and a 34% to 80% drop in the
          cross-domain traffic generated by such application.
        </t>
      </section>
      <section title="Oracle-based ISP-P2P Collaboration"
               anchor="oracle">
        <t>
          In the general solution proposed by Aggarwal et al. <xref
          target="Aggarwal"/>, network providers host servers,
          called "oracles", that help P2P users choose optimal
          neighbours.
        </t>
        <t>
          The mechanism is fairly simple: a P2P user sends the list of
          potential peers to the oracle hosted by its ISP, which ranks
          such a list based on its local policies.  For instance, the
          ISP can prefer peers within its network, to prevent traffic
          from leaving its network; further, it can pick higher
          bandwidth links, or peers that are geographically closer.
          Once the application has obtained an ordered list, it is up
          to it to establish connections with a number of peers it can
          individually choose, but it has enough information to
          perform an optimal choice.
        </t>
        <t>
          Such a solution has been evaluated with simulations and
          experiments run on the PlanetLab testbed and the results
          show both improvements in content download time and a
          reduction of overall P2P traffic, even when only a subset of
          the applications actually query the oracle to make their
          decisions.
        </t>
      </section>
      <section title="ISP-Driven Informed Path Selection (IDIPS)
                      Service">
        <t>
          The solution proposed by Saucez et al. <xref
          target="Saucez"/> is essentially a modified version of the
          oracle-based approach described in <xref target="oracle"/>,
          intended to provide a network-layer service for finding best
          source and destination addresses when establishing a
          connection between two endpoints in multi-homed environments
          (which are common in IPv6 networking). Peer selection
          optimization in P2P systems -- the ALTO problem in today's
          Internet -- can be addressed by the IDIPS solution as a
          specific sub-case where the options for the destination
          address consist of all the peers sharing a desired resource,
          while the choice of the source address is fixed. An
          evaluation performed on IDIPS shows that costs for both
          providing and accessing the service are negligible.
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section title="Application-Level Topology Estimation and the ALTO Problem">
    <t>
      The application-level techniques described in Section <xref
      target="app-level"/> provide tools for peer-to-peer applications
      to estimate parameters of the underlying network
      topology. Although these techniques can improve application
      performance, there are limitations of what can be achieved by
      operating only on the application level. 
    </t>
    <t>
      Topology estimation techniques use abstractions of the network
      topology which often hide features that would be of interest to
      the application. Network coordinate systems, for example, are
      unable to detect overlay paths shorter than the direct path in
      the Internet topology. However, these paths frequently exist in
      the Internet <xref target="Wang"/>. Similarly,
      application-level techniques may not accurately estimate
      topologies with multipath routing.
    </t>
    <t>
      When using network coordinates to estimate topology information
      the underlying assumption is that distance in terms of latency
      determines performance. However, for file sharing and content
      distribution applications there is more to performance than just
      the network latency between nodes. The utility of a long-lived
      data transfer is determined by the throughput of the underlying
      TCP protocol, which depends on the round-trip time as well as
      the loss rate experienced on the corresponding path <xref
      target="Padhye"/>. Hence, these applications benefit from a
      richer set of topology information that goes beyond latency
      including loss rate, capacity, available bandwidth.
    </t>
    <t>
      Some of the topology estimation techniques used by P2P
      applications need time to converge to a result. For example,
      current BitTorrent clients implement local, passive traffic
      measurements and a tit-for-tat bandwidth reciprocity mechanism
      to optimize peer selection at a local level. Peers eventually
      settle on a set of neighbors that maximizes their download rate
      but because peers cannot reason about the value of neighbors
      without actively exchanging data with them and the number of
      concurrent data transfers is limited (typically to 5-7),
      convergence is delayed and easily can be sub-optimal.
    </t>
    <t>
      Skype's P2P VoIP application chooses a relay node in cases where
      two peers are behind NATs and cannot connect directly. Ren et
      al. <xref target="Ren"/> measured that the relay selection
      mechanism of Skype is (1) not able to discover the best possible
      relay nodes in terms of minimum RTT (2) requires a long setup
      and stabilization time, which degrades the end user experience
      (3) is creating a non-negligible amount of overhead traffic due
      to probing a large number of nodes. They further showed that the
      quality of the relay paths could be improved when the underlying
      network AS topology is considered.
    </t>
    <t>
      Some features of the network topology are hard to infer through
      application-level techniques and it may not be possible to infer
      them at all. An example for such a features are service provider
      policies and preferences such as the state and cost associated
      with interdomain peering and transit links.  Another example is
      the traffic engineering policy of a service provider, which may
      counteract the routing objective of the overlay network leading
      to a poor overall performance <xref target="Seetharaman"/>.
    </t>
    <t>
      Finally, application-level techniques often require applications
      to perform measurements on the topology. These measurements
      create traffic overhead, in particular, if measurements are
      performed individually by all applications interested in
      estimating topology.
    </t>

  </section>

  <section title="Open Issues">

    <t>
      Beyond a significant of research work on the topic, we believe
      that there are sizable open issues to address in an
      infrastructure-based approach to traffic optimization.  The
      following is not an exhaustive list, but a representative sample
      of the pertinent issues.
    </t>

    <section title="Coordinate estimation or path latencies?">
      <t>
        Despite the many solutions that have been proposed for
        providing applications with topology information in a fully
        distributed manner, there is currently an ongoing debate in
        the research community whether such solutions should focus on
        estimating nodes' coordinates or path latencies.  Such a
        debate has recently been fed by studies showing that the
        triangle inequality on which coordinate systems are based is
        often proved false in the Internet <xref target="Ledlie"/>.
        Proposed systems following both approaches -- in particular,
        Vivaldi <xref target="Dabek"/> and PIC <xref
        target="Costa"/> following the former, Meridian <xref
        target="Wong"/> and iPlane <xref target="Madhyastha"/> the
        latter -- have been simulated, implemented and studied in
        real-world trials, each one showing different points of
        strength and weaknesses.  Concentrated work will be needed to
        determine which of the two solutions will be conducive to the
        {ALTO} problem.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section title="Malicious nodes">
      <t>
        Another open issue common in most distributed environments
        consisting of a large number of peers is the resistance
        against malicious nodes.  Security mechanisms to identify
        misbehavior are based on triangle inequality checks <xref
        target="Costa"/>, which however tend to fail and thus return
        false positives in presence of measurement inaccuracies
        induced, for example, by traffic fluctuations that occur quite
        often in large networks <xref target="Ledlie"/>.  Beyond the
        issue of using triangle inequality checks, authoritatively
        authenticating the identity of an oracle, and preventing an
        oracle from attacks are also important.  Exploration of
        existing techniques -- such as public key infrastructure or
        identity-based encryption for authenticating the identity and
        the use of secure multi-party computation techniques to
        prevent an oracle from collusion attacks -- need to be studied
        for judicious use in {ALTO}-type of solutions.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section title="Information integrity">
      <t>
        Similarly, even in controlled architectures deployed by
        network operators where system elements may be authenticated
        <xref target="Xie"/>, <xref target="Aggarwal"/>,<xref
        target="Saucez"/>, it is still possible that the information
        returned to applications is deliberately altered, for example,
        assigning higher priority to cheap (monetary-wise) links
        instead of neutrally applying proximity criteria.  What are
        the effects of such deliberate alterations if multiple peers
        collude to determine a different route to the target, one that
        is not provided by an oracle?  Similarly, what are the
        consequences if an oracle targets a particular node in another
        AS by redirecting an inordinate number of querying peers to it
        causing, essentially, a DDoS attack on the node?  Furthermore,
        does an oracle broadcast or multicast a response to a query?
        If so, techniques to protect the confidentiality of the
        multi-cast stream will need to be investigated to thwart
        ``free riding'' peers.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section title="Richness of topological information">
      <t>
        Many systems already use RTT to account for delay when
        establishing connections with peers (e.g., CAN, Bamboo).  An
        operator can provide not only the delay metric but other
        metrics that the peer cannot figure out on its own.  These
        metrics may include the characteristics of the access links to
        other peers, bandwidth available to peers (based on operator's
        engineering of its network), network policies, and preferences
        such as state and cost associated with intradomain peering
        links, and so on.  Exactly what kinds of metrics can an
        operator provide to stabilize the network throughput will also
        need to be investigated.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section title="Hybrid solutions">
      <t>
        It is conceivable that P2P users may not be comfortable with
        operator intervention to provide topology information.  To
        eliminate this intervention, alternative schemes to estimate
        topological distance can be used. For instance, Ono uses
        client redirections generated by Akamai CDN servers as an
        approximation for estimating distance to peers; Vivaldi, GNP
        and PIC use synthetic coordinate systems.  A neutral
        third-party can make available a hybrid layer cooperation
        service -- without the active participation of the ISP -- that
        uses alternative techniques discussed in <xref
        target="app-level"/> to create a toplogical map.  This map can
        be subsequently used by a subset of users who may not trust
        the ISP.
      </t>
    </section>

  </section>

  <section title="Security Considerations">
    <t>
      This draft is a survey of existing literature on topology
      estimation.  As such, it does not introduce any new security
      considerations to be taken in account beyond what is already
      discussed in each paper surveyed.
    </t>
  </section>

  <section title="Acknowledgments">
    <t>
      This document is a derivative work of a position paper submitted
      at the IETF RAI area/MIT workshop held on May 28th, 2008 on the
      topic of Peer-to-Peer Infrastructure (P2Pi). The article "A
      Survey of Research on the Application-Layer Traffic Optimization
      Problem and the Need for Layer Cooperation" appeared on IEEE
      Communications Magazine, Vol. 47, No. 8 was also partially
      derived from the same paper. The authors thank profusely the
      many people that have participated in discussions and provided
      insightful feedback at any stage of this work.
    </t>
  </section>

</middle>

<back>

  <references title="Informative References">

    <reference anchor="Meeker"
               target="http://www.morganstanley.com/institutional/techresearch/pdfs/
Webtwopto2006.pdf">
      <front>
        <title>
          The State of the Internet, Part 3
        </title>
        <author initials="M." surname="Meeker">
          <organization/>
        </author>
        <author initials="D." surname="Joseph">
          <organization/>
        </author>
      </front>
    </reference>

    <reference anchor="Karagiannis"
               target="">
      <front>
        <title>
          Is P2P dying or just hiding?
        </title>
        <author initials="T." surname="Karagiannis">
          <organization/>
        </author>
        <author initials="A." surname="Broido">
          <organization/>
        </author>
        <author initials="N." surname="Brownlee">
          <organization/>
        </author>
        <author initials="K. C." surname="Claffy">
          <organization/>
        </author>
        <author initials="M." surname="Faloutsos">
          <organization/>
        </author>
      </front>
    </reference>

    <reference anchor="LightReading"
               target="http://www.lightreading.com/document.asp?site=lightreading%26doc%20id=44435%26page%20number=3">
      <front>
        <title>
          Controlling P2P traffic
        </title>
        <author surname="LightReading">
          <organization/>
        </author>
      </front>
    </reference>

    <reference anchor="LinuxReviews"
               target="http://linuxreviews.org/news/2004/11/05 p2p/">
      <front>
        <title>
          Peer to peer network traffic may account for up to 85% of Internetâ??s bandwidth usage
        </title>
        <author surname="linuxReviews.org">
          <organization/>
        </author>
      </front>
    </reference>

    <reference anchor="Parker"
               target="http://www.cachelogic.com">
      <front>
        <title>
          The true picture of peer-to-peer filesharing
        </title>
        <author initials="A." surname="Parker">
          <organization/>
        </author>
      </front>
    </reference>

    <reference anchor="Glasner"
               target="http://www.wired.com/techbiz/media/news/2005/04/67202">
      <front>
        <title>
          P2P fuels global bandwidth binge
        </title>
        <author initials="J." surname="Glasner">
          <organization/>
        </author>
      </front>
    </reference>

    <reference anchor="Gummadi"
               target="">
      <front>
        <title>
          The impact of DHT routing geometry on resilience and proximity
        </title>
        <author initials="K." surname="Gummadi">
          <organization/>
        </author>
        <author initials="R." surname="Gummadi">
          <organization/>
        </author>
        <author initials="S." surname="Gribble">
          <organization/>
        </author>
        <author initials="S." surname="Ratnasamy">
          <organization/>
        </author>
        <author initials="S." surname="Shenker">
          <organization/>
        </author>
        <author initials="I." surname="Stoica">
          <organization/>
        </author>
      </front>
    </reference>

    <reference anchor="RFC5693">
      <front>
        <title>
          Application-Layer Traffic Optimization (ALTO) Problem
          Statement
        </title>
        <author initials="J." surname="Seedorf" fullname="J. Seedorf">
          <organization/>
        </author>
        <author initials="E." surname="Burger" fullname="E. Burger">
          <organization/>
        </author>
        <date year="2009" month="October"/>
      </front>
      <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="5693"/>
      <format type="TXT" octets="34234"
              target="ftp://ftp.isi.edu/in-notes/rfc5693.txt"/>
    </reference>

    <reference anchor="Francis"
               target="">
      <front>
        <title>
          IDMaps: A global Internet host distance estimation service
        </title>
        <author initials="P." surname="Francis">
          <organization/>
        </author>
        <author initials="S." surname="Jamin">
          <organization/>
        </author>
        <author initials="C." surname="Jin">
          <organization/>
        </author>
        <author initials="Y." surname="Jin">
          <organization/>
        </author>
        <author initials="D." surname="Raz">
          <organization/>
        </author>
        <author initials="Y." surname="Shavitt">
          <organization/>
        </author>
        <author initials="L." surname="Zhang">
          <organization/>
        </author>
      </front>
    </reference>

    <reference anchor="Ng"
               target="">
      <front>
        <title>
          Predicting internet network distance with coordinates-based approaches
        </title>
        <author initials="T. S. E." surname="Ng">
          <organization/>
        </author>
        <author initials="H." surname="Zhang">
          <organization/>
        </author>
     </front>
    </reference>

    <reference anchor="Dabek"
               target="">
      <front>
        <title>
          Vivaldi: A Decentralized Network Coordinate System
        </title>
        <author initials="F." surname="Dabek">
          <organization/>
        </author>
        <author initials="R." surname="Cox">
          <organization/>
        </author>
        <author initials="F." surname="Kaashoek">
          <organization/>
        </author>
        <author initials="R." surname="Morris">
          <organization/>
        </author>
      </front>
    </reference>

    <reference anchor="Costa"
               target="">
      <front>
        <title>
          PIC: Practical Internet coordinates for distance estimation
        </title>
        <author initials="M." surname="Costa">
          <organization/>
        </author>
        <author initials="M." surname="Castro">
          <organization/>
        </author>
        <author initials="A." surname="Rowstron">
          <organization/>
        </author>
        <author initials="P." surname="Key">
          <organization/>
        </author>
      </front>
    </reference>

    <reference anchor="Wong"
               target="">
      <front>
        <title>
          Meridian: A lightweight network location service without virtual coordinates
        </title>
        <author initials="B." surname="Wong">
          <organization/>
        </author>
        <author initials="A." surname="Slivkins">
          <organization/>
        </author>
        <author initials="E. G." surname="Sirer">
          <organization/>
        </author>
      </front>
    </reference>

    <reference anchor="Madhyastha"
               target="">
      <front>
        <title>
          iPlane: an information plane for distributed services
        </title>
        <author initials="H. V." surname="Madhyastha">
          <organization/>
        </author>
        <author initials="T." surname="Isdal">
          <organization/>
        </author>
        <author initials="M." surname="Piatek">
          <organization/>
        </author>
        <author initials="C." surname="Dixon">
          <organization/>
        </author>
        <author initials="T." surname="Anderson">
          <organization/>
        </author>
        <author initials="A." surname="Krishnamurthy">
          <organization/>
        </author>
        <author initials="A." surname="Venkataramani.">
          <organization/>
        </author>
      </front>
    </reference>

    <reference anchor="Azureus"
               target="http://www.azureus.com/">
      <front>
        <title>
           Azureus BitTorrent Client
        </title>
        <author initials="" surname="">
          <organization/>
        </author>
      </front>
    </reference>

    <reference anchor="Xie"
               target="http://www.dcia.info/documents/P4P Overview.pdf.">
      <front>
        <title>
          P4P: Explicit Communications for Cooperative Control Between P2P and Network Providers
        </title>
        <author initials="H." surname="Xie">
          <organization/>
        </author>
        <author initials="A." surname="Krishnamurthy">
          <organization/>
        </author>
        <author initials="A." surname="Silberschatz">
          <organization/>
        </author>
        <author initials="Y. R." surname="Yang">
          <organization/>
        </author>
      </front>
    </reference>

    <reference anchor="Aggarwal"
               target="">
      <front>
        <title>
          Can ISPs and P2P systems co-operate for improved performance?
        </title>
        <author initials="V." surname="Aggarwal">
          <organization/>
        </author>
        <author initials="A." surname="Feldmann">
          <organization/>
        </author>
        <author initials="C." surname="Scheidler">
          <organization/>
        </author>
      </front>
    </reference>

    <reference anchor="Seetharaman"
               target="">
      <front>
        <title>
          Preemptive Strategies to Improve Routing Performance of
          Native and Overlay Layers
        </title>
        <author initials="S." surname="Seetharaman">
          <organization/>
        </author>
        <author initials="V." surname="Hilt">
          <organization/>
        </author>
        <author initials="M." surname="Hofmann">
          <organization/>
        </author>
        <author initials="M." surname="Ammar">
          <organization/>
        </author>
      </front>
    </reference>

<!--
    <reference anchor="Pappas"
               target="">
      <front>
        <title>
          Coordinate-Based Routing for Overlay Networks
        </title>
        <author initials="V." surname="Pappas">
          <organization/>
        </author>
        <author initials="V." surname="Hilt">
          <organization/>
        </author>
        <author initials="M." surname="Hofmann">
          <organization/>
        </author>
      </front>
    </reference>
-->

    <reference anchor="Ledlie"
               target="">
      <front>
        <title>
          Network Coordinates in the Wild
        </title>
        <author initials="J." surname="Ledlie">
          <organization/>
        </author>
        <author initials="P." surname="Gardner">
          <organization/>
        </author>
        <author initials="M." surname="Seltzer">
          <organization/>
        </author>
      </front>
    </reference>

    <reference anchor="Ono"
               target="http://www.aqualab.cs.northwestern.edu/projects/Ono.html">
      <front>
        <title>
          Northwestern University Ono Project
        </title>
        <author initials="" surname="">
          <organization/>
        </author>
      </front>
    </reference>

    <reference anchor="Su"
               target="">
      <front>
        <title>
          Drafting behind Akamai (travelocity-based detouring)
        </title>
        <author initials="A.-J." surname="Su">
          <organization/>
        </author>
        <author initials="D. R." surname="Choffnes">
          <organization/>
        </author>
        <author initials="A." surname="Kuzmanovic">
          <organization/>
        </author>
        <author initials="F. E." surname="Bustamante">
          <organization/>
        </author>
      </front>
    </reference>

    <reference anchor="Wang"
               target="">
      <front>
        <title>
          Towards Network Triangle Inequality Violation Aware Distributed Systems
        </title>
        <author initials="G." surname="Wang">
          <organization/>
        </author>
        <author initials="B." surname="Zhang">
          <organization/>
        </author>
        <author initials="T. S. E." surname="Ng">
          <organization/>
        </author>
      </front>
    </reference>

    <reference anchor="Dovrolis"
               target="">
      <front>
        <title>
          What do packet dispersion techniques measure?
        </title>
        <author initials="C." surname="Dovrolis">
          <organization/>
        </author>
        <author initials="P." surname="Ramanathan">
          <organization/>
        </author>
        <author initials="D." surname="Moore">
          <organization/>
        </author>
      </front>
    </reference>

    <reference anchor="Coates"
               target="">
      <front>
        <title>
          Internet Tomography
        </title>
        <author initials="M." surname="Coates">
          <organization/>
        </author>
        <author initials="A." surname="Hero">
          <organization/>
        </author>
        <author initials="R." surname="Nowak">
          <organization/>
        </author>
        <author initials="B." surname="Yu">
          <organization/>
        </author>
      </front>
    </reference>

    <reference anchor="P4P"
               target="http://www.dcia.info/activities/#P4P.">
      <front>
        <title>
          DCIA P4P Working group
        </title>
        <author initials="" surname="">
          <organization/>
        </author>
      </front>
    </reference>

    <reference anchor="RFC5632">
      <front>
        <title>
          Comcast's ISP Experiences in a Proactive Network Provider
          Participation for P2P (P4P) Technical Trial
        </title>
        <author initials="C." surname="Griffiths" fullname="C. Griffiths">
          <organization/>
        </author>
        <author initials="J." surname="Livingood" fullname="J. Livingood">
          <organization/>
        </author>
        <author initials="L." surname="Popkin" fullname="L. Popkin">
          <organization/>
        </author>
        <author initials="R." surname="Woundy" fullname="R. Woundy">
          <organization/>
        </author>
        <author initials="Y." surname="Yang" fullname="Y. Yang">
          <organization/>
        </author>
        <date year="2009" month="September"/>
      </front>
      <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="5632"/>
      <format type="TXT" octets="27920"
              target="ftp://ftp.isi.edu/in-notes/rfc5632.txt"/>
    </reference>

    <reference anchor="Saucez"
               target="">
      <front>
        <title>
          Implementation and Preliminary Evaluation of an ISP-Driven Informed Path Selection
        </title>
        <author initials="D." surname="Saucez">
          <organization/>
        </author>
        <author initials="B." surname="Donnet">
          <organization/>
        </author>
        <author initials="O." surname="Bonaventure">
          <organization/>
        </author>
      </front>
    </reference>

    <reference anchor="Padhye"
               target="">
      <front>
        <title>
          Modeling TCP throughput: A simple model and its empirical validation
        </title>
        <author initials="J." surname="Padhye">
          <organization/>
        </author>
        <author initials="V." surname="Firoiu">
          <organization/>
        </author>
        <author initials="D." surname="Towsley">
          <organization/>
        </author>
        <author initials="J." surname="Kurose">
          <organization/>
        </author>
      </front>
    </reference>

    <reference anchor="Ren"
               target="">
      <front>
        <title>
          ASAP: An AS-aware peer-relay protocol for high quality VoIP
        </title>
        <author initials="S." surname="Ren">
          <organization/>
        </author>
        <author initials="L." surname="Guo">
          <organization/>
        </author>
        <author initials="X." surname="Zhang">
          <organization/>
        </author>
      </front>
    </reference>

  </references>
</back>

</rfc>

