<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY rfc2119 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc2629 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2629.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc6325 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6325.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc6326 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6326.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc6327 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6327.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc6361 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6361.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc4327 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4327.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc5246 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5246.xml">
]>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<?rfc strict="yes"?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="6"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<rfc category="std" docName="draft-mrw-trill-over-ip-02.txt" ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="TRILL over IP">Transparent Interconnection of Lots of Links
    (TRILL) over IP</title>

    <author fullname="Margaret Wasserman" initials="M." surname="Wasserman">
      <organization>Painless Security</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>356 Abbott Street</street>

          <city>North Andover</city>

          <region>MA</region>

          <code>01845</code>

          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>

        <phone>+1 781 405-7464</phone>

        <email>mrw@painless-security.com</email>

        <uri>http://www.painless-security.com</uri>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Donald Eastlake" initials="D." surname="Eastlake">
      <organization>Huawei R&amp;D USA</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>155 Beaver Street</street>

          <city>Milford</city>

          <region>MA</region>

          <code>01757</code>

          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>

        <phone>+1 508 333-2270</phone>

        <email>d3e3e3@gmail.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Dacheng Zhang" initials="D." surname="Zhang">
      <organization>Huawei Technologies</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Q14, Huawei Campus</street>

          <street>No.156 Beiqing Rd.</street>

          <city>Beijing</city>

          <region>Hai-Dian District</region>

          <code>100095</code>

          <country>P.R. China</country>
        </postal>

        <phone/>

        <email>zhangdacheng@huawei.com</email>

        <uri/>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date day="6" month="September" year="2012"/>

    <area>Internet</area>

    <abstract>
      <t>The Transparent Interconnection of Lots of Links (TRILL) protocol is
      implemented by devices called Routing Bridges (RBridges). TRILL supports
      both point-to-point and multi-access links and is designed so that a
      variety of link protocols can be used between RBridge ports. This
      document standardizes methods for encapsulating TRILL in UDP/IP(v4 or
      v6) to provide a unified TRILL campus.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Requirements Terminology">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
      document are to be interpreted as described in RFC 2119 <xref
      target="RFC2119"/>.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>RBridges are devices that implement the IETF TRILL protocol <xref
      target="RFC6325"/> <xref target="RFC6326"/> <xref
      target="RFC6327"/>.</t>

      <t>RBridges provide transparent forwarding of frames within an arbitrary
      network topology, using least cost paths for unicast traffic. They
      support VLANs and multipathing of unicast and multi-destination traffic.
      They use IS-IS link state routing and encapsulation with a hop count.
      The are compatible with IEEE 802.1 customer bridges, and can
      incrementally replace them.</t>

      <t>Two or more RBridges can communicate over a variety of different link
      types, such as Ethernet <xref target="RFC6325"/> or PPP <xref
      target="RFC6361"/>.</t>

      <t>This document defines a method for RBridges to communicate over
      UPD/IP(v4 or v6). TRILL over IP will allow remote, Internet-connected
      RBridges to form a single RBridge campus, or multiple TRILL over IP
      networks within a campus to be connected as a single TRILL campus via a
      TRILL over IP backbone.</t>

      <t>TRILL over IP connects RBridge ports using IPv4 or IPv6 as a
      transport in such a way that the ports appear to TRILL to be connected
      by a single link. The link will be a multi-access link if more than two
      RBridge ports are connected via a single TRILL over IP link, so that any
      pair of ports can communicate.</t>

      <t>To support cases where RBridges are connected via links (such as the
      public Internet) that are not under the same administrative control as
      the TRILL campus, this document specifies the use of Datagram Transport
      Layer Security (DTLS) <xref target="RFC4327"/> to secure communication
      between RBridges running TRILL over IP.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Use Cases for TRILL over IP">
      <t>In this document, we consider two use cases that are typical of
      situations where network administrators may choose to use TRILL over an
      IP network: a remote office scenario, and an IP backbone scenario.</t>

      <section title="Remote Office Scenario">
        <t>In the Remote Office Scenario, a remote TRILL network is connected
        to a TRILL campus across a multihop non-TRILL IP network, such as the
        public Internet. The TRILL network in the remote office becomes a
        logical part of TRILL campus, and nodes in the remote office can be
        attached to the same VLANs as local campus nodes. In many cases, a
        remote office may be attached to the TRILL campus by a single pair of
        RBridges, one on the campus end, and the other in the remote office.
        In this use case, the TRILL over IP link will often cross logical and
        physical IP networks that do not support TRILL, and are not under the
        same administrative control as the TRILL campus.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="IP Backbone Scenario">
        <t>In the IP Backbone Scenario, TRILL over IP is used to connect a
        number of TRILL networks to form a single TRILL campus. For example, a
        TRILL over IP backbone could be used to connect multiple TRILL
        networks on different floors of a large building, or to connect TRILL
        networks in separate buildings of a multi-building site. In this use
        case, there may often be several TRILL RBridges on a single TRILL over
        IP link, and the IP link(s) used by TRILL over IP are typically under
        the same administrative control as the rest of the TRILL campus.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Important Properties of the Scenarios">
        <t>There are a number of differences between the two scenarios listed
        above, some of which drive features of this specification. These
        differences are especially pertinent to the security requirements of
        the solution, how multicast data frames are handled, and how the
        RBridges discover each other.</t>

        <section title="Security Requirements">
          <t>In the IP Backbone Scenario, TRILL over IP is used between a
          number of RBridges, on a network link that is in the same
          administrative control as the remainder of the TRILL campus. While
          it is desirable in this scenario to prevent the association of rogue
          RBridges, this can be accomplished using existing IS-IS security
          mechanisms. There may be no need to protect the data traffic, beyond
          any protections that are already in place on the local network.</t>

          <t>In the Remote Office Scenario, TRILL over IP may run over a
          network that is not under the same administrative control as the
          TRILL network. Nodes on the network may think that they are sending
          traffic locally, while that traffic is actually being sent, in a
          UDP/IP tunnel, over the public Internet. It is necessary in this
          scenario to protect user privacy, as well as ensuring that no
          unauthorized RBridges can gain access to the RBridge campus. The
          data privacy requirement is addressed by the use of DTLS for both
          IS-IS frames and data frames between RBridges in this scenario.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Multicast Handling">
          <t>In the IP Backbone scenario, native mutlicast may be supported on
          the TRILL over IP link. If so, it will be used to send TRILL IS-IS
          and multicast data frames, as discussed later in this document.</t>

          <t>In the Remote Office Scenario, there will often be only one pair
          of RBridges connecting a given site, and even when multiple RBridges
          are used to connect a Remote Office to the TRILL campus, the
          intervening network may not provide reliable (or any) multicast
          connectivity. Also, it is difficult to provide strong data privacy
          for multicast traffic. For all of these reasons, the connections
          between local and remote RBridges will be treated like
          point-to-point links, and all TRILL IS-IS control messages and
          multicast data frames that are transmitted between the Remote Office
          and the TRILL campus will be serialized, as discussed later in this
          document.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="RBridge Discovery">
          <t>In the IP Backbone Scenario, RBridges that use TRILL over IP will
          use the normal TRILL IS-IS Hello mechanisms to discover the
          existence of other RBridges on the link <xref target="RFC6327"/>,
          and to establish authenticated communication with those
          RBridges.</t>

          <t>In the Remote Office Scenario, a DTLS session will need to be
          established between RBridges before TRILL IS-IS traffic can be
          exchanged, as discussed below. In this case, one of the RBRidges
          will need to be configured to establish a DTLS session with the
          other RBridge. This will typically be accomplished by configuring
          the RBridge at a Remote Office to initiate a DTLS session, and
          subsequent TRILL exchanges, with a TRILL over IP-enabled RBridge
          attached to the TRILL campus.</t>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="TRILL Frame Formats">
      <t>To support the TRILL base protocol standard <xref target="RFC6325"/>.
      , two types of frames will be transmitted between RBridges: TRILL Data
      frames and TRILL IS-IS frames.</t>

      <section title="TRILL Data Frame">
        <t>The on-the-wire form of a TRILL Data frame in transit between two
        neighboring RBridges is as shown below:</t>

        <figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[ 
	     
   +--------------+----------+----------------+-----------+
   | TRILL Data   |  TRILL   |  Encapsulated  |   Link    |
   | Link Header  |  Header  |  Native Frame  |  Trailer  |
   +--------------+----------+----------------+-----------+
             
	  ]]></artwork>
        </figure>

        <t>Where the Encapsulated Native Frame is in Ethernet frame format
        with a VLAN tag but with no trailing Frame Check Sequence (FCS).</t>
      </section>

      <section title="TRILL IS-IS Frame">
        <t>TRILL IS-IS frames are formatted on-the-wire as follows:</t>

        <figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[ 
	     
   +--------------+---------------+-----------+
   | TRILL IS-IS  |  TRILL IS-IS  |   Link    |
   | Link Header  |    Payload    |  Trailer  |
   +--------------+---------------+-----------+
             
	  ]]></artwork>
        </figure>

        <t>The Link Header and Link Trailer in these formats depend on the
        specific link technology. The Link Header usually contains one or more
        fields that distinguish TRILL Data from TRILL IS-IS. For example, over
        Ethernet, the TRILL Data Link Header ends with the TRILL Ethertype
        while the TRILL IS-IS Link Header ends with the L2-IS-IS Ethertype; on
        the other hand, over PPP, there are no Ethertypes but PPP protocol
        code points are included that distinguish TRILL Data from TRILL
        IS-IS.</t>

        <t>In TRILL over IP, we will use UDP/IP (v4 or v6) as the link header,
        and the TRILL frame type will be determined based on the UDP port
        number. In TRILL over IP, no Link Trailer is specified, although one
        may be added when the resulting IP packets are encapsulated for
        transmission on a network (e.g. Ethernet).</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Link Protocol Specifics">
      <t>TRILL Data packets can be unicast to a specific RBridge or multicast
      to all RBridges on the link. TRILL IS-IS packets are always multicast to
      all other RBridge on the link (except for TRILL IS-IS MTU PDUs, which
      may be unicast). On Ethernet links, the Ethernet multicast address
      All-RBridges is used for TRILL Data and All-IS-IS-RBridges for TRILL
      IS-IS.</t>

      <t>To properly handle TRILL base protocol frames on a TRILL over IP
      link, either native multicast mode must be enabled on that link, or
      multicast must be simulated using serial unicast, as discussed
      below.</t>

      <t>In TRILL Hello PDUs used on TRILL IP links, the IP addresses of the
      connected IP ports are their SNPA addresses. Thus, all TRILL Neighbor
      TLVs in such Hellos MUST specify that the size of the SNPA is 4-bytes
      for an IPv4 link or 16-bytes for an IPv6 link [rfc6326bis]. Note that
      SNPA addresses and their size are independent of TRILL System IDs which
      are 6-bytes.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Port Configuration">
      <t>Each RBridge port used for a TRILL over IP link MUST have at least
      one IP (v4 or v6) address. Implementations MAY allow a single physical
      port to operate as multiple IPv4 and/or IPv6 logical ports.</t>

      <t>TBD: MUST be able to configure list of IP addresses for serial
      unicast. MUST be able to configure non-standard IP multi-cast
      addresses.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="TRILL over UDP/IP Format">
      <t>The general format of a TRILL over UDP/IP packet is shown below.</t>

      <figure>
        <artwork><![CDATA[ 
	   
   +----------+--------+-----------------------+
   | IP       | UDP    |  TRILL                |
   | Header   | Header |  Payload              |
   +----------+--------+-----------------------+
           
	]]></artwork>
      </figure>

      <t>Where the UDP Header is as follows:</t>

      <figure>
        <artwork><![CDATA[ 
	   
   TBD
           
	]]></artwork>
      </figure>
    </section>

    <section title="Handling Multicast ">
      <t/>

      <section title="Multicast of TRILL IS-IS Packets">
        <t>By default, TRILL IS-IS packets are sent to an IPv4 multicast
        address.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Multicast Data Frames">
        <t>TBD</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Use of DTLS">
      <t>All RBridges that support TRILL over IP MUST implement DTLS and
      support the use of DTLS to secure both TRILL IS-IS and data traffic.
      When DTLS is used to secure a TRILL over IP link, the DTLS session MUST
      be fully established before any TRILL IS-IS or data frames are
      exchanged.</t>

      <t>RBridges that implement TRILL over IP MUST support the use of
      certificates for DTLS, and MUST support the following algorithm: <list
          style="symbols">
          <t>TLS_RSA_WITH_AES_128_CBC_SHA <xref target="RFC5246"/></t>
        </list></t>

      <t>RBridges that support TRILL over IP MAY support the use of pre-shared
      keys for DTLS. If the communicating RBridges have IS-IS authentication
      enabled with a pre-shared key, then that key may be used for DTLS unless
      some other pre-shared key is configured. If pre-shared keys are
      supported, the following cryptographic algorithms MUST be supported for
      use with pre-shared keys: <list style="symbols">
          <t>TLS_PSK_WITH_AES_128_CBC_SHA <xref target="RFC5246"/></t>
        </list></t>
    </section>

    <section title="Transport Considerations">
      <section title="Recursive Encapsulation">
        <t>TRILL is designed to transport end station Ethernet traffic and IP
        is frequently transported over Ethernet. Thus, an end station Ethernet
        frame EF might get TRILL encapsulated to TRILL(EF) which was then send
        on a TRILL over IP over Ethernet link resulting in an Ethernet frame
        of the form Ethernet(IP(TRILL(EF))). There is a risk of such an
        Ethernet frame being re-ingressed by the same TRILL campus, due to
        physical or logical misconfiguration, looping round, being further
        encapsulated and re-ingressed, etc. The frame might get discarded if
        it got too large but if fragmentation is enabled, it would just keep
        getting split into fragment that would continue to loop and grow and
        re-fragment until the path was saturated with junk and frames were
        being discarded due to queue overflow. TTL would provide no protection
        because each TRILL encapsulation adds a new TTL.</t>

        <t>To protect against this scenario, TRILL over IP output ports MUST
        be able to test whether a TRILL frame they are above to send is, in
        fact a TRILL encapsulation of a TRILL over IP over Ethernet frame.
        That is, is it of the form TRILL(Ethernet(IP(TRILL(&hellip;))). If so,
        the default action of the TRILL over IP output port is to discard the
        frame. However, there are cases where some level of multiple
        encapsulations is desired so it MUST be possible to configure the port
        to allow such frames.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="MTU Considerations">
      <t>In TRILL each RBridge advertises the largest LSP frame it can accept
      (but not less than 1,470 bytes) on any of its interfaces (at least those
      interfaces with adjacencies to other RBridges in the campus) in its LSP
      number zero through the originatingLSPBufferSize TLV [RFC6325]
      [rfc6326bis]. The campus minimum MTU, denoted Sz, is then established by
      taking the minimum of this advertised MTU for all RBridges in the
      campus. Links that do not meet the Sz MTU are not included in the
      routing topology. This protects the operation of IS-IS from links that
      would be unable to accommodate some LSPs.</t>

      <t>Exact methods of determining originatingLSPBufferSize for an RBridge
      with one or more TRILL over IP ports are beyond the scope of this
      document. However, if an IP link either can accommodate jumbo frames or
      is a link on which IP fragmentation is enabled and acceptable, then it
      is unlikely that the IP link will be a constraint on the RBridge&rsquo;s
      originatingLSPBufferSize. On the other hand, if the IP link can only
      handle smaller frames and fragmentation is to be avoided when possible,
      a TRILL over IP port might constrain the RBridge&rsquo;s
      originatingLSPBufferSize. Because TRILL sets the minimum values of Sz at
      1,470 bytes, there may be links that meet the minimum MTU for the IP
      protocol (1,280 bytes for IPv6, theoretically 68 bytes for IPv4) on
      which it would be necessary to enable fragmentation for TRILL use.</t>

      <t>The optional use of TRILL IS-IS MTU PDUs, as specified in [RFC6325]
      and [RFC6327] can provide added assurance of the actual MTU of a
      link.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Middlebox Considerations">
      <t>TBD</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Security Considerations">
      <t>TRILL over IP is subject to all of the security considerations for
      the base TRILL protocol. In addition, there are specific security
      requirements for different TRILL deployment scenarios, as discussed in
      the "Use Cases for TRILL over IP" section above.</t>

      <t>This document specifies that all RBridges that support TRILL over IP
      MUST implement DTLS, and makes it clear that it is both wise and good to
      use DTLS in all cases where a TRILL over IP link will traverse a network
      that is not under the same administrative control as the rest of the
      TRILL campus. DTLS is necessary, in these cases to protect the privacy
      and integrity of data traffic.</t>

      <t>TRILL over IP is completely compatible with the use of IS-IS
      security, which can be used to authenticte RBridges before allowing them
      to join a TRILL campus. This is sufficient to protect against rogue
      RBridges, but is not sufficient to protect data frames that may be sent,
      in UDP/IP tunnels, outside of the local network, or even across the
      public Internet. To protect the privacy and integrity of that traffic,
      use DTLS.</t>

      <t>In cases were DTLS is used, the use of IS-IS security may not be
      necessary, but there is nothing about this specification that would
      prevent using both DTLS and IS-IS security together. In cases where both
      types of security are enabled, implementations MAY allow users to
      configure a single shared key that will be used for both mechanisms.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>IANA has allocated the following UDP Ports for the TRILL IS-IS and
      Data channels:</t>

      <figure>
        <artwork><![CDATA[ 
	   
       UDP Port           Protocol

       (TBD)              TRILL IS-IS Channel           
       (TBD)              TRILL Data Channel
           
	]]></artwork>
      </figure>

      <t>IANA has allocated one IPv4 and one IPv6 multicast address, as shown
      below, which correspond to the All-RBridges and All-IS-IS-RBridges
      multicast MAC addresses that the IEEE Registration Authority has
      assigned for TRILL. Because the low level hardware MAC address dispatch
      considerations for TRILL over Ethernet do not apply to TRILL over IP,
      one IP multicast address for each version of IP is sufficient.</t>

      <t>[Values recommended to IANA:]</t>

      <figure>
        <artwork><![CDATA[ 
	   
      Name                 IPv4              IPv6

      All-RBridges         233.252.14.0      FF0X:0:0:0:0:0:0:205
           
	]]></artwork>
      </figure>

      <t>Note: when these IPv4 and IPv6 multicast addresses are used and the
      resulting IP frame is sent over Ethernet, the usual IP derived MAC
      address is used.</t>

      <t>[Need to discuss scopes for IPv6 multicast (the "X" in the addresses)
      somewhere. Default to "site" scope but MUST be configurable?]</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>This document was written using the xml2rfc tool described in RFC
      2629 <xref target="RFC2629"/>.</t>

      <t>The following people have provided useful feedback on the contents of
      this document: Sam Hartman.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      &rfc2119;

      &rfc6325;

      &rfc6326;

      &rfc6327;

      &rfc4327;

      &rfc5246;
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      &rfc2629;

      &rfc6361;
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
