<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629-fixed.xslt' ?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd"[



<!ENTITY rfc2119 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml'>

<!ENTITY rfc5378 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5378.xml'>

]>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="no"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<?rfc iprnotified="no" ?>
<?rfc strict="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc colonspace='yes' ?>
<rfc category="std" docName="draft-hain-ipv6-fwrh-03" ipr="pre5378Trust200902" obsoletes="" updates="" xml:lang="en" submissionType="IETF">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="IPv6 FWRH">IPv6 Firewall Routing Header</title>
    <author fullname="Tony Hain" initials="T." surname="Hain">
      <organization>Cisco Systems</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>500 108th Ave NE</street>
          <street></street>
          <city>Bellevue</city>
          <region>WA</region>
          <code>98004</code>
          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>
        <phone>+1 425 468-1061</phone>
        <email>alh-ietf@tndh.net</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date day="10" month="July" year="2010" />
    <abstract>
      <t>This document specifies a routing header for use by firewalls to enforce routing symmetry. </t>
      <t>The draft is being discussed on the ipv6@ietf.org list. </t>
    </abstract>
    <note title="Legal">
      <t>This documents and the information contained therein are provided on
      an "AS IS" basis and THE CONTRIBUTOR, THE ORGANIZATION HE/SHE REPRESENTS
      OR IS SPONSORED BY (IF ANY), THE INTERNET SOCIETY, THE IETF TRUST AND
      THE INTERNET ENGINEERING TASK FORCE DISCLAIM ALL WARRANTIES, EXPRESS OR
      IMPLIED, INCLUDING BUT NOT LIMITED TO ANY WARRANTY THAT THE USE OF THE
      INFORMATION THEREIN WILL NOT INFRINGE ANY RIGHTS OR ANY IMPLIED
      WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY OR FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.</t>
    </note>
  </front>
  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction" toc="default">
      <t>With the deprecation of RH0   <xref target="RFC5095" pageno="false" format="default"></xref>the ability of a node to influence traffic to traverse the same firewall in opposing directions was eliminated. Operation of stateful firewalls requires path symmetry at least through that device. The likelihood of asymmetry is particularly true on the Internet side, but is also a problem when the exit path changes on the private side during an established packet exchange. This document targets the specific use case of symmetric firewall selection, and then defines an IPv6 Firewall Routing Header and associated IPv6 ICMP error messages. Other use cases may take advantage of these mechanisms, but are explicitly out of scope for the development and definition here. Also, this option is not trying to solve every possible topology of firewall deployments, or source of asymmetry, but is should be useful for the most common existing deployments.</t>
      <t>While this Firewall Routing Header mechanism allows for changes in the firewalls in use during a packet exchange, any mechanisms that would be used to pass state between disperse firewalls is out of scope here. If those state passing mechanisms exist, it will be possible for an end-to-end packet exchange to persist during a routing shift, even over vast geographic path changes. Since the ability to force routing through a single intermediary can be used by attackers to receive traffic they otherwise would not, the ICMP error messages used here should be integrity protected, and in any event should be dropped if originating outside of a policy domain. The method that a node would use to verify that signature is out of scope here.</t>
    </section>
    <section title="Terminology" toc="default">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
      document are to be interpreted as described in <xref target="RFC2119" pageno="false" format="default">RFC 2119</xref>.</t>
    </section>
    <section title="Mechanisms" toc="default">
      <section title="Overview" toc="default">
        <t>To deal with the asymmetry issue, a function specific IPv6 routing header is defined, the Firewall Routing Header (FWRH). This routing header is used to pass information to a correspondent, so that return packets are routed through a firewall that is maintaining state for this transaction. In the case where an organization deploys multiple firewalls from different vendors in series to reduce vendor specific issues, this option would be related to the most public facing firewall of the set. A flag (Origin Flag) will be used to indicate which instance this is in the case where there are firewalls on each end (note: this assumes that a firewall would allow an initial inbound packet, then enforce subsequent packets through itself). There can be at most 2 (one with each value of the Origin Flag) FWRH's in any given extension header chain.</t>
        <t>An originating node is probably unaware of the presence of a firewall on its path to any given destination, so it will likely send an initial packet without the FWRH option. (It may have cached the value received in a prior ICMP error message for non-local prefixes, and if so can optimistically minimize the chance for an initial error by including the cached value in the optional FWRH.) On receipt of any ICMP Routing Header Required message, the origin node will extract the return-via address from the ICMP, optionally verify any signature that may be present, then cache it for use over the lifetime of the current packet exchange, and optionally for use with other non-local prefixes. The packet which generated the error is reconstructed with the appropriate FWRH option, and resent. If the FWRH option with the appropriate Origin Flag value is missing when a packet is being sent outbound (from the perspective of the firewall - private toward public), or if the return-via address in the FWRH option does not match any address on the firewall that is processing the packet, an ICMP error (RHR type ???) is returned to the source address of the packet, indicating the value that is expected to result in return-path symmetry through an interface on this specific firewall. That ICMP error SHOULD be signed, and if so the ICMP packet indicates which signing method was used. Outbound packets with the matching Origin Flag and return-via address will receive normal firewall handling before forwarding. If the source address prefix does not match any prefix that being exchanged in routing protocols with the next hop, an RPF-error (type ???+1) ICMP message should be returned.</t>
        <t>The correspondent node will extract the return-via address from a received FWRH option with an Origin Flag that is opposite the one it will use when sending, and cache it for use related to this specific packet exchange. When constructing packets related to this specific exchange; after all normal processing is complete, the ultimate destination address will be swapped into the FWRH with the appropriate Origin Flag, and the previously cached value from any received FWRH with the opposing Origin Flag will be swapped as the initial destination address of the packet.</t>
        <t>Inbound packets to the public side of a firewall will be addressed with it as the destination address of the base IPv6 header, and the FWRH with the Origin flag matching existing state will contain the address of the ultimate destination. The contents of the FWRH with the matching Origin flag will be swapped with the destination addresses in the packet, before normal firewall processing and forwarding.</t>
      </section>
      <section title="Firewall Routing Header Option" toc="default">
        <t>The Firewall Routing header is used by an IPv6 source to list a single intermediate node to be "visited" by returning packets.  The Firewall Routing header is identified by a Next Header value of 43 in the immediately preceding header, and has the following format:
</t>
        <figure title="" suppress-title="false" align="left" alt="" width="" height="">
          <artwork xml:space="preserve" name="" type="" align="left" alt="" width="" height="">
<![CDATA[
     0                   1                   2                   3
     0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
    |  Next Header  |  Hdr Ext Len  |  Routing Type |     Flags     |
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
    |                            Reserved                           |
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
    |                                                               |
    +                            Address                            +
    |                        return-via or                          |
    +                      ultimate destination                     +
    |                                                               |
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+

   Next Header	8-bit selector.  
	Identifies the type of header immediately following the 
	Routing header. Uses the same values as the IPv4 Protocol 
	field    [RFC-1700 et seq.].

   Hdr Ext Len	8-bit unsigned integer.  Length of the Routing
	header in 8-octet units, not including the first 8 octets.

   Routing Type	8-bit identifier of this particular Routing 
	header variant.

   Origin Flag	The Origin Flag (Flags - bit 0) 
	is used to indicate the direction that corresponds to 
	this instance of the FWRH. A value of 1 indicates 
	that a firewall exists in the initial packet direction 
	(for TCP this is the SYN), while a value of 0 indicates
	that a firewall exists in the response direction 
	(for TCP this is the SYN-ACK). 

   Reserved	32-bit reserved field.  
	Initialized to zero for transmission; ignored on reception.

   Address	Direction/location dependent address, 
	where from the origin node toward a correspondent it 
	contains the address of the firewall to be returned 
	through and from the correspondent to the intermediate
	firewall contains the ultimate destination address
	that the firewall will deliver the packet to.  
]]>
</artwork>
        </figure>
        <t>**** Within an enterprise network both FWRH options might contain the same address if there was an audit function, or traffic engineering reason to route both directions through the same mid-point.</t>
        <t>A FWRH option SHOULD NOT contain an address that matches either the source or destination addresses of the packet.  If there are two FWRH options present:
Their Origin Flag values MUST be different
Both options SHOULD NOT contain the same address</t>
      </section>
      <section title="Routing Header Required ICMP Message" toc="default">
        <t>Informing the originating endpoint that it needs to insert a routing header is accomplished with a specific ICMP error - 'Routing Header Required' (type ???).  This ICMP error may optionally be signed to mitigate a man-in-the-middle attack vector which could be used to route all return-path traffic through an attacker's node. </t>
        <figure title="" suppress-title="false" align="left" alt="" width="" height="">
          <artwork xml:space="preserve" name="" type="" align="left" alt="" width="" height="">
<![CDATA[    0                   1                   2                   3
    0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |     Type      |     Code      |          Checksum             |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |                            Reserved                           |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |                                                               |
   +                                                               +
   |                     Return-Via  IPv6 address                  |
   +                                                               +
   |                                                               |
   +                                                               +
   |                                                               |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |     MAC-type      |              MAC-length                   |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |                                                               |
   +                                                               +
   |                 Message Authentication Code                   |
   +                                                               +
   |                                                               |
   +                                                               +

IPv6 Fields:

   Destination Address

                        Copied from the Source Address field of the 
                        invoking packet.

   ICMPv6 Fields:

   Type           ???? --- 5

   Code           0 - unsigned
		    1 - signed

   Reserved             32-bit reserved field.  Initialized to zero 
                        for transmission; ignored on reception.


   MAC-type       0 - unused
		    1 - HMAC-SHA1
		    2 - AES-CMAC
		    ...

   MAC-length    Length of the message authentication option

   MAC           Value of the message authenticator
]]>
</artwork>
        </figure>
        <t>The optional authentication covers the source and destination address of this specific packet exchange, plus the return-via address.</t>
      </section>
      <section title="***** This needs to be a separate Doc *****  ReturnPathForwarding ICMP Error Message" toc="default">
        <t>Informing the origin that the source prefix is not appropriate for the next hop as a symmetric return path.</t>
        <figure title="" suppress-title="false" align="left" alt="" width="" height="">
          <artwork xml:space="preserve" name="" type="" align="left" alt="" width="" height=""><![CDATA[    0                   1                   2                   3
    0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |     Type      |     Code      |          Checksum             |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |                         Prefix Length                         |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |                                                               |
   +                                                               +
   |                 Source Prefix for this Path                   |
   +                                                               +
   |                                                               |
   +                                                               +
   |                                                               |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |     MAC-type      |              MAC-length                   |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |                                                               |
   +                                                               +
   |                 Message Authentication Code                   |
   +                                                               +
   |                                                               |
   +                                                               +

IPv6 Fields:

   Destination Address

                        Copied from the Source Address field of the 
                        invoking packet.

   ICMPv6 Fields:

   Type           ???? --- 6

   Code           0 - unsigned
		    1 - signed

   Reserved             32-bit reserved field.  Initialized to zero 
                        for transmission; ignored on reception.


   MAC-type       0 - unused
		    1 - HMAC-SHA1
		    2 - AES-CMAC
		    ...

   MAC-length    Length of the message authentication option

   MAC           Value of the message authenticator
]]></artwork>
        </figure>
        <t>The optional authentication covers the source and destination address of this specific packet exchange, plus the return-via address.</t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section title="Examples" toc="default">
      <t>Example 1 - Single firewall connecting a private network to the Internet.</t>
      <figure anchor="fig-1" title="" suppress-title="false" align="left" alt="" width="" height="">
        <artwork xml:space="preserve" name="" type="" align="left" alt="" width="" height=""><![CDATA[       A	   FW1		   B 
       |__Private__|  |__Internet__|

Initial packet exchange sequence -
A   ->>		DST = B 
FW1 ICMP(5) <<-	DST = A : SRC = FW1(P) : value - FW1(I)
A   ->>		DST = B : FWRH(OF=1) = FW1(I)
B   <<-		DST = FW1(I) : FWRH(OF=1) = A
FW1 <<-		DST = A : FWRH(OF=1) = FW1(I) 
A   ->>		DST = B : FWRH(OF=1) = FW1(I)
B   <<-		DST = FW1(I) : FWRH(OF=1) = A
FW1 <<-		DST = A : FWRH(OF=1) = FW1(I) 
			...
]]></artwork>
      </figure>
      <t>In this case as node A attempts to connect to node B, FW1 rejects the first attempt with an error message informing that the FWRH is required.  The subsequent packet including the FWRH with Origin Flag set is forwarded by FW1 toward B. B sends the return packet to FW1, where the DST is swapped with the locator for A in the FWRH with the Origin Flag set.</t>
      <figure anchor="fig-2" title="" suppress-title="false" align="left" alt="" width="" height="">
        <artwork xml:space="preserve" name="" type="" align="left" alt="" width="" height=""><![CDATA[       A	   FW1		   B 
       |__Private__|  |__Internet__|
		   |               |
		   FW2 _ Internet _|

Initial packet exchange sequence -
A   ->>		DST = B 
FW1 ICMP(5) <<-	DST = A : SRC = FW1(P) : value - FW1(I)
A   ->>		DST = B : FWRH(OF=1) = FW1(I)
B   <<-		DST = FW1(I) : FWRH(OF=1) = A
FW1 <<-		DST = A : FWRH(OF=1) = FW1(I) 
	--- FW1 dies
A   ->>		DST = B : FWRH(OF=1) = FW1(I)
FW2 ICMP(5) <<-	DST = A : SRC = FW2(P) : value - FW2(I)
FW2 ICMP(6) <<-	DST = A : SRC = FW2(P) : value - /48 FW2(I)
A   ->>		DST = B : FWRH(OF=1) = FW2(I)
B   <<-		DST = FW2(I) : FWRH(OF=1) = A
FW2 <<-		DST = A : FWRH(OF=1) = FW1(I) 
			...]]></artwork>
      </figure>
      <t>This case is the same as above, except there is an alternate firewall available to A.  At some point after the connection is established, FW1 dies, and routing redirects packets to B through FW2. FW2 has acquired state from FW1, so the connection between A &amp; B does not have to be reset, but FW2 still rejects the next packet with an error message informing that the FWRH does not have the public address of FW2. The subsequent packet including the FWRH with Origin Flag set is forwarded by FW2 toward B. B sends the return packet to FW2, where the DST is swapped with the locator for A in the FWRH with the Origin Flag set. </t>
      <figure anchor="fig-3" title="" suppress-title="false" align="left" alt="" width="" height="">
        <artwork xml:space="preserve" name="" type="" align="left" alt="" width="" height=""><![CDATA[       A	   FW1		   FW2		 B 
       |__Private__|  |__Internet__| |__Private__|

Initial packet exchange sequence -
A   ->>		DST = B 
FW1 ICMP(5) <<-	DST = A : SRC = FW1(P) : value - FW1(I)
A   ->>		DST = B : FWRH(OF=1) = FW1(I)
FW2 ->>		(presumes that FW2 allows initial pkt without state)
B   <<-		DST = FW1(I) : FWRH(OF=1) = A
FW2 ICMP(5) ->>	DST = B : SRC = FW2(P) : value - FW2(I)
B   <<-		DST = FW1(I) : FWRH(OF=1) = A : FWRH(OF=0) = FW2(I)
FW1 <<-		DST = A : FWRH(OF=1) = FW1(I) : FWRH(OF=0) = FW2(I)
A   ->>		DST= FW2(I) : FWRH(OF=1) = FW1(I) : FWRH(OF=0) = B
FW2 ->>		DST = B : FWRH(OF=1) = FW1(I) : FWRH(OF=0) = FW2(I)
			...]]></artwork>
      </figure>
      <t>In this case there are firewalls at each end, and both require a FWRH.  The value of the Origin Flag identifies which FWRH option is associated with each firewall. Note that before forwarding to the private side of each firewall, the DST &amp; FWRH(OF=1) was swapped at FW1, while DST &amp; FWRH(OF=0) was swapped at FW2.</t>
    </section>
    <section title="IANA Considerations" toc="default">
      <t>This specification registers a Routing Header type &amp; two ICMP message types</t>
    </section>
    <section title="Security Considerations" toc="default">
      <t>A routing header is used to cause packets to traverse a specific node, and if used maliciously would allow an attacker to see all packets in an exchange.  The risk of this attack is minimized by filtering out any ICMP Routing Header Required and ICMP RPF-error messages that originate outside the policy domain, and/or signing &amp; verifying those ICMP error messages when generated internally.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="acks" title="Acknowledgements" toc="default">
      <t>The need to resolve routing symmetry for firewalls was initially championed by William Dixon, and discussed with many attendees at IETF 74. </t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="comments" title="Pending comments" toc="default">
      <t>It has been suggested the Origin Flag model will fail in simultaneous-open situations. Recommendation to change the OF to indicate src &lt; dst.  If that was done as a rule, there wouldn't need to be a flag.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>
  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <reference anchor="RFC2119">
        <front>
          <title abbrev="RFC Key Words">Key words for use in RFCs to Indicate
          Requirement Levels</title>
          <author fullname="Scott Bradner" initials="S." surname="Bradner">
            <organization>Harvard University</organization>
            <address>
              <postal>
                <street>1350 Mass. Ave.</street>
                <street>Cambridge</street>
                <street>MA 02138</street>
              </postal>
              <phone>- +1 617 495 3864</phone>
              <email>sob@harvard.edu</email>
            </address>
          </author>
          <date month="March" year="1997" />
          <area>General</area>
          <keyword>keyword</keyword>
          <abstract>
            <t>In many standards track documents several words are used to
            signify the requirements in the specification.  These words are
            often capitalized. This document defines these words as they
            should be interpreted in IETF documents. Authors who follow these
            guidelines should incorporate this phrase near the beginning of
            their document: <list style="empty"><t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL",
                "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and
                "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described
                in RFC 2119.</t></list></t>
            <t>Note that the force of these words is modified by the
            requirement level of the document in which they are used.</t>
          </abstract>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="BCP" value="14" />
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="2119" />
        <format octets="4723" target="ftp://ftp.isi.edu/in-notes/rfc2119.txt" type="TXT" />
        <format octets="17491" target="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/html/rfc2119.html" type="HTML" />
        <format octets="5777" target="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/xml/rfc2119.xml" type="XML" />
      </reference>
    </references>
    <references title="Informative References">
      <reference anchor="RFC5095">
        <front>
          <title abbrev="Deprecate RH0">Deprecation of Type 0 Routing Headers in IPv6
	</title>
          <author fullname="J. Abley" initials="J." surname="Abley">
            <organization>Afilias</organization>
            <address>
              <postal>
                <street>Suite 204, 4141 Yonge Street</street>
                <street>Toronto, ON, CA</street>
                <street>M2P 2A8</street>
              </postal>
              <phone>- +1 416 673 4176</phone>
              <email>jabley@ca.afilias.info</email>
            </address>
          </author>
          <date month="December" year="2007" />
          <area>Internet</area>
          <keyword>RH0</keyword>
          <abstract>
            <t>The functionality provided by IPv6's Type 0 Routing Header can be
   exploited in order to achieve traffic amplification over a remote
   path for the purposes of generating denial-of-service traffic.  This
   document updates the IPv6 specification to deprecate the use of IPv6
   Type 0 Routing Headers, in light of this security concern.
	    </t>
          </abstract>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="5095" />
        <format octets="4723" target="ftp://ftp.isi.edu/in-notes/rfc5095.txt" type="TXT" />
        <format octets="17491" target="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/html/rfc5095.html" type="HTML" />
        <format octets="5777" target="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/xml/rfc5095.xml" type="XML" />
      </reference>
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>