<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!-- This template is for creating an Internet Draft using xml2rfc,
     which is available here: http://xml.resource.org. -->
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!-- One method to get references from the online citation libraries.
     There has to be one entity for each item to be referenced. 
     An alternate method (rfc include) is described in the references. -->
]>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<!-- used by XSLT processors -->
<!-- For a complete list and description of processing instructions (PIs), 
     please see http://xml.resource.org/authoring/README.html. -->
<!-- Below are generally applicable Processing Instructions (PIs) that most I-Ds might want to use.
     (Here they are set differently than their defaults in xml2rfc v1.32) -->
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<!-- give errors regarding ID-nits and DTD validation -->
<!-- control the table of contents (ToC) -->
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<!-- generate a ToC -->
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<!-- the number of levels of subsections in ToC. default: 3 -->
<!-- control references -->
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<!-- use symbolic references tags, i.e, [RFC2119] instead of [1] -->
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<!-- sort the reference entries alphabetically -->
<!-- control vertical white space 
     (using these PIs as follows is recommended by the RFC Editor) -->
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<!-- do not start each main section on a new page -->
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<!-- keep one blank line between list items -->
<!-- end of list of popular I-D processing instructions -->
<rfc category="info" docName="draft-ietf-6man-udpzero-02" ipr="trust200902">
  <!--1 category values: std, bcp, info, exp, and historic
     ipr values: full3667, noModification3667, noDerivatives3667
     you can add the attributes updates="NNNN" and obsoletes="NNNN" 
     they will automatically be output with "(if approved)" -->

  <!-- ***** FRONT MATTER ***** -->

  <front>
    <!-- The abbreviated title is used in the page header - it is only necessary if the 
         full title is longer than 39 characters -->

    <title abbrev="">IPv6 UDP Checksum Considerations</title>

    <!-- add 'role="editor"' below for the editors if appropriate -->

    <!-- Another author who claims to be an editor -->

    <author fullname="Godred Fairhurst" initials="G." surname="Fairhurst">
      <organization>University of Aberdeen</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>School of Engineering</street>

          <!-- Reorder these if your country does things differently -->

          <city>Aberdeen, AB24 3UE</city>

          <region></region>

          <code></code>

          <country>Scotland, UK</country>
        </postal>

        <phone></phone>

        <email>gorry@erg.abdn.ac.uk</email>

        <uri>http://www.erg.abdn.ac.uk/users/gorry</uri>

        <!-- uri and facsimile elements may also be added -->
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Magnus Westerlund" initials="M" surname="Westerlund">
      <organization>Ericsson</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Farogatan 6</street>

          <city>Stockholm</city>

          <region></region>

          <code>SE-164 80</code>

          <country>Sweden</country>
        </postal>

        <phone>+46 8 719 0000</phone>

        <facsimile></facsimile>

        <email>magnus.westerlund@ericsson.com</email>

        <uri></uri>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date day="24" month="October" year="2010" />

    <!-- If the month and year are both specified and are the current ones, xml2rfc will fill 
         in the current day for you. If only the current year is specified, xml2rfc will fill 
	 in the current day and month for you. If the year is not the current one, it is 
	 necessary to specify at least a month (xml2rfc assumes day="1" if not specified for the 
	 purpose of calculating the expiry date).  With drafts it is normally sufficient to 
	 specify just the year. -->

    <!-- Meta-data Declarations -->

    <area>General</area>

    <workgroup>Internet Engineering Task Force</workgroup>

    <!-- WG name at the upperleft corner of the doc,
         IETF is fine for individual submissions.  
	 If this element is not present, the default is "Network Working Group",
         which is used by the RFC Editor as a nod to the history of the IETF. -->

    <keyword>template</keyword>

    <!-- Keywords will be incorporated into HTML output
         files in a meta tag but they have no effect on text or nroff
         output. If you submit your draft to the RFC Editor, the
         keywords will be used for the search engine. -->

    <abstract>
      <t>This document examines the role of the UDP transport checksum when
      used with IPv6, as defined in RFC2460. It presents a summary of the
      trade-offs for evaluating the safety of updating RFC 2460 to permit an
      IPv6 UDP endpoint to use a zero value in the checksum field as an
      indication that no checksum is present. This method is compared with
      some other possibilities. The document also describes the issues and
      design principles that need to be considered when UDP is used with IPv6
      to support tunnel encapsulations. It concludes that UDP with a zero
      checksum in IPv6 can safely be used for this purpose, provided that this
      usage is governed by a set of constraints.</t>

      <!--                      -->
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section anchor="sec-intro" title="Introduction">
      <t>The User Datagram Protocol (UDP) transport was defined by <xref
      target="RFC0768">RFC768</xref> for IPv4 <xref
      target="RFC0791">RFC791</xref> and is defined in <xref
      target="RFC2460">RFC2460</xref> for IPv6 hosts and routers. The UDP
      transport protocol has a minimal set of features. This limited set has
      enabled a wide range of applications to use UDP, but these application
      do need to provide many important transport functions on top of UDP. The
      <xref target="RFC5405">UDP Usage Guidelines</xref> provides overall
      guidance for application designers, including the use of UDP to support
      tunneling. The key difference between UDP usage with IPv4 and IPv6 is
      that IPv6 mandates use of the UDP checksum, i.e. a non-zero value, due
      to the lack of an IPv6 header checksum.</t>

      <t>The lack of a possibility to use UDP with a zero-checksum in IPv6 has
      been observed as a real problem for certain classes of application,
      primarily tunnel applications. This class of application has been
      deployed with a zero checksum using IPv4. The design of IPv6 raises
      different issues when considering the safety of using a zero checksum
      for UDP with IPv6. These issues can significantly affect applications,
      both when an endpoint is the intended user and when an innocent
      bystander (received by a different endpoint to that intended). The
      document examines these issues and compares the strengths and weaknesses
      of a number of proposed solutions. This analysis presents a set of
      issues that must be considered and mitigated to be able to safely deploy
      UDP with a zero checksum over IPv6. The provided comparison of methods
      is expected to also be useful when considering applications that have
      different goals from the ones that initiated the writing of this
      document, especially the use of already standardized methods.</t>

      <t>The analysis concludes that using UDP with a zero checksum is the
      best method of the proposed alternatives to meet the goals for certain
      tunnel applications. Unfortunately, this usage is expected to have some
      deployment issues related to middleboxes, limiting the usability more
      than desired in the currently deployed internet. However, this
      limitation will be largest initially and will reduce as updates for
      support of UDP zero checksum for IPv6 are provided to middleboxes. The
      document therefore derives a set of constraints required to ensure safe
      deployment of zero checksum in UDP. It also identifies some issues that
      require future consideration and possibly additional research.</t>

      <section title="Document Structure">
        <t><xref target="sec-intro"></xref> provides a background to key
        issues, and introduces the use of UDP as a tunnel transport
        protocol.</t>

        <t><xref target="sec-standards"></xref> describes a set of
        standards-track datagram transport protocols that may be used to
        support tunnels.</t>

        <t><xref target="Issues"></xref> discusses issues with a zero checksum
        in UDP for IPv6. It considers the impact of corruption, the need for
        validation of the path and when it is suitable to use a zero
        checksum.</t>

        <t><xref target="Proposal"></xref> evaluates a set of proposals to
        update the UDP transport behaviour and other alternatives intended to
        improve support for tunnel protocols. It focuses on a proposal to
        allow a zero checksum for this use-case with IPv6 and assess the
        trade-offs that would arise.</t>

        <t><xref target="sec-constraints"></xref> lists the constraints
        perceived for safe deployment of zero-checksum.</t>

        <t><xref target="sec-summary"></xref> provides the recommendations for
        standardization of zero-checksum with a summary of the findings and
        notes remaining issues needing future work .</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Background">
        <t>This section provides a background on topics relevant to the
        following discussion.</t>

        <section title="The Role of a Transport Endpoint">
          <t>An Internet transport endpoint should concern itself with the
          following issues:</t>

          <t><list style="symbols">
              <t>Protection of the endpoint transport state from unnecessary
              extra state (e.g. Invalid state from rogue packets).</t>

              <t>Protection of the endpoint transport state from corruption of
              internal state.</t>

              <t>Pre-filtering by the endpoint of erroneous data, to protect
              the transport from unnecessary processing and from corruption
              that it can not itself reject.</t>

              <t>Pre-filtering of incorrectly addressed destination packets,
              before responding to a source address.</t>
            </list></t>

          <t></t>
        </section>

        <section title="The UDP Checksum">
          <t>UDP, as defined in <xref target="RFC0768"></xref>, supports two
          checksum behaviours when used with IPv4. The normal behaviour is for
          the sender to calculate a checksum over a block of data that
          includes a pseudo header and the UDP datagram payload. The UDP
          header includes a 16-bit one's complement checksum that provides a
          statistical guarantee that the payload was not corrupted in transit.
          This also allows a receiver to verify that the endpoint was the
          intended destination of the datagram, because the transport pseudo
          header covers the IP addresses, port numbers, transport payload
          length, and Next Header/Protocol value corresponding to the UDP
          transport protocol <xref target="RFC1071"></xref>. The length field
          verifies that the datagram is not truncated or padded. The checksum
          therefore protects an application against receiving corrupted
          payload data in place of, or in addition to, the data that was sent.
          Although the IPv4 <xref target="RFC0768">UDP</xref> checksum may be
          disabled, applications are recommended to enable UDP checksums <xref
          target="RFC5405"></xref>.</t>

          <t>The network-layer fields that are validated by a transport
          checksum are:</t>

          <t><list style="symbols">
              <t>Endpoint IP source address (always included in the pseudo
              header of the checksum)</t>

              <t>Endpoint IP destination address (always included in the
              pseudo header of the checksum)</t>

              <t>Upper layer payload type (always included in the pseudo
              header of the checksum)</t>

              <t>IP length of payload (always included in the pseudo header of
              the checksum)</t>

              <t>Length of the network layer extension headers (i.e. by
              correct position of the checksum bytes)</t>
            </list></t>

          <t>The transport-layer fields that are validated by a transport
          checksum are:<list style="symbols">
              <t>Transport demultiplexing, i.e. ports (always included in the
              checksum)</t>

              <t>Transport payload size (always included in the checksum)</t>
            </list></t>

          <t>Transport endpoints also need to verify the correctness of
          reassembly of any fragmented datagram. For UDP, this is normally
          provided as a part of the integrity check. Disabling the IPv4
          checksum prevents this check. A lack of the UDP header and checksum
          in fragments can lead to issues in a translator or middlebox. For
          example, many IPv4 Network Address Translators, NATs, rely on port
          numbers to find the mappings, packet fragments do not carry port
          numbers, so fragments get dropped. <xref
          target="RFC2765">RFC2765</xref> provides some guidance on the
          processing of fragmented IPv4 UDP datagrams that do not carry a UDP
          checksum.</t>

          <t>IPv4 UDP checksum control is often a kernel-wide configuration
          control (e.g. In Linux and BSD), rather than a per socket call.
          There are also Networking Interface Cards (NICs) that automatically
          calculate <xref target="RFC0793">TCP </xref> and UDP checksums on
          transmission when a checksum of zero is sent to the NIC, using a
          method known as checksum offloading.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Differences between IPv6 and IPv4">
          <t>IPv6 does not provide a network-layer integrity check. The
          removal of the header checksum from the IPv6 specification released
          routers from a need to update a network-layer checksum for each
          router hop as the IPv6 Hop Count is changed (in contrast to the
          checksum update needed when an IPv4 router modifies the Time-To-Live
          (TTL)).</t>

          <t>The IP header checksum calculation was seen as redundant for most
          traffic (with UDP or TCP checksums enabled), and people wanted to
          avoid this extra processing. However, there was concern that the
          removal of the IP header checksum in IPv6 combined with a UDP
          checksum set to zero would lessen the protection of the
          source/destination IP addresses and result in a significant (a
          multiplier of ~32,000) increase in the number of times that a UDP
          packet was accidentally delivered to the wrong destination address
          and/or apparently sourced from the wrong source address. This would
          have had implications on the detectability of mis-delivery of a
          packet to an incorrect endpoint/socket, and the robustness of the
          Internet infrastructure. The use of the UDP checksum is therefore
          required <xref target="RFC2460"> </xref> when endpoint application s
          transmit UDP datagrams over IPv6.</t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section title="Use of UDP Tunnels ">
        <t>One increasingly popular use of UDP is as a tunneling protocol,
        where a tunnel endpoint encapsulates the packets of another protocol
        inside UDP datagrams and transmits them to another tunnel endpoint.
        Using UDP as a tunneling protocol is attractive when the payload
        protocol is not supported by the middleboxes that may exist along the
        path, because many middleboxes support transmission using UDP. In this
        use, the receiving endpoint decapsulates the UDP datagrams and
        forwards the original packets contained in the payload <xref
        target="RFC5405"></xref>. Tunnels establish virtual links that appear
        to directly connect locations that are distant in the physical
        Internet topology and can be used to create virtual (private)
        networks.</t>

        <section title="Motivation for new approaches">
          <t>A number of tunnel encapsulations deployed over IPv4 have used
          the UDP transport with a zero checksum. Users of these protocols
          expect a similar solution for IPv6.</t>

          <t>A number of tunnel protocols are also currently being defined
          (e.g. Automated Multicast Tunnels, <xref target="AMT">AMT</xref>,
          and the Locator/Identifier Separation Protocol, <xref
          target="LISP">LISP</xref>). These protocols have proposed an update
          to IPv6 UDP checksum processing. These tunnel protocols could
          benefit from simpler checksum processing for various reasons:<list
              style="symbols">
              <t>Reducing forwarding costs, motivated by redundancy present in
              the encapsulated packet header, since in tunnel encapsulations,
              payload integrity and length verification may be provided by
              higher layer encapsulations (often using the IPv4, UDP,
              UDP-Lite, or TCP checksums).</t>

              <t>Eliminating a need to access the entire packet when
              forwarding the packet by a tunnel endpoint.</t>

              <t>Enhancing ability to traverse middleboxes, especially Network
              Address Translators, NATs.</t>

              <t>A desire to use the port number space to enable
              load-sharing.</t>
            </list></t>
        </section>

        <section title="Reducing forwarding cost">
          <t>It is a common requirement to terminate a large number of tunnels
          on a single router/host. Processing per tunnel concerns both state
          (memory requirements) and per-packet processing costs.</t>

          <t>Automatic IP Multicast Without Explicit Tunnels, known as <xref
          target="AMT">AMT</xref> currently specifies UDP as the transport
          protocol for packets carrying tunneled IP multicast packets. The
          current specification for AMT requires that the UDP checksum in the
          outer packet header should be 0 (see Section 6.6). It argues that
          the computation of an additional checksum, when an inner packet is
          already adequately protected, is an unwarranted burden on nodes
          implementing lightweight tunneling protocols. The AMT protocol needs
          to replicate a multicast packet to each gateway tunnel. In this
          case, the outer IP addresses are different for each tunnel and
          therefore require a different pseudo header to be built for each UDP
          replicated encapsulation.</t>

          <t>The argument concerning redundant processing costs is valid
          regarding the integrity of a tunneled packet. In some architectures
          (e.g. PC-based routers), other mechanisms may also significantly
          reduce checksum processing costs: There are implementations that
          have optimised checksum processing algorithms, including the use of
          checksum-offloading. This processing is readily available for IPv4
          packets at high line rates. Such processing may be anticipated for
          IPv6 endpoints, allowing receivers to reject corrupted packets
          without further processing. However, there are certain classes of
          tunnel end-points where this off-loading is not available and
          unlikely to become available in the near future.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Need to inspect the entire packet">
          <t>The currently-deployed hardware in many routers uses a fast-path
          processing that only provides the first n bytes of a packet to the
          forwarding engine, where typically n &lt;= 128. This prevents fast
          processing of a transport checksum over an entire (large) packet.
          Hence the currently defined IPv6 UDP checksum is poorly suited to
          use within a router that is unable to access the entire packet and
          does not provide checksum-offloading. Thus enabling checksum
          calculation over the complete packet can impact router design,
          performance improvement, energy consumption and/or cost.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Interactions with middleboxes">
          <t>In IPv4, UDP-encapsulation may be desirable for NAT traversal,
          since UDP support is commonly provided. It is also necessary due to
          the almost ubiquitous deployment of IPv4 NATs. There has also been
          discussion of NAT for IPv6, although not for the same reason as in
          IPv4. If IPv6 NAT becomes a reality they hopefully do not present
          the same protocol issues as for IPv4. If NAT is defined for IPv6, it
          should take UDP zero checksum into consideration.</t>

          <t>The requirements for IPv6 firewall traversal are likely be to be
          similar to those for IPv4. In addition, it can be reasonably
          expected that a firewall conforming to RFC 2460 will not regard UDP
          datagrams with a zero checksum as valid packets. If an zero-checksum
          for UDP were to be allowed for IPv6, this would need firewalls to be
          updated before full utility of the change is available.</t>

          <t>It can be expected that UDP with zero-checksum will initially not
          have the same middlebox traversal characteristics as regular UDP.
          However, if standardized we can expect an improvement over time of
          the traversal capabilities. We also note that deployment of
          IPv6-capable middleboxes is still in its initial phases. Thus, it
          might be that the number of non-updated boxes quickly become a very
          small percentage of the deployed middleboxes.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Support for load balancing">
          <t>The UDP port number fields have been used as a basis to design
          load-balancing solutions for IPv4. This approach has also been
          leveraged for IPv6. An alternate method would be to utilise the IPv6
          Flow Label as basis for entropy for the load balancing. This would
          have the desirable effect of releasing IPv6 load-balancing devices
          from the need to assume semantics for the use of the transport port
          field and also works for all type of transport protocols. This use
          of the flow-label is consistent with the intended use, although
          further clarity may be needed to ensure the field can be
          consistently used for this purpose, (e.g. Equal-Cost Multi-Path
          routing, ECMP <xref target="ECMP"></xref>).</t>

          <t>Router vendors could be encouraged to start using the IPv6 Flow
          Label as a part of the flow hash, providing support for ECMP without
          requiring use of UDP. However, the method for populating the outer
          IPv6 header with a value for the flow label is not trivial: If the
          inner packet uses IPv6, then the flow label value could be copied to
          the outer packet header. However, many current end-points set the
          flow label to a zero value (thus no entropy). The ingress of a
          tunnel seeking to provide good entropy in the flow label field would
          therefore need to create a random flow label value and keep
          corresponding state, so that all packets that were associated with a
          flow would be consistently given the same flow label. Although
          possible, this complexity may not be desirable in a tunnel
          ingress.</t>

          <t>The end-to-end use of flow labels for load balancing is a
          long-term solution. Even if the usage of the flow label is
          clarified, there would be a transition time before a significant
          proportion of end-points start to assign a good quality flow label
          to the flows that they originate, with continued use of load
          balancing using the transport header fields until any widespread
          deployment is finally achieved.</t>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="sec-standards" title="Standards-Track Transports">
      <t>The IETF has defined a set of transport protocols that may be
      applicable for tunnels with IPv6. There are also a set of network layer
      encapsulation tunnels such as IP-in-IP and GRE. These already
      standardized solutions are discussed here prior to the issues, as
      background for the issue description and some comparison of where the
      issue may already occur.</t>

      <section title="UDP with Standard Checksum">
        <t><xref target="RFC0768">UDP</xref> with standard checksum behaviour
        is defined in RFC 2460 has already been discussed. UDP usage
        guidelines are provided in <xref target="RFC5405"></xref>.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="UDP-Lite">
        <t>UDP-Lite <xref target="RFC3828"></xref> offers an alternate
        transport to UDP, specified as a proposed standard, RFC 3828. A MIB is
        defined in RFC 5097 and unicast usage guidelines in <xref
        target="RFC5405"></xref>. There is at least one open source
        implementation as a part of the Linux kernel since version 2.6.20.</t>

        <t>UDP-Lite provides a checksum with optional partial coverage. When
        using this option, a datagram is divided into a sensitive part
        (covered by the checksum) and an insensitive part (not covered by the
        checksum). When the checksum covers the entire packet, UDP-Lite is
        fully equivalent with UDP. Errors/corruption in the insensitive part
        will not cause the datagram to be discarded by the transport layer at
        the receiving endpoint. A minor side-effect of using UDP-Lite is that
        this was specified for damage-tolerant payloads, and some link-layers
        may employ different link encapsulations when forwarding UDP-Lite
        segments (e.g. radio access bearers). Most link-layers will also cover
        the insensitive part by a strong layer 2 frame CRC.</t>

        <section title="Using UDP-Lite as a Tunnel Encapsulation">
          <t>Tunnel encapsulations can use UDP-Lite (e.g. Control And
          Provisioning of Wireless Access Points, CAPWAP <xref
          target="RFC5415"></xref>), since UDP-Lite provides a transport-layer
          checksum, including an IP pseudo header checksum, in IPv6, without
          the need for a router/middelbox to traverse the entire packet
          payload. This provides most of the delivery verifications and still
          keep the complexity of the checksumming operation low. UDP-Lite may
          set the length of checksum coverage on a per packet basis. This
          feature could be used if a tunnel protocol is designed to only
          verify delivery of the tunneled payload and uses full checksumming
          for control information.</t>

          <t>There is currently poor support for middlebox traversal using
          UDP-Lite, because UDP-Lite uses a different IPv6 network-layer Next
          Header value to that of UDP, and few middleboxes are able to
          interpret UDP-Lite and take appropriate actions when forwarding the
          packet. This makes UDP-Lite less suited to protocols needing general
          Internet support, until such time that UDP-Lite has achieved better
          support in middleboxes and end-points.</t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section title="General Tunnel Encapsulations">
        <t>The IETF has defined a set of tunneling protocols or network layer
        encapsulations, like IP-in-IP and GRE. These either do not include a
        checksum or use a checksum that is optional, since tunnel
        encapsulations are typically layered directly over the Internet layer
        (identified by the upper layer type in the IPv6 Next Header field) and
        are also not used as endpoint transport protocols. There is little
        chance of confusing a tunnel-encapsulated packet with other
        application data that could result in corruption of application state
        or data.</t>

        <t>From the end-to-end perspective, the principal difference is that
        the network-layer Next Header field identifies a separate transport,
        which reduces the probability that corruption could result in the
        packet being delivered to the wrong endpoint or application.
        Specifically, packets are only delivered to protocol modules that
        process a specific next header value. The next header field therefore
        provides a first-level check of correct demultiplexing. In contrast,
        the UDP port space is shared by many diverse applications and
        therefore UDP demultiplexing relies solely on the port numbers.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Issues" title="Issues Requiring Consideration">
      <t>This section evaluates issues around the proposal to update IPv6
      [RFC2460], to provide the option of using a UDP transport checksum set
      to zero. Some of the identified issues are shared with other protocols
      already in use.</t>

      <t>The decision by IPv6 to omit an integrity check at the network level
      has meant that the transport check was overloaded with many functions,
      including validating: <list style="symbols">
          <t>the endpoint address was not corrupted within a router - i.e. A
          packet was intended to be received by this destination and a wrong
          header has not been spliced to a different payload;</t>

          <t>that extension header processing is correctly delimited - i.e.
          The start of data has not been corrupted. In this case, reception of
          a valid next header value provides some protection;</t>

          <t>reassembly processing, when used;</t>

          <t>the length of the payload;</t>

          <t>the port values - i.e. The correct application receives the
          payload (applications should also check the expected use of source
          ports/addresses);</t>

          <t>the payload integrity.</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>In IPv4, the first four checks are performed using the IPv4 header
      checksum.</t>

      <t>In IPv6, these checks occur within the endpoint stack using the UDP
      checksum information. An IPv6 node also relies on the header information
      to determine whether to send an ICMPv6 error message <xref
      target="RFC4443"></xref> and to determine the node to which this is
      sent. Corrupted information may lead to misdelivery to an unintended
      application socket on an unexpected host.</t>

      <section title="Effect of packet modification in the network">
        <t>IP packets may be corrupted as they traverse an Internet path.
        Evidence has been presented <xref target="Sigcomm2000"></xref> to show
        that this was once an issue with IPv4 routers, and occasional
        corruption could result from bad internal router processing in routers
        or hosts. These errors are not detected by the strong frame checksums
        employed at the link-layer <xref target="RFC3819"></xref>. There is no
        current evidence that such cases are rare in the modern Internet, nor
        that they may not be applicable to IPv6. It therefore seems prudent
        not to relax this constraint. The emergence of low-end IPv6 routers
        and the proposed use of NAT with IPv6 further motivate the need to
        protect from this type of error.</t>

        <t>Corruption in the network may result in: <list style="symbols">
            <t>A datagram being mis-delivered to the wrong host/router or the
            wrong transport entity within an endpoint. Such a datagram needs
            to be discarded;</t>

            <t>A datagram payload being corrupted, but still delivered to the
            intended host/router transport entity. Such a datagram needs to be
            either discarded or correctly processed by an application that
            provides its own integrity checks;</t>

            <t>A datagram payload being truncated by corruption of the length
            field. Such a datagram needs to be discarded.</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>When a checksum is used, this significantly reduces the impact of
        errors, reducing the probability of undetected corruption of state
        (and data) on both the host stack and the applications using the
        transport service.</t>

        <t>The following sections examine the impact of modifying each of
        these header fields.</t>

        <section title="Corruption of the destination IP address">
          <t>An IP endpoint destination address could be modified in the
          network (e.g. corrupted by an error). This is not a concern for
          IPv4, because the IP header checksum will result in this packet
          being discarded by the receiving IP stack. Such modification in the
          network can not be detected at the network layer when using
          IPv6.</t>

          <t>There are two possible outcomes:</t>

          <t><list style="symbols">
              <t>Delivery to a destination address that is not in use (the
              packet will not be delivered, but could result in an error
              report);</t>

              <t>Delivery to a different destination address. This
              modification will normally be detected by the transport
              checksum, resulting in silent discard. Without this checksum,
              the packet would be passed to the endpoint port demultiplexing
              function. If an application is bound to the associated ports,
              the packet payload will be passed to the application (see the
              subsequent section on port processing).</t>
            </list></t>
        </section>

        <section title="Corruption of the source IP address">
          <t>This section examines what happens when the source address is
          corrupted in transit. This is not a concern in IPv4, because the IP
          header checksum will normally result in this packet being discarded
          by the receiving IP stack.</t>

          <t>Corruption of an IPv6 source address does not result in the IP
          packet being delivered to a different endpoint protocol or
          destination address. If only the source address is corrupted, the
          datagram will likely be processed in the intended context, although
          with erroneous origin information. The result will depend on the
          application or protocol that processes the packet. Some examples
          are:</t>

          <t><list style="symbols">
              <t>An application that requires a per-established context may
              disregard the datagram as invalid, or could map this to another
              context (if a context for the modified source address was
              already activated).</t>

              <t>A stateless application will process the datagram outside of
              any context, a simple example is the ECHO server, which will
              respond with a datagram directed to the modified source address.
              This would create unwanted additional processing load, and
              generate traffic to the modified endpoint address.</t>

              <t>Some datagram applications build state using the information
              from packet headers. A previously unused source address would
              result in receiver processing and the creation of unnecessary
              transport-layer state at the receiver. For example, Real Time
              Protocol (RTP) <xref target="RFC3550"></xref> flows commonly
              employ a source independent receiver port. State is created for
              each received flow. Reception of a datagram with a corrupted
              source address will therefore result in accumulation of
              unnecessary state in the RTP state machine, including collision
              detection and response (since the same synchronization source,
              SSRC, value will appear to arrive from multiple source IP
              addresses).</t>
            </list></t>

          <t>In general, the effect of corrupting the source address will
          depend upon the protocol that processes the packet and its
          robustness to this error. For the case where the packet is received
          by a tunnel endpoint, the tunnel application is expected to
          correctly handle a corrupted source address.</t>

          <t>The impact of source address modification is more difficult to
          quantify when the receiving application is not that originally
          intended and several fields have been modified in transit.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Corruption of Port Information">
          <t>This section describes what happens if one or both of the UDP
          port values are corrupted in transit. This can also happen with IPv4
          in the zero checksum case, but not when UDP checksums are enabled or
          with UDP-Lite. If the ports carried in the transport header of an
          IPv6 packet were corrupted in transit, packets may be delivered to
          the wrong process (on the intended machine) and/or responses or
          errors sent to the wrong application process (on the intended
          machine).</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Delivery to an unexpected port">
          <t>If one combines the corruption effects there is a number of
          potential outcomes when traffic arrives at an unexpected port. This
          section discusses these possibilities and their outcomes for a
          packet that does not use the UDP checksum validation:</t>

          <t><list style="symbols">
              <t>Delivery to a port that is not in use. The packet is
              discarded, but could generate an ICMPv6 message (e.g. port
              unreachable).</t>

              <t>It could be delivered to a different node that implements the
              same application, where the packet may be accepted, generating
              side-effects or accumulated state.</t>

              <t>It could be delivered to an application that does not
              implement the tunnel protocol, where the packet may be
              incorrectly parsed, and may be misinterpreted, generating
              side-effects or accumulated state.</t>
            </list></t>

          <t>The probability of each outcome depends on the statistical
          probability that the source address and the destination port of the
          datagram (the source port is not always used in UDP) match those of
          an existing connection. Unfortunately, such a match may be more
          likely for UDP than for connection-oriented transports,
          because:<list style="numbers">
              <t>There is no handshake prior to communication and no sequence
              numbers (as in TCP, DCCP, or SCTP). Together, this makes it hard
              to verify that an application is given only the data associated
              with a transport session.</t>

              <t>Applications writers often bind to wild-card values in
              endpoint identifiers and do not always validate correctness of
              datagrams they receive (guidance on this topic is provided in
              <xref target="RFC5405"></xref>).</t>
            </list>While these rules could, in principle, be revised to
          declare naive applications as "Historic". This remedy is not
          realistic: the transport owes it to the stack to do its best to
          reject bogus datagrams.</t>

          <t>If checksum coverage is suppressed, the application therefore
          needs to provide a method to detect and discard the unwanted data. A
          tunnel protocol would need to perform its own integrity checks on
          any control information if transported in UDP with zero-checksum. If
          the tunnel payload is another IP packet, the packets requiring
          checksums can be assumed to have their own checksums provided that
          the rate of corrupted packets is not significantly larger due to the
          tunnel encapsulation. If a tunnel transports other inner payloads
          that do not use IP, the assumptions of corruption detection for that
          particular protocol must be fulfilled, this may require an
          additional checksum/CRC and/or integrity protection &gt; of the
          payload and tunnel headers.</t>

          <t>A protocol using UDP zero-checksum can never assume that it is
          the only protocol using a zero checksum. Therefore, it needs to
          gracefully handle misdelivery. It must be robust to reception of
          malformed packets received on a listening port and expect that these
          packets may contain corrupted data or data associated with a
          completely different protocol.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Corruption of Fragmentation Information">
          <t>The fragmentation information in IPv6 employs a 32-bit identity
          field, compared to only a 16-bit filed in IPv4, a 13-bit fragment
          offset and a 1-bit flag, indicating if there are more fragments.
          Corruption of any of these field may result in one of two
          outcomes:</t>

          <t><list style="hanging">
              <t hangText="Reassembly failure: ">An error in the "More
              Fragments" field for the last fragment will for example result
              in the packet never being considered complete and will
              eventually be timed out and discarded. A corruption in the ID
              field will result in the fragment not being delivered to the
              intended context thus leaving the rest incomplete, unless that
              packet has been duplicated prior to corruption. The incomplete
              packet will eventually be timed out and discarded.</t>

              <t hangText="Erroneous reassembly:">The re-assemblied packet did
              not match the original packet. This can occur when the ID field
              of a fragment is corrupted, resulting in a fragment becoming
              associated with another packet and taking the place of another
              fragment. Corruption in the offset information can cause the
              fragment to be misaligned in the reassembly buffer, resulting in
              incorrect reassembly. Corruption can cause the packet to become
              shorter or longer, however completion of reassembly is much less
              probable, since this would requires consistent corruption of the
              IPv6 headers payload length field and the offset field. The
              possibility of mis-assembly requires the reassembling stack to
              provide strong checks that detect overlap or missing data, note
              however that this is not guaranteed and has recently been
              clarified in <xref target="RFC5722">"Handling of Overlapping
              IPv6 Fragments"</xref>.</t>
            </list>The erroneous reassembly of packets is a general concern
          and such packets should be discarded instead of being passed to
          higher layer processes. The primary detector of packet length
          changes is the IP payload length field, with a secondary check by
          the transport checksum. The Upper-Layer Packet length field included
          in the pseudo header assists in verifying correct reassembly, since
          the Internet checksum has a low probability of detecting insertion
          of data or overlap errors (due to misplacement of data).The checksum
          is also incapable of detecting insertion or removal of all zero-data
          that occurs in a multiple of a 16-bit chunk.</t>

          <t>The most significant risk of corruption results following
          mis-association of a fragment with a different packet. This risk can
          be significant, since the size of fragments is often the same (e.g.
          fragments resulting when the path MTU results in fragmentation of a
          larger packet, common when addition of a tunnel encapsulation header
          expands the size of a packet). Detection of this type of error
          requires a checksum or other integrity check of the headers and the
          payload. Such protection is anyway desirable for tunnel
          encapsulations using IPv4, since the small fragmentation ID can
          easily result in wrap-around <xref target="RFC4963"></xref>, this is
          especially the case for tunnels that perform flow aggregation <xref
          target="I-D.ietf-intarea-tunnels"></xref>.</t>

          <t>Tunnel fragmentation behavior matters. There can be outer or
          inner fragmentation <xref target="I-D.ietf-intarea-tunnels">"Tunnels
          in the Internet Architecture"</xref>. If there is inner
          fragmentation by the tunnel, the outer headers will never be
          fragmented and thus a zero-checksum in the outer header will not
          affect the reassembly process. When a tunnel performs outer header
          fragmentation, the tunnel egress needs to perform reassembly of the
          outer fragments into an inner packet. The inner packet is either a
          complete packet or a fragment. If it is a fragment, the destination
          endpoint of the fragment will perform reassembly of the received
          fragments. The complete packet or the reassembled fragments will
          then be processed according to the packet next header field. The
          receiver may only detect reassembly anomalies when it uses a
          protocol with a checksum. The larger the number of reassembly
          processes to which a packet has been subjected, the greater the
          probability of an error.</t>

          <t><list style="symbols">
              <t>An IP-in-IP tunnel that performs inner fragmentation has
              similar properties to a UDP tunnel with a zero-checksum that
              also performs inner fragmentation.</t>

              <t>An IP-in-IP tunnel that performs outer fragmentation has
              similar properties to a UDP tunnel with a zero checksum that
              performs outer fragmentation.</t>

              <t>A tunnel that performs outer fragmentation can result in a
              higher level of corruption due to both inner and outer
              fragmentation, enabling more chances for reassembly errors to
              occur.</t>

              <t>Recursive tunneling can result in fragmentation at more than
              one header level, even for inner fragmentation unless it goes to
              the inner most IP header.</t>

              <t>Unless there is verification at each reassembly the
              probability for undetected error will increase with the number
              of times fragmentation is recursively applied. Making IP-in-IP
              and UDP with zero checksum equal subject to this effect.</t>
            </list></t>

          <t>In conclusion fragmentation of packets with a zero-checksum does
          not worsen the situation compared to some other commonly used tunnel
          encapsulations. However, caution is needed for recursive tunneling
          without any additional verification at the different tunnel
          layers.</t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section title="Validating the network path">
        <t>IP transports designed for use in the general Internet should not
        assume specific path characteristics. Network protocols may reroute
        packets that change the set of routers and middleboxes along a path.
        Therefore transports such as TCP, SCTP and DCCP have been designed to
        negotiate protocol parameters, adapt to different network path
        characteristics, and receive feedback to verify that the current path
        is suited to the intended application. Applications using UDP and
        UDP-Lite need to provide their own mechanisms to confirm the validity
        of the current network path.</t>

        <t>The zero-checksum in UDP is explicitly disallowed in RFC2460. Thus
        it may be expected that any device on the path that has a reason to
        look beyond the IP header will consider such a packet as erroneous or
        illegal and may likely discard it, unless the device is updated to
        support a new behavior. A pair of end-points intending to use a new
        behavior will therefore not only need to ensure support at each
        end-point, but also that the path between them will deliver packets
        with the new behavior. This may require negotiation or an explicit
        mandate to use the new behavior by all nodes intended to use a new
        protocol.</t>

        <t>Support along the path between end points may be guaranteed in
        limited deployments by appropriate configuration. In general, it can
        be expected to take time for deployment of any updated behaviour to
        become ubiquitous. A sender will need to probe the path to verify the
        expected behavior. Path characteristics may change, and usage
        therefore should be robust and able to detect a failure of the path
        under normal usage and re-negotiate. This will require periodic
        validation of the path, adding complexity to any solution using the
        new behavior.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Applicability of method">
        <t>The expectation of the present proposal defined in <xref
        target="UDPZ"></xref> is that this change would only apply to IPv6
        router nodes that implement specific protocols that permit omission of
        UDP checksums. However, the distinction between a router and a host is
        not always clear, especially at the transport level. Systems (such as
        unix-based operating systems) routinely provide both functions. There
        is also no way to identify the role of a receiver from a received
        packet.</t>

        <t>Any new method would therefore need a specific applicability
        statement indicating when the mechanism can (and can not) be used.
        Enabling this, and ensuring correct interactions with the stack,
        implies much more than simply disabling the checksum algorithm for
        specific packets at the transport interface.</t>

        <t>The IETF should carefully consider constraints on sanctioning the
        use of any new transport mode. If this is specified and widely
        available, it may be expected to be used by applications that are
        perceived to gain benefit. Any solution that uses an end-to-end
        transport protocol, rather than an IP-in-IP encapsulation, needs to
        minimise the possibility that end-hosts could confuse a corrupted or
        wrongly delivered packet with that of data addressed to an application
        running on their endpoint unless they accept that behavior.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Impact on non-supporting devices or applications">
        <t>It is important to consider what potential impact the zero-checksum
        behavior may have on end-points, devices or applications that are not
        modified to support the new behavior or by default or preference, use
        the regular behavior. These applications must not be significantly
        impacted by the changes.</t>

        <t>To illustrate a potential issue, consider the implications of a
        node that were to enable use of a zero-checksum at the interface
        level: This would result in all applications that listen to a UDP
        socket receiving datagram where the checksum was not verified. This
        could have a significant impact on an application that was not
        designed with the additional robustness needed to handle received
        packets with corruption, creating state or destroying existing state
        in the application.</t>

        <t>In contrast, the use of a zero-checksum could be enabled only for
        individual ports using an explicit request by the application. In this
        case, applications using other ports would maintain the current IPv6
        behavior, discarding incoming UDP datagrams with a zero-checksum.
        These other applications would not be effected by this changed
        behavior. An application that allows the changed behavior should be
        aware of the risk for corruption and the increased level of
        misdirected traffic, and can be designed robustly to handle this
        risk.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Proposal"
             title="Evaluation of proposal to update RFC 2460 to support zero checksum">
      <t>This section evaluates the proposal to update IPv6 [RFC2460], to
      provide the option that some nodes may suppress generation and checking
      of the UDP transport checksum. It also compares the proposal with other
      alternatives.</t>

      <section title="Alternatives to the Standard Checksum">
        <t>There are several alternatives to the normal method for calculating
        the UDP Checksum that do not require a tunnel endpoint to inspect the
        entire packet when computing a checksum. These include (in decreasing
        order of complexity):<list style="symbols">
            <t>Delta computation of the checksum from an encapsulated checksum
            field. Since the checksum is a cumulative sum <xref
            target="RFC1624"></xref>, an encapsulating header checksum can be
            derived from the new pseudo header, the inner checksum and the sum
            of the other network-layer fields not included in the pseudo
            header of the encapsulated packet, in a manner resembling
            incremental checksum update <xref target="RFC1141"></xref>. This
            would not require access to the whole packet, but does require
            fields to be collected across the header, and arithmetic
            operations on each packet. The method would only work for packets
            that contain a 2's complement transport checksum (i.e. it would
            not be appropriate for SCTP or when IP fragmentation is used).</t>

            <t>UDP-Lite with the checksum coverage set to only the header
            portion of a packet. This requires a pseudo header checksum
            calculation only on the encapsulating packet header. The computed
            checksum value may be cached (before adding the Length field) for
            each flow/destination and subsequently combined with the Length of
            each packet to minimise per-packet processing. This value is
            combined with the UDP payload length for the pseudo header,
            however this length is expected to be known when performing packet
            forwarding.</t>

            <t>The proposed UDP Tunnel Transport, UDPTT <xref
            target="UDPTT"></xref> suggested a method where UDP would be
            modified to derive the checksum only from the encapsulating packet
            protocol header. This value does not change between packets in a
            single flow. The value may be cached per flow/destination to
            minimise per-packet processing.</t>

            <t>There has been a proposal to simply ignore the UDP checksum
            value on reception at the tunnel egress, allowing a tunnel ingress
            to insert any value correct or false. For tunnel usage, a non
            standard checksum value may be used, forcing an RFC 2460 receiver
            to drop the packet. The main downside is that it would be
            impossible to identify a UDP packet (in the network or an
            endpoint) that is treated in this way compared to a packet that
            has actually been corrupted.</t>

            <t>A method has been proposed that uses a new (to be defined) IPv6
            Destination Options Header to provide an end-to-end validation
            check at the network layer. This would allow an endpoint to verify
            delivery to an appropriate end point, but would also require IPv6
            nodes to correctly handle the additional header, and would require
            changes to middlebox behavior (e.g. when used with a NAT that
            always adjusts the checksum value).</t>

            <t>UDP modified to disable checksum processing<xref target="UDPZ">
            </xref>. This requires no checksum calculation, but would require
            constraints on appropriate usage and updates to end-points and
            middleboxes.</t>

            <t>IP-in-IP tunneling. As this method completely dispenses with a
            transport protocol in the outer-layer it has reduced overhead and
            complexity, but also reduced functionality. There is no outer
            checksum over the packet and also no ports to perform
            demultiplexing between different tunnel types. This reduces the
            information available upon which a load balancer may act.</t>
          </list>These options are compared and discussed further in the
        following sections.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Comparison">
        <t>This section compares the above listed methods to support datagram
        tunneling. It includes proposals for updating the behaviour of
        UDP.</t>

        <section title="Middlebox Traversal">
          <t>Regular UDP with a standard checksum or the delta encoded
          optimization for creating correct checksums have the best
          possibilities for successful traversal of a middlebox. No new
          support is required.</t>

          <t>A method that ignores the UDP checksum on reception is expected
          to have a good probability of traversal, because most middleboxes
          perform an incremental checksum update. UDPTT may also traverse a
          middlebox with this behaviour. However, a middlebox on the path that
          attempts to verify a standard checksum will not forward packets
          using either of these methods, preventing traversal. The methods
          that ignores the checksum has an additional downside in that
          middlebox traversal can not be improved, because there is no way to
          identify which packets use the modified checksum behaviour.</t>

          <t>IP-in-IP or GRE tunnels offer good traversal of middleboxes that
          have not been designed for security, e.g. firewalls. However,
          firewalls may be expected to be configured to block general tunnels
          as they present a large attack surface.</t>

          <t>A new IPv6 Destination Options header will suffer traversal
          issues with middleboxes, especially Firewalls and NATs, and will
          likely require them to be updated before the extension header is
          passed.</t>

          <t>Packets using UDP with a zero checksum will not be passed by any
          middlebox that validates the checksum using RFC 2460 or updates the
          checksum field, such as NAT or firewalls. This would require an
          update to correctly handle the zero checksum packets.</t>

          <t>UDP-Lite will require an update of almost all type of
          middleboxes, because it requires support for a separate
          network-layer protocol number. Once enabled, the method to support
          incremental checksum update would be identical to that for UDP, but
          different for checksum validation.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Load Balancing">
          <t>The usefulness of solutions for load balancers depends on the
          difference in entropy in the headers for different flows that can be
          included in a hash function. All the proposals that use the UDP
          protocol number have equal behavior. UDP-Lite has the potential for
          equally good behavior as for UDP. However, UDP-Lite is currently
          likely to not be supported by deployed hashing mechanisms, which may
          cause a load balancer to not use the transport header in the
          computed hash. A load balancer that only uses the IP header will
          have low entropy, but could be improved by including the IPv6 the
          flow label, providing that the tunnel ingress ensures that different
          flow labels are assigned to different flows. However, a transition
          to the common use of good quality flow labels is likely to take time
          to deploy.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Ingress and Egress Performance Implications">
          <t>IP-in-IP tunnels are often considered efficient, because they
          introduce very little processing and low data overhead. The other
          proposals introduce a UDP-like header incurring associated data
          overhead. Processing is minimised for the zero-checksum method,
          ignoring the checksum on reception, and only slightly higher for
          UDPTT, the extension header and UDP-Lite. The delta-calculation
          scheme operates on a few more fields, but also introduces serious
          failure modes that can result in a need to calculate a checksum over
          the complete packet. Regular UDP is clearly the most costly to
          process, always requiring checksum calculation over the entire
          packet.</t>

          <t>It is important to note that the zero-checksum method, ignoring
          checksum on reception, the Option Header, UDPTT and UDP-Lite will
          likely incur additional complexities in the application to
          incorporate a negotiation and validation mechanism.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Deployability">
          <t>The major factors influencing deployability of these solutions
          are a need to update both end-points, a need for negotiation and the
          need to update middleboxes. These are summarised below:<list
              style="symbols">
              <t>The solution with the best deployability is regular UDP. This
              requires no changes and has good middlebox traversal
              characteristics.</t>

              <t>The next easiest to deploy is the delta checksum solution.
              This does not modify the protocol on the wire and only needs
              changes in tunnel ingress.</t>

              <t>IP-in-IP tunnels should not require changes to the
              end-points, but raise issues when traversing firewalls and other
              security-type devices, which are expected to require
              updates.</t>

              <t>Ignoring the checksum on reception will require changes at
              both end-points. The never ceasing risk of path failure requires
              additional checks to ensure this solution is robust and will
              require changes or additions to the tunneling control protocol
              to negotiate support and validate the path.</t>

              <t>The remaining solutions offer similar deployability. UDP-Lite
              requires support at both end-points and in middleboxes. UDPTT
              and Zero-checksum with or without an Extension header require
              support at both end-points and in middleboxes. UDP-Lite, UDPTT,
              and Zero-checksum and Extension header may additionally require
              changes or additions to the tunneling control protocol to
              negotiate support and path validation.</t>
            </list></t>
        </section>

        <section title="Corruption Detection Strength">
          <t>The standard UDP checksum and the delta checksum can both provide
          some verification at the tunnel egress. This can significantly
          reduce the probability that a corrupted inner packet is forwarded.
          UDP-Lite, UDPTT and the extension header all provide some
          verification against corruption, but do not verify the inner packet.
          They only provide a strong indication that the delivered packet was
          intended for the tunnel egress and was correctly delimited. The
          Zero-checksum, ignoring the checksum on reception and IP-and-IP
          encapsulation provide no verification that a received packet was
          intended to be processed by a specific tunnel egress or that the
          inner packet was correct.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Comparison Summary">
          <t>The comparisons above may be summarised as "there is no silver
          bullet that will slay all the issues". One has to select which down
          side(s) can best be lived with. Focusing on the existing solutions,
          this can be summarized as:</t>

          <t><list style="hanging">
              <t hangText="Regular UDP:">Good middlebox traversal and load
              balancing and multiplexing, requiring a checksum in the outer
              headers covering the whole packet.</t>

              <t hangText="IP in IP:">A low complexity encapsulation, with
              limited middlebox traversal, no multiplexing support, and
              currently poor load balancing support that could improve over
              time.</t>

              <t hangText="UDP-Lite:">A medium complexity encapsulation, with
              good multiplexing support, limited middlebox traversal, but
              possible to improve over time, currently poor load balancing
              support that could improve over time, in most cases requiring
              application level negotiation and validation.</t>
            </list>The delta-checksum is an optimization in the processing of
          UDP, as such &gt; it exhibits some of the drawbacks of using regular
          UDP.<!----></t>

          <t>The remaining proposals may be described in similar terms:</t>

          <t><list style="hanging">
              <t hangText="Zero-Checksum:">A low complexity encapsulation,
              with good multiplexing support, limited middlebox traversal that
              could improve over time, good load balancing support, in most
              cases requiring application level negotiation and
              validation.</t>

              <t hangText="UDPTT:">A medium complexity encapsulation, with
              good multiplexing support, limited middlebox traversal, but
              possible to improve over time, good load balancing support, in
              most cases requiring application level negotiation and
              validation.</t>

              <t hangText="IPv6 Destination Option IP in IP tunneling:">A
              medium complexity, with no multiplexing support, limited
              middlebox traversal, currently poor load balancing support that
              could improve over time, in most cases requiring application
              level negotiation and validation.</t>

              <t
              hangText="IPv6 Destination Option combined with UDP Zero-checksuming:">A
              medium complexity encapsulation, with good multiplexing support,
              limited load balancing support that could improve over time, in
              most cases requiring application level negotiation and
              validation.</t>

              <t hangText="Ignore the checksum on reception:">A low complexity
              encapsulation, with good multiplexing support, medium middlebox
              traversal that never can improve, good load balancing support,
              in most cases requiring application level negotiation and
              validation.</t>
            </list></t>

          <t>There is no clear single optimum solution. If the most important
          need is to traverse middleboxes, then the best choice is to stay
          with regular UDP and consider the optimizations that may be required
          to perform the checksumming. If one can live with limited middlebox
          traversal, low complexity is necessary and one does not require load
          balancing, then IP-in-IP tunneling is the simplest. If one wants
          strengthened error detection, but with currently limited middlebox
          traversal and load-balancing. UDP-Lite is appropriate. UDP
          Zero-checksum addresses another set of constraints, low complexity
          and a need for load balancing from the current Internet, providing
          it can live with currently limited middlebox traversal.</t>

          <t>Techniques for load balancing and middlebox traversal do continue
          to evolve. Over a long time, developments in load balancing have
          good potential to improve. This time horizon is long since it
          requires end-point updates to get full benefit. The challenges of
          middlebox traversal are also expected to change with time, as device
          capabilities evolve. Middleboxes are very prolific with a larger
          proportion of end-user ownership, and therefore may be expected to
          take long time cycles to evolve. One potential advantage is that the
          deployment of IPv6 capable middleboxes are still in its initial
          phase and the quicker zero-checksum becomes standardized the fewer
          boxes will be non-compliant.</t>

          <t><!--XXX GF: The last sentence would also apply equally to UDP-Lite for IPv6! :-)--></t>

          <t>Thus, the question of whether to allow UDP with a zero-checksum
          for IPv6 under reasonable constraints, is therefore best viewed as a
          trade-off between a number of more subjective questions:</t>

          <t><list style="symbols">
              <t>Is there sufficient interest in zero-checksum with the given
              constraints (summarised below)?</t>

              <t>Are there other avenues of change that will resolve the issue
              in a better way and sufficiently quickly ?</t>

              <t>Do we accept the complexity cost of having one more solution
              in the future?</t>
            </list>The authors do think the answer to the above questions are
          such that zero-checksum should be standardized for use by tunnel
          encapsulations.</t>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Requirements on the specification of transported protocols">
      <section anchor="sec-constraints"
               title="Constraints required on usage of a zero checksum">
        <t>If a zero checksum approach were to be adopted by the IETF, the
        specification should consider adding the following constraints on
        usage:</t>

        <t><list style="numbers">
            <t>IPv6 protocol stack implementations should not by default allow
            the new method. The default node receiver behaviour must discard
            all IPv6 packets carrying UDP packets with a zero checksum.</t>

            <t>Implementations must provide a way to signal the set of ports
            that will be enabled to receive UDP datagrams with a zero
            checksum. An IPv6 node that enables reception of UDP packets with
            a zero-checksum, must enable this only for a specific port or
            port-range. This may be implemented via a socket API call, or
            similar mechanism.</t>

            <t>RFC 2460 specifies that IPv6 nodes should log UDP datagrams
            with a zero-checksum. This should remain the case for any datagram
            received on a port that does not explicitly enable zero-checksum
            processing. A port for which zero-checksum has been enabled must
            not log the datagram.</t>

            <t>A stack may separately identify UDP datagrams that are
            discarded with a zero checksum. It should not add these to the
            standard log, since the endpoint has not been verified.</t>

            <t>Tunnels that encapsulate IP may rely on the inner packet
            integrity checks provided that the tunnel will not significantly
            increase the rate of corruption of the inner IP packet. If a
            significantly increased corruption rate can occur, then the tunnel
            must provide an additional integrity verification mechanism. An
            integrity mechanisms is always recommended at the tunnel layer to
            ensure that corruption rates of the inner most packet are not
            increased.</t>

            <t>Tunnels that encapsulate Non-IP packets must have a CRC or
            other mechanism for checking packet integrity, unless the Non-IP
            packet specifically is designed for transmission over lower layers
            that do not provide any packet integrity guarantee. In particular,
            the application must be designed so that corruption of this
            information does not result in accumulated state or incorrect
            processing of a tunneled payload.</t>

            <t>UDP applications that support use of a zero-checksum, should
            not rely upon correct reception of the IP and UDP protocol
            information (including the length of the packet) when decoding and
            processing the packet payload. In particular, the application must
            be designed so that corruption of this information does not result
            in accumulated state or incorrect processing of a tunneled
            payload.</t>

            <t>If a method proposes recursive tunnels, it needs to provide
            guidance that is appropriate for all use-cases. Restrictions may
            be needed to the use of a tunnel encapsulations and the use of
            recursive tunnels (e.g. Necessary when the endpoint is not
            verified).</t>

            <t>IPv6 nodes that receive ICMPv6 messages that refer to packets
            with a zero UDP checksum must provide appropriate checks
            concerning the consistency of the reported packet to verify that
            the reported packet actually originated from the node, before
            acting upon the information (e.g. validating the address and port
            numbers in the ICMPv6 message body).</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>Deployment of the new method needs to remain restricted to
        endpoints that explicitly enable this mode and adopt the above
        procedures. Any middlebox that examines or interact with the UDP
        header over IPv6 should support the new method.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="sec-summary" title="Summary">
      <t>This document examines the role of the transport checksum when used
      with IPv6, as defined in RFC2460.</t>

      <t>It presents a summary of the trade-offs for evaluating the safety of
      updating RFC 2460 to permit an IPv6 UDP endpoint to use a zero value in
      the checksum field to indicate that no checksum is present. A decision
      not to include a UDP checksum in received IPv6 datagrams could impact a
      tunnel application that receives these packets. However, a well-designed
      tunnel application should include consistency checks to validate any
      header information encapsulated with a packet. In most cases tunnels
      encapsulating IP packets can rely on the inner packets own integrity
      protection. When correctly implemented, such a tunnel endpoint will not
      be negatively impacted by omission of the transport-layer checksum.
      Recursive tunneling and fragmentation is a potential issues that can
      raise corruption rates significantly, and requires careful
      consideration.</t>

      <t>Other applications at the intended destination node or another IPv6
      node can be impacted if they are allowed to receive datagrams without a
      transport-layer checksum. It is particularly important that already
      deployed applications are not impacted by any change at the transport
      layer. If these applications execute on nodes that implement RFC 2460,
      they will reject all datagrams with a zero UDP checksum, thus this is
      not an issue. For nodes that implement support for zero-checksum it is
      important to ensure that only UDP applications that desire zero-checksum
      can receive and originate zero-checksum packets. Thus, the enabling of
      zero-checksum needs to be at a port level, not for the entire host or
      for all use of an interface.</t>

      <t>The implications on firewalls, NATs and other middleboxes need to be
      considered. It is not expected that IPv6 NATs handle IPv6 UDP datagrams
      in the same way that they handle IPv4 UDP datagrams. This possibly
      reduces the need to update the checksum. Firewalls are intended to be
      configured, and therefore may need to be explicitly updated to allow new
      services or protocols. IPv6 middlebox deployment is not yet as prolific
      as it is in IPv4. Thus, relatively few current middleboxes may actually
      block IPv6 UDP with a zero checksum.</t>

      <t>In general, UDP-based applications need to employ a mechanism that
      allows a large percentage of the corrupted packets to be removed before
      they reach an application, both to protect the applications data stream
      and the control plane of higher layer protocols. These checks are
      currently performed by the UDP checksum for IPv6, or the reduced
      checksum for UDP-Lite when used with IPv6.</t>

      <t>The use of UDP with no checksum has merits for some applications,
      such as tunnel encapsulation, and is widely used in IPv4. However, there
      are dangers for IPv6: There is a bigger risk of corruption and
      miss-delivery when using zero-checksum in IPv6 compared to IPv4 due to
      the removed IP header checksum. Thus, applications needs to make a new
      evaluation of the risks of enabling a zero-checksum. Some applications
      will need to re-consider their usage of zero-checksum, and possibly
      consider a solution that at least provides the same delivery protection
      as for IPv4, for example by utilizing UDP-Lite, or by enabling the UDP
      checksum. Tunnel applications using UDP for encapsulation can in many
      case use zero-checksum without significant impact on the corruption
      rate. In some cases, the use of checksum off-loading may help alleviate
      the checksum processing cost.</t>

      <t>Recursive tunneling and fragmentation is a difficult issue relating
      to tunnels in general. There is an increased risk of an error in the
      inner-most packet when fragmentation when several layers of tunneling
      and several different reassembly processes are run without any
      verification of correctness. This issue requires future thought and
      consideration.</t>

      <t>The conclusion is that UDP zero checksum in IPv6 should be
      standardized, as it satisfies usage requirements that are currently
      difficult to address. We do note that a safe deployment of zero-checksum
      will need to follow a set of constraints listed in <xref
      target="sec-constraints"></xref>.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>Brian Haberman, Brian Carpenter, Magaret Wasserman, Lars Eggert,
      others in the TSV directorate.</t>

      <t>Thanks also to: R&eacute;mi Denis-Courmont, Pekka Savola and many
      others who contributed comments and ideas via the 6man, behave, lisp and
      mboned lists.</t>
    </section>

    <!-- Possibly a 'Contributors' section ... -->

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>This document does not require IANA considerations.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>Transport checksums provide the first stage of protection for the
      stack, although they can not be considered authentication mechanisms.
      These checks are also desirable to ensure packet counters correctly log
      actual activity, and can be used to detect unusual behaviours.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <!--  *****BACK MATTER ***** -->

  <back>
    <!-- -->

    <references title="Normative References">
      <!--?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"?-->

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.0791'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.0793'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.1071'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.2460'?>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <!-- Here we use entities that we defined at the beginning. -->

      <reference anchor="AMT">
        <front>
          <title>Automatic IP Multicast Without Explicit Tunnels (AMT)</title>

          <author fullname="D. Thaler, et al" surname="">
            <organization>Internet draft,
            draft-ietf-mboned-auto-multicast-10</organization>
          </author>

          <date day="07" month="March" year="2010" />
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="UDPTT">
        <front>
          <title>The UDP Tunnel Transport mode</title>

          <author fullname="G Fairhurst" surname="">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date day="20" month="Feb" year="2010" />
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="UDPZ">
        <front>
          <title>UDP Checksums for Tunneled Packets</title>

          <author fullname="M. Eubanks and P. Chimento" surname="">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date day="01" month="(Oct" year="2009" />
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="LISP">
        <front>
          <title>Locator/ID Separation Protocol (LISP)</title>

          <author fullname="D. Farinacci et al" surname="">
            <organization>Internet draft,
            draft-farinacci-lisp-12.txt</organization>
          </author>

          <date day="02" month="March" year="2009" />
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="Sigcomm2000">
        <front>
          <title>When the CRC and TCP Checksum Disagree</title>

          <author fullname="Jonathan Stone and Craig Partridge " surname="">
            <organization>http://conferences.sigcomm.org/sigcomm/2000/conf/abstract/9-1.htm</organization>
          </author>

          <date year="2000" />
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="ECMP">
        <front>
          <title>Using the IPv6 flow label for equal cost multipath routing in
          tunnels (draft-carpenter-flow-ecmp)</title>

          <author fullname="B. Carpenter">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date />
        </front>
      </reference>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.0768'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.1141'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.1624'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.4443'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-intarea-tunnels'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.2765'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.3550'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.3819'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.3828'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.4963'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.5405'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.5415'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.5722'?>

      <!-- A reference written by by an organization not a person. 


Discusses IPv4 cksum=0, and alludes to IPv6 case:
UDP Encapsulation of IPsec ESP Packets (draft-ietf-ipsec-udp-encaps-09)


-->
    </references>

    <section title="Document Change History">
      <t>{RFC EDITOR NOTE: This section must be deleted prior to
      publication}</t>

      <t><list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="Individual Draft 00 ">This is the first DRAFT of this
          document - It contains a compilation of various discussions and
          contributions from a variety of IETF WGs, including: mboned, tsv,
          6man, lisp, and behave. This includes contributions from Magnus with
          text on RTP, and various updates.</t>

          <t hangText="Individual Draft 01"><list style="symbols">
              <t>This version corrects some typos and editorial NiTs and adds
              discussion of the need to negotiate and verify operation of a
              new mechanism (3.3.4).</t>
            </list></t>

          <t hangText="Individual Draft 02"><list style="symbols">
              <t>Version -02 corrects some typos and editorial NiTs.</t>

              <t>Added reference to ECMP for tunnels.</t>

              <t>Clarifies the recommendations at the end of the document.</t>
            </list></t>

          <t hangText="Working Group Draft 00"><list style="symbols">
              <t>Working Group Version -00 corrects some typos and removes
              much of rationale for UDPTT. It also adds some discussion of
              IPv6 extension header.</t>
            </list></t>

          <t hangText="Working Group Draft 01"><list style="symbols">
              <t>Working Group Version -01 updates the rules and incorporates
              off-list feedback. This version is intended for wider review
              within the 6man working group.</t>
            </list></t>

          <t hangText="Working Group Draft 02"><list style="symbols">
              <t>This version is the result of a major rewrite and re-ordering
              of the document.</t>

              <t>A new section comparing the results have been added.</t>

              <t>The constraints list has been significantly altered by
              removing some and rewording other constraints.</t>

              <t>This contains other significant language updates to clarify
              the intent of this draft.</t>
            </list></t>

          <t hangText="**TO BE DONE **"><list style="symbols">
              <t>This version requires review from proponents and opponents to
              the UDP zero checksum proposal.</t>

              <t></t>
            </list></t>
        </list></t>
    </section>

    <!-- Change Log
-->
  </back>
</rfc>
