<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">

<!-- For a complete list and description of processing instructions (PIs), 
please see http://xml.resource.org/authoring/README.html. -->

<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc tocdepth="2" ?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>

<rfc
    category="info"
    docName="draft-ietf-repute-model-02"
    ipr="trust200902">

  <front>

    <title
        abbrev="Reputation Reporting Model"> A Model for Reputation
    Reporting </title>
    <author
        fullname="Nathaniel Borenstein"
        initials="N."
        surname="Borenstein">
      <organization>Mimecast</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>203 Crescent St., Suite 303</street>
          <city>Waltham</city>
          <region>MA</region>
          <code>02453</code>
          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>
        <phone>+1 781 996 5340</phone>
        <email>nsb@guppylake.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author
        fullname="Murray S. Kucherawy"
        initials="M. S."
        surname="Kucherawy">
      <organization>Cloudmark</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>128 King St., 2nd Floor</street>
          <city>San Francisco</city>
          <region>CA</region>
          <code>94107</code>
          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>
        <email>superuser@gmail.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author
        role="editor"
        fullname="Andrew Sullivan"
        initials="A."
        surname="Sullivan">
      <organization>Dyn, Inc.</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>150 Dow St.</street>
          <city>Manchester</city>
          <region>NH</region>
          <code>03101</code>
          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>
        <email>asullivan@dyn.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date
        year="2012"></date>

    <area>Applications</area>
    <workgroup>REPUTE Working Group</workgroup>

    <keyword>domain</keyword>
    <keyword>security</keyword>
    <keyword>messaging</keyword>
    <keyword>dkim</keyword>
    <keyword>spf</keyword>
    <keyword>authentication</keyword>
    <keyword>reputation</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t> This document describes a general architecture for a
      reputation-based service and a model for the exchange of
      reputation information on the Internet. The document roughly
      follows the recommendations of RFC4101 for describing a protocol
      model. </t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section
        title="Introduction">
      <t> Historically, many Internet protocols have operated between
      unauthenticated entities. For example, an email message's author
      field (From) <xref
      target="MAIL"></xref> can contain any display name or
      address and is not verified by the recipient or other agents
      along the delivery path. Similarly, a sending email server using <xref
      target="SMTP"></xref> trusts that the <xref
      target="DNS"></xref> has led it to the intended receiving
      server. Both kinds of trust are easily betrayed,
      opening the operation to subversion of some kind,
      which leads to spam, phishing, and other attacks. </t>

      <t> In recent years, stronger identity mechanisms have
      begun to see wider deployment. For example, the <xref
      target="DKIM"></xref> protocol permits associating a
      validated identifier to a message.  This association is
      cryptographically strong, and is an improvement over the
      prior state of affairs, but it does not distinguish
      between identifiers of good actors and bad. Even
      when it is possible to validate the domain name in an
      author field (e.g. "trustworthy.example.com" in
      "john.doe@trustworthy.example.com") there is no basis for
      knowing whether it is associated with a good actor worthy
      of trust. As a practical matter, both bad actors and good
      adopt basic authentication mechanisms like DKIM. In fact,
      bad actors tend to adopt them even more rapidly than the
      good actors do in the hope that some receivers will confuse
      identity authentication with identity assessment. The
      former merely means that the name is being used by its
      owner or their agent, while the latter makes a statement
      about the quality of the owner.</t>

      <t> The added requirement -- which can usefully be undertaken
      only in the presence of such stronger identity validation -- is
      for a mechanism by which mutually trusted parties can exchange
      assessment information about other actors.  For these purposes,
      we may usefully define "reputation" as "the estimation in which
      an identifiable actor is held, especially by the community or
      the Internet public generally".  We may call an aggregation of
      individual assessments "reputation information."
      </t>

      <t> While the need for reputation information has been perhaps
      most clear in the email world, where abuses are commonplace,
      other Internet services are coming under attack and may have a
      similar need.  For instance, a reputation mechanism could be
      useful in rating the security of web sites; the quality of
      service of an Internet Service Provider (ISP) or Application
      Service Provider (ASP); customer satisfaction at e-commerce
      sites; and even things unrelated to Internet protocols, such as
      plumbers, hotels, or books. Just as human beings traditionally
      rely on the recommendations of trusted parties in the physical
      world, so too they can be expected to make use of such
      reputation information in a variety of applications on the
      Internet. </t>
      
      <t> A full trust architecture encompasses a range of actors and
      activities, to enable an end-to-end service for creating and
      consuming trust-related information.  One component of that is a
      query mechanism, to permit retrieval of reputation information.
      Not all such reputation services will need to convey the same
      information.  Some need only produce a basic rating, while
      others need to provide underlying detail.  This is akin to the
      difference between check approval versus a credit report. </t>

      <t>An overall reckoning of goodness versus badness can be
      defined generically, but specific applications are likely to
      want to describe reputations for multiple attributes: an
      e-commerce site might be rated on price, speed of delivery,
      customer service, etc., and might receive very different ratings
      on each.  Therefore, a model defines a generic query mechanism
      and basic format for reputation information, but allows
      extensions for each application. </t>

      <t> Omitted from this model is the means by which an
      reputation-reporting agent goes about collecting such data and
      the mechanism for creating an evaluation.  The mechanism defined
      here merely enables asking a question and getting an answer; the
      remainder of an overall service provided by such a reputation
      agent is specific to the implementation of that service and is
      out of scope here. </t>
    </section>
    <!-- Introduction -->
    
    <section
        title="High-Level Architecture">
      <t>A reputation mechanism functions as a component of a service,
      such as that depicted in Figure 1 of <xref
      target="RFC5863"></xref>, reproduced here: <figure
      anchor="rfc5683-fig1"
      title="RFC5683 'Actors in a Trust Sequence Using DKIM'">
                    <artwork>
<![CDATA[     +------+------+                            +------+------+
     |   Author    |                            |  Recipient  |
     +------+------+                            +------+------+
            |                                          ^
            |                                          |
            |                                   +------+------+
            |                                -->|  Handling   |<--
            |                                -->|   Filter    |<--
            |                                   +-------------+
            |                                          ^
            V                  Responsible             |
     +-------------+           Identifier       +------+------+
     | Responsible |. .       . . . . . . . . .>|  Identity   |
     |  Identity   |  .       .                 |  Assessor   |
     +------+------+  .       .                 +-------------+
            |         V       .                       ^ ^
            V         .       .                       | |
   +------------------.-------.--------------------+  | |
   | +------+------+  . . . > .   +-------------+  |  | |  +-----------+
   | | Identifier  |              | Identifier  +--|--+ +--+ Assessment|
   | |   Signer    +------------->| Validator   |  |       | Databases |
   | +-------------+              +-------------+  |       +-----------+
   |                 DKIM Service                  |
   +-----------------------------------------------+]]>
        </artwork>
        </figure> Here, the reputation mechanism is shown only as a
      query by an Identity Assessor, made to Assessment Databases. </t>
      
      <t>This memo outlines the query and response mechanism. It
      provides the following definitions:
      <list style="symbols">
        <t>Vocabulary for the current work and work of this type;</t>
        <t>The types and content of queries that can be
        supported;</t>
        <t>The extensible range of response information that can be
        provided;</t>
        <t>A query/response protocol;</t>
        <t>Query/response transport conventions.</t>
        </list>It provides an extremely simple
        query/response model that can be carried over a variety of
        transports, including the Domain Name System.  (Although not
        typically thought of as a 'transport', the DNS provides generic
        capabilities and can be thought of as a mechanism for transporting
        queries and responses that have nothing to do with addresses.)
        Each specification for Repute transport is independent of any
        other specification.  A diagram of the basic query service is
        found in <xref target="query-fig" />.<figure
        anchor="query-fig"
        title="Basic Reputation Query Service">
                    <artwork>
<![CDATA[     +-----------+         Query              +----------+
     |           +. . . . . . . . . . . . . .>|          |
     |  Client   |                            |  Server  |
     |           <. . . . . . . . . . . . . . +          |
     +-----+-----+         Response           +-------+--+
           |                                     ^    |
           V                                     |    |
     +------+----+                +-----------+  |    | Response
     | Transport |--------------->| Transport |--+    | Set
     +-----------+    DNS         +-----------+       |
                      TCP                             V
                      UDP                      +------------+
                      ...                      | Reputation |
                                               | Database   |
                                               +------------+]]>
            </artwork>
          </figure>
      </t>

      <t>Both the query and response are application-specific.  An
      application of the model defines the parameters available to
      queries of that type, and also defines the data returned in
      response to any query.</t>
    </section>
    
    <section
        anchor="terms_and_defs"
        title="Terminology and Definitions">
      <t>This section defines terms used in the rest of the document.</t>
      
      <section
          anchor="defs_vocabulary"
          title="Response Set">
        <t> A "Response Set" comprises those data that are returned in
        response to a reputation query about a particular entity.
        The types of data are specific to an application; the data
        returned in the evaluation of email senders would be
        different than the reputation data returned about a movie or
        a baseball player. </t>
        
        <t> Response Sets have symbolic names, and these have to be
        registered with IANA to prevent name collisions.  IANA
        registries are created in a separate memo.  Each definition of
        a Response Set needs to define its registry entry.</t>
      </section>
      <!-- Vocabulary -->
    </section>
    <!-- Terminology and Definitions -->
    
    <section
        anchor="protoinfo"
        title="Information Represented in a Response Set">
      <t> The basic information to be represented in the protocol is
      fairly simple, and includes the following: <list style="symbols">
      
      <t> the identity of the entity providing the reputation
      information; </t>
      
      <t> the identity of the entity being rated; </t>
      
      <t> the overall rating score for that entity; </t>
      
      <t> the level of confidence in the accuracy of that rating;
      and </t>

      <t> the number of data points underlying that score. </t>
    </list>
      </t>
      
      <t> Beyond this, arbitrary amounts of additional information
      might be provided for specific uses of the service. The entire
      collection is the Response Set for that application. The
      query/response protocol defines a syntax for representing such
      Response Sets, but each application defines its own Response
      Set. Thus, the basic information also includes the name of the
      application for which the reputation data is being
      expressed. </t>

      <t>Each application requires its own specification of the
      Response Set.  For example, a specification might be needed for
      a reputation Response Set for an "email-sending-domain"; the
      Response Set might include information on how often spam was
      received from that domain. Additional documents define a <xref
      target="MIME"></xref> type for reputation data, and protocols
      for exchanging such data. </t>
    </section>
    <!-- Information Represented in the Protocol -->
    
    <section
        anchor="protoflow"
        title="Information Flow in the Protocol">
      <t> The basic Response Set could be wrapped into a new MIME media
      type <xref
      target="MIME"></xref> or a DNS RR, and transported
      accordingly. It also could be the integral payload of a
      purpose-built protocol. For a basic request/response scenario, one
      entity (the Client) will ask a second entity (the Server) for
      reputation data about a third entity (the Target), and the
      second entity will respond with that data. </t>
      
      <t> An applications might benefit from an extremely lightweight
      mechanism, supporting constrained queries and responses, while
      others might need to support larger and more complex responses.
      </t>
    </section>
    <!-- Information Flow in the Protocol -->
    
    <section
        anchor="iana_considerations"
        title="IANA Considerations">
      <t> This memo presents no actions for IANA. </t>
    </section>
    <!-- IANA Considerations -->

    <section
        anchor="priv_considerations"
        title="Privacy Considerations">
      <t>Some kinds of reputation data are sensitive, and should not
      be shared publicly.  For applications that have such
      sensitivity, it is imperative to pick a transport that will
      provide the required authentication and authorization mechanisms
      in order to secure communication and deliver responses correctly
      according to the proferred credentials.  Such transport
      questions are the province of the application definitions.</t>
    </section>
    
    <section
        anchor="sec_considerations"
        title="Security Considerations">
      <t> This memo introduces an overall protocol model, but no
      implementation details. As such, the security considerations
      presented here are very high-level. The detailed analyses of the
      various specific components of the protocol can be found the
      documents that instantiate this model. </t>

      <section
          anchor="sec_biased"
          title="Biased Reputation Agents">
        <t> As with <xref target="VBR"></xref>, an agent seeking to
        make use of a reputation reporting service is placing some
        trust that the service presents an unbiased "opinion" of the
        object about which reputation is being returned. The result of
        trusting the data is, presumably, to guide action taken by the
        reputation client. It follows, then, that bias in the
        reputation service can adversely affect the client. Clients
        therefore need to be aware of this possibility and the effect
        it might have. For example, a biased system returning
        reputation information about a DNS domain found in email
        messages could result in the admission of spam, phishing or
        malware through a mail gateway (by rating the domain name more
        favourably than warranted) or could result in the needless
        rejection or delay of mail (by rating the domain more
        unfavourably than warranted).  As a possible mitigation
        strategy, clients might seek to interact only with reputation
        services that offer some disclosure of the computation methods
        for the results they return.  Such disclosure and evaluation
        is beyond the scope of the present memo. </t>
        
        <t> Similarly, a client placing trust in the results returned
        by such a service might suffer if the service itself is
        compromised, returning biased results under the control of an
        attacker without the knowledge of the agency providing the
        reputation service. This might result from an attack on the
        data being returned at the source, or from a man-in-the-middle
        attack. Protocols, therefore, need to be designed so as to be
        as resilient against such attacks as possible. </t>
      </section>
      <!-- Biased Reputation Agents -->
      
      <section
          anchor="sec_malformed"
          title="Malformed Messages">
        <t> Both clients and servers of reputation systems need to be
        resistant to attacks that involve malformed messages,
        deliberate or otherwise. Failure to do so creates an
        opportunity for a denial-of-service. </t>
      </section>
      <!-- Malformed Messages -->
    </section>
    <!-- Security Considerations -->
  </middle>
  
  <back>
    <references
        title="Informative References">
      
      <reference
          anchor="MAIL">
        <front>
          <title>Internet Message Format</title>
          <author
              fullname="P. Resnick"
              initials="P."
              surname="Resnick">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>
          
          <date
              month="October"
              year="2008"></date>
          
          <abstract>
            <t>This document specifies a syntax for text messages
            that are sent between computer users, within the
            framework of "electronic mail" messages. [STANDARDS
            TRACK]</t>
          </abstract>
        </front>
        
        <seriesInfo
            name="RFC"
            value="5322"></seriesInfo>
        <format
            octets="110695"
            target="http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc5322.txt"
            type="TXT"></format>
      </reference>
      
      <reference
          anchor="RFC5863">
        
        <front>
          <title>DomainKeys Identified Mail (DKIM) Development,
          Deployment, and Operations</title>
          <author
              fullname="T. Hansen"
              initials="T."
              surname="Hansen">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>
          <author
              fullname="E. Siegel"
              initials="E."
              surname="Siegel">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>
          <author
              fullname="P. Hallam-Baker"
              initials="P."
              surname="Hallam-Baker">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>
          <author
              fullname="D. Crocker"
              initials="D."
              surname="Crocker">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>
          <date
              month="May"
              year="2010"></date>
          <abstract>
            <t>DomainKeys Identified Mail (DKIM) allows an
            organization to claim responsibility for
            transmitting a message, in a way that can be
            validated by a recipient. The organization can be
            the author's, the originating sending site, an
            intermediary, or one of their agents. A message can
            contain multiple signatures, from the same or
            different organizations involved with the message.
            DKIM defines a domain-level digital signature
            authentication framework for email, using public key
            cryptography and using the domain name service as
            its key server technology. This permits verification
            of a responsible organization, as well as the
            integrity of the message content. DKIM will also
            provide a mechanism that permits potential email
            signers to publish information about their email
            signing practices; this will permit email receivers
            to make additional assessments about messages.
            DKIM's authentication of email identity can assist
            in the global control of "spam" and "phishing". This
            document provides implementation, deployment,
            operational, and migration considerations for DKIM.
            This document is not an Internet Standards Track
            specification; it is published for informational
            purposes.</t>
          </abstract>
        </front>
        
        <seriesInfo
            name="RFC"
            value="5863"></seriesInfo>
        <format
            octets="126915"
            target="http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc5863.txt"
            type="TXT"></format>
      </reference>
      
      
      
      <reference
          anchor="DKIM">
        <front>
          <title> DomainKeys Identified Mail (DKIM) Signatures </title>
          
          <author
              fullname="E. Allman"
              initials="E."
              surname="Allman">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>
          
          <author
              fullname="J. Callas"
              initials="J."
              surname="Callas">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>
          
          <author
              fullname="M. Delany"
              initials="M."
              surname="Delany">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>
          
          <author
                        fullname="M. Libbey"
                        initials="M."
                        surname="Libbey">
                        <organization></organization>
                    </author>

                    <author
                        fullname="J. Fenton"
                        initials="J."
                        surname="Fenton">
                        <organization></organization>
                    </author>

                    <author
                        fullname="M. Thomas"
                        initials="M."
                        surname="Thomas">
                        <organization></organization>
                    </author>

                    <date
                        month="May"
                        year="2007"></date>
                </front>

                <seriesInfo
                    name="RFC"
                    value="4871"></seriesInfo>
            </reference>

            <reference
                anchor="DNS">
                <front>
                    <title abbrev="Domain Implementation and
                    Specification"> Domain names - implementation and
                    specification </title>

                    <author
                        fullname="P. Mockapetris"
                        initials="P."
                        surname="Mockapetris">
                        <organization>USC/ISI</organization>

                    </author>

                    <date
                        day="1"
                        month="November"
                        year="1987"></date>
                </front>

                <seriesInfo
                    name="STD"
                    value="13"></seriesInfo>

                <seriesInfo
                    name="RFC"
                    value="1035"></seriesInfo>
            </reference>

<!-- these never get used.
           <reference
                anchor="HTTP">
                <front>
                    <title> Hypertext Transfer Protocol -- HTTP/1.1 </title>
                    <author
                        fullname="R. Fielding"
                        initials="R."
                        surname="Fielding">
                        <organization> UC Irvine </organization>
                    </author>
                    <author
                        fullname="J. Gettys"
                        initials="J."
                        surname="Gettys">
                        <organization> Compaq/W3C </organization>
                    </author>
                    <author
                        fullname="J. Mogul"
                        initials="J."
                        surname="Mogul">
                        <organization> Compaq </organization>
                    </author>
                    <author
                        fullname="H. Frystyk"
                        initials="H."
                        surname="Frystyk">
                        <organization> W3C/MIT </organization>
                    </author>
                    <author
                        fullname="L. Masinter"
                        initials="L."
                        surname="Masinter">
                        <organization> Xerox </organization>
                    </author>
                    <author
                        fullname="P. Leach"
                        initials="P."
                        surname="Leach">
                        <organization> Microsoft </organization>
                    </author>
                    <author
                        fullname="T. Berners-Lee"
                        initials="T."
                        surname="Berners-Lee">
                        <organization> W3C/MIT </organization>
                    </author>
                    <date
                        month="June"
                        year="1999"></date>
                </front>

                <seriesInfo
                    name="RFC"
                    value="2616"></seriesInfo>
            </reference>

            <reference
                anchor="KEYWORDS">
                <front>
                    <title
                        abbrev="RFC Key Words">Key words for use in RFCs to
                        Indicate Requirement Levels</title>

                    <author
                        fullname="Scott Bradner"
                        initials="S."
                        surname="Bradner">
                        <organization>Harvard University</organization>
                    </author>

                    <date
                        month="March"
                        year="1997"></date>
                </front>

                <seriesInfo
                    name="BCP"
                    value="14"></seriesInfo>
                <seriesInfo
                    name="RFC"
                    value="2119"></seriesInfo>
            </reference>

-->

            <reference
                anchor="MIME">
                <front>
                    <title
                        abbrev="Internet Message Bodies"> Multipurpose Internet
                        Mail Extensions (MIME) Part One: Format of Internet
                        Message Bodies </title>

                    <author
                        fullname="Ned Freed"
                        initials="N."
                        surname="Freed">
                        <organization> Innosoft International, Inc.
                        </organization>
                    </author>

                    <author
                        fullname="Nathaniel S. Borenstein"
                        initials="N.S."
                        surname="Borenstein">
                        <organization> First Virtual Holdings </organization>
                    </author>

                    <date
                        month="November"
                        year="1996"></date>
                </front>

                <seriesInfo
                    name="RFC"
                    value="2045"></seriesInfo>
            </reference>

            <reference
                anchor="SMTP">
                <front>
                    <title>Simple Mail Transfer Protocol</title>

                    <author
                        fullname="J. Klensin"
                        initials="J."
                        surname="Klensin">
                        <organization></organization>
                    </author>

                    <date
                        month="October"
                        year="2008"></date>

                </front>

                <seriesInfo
                    name="RFC"
                    value="5321"></seriesInfo>
            </reference>

            <reference
                anchor="VBR">
                <front>
                    <title> Vouch By Reference </title>

                    <author
                        fullname="P. Hoffman"
                        initials="P."
                        surname="Hoffman">
                        <organization> Domain Assurance Council </organization>
                    </author>

                    <author
                        fullname="J. Levine"
                        initials="J."
                        surname="Levine">
                        <organization> Domain Assurance Council </organization>
                    </author>

                    <author
                        fullname="A. Hathcock"
                        initials="A."
                        surname="Hathcock">
                        <organization> Alt-N Technologies </organization>
                    </author>

                    <date
                        month="April"
                        year="2009"></date>
                </front>

                <seriesInfo
                    name="RFC"
                    value="5518"></seriesInfo>
            </reference>
        </references>

        <section
            anchor="public"
            title="Public Discussion">
            <t> Public discussion of this suite of memos takes place on the
                domainrep@ietf.org mailing list. See
                https://www.ietf.org/mailman/listinfo/domainrep. </t>
        </section>
    </back>
</rfc>
