<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<rfc category="exp" docName="draft-dubrovsky-ospf-non-compatible-00"
     ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="OSPF Non-Backward-Compatible">Extensions to OSPF
    facilitating the deployment of non-backward-compatible changes.</title>

    <author fullname="Mike Dubrovsky" initials="M" surname="Dubrovsky">
      <organization>Cisco Systems</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>510 McCarthy Blvd.</street>

          <city>Milpitas</city>

          <code>95035</code>

          <region>CA</region>

          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>

        <email>mdubrovs@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Rashmi Shrivastava" initials="R" surname="Shrivastava">
      <organization>Cisco Systems</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>10 West Tasman Drive</street>

          <city>San Jose</city>

          <code>95134</code>

          <region>CA</region>

          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>

        <email>rashi@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Dean Cheng" initials="D" surname="Cheng">
      <organization>Huawei Technologies</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>2330 Central Expressway</street>

          <city>Santa Clara</city>

          <code>95050</code>

          <region>CA</region>

          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>

        <email>dean.cheng@huawei.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date day="15" month="February" year="2013"/>

    <abstract>
      <t>This document specifies a generic mechanism that facilitates the
      deployment of non-backward-compatible changes in OSPF protocol. This
      mechanism allows the OSPF routers to advertise the capability of
      non-backward-compatible functionality and to make the functionality
      operational only when supported by all participating routers. Depending
      on the functionality scope, capability advertisements must be propagated
      across a link, area or autonomous system (AS). For link and area scope
      functionality, Router Information Link State Advertisement (LSA) is
      utilized to propagate the capability information. For the cases when
      compatibility must be maintained across the whole OSPF autonomous
      system, new Area Information (AI) LSA is introduced. The AI LSA is a
      TLV-based analog of Indication-LSA that is used for demand circuit
      functionality and described in RFC1793.</t>
    </abstract>

    <note title="Requirements Language">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
      document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
      target="RFC2119">RFC 2119</xref>.</t>
    </note>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>The evolution of OSPF protocol brought up changes that are not
      backward-compatible. Some of those changes (for example
      RFC1583Compatibility flag) can cause a routing loop in mixed
      environments. It therefore requires careful deployment planning, which
      is difficult to achieve in complex multivendor topologies. Most
      importantly, the lack of standard extendable mechanism that facilitates
      the deployment of non-backward-compatible changes obstructs the
      development of new protocol extensions.</t>

      <t>As a solution for the above described problems, this document
      proposes an extendable mechanism, which guarantees that the
      non-backward-compatible functionality is turned on only when supported
      by all participating routers.</t>

      <t>The proposed mechanism is not new; the existing demand circuit
      functionality <xref target="DEMAND"/> uses the same approach. This
      document simply makes the solution generic.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Method"
             title="Method to deploy non-backward-compatible changes">
      <t>Each participating router advertises the capability of functionality
      that it supports in the Router Information LSA as described in RFC 4970
      <xref target="OSPF-CAP"/>. Routers only turn on a new functionality when
      it is supported by every router within the functionality scope. The
      routers revert back to their original behavior as soon as one
      incompatible device is detected.</t>

      <t>The scope of functionality could be link, area or AS wide. For link
      and area wide, the router accordingly originates a link or area scope RI
      LSA. For AS functionality, an area scope RI LSA is used. To propagate
      compatibility information across area borders, a new LSA type Area
      Information is introduced.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="AI" title="Area Information LSA">
      <t>The Area Border Router inserts a particular capability TLV into an
      Area Information (AI) LSA to signal that at least one router in the
      attached areas does not support the functionality. Therefore, the
      presence of a particular TLV in AI LSA signals the opposite case to the
      presence of the same TLV in RI LSA. The AI LSA origination algorithm is
      very similar to the algorithm of Indication-LSA origination <xref
      target="DEMAND"/> and outlined below in <xref target="AIOrigination"/>.
      The AI LSA format is very similar to RI LSA <xref target="OSPF-CAP"/>.
      In OSPFv2, the AI LSA will be implemented with a new opaque LSA type ID.
      In OSPFv3, the AI LSA will be implemented with a new LSA type function
      code. In both protocols, the AI LSA will have an area flooding scope.
      The exact format of AI LSA is outlined in the sections 3.1 and 3.2.</t>

      <section anchor="OSPFv2AI"
               title="OSPFv2 Area Information (AI) Opaque LSA">
        <t>OSPFv2 routers will advertise an area-scoped Opaque-LSA <xref
        target="OPAQUE"/>. The OSPFv2 Area Information LSA has a Link-State
        type of 10 indicating that the flooding scope is area-local, an Opaque
        type of TBD and Opaque ID of 0.</t>

        <t><figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[
        0                   1                   2                   3
        0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
       +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
       |            LS age             |     Options   |       10      |
       +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
       |      TBD      |                    0                          |
       +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
       |                     Advertising Router                        |
       +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
       |                     LS sequence number                        |
       +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
       |         LS checksum           |             length            |
       +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
       |                                                               |
       +-                            TLVs                             -+
       |                             ...                               |

                    OSPFv2 Area Information Opaque LSA

]]></artwork>
          </figure>The format of the TLVs within the body of an AI LSA is
        defined in <xref target="AI_TLV"/>.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="OSPFv3AI" title="OSPFv3 Area Information (AI) LSA">
        <t>The OSPFv3 Area Information LSA has a function code of TBD while
        the S1/S2 bits are set to 1/0, indicating the area flooding scope for
        the LSA.</t>

        <t>The U bit is set indicating that the OSPFv3 AI LSA should be
        flooded even if it is not understood. The Link State ID (LSID) value
        for this LSA is 0. This is unambiguous since an OSPFv3 router will
        only advertise a single AI LSA per flooding scope.</t>

        <t><figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[        0                   1                   2                   3
        0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
       +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
       |            LS age             |1|0 1|          TBD            |
       +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
       |                       0  (Link State ID)                      |
       +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
       |                       Advertising Router                      |
       +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
       |                       LS sequence number                      |
       +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
       |        LS checksum           |             Length             |
       +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
       |                                                               |
       +-                            TLVs                             -+
       |                             ...                               |

                       OSPFv3 Area Information LSA

]]></artwork>
          </figure></t>

        <t>The format of the TLVs within the body of an AI LSA is defined in
        <xref target="AI_TLV"/>.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="AI_TLV" title="Area Information LSA TLV format">
        <t>The format of the TLVs within the body of an AI LSA is exactly the
        same as the corresponding RI LSA TLV format, which in turn is the same
        as the format used by the Traffic Engineering Extensions to OSPF [TE].
        The LSA payload consists of one or more nested Type/Length/Value (TLV)
        triplets. The format of each TLV is:</t>

        <t><figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[
        0                   1                   2                   3
        0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
       +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
       |              Type             |             Length            |
       +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
       |                            Value...                           |
       +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+

                                TLV Format

]]></artwork>
          </figure>The Length field defines the length of the value portion in
        octets (thus a TLV with no value portion would have a length of 0).
        The TLV is padded to a 4-octet alignment; padding is not included in
        the length field (so a 3-octet value would have a length of 3, but the
        total size of the TLV would be 8 octets). Nested TLVs are also 32-bit
        aligned. For example, a 1-byte value would have the length field set
        to 1, and 3 octets of padding would be added to the end of the value
        portion of the TLV. Unrecognized types are ignored.</t>

        <t>When new Area Information LSA TLV is defined, the specification
        MUST explicitly state whether the TLV is applicable to OSPFv2 only,
        OSPFv3 only, or both OSPFv2 and OSPFv3.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="AIOrigination" title="Area Information LSA origination">
        <t>Through the origination of AI LSAs, information about the existence
        of incapable routers propagates from non-backbone areas, to the
        backbone area and from there to all other areas. The following two
        cases summarize the requirements for an area border router to
        originate AI LSAs:</t>

        <t>1. Suppose an area border router (Router X) is connected to a
        non-backbone OSPF area (Area A). Furthermore, assume that Area A has
        an incapable router i.e. a router LSA without corresponding RI LSA
        TLV. Then Router X should originate the AI LSAs into all other
        directly connected areas, including the backbone area, in accordance
        with the guidelines of <xref target="Limit"/>.</t>

        <t>2. Suppose an area border router (Router X) is connected to the
        backbone OSPF area (Area 0.0.0.0). Furthermore, assume that the
        backbone has an indication of an existing incapable device via
        either</t>

        <t>a) the existence of a router LSA without corresponding RI LSA
        TLV</t>

        <t>or</t>

        <t>b) AI LSAs that have been originated by routers other than Router
        X. Then Router X should originate AI LSAs into all other directly
        connected non-backbone areas, keeping the guidelines of <xref
        target="Limit"/> in mind.</t>

        <section anchor="Limit"
                 title="Limiting Area Information LSA origination">
          <t>The following guidelines should be observed by an area border
          router (Router X) when originating AI LSAs in order to limit their
          number. First, AI LSAs with corresponding TLV are not originated
          into an Area A when A has incapable routers; i.e. router LSAs
          without corresponding RI LSA TLV. Secondly, if another area border
          router has originated an AI LSA with corresponding TLV into Area A,
          and that area border router has a higher OSPF Router ID than Router
          X (same tie-breaker as for forwarding the address origination; see
          Section 12.4.4.1 of <xref target="OSPF"/>), then Router X should not
          originate an AI LSA with corresponding TLV into Area A.</t>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Sync" title="RI LSA coupling with Router-LSA">
      <t>RI LSA is essentially an extension to the router-lsa that overcomes
      it's extendability limitations. In some scenarios there will be a
      requirement to ensure that the latest versions of both LSAs are received
      before further processing of the pair. Therefore we need a mechanism to
      couple the two LSAs together.</t>

      <t>A new X-bit from the OSPF Options Field is introduced to signal to
      wait for the RI LSA arrival before processing the router-lsa. When the
      X-bit is set in a router-lsa, the lsa won't be further processed until
      the corresponding RI LSA with the same LS sequence number becomes
      available.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="LinkLocal"
             title="Capability negotiation before adjacency is fully formed">
      <t>For negotiating link scope capability before adjacency is fully
      formed, link local signaling <xref target="LLS"/> should be used instead
      of RI LSA. An example of such a functionality would be a modification to
      OSPF adjacency formation FSM.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="BackwardCompat" title="Backward Compatibility">
      <t>The mechanism is backward compatible with the existing OSPF
      specification. Setting the U bit in OSPFv3 AI LSA allows LSA propagation
      even if some routers in the area can not decode the LSA content. The
      Opaque LSA specification <xref target="OPAQUE"/> also guarantees the
      propagation of OSPFv2 AI LSA, even if the content is not understood by
      some of the transit routers.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>The following IANA assignments are to be made from existing
      registries:</t>

      <t>The OSPFv2 opaque LSA option type TBD will need to be reserved for
      the OSPFv2 AI opaque LSA via IETF Consensus.</t>

      <t>OSPFv3 LSA Function Codes TBD will need to be reserved for the OSPFv3
      Area Information (AI) LSA via Standards Action.</t>

      <t>IANA allocated X-bit in the "OSPFv2 Options Registry" and "OSPFv3
      Options Registry" as per <xref target="Sync"/>.</t>

      <t>Both Standards Action and IETF Consensus registration procedures are
      described in the update of RFC 2434
      [I-D.narten-iana-considerations-rfc2434bis].</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>This document describes a generic mechanism for deployment of
      non-backward-compatible changes and it introduces Area-Information LSA
      for AS scope compatibility. The security considerations for those
      entities are as critical as the topology information currently
      advertised by the base OSPF protocol. Security considerations for the
      base OSPF protocol are covered in [OSPF] and [OSPFV3].</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>The author would like to acknowledge the helpful comments of Cisco
      OSPF Development team.</t>

      <t>This memo is a product of the OSPF Working Group.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <reference anchor="TE">
        <front>
          <title>Traffic Engineering (TE) Extensions to OSPF Version 2</title>

          <author fullname="D. Katz" initials="D." surname="Katz">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <author fullname="K. Kompella" initials="K." surname="Kompella">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <author fullname="D. Yeung" initials="D." surname="Yeung">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <date month="September" year="2003"/>

          <abstract>
            <t>This document describes extensions to the OSPF protocol version
            2 to support intra-area Traffic Engineering (TE), using Opaque
            Link State Advertisements.</t>
          </abstract>
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="3630"/>

        <format octets="27717"
                target="http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc3630.txt" type="TXT"/>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="OSPF-MIB">
        <front>
          <title>OSPF Version 2 Management Information Base</title>

          <author fullname="D. Joyal" initials="D." surname="Joyal">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <author fullname="P. Galecki" initials="P." surname="Galecki">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <author fullname="S. Giacalone" initials="S." surname="Giacalone">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <author fullname="R. Coltun" initials="R." surname="Coltun">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <author fullname="F. Baker" initials="F." surname="Baker">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <date month="December" year="2006"/>

          <abstract>
            <t>This memo defines a portion of the Management Information Base
            (MIB) for use with network management protocols in TCP/IP-based
            internets. In particular, it defines objects for managing version
            2 of the Open Shortest Path First Routing Protocol. Version 2 of
            the OSPF protocol is specific to the IPv4 address family. Version
            3 of the OSPF protocol is specific to the IPv6 address family.</t>

            <t>This memo obsoletes RFC 1850; however, it is designed to be
            backwards compatible. The functional differences between this memo
            and RFC 1850 are explained in Appendix B. [STANDARDS-TRACK]</t>
          </abstract>
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="4750"/>

        <format octets="222459"
                target="http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc4750.txt" type="TXT"/>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="OPAQUE">
        <front>
          <title>The OSPF Opaque LSA Option</title>

          <author fullname="Rob Coltun" initials="R." surname="Coltun">
            <organization>FORE Systems</organization>

            <address>
              <phone>(703) 245-4543</phone>

              <email>rcoltun@fore.com</email>
            </address>
          </author>

          <date month="July" year="1998"/>

          <area>Routing</area>

          <keyword>open shortest-path first protocol</keyword>

          <keyword>OSPF</keyword>
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="2370"/>

        <format octets="33789"
                target="http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc2370.txt" type="TXT"/>

        <format octets="47298"
                target="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/html/rfc2370.html"
                type="HTML"/>

        <format octets="34341"
                target="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/xml/rfc2370.xml"
                type="XML"/>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="OSPF">
        <front>
          <title>OSPF Version 2</title>

          <author fullname="John Moy" initials="J." surname="Moy">
            <organization>Ascend Communications, Inc.</organization>

            <address>
              <postal>
                <street>1 Robbins Road</street>

                <city>Westford</city>

                <region>MA</region>

                <code>01886</code>
              </postal>

              <phone>978-952-1367</phone>

              <facsimile>978-392-2075</facsimile>

              <email>jmoy@casc.com</email>
            </address>
          </author>

          <date month="April" year="1998"/>

          <area>Routing</area>

          <keyword>open shortest-path first protocol</keyword>

          <keyword>routing</keyword>

          <keyword>OSPF</keyword>

          <abstract>
            <t>This memo documents version 2 of the OSPF protocol. OSPF is a
            link-state routing protocol. It is designed to be run internal to
            a single Autonomous System. Each OSPF router maintains an
            identical database describing the Autonomous System's topology.
            From this database, a routing table is calculated by constructing
            a shortest- path tree.</t>

            <t>OSPF recalculates routes quickly in the face of topological
            changes, utilizing a minimum of routing protocol traffic. OSPF
            provides support for equal-cost multipath. An area routing
            capability is provided, enabling an additional level of routing
            protection and a reduction in routing protocol traffic. In
            addition, all OSPF routing protocol exchanges are
            authenticated.</t>

            <t>The differences between this memo and RFC 2178 are explained in
            Appendix G. All differences are backward-compatible in nature.
            Implementations of this memo and of RFCs 2178, 1583, and 1247 will
            interoperate.</t>

            <t>Please send comments to ospf@gated.cornell.edu.</t>
          </abstract>
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="STD" value="54"/>

        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="2328"/>

        <format octets="447367"
                target="http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc2328.txt" type="TXT"/>

        <format octets="466915"
                target="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/html/rfc2328.html"
                type="HTML"/>

        <format octets="446761"
                target="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/xml/rfc2328.xml"
                type="XML"/>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="OSPF-CAP">
        <front>
          <title>Extensions to OSPF for Advertising Optional Router
          Capabilities</title>

          <author fullname="A. Lindem" initials="A." surname="Lindem">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <author fullname="N. Shen" initials="N." surname="Shen">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <author fullname="JP. Vasseur" initials="JP." surname="Vasseur">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <author fullname="R. Aggarwal" initials="R." surname="Aggarwal">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <author fullname="S. Shaffer" initials="S." surname="Shaffer">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <date month="July" year="2007"/>

          <abstract>
            <t>It is useful for routers in an OSPFv2 or OSPFv3 routing domain
            to know the capabilities of their neighbors and other routers in
            the routing domain. This document proposes extensions to OSPFv2
            and OSPFv3 for advertising optional router capabilities. A new
            Router Information (RI) Link State Advertisement (LSA) is proposed
            for this purpose. In OSPFv2, the RI LSA will be implemented with a
            new opaque LSA type ID. In OSPFv3, the RI LSA will be implemented
            with a new LSA type function code. In both protocols, the RI LSA
            can be advertised at any of the defined flooding scopes (link,
            area, or autonomous system (AS)). [STANDARDS-TRACK]</t>
          </abstract>
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="4970"/>

        <format octets="26416"
                target="http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc4970.txt" type="TXT"/>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="OSPFV3">
        <front>
          <title>OSPF for IPv6</title>

          <author fullname="R. Coltun" initials="R." surname="Coltun">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <author fullname="D. Ferguson" initials="D." surname="Ferguson">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <author fullname="J. Moy" initials="J." surname="Moy">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <author fullname="A. Lindem" initials="A." surname="Lindem">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <date month="July" year="2008"/>

          <abstract>
            <t>This document describes the modifications to OSPF to support
            version 6 of the Internet Protocol (IPv6). The fundamental
            mechanisms of OSPF (flooding, Designated Router (DR) election,
            area support, Short Path First (SPF) calculations, etc.) remain
            unchanged. However, some changes have been necessary, either due
            to changes in protocol semantics between IPv4 and IPv6, or simply
            to handle the increased address size of IPv6. These modifications
            will necessitate incrementing the protocol version from version 2
            to version 3. OSPF for IPv6 is also referred to as OSPF version 3
            (OSPFv3).</t>

            <t>Changes between OSPF for IPv4, OSPF Version 2, and OSPF for
            IPv6 as described herein include the following. Addressing
            semantics have been removed from OSPF packets and the basic Link
            State Advertisements (LSAs). New LSAs have been created to carry
            IPv6 addresses and prefixes. OSPF now runs on a per-link basis
            rather than on a per-IP-subnet basis. Flooding scope for LSAs has
            been generalized. Authentication has been removed from the OSPF
            protocol and instead relies on IPv6's Authentication Header and
            Encapsulating Security Payload (ESP).</t>

            <t>Even with larger IPv6 addresses, most packets in OSPF for IPv6
            are almost as compact as those in OSPF for IPv4. Most fields and
            packet- size limitations present in OSPF for IPv4 have been
            relaxed. In addition, option handling has been made more
            flexible.</t>

            <t>All of OSPF for IPv4's optional capabilities, including demand
            circuit support and Not-So-Stubby Areas (NSSAs), are also
            supported in OSPF for IPv6. [STANDARDS-TRACK]</t>
          </abstract>
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="5340"/>

        <format octets="225664"
                target="http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc5340.txt" type="TXT"/>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="LLS">
        <front>
          <title>OSPF Link-Local Signaling</title>

          <author fullname="A. Zinin" initials="A." surname="Zinin">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <author fullname="A. Roy" initials="A." surname="Roy">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <author fullname="L. Nguyen" initials="L." surname="Nguyen">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <author fullname="B. Friedman" initials="B." surname="Friedman">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <author fullname="D. Yeung" initials="D." surname="Yeung">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <date month="August" year="2009"/>

          <abstract>
            <t>OSPF is a link-state intra-domain routing protocol. OSPF
            routers exchange information on a link using packets that follow a
            well-defined fixed format. The format is not flexible enough to
            enable new features that need to exchange arbitrary data. This
            document describes a backward-compatible technique to perform
            link-local signaling, i.e., exchange arbitrary data on a link.
            This document replaces the experimental specification published in
            RFC 4813 to bring it on the Standards Track.</t>
          </abstract>
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="5613"/>

        <format octets="23092"
                target="http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc5613.txt" type="TXT"/>
      </reference>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119"?>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <reference anchor="DEMAND">
        <front>
          <title abbrev="OSPF over Demand Circuits">Extending OSPF to Support
          Demand Circuits</title>

          <author fullname="John Moy" initials="J." surname="Moy">
            <organization>Cascade Communications Corp.</organization>

            <address>
              <postal>
                <street>5 Carlisle Road</street>

                <city>Westford</city>

                <region>MA</region>

                <code>01886</code>

                <country>US</country>
              </postal>

              <phone>+1 508 692 2600 x394</phone>

              <facsimile>+1 508 692 9214</facsimile>

              <email>jmoy@casc.com</email>
            </address>
          </author>

          <date month="April" year="1995"/>

          <abstract>
            <t>This memo defines enhancements to the OSPF protocol that allow
            efficient operation over "demand circuits". Demand circuits are
            network segments whose costs vary with usage; charges can be based
            both on connect time and on bytes/packets transmitted. Examples of
            demand circuits include ISDN circuits, X.25 SVCs, and dial-up
            lines. The periodic nature of OSPF routing traffic has until now
            required a demand circuit's underlying data-link connection to be
            constantly open, resulting in unwanted usage charges. With the
            modifications described herein, OSPF Hellos and the refresh of
            OSPF routing information are suppressed on demand circuits,
            allowing the underlying data-link connections to be closed when
            not carrying application traffic.</t>

            <t>Demand circuits and regular network segments (e.g., leased
            lines) are allowed to be combined in any manner. In other words,
            there are no topological restrictions on the demand circuit
            support. However, while any OSPF network segment can be defined as
            a demand circuit, only point-to-point networks receive the full
            benefit. When broadcast and NBMA networks are declared demand
            circuits, routing update traffic is reduced but the periodic
            sending of Hellos is not, which in effect still requires that the
            data-link connections remain constantly open.</t>

            <t>While mainly intended for use with cost-conscious network links
            such as ISDN, X.25 and dial-up, the modifications in this memo may
            also prove useful over bandwidth-limited network links such as
            slow-speed leased lines and packet radio.</t>

            <t>The enhancements defined in this memo are backward-compatible
            with the OSPF specification defined in, and with the OSPF
            extensions defined in(OSPF NSSA areas),(MOSPF) and(OSPF
            Point-to-MultiPoint Interface).</t>

            <t>This memo provides functionality similar to that specified for
            RIP in, with the main difference being the way the two proposals
            handle oversubscription (see Sections 4.3 and 7 below). However,
            because OSPF employs link-state routing technology as opposed to
            RIP's Distance Vector base, the mechanisms used to achieve the
            demand circuit functionality are quite different.</t>

            <t>Please send comments to ospf@gated.cornell.edu.</t>
          </abstract>
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="1793"/>

        <format octets="78728"
                target="http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc1793.txt" type="TXT"/>
      </reference>
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
