<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<?rfc strict='no'?>
<?rfc iprnotified='no'?>
<rfc category="info" docName="draft-templin-mif-ironapp-00.txt"
     ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="IRON">IRON Applicability for Multiple Interface
    Nodes</title>

    <author fullname="Fred L. Templin" initials="F." role="editor"
            surname="Templin">
      <organization>Boeing Research &amp; Technology</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>P.O. Box 3707 MC 7L-49</street>

          <city>Seattle</city>

          <region>WA</region>

          <code>98124</code>

          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>

        <email>fltemplin@acm.org</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date day="04" month="January" year="2012" />

    <workgroup>Network Working Group</workgroup>

    <keyword>I-D</keyword>

    <keyword>Internet-Draft</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>The Internet Routing Overlay Network (IRON) is a new internetworking
      and routing architecture that addresses important issues including
      routing scaling, network renumbering, mobility management, mobile
      networks, multihoming, traffic engineering, NAT traversal and security.
      In this document, we focus on IRON's applicability for multiple
      interface (mif) nodes.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section anchor="intro" title="Introduction">
      <t>The Internet Routing Overlay Network (IRON) <xref
      target="IRON"></xref> is a new internetworking and routing architecture
      that addresses numerous important issues including routing scaling,
      network renumbering, mobility management, mobile networks, multihoming,
      traffic engineering, NAT traversal and security. IRON further provides a
      new interface type that augments the collection of interfaces available
      to a multiple interface (mif) node.</t>

      <t>Mif nodes are presented with the problem of managing a collection of
      multiple interfaces; each of which connects to an Internet Service
      Provider (ISP) and its respective provisioning domain <xref
      target="RFC6418"></xref><xref target="RFC6419"></xref>. Each such ISP
      interface receives a configuration that is specific to the ISP's
      provisioning domain, including network-layer addresses and prefixes, DNS
      server addresses, etc. In operational practice, the mif node may receive
      overlapping provisioning information, e.g., if multiple ISPs supply the
      node with configuration information from the same private addressing
      plan. Moreover, each ISP interface's provisioning information may change
      over time, e.g., if the node is mobile. It is therefore essential that
      the mif node select the correct interface for communications with
      services within a specific ISP provisioning domain and/or with
      correspondents in the global Internet.</t>

      <t>In this document, we focus on IRON's applicability for mif nodes with
      these ISP interface characteristics. We show that IRON presents a new
      interface type that complements the mif node's ISP interface collection,
      i.e., the mif node need not use the IRON interface exclusively but
      instead views it as "just another interface" albeit with certain
      desirable properties not commonly supported by ISP interfaces. IRON
      further observes the Internet Protocol (IP) standards <xref
      target="RFC0791"></xref><xref target="RFC2460"></xref>, i.e., the same
      as for ordinary ISP interfaces.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="iron" title="The IRON Interface">
      <t>The IRON interface is a non-broadcast, multiple access (NBMA) tunnel
      virtual interface that is configured over one or several ISP interfaces
      and coordinated with a Virtual Service Provider (VSP) server that may or
      may not be independent of any of the mif node's ISPs. Example ISPs
      include 3GPP and BBF providers, but the IRON domain of applicability
      extends to all ISP network connection interface types. While the IRON
      interface is configured over ISP interfaces, it appears to the mif node
      as "just another interface" in addition to the ISP interfaces.</t>

      <t>IRON is based on Virtual Enterprise Traversal (VET) <xref
      target="INTAREA-VET"></xref>, the Subnetwork Encapsulation and
      Adaptation Layer (SEAL) <xref target="INTAREA-SEAL"></xref> and
      Asymmetric Extended Route Optimization <xref target="AERO"></xref> as
      its functional building blocks. VET defines the IRON NBMA tunnel virtual
      interface model and specifies autoconfiguration and internetworking
      operation over the interface (including IRON interface neighbor
      coordination). SEAL specifies the encapsulation format used by the IRON
      interface for deterministic error messaging as well as optional
      authentication, integrity and anti-replay capabilities. Finally, AERO
      specifies a route optimization capability that the mif node can use to
      dynamically discover an IRON interface neighbor that is close to the
      final destination.</t>

      <t>The IRON interface receives persistent provisioning domain
      configuration information (including IP addresses/prefixes) from a VSP,
      and uses a nearby VSP server located in the Internet as a default router
      for reaching Internet correspondents. The VSP provisioning information
      remains stable even if the mif node's ISP interface configurations
      change. The IRON interface therefore appears as a virtual direct
      connection to the Internet independent of any ISPs as shown in <xref
      target="mifnode"></xref>:</t>

      <t><figure anchor="mifnode" title="MIF Node with IRON Interface">
          <artwork><![CDATA[                         _______________
                        (:::::::::::::::)-.
                    .-(::::::::::::::::::::)
                 .-(::::::::::::::: VSP ::::)-.
                (:::: Internet ::: Server <====)======+
                 ^`-(:::::::::::::::::::::::)-'      ||
            +-------> (::::::::::::::::::) <--+      ||
            |            ^                    |      ||
            |            |                    |      || 
       .-.  |           .v.              .-.  |      ||
    ,-(  _'-v        ,-(  _)-.        ,-(  _)-v      ||
 .-(_    (_  )-.  .-(_    (_  )-.  .-(_    (_  )-.   ||
(__    ISP1    _)(__    ISP2    _)(__    ISP3    _)  ||
   `-(__^___)-'     `-(__^___)-'     `-(__^___)-'    ||
        |                |                |          ||
        +-------+        |         +------+          ||
                |        |         |                 ||
                |        |         |                 ||
             +--v--------v---------v--+              ||
             |  <- ISP Interfaces ->  |              ||
             |                        |              ||
             |        MIF Node        |              ||
             |                        |              ||
             |     IRON Interface ->  <===============+
             +------------------------+]]></artwork>
        </figure>The IRON interface provides the mif node with a stable
      "handle" for connecting to correspondents in the Internet. Since the
      IRON interface configuration remains stable even if the underlying ISP
      interface configurations change, the interface supports mobility
      management, multihoming and traffic engineering. However, the IRON
      interface need not be used for communications between the mif node and
      services within a specific ISP network, since the ISP interface itself
      may be better positioned to access those services.</t>

      <t>A common mif node scenario involves a mobile device such as a handset
      with both 3GPP and WiFi interfaces, where the 3GPP interface connects to
      a cellular service provider and the WiFi interface connects to a
      wireless network serviced by a BBF cable modem provider. In that case,
      the IRON interface can provide simultaneous operation over both
      underlying interfaces even if both interfaces receive overlapping IP
      address and prefix information. This is due to the fact that the IRON
      interface operates based on interface identifiers and not IP addresses
      as the means for keeping the underlying interfaces separate.</t>

      <t>The IRON interface therefore becomes just another candidate for
      interface selection the same as the ISP interfaces, and can be selected
      for communications in which a stable addressing configuration is
      necessary. As a result, the IRON interface is a new interface type that
      should be accounted for by mif node interface selection standards.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="relate" title="Related Work">
      <t>Routing and Addressing in Networks with Global Enterprise Recursion
      (RANGER) <xref target="RFC5720"></xref> examines recursive arrangements
      of enterprise networks that can apply to a very broad set of use-case
      scenarios <xref target="RFC6139"></xref>. These same use-case scenarios
      apply also to IRON.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="iana" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>There are no IANA considerations for this document.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="secure" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>Security considerations appear in the IRON, VET, SEAL and AERO
      documents.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="ack" title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>This work was motivated through discussions on the IETF Multiple
      Interfaces (mif) working group mailing list.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc rfcedstyle="no" ?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.0791"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2460"?>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6418"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6419"?>

      <!--     <?rfc include="reference.I-D.templin-aero"?> -->

      <reference anchor="AERO">
        <front>
          <title>Asymmetric Extended Route Optimization (AERO)</title>

          <author fullname="Fred Templin" initials="F" role="editor"
                  surname="Templin">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date day="19" month="December" year="2011" />

          <abstract>
            <t>Nodes (i.e., gateways, routers and hosts) attached to link
            types such as multicast-capable, shared media and non-broadcast
            multiple access (NBMA), etc. can exchange packets as neighbors on
            the link. Each node should therefore be able to discover a
            neighboring gateway that can provide default routing services to
            reach off-link destinations, and should also accept redirection
            messages from the gateway informing it of a neighbor that is
            closer to the final destination. This redirect function can
            provide a useful route optimization, since the triangular path
            from the ingress link neighbor, to the gateway, and finally to the
            egress link neighbor may be considerably longer than the direct
            path between the neighbors. However, ordinary redirection may lead
            to operational issues on certain link types and/or in certain
            deployment scenarios. This document therefore introduces an
            Asymmetric Extended Route Optimization (AERO) capability that
            addresses the issues.</t>
          </abstract>
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="Work in" value="Progress" />
      </reference>

      <!--     <?rfc include="reference.I-D.templin-intarea-seal"?> -->

      <reference anchor="INTAREA-SEAL">
        <front>
          <title>The Subnetwork Encapsulation and Adaptation Layer
          (SEAL)</title>

          <author fullname="Fred Templin" initials="F" role="editor"
                  surname="Templin">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date day="19" month="December" year="2011" />

          <abstract>
            <t>For the purpose of this document, a subnetwork is defined as a
            virtual topology configured over a connected IP network routing
            region and bounded by encapsulating border nodes. These virtual
            topologies are manifested by tunnels that may span multiple IP
            and/or sub-IP layer forwarding hops, and can introduce failure
            modes due to packet duplication and/or links with diverse Maximum
            Transmission Units (MTUs). This document specifies a Subnetwork
            Encapsulation and Adaptation Layer (SEAL) that accommodates such
            virtual topologies over diverse underlying link technologies.</t>
          </abstract>
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="Work in" value="Progress" />
      </reference>

      <!--      <?rfc include="reference.I-D.templin-intarea-vet"?> -->

      <reference anchor="INTAREA-VET">
        <front>
          <title>Virtual Enterprise Traversal (VET)</title>

          <author fullname="Fred Templin" initials="F" role="editor"
                  surname="Templin">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date day="19" month="December" year="2011" />

          <abstract>
            <t>Enterprise networks connect hosts and routers over various link
            types, and often also connect to provider networks and/or the
            global Internet. Enterprise network nodes require a means to
            automatically provision addresses/prefixes and support
            internetworking operation in a wide variety of use cases including
            Small Office, Home Office (SOHO) networks, Mobile Ad hoc Networks
            (MANETs), ISP networks, multi-organizational corporate networks
            and the interdomain core of the global Internet itself. This
            document specifies a Virtual Enterprise Traversal (VET)
            abstraction for autoconfiguration and operation of nodes in
            enterprise networks.</t>
          </abstract>
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="Work in" value="Progress" />
      </reference>

      <!--      <?rfc include="reference.I-D.templin-ironbis"?> -->

      <reference anchor="IRON">
        <front>
          <title>The Internet Routing Overlay Network (IRON)</title>

          <author fullname="Fred Templin" initials="F" role="editor"
                  surname="Templin">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date day="19" month="December" year="2011" />
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="Work in" value="Progress" />
      </reference>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5720"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6139"?>
    </references>

    <?rfc rfcedstyle="yes" ?>
  </back>
</rfc>
