<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<?rfc strict='yes'?>
<rfc category="info" docName="draft-templin-v6ops-isops-04.txt"
     ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="Routing Loop Attack">Operational Guidance for IPv6
    Deployment in IPv4 Sites using ISATAP</title>

    <author fullname="Fred L. Templin" initials="F." surname="Templin">
      <organization>Boeing Research &amp; Technology</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>P.O. Box 3707 MC 7L-49</street>

          <city>Seattle</city>

          <region>WA</region>

          <code>98124</code>

          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>

        <email>fltemplin@acm.org</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date day="20" month="May" year="2011" />

    <keyword>I-D</keyword>

    <keyword>Internet-Draft</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>Many end user sites in the Internet today still have predominantly
      IPv4 internal infrastructures. These sites range in size from small
      home/office networks to large corporate enterprise networks, but share
      the commonality that IPv4 continues to provide satisfactory internal
      routing and addressing services for most applications. As more and more
      IPv6-only services are deployed in the Internet, however, end user
      devices within such sites will increasingly require at least basic IPv6
      functionality for external access. It is also expected that more and
      more IPv6-only devices will be deployed within the site over time. This
      document therefore provides operational guidance for deployment of IPv6
      within predominantly IPv4 sites using the Intra-Site Automatic Tunnel
      Addressing Protocol (ISATAP).</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>End user sites in the Internet today currently use IPv4 routing and
      addressing internally for core operating functions such as web browsing,
      filesharing, network printing, e-mail, teleconferencing and numerous
      other site-internal networking services. Such sites typically have an
      abundance of public or private IPv4 addresses for internal networking,
      and are separated from the public Internet by firewalls, packet
      filtering gateways, proxies, address translators and other site border
      demarcation devices. To date, such sites have had little incentive to
      enable IPv6 services internally <xref target="RFC1687"></xref>.</t>

      <t>End-user sites that currently use IPv4 services internally come in
      endless sizes and varieties. For example, a home network behind a
      Network Address Translator (NAT) may consist of a single link supporting
      a few laptops, printers etc. As a larger example, a small business may
      consist of one or a few offices with several networks connecting
      considerably larger numbers of computers, routers, handheld devices,
      printers, faxes, etc. Moving further up the scale, large banks,
      restaurants, major retailers, large corporations, etc. may consist of
      hundreds or thousands of branches worldwide that are tied together in a
      complex global enterprise network. Additional examples include
      personal-area networks, mobile vehicular networks, disaster relief
      networks, tactical military networks, and various forms of Mobile Ad-hoc
      Networks (MANETs). These cases and more are discussed in RANGERS<xref
      target="RFC6139"> </xref>.</t>

      <t>With the proliferation of IPv6 devices in the public Internet,
      however, existing IPv4 sites will increasingly require a means for
      enabling IPv6 services so that hosts within the site can communicate
      with IPv6-only correspondents. Such services must be deployable with
      minimal configuration, and in a fashion that will not cause disruptions
      to existing IPv4 services. The Intra-Site Automatic Tunnel Addressing
      Protocol (ISATAP) <xref target="RFC5214"></xref> provides a
      simple-to-use service that sites can deploy in the near term to meet
      these requirements. This document therefore provides operational
      guidance for using ISATAP to enable IPv6 services within predominantly
      IPv4 sites while causing no disruptions to existing IPv4 services.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Enabling IPv6 Services using ISATAP">
      <t>Many existing sites within the Internet predominantly use IPv4-based
      services for their internal networking needs, but there is a growing
      requirement for enabling IPv6 services to support communications with
      IPv6-only correspondents. Smaller sites that wish to enable IPv6
      typically arrange to obtain public IPv6 prefixes from an Internet
      Service Provider (ISP), where the prefixes may be either purely native
      or the near-native prefixes offered by 6rd <xref
      target="RFC5969"></xref>. Larger sites typically obtain provider
      independent IPv6 prefixes from an Internet registry and advertise the
      prefixes into the IPv6 routing system on their own behalf, i.e., they
      act as an ISP unto themselves. In either case, after obtaining IPv6
      prefixes the site can automatically enable IPv6 services internally by
      configuring ISATAP.</t>

      <t>The ISATAP service uses a Non-Broadcast, Multiple Access (NBMA)
      tunnel virtual interface model <xref target="RFC2491"></xref><xref
      target="RFC2529"></xref> based on IPv6-in-IPv4 encapsulation <xref
      target="RFC4213"></xref>. The encapsulation format can further use
      Differentiated Service (DS) <xref target="RFC2983"></xref> and Explicit
      Congestion Notification (ECN) <xref target="RFC3168"></xref> mapping
      between the inner and outer IP headers to ensure expected per-hop
      behavior within well-managed sites.</t>

      <t>The ISATAP service is based on three basic node types known as
      advertising ISATAP routers, non-advertising ISATAP routers and ISATAP
      hosts. Advertising ISATAP routers configure their site-facing ISATAP
      interfaces as advertising router interfaces (see: <xref
      target="RFC4861"></xref>, Section 6.2.2). Non-advertising ISATAP routers
      configure their site-facing ISATAP interfaces as non-advertising router
      interfaces and obtain IPv6 addresses/prefixes via autoconfiguration
      exchanges with advertising ISATAP routers. Finally, ISATAP hosts
      configure their site-facing ISATAP interfaces as simple host interfaces
      and also coordinate their autoconfiguration operations with advertising
      ISATAP routers. In this sense, advertising ISATAP routers are "servers"
      while non-advertising ISATAP routers and ISATAP hosts are "clients" in
      the service model.</t>

      <t>Advertising ISATAP routers arrange to add their IPv4 address to the
      Potential Router List (PRL) within the site name service. The name
      service could be either the DNS or some other site-internal name
      resolution system, but the PRL should be published in such a way that
      ISATAP clients can resolve the name "isatap.domainname" for the
      "domainname" suffix associated with their attached link. For example, if
      the domainname suffix associated with an ISATAP client's attached link
      is "example.com", then the name of the PRL for that link attachment
      point is "isatap.example.com". Alternatively, if the site name service
      is operating without a domainname suffix, then the name of the PRL is
      simply "isatap". (In either case, however, site administrators should
      ensure that the name resolution returns IPv4 addresses of advertising
      ISATAP routers that are topologically close to each ISATAP client
      depending on their locations.)</t>

      <t>After the PRL is published, ISATAP clients within the site will
      automatically perform a standard IPv6 Neighbor Discovery Router
      Solicitation (RS) / Router Advertisement (RA) exchange with advertising
      ISATAP routers <xref target="RFC4861"></xref><xref
      target="RFC5214"></xref>. Each ISATAP client can also test the
      round-trip delays to multiple advertising ISATAP routers listed in the
      PRL during an initial exchange, and select those routers with the
      smallest delays. Alternatively, site administrators could include an
      IPv4 anycast address in the PRL and assign the address to multiple
      advertising ISATAP routers. In that case, IPv4 routing within the site
      would direct the ISATAP client to the nearest advertising ISATAP
      router.</t>

      <t>Following router discovery, ISATAP clients initiate Stateless Address
      AutoConfiguration (SLAAC) <xref target="RFC4862"></xref><xref
      target="RFC5214"></xref>, the Dynamic Host Configuration Protocol for
      IPv6 (DHCPv6) <xref target="RFC3315"></xref> or both.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="SLAAC Services">
      <t>Predominantly IPv4 sites can enable SLAAC services for ISATAP clients
      that need to communicate with IPv6 correspondents. SLAAC services are
      enabled using either the "shared" or "individual" prefix model. In the
      shared prefix model, all advertising ISATAP routers advertise a common
      prefix (e.g., 2001:db8::/64) to ISATAP clients within the site. In the
      individual prefix model, advertising ISATAP router advertise individual
      prefixes (e.g., 2001:db8:0:1::/64, 2001:db8:0:2::/64, 2001:db8:0:3::/64,
      etc.) to ISATAP clients within the site. Note that combinations of the
      shared and individual prefix models are also possible, in which some of
      the site's ISATAP routers advertise shared prefixes and others advertise
      individual prefixes</t>

      <t>The following sections discuss operational considerations for
      enabling ISATAP SLAAC services within predominantly IPv4 sites.</t>

      <section anchor="router-slaac"
               title="Advertising ISATAP Router Behavior">
        <t>Advertising ISATAP routers that support SLAAC services send RA
        messages in response to RS messages received on an advertising ISATAP
        interface. SLAAC services are enabled when advertising ISATAP routers
        advertise non-link-local IPv6 prefixes in Prefix Information Options
        (PIOs) with the A flag set to 1<xref target="RFC4861"></xref>. When
        there are multiple advertising ISATAP routers, the routers can
        advertise a shared IPv6 prefix or individual IPv6 prefixes.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="non-router-slaac"
               title="Non-Advertising ISATAP Router Behavior">
        <t>Non-advertising ISATAP routers that engage in SLAAC behave the same
        as for hosts (see below).</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="host-slaac" title="ISATAP Host Behavior">
        <t>ISATAP hosts resolve the PRL and send RS messages to obtain RA
        messages from an advertising ISATAP router. When the host receives RA
        messages, it uses SLAAC to configure IPv6 addresses from any
        advertised prefixes with the A flag set to 1 as specified in <xref
        target="RFC4862"></xref><xref target="RFC5214"></xref> then assigns
        the addresses to the ISATAP interface. The host also assigns any of
        the advertised prefixes with the L flag set to 1 to the ISATAP
        interface.</t>

        <t>Any IPv6 addresses configured in this fashion and assigned to an
        ISATAP interface are known as ISATAP addresses.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="shared"
               title="Reference Operational Scenario - Shared Prefix Model">
        <t><xref target="shared-prefix-fig"></xref> depicts a reference ISATAP
        network topology for allowing hosts within a predominantly IPv4 site
        to configure ISATAP services using SLAAC with the shared prefix model.
        The scenario shows two advertising ISATAP routers ('A', 'B'), two
        ISATAP hosts ('C', 'D'), and an ordinary IPv6 host ('E') outside of
        the site in a typical deployment configuration. In this model, routers
        'A' and 'B' both advertise the same (shared) IPv6 prefix 2001:db8::/64
        into the IPv6 routing system, and also advertise the prefix to ISATAP
        clients within the site for SLAAC purposes.</t>

        <figure anchor="shared-prefix-fig"
                title="Reference ISATAP Network Topology using Shared Prefix Model">
          <artwork><![CDATA[               .-(::::::::)      2001:db8:1::1
            .-(::: IPv6 :::)-.  +-------------+
           (:::: Internet ::::) | IPv6 Host E |
            `-(::::::::::::)-'  +-------------+
               `-(::::::)-'
   +------------+       +------------+
   |  Router A  |---.---|  Router B  |.
  ,|  (isatap)  |       |  (isatap)  | `\
 . | 192.0.2.1  |       | 192.0.2.1  |   \
 / +------------+       +------------+    \
:  fe80::*:192.0.2.17   fe80::*:192.0.2.33 :
 \  2001:db8::/64        2001:db8::/64    /
  :                                      :
   :                                   :
   +-             IPv4 Site         -+
  ;            (PRL: 192.0.2.1)       :
  |                                   ;
  :                                -+-'
   `-.                              .)
      \                           _)
       `-----+--------)----+'----'
   fe80::*:192.0.2.18         fe80::*:192.0.2.34
 2001:db8::*:192.0.2.18     2001:db8::*:192.0.2.34
  +--------------+           +--------------+
  |   (isatap)   |           |   (isatap)   |
  |    Host C    |           |    Host D    |
  +--------------+           +--------------+

(* == "5efe")
]]></artwork>
        </figure>

        <t>With reference to <xref target="shared-prefix-fig"></xref>,
        advertising ISATAP routers 'A' and 'B' within the IPv4 site connect to
        the IPv6 Internet either directly or via a companion gateway (e.g., as
        shown in <xref target="no-onlink-prefix-fig"></xref>). The routers
        advertise the shared prefix 2001:db8::/64 into the IPv6 Internet
        routing system either as a singleton /64 or as part of a shorter
        aggregated IPv6 prefix if the routing system will not accept prefixes
        as long as a /64. For the purpose of this example, we also assume that
        the IPv4 site is configured within multiple IPv4 subnets - each with
        an IPv4 prefix length of /28.</t>

        <t>Advertising ISATAP routers 'A' and 'B' both configure the IPv4
        anycast address 192.0.2.1, e.g., on a loopback interface, and the site
        administrator places the single IPv4 address 192.0.2.1 in the PRL for
        the site. 'A' and 'B' then both advertise the anycast address/prefix
        into the site's IPv4 routing system so that ISATAP clients can locate
        the router that is topologically closest.</t>

        <t>Advertising ISATAP router 'A' next configures a site-interior IPv4
        interface with address 192.0.2.17 and netmask /28, then configures an
        advertising ISATAP router interface with link-local ISATAP address
        fe80::5efe:192.0.2.17 over the IPv4 interface. In the same fashion,
        'B' configures a site-interior IPv4 interface with address
        192.0.2.33/28, then configures its advertising ISATAP router interface
        with link-local ISATAP address fe80::5efe:192.0.2.33.</t>

        <t>ISATAP host 'C' connects to the site via an IPv4 interface with
        address 192.0.2.18/28, and also configures an ISATAP host interface
        with link-local ISATAP address fe80::5efe:192.0.2.18 over the IPv4
        interface. 'C' next resolves the PRL, and sends an IPv6-in-IPv4
        encapsulated RS message to the IPv4 address 192.0.2.1, where IPv4
        routing will direct it to the closest of either 'A' or 'B'. Assuming
        'A' is closest, 'C' receives an RA from 'A' then configures a default
        IPv6 route with next-hop address fe80::5efe:192.0.2.17 via the ISATAP
        interface and processes the IPv6 prefix 2001:db8::/64 advertised in
        the PIO. If the A flag is set in the PIO, 'C' uses SLAAC to
        automatically configure the ISATAP address 2001:db8::5efe:192.0.2.18
        and assigns the address to the ISATAP interface. If the L flag is set,
        'C' also assigns the prefix 2001:db8::/64 to the ISATAP interface.</t>

        <t>In the same fashion, ISATAP host 'D' configures its IPv4 interface
        with address 192.0.2.34/28 and configures its ISATAP interface with
        link-local ISATAP address fe80::5efe:192.0.2.34. 'D' next performs an
        anycast RS/RA exchange that is serviced by 'B', then uses SLAAC to
        autoconfigure the ISATAP address 2001:db8::5efe:192.0.2.34 and a
        default IPv6 route with next-hop address fe80::5efe:192.0.2.33.
        Finally, IPv6 host 'E' connects to an IPv6 network outside of the
        site. 'E' configures its IPv6 interface in a manner specific to its
        attached IPv6 link, and autoconfigures the IPv6 address
        2001:db8:1::1.</t>

        <t>Following this autoconfiguration, when host 'C' inside the site has
        an IPv6 packet to send to host 'E' outside the site, it prepares the
        packet with source address 2001:db8::5efe:192.0.2.18 and destination
        address 2001:db8:1::1. 'C' then uses IPv6-in-IPv4 encapsulation to
        forward the packet to the link-local address of its default router 'A'
        (i.e., fe80::5efe:192.0.2.17). 'A' in turn decapsulates the packet and
        forwards it into the public IPv6 Internet where it will be conveyed to
        'E' via normal IPv6 routing. In the same fashion, host 'D' uses
        IPv6-in-IPv4 encapsulation via its default router 'B' to send IPv6
        packets to IPv6 Internet hosts such as 'E'.</t>

        <t>When host 'E' outside the site sends IPv6 packets to ISATAP host
        'C' inside the site, the IPv6 routing system may direct the packet to
        either of 'A' or 'B'. If the site is not partitioned internally, the
        router that receives the packet can use ISATAP to statelessly forward
        the packet directly to 'C'. If the site may be partitioned internally,
        however, the packet must first be forwarded to 'C's serving router
        based on IPv6 routing information. This implies that, in a partitioned
        site, the advertising ISATAP routers must connect within a full or
        partial mesh of IPv6 links, and must either run a dynamic IPv6 routing
        protocol or configure static routes so that incoming IPv6 packets can
        be forwarded to the correct serving router.</t>

        <t>In this example, 'A' can configure the IPv6 route
        2001:db8::5efe:192.0.2.32/124 with the IPv6 address of the next hop
        toward 'B' in the mesh network as the next hop, and 'B' can configure
        the IPv6 route 2001:db8::5efe:192.0.2.16/124 with the IPv6 address of
        the next hop toward 'A' as the next hop. (Notice that the /124
        prefixes properly cover the /28 prefix of the IPv4 address that is
        embedded within the IPv6 ISATAP address.) In that case, when 'A'
        receives a packet from the IPv6 Internet with destination address
        2001:db8::5efe:192.0.2.34, it first forwards the packet toward 'B'
        over an IPv6 mesh link. 'B' in turn uses ISATAP to forward the packet
        into the site, where IPv4 routing will direct it to 'D'. In the same
        fashion, when 'B' receives a packet from the IPv6 Internet with
        destination address 2001:db8::5efe:192.0.2.18, it first forwards the
        packet toward 'A' over an IPv6 mesh link. 'A' then uses ISATAP to
        forward the packet into the site, where IPv4 routing will direct it to
        'C'.</t>

        <t>Finally, when host 'C' inside the site connects to host 'D' inside
        the site, it has the option of using the native IPv4 service or the
        ISATAP IPv6-in-IPv4 encapsulation service. When there is operational
        assurance that IPv4 services between the two hosts are available, the
        hosts would be better served to continue to use legacy IPv4 services
        in order to avoid encapsulation overhead and to avoid any IPv4
        protocol-41 filtering middleboxes that may be in the path. If 'C' and
        'D' may be in different IPv4 network partitions, however, IPv6-in-IPv4
        encapsulation should be used with one or both of routers 'A' and 'B'
        serving as intermediate gateways.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="individ"
               title="Reference Operational Scenario - Individual Prefix Model">
        <t><xref target="individ-prefix-fig"></xref> depicts a reference
        ISATAP network topology for allowing hosts within a predominantly IPv4
        site to configure ISATAP services using SLAAC with the individual
        prefix model. The scenario shows two advertising ISATAP routers ('A',
        'B'), two ISATAP hosts ('C', 'D'), and an ordinary IPv6 host ('E')
        outside of the site in a typical deployment configuration. In the
        figure, ISATAP routers 'A' and 'B' both advertise different prefixes
        taken from the aggregated prefix 2001:db8::/48, with 'A' advertising
        2001:db8:0:1::/64 and 'B' advertising 2001:db8:0:2::/64.</t>

        <figure anchor="individ-prefix-fig"
                title="Reference ISATAP Network Topology using Individual Prefix Model">
          <artwork><![CDATA[               .-(::::::::)      2001:db8:1::1
            .-(::: IPv6 :::)-.  +-------------+
           (:::: Internet ::::) | IPv6 Host E |
            `-(::::::::::::)-'  +-------------+
               `-(::::::)-'
   +------------+       +------------+
   |  Router A  |---.---|  Router B  |.
  ,|  (isatap)  |       |  (isatap)  | `\
 . | 192.0.2.1  |       | 192.0.2.1  |   \
 / +------------+       +------------+    \
:  fe80::*:192.0.2.17   fe80::*:192.0.2.33 :
 \ 2001:db8:0:1::/64    2001:db8:0:2::/64  /
  :                                      :
   :                                   :
   +-             IPv4 Site         -+
  ;            (PRL: 192.0.2.1)       :
  |                                   ;
  :                                -+-'
   `-.                              .)
      \                           _)
       `-----+--------)----+'----'
   fe80::*:192.0.2.18         fe80::*:192.0.2.34
2001:db8:0:1::*:192.0.2.18  2001:db8:0:2::*:192.0.2.34
  +--------------+           +--------------+
  |   (isatap)   |           |   (isatap)   |
  |    Host C    |           |    Host D    |
  +--------------+           +--------------+

(* == "5efe")
]]></artwork>
        </figure>

        <t>With reference to <xref target="individ-prefix-fig"></xref>,
        advertising ISATAP routers 'A' and 'B' within the IPv4 site connect to
        the IPv6 Internet either directly or via a companion gateway (e.g., as
        shown in <xref target="no-onlink-prefix-fig"></xref>). Router 'A'
        advertises the individual prefix 2001:db8:0:1::/64 into the IPv6
        Internet routing system, and router 'B' advertises the individual
        prefix 2001:db8:0:2::/64. The routers could instead both advertise a
        shorter shared prefix such as 2001:db8::/48 into the IPv6 routing
        system, but in that case they would need to configure a mesh of IPv6
        links between themselves in the same fashion as described for the
        shared prefix model in Section 3.4. For the purpose of this example,
        we also assume that the IPv4 site is configured within multiple IPv4
        subnets - each with an IPv4 prefix length of /28.</t>

        <t>Advertising ISATAP routers 'A' and 'B' both configure the IPv4
        anycast address 192.0.2.1, e.g., on a loopback interface, and the site
        administrator places the single IPv4 address 192.0.2.1 in the PRL for
        the site. 'A' and 'B' then both advertise the anycast address/prefix
        into the site's IPv4 routing system so that ISATAP clients can locate
        the router that is topologically closest.</t>

        <t>Advertising ISATAP router 'A' next configures a site-interior IPv4
        interface with address 192.0.2.17/28, then configures an advertising
        ISATAP router interface with link-local ISATAP address
        fe80::5efe:192.0.2.17 over the IPv4 interface. In the same fashion,
        'B' configures the IPv4 interface address 192.0.2.33/28, then
        configures its advertising ISATAP router interface with link-local
        ISATAP address fe80::5efe:192.0.2.33.</t>

        <t>ISATAP host 'C' connects to the site via an IPv4 interface with
        address 192.0.2.18/28, and also configures an ISATAP host interface
        with link-local ISATAP address fe80::5efe:192.0.2.18 over the IPv4
        interface. 'C' next resolves the PRL, and sends an IPv6-in-IPv4
        encapsulated RS message to the IPv4 address 192.0.2.1, where IPv4
        routing will direct it to the closest of either 'A' or 'B'. Assuming
        'A' is closest, 'C' receives an RA from 'A' then configures a default
        IPv6 route with next-hop address fe80::5efe:192.0.2.17 via the ISATAP
        interface and processes the IPv6 prefix 2001:db8:0:1::/64 advertised
        in the PIO. If the A flag is set in the PIO, 'C' uses SLAAC to
        automatically configure the ISATAP address
        2001:db8:0:1::5efe:192.0.2.18 and assigns the address to the ISATAP
        interface. If the L flag is set, 'C' also assigns the prefix
        2001:db8:0:1::/64 to the ISATAP interface.</t>

        <t>In the same fashion, ISATAP host 'D' configures its IPv4 interface
        with address 192.0.2.34/28 and configures its ISATAP interface with
        link-local ISATAP address fe80::5efe:192.0.2.34. 'D' next performs an
        anycast RS/RA exchange that is serviced by 'B', then uses SLAAC to
        autoconfigure the ISATAP address 2001:db8:0:2::5efe:192.0.2.34 and a
        default IPv6 route with next-hop address fe80::5efe:192.0.2.33.
        Finally, IPv6 host 'E' connects to an IPv6 network outside of the
        site. 'E' configures its IPv6 interface in a manner specific to its
        attached IPv6 link, and autoconfigures the IPv6 address
        2001:db8:1::1.</t>

        <t>Following this autoconfiguration, when host 'C' inside the site has
        an IPv6 packet to send to host 'E' outside the site, it prepares the
        packet with source address 2001:db8:0:1::5efe:192.0.2.18 and
        destination address 2001:db8:1::1. 'C' then uses IPv6-in-IPv4
        encapsulation to forward the packet to the link-local ISATAP address
        of 'A' (fe80::5efe:192.0.2.17), where 'A' in turn decapsulates the
        packet and forwards it into the public IPv6 Internet where it will be
        conveyed to 'E' via normal IPv6 routing. In the same fashion, host 'D'
        uses IPv6-in-IPv4 encapsulation via its default router 'B' to send
        IPv6 packets to IPv6 Internet hosts such as 'E'.</t>

        <t>When host 'E' outside the site sends IPv6 packets to ISATAP host
        'C' inside the site, the IPv6 routing system will direct the packet to
        'A' since 'A' advertises the individual prefix that matches 'C's
        destination address. 'A' can then use ISATAP to statelessly forward
        the packet directly to 'C'. If 'A' and 'B' both advertise the shared
        shorter prefix 2001:db8::/48 into the IPv6 routing system, however
        packets coming from 'E' may be directed to either 'A' or 'B'. In that
        case, the advertising ISATAP routers must connect within a full or
        partial mesh of IPv6 links the same as for the shared prefix model,
        and must either run a dynamic IPv6 routing protocol or configure
        static routes so that incoming IPv6 packets can be forwarded to the
        correct serving router.</t>

        <t>In this example, 'A' can configure the IPv6 route 2001:db8:0:2::/64
        with the IPv6 address of the next hop toward 'B' in the mesh network
        as the next hop, and 'B' can configure the IPv6 route
        2001:db8:0.1::/64 with the IPv6 address of the next hop toward 'A' as
        the next hop. Then, when 'A' receives a packet from the IPv6 Internet
        with destination address 2001:db8:0:2::5efe:192.0.2.34, it first
        forwards the packet toward 'B' over an IPv6 mesh link. 'B' in turn
        uses ISATAP to forward the packet into the site, where IPv4 routing
        will direct it to 'D'. In the same fashion, when 'B' receives a packet
        from the IPv6 Internet with destination address
        2001:db8:0:1::5efe:192.0.2.18, it first forwards the packet toward 'A'
        over an IPv6 mesh link. 'A' then uses ISATAP to forward the packet
        into the site, where IPv4 routing will direct it to 'C'.</t>

        <t>Finally, when host 'C' inside the site connects to host 'D' inside
        the site, it has the option of using the native IPv4 service or the
        ISATAP IPv6-in-IPv4 encapsulation service. When there is operational
        assurance that IPv4 services between the two hosts are available, the
        hosts would be better served to continue to use legacy IPv4 services
        in order to avoid encapsulation overhead and to avoid any IPv4
        protocol-41 filtering middleboxes that may be in the path. If 'C' and
        'D' may be in different IPv4 network partitions, however, IPv6-in-IPv4
        encapsulation should be used with one or both of routers 'A' and 'B'
        serving as intermediate gateways.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="SLAAC Site Administration Guidance">
        <t>In common practice, firewalls, gateways and packet filtering
        devices of various forms are often deployed in order to divide the
        site into separate partitions. In both the shared and individual
        prefix models described above, the entire site can be represented by
        the aggregate IPv6 prefix assigned to the site, while each site
        partition can be represented by "sliver" IPv6 prefixes taken from the
        aggregate. In order to provide a simple service that does not interact
        poorly with the site topology, site administrators should therefore
        institute an address plan to align IPv6 sliver prefixes with IPv4 site
        partition boundaries.</t>

        <t>For example, in the shared prefix model in <xref
        target="shared"></xref>, the aggregate prefix is 2001:db8::/64, and
        the sliver prefixes are 2001:db8::5efe:192.0.2.0/124,
        2001:db8::5efe:192.0.2.16/124, 2001:db8::5efe:192.0.2.32/124, etc. In
        the individual prefix model in <xref target="individ"></xref>, the
        aggregate prefix is 2001:db8::/48 and the sliver prefixes are
        2001:db8:0:0::/64, 2001:db8:0:1::/64, 2001:db8:0:2::/64, etc.</t>

        <t>When individual prefixes are used, site administrators can
        configure advertising ISATAP routers to advertise different individual
        (sliver) prefixes to different sets of clients, e.g., based on the
        client's IPv4 subnet prefix. When a shared prefix is used, the site
        administrator could instead configure the ISATAP routers to advertise
        the shared (aggregate) prefix with L=0 so that clients will not
        consider any IPv6 addresses derived from the prefix as on-link.</t>

        <t>Site administrators can then institute a policy that prefers native
        IPv4 addresses over ISATAP addresses for communications between
        clients covered by the same sliver prefix. Site administrators
        implement this policy by configuring address selection policy rules
        <xref target="RFC3484"></xref> in each ISATAP client in order to give
        preference to IPv4 destination addresses over destination addresses
        derived from one of the client's IPv6 sliver prefixes.</t>

        <t>For example, each ISATAP client associated with the sliver prefix
        2001:db8::5efe:192.0.2.64/124 can add the prefix to its address
        selection policy table with a lower precedence than the prefix
        ::ffff:0:0/96. In this way, IPv4 addresses are preferred over IPv6
        addresses from within the same sliver. The prefix could be added to
        each ISATAP client either manually, or through an automated service
        such as a DHCP option <xref
        target="I-D.ietf-6man-addr-select-opt"></xref>. In this way, clients
        will use IPv4 communications to reach correspondents within the same
        IPv4 site partition, and will use IPv6 communications to reach
        correspondents in other partitions and/or outside of the site.</t>

        <t>It should be noted that sliver prefixes longer than /64 cannot be
        advertised for SLAAC purposes. Also, sliver prefixes longer than /64
        do not allow for interface identifier rewriting by address
        translators. These factors may favor the individual prefix model in
        some deployment scenarios, while the flexibility afforded by the
        shared prefix model may be more desirable in others.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="loopavoid-slaac" title="Loop Avoidance">
        <t>In sites that provide IPv6 services through ISATAP with SLAAC as
        described in this section, advertising ISATAP routers must take
        operational precautions to avoid routing loops. For example, with
        reference to <xref target="individ-prefix-fig"></xref> an IPv6 packet
        that enters the site via advertising ISATAP router 'A' must not be
        allowed to exit the site via advertising ISATAP router 'B' based on an
        invalid SLAAC address.</t>

        <t>As a simple mitigation, each advertising ISATAP router should drop
        any packets coming from the IPv6 Internet that would be forwarded back
        to the Internet via another advertising router. Additionally, each
        advertising ISATAP router should drop any encapsulated packets
        received from another advertising router that would be forwarded to
        the IPv6 Internet. (Note that IPv6 packets with link-local ISATAP
        addresses are excluded from these checks, since they cannot be
        forwarded by an IPv6 router and may be necessary for router-to-router
        coordinations.) This corresponds to the mitigation documented in
        Section 3.2.3 of <xref target="I-D.ietf-v6ops-tunnel-loops"></xref>,
        but other mitigations specified in that document can also be
        employed.</t>

        <t>Again with reference to <xref target="individ-prefix-fig"></xref>,
        when 'A' receives a packet coming from the IPv6 Internet with
        destination address 2001:db8:1::5efe:192.0.2.2, it drops the packet
        since the IPv4 address 192.0.2.2 corresponds to advertising ISATAP
        router 'B'. Similarly, when 'B' receives a packet coming from the
        tunnel with an IPv6 destination address that would cause the packet to
        be forwarded back out to the IPv6 Internet and with an IPv4 source
        address 192.0.2.1, it drops the packet since 192.0.2.1 corresponds to
        advertising ISATAP router 'A'.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="DHCPv6 Services">
      <t>Whether or not advertising ISATAP routers make stateless IPv6
      services available using SLAAC, they can also provide managed IPv6
      services to ISATAP clients (i.e., both hosts and non-advertising ISATAP
      routers) using the Dynamic Host Configuration Protocol for IPv6
      (DHCPv6). Any addresses/prefixes obtained via DHCPv6 are distinct from
      any IPv6 prefixes advertised on the ISATAP interface for SLAAC purposes,
      however. In this way, DHCPv6 addresses/prefixes are reached by viewing
      the ISATAP tunnel interface as a "transit" rather than viewing it as an
      ordinary IPv6 host interface. We refer to this as the "no prefix"
      model.</t>

      <t>ISATAP nodes employ the source address verification checks specified
      in Section 7.3 of <xref target="RFC5214"></xref> as a prerequisite for
      decapsulation of packets received on an ISATAP interface. In order to
      accommodate direct communications with hosts and non-advertising ISATAP
      routers that use DHCPv6, ISATAP nodes that support route optimization
      must employ an additional source address verification check. Namely, the
      node also considers the outer IPv4 source address correct for the inner
      IPv6 source address if:</t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>a forwarding table entry exists that lists the packet's IPv4
          source address as the link-layer address corresponding to the inner
          IPv6 source address via the ISATAP interface.</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>The following sections discuss operational considerations for
      enabling ISATAP DHCPv6 services within predominantly IPv4 sites.</t>

      <section anchor="router-dhcpv6"
               title="Advertising ISATAP Router Behavior">
        <t>Advertising ISATAP routers that support DHCPv6 services send RA
        messages in response to RS messages received on an advertising ISATAP
        interface. Advertising ISATAP routers also configure either a DHCPv6
        relay or server function to service DHCPv6 requests received from
        ISATAP clients.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="non-router-dhcpv6"
               title="Non-Advertising ISATAP Router Behavior">
        <t>Non-advertising ISATAP routers can acquire IPv6 prefixes, e.g.,
        through the use of DHCPv6 Prefix Delegation <xref
        target="RFC3633"></xref> via an advertising router in the same fashion
        as described for host-based DHCPv6 stateful address autoconfiguration
        in <xref target="host-dhcpv6"></xref>. The advertising router in turn
        maintains IPv6 forwarding table entries that list the IPv4 address of
        the non-advertising router as the link-layer address of the next hop
        toward the delegated IPv6 prefixes.</t>

        <t>In many use case scenarios (e.g., small enterprise networks,
        MANETs, etc.), advertising and non-advertising ISATAP routers can
        engage in a proactive dynamic IPv6 routing protocol (e.g., OSPFv3,
        RIPng, etc.) over their ISATAP interfaces so that IPv6
        routing/forwarding tables can be populated and standard IPv6
        forwarding between ISATAP routers can be used. In other scenarios
        (e.g., large enterprise networks, highly mobile MANETs, etc.), this
        might be impractical dues to scaling issues. When a proactive dynamic
        routing protocol cannot be used, non-advertising ISATAP routers send
        RS messages to obtain RA messages from an advertising ISATAP router,
        i.e., they act as "hosts" on their non-advertising ISATAP
        interfaces.</t>

        <t>After the non-advertising ISATAP router acquires IPv6 prefixes, it
        can sub-delegate them to routers and links within its attached IPv6
        edge networks, then can forward any outbound IPv6 packets coming from
        its edge networks via other ISATAP nodes on the link.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="host-dhcpv6" title="ISATAP Host Behavior">
        <t>ISATAP hosts resolve the PRL and send RS messages to obtain RA
        messages from an advertising ISATAP router. Whether or not IPv6
        prefixes for SLAAC are advertised, the host can acquire IPv6
        addresses, e.g., through the use of DHCPv6 stateful address
        autoconfiguration <xref target="RFC3315"></xref>. To acquire
        addresses, the host performs standard DHCPv6 exchanges while mapping
        the IPv6 "All_DHCP_Relay_Agents_and_Servers" link-scoped multicast
        address to the IPv4 address of an advertising ISATAP router.</t>

        <t>After the host receives IPv6 addresses, it assigns them to its
        ISATAP interface and forwards any of its outbound IPv6 packets via the
        advertising router as a default router. The advertising router in turn
        maintains IPv6 forwarding table entries that list the IPv4 address of
        the host as the link-layer address of the delegated IPv6 addresses.
        Note that IPv6 addresses acquired from DHCPv6 therefore need not be
        ISATAP addresses, i.e., even though the addresses are assigned to the
        ISATAP interface.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="avoidance-fig"
               title="Reference Operational Scenario - No Prefix Model">
        <t><xref target="no-onlink-prefix-fig"></xref> depicts a reference
        ISATAP network topology that uses DHCPv6. The scenario shows two
        advertising ISATAP routers ('A', 'B'), two non-advertising ISATAP
        routers ('C', 'E'), an ISATAP host ('G'), and three ordinary IPv6
        hosts ('D', 'F', 'H') in a typical deployment configuration:</t>

        <figure anchor="no-onlink-prefix-fig"
                title="Reference ISATAP Network Topology using No Prefix Model">
          <artwork><![CDATA[                 .-(::::::::)      2001:db8:3::1
              .-(::: IPv6 :::)-.  +-------------+
             (:::: Internet ::::) | IPv6 Host H |
              `-(::::::::::::)-'  +-------------+
                 `-(::::::)-'
             ,~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~,
        ,----|companion gateway|--.
       /     '~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~'  :
      /                           |.
   ,-'                              `.
  ;  +------------+   +------------+  )
  :  |  Router A  |   |  Router B  |  /
   : |  (isatap)  |   |  (isatap)  |  :    fe80::*192.0.2.6
   : | 192.0.2.1  |   | 192.0.2.1  | ;       2001:db8:2::1
   + +------------+   +------------+  \    +--------------+
  fe80::*:192.0.2.2   fe80::*:192.0.2.3    |   (isatap)   |
  |                                   ;    |    Host G    |
  :              IPv4 Site         -+-'    +--------------+
   `-.       (PRL: 192.0.2.1)       .)
      \                           _)
       `-----+--------)----+'----'
  fe80::*:192.0.2.4        fe80::*:192.0.2.5         .-.
  +--------------+         +--------------+       ,-(  _)-.
  |   (isatap)   |         |   (isatap)   |    .-(_ IPv6  )-.
  |   Router C   |         |   Router E   |--(__Edge Network )
  +--------------+         +--------------+     `-(______)-'
   2001:db8:0::/48          2001:db8:1::/48           |
          |                                     2001:db8:1::1
         .-.                                   +-------------+
      ,-(  _)-.       2001:db8::1              | IPv6 Host F |
   .-(_ IPv6  )-.   +-------------+            +-------------+
 (__Edge Network )--| IPv6 Host D |
    `-(______)-'    +-------------+

(* == "5efe")
]]></artwork>
        </figure>

        <t>In <xref target="no-onlink-prefix-fig"></xref>, advertising ISATAP
        routers 'A' and 'B' within the IPv4 site connect to the IPv6 Internet
        via a companion gateway. (Note that the routers may instead connect to
        the IPv6 Internet directly as shown in <xref
        target="shared-prefix-fig"></xref>. For the purpose of this example,
        we also assume that the IPv4 site is configured within a single IPv4
        subnet.</t>

        <t>Advertising ISATAP routers 'A' and 'B' both configure the IPv4
        anycast address 192.0.2.1, e.g., on a loopback interface, and the site
        administrator places the single IPv4 address 192.0.2.1 in the PRL for
        the site. 'A' and 'B' then both advertise the anycast address/prefix
        into the site's IPv4 routing system so that ISATAP clients can locate
        the router that is topologically closest.</t>

        <t>Advertising ISATAP router 'A' next configures a site-interior IPv4
        interface with address 192.0.2.2, then configures an advertising
        ISATAP router interface with link-local ISATAP address
        fe80::5efe:192.0.2.2 over the IPv4 interface. In the same fashion, 'B'
        configures the IPv4 interface address 192.0.2.3, then configures its
        advertising ISATAP router interface with link-local ISATAP address
        fe80::5efe:192.0.2.3.</t>

        <t>Non-advertising ISATAP router 'C' connects to one or more IPv6 edge
        networks and also connects to the site via an IPv4 interface with
        address 192.0.2.4, but it does not advertise the site's IPv4 anycast
        address/prefix. 'C' next configures a non-advertising ISATAP router
        interface with link-local ISATAP address fe80::5efe:192.0.2.4, then
        discovers router 'A' via an IPv6-in-IPv4 encapsulated RS/RA exchange.
        'C' next receives the IPv6 prefix 2001:db8::/48 through a DHCPv6
        prefix delegation exchange via 'A', then engages in an IPv6 routing
        protocol over its ISATAP interface and announces the delegated IPv6
        prefix. 'C' finally sub-delegates the prefix to its attached edge
        networks, where IPv6 host 'D' autoconfigures the address
        2001:db8::1.</t>

        <t>Non-advertising ISATAP router 'E' connects to the site, configures
        its ISATAP interface, performs an RS/RA exchange, receives a DHCPv6
        prefix delegation, and engages in the IPv6 routing protocol the same
        as for 'C'. In particular, 'E' configures the IPv4 address 192.0.2.5
        and the link-local ISATAP address fe80::5efe:192.0.2.5. 'E' then
        receives the delegated IPv6 prefix 2001:db8:1::/48 and sub-delegates
        the prefix to its attached edge networks, where IPv6 host 'F'
        autoconfigures IPv6 address 2001:db8:1::1.</t>

        <t>ISATAP host 'G' connects to the site via an IPv4 interface with
        address 192.0.2.6, and also configures an ISATAP host interface with
        link-local ISATAP address fe80::5efe:192.0.2.6 over the IPv4
        interface. 'G' next performs an anycast RS/RA exchange to discover 'B"
        and configure a default IPv6 route with next-hop address
        fe80::5efe:192.0.2.3. 'G' then receives the IPv6 address 2001:db8:2::1
        from a DHCPv6 address configuration exchange via 'B'; it then assigns
        the address to the ISATAP interface but does not assign a
        non-link-local IPv6 prefix to the interface.</t>

        <t>Finally, IPv6 host 'H' connects to an IPv6 network outside of the
        ISATAP domain. 'H' configures its IPv6 interface in a manner specific
        to its attached IPv6 link, and autoconfigures the IPv6 address
        2001:db8:3::1.</t>

        <t>Following this autoconfiguration, when host 'D' has an IPv6 packet
        to send to host 'F', it prepares the packet with source address
        2001:db8::1 and destination address 2001:db8:1::1, then sends the
        packet into the edge network where IPv6 forwarding will eventually
        convey it to router 'C'. 'C' then uses IPv6-in-IPv4 encapsulation to
        forward the packet to router 'E', since it has discovered a route to
        2001:db8:1::/48 with next hop 'E' via dynamic routing over the ISATAP
        interface. Router 'E' finally sends the packet into the edge network
        where IPv6 forwarding will eventually convey it to host 'F'.</t>

        <t>In a second scenario, when 'D' has a packet to send to ISATAP host
        'G', it prepares the packet with source address 2001:db8::1 and
        destination address 2001:db8:2::1, then sends the packet into the edge
        network where it will eventually be forwarded to router 'C' the same
        as above. 'C' then uses IPv6-in-IPv4 encapsulation to forward the
        packet to router 'A' (i.e., 'C's default router), which in turn
        forwards the packet to 'G'. Note that this operation entails two hops
        across the ISATAP link (i.e., one from 'C' to 'A', and a second from
        'A' to 'G'). If 'G' also participates in the dynamic IPv6 routing
        protocol, however, 'C' could instead forward the packet directly to
        'G' without involving 'A'.</t>

        <t>In a third scenario, when 'D' has a packet to send to host 'H' in
        the IPv6 Internet, the packet is forwarded to 'C' the same as above.
        'C' then forwards the packet to 'A', which forwards the packet into
        the IPv6 Internet.</t>

        <t>In a final scenario, when 'G' has a packet to send to host 'H' in
        the IPv6 Internet, the packet is forwarded directly to 'B', which
        forwards the packet into the IPv6 Internet.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="predirect" title="On-Demand Dynamic Routing for DHCP">
        <t>With respect to the reference operational scenarios depicted in
        <xref target="no-onlink-prefix-fig"></xref>, there may be use cases in
        which a proactive dynamic IPv6 routing protocol cannot be used. For
        example, in large enterprise network deployments it would be
        impractical for all ISATAP routers to engage in a common routing
        protocol instance due to scaling considerations.</t>

        <t>In those cases, an on-demand routing capability can be enabled in
        which ISATAP nodes send initial packets via an advertising ISATAP
        router and receive redirection messages back. For example, when a
        non-advertising ISATAP router 'C' has a packet to send to a host
        located behind non-advertising ISATAP router 'E', it can send the
        initial packets via advertising router 'A' which will return
        redirection messages to inform 'C' that 'E' is a better first hop.
        Protocol details for this redirection procedure (including a means for
        detecting whether the direct path is usable) are specified in <xref
        target="I-D.templin-aero"></xref>.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="loopavoid-dhcp" title="Loop Avoidance">
        <t>In a purely DHCPv6-based ISATAP deployment, no non-link-local IPv6
        prefixes are assigned to ISATAP router interfaces. Therefore, an
        ISATAP router cannot mistake another router for an ISATAP host due to
        an address that matches an on-link prefix. This corresponds to the
        mitigation documented in Section 3.2.4 of <xref
        target="I-D.ietf-v6ops-tunnel-loops"></xref>.</t>

        <t>Any routing loops introduced in the DHCPv6 scenario would therefore
        be due to a misconfiguration in IPv6 routing the same as for any IPv6
        router, and hence are out of scope for this document.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="scaling" title="Scaling Considerations">
      <t>Sections 3 and 4 depict ISATAP network topologies with only two
      advertising ISATAP routers within the site. In order to support larger
      numbers of ISATAP clients (and/or multiple site partitions), the site
      can deploy more advertising ISATAP routers to support load balancing and
      generally shortest-path routing.</t>

      <t>Such an arrangement requires that the advertising ISATAP routers
      participate in an IPv6 routing protocol instance so that IPv6
      addresses/prefixes can be mapped to the correct ISATAP router. The
      routing protocol instance can be configured as either a full mesh
      topology involving all advertising ISATAP routers, or as a partial mesh
      topology with each advertising ISATAP router associating with one or
      more companion gateways. Each such companion gateway would in turn
      participate in a full mesh between all companion gateways.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Site Renumbering Considerations">
      <t>Advertising ISATAP routers distribute IPv6 prefixes to ISATAP clients
      within the site via DHCPv6 and/or SLAAC. If the site subsequently
      reconnects to a different ISP, however, the site must renumber to use
      addresses derived from the new IPv6 prefixes <xref
      target="RFC1900"></xref><xref target="RFC4192"></xref><xref
      target="RFC5887"></xref>.</t>

      <t>For IPv6 services provided by SLAAC, site renumbering in the event of
      a change in an ISP-served IPv6 prefix entails a simple renumbering of
      IPv6 addresses and/or prefixes that are assigned to the ISATAP
      interfaces of clients within the site. In some cases, filtering rules
      (e.g., within site border firewall filtering tables) may also require
      renumbering, but this operation can be automated and limited to only one
      or a few administrative "touch points".</t>

      <t>In order to renumber the ISATAP interfaces of clients within the site
      using SLAAC, advertising ISATAP routers need only schedule the services
      offered by the old ISP for deprecation and begin to advertise the IPv6
      prefixes provided by the new ISP. ISATAP client interface address
      lifetimes will eventually expire, and the host will renumber its
      interfaces with addresses derived from the new prefixes. ISATAP clients
      should also eventually remove any deprecated SLAAC prefixes from their
      address selection policy tables, but this action is not
      time-critical.</t>

      <t>Finally, site renumbering in the event of a change in an ISP-served
      IPv6 prefix further entails locating and rewriting all IPv6 addresses in
      naming services, databases, configuration files, packet filtering rules,
      documentation, etc. If the site has published the IPv6 addresses of any
      site-internal nodes within the public Internet DNS system, then the
      corresponding resource records will also need to be updated during the
      renumbering operation. This can be accomplished via secure dynamic
      updates to the DNS.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Path MTU Considerations">
      <t>IPv6-in-IPv4 encapsulation overhead effectively reduces the size of
      IPv6 packets that can traverse the tunnel in relation to the actual
      Maximum Transmission Unit (MTU) of the underlying IPv4 network path
      between the encapsulator and decapsulator. Two methods for accommodating
      IPv6 path MTU discovery over IPv6-in-IPv4 tunnels (i.e., the static and
      dynamic methods) are documented in Section 3.2 of <xref
      target="RFC4213"></xref>.</t>

      <t>The static method places a "safe" upper bound on the size of IPv6
      packets permitted to enter the tunnel, however the method can be overly
      conservative when larger IPv4 path MTUs are available. The dynamic
      method can accommodate much larger IPv6 packet sizes in some cases, but
      can fail silently if the underlying IPv4 network path does not return
      the necessary error messages.</t>

      <t>This document notes that sites that include well-managed IPv4 links,
      routers and other network middleboxes are candidates for use of the
      dynamic MTU determination method, which may provide for a better
      operational IPv6 experience in the presence of IPv6-in-IPv4 tunnels. The
      dynamic MTU determination method can potentially also present a larger
      MTU to IPv6 correspondents outside of the site, since IPv6 path MTU
      discovery is considered robust even over the wide area in the public
      IPv6 Internet.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Anycast Considerations">
      <t>When an advertising ISATAP router configures an IPv4 anycast address,
      and site administrators place the address in the PRL, the router uses
      the anycast address as the IPv4 source address for all IPv6-in-IPv4
      encapsulated packets it sends. However, the router must also derive its
      ISATAP link-local addresses from an IPv4 unicast address assigned to an
      underlying IPv4 interface instead of from the anycast address.</t>

      <t>For example, if an advertising ISATAP router configures the IPv4
      anycast address 192.0.2.1 and also configures an ordinary IPv4 interface
      with IPv4 unicast address 192.0.2.91, the router must configure the
      ISATAP link-local address fe80::5efe:192.0.2.91 and use this address as
      the IPv6 source / destination address in link-local messages it
      exchanges with other ISATAP nodes.</t>

      <t>This arrangement is necessary so that ISATAP clients can
      unambiguously differentiate advertising ISATAP routers. Furthermore,
      since the IPv4 anycast source address is a member of the PRL, ISATAP
      clients will accept any messages coming from the advertising router even
      though the IPv4 source address does not match the IPv4 address embedded
      in the IPv6 source address.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Alternative Approaches">
      <t><xref target="RFC4554"></xref> proposes a use of VLANs for IPv4-IPv6
      coexistence in enterprise networks. The ISATAP approach provides a more
      flexible and broadly-applicable alternative, and with fewer
      administrative touch points.</t>

      <t>The tunnel broker service <xref target="RFC3053"></xref> uses
      point-to-point tunnels that require end users to establish an explicit
      administrative configuration of the tunnel far end, which may be outside
      of the administrative boundaries of the site.</t>

      <t>6to4 <xref target="RFC3056"></xref> and Teredo <xref
      target="RFC4380"></xref> provide "last resort" unmanaged automatic
      tunneling services when no other means for IPv6 connectivity is
      available. These services are given lower priority when the ISATAP
      managed service and/or native IPv6 services are enabled.</t>

      <t>IRON <xref target="RFC6179"></xref>, RANGER <xref
      target="RFC5720"></xref>, VET <xref target="RFC5558"></xref> and SEAL
      <xref target="RFC5320"></xref> are a tribute to those in all walks of
      life who serve with dignity and honor for the benefit of others.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>This document has no IANA considerations.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>In addition to the security considerations documented in <xref
      target="RFC5214"></xref>, sites that use ISATAP should take care to
      ensure that no routing loops are enabled <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-v6ops-tunnel-loops"></xref>. Additional security
      concerns with IP tunneling are documented in <xref
      target="RFC6169"></xref>.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="acknowledge" title="Acknowledgments">
      <t>The following are acknowledged for their insights that helped shape
      this work: Fred Baker, Brian Carpenter, Thomas Henderson, Philip
      Homburg, Lee Howard, Ray Hunter, Joel Jaeggli, Gabi Nakibly, Hemant
      Singh, Mark Smith, Ole Troan, Gunter Van de Velde, ...</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5214"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.1918"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4861"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4862"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4213"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3315"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3633"?>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6139"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.1900"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4192"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5887"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.1687"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5969"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2491"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2529"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4554"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3053"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3056"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4380"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5320"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5558"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5720"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6169"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6179"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2983"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3168"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3484"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.I-D.ietf-v6ops-tunnel-loops"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.I-D.ietf-6man-addr-select-opt"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.I-D.templin-aero"?>
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
