<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">

<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc iprnotified="no"?>
<?rfc strict="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?> 
<?rfc subcompact="yes" ?>


<rfc category="info" ipr="trust200902" docName="draft-liu-i2rs-architecture-01">
<front>
<title abbrev="i2rs architecture">Architecture Discussion of I2RS</title>

<author initials="D." surname="Liu" fullname="Dapeng Liu">
  <organization>China Mobile</organization>
  <address>
    <postal>
      <street>Unit2, 28 Xuanwumenxi Ave,Xuanwu District</street>
      <city>Beijing 100053</city>
      <country>China</country>
    </postal>
    <email>liudapeng@chinamobile.com
    </email>
  </address>
</author>


<author initials="B." surname="Khasnabish" fullname="Bhumip Khasnabish">
  <organization>ZTE</organization>
  <address>
    <postal>
          <street>55 Madison Avenue, Suite 160</street>
          <city>Morristown</city>
          <region>New Jersey</region>
          <code>07960</code>
          <country>USA </country>
     </postal>
      <phone>+001-781-752-8003</phone>
      <email>vumip1@gmail.com, bhumip.khasnabish@zteusa.com</email>
  </address>
</author>


<author initials="H." surname="Deng" fullname="Hui Deng">
  <organization>China Mobile</organization><address>
  <postal>
  <street>Unit2, 28 Xuanwumenxi Ave,Xuanwu District</street><city>Beijing 100053</city><country>China</country></postal>
  <email>denghui@chinamobile.com</email></address>
</author>



<date month="July" year="2013"/><area></area><workgroup>I2RS</workgroup>

 <abstract>
  <t>
    This document discusses the high level architecture of I2RS. We plan to include discussion on 
    virtualization, service chaining, and grouping in a future version of this draft. 
  </t>
</abstract>
</front>

<middle>
<section anchor="intro" title="Introduction">
  <t>
    This document discusses the high level architecture of I2RS.
    As illustrated in figure 1, the I2RS architecture is composed by three types of building blocks.
    The first type of the building block is the user of I2RS interface. The users could be 
    network controllers, network management functions, other user applications etc. The user application uses 
    the I2RS interface interacts with the routing system. The second type of the building block is management 
    functions. This include configuration management function and security management function. The configuration management
    function is used to configure the I2RS interface. The security function is used to enforce the security polices of 
    the I2RS interface. The third type of the building block is routing function. This build block includes routing 
    information base, IP forwarding table etc. The routing information base could be accessed by the I2RS users using 
    the I2RS interface.        
  </t>

   <t>Figure 1 architecture of I2RS </t>
    <figure align="center" anchor="xml_happy">
       
        <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[

+------------------+  +------------------+  +-----------------+
|Network Controller|  |Network Management|  | User Application|..
+------------------+  +------------------+  +-----------------+
            |               | |                     |
            \---------------| |--------------------/
                            | | I2RS Interface
+----------------------+    | |     +------------------+
|Configuration Function|----| |-----|Security Function |
+----------------------+    | |     +------------------+
                            | |
                            | |                 Routing Function
+---------------------------| |--------------------------------+
|                           | |                                |
|   +------------+          | |             +-----------+      |
|   |OSPF process|          | |             |BGP process| ...  |
|   +------------+          | |             +-----------+      |
|          |                | |                   |            |
|          |     +------------------------+       |            |                  
|          +-----|Routing Information Base|-------+            |
|                +------------------------+                    |
|                           |                                  |
+---------------------------|----------------------------------+
                            |
 {OF, ForCES, .. Protocol}  |               Forwarding Function
+---------------------------|----------------------------------+
|                           |                                  |
|                           |                                  |
|                   +--------------------+                     |
|                   | IP Forwarding Table|                     |
|                   +--------------------+                     |
|                                                              |
+--------------------------------------------------------------+

            ]]></artwork>
      </figure>
     
</section>



<section title="Conventions used in this document">
<t>
The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in RFC-2119 [RFC2119]. 
</t>
<t>
In this document, these words will appear with that interpretation only when in ALL CAPS. Lower case uses of these words are not to be interpreted as carrying RFC-2119 significance.
</t>
   
<t>
A list of acronyms and abbreviations used in this document are presented below.
</t>

<t>
  <list style='symbols'> 

	<t> ForCES: Forwarding and Control Element separation </t>

	<t> I2RS: Interface to Routing System </t>

	<t> NSC: Network Service Chaining </t>

	<t> NSG: Network Service Grouping </t>   

	<t> OF: Open Flow </t>

	<t> RIB: Routing Information Base </t>

	<t> TIB: Topology Information Base </t>
	 

  </list>
</t>

</section> <!-- END of Conventions used in this document -->

 


<section title="Architecture of I2RS">
  <t>
    This section discusses the function of the building block of the I2RS architecture.
  </t>

  <t>
    i. I2RS user application
  </t>
  <t>
    The I2RS user application communicate with the routing information base using the I2RS interface.
    The user application can read the routing information from the routing information base, it can also inject
    polices, routing information etc into the routing information base. The I2RS interface could be RESTful API or
    websocket etc. There should be an authentication mechanism in the I2RS architecture that only allow the authorized 
    application communicate with the routing system.
  </t>

  <t>
    ii. Configuration function
  </t>
  <t>
    The I2RS interface could be configured by the configuration function. The I2RS user application could customize 
    the I2RS interface function and set the I2RS interface parameters by the configuration function.
  </t>

  <t>
    iii. Security function
  </t>
  <t>
    Security function is an important building block of the I2RS architecture. It will ensure only authorized application 
    can use the I2RS interface and communicate with the routing system. There could be different level of authorization. 
    For example, the security function can allow some application only read from the routing system while other application 
    can both read and inject polices into the routing system.
  </t>

  <t>
    iv. Routing function
  </t>
  <t>
    The routing function is composed of routing information base (RIB), IP forwarding table and the routing processes. 
    The I2RS application could communicate with the routing information base using the I2RS interface. It can read or 
    inject routing information into the routing information base. The routing processes can also inject routing 
    information into the routing information base. 

  </t>

  <t>
    iv. Forwarding function
  </t>
  <t>
    The forwarding function facilitates forwarding of flows/packets. It can operate using simple
    Table or sophisticated dynamic matrix for intelligent processing of flows. 
  </t>
</section>

<section title="I2RS Application/Agent">
	<t>
		This section discusses the I2RS application and agent function in the architecture.
		There are many applications can use the I2RS interfaces. For example, network management
		application can use I2RS interface to get the network topology information.
		I2RS agent locates in the routing function and communicates with the I2RS application.
	</t>
</section>

<section title="I2RS Interfaces">
	<t>
		This section discusses the I2RS interfaces in the architecture. The I2RS interface
		is the interface between the I2RS application and the I2RS agent.
	</t>
</section>

<section title="Network/Service Control">
	<t>
		This section discusses the network and service control in the architecture.
		Network control may include control of both virtual and physical network entities.
                The services may include chaining of network services (NSCs) and grouping network services (NSGs).
	</t>
</section>

<section title="Management Considerations">
	<t>
		This section discusses the management consideration of the architecture. In addition to managing
		the configurations of the virtual and physical network entities, this may include managing
		service-specific meta-data and configurations of the hosts that provide network-based
		value-added services like policy, compliance, load-balancing, and so on.
	</t>
</section>
     
<section anchor="security" title="Security Considerations">
  <t>
    Security function is very important for the I2RS architecture. It should provide authentication mechanism and 
    data protection mechanism to protect critical routing information.
  </t>
</section>

<section title="IANA Considerations">
<t>No IANA action is required.</t>
</section>


<section title="Acknowledgments">
<t>.</t>
</section>

</middle>

<back>

<references title="Normative References">
  <?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"?>     

</references>
             
<references title="Informative References">
<?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2328.xml"?> 
<?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4271.xml"?>     

</references>

</back>
</rfc>