<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!-- This template is for creating an Internet Draft using xml2rfc,
     which is available here: http://xml.resource.org. -->
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!-- One method to get references from the online citation libraries.
     There has to be one entity for each item to be referenced. 
     An alternate method (rfc include) is described in the references. -->

<!ENTITY RFC2119 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC2629 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2629.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3552 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3552.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC2460 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2460.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC2461 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2461.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC2462 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2462.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3375 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3375.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4429 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4429.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4968 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4968.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5121 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5121.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5154 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5154.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.narten-iana-considerations-rfc2434bis SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.narten-iana-considerations-rfc2434bis.xml">
]>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<!-- used by XSLT processors -->
<!-- For a complete list and description of processing instructions (PIs), 
     please see http://xml.resource.org/authoring/README.html. -->
<!-- Below are generally applicable Processing Instructions (PIs) that most I-Ds might want to use.
     (Here they are set differently than their defaults in xml2rfc v1.32) -->
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<!-- give errors regarding ID-nits and DTD validation -->
<!-- control the table of contents (ToC) -->
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<!-- generate a ToC -->
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<!-- the number of levels of subsections in ToC. default: 3 -->
<!-- control references -->
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<!-- use symbolic references tags, i.e, [RFC2119] instead of [1] -->
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<!-- sort the reference entries alphabetically -->
<!-- control vertical white space 
     (using these PIs as follows is recommended by the RFC Editor) -->
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<!-- do not start each main section on a new page -->
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<!-- keep one blank line between list items -->
<!-- end of list of popular I-D processing instructions -->
<rfc category="std" docName="draft-liu-ipv6-fdad-00" ipr="trust200902">
  <!-- category values: std, bcp, info, exp, and historic
     ipr values: full3667, noModification3667, noDerivatives3667
     you can add the attributes updates="NNNN" and obsoletes="NNNN" 
     they will automatically be output with "(if approved)" -->

  <!-- ***** FRONT MATTER ***** -->

  <front>
    <!-- The abbreviated title is used in the page header - it is only necessary if the 
         full title is longer than 39 characters -->

    <title abbrev="Fast DAD">Fast Stateless Address Auto-configuration and Duplicate Address Detection in IPv6 Network</title>

    <!-- add 'role="editor"' below for the editors if appropriate -->

    <!-- Another author who claims to be an editor -->

    <author fullname="Fang Liu" initials="F" 
            surname="Liu">
      <organization>Alcatel-Lucent</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>

          <!-- Reorder these if your country does things differently -->

          <city>Beijing</city>

          <region></region>

          <code></code>

          <country>China</country>
        </postal>

        <phone>+86 10 58605827</phone>

        <email>christine.liu@alcatel-lucent.com</email>

        <!-- uri and facsimile elements may also be added -->
      </address>
    </author>
	
	 <author fullname="Caixia Chi" initials="C" 
            surname="Chi">
      <organization>Alcatel-Lucent</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>

          <!-- Reorder these if your country does things differently -->

          <city>Beijing</city>

          <region></region>

          <code></code>

          <country>China</country>
        </postal>

        <phone>+86 10 58605828</phone>

        <email>caixia.chi@alcatel-lucent.com</email>

        <!-- uri and facsimile elements may also be added -->
      </address>
    </author>

    <date month="May" year="2010" />

    <!-- If the month and year are both specified and are the current ones, xml2rfc will fill 
         in the current day for you. If only the current year is specified, xml2rfc will fill 
	 in the current day and month for you. If the year is not the current one, it is 
	 necessary to specify at least a month (xml2rfc assumes day="1" if not specified for the 
	 purpose of calculating the expiry date).  With drafts it is normally sufficient to 
	 specify just the year. -->

    <!-- Meta-data Declarations -->

    <area>General</area>

    <workgroup>Internet Engineering Task Force</workgroup>

    <!-- WG name at the upperleft corner of the doc,
         IETF is fine for individual submissions.  
	 If this element is not present, the default is "Network Working Group",
         which is used by the RFC Editor as a nod to the history of the IETF. -->

    <keyword>template</keyword>

    <!-- Keywords will be incorporated into HTML output
         files in a meta tag but they have no effect on text or nroff
         output. If you submit your draft to the RFC Editor, the
         keywords will be used for the search engine. -->

    <abstract>
      <t>This document proposes an efficient method to speed the address auto-configuration and Duplicate Address Detection (DAD) in IPv6 network and thus greatly decrease the time spend on the address configuration and DAD. This is achieved by modifing the host and router's behaviour and related IPv6 messages.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">

	  <t><xref target="RFC2460">IPv6</xref> is the Internet Protocol designed for the next generation network. Compared with IPv4, some new features are introduced. Among these new features, Stateless Address Configuration <xref target="RFC2462"></xref>  allows a host to generate its own IPv6 addresses using a combination of locally available information and information advertised by routers. Routers advertise prefixes that identify the subnet(s) associated with a link, while hosts generate an "interface identifier" that uniquely identifies an interface on a subnet. An address is formed by combining the two. Router sends Router Advertisements (RA) periodically which contain two flags indicating what type of auto-configuration (if any) should be performed. A "managed address configuration" flag indicates whether hosts should use stateless auto-configuration to obtain addresses. The RA message also contains zero or more Prefix Information options that provide on-link prefixes for address auto-configuration. 
	  </t>
	  <t> Upon receiving the RA message, the host generates an IPv6 address based on the received Prefix Information by itself. Then the host performs Duplicate Address Detection (DAD) by sending out a Neighbor Solicitation (NS) message containing the newly generated address. If the address is already used by another host, that host replies with a Neighbor Advertisement (NA) defending the address. Once a defending NA is received, the address auto-configuration process is stopped, another address is re-generated or manual configuration is performed. 

Once it has sent the NS, the node waits for RetransTimer milliseconds (ms) for a defending NA, and this solicit-and-wait process is repeated DupAddrDetectTransmits times.  The default value of RetransTimer is 1000ms and by default the process is done once, resulting in a default delay of 1000ms, i.e., 1 second (s) for DAD.
	  </t>
	  <t> For Mobile IPv6 [RFC3775] enabled nodes, part of the Layer 3 handover delay is contributed by the configuration of the Care-of-Address (CoA) and DAD when the node moves into a visiting network. From the above analysis, the address configuration and DAD process may add up to 1s delay, which is significant for real-time applications such as VoIP. Hence if we could reduce the time spending on DAD procedure, the whole Mobile IPv6 handover procedure could be speed up. 
	  </t>

		<t>
		Some methods have been proposed to reduce the duration time of DAD. 
		
		<!--For example, Advance Duplicate Address Detection [A-DAD] is proposed by Youn-Hee Han. In this method, each access router maintains 'Passive Proxy Cache' of which each address is in advance generated and tested for its uniqueness by the access router. After successfully acquiring the address from the router, the host assigns it on its interface which attaches to the new link, without the DAD defined in [RFC2461]. However, this method is more like the stateful address configuration such as DHCPv6. It lacks the flexibility provided by stateless address configuration.-->
		</t>
		
		<t>	
 In [RFC4429], Optimistic Duplicate Address Detection is proposed by N. Moore. In this proposal, a new address state, 'Optimistic', is introduced. This state is used to mark an address that is available for use but that has not completed DAD. The use of Optimistic Address is limited, for example, it should not be used as a source address in new communications. However for MIPv6, if the Optimistic Address is used in the Binding Update message as the Care-of-Address before the DAD process is finished, the handover process may be disrupted when duplicated address is detected. 
		</t>
		
		<!--<t>
In [UNDAD], the authors propose a scheme of using the Neighbor Cache Entries (NCE) of the access router for an efficient DAD process. Access Routers are required to perform additional functionalities in order to maintain the complete list of nodes present in the subnet in their Neighbor Cache. IPv6 hosts query the Access Router about the uniqueness of their auto-configured addresses. The Access Routers check the Neighbor Cache for any matching information and respond to the mobile nodes query. However, if the no duplicated address is found, the host still has to wait for at least RetransTimer before assigning the configured address to itself. Hence the DAD process is not speed up.
		</t> -->
		
		<t>
In [END], the Access Router maintains an Address Cache which contains a list of addresses of all connected hosts. To check an address, an MS sends Neighbor Solicitations per RFC2461 and RFC2462.  Upon receiving the NS, the Access Router compares the tentative address in the NS against the entries in its Address Cache.  If there is no match, the Access Router makes an entry for the (tentative) address in its Address Cache and sends a special Router Advertisement to the MS indicating the address's uniqueness. If there is a match that indicates that the address is conflict with another host, the Access Router relays the NS to the address owner without any modification.  Upon receiving the NS, the address owner replies with an NA to defend its address. The Access Router relays the NA to the soliciting MS without any modification.  Upon receiving the defending NA, the soliciting MS perceives the address conflict and refrains from assigning the tentative address to the interface. This mechanism reduces the DAD process significantly, however, there is still some delay introduced by the signaling exchange.
		</t>
		
		<t>
		<!--
		In addition, for those existing mechanism based on Proxy Neighbour Discovery, the address information is learned from the NS message sent by the host during the DAD procedure. However this method is not reliable sometimes. If the address is learned from the NS message, according to [RFC2462] the host may not perform DAD and does not send the NS after the address configuration. For example, if the address uniqueness is determined solely by the interface identifier, assuming that subnet prefixes are assigned correctly (i.e., if all of an interface's addresses are generated from the same identifier, either all addresses or none of them will be duplicated). Thus, for a set of addresses formed from the same interface identifier, it is sufficient to check that the link-local address generated from the identifier is unique on the link. The DAD is not performed for other address derived from the same interface identifier. So in this case, the access router has no way to learn the address information of the host. Thus the information contained in the Address Cache is not correct.
		-->
		</t>	  
		
		<!--
		<t> In this draft a method is proposed to speed the address auto-configuration and Duplicate Address Detection process in IPv6 network and thus will greatly decrease the mobile terminals handover delay. It can be used to any network with mobile IPv6 as layer 3.
		</t>
		-->
		
		<t> 
		Some access networks are point-to-multipoint networks in which the hosts can not communicate with other hosts connected to the same access router and all communication should go through the access router first. For example, in IEEE 802.16 (WiMAX) network [RFC5154], the subscriber station is not capable of multicasting (e.g., for neighbor discovery, IP multicasting services, etc.) or direct communication to the other nodes attached to the same Base Station within the same subnet (prefix).   
		</t>
		
		<t> Proxy Neighbour Discovery (PND) is often used to handle the neighbour discovery problem in the above networks. The access router maintains an address table which contains a list of IPv6 addresses and corresponding link-layer addresses that are being used by all IPv6 hosts in the same subnet. Upon receiving NS, the router would relay the NS message to the solicited host or send back a NA message directly on behalf of the solicited host.   
		</t>
	
		<t> In this document, a fast Stateless Address Auto-configuration and DAD process is proposed, in which an Address Table is used to contain the addresses and their corresponding link-layer addresses of all hosts in the same link. Unlike the standard method as defined in [RFC2462], after the stateless address configuration, an explicit NS message is sent to notify the access router. In addition, since the probability of having a duplicate address is too small, the DAD process is omitted by the host. Instead, the access router performs the DAD on behalf of the host. If duplicate address is detected, then the access router notifies the host to re-generate a new address.  
		</t>
    </section>
	<section title="Terminology">
	<t>
The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT","SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
   document are to be interpreted as described in BCP 14 [STANDARDS].
	</t>
	<t><list style="symbols">
		<t> MS - Mobile Station. </t>
		<t> BS - Base Station. </t>
</list></t>
	</section>

	<section title="Requirements">
	
	<section title="Host's Requirements">
	<t>
	The host should set the access router as the default gateway after receiving the RA message from it and all communication should go through the router;
The host should be able to process the modified messages as defined below.
	</t>
	</section>
	<section title="Access Router's Requirements">
	<t>
	The access router should maintain an address table. This table contains the host's IPv6 address, link-layer address, life time and etc. 
	Access routers should process all received NS with specified and unspecified source address and solicited-node-multicast destination address for DAD and address resolving.
	</t>
	</section>
	</section>
	
	<section title="General Fast DAD Procedure">
	<t>
	When a host boots up or moves into a new network, it sends a Router Solicitation (RS) message to perform router and prefix discovery as defined in [RFC2461]. After receiving a valid RS message, the access router should send a special Router Advertisement (RA) as reply. The RA message is used to indicate the fast address configuration and DAD should be used by the host.
	</t>
	<t>
If the host could recognize the special RA message, it generates a stateless IPv6 address as described in RFC2462. Then the host would skip the normal DAD process and sends a special NS message immediately to the access router to notify its configured address.
	</t>
	<t>
After receiving the NS message, the access router compares the address in the message against the entries in its Address Table. If there is no match, the access router create an entry contains the address and the corresponding link-layer address of the host. 
	</t>
	<t>
Otherwise, if there exists a match indicates that the address is duplicate, the access router sends a special NA message to notify the host that duplicate address is detected and another address needs to be generated. Before a new unique address is generated by the host, the access router does not forward the data packet from or to this host.
	</t>
	<t>
If the host receives the special NA message, it should abandon the duplicate address contained in the message. And it should re-generate a new stateless address automatically and repeat the above process.
	</t>
	</section>

	<section title="Message Format">
	<section title="Overview">
	<t> In this document, the messages defined in IPv6 standards are reused and some modification are made as described below:</t>
	<t>
	<list style="symbols">
	<t> 
	An "E" indication bit is added to the reserved section of the RA message.
	</t>
	<t>
	An "E" and "D" indication bit is added to the reserved section of the NS message.
	</t>
	<t>
	An "E" indication bit is added to the reserved section of the NA message.
	</t>
	</list>
	</t>
	</section>
	<section title="Modified Router Advertisement Message Format">
	<t>
The fields in the message are as defined in RFC2461 <xref target="RFC2461">RFC 2461</xref>except one bit (E bit) is added to the 'Reserved' field. If the access router wants to request the hosts to use the fast stateless address configuration, it must set the 'E' bit of the RA message sent to the hosts in order to indicate the fast address configuration and DAD may be used.  
	</t>
	    <figure anchor="fig1" title="Modified Router Advertisement Message">

        <artwork><![CDATA[
      0                   1                   2                   3
      0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
     +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
     |     Type      |     Code      |          Checksum             |
     +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
     | Cur Hop Limit |M|O|E|Reserved |       Router Lifetime         |
     +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
     |                         Reachable Time                        |
     +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
     |                          Retrans Timer                        |
     +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
     |                 Prefix Information Option                     |
     +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
        ]]></artwork> </figure>
	</section>

	<section title="Modified Neighbour Solicitation Message Format">
	<t>

The fields in the message are as defined in RFC2461 except two bits ('E' bit and 'D' bit) is added to the 'Reserved' field. The 'E' bit is set if the host want to register its auto-configured address with the access router explicitly. The 'D' bit is set if the host want to de-register its generated address with the access router explicitly. The 'Target Address' is set to the address auto-configured by the host.
	</t>
    <figure anchor="fig2" title="Modified Neighbour Solicitation Message">

        <artwork><![CDATA[
      0                   1                   2                   3
      0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
     +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
     |     Type      |     Code      |          Checksum             |
     +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
     |E|D|                        Reserved                           |
     +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
     |                        Target Address                         |
     +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
     |   Options ...
     +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-
        ]]></artwork> </figure>	
	</section>
	
	<section title="Modified Neighbour Advertisement Message Format">
	<t>
The fields in the message are as defined in RFC2461. One bit (E bit) is added to the 'Reserved' field. This message is sent to the host by the access router to indicate that duplicate address is detected. The 'Target Address' is the duplicated address detected by the access router.
	</t>
    <figure anchor="fig3" title="Modified Neighbour Advertisement Message">

        <artwork><![CDATA[
      0                   1                   2                   3
      0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
     +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
     |     Type      |     Code      |          Checksum             |
     +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
     |R|S|0|E|                    Reserved                           |
     +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
     |                        Target Address                         |
     +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
     |   Options ...
     +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-
        ]]></artwork> </figure>
	</section>
	</section>
	<section title="Modified Host and Router Behaviour">
	<t>The host and access router behaviours should be modified to deal with these modified messages.</t>
	<section title="Modified Host Behaviour">
	<t>
Upon receiving a RA message, the host should check the 'E' bit of the message to see if the fast stateless address auto-configuration is required. If the 'M' bit is not set and 'E' bit is set, a stateless IPv6 address is generated according to the procedure defined in RFC2462. In the proposed mechanism, the 'Tentative Address' is not used anymore. The generated address is assigned to the host's interface as an effective address and an explicit NS message is send to the access router immediately. In this message, the 'E' bit is set to indicate that this is an explicit registration message for fast DAD. 
	</t>

	<t>
Afterwards, if a NA message is received and the 'E' bit is set in the message, the host compares the 'Target Address' with its own generated address. If the two addresses are the same, then a duplicate address is detected by the access router. The host must abandon the current assigned address and re-generated an address as defined in RFC2462. As described as above, the data packets sent before the NA message is received are discarded by the router. Because the router would send the NA message to the host immediately after the duplicated address is detected, the impact on the host is small. 
	</t>
	
	<t>
When the host wants to move out of the subnet or stop using the address, it sends a NS message with 'D' bit set to the access router to de-register the address explicitly.
	</t>

	<t>
If the host can not recognize the 'E' and 'D' bit in the RA and NA message, its behavior is the same as defined in RFC2462.
	</t>
	</section>

	
	<section title="Modified Router Behaviour">
	<t>
In the proposed mechanism, the 'E' bit is set in the RA message to indicate the fast address configuration and DAD are used. The RA message is sent periodically or when a Router Solicitation message is received. Upon receiving a Neighbour Solicitation message, the router checks if the 'E' bit of the message is set. If the 'E' bit is set, the router compares the 'Target Address' field in the message against the Address Table. If there is a match, then the address is conflict with another host. The router must send the host a NA message with 'E' bit set to indicate the duplicate address is detected. Before a unique address is re-generated by the host, all messages sent from the host must not be forwarded to other nodes, so the duplicate address does not cause problems for other hosts. If there is no match in the Address Table, the router creates an entry in the Address Table to store the 'Target Address' and the corresponding link-layer address. 
	</t>
	<t>
If the 'D' bit is set in the received NS message, the access router compares the 'Target Address' field in the message against the Address Table. If there is a match, then delete the entry that contains the address. If there is no match in the Address Table, just ignore the message.
	</t>
	<t>
After the entry is created, the updating and ageing of the contents of the entry could refer to the Neighbor Cache maintaining procedure described in RFC2461. 
	</t>
	<t>
If the 'E' bit and 'D' bit are not set in the received NS message, the NS is treated as a normal address resolving message. The router compares the 'Target Address' field against the address list. If there is a match, then a normal NA message is sent to the soliciting host. In this NA message, the 'Target Address' field is set to the one in the NS message. If there is no match and the source address of the NS message is unspecified, then the NS message is sent out in the normal DAD process. Then an entry is created to contain the 'Target Address' and link-layer address in the NS message. So the router could support both modified hosts and un-modified hosts.
		</t>
	</section>
	</section>
	<section anchor="procedure" title="The Example Usage in 802.16 Network">
	<t>
Let's suppose a mobile subscriber station (MS) is moving into a mobile WiMAX network (802.16e) in which Mobile IPv6 (MIPv6) is supported. As mentioned as above, the WiMAX IP network is a point-to-multipoint network.  A MS can not communicate with another MS directly. All the traffic should go through an Access Router (ASN-GW) as shown in Figure 4. One thing to be noted is that in 802.16 networks sometimes the DAD process can be omitted, e.g., as described in [RFC5121] [RFC5154]. In these cases, the method described in the document is not necessary.

The process when the MS roams into a new access network is described as the follow:
<list style="numbers">
<t>	After finishing layer-2 handover, the MS send a RS message to the Access Router (AR); </t>
<t>
Upon receipt of the RS message, the AR sends a RA message to the MS. In this message, the 'E' bit is set to indicate the fast address configuration and DAD. Also the 'Prefix Information' option is included in the message;
</t>
<t>
The MS generates a stateless address based on the prefix information extracted from the RA message. The MS also set the AR as the default gateway;
</t>
<t>
After the address is generated, an explicit NS message is sent to the AR.
</t>
<t>
The AR checks the address contained in the NS message in its address list. If not found, the AR creates an entry for this MS in which the CoA and the corresponding link-layer address is contained.
</t>
<t>
If duplicate address is found, an NA message with 'E' bit set is sent to the MS by the AR.

</t>
<t>
The MS uses the address as the Care-of-Address (CoA), and sends a Binding Update (BU) message to register with Home Agent. If the CoA is not in conflict with other MSs, the AR forwards the BU message to the next hop. Otherwise, the BU message is discarded by the AR. And the MS must re-generate a new CoA and repeats the above steps; When the MS is about to move out from the subnet, it sends a NS message with 'D' bit set to de-register with the access router explicitly. If the MS does not send the explicit de-register message before moving out, the corresponding entry in the access router would be invalid after the lifetime expires.
</t>
</list>
From the above procedure, we could see that the proposed mechanism can significantly decrease the overall handover delay by reducing the time spent in address configuration and DAD. So it could reduce the overall handover delay in Mobile IPv6 networks.

	</t>
	
	<figure anchor="fig4" title="Handover in Mobile 802.16 Networks">

        <artwork><![CDATA[
              +-----+       +-----+      +----------+          +----+
              | MS1 |-------|     |      | +-----+  |          | CN |
              +-----+       |     |------| | HA  |  |          +----+
              +-----+       | AR1 |      | +-----+  |             |
              | MS2 |-------|     |      |          |             |
           |  +-----+       +-----+      |          |             |
           |                             | +-----+  |--------- Internet
           |  +-----+       +-----+      | | AAA |  |
           V  | MS2 |-------|     |------| +-----+  |       
              +-----+       |     |      |          |
              +-----+       | AR2 |      +----------+
              | MS3 |-------|     |
              +-----+       +-----+                     
        ]]></artwork> </figure>
	</section>
      
  

    <!-- This PI places the pagebreak correctly (before the section title) in the text output. -->

    <!-- <?rfc needLines="8" ?>  -->
   

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>This document includes no request to IANA.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>This document does not introduce any new vulnerabilities to IPv6
   specifications or operation.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <!--  *****BACK MATTER ***** -->

  <back>
    <!-- References split into informative and normative -->

    <!-- There are 2 ways to insert reference entries from the citation libraries:
     1. define an ENTITY at the top, and use "ampersand character"RFC2629; here (as shown)
     2. simply use a PI "less than character"?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119.xml"?> here
        (for I-Ds: include="reference.I-D.narten-iana-considerations-rfc2434bis.xml")

     Both are cited textually in the same manner: by using xref elements.
     If you use the PI option, xml2rfc will, by default, try to find included files in the same
     directory as the including file. You can also define the XML_LIBRARY environment variable
     with a value containing a set of directories to search.  These can be either in the local
     filing system or remote ones accessed by http (http://domain/dir/... ).-->

    <references title="Normative References">
      <!--?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"?-->
      <!--&RFC2119; -->

	  &RFC2460;

      &RFC2461;
	  
	  &RFC2462;
    
	  &RFC4429;
	  
	  &RFC4968;
	  
	  &RFC5121;
	  
	  &RFC5154;
	     
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <!-- Here we use entities that we defined at the beginning. -->




      <!-- A reference written by by an organization not a person. -->
	  <reference anchor="ADAD">
        <front>
          <title>Advance Duplicate Address Detection</title>

          <author>
            <organization>Han, Y., Choi, J., Jang, H., and S. Park</organization>
          </author>
          <date year="2003" />
        </front>
		<seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-han-mobileip-adad-01.txt"/>
      </reference>
	  
	  <reference anchor="END">
		<front>
		<title>Duplicate Address Detection Optimization Using Enhanced Neighbor Discovery</title> 
		<author initials="F" surname="Xia" fullname="Frank Xia">
		<organization /> 
		</author>
		<author initials="B" surname="Sarikaya" fullname="Behcet Sarikaya">
			<organization /> 
		</author>
		<date month="December" day="11" year="2006" /> 
		<abstract>
			<t>This draft describes a possible optimization to Duplicate Address Detection (DAD) which can be used to successfully terminate DAD early. The method is based on a positive RA message sent by an Neighbor Discovery Relay Agent that knows all the IPv6 addresses of the nodes currently attached to it.</t> 
		</abstract>
		</front>
		<seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-xia-16ng-end-01" /> 
		<format type="TXT" target="http://www.ietf.org/internet-drafts/draft-xia-16ng-end-01.txt" /> 
		</reference>
	<!--
      <reference anchor="DOMINATION"
                 target="http://www.example.com/dominator.html">
        <front>
          <title>Ultimate Plan for Taking Over the World</title>

          <author>
            <organization>Mad Dominators, Inc.</organization>
          </author>

          <date year="1984" />
        </front>
      </reference>
	  -->
    </references>

	<!--
    <section anchor="app-additional" title="Additional Stuff">
      <t>This becomes an Appendix.</t>
    </section>
	-->
    <!-- Change Log

v00 2006-03-15  EBD   Initial version

v01 2006-04-03  EBD   Moved PI location back to position 1 -
                      v3.1 of XMLmind is better with them at this location.
v02 2007-03-07  AH    removed extraneous nested_list attribute,
                      other minor corrections
v03 2007-03-09  EBD   Added comments on null IANA sections and fixed heading capitalization.
                      Modified comments around figure to reflect non-implementation of
                      figure indent control.  Put in reference using anchor="DOMINATION".
                      Fixed up the date specification comments to reflect current truth.
v04 2007-03-09 AH     Major changes: shortened discussion of PIs,
                      added discussion of rfc include.
v05 2007-03-10 EBD    Added preamble to C program example to tell about ABNF and alternative 
                      images. Removed meta-characters from comments (causes problems).  -->
  </back>
</rfc>
