<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [

	<!ENTITY rfc2119 PUBLIC '' 
	  'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml'>
	  
	  <!ENTITY rfc2002 PUBLIC '' 
	  'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2002.xml'>
	  
	  <!ENTITY rfc3775 PUBLIC '' 
	  'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3775.xml'>
	  
	  <!ENTITY rfc5213 PUBLIC '' 
	  'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5213.xml'>
	  
	  <!ENTITY rfc5555 PUBLIC '' 
	  'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5555.xml'>
  
]>

<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>

<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc iprnotified="no"?>
<?rfc strict="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?> 
<?rfc subcompact="yes" ?>

<rfc category="info" ipr="trust200902" 
docName="draft-liu-sdn-mobility-00">

<front>
<title abbrev="sdn-mobility">
Mobility Support in Software Defined Networking
</title>

<author initials="D"  surname="Liu" fullname="Dapeng Liu">
<organization>China Mobile</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street>Unit2, 28 Xuanwumenxi Ave, Xuanwu District, 
Beijing 100053, China</street>
<street>Email: liudapeng@chinamobile.com</street>
</postal>
</address>
</author>

<author fullname="Hui Deng" initials="H." surname="Deng">
      <organization>China Mobile</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>32 Xuanwumen West Street</street>
          <city>Beijng</city>
          <region>Xicheng District</region>
          <code>100053</code>
          <country>China</country>
        </postal>
        <phone></phone>
        <facsimile></facsimile>
        <email>denghui@chinamobile.com</email>
        <uri></uri>
      </address>
</author>

<date month="July" year="2013"></date>
<area>Internet</area>
<workgroup></workgroup>
<abstract>
<t>
This document discusses the SDN mobility problem and potential solutions.
</t>
</abstract>
</front>

<middle>

<!-- Introduction -->

<section anchor="intro" title="Introduction">
<t>
Software defined networking provides a very flexible way to process IP packets and 
flows. It decouples the control and forwarding function of traditional IP appliance.
IP mobility support has been specified by IETF. There is currently not much discussion regarding
the mobility support in SDN network. This document discusses the motivation, problem and potential solution
of the mobility support in SDN network.
</t>

</section>

<!-- 2 Conventions and terminologies -->

<section title="Conventions and Terminologies">

<!-- 2.1 Conventions -->
<section title="Conventions used in this document">
<t>
The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL","SHALL NOT", 
"SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" 
in this document are to be interpreted as described 
in <xref target="RFC2119" />.
</t>
</section>

<!-- 2.2 Definitions -->
<section title="Terminology">
	<t>
		SDN: Software Defined Networking
	</t>
</section>
</section>

<!-- 3 Motivation of SDN mobility -->

<section title="Motivation of SDN mobility">
	<t>
		IP mobility support has been specified in IETF for years. Both <xref target="RFC2002"/>, <xref target="RFC3775"/>,
	  <xref target="RFC5555"/>,<xref target="RFC5213"/> share the similar idea that it introduce an anchoring point 
	  to maintain the mapping of the home address and routing address of the mobile node. It uses tunnel to encapsulate 
	  the user traffic so that the application layer is not aware  of the mobility event.
	</t>
	<t>
		IP protocol has been used intensively in current cellular network architecture. For example, in LTE network architecture,
		IP support is enabled in the data plane. Also In the control plane and mobility supprot, IP moblitliy protocol is used.
		Both S2a/S2b/S2c interface is specified that can based on IP mobility protocol.
	</t>
	<t> 
		There is ongoing research work and discussions of using SDN in cellular network. SDN can provide the IP packets
		processing ability for the cellular core network. Mobility support is critical for the cellular core network. If mobility
		can be supported by SDN, the cellular core network can be significantly simplified. The data plane traffic routing can also be
		optimized. The following figure shows an architecture of the cellular core network that build upon SDN concept. 
	</t>
	
	<!--
	123456789012345678901234567890123456789012345678901234567890123456789012
	-->
	      <figure>
	        <preamble></preamble>
	        <artwork><![CDATA[
	    
	    +--------------------+      +--------------+        +----------+
	    |mobility management |      | Charging     |        | Policy   |
	    +--------------------+      +--------------+        +----------+
	    +----------|----------------------|----------------------|-------------+
	    |                            controller                                |
	    +----------------------------------------------------------------------+
	    +---------------------------------|------------------------------------+
	    |           forwarding and packet swithching function                  |
	    +----------------------------------------------------------------------+
	    +---------------------------------|------------------------------------+
	    |                      wireless access network                         |
	    +----------------------------------------------------------------------+
	      	]]></artwork>
	        <postamble></postamble>
	      </figure>
	
	<t>Figure 1. SDN based Mobile core network </t>

</section>


<!-- 4 SDN mobility problem statement -->

<section title="SDN mobility problem analysis and potential solutions">
	<t>
		The purpose of mobility management is to maintain the session continuity
		from the application's perspective. Normally, when a mobile node change
		its attachment point, its IP address will be changed accordingly. If there is
		no mobility support, the application layer session will be broken. For example,
		TCP session can not survive when the source IP address changes.
	</t>
	<t>
		There are several potential ways for SDN network to support mobility. The 
		following sections will discuss the potential solution in detail.
	</t>
	<section title="Enhance SDN to support mobility tunnel handling.">
		<t>
			Current mobility protocol mainly follows the concept of mobility anchor.
			Mobility anchor point maintain the mapping of home address and routing address.
			For example, in Mobile IP, the home agent maintain the mapping of home address
			and care of address. When the care of address changes due to mobile node's 
			movement, the foreign agent or the mobile node will send binding update
			request to the home agent to update the binding cache entry. The foreign agent
			or the mobile node will set up bi-directional tunnel towards the home agent.
			All the user traffic will be encapsulated in the bi-directional tunnel.
		</t>
		<t>
			To enable SDN to support mobility, one potential solution is to enable the SDN
			controller and SDN forwarding function to support IP mobility protocol related
			tunnelling processing. 
		</t>
			<!--
			123456789012345678901234567890123456789012345678901234567890123456789012
			-->
			      <figure>
			        <preamble></preamble>
			        <artwork><![CDATA[
                           +-------------------+
                           |mobility management|
                           +-------------------+
                                     | API
                            +-----------------+
                +-----------|    controller   |------------+
                |           +-----------------+            |
                |                    |                     |
			    |   		         |                     |
			    |   		         |                     |
                |                    |                     |
                |                    |                     |
			    | +--------------------------------------+ |
			    | |                  |                   | |
			 +---------+       +---------+        +----------+     
			 | FA/MAG  |       |  FA/MAG |        |  LMA/HA  |                                           
			 +---------+       +---------+        +----------+                                
			      	]]></artwork>
			        <postamble></postamble>
			      </figure>
			
			<t>Figure 2. Enhance SDN to support mobility tunnel processing</t>
			
		<t>
			The mobility management function could run on top of the controller. The controller
			controlls the forwarding function. To support mobility, the mobility management function
			monitors the mobile node's movement event. When the FA/MAG detects the mobile node's
			movement, it needs to update the binding cache entry that maybe maintained in the
			mobility management function. The mobility management function then control the forwarding
			function(FA/MAG) to do the mobility tunnel processing. When the packets arrives at the
			LMA/HA, the mobility management function will controll the forwarding function to decapsulate
			the packets and forward the packets to the Internet.
		</t>
	</section>
	
	<section title="Routing based SDN mobility support">
		<t>
			SDN provides a very flexiable way of packet and flow processing. It is in nature can react quickly
			on the routing changes of the network. When the mobile node changes its point of attachment,
			the forwarding function will notify the mobility management function running on top of the 
			controller, the controller then calculate the forwarding rules based on the destination IP address
			of the IP packet. The controller then push the forwarding rules to the forwarding function and the
			IP packet will be forwarded accordingly. When the user session terminated, the mobility management
			function will delete the forwarding rules. In this manner, the application lalyer session
			continuity will be guaranteed since the mobile node's IP address is not changed during the movement. 
		</t>
		<t>
			There are lots of interesting problems need to be solved to make SDN support mobility. For example,
			the forwarding function needs to detect the movement event of the mobile node and notify the 
			controller and mobility management function in a timely manner. A routing path needs to be
			set up from the MAG/FA to the Internet access point in a timely manner. To achieve this, new protocol
			and mechnism may need to be defined in IETF.
		</t>
	</section>
	
</section>

<section anchor="security" title="Security Considerations">
<t>TBD</t>
</section>


<section title="IANA Considerations">
<t>None</t>
</section>


</middle>


<back>

<references title="Normative References">
  &rfc2119;
</references>

<references title="Informative References">
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.6275" ?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.2002" ?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.5213" ?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.5555" ?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.3775" ?>
</references>

</back>
</rfc>
