<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!-- This template is for creating an Internet Draft using xml2rfc,
     which is available here: http://xml.resource.org. -->
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY RFC3325 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3325.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6072 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6072.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4474 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4474.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3323 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3323.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5767 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5767.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5379 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5379.xml">

]>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<!-- used by XSLT processors -->
<!-- For a complete list and description of processing instructions (PIs), 
     please see http://xml.resource.org/authoring/README.html. -->
<!-- Below are generally applicable Processing Instructions (PIs) that most I-Ds might want to use.
     (Here they are set differently than their defaults in xml2rfc v1.32) -->
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<!-- give errors regarding ID-nits and DTD validation -->
<!-- control the table of contents (ToC) -->
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<!-- generate a ToC -->
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<!-- the number of levels of subsections in ToC. default: 3 -->
<!-- control references -->
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<!-- use symbolic references tags, i.e, [RFC2119] instead of [1] -->
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<!-- sort the reference entries alphabetically -->
<!-- control vertical white space 
     (using these PIs as follows is recommended by the RFC Editor) -->
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<!-- do not start each main section on a new page -->
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<!-- keep one blank line between list items -->
<!-- end of list of popular I-D processing instructions -->
<rfc category="info" docName="draft-cooper-iab-secure-origin-00.txt"
     ipr="trust200902">
  <!-- category values: std, bcp, info, exp, and historic
     ipr values: full3667, noModification3667, noDerivatives3667
     you can add the attributes updates="NNNN" and obsoletes="NNNN" 
     they will automatically be output with "(if approved)" -->

  <!-- ***** FRONT MATTER ***** -->

  <front>
    <!-- The abbreviated title is used in the page header - it is only necessary if the 
         full title is longer than 39 characters -->

    <title abbrev="Secure Origin">Secure Call Origin Identification</title>

    <!--add 'role="editor"' below for the editors if appropriate -->

    <!-- Another author who claims to be an editor -->

    <author fullname="Alissa Cooper" initials="A." surname="Cooper">
      <organization>CDT</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>1634 Eye St. NW, Suite 1100</street>

          <city>Washington</city>

          <region>DC</region>

          <code>20006</code>

          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>

        <email>acooper@cdt.org</email>

        <!-- uri and facsimile elements may also be added -->
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Hannes Tschofenig" initials="H." surname="Tschofenig">
      <organization>Nokia Siemens Networks</organization>
      <address>
        <email>hannes.tschofenig@gmx.net</email>
      </address>
    </author>

	<author fullname="Jon Peterson" initials="J." surname="Peterson">
      <organization>NeuStar</organization>
      <address>
        <email>jon.peterson@neustar.biz</email>
      </address>
    </author>

	<author fullname="Bernard Aboba" initials="B." surname="Aboba">
      <organization>Microsoft</organization>
      <address>
        <email>bernard.aboba@gmail.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date day="30" month="November" year="2012"/>

    <!-- If the month and year are both specified and are the current ones, xml2rfc will fill 
         in the current day for you. If only the current year is specified, xml2rfc will fill 
	 in the current day and month for you. If the year is not the current one, it is 
	 necessary to specify at least a month (xml2rfc assumes day="1" if not specified for the 
	 purpose of calculating the expiry date).  With drafts it is normally sufficient to 
	 specify just the year. -->

    <!-- Meta-data Declarations -->

    <area>General</area>

    <workgroup>Network Working Group</workgroup>

    <!-- WG name at the upperleft corner of the doc,
         IETF is fine for individual submissions.  
	 If this element is not present, the default is "Network Working Group",
         which is used by the RFC Editor as a nod to the history of the IETF. -->

    <abstract>
      <t>A number of parties have suggested creating mandates such that
		   networks receiving voice calls would be capable of securely
		   identifying the call origin. This
		   document provides insights about the capabilities and limitations of
		   supporting call origin identification in a secure and privacy-
		   friendly way in the PSTN and for IP-based real-time communications.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>A number of parties have suggested creating mandates such that networks receiving voice calls would be capable of securely identifying the call origin <xref target="TD-62" />. These proposals are primarily motivated by concerns over fraudulent calls and the associated economic impact that spoofed or fraudulent origin identification can have on telecommunications settlement agreements. Concerns have also been raised about ensuring secure origin identification for law enforcement and abuse tracking purposes.</t>

		<t>Support for caller identification in the public switched telephone network (PSTN) has been developed to meet existing regulatory needs and for other purposes, but it has limitations. As real-time communication has become IP-based, it has become significantly more difficult to identify the origin of real-time communication for a number of reasons. Furthermore, to the extent that new mandates are being suggested to require origin identification for all IP traffic -- real-time or not -- it is unclear how such identification would be accomplished given the complexity and diversity of today's IP network traffic. This document provides insights about the capabilities and limitations of supporting call origin identification in a secure and privacy-friendly way in the PSTN and for IP-based real-time communications.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Secure Origin Challenges in the PSTN">
      <t>The problems facing origin identification are not limited to the Internet. In the traditional public switched telephone network, information about the calling party is often missing from signaling messages. This is because, per the ITU-T and related national specifications (beginning with Q.761), the calling party number field of a call establishment message (IAM) is an optional parameter. There remain a number of legitimate reasons today why the origin of a telephone call might be absent from call establishment signaling: because of interworking with a legacy (pre-SS7) network or a private branch exchange which lacks the capability to identify subscribers, for example, or because the call has been handled by an interexchange carrier using calling cards that require the customer to dial a relay number. So long as there are legitimate reasons why the calling party number might be missing from a call, and the parameter remains optional in the SS7 standards, carriers will sometimes fail to provide origin identification in the telephone network. Parties who want to obscure their identity can rely on equipment or carriers that do not provide the calling party number.</t>

	<t>Whether or not the calling party number should be trusted, if it is present, is a separate but related question. Private branch exchanges that signal calls via ISDN (Q.931) can provide an arbitrary calling party number in their own call establishment message (SETUP), and some operators translate those numbers directly to the calling party number field of SS7. Due to the transitive trust inherent in the SS7 network, there is no way for the recipient of a call to determine how trustworthy the calling party number field is: effectively, all carriers in the telephone network necessarily trust the origin identification provided by any carrier. These difficulties have been exacerbated by the widespread deployment of Internet gateways. For these gateways, it is almost always better to supply no calling party number to the SS7 network than it is to accept a number provided by Internet signaling. Because some gateways do accept the numbers provided by Internet callers, however, this further weakens the trustworthiness of calling party number information on the telephone network. These concerns are not limited to calls either: text messages have similar problems resulting from email-to-text gateways.</t>

		<t>Our ability to solve origin identification for Internet calling depends on solving it for the telephone network, as Internet telephony solutions inevitably exchange traffic with the telephone network. Given the inherent limitations of SS7 standards for origin identification, the transitive trust properties of the telephone network, and the widespread acceptance of calls without origin identification in the telephone system today, the prospects are very doubtful for remedying this problem by simply mandating that carriers provide origin identification.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Secure Origin Challenges for VoIP">
      <t>Standards for Voice Over IP (VoIP) originally focused on Session Initiation Protocol (SIP) and  Extensible Messaging and Presence Protocol (XMPP)-based systems, with SIP becoming a popular foundation for many proprietary VoIP systems. SIP provides a number of different mechanisms for asserting the identity of a caller, including "P-Asserted-Identity" (PAI) <xref target="RFC3325" />, "SIP Cert" <xref target="RFC6072" /> and the "SIP Identity" mechanism <xref target="RFC4474" />. PAI and SIP Identity allow SIP application servers in the network to insert caller information into the 'From' header of outgoing calls.</t>

		<t>However, not all calls will necessarily identify the calling party in any way, and there are no standardized requirements to use any particular caller identification solution. Anonymous calls and calls made from outbound-only calling services generally do not contain identity information. In addition, in some situations, calls made through relay services may identify the relay as the calling party rather than the original caller.</t>  

		<t>In addition, the identifier syntax used in SIP varies from email-address-style identifiers to ones that use E.164 telephone numbers. Because of the security shortcomings of the PSTN described above, SIP-based services that seek to make authentication and identification guarantees cannot do so purely with E.164 numbers. Such guarantees would require a universal move toward email-style identifiers.</t> 

		<t>Even in a SIP-only environment, the choice of syntax, made separately by different implementers and users, impacts the security mechanisms that can be used for attesting to the authenticity of the identifier. Without any form of cryptographic identity assertion, the 'From' header can be easily forged, and headers are often stripped or modified by intermediaries in transit. Attempts at enhancing the integrity protection of SIP identity have not seen wide deployment.</t>

		<t>Finally, SIP supports a number of privacy mechanisms that allow SIP users to shield their identities from the network and the called party <xref target="RFC3323" /> <xref target="RFC5767" /> <xref target="RFC5379" />. SIP privacy has valid uses; for example, it enables users to avoid exposing their identity to destinations that might make them a target for unsolicited advertising or other undesirable consequences. As in the PSTN, parties that do not wish to disclose their identities can use services that support this functionality.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Secure Origin Challenges for Real-Time Communication on the Web">
      <t>While SIP and XMPP were originally designed to facilitate interoperable real-time communications between systems developed by different vendors, the last 10 years have seen the rise of a new platform for deployment of applications: the world wide web. Web applications that run in a secure execution environment inside a web browser are now commonplace. As a result, real-time communications -- including voice and video telephony -- are migrating to the web as well.</t>

		<t>This new trend in application development enables real-time application to be downloaded on-demand and executed within the browser utilizing new interfaces in the browser platform to interact with the microphone, camera, and other sensors. The integration of real-time communication into the huge web ecosystem opens a number of new possibilities that were previously only possible with proprietary browser plug-ins.</t> 

		<t>This migration to the web does not eliminate the challenges associated with providing secure call origin identification; in some ways, it even serves to complicate the situation. While web servers have a common and widely used means of authenticating themselves -- public key-based authentication infrastructure for use with SSL -- no single client-side authentication mechanism has emerged to authenticate users sitting in front of their browsers. Instead, a variety of technologies have been deployed, often with applicability only in narrow sectors.</t> 

		<t>Enterprise networks, for example, often use hardware tokens to authenticate employees. Banking web sites often require one-time secrets in combination with knowledge-based security. Many consumer-focused web sites tend to rely on insecure password-based authentication. With so many web sites requiring authentication, Web Single-Sign-On (WebSSO) deployments have emerged to attempt to create a uniform authentication mechanism. But while individual identity providers offering such WebSSO solutions offer security benefits and great convenience for end users, they too are typically limited as far as the scope of web sites that can rely on them for authentication. Relying web sites, likewise, usually only support a single or limited set of identity providers. Consequently, users are confronted with islands on the web that use different identity technologies.</t> 

		<t>Because web-based real-time applications extends the existing web ecosystem, they also inherit its identity management ecosystem, a system that is still in flux. With new technology being developed every day it is unlikely that a single identity management technology will dominate in the near future. Furthermore, because of the technological differences between web identity management and caller identification in SIP and other previously developed real-time communication technologies, the seamless flow of identity information across these technologies will likely remain elusive for the foreseeable future.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Conclusion">
        <t>Every calling technology presents significant challenges to the secure identification of the caller. The interoperation of all of these technologies -- from legacy pre-SS7 telephone networks to cutting edge web-based calling services -- further complicates the task of identifying the origin of a call in a trusted and interoperable way. While industry efforts are underway to address some of these challenges, a uniform origin identification system is unlikely to emerge, regardless of potential regulatory mandates.</t>
      </section>

    <section title="Security Considerations">
      <t>This document describes, at a high level, some of the security challenges of providing trustworthy call origin information. There are further detailed privacy and security aspects related to call origin identification that will be addressed in a future version of this document.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <!--  *****BACK MATTER ***** -->

  <back>
    <references title="Informative References">

      &RFC3325;
      &RFC6072;
      &RFC4474;
      &RFC3323;
      &RFC5767;
      &RFC5379;

      <reference anchor="TD-62"
                 target="http://files.wcitleaks.org/public/T09-CWG.WCIT12-120620-TD-PLEN-0062R2.pdf">
        <front>
          <title>CWG-WCIT12 Temporary Document 62 Rev.2 - Draft Compilation of Proposals with Options for Revisions to the ITRs</title>

          <author fullname="Council Working Group Chairman">
            <organization>Council Working Group to Prepare for the 2012 World Conference on International Telecommunications</organization>
          </author>

          <date year="2012"/>
        </front>
      </reference>

    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
