<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!-- This template is for creating an Internet Draft using xml2rfc,
     which is available here: http://xml.resource.org. -->
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!-- One method to get references from the online citation libraries.
     There has to be one entity for each item to be referenced. 
     An alternate method (rfc include) is described in the references. -->
]>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629toFO.xslt' ?>
<!-- used by XSLT processors -->
<!-- For a complete list and description of processing instructions (PIs), 
     please see http://xml.resource.org/authoring/README.html. -->
<!-- Below are generally applicable Processing Instructions (PIs) that most I-Ds might want to use.
     (Here they are set differently than their defaults in xml2rfc v1.32) -->
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<!-- give errors regarding ID-nits and DTD validation -->
<!-- control the table of contents (ToC) -->
<?rfc toc="no"?>
<!-- generate a ToC -->
<?rfc tocdepth="4" ?>
<!-- the number of levels of subsections in ToC. default: 3 -->
<!-- control references -->
<?rfc symrefs="no" ?>
<!-- use symbolic references tags, i.e, [RFC2119] instead of [1] -->
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<!-- sort the reference entries alphabetically -->
<!-- control vertical white space 
     (using these PIs as follows is recommended by the RFC Editor) -->
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<!-- do not start each main section on a new page -->
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<!-- keep one blank line between list items -->
<!-- end of list of popular I-D processing instructions -->
<rfc category="info" docName="draft-cooper-privacy-policy-00" ipr="trust200902">
  <!-- category values: std, bcp, info, exp, and historic
     ipr values: full3667, noModification3667, noDerivatives3667
     you can add the attributes updates="NNNN" and obsoletes="NNNN" 
     they will automatically be output with "(if approved)" -->

  <!-- ***** FRONT MATTER ***** -->

  <front>
    <title abbrev="IETF Privacy Policy">IETF Privacy Policy</title>

	<author fullname="Alissa Cooper" initials="A." surname="Cooper">
		<organization>Center for Democracy &amp; Technology</organization>
		<address>
			<postal>
				<street>1634 I Street NW, Suite 1100</street>
				<city>Washington</city>
				<region>DC</region>
				<code></code>
				<country>USA</country>
			</postal>
			<email>acooper@cdt.org</email>
		</address>
	</author>
   <date year="2010" />

    <!-- If the month and year are both specified and are the current ones, xml2rfc will fill in the current day for you. If only the current year is specified, xml2rfc will fill in the current day and month for you. If the year is not the current one, it is necessary to specify at least a month (xml2rfc assumes day="1" if not specified for the purpose of calculating the expiry date).  With drafts it is normally sufficient to specify just the year. -->

    <!-- Meta-data Declarations -->

    <workgroup>IETF</workgroup>

    <!-- WG name at the upperleft corner of the doc, IETF is fine for individual submissions.  If this element is not present, the default is "Network Working Group", which is used by the RFC Editor as a nod to the history of the IETF. -->

    <abstract>
      <t>
This document proposes to serve as the IETF's privacy policy. This policy applies to data collected in conjunction with IETF activities and on public IETF-related web sites.
      </t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

<middle>

    <!-- Introduction -->
    <section anchor="intro-sec" title="Introduction">
<t>In keeping with the goals and objectives of this standards body, the IETF is committed to the highest degree of respect for the privacy of IETF participants and site visitors. This policy applies to data collected in conjunction with IETF activities, whether online or in person, and on public web sites hosted on ietf.org, iab.org, iesg.org, rfc-editor.org, and irtf.org (known hereafter as "IETF-related web sites"). This policy explains how the IETF applies the Fair Information Practices -- a widely accepted set of privacy principles <xref target="OECD"/> -- to the data we collect. </t>

<t>[Note: This document is meant to be a strawman proposal for a public-facing privacy policy that any visitor to IETF-related web sites can read and understand. The policies described are a combination of observations about the data the IETF collects, language from the ISOC privacy policy, and examples of good policies from other organizations. The document was drafted without direct knowledge of the server log practices on ietf.org and the other domains, but instead based on common web server practices. The text of this document should be modified to reflect actual IETF practices should they differ from common practices.</t>
	
	<t>The hope is that this document will generate discussion within the community and attention from those who know more about what the IETF's privacy practices actually are. It is not clear that the RFC model is the best model for a document like this, but hopefully by starting this way we can generate a good discussion.]</t>
</section> 

<section anchor="auto-collected-sec" title="Information that is automatically collected on IETF-related web sites">
	<t>Several different kinds of information are automatically collected when you visit IETF-related web sites:
		
		<list style="symbols">
		<t>Internet Protocol (IP) address: The address of your computer on the Internet. Your IP address gets transmitted whenever you communicate online or visit web sites so that the content you are accessing can be delivered to you.</t>
		
		<t>Browser type and operating system: The name and version number of your web browser (for example, Internet Explorer 7 or Firefox 3.5.3) and operating system (for example,  Windows XP or Mac OS X).</t>

		<t>Cookie: A piece of information that your browser can record after visiting a web site. We use cookies on www.ietf.org, tools.ietf.org, and [fill in other subdomains as appropriate].</t>

		<t>URL of the page that directed you to our site: If you arrive at an IETF-related web site through a link on another web site -- a search engine or a blog, for example -- our web servers will record the address of the web page that referred you to our site. If you arrive at our web site by clicking on a search result returned by a search engine, our servers may (depending on the search engine) record the search terms that you used.</t> 

		<t>Whether you have bookmarked our web site(s) on your web browser. This information is only reported for Internet Explorer users. [Note: This is true for other organizations' privacy policies, but not sure if it belongs here.]</t>

		<t>The web page(s) within our site(s) that you visit, the web page you visit first on one of our sites (the entry page), and the web page you visit last on one of our sites (the exit page)</t> 

		<t>Bandwidth used: The total number of bytes downloaded when you browse one of our sites</t> 

		<t>Amount of time you spend during a visit to one of our sites</t> 

		<t>Time and date of your site visit</t>
	</list></t>
	
	<t>[Note: Is the list above correct? What else gets collected automatically?]</t>

	<t>This individualized, non-aggregated data is stored in log files that we will delete every [X] days. We may occasionally examine these individualized log files for troubleshooting and security purposes. [Note: Is this true? What else is done with this data?]</t>

	<t>We use persistent cookies on www.ietf.org to record your preference about how you like to view the web site. These cookies have a [fill in expiration period] lifetime. We use persistent cookies on tools.ietf.org for [fill in purposes]. These cookies have a [fill in expiration period] lifetime.</t>
	
</section>

 <section anchor="choose-sec" title="Information you can choose to share with the IETF">
	<t>You can choose to share information with the IETF in a number of ways:</t>

	<t>Searching on IETF-related web sites:<vspace />
	The search terms you enter on IETF-related web sites are used only to provide you with search results.</t>

	<t>Making an IETF Contribution:<vspace />
		As defined in <xref target="RFC3979"/>, an "IETF Contribution" is any submission to the IETF intended by the contributor for publication as all or part of an Internet-Draft or RFC (with limited exceptions) and any statement made within the context of an IETF activity. Such statements include oral statements in IETF sessions, as well as written and electronic communications made at any time or place which are addressed to the IETF. All IETF Contributions are public information that we may indefinitely retain and post publicly.</t> 
	
	<t>Signing up for a mailing list:<vspace />
	When you sign up for an IETF mailing list, you must provide an email address, and you may optionally provide your name and a password. We use this information only to deliver list mail to you and to administer the mailing lists.</t>
	
	<t>Registering to attend a meeting or social event:<vspace /> 
	When you register to attend an IETF meeting or an IETF social event, we ask you for certain information about yourself, commonly including your name, affiliation, address, email address, phone number, t-shirt size, dietary restrictions, profile URL, and credit card information. We use this information to register you for the meeting and to process your payment. [Note: What else is this information used for? With whom is it shared? Is it appropriate to include the social event registration in this item, or is that information sometimes collected and processed by the sponsor?]</t>
	
	<t>Attending a meeting:<vspace />
	When you attend a working group session at an IETF meeting, you are required to provide your name and email address on a form known as a "blue sheet" (which often but not always is blue). The blue sheets serve as the official attendance record for working group sessions, and such records are required by <xref target="RFC2418"/> in support of an open Internet standards process. To the extent <xref target="RFC2418"/> is revised to require practices in conflict with this privacy policy, this policy must be revised at the same time as <xref target="RFC2418"/>. We may also from time to time experiment with other ways of collecting attendance information (such as the RFID experiment conducted at IETF 76 <xref target="RFID-experiment"/>). The policies surrounding the data collection and use involved in these experiments will always be announced well in advance and linked from this policy.</t>
	
	<t>Submitting or updating an Intellectual Property Rights (IPR) disclosure:<vspace /> 
	When you submit or update an IPR disclosure (per <xref target="RFC3979"/>), we ask you for certain information about yourself, including your name, address, telephone number, and email address. We use this information only as described in <xref target="RFC3979"/> to handle IPR issues.</t>
	
	<t>Using IETF tools:<vspace /> 
	The IETF hosts several tools <xref target="Tools" /> on its web site -- including rfcdiff, idnits, and idspell -- that take Internet-Drafts or potential Internet-Drafts as input. We use these inputs only for the purpose of providing the tools.</t>  

	<t>[Note: What is missing from this list?]</t>
	
	<t>Working group chairs, IESG members, and IAB members have many additional opportunities to share information with the IETF which are not covered by this policy. [Note: Should those be documented here and covered by this policy? Or should they be documented elsewhere and linked from here?]</t>
</section>

<section anchor="disclosure-sec" title="Data disclosure">

<t>The IETF does not sell, rent, or exchange any information that we collect about our participants or site visitors. However, we will disclose information under the following circumstances:</t>

<t>All IETF Contributions are public information and are usually disclosed at the time the Contributions are made.</t>

<t>We may disclose to our payment processor [Note: Who is this?] the payment information you provide to us when you register to attend an IETF meeting in order to process your payment.</t>

<t>For all of the information we retain, we will comply with lawful requests from law enforcement and civil litigants that follow appropriate legal standards and procedures. If the law or a lawful order requires us to disclose information about your activities, we will (unless prohibited by law from doing so) attempt to contact you prior to such disclosure, and attempt to disclose to you the fact that we have submitted information to legal authorities or civil litigants (including disclosing which information we have submitted). We will object to disclosure requests that we believe are improper.</t>

</section>

<section anchor="retention-sec" title="Data retention">

<t>All log files of automatically collected data about our site visitors are deleted every [X] days. [Note: Some information about log file back-ups and the retention of search terms should be inserted here.] Aggregated data about visitors to our web site which cannot be linked back to individual visitors may be retained permanently.</t>

<t>Meeting registration information other than credit card information is permanently retained. Credit card processing records are retained for 18 months. [Note: This is how the policy appears based on the IETF Trust Records Retention and Management Policy.]</t>

<t>Blue sheets are permanently retained.</t>

<t>IPR Disclosures are permanently retained.</t>

<t>IETF Tools inputs are [fill in the correct policy].</t>

<t>More information about IETF data retention policies can be found in the IETF Trust Records Retention Policy <xref target="Trust-retention" />.</t>

</section>

<section anchor="security-sec" title="Security Considerations">

<t>Online transactions of a sensitive nature, such as those involving credit card numbers, are protected by secure browser connections. Our site supports the use of secure socket layer (SSL) encryption technology to encrypt your information prior to transmission over the Internet.</t> 

<t>[Note: This is derived from ISOC's policy. Does the IETF have the same policy? Is there more to say here?]</t>
</section>

<section anchor="changes-sec" title="Changes to the privacy policy">

<t>If we make substantial changes to this privacy policy, we will post a prominent notification on www.ietf.org and we will send a notice to the IETF-Announce mailing list about the changes. You can sign up for that mailing list at <xref target="IETF-Announce"/>.</t>

</section>

<section anchor="priv-questions-sec" title="Your privacy questions">

<t>Feel free to contact us at [insert appropriate email address] to ask us to disclose to you any information we have about you. You have the right to correct, update, or delete information that we may have about you, except to the extent that such alteration or deletion would be contrary to the purpose and terms of <xref target="RFC3979"/> or <xref target="RFC2418"/>.</t>

<t>If you have any concerns about this policy, please contact [insert appropriate email address].</t>

<t>[Note: This is derived from CDT's privacy policy and is offered as an example of a policy that the IETF could have.]</t>
</section>

<section anchor="IANA-sec" title="IANA Considerations">
  <t>This document makes no request of IANA.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="ack-sec" title="Acknowledgements">
	<t>I would like to thank Fred Baker and John Morris for their reviews of this document.</t>
</section>


</middle>

 <!--  *****BACK MATTER ***** -->

 <back>
   <references title="Informative References">
	
		<reference anchor='IETF-Announce'>
			<front>
				<title>IETF-Announce Info Page</title>
				<author>
					<organization abbrev='IETF'>
						Internet Engineering Task Force
					</organization>
				</author>
			</front>
			<seriesInfo name="" value="https://www.ietf.org/mailman/listinfo/IETF-Announce" />
			<format type="HTML" target="https://www.ietf.org/mailman/listinfo/IETF-Announce" />
		</reference>
		<reference anchor='RFID-experiment'>
		    <front>
		        <title>RFID Tagging Experiment at IETF 76</title>
		        <author>
		            <organization abbrev='IETF'>
		            Internet Engineering Task Force
		            </organization>
		        </author>
		        <date year='2009' />
		    </front>
		    <seriesInfo name="" value="http://www.ietf.org/EbluesheetInformation.html" />
		<format type="HTML" target="http://www.ietf.org/EbluesheetInformation.html" />
		</reference>
		
		<reference anchor='Tools'>
		    <front>
		        <title>IETF Tools</title>
		        <author>
		            <organization abbrev='IETF'>
		            Internet Engineering Task Force
		            </organization>
		        </author>
		        <date year='2009' />
		    </front>
		    <seriesInfo name="" value="http://tools.ietf.org/tools/" />
		<format type="HTML" target="http://tools.ietf.org/tools/" />
		</reference>
	
		<reference anchor='Trust-retention'>
		    <front>
		        <title>IETF Trust Records Retention and Management Policy</title>
		        <author>
		            <organization abbrev='IETF'>
		            IETF Trust
		            </organization>
		        </author>
		        <date year='2007' />
		    </front>
		    <seriesInfo name="" value="http://trustee.ietf.org/docs/IETF_Trust_Records_Retention_Policy_(Complete_Final).pdf" />
		<format type="PDF" target="http://trustee.ietf.org/docs/IETF_Trust_Records_Retention_Policy_(Complete_Final).pdf" />
		</reference>
		
		<reference anchor='OECD'>
		    <front>
		        <title>OECD Guidelines on the Protection of Privacy and Transborder Flows of Personal Data</title>
		        <author>
		            <organization abbrev='OECD'>
		            Organization for Economic Cooperation and Development
		            </organization>
		        </author>
		        <date year='1980' />
		    </front>
		    <seriesInfo name="" value="http://www.oecd.org/document/18/0,3343,en_2649_34255_1815186_1_1_1_1,00.html" />
			<format type="HTML" target="http://www.oecd.org/document/18/0,3343,en_2649_34255_1815186_1_1_1_1,00.html" />
		</reference>
	
	<?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3979.xml"?>
	<?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2418.xml"?>
 </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
		