<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<rfc category="std" docName="draft-burman-rtcweb-h264-proposal-01"
     ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="H.264 as Mandatory in WebRTC">H.264 as Mandatory to
    Implement Video Codec for WebRTC</title>

    <author fullname="Bo Burman" initials="B.B." surname="Burman">
      <organization>Ericsson</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Farogatan 6</street>

          <code>16480</code>

          <city>Stockholm</city>

          <country>Sweden</country>
        </postal>

        <email>bo.burman@ericsson.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Markus Isomaki" initials="M.I." surname="Isomaki">
      <organization>Nokia</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Keilalahdentie 2-4</street>

          <city>Espoo</city>

          <code>FI-02150</code>

          <country>Finland</country>
        </postal>

        <email>markus.isomaki@nokia.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Bernard Aboba" initials="B.A." surname="Aboba">
      <organization>Microsoft Corporation</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>One Microsoft Way</street>

          <city>Redmond</city>

          <region>WA</region>

          <code>98052</code>

          <country>US</country>
        </postal>

        <email>bernard_aboba@hotmail.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Gaelle Martin-Cocher" initials="G.M-C."
            surname="Martin-Cocher">
      <organization>RIM</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>1875 Buckhorn Gate</street>

          <city>Mississauga</city>

          <region>ON</region>

          <code>L4W 5P1</code>

          <country>Canada</country>
        </postal>

        <email>gmartincocher@rim.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Giri Mandyam" initials="G.M." surname="Mandyam">
      <organization>Qualcomm Innovation Center</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street/>

          <city/>

          <region/>

          <code/>

          <country/>
        </postal>

        <email>mandyam@quicinc.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Xavier Marjou" initials="X.M." surname="Marjou">
      <organization>France Telecom Orange</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>2, avenue Pierre Marzin</street>

          <city>Lannion</city>

          <region/>

          <code>22307</code>

          <country>France</country>
        </postal>

        <email>xavier.marjou@orange.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date day="25" month="February" year="2013"/>

    <area>Transport</area>

    <workgroup>RTCWEB Working Group</workgroup>

    <keyword>browser</keyword>

    <keyword>websocket</keyword>

    <keyword>real-time</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>This document proposes that, and motivates why, H.264 should be a
      Mandatory To Implement video codec for WebRTC.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction" toc="default">
      <t>The selection of a Mandatory To Implement (MTI) video codec for
      WebRTC has been discussed for quite some time in the RTCWEB WG. This
      document proposes that the H.264 video codec should be mandatory to
      implement for WebRTC implementations and gives motivation to this
      proposal.</t>

      <t>The core of the proposal is that H.264 Constrained Baseline Profile
      Level 1.2 MUST be supported as Mandatory To Implement video codec. To
      enable higher quality for devices capable of it, support for H.264
      Constrained High Profile Level 1.3, extended to support 720p resolution
      at 30 Hz framerate is RECOMMENDED.</t>

      <t>This draft discusses the advantages of H.264 as the authors of this
      draft see them; a richness of implementations and hardware support, well
      known licensing conditions, good performance, and well defined handling
      of varying device capabilities.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Terminology" toc="default">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
      document are to be interpreted as described in BCP 14, RFC 2119 <xref
      format="default" pageno="false" target="RFC2119"/>.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="H.264 Overview" toc="default">
      <t>The video coding standard Advanced Video Coding (<xref
      target="H264">ITU-T H.264 | ISO/IEC 14496-10</xref>) has been around for
      almost ten years by now. Developed jointly by MPEG and ITU-T in the
      Joint Video Team, it was published in its first version in 2003 and
      amended with support for higher-fidelity video in 2004. Other
      significant updates include support for scalability (2007) and multiview
      (2009). The codec goes under the names H.264, AVC and MPEG-4 Part10. In
      this memo the term "H.264" will be used.</t>

      <t>H.264 was from the start very successful and has become widely
      adopted for (video) content as well as (video) communication services
      worldwide.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="sec-implementations" title="Implementations"
             toc="default">
      <t>Arguably, hardware or DSP acceleration for video encoding/decoding
      would be mostly beneficial for devices that has relatively lower
      capacity in terms of CPU and power (smaller batteries), and the most
      common devices in this category are phones and tablets. There is a long
      list of vendors offering hardware or DSP implementations of H.264. In
      particular all vendors of platforms for mobile high-range phones,
      smartphones, and tablets support H.264/AVC High Profile encoding and
      decoding at least 1080p30, but those platforms are currently in general
      not used for low- to mid-range devices. These vendors are ST-Ericsson,
      Qualcomm, TI, Nvidia, Renesas, Mediatek, Huawei Hisilicon, Intel,
      Broadcom, Samsung. Those platforms all support H.264/AVC codec with
      dedicated HW or DSP. For at least the ST-Ericsson and Qualcomm hardware
      it is verified that the implementation has low-delay real-time support,
      but it seems likely that this is the case for at least the majority of
      the others as well.</t>

      <t>There are also other specifications that implement support for H.264,
      such as HDMI(TM).</t>

      <t>Regarding software implementations there is a long list of available
      implementations. Wikipedia provides an illustration of this with their
      <xref target="Implementations">list</xref>, and more implementations
      appear, e.g. <xref target="Woon"/>. Not only are there standalone
      implementations available, including open source, but in addition recent
      Windows and Mac OS X versions support H.264 encoding and decoding.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Licensing" toc="default">
      <t>H.264 is a mature codec with a mature and well-known licensing model.
      MPEG-LA released their AVC Patent Portfolio License already in 2004 and
      in 2010 they announced that H.264 encoded Internet video is free to end
      users will never be charged royalties <xref target="MPEGLA"/>. Real-time
      generated content, the content most applicable to WebRTC, was free
      already from the establishment of the MPEG-LA license. License fees for
      products that decode and encode H.264 video remain though. Those fees
      are, and will very likely continue to be for the lifetime of MPEG-LA
      pool, $0.20 per codec or less. It can be noted that for MPEG-LA, since
      one license covers both an encoder and decoder, there is no additional
      cost of using an encoder to an implementation that supports decoding of
      H.264.</t>

      <t>It is a well-established fact that not all H.264 right holders are
      MPEG-LA pool members. H.264 is however an ITU/ISO/IEC international
      standard, developed under their respective patent policies, and all
      contributors must license their patents under Reasonable And
      Non-Discriminatory (RAND) terms. In the field of video coding, most
      major research groups interested in patents do contribute to the
      ITU/ISO/IEC standards process and are therefore bound by those
      terms.</t>

      <t>VP8 is a much younger codec than H.264 and it is fair to say that the
      licensing situation is less clear than for H.264. Google has provided
      their patent rights on VP8 under a open source friendly license with
      very restrictive reciprocity conditions. According to MPEG-LA's web page
      <xref target="MpegLaVp8"/>, MPEG-LA is in the process of forming a
      royalty-bearing patent pool for VP8. Also, according to press reports
      <xref target="DoJ"/>, at least the US Department of Justice investigate
      MPEG-LA for anticompetitive activity in conjunction with the VP8 pool
      formation. This indicates that the licensing situation for VP8 has not
      settled.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Performance" toc="default">
      <t>Comparing video quality is difficult. Practically no modern video
      encoding method includes any bit-exact encoding where a given (video)
      input produces a specified encoded output bitstream. Instead, the
      encoded bitstream syntax and semantics are specified such that a decoder
      can correctly interpret it and produce a known output. This is true both
      for H.264 and VP8. Significant freedom is left to the encoder
      implementation to choose how to represent the encoded video, for example
      given a specific targeted bitrate. Thus it cannot in general be expected
      that any encoded video bitstream represents the best possible or most
      efficient representation, given the defined bitstream syntax elements
      available to that codec. The actually achieved quality for a certain
      bitstream, how close it is to the optimally possible with available
      syntax, at any given bitrate rather depends on the performance of the
      individual encoder implementation.</t>

      <t>Also, not only is the resulting experienced video quality subjective,
      but also depends on the source material, on the point of operation and a
      number of other considerations. In addition, performance can be measured
      vs. bitrate, but also vs. e.g. complexity - and here another can of
      worms can be opened because complexity depends on hardware used (some
      platforms have video codec accelerations), SW platform (and how
      efficient it can use the hardware) and so on. On top of this comes that
      different implementations can have different performance, and can be
      operated in different ways (e.g. tradeoffs between complexity and
      quality can be made). Regardless of how a performance evaluation is
      carried out it can always be said that it is not "fair". This section
      nevertheless attempts to shed some light on this subject, and
      specifically the performance (measured against bitrate) of H.264
      compared to VP8.</t>

      <t>A number of studies <xref target="H264perf1"/><xref
      target="H264perf2"/><xref target="H264perf3"/> have been made to compare
      the compression efficiency performance between H.264 and VP8. These
      studies show that H.264 is in general performing better than VP8 but the
      studies are not specifically targeting video conferencing. Therefore,
      Ericsson made a comparison where a number of video conferencing type
      sequences were encoded using both H.264 and VP8. Eight video
      conferencing type test sequences were used; three were taken from the
      MPEG/ITU test set (vidyo2-4) and five were recorded by Ericsson. The
      sequences were all 720p 25/30Hz.</t>

      <t>The focus of that test was to evaluate the best compression
      efficiency that could be achieved with both codecs since it was believed
      to be harder to make a fair comparison trying to use complexity
      constraints. The results showed that H.264 High Profile provides an
      average bitrate compared to VP8 of -23% (minus here means that H.264 is
      better) using PSNR-based Bjontegaard Delta bitrate (BD-rate) <xref
      target="PSNRdiff"/>. H.264 Constrained High Profile provided -16% and
      Constrained Baseline Profile resulted in +16% (plus here means that VP8
      is better).</t>

      <t>For H.264, JM 18.3 in low-delay mode without reordering of B or P
      pictures was used. For VP8 encoding, v1.1.0 with the "best" preset was
      used.</t>

      <t>Again, video quality is difficult to compare. The authors however
      believe that the data provided in this section shows that H.264 is at
      least on par with VP8. As a final note, the new H.265/HEVC standard
      clearly outperforms both of them, but the authors think it is premature
      to mandate HEVC for WebRTC.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="sec-profile-level" title="Profile/level" toc="default">
      <t><xref target="H264">H.264/AVC</xref> has a large number of encoding
      tools, grouped in functionally reasonable toolsets by codec profiles,
      and a wide range of possible implementation capability and complexity,
      specified by codec levels. It is typically not reasonable for H.264
      encoders and decoders to implement maximum complexity capability for all
      of the available tools. Thus, any H.264 decoder implementation is
      typically not able to receive all possible H.264 streams. Which streams
      can be received is described by what profile and level the decoder
      conforms to. Any video stream produced by an H.264 encoder must keep
      within the limits defined by the intended receiving decoder's profile
      and level to ensure that the video stream can be correctly decoded.</t>

      <t>Profiles can be "ranked" in terms of the amount of tools included,
      such that some profiles with few tools are "lower" than profiles with
      more tools. However, profiles are typically not strictly supersets or
      subsets of each other in terms of which tools are used, so a strict
      ranking cannot be defined. It is also in some cases possible to express
      compliance to the common subset of tools between two different profiles.
      This is fairly well described in <xref target="RFC6184"/>.</t>

      <t>When choosing a Mandatory To Implement codec, it is desirable to use
      a profile and level that is as widely supported as possible. Therefore,
      H.264 Constrained Baseline Profile Level 1.2 MUST be supported as
      Mandatory To Implement video codec. This is possible to support with
      significant margin in <xref target="sec-implementations">hardware
      devices</xref> and should likely also not cause performance problems for
      software-only implementations. All Level definitions (Annex A of <xref
      target="H264"/>) include a maximum framesize in macroblocks (16*16
      pixels) as well as a maximum processing requirement in macroblocks per
      second. That number of macroblocks per second can be almost freely
      distributed between framesize and framerate. The maximum framesize for
      Level 1.2 corresponds to 352*288 pixels (CIF). Examples of allowed
      framesize and framerate combinations for Level 1.2 are CIF (352*288
      pixels) at 15 Hz, QVGA (320*240 pixels) at 20 Hz, and QCIF (176*144
      pixels) at 60 Hz.</t>

      <t>Recognizing that while the above profile and level will likely be
      possible to implement in any device, it is also likely not sufficient
      for applications that require higher quality. Therefore, it is
      RECOMMENDED that devices and implementations that can meet the
      additional requirements also implement at least H.264 Constrained High
      Profile Level 1.3, extended to support 720p resolution at 30 Hz
      framerate, but the extension MAY alternatively be made from any Level
      higher than 1.3.</t>

      <t>Note that the lowest non-extended Level that support 720p30 is Level
      3.1, but fully supporting Level 3.1 also requires fairly high bitrate,
      large buffers, and other encoding parameters included in that Level
      definition that are likely not reasonable for the targeted communication
      scenario. This method of <xref target="sec-negotiation">extending a
      lower level in SDP</xref> with a smaller set of applicable parameters is
      fully in line with <xref target="RFC6184"/>, and is already used by some
      video conferencing vendors.</t>

      <t>When considering the main WebRTC use case, real-time communication,
      the lack of need to support interlaced image format in that context, the
      limited use of and added delay from bi-directionally predicted (B)
      pictures, and the added implementation and computation complexity that
      comes with interlace and B-picture handling suggests that Constrained
      High Profile should be preferred over High Profile as optional codec.
      Note also that while Constrained High Profile is currently less
      supported in devices than High Profile, any High Profile decoder will be
      capable of decoding a Constrained High Profile bitstream since it is a
      subset of High Profile. To make a High Profile encoder support
      Constrained High Profile encoding, it will have to turn off interlace
      encoding and turn off the use of bi-directional prediction.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="sec-negotiation" title="Negotiation" toc="default">
      <t>Given that there exist a fairly large set of defined <xref
      target="sec-profile-level">profiles and levels</xref>, the probability
      is rather low that randomly chosen H.264 encoder and decoder
      implementations have exactly matching capabilities. In any communication
      scenario, there is therefore a need for a decoder to be able to convey
      its maximum supported profile and level that the encoder must not
      exceed.</t>

      <t>In addition and depending on the wanted use case and the conditions
      that apply at a certain communication instance, there may also be a need
      to describe the currently wanted profile and level at the start of the
      communication session, which may be lower than the maximum supported by
      the implementation. In this scenario it may also be of interest to
      communicate from the encoder to the decoder both which profile and level
      that will actually be used and what is the maximum supported profile and
      level. The reason to communicate not only the starting point but also
      the maximum assumes that communication conditions may change during the
      conditions, maybe multiple times, possibly making another profile and
      level be a more appropriate choice.</t>

      <t>Communication of maximum supported profile and level is the only
      mandatory <xref target="RFC4566">SDP</xref> parameter in the <xref
      target="RFC6184">H.264 payload format</xref>, which also includes a
      large set of optional parameters, describing available use (decoder) and
      intended use (encoder) of those parameters for a specific <xref
      target="RFC3264">offered</xref> stream.</t>

      <t>If the <xref target="sec-profile-level">above mentioned</xref>
      capability for 720p30 is supported as an extension to Constrained High
      Profile Level 1.3 (or higher), the level extension SHOULD be signaled in
      SDP using the following parameters as defined in section 8.1 of <xref
      target="RFC6184"/>:<list style="symbols">
          <t>profile-level-id=640c0d (or corresponding to a higher Level of
          Constrained High profile)</t>

          <t>max-fs=3600 (or greater)</t>

          <t>max-mbps=108000 (or greater)</t>

          <t>max-br=768 (or greater, whatever the device implementation can
          support)</t>
        </list></t>
    </section>

    <section title="Summary" toc="default">
      <t>H.264 is widely adopted and used for a large set of video services.
      This in turn is because H.264 offers great performance, reasonable
      licensing terms (and manageable risks). As a consequence of its adoption
      for many services, a multitude implementations in software and hardware
      are available. Another result of the widespread adoption is that all
      associated technologies, such as payload formats, negotiation mechanisms
      and so on are well defined and standardized. In addition, using H.264
      enables interoperability with many other services without video
      transcoding.</t>

      <t>We therefore propose to the WG that H.264 shall be mandatory to
      implement for all WebRTC endpoints that support video, according to the
      details described in <xref target="sec-profile-level"/> and <xref
      target="sec-negotiation"/>.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>This document makes no request of IANA.</t>

      <t>Note to RFC Editor: this section may be removed on publication as an
      RFC.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>No specific considerations apply to the information in this
      document.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>All that provided valuable descriptions, comments and insights about
      the H.264 codec on the IETF mailing lists.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119"?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.3264'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.4566'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6184'?>

      <reference anchor="H264">
        <front>
          <title>Advanced video coding for generic audiovisual
          services</title>

          <author>
            <organization>ITU-T Recommendation H.264</organization>
          </author>

          <date month="March" year="2010"/>
        </front>
      </reference>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <reference anchor="MPEGLA"
                 target="www.mpegla.com/Lists/MPEG%20LA%20News%20List/Attachments/231/n-10-08-26.pdf">
        <front>
          <title>MPEG LAs AVC License Will Not Charge Royalties for Internet
          Video that is Free to End Users through Life of License</title>

          <author fullname="" initials="" surname="">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <date month="August" year="2010"/>
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="MPEGLA" value="News Release"/>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="H264perf1"
                 target="http://compression.graphicon.ru/video/codec_comparison/h264_2010/appendixes.html#Appendix_8">
        <front>
          <title>MPEG-4 AVC/H.264 Video Codecs Comparison 2010 -
          Appendixes</title>

          <author fullname="Dmitriy Vatolin" initials="D.V." surname="Vatolin">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <date month="May" year="2010"/>
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="" value=""/>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="H264perf2"
                 target="http://www-ee.uta.edu/Dip/Courses/EE5359/2011SpringFinalReportPPT/Shah_EE5359Spring2011FinalPPT.pdf">
        <front>
          <title>Implementation, performance analysis and comparison of VP8
          and H.264.</title>

          <author fullname="Keyur Shah" initials="K.S." surname="Shah">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <date month="" year="2011"/>
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="University of Texas at Arlington"
                    value="Department of Electrical Engineering"/>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="H264perf3"
                 target="http://infoscience.epfl.ch/record/168259/files/article.pdf">
        <front>
          <title>Performance analysis of VP8 image and video compression based
          on subjective evaluations</title>

          <author fullname="Francesca De Simone" initials="F.S."
                  surname="De Simone">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <author fullname="Lutz Goldmann" initials="L.G." surname="Goldmann">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <author fullname="Jong-Seok Lee" initials="J.L." surname="Lee">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <author fullname="Touradj Ebrahimi" initials="T.E."
                  surname="Ebrahimi">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <date month="Aug" year="2011"/>
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="Ecole Polytechnique F'd'rale de Lausanne (EPFL)"
                    value=""/>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="PSNRdiff" target="">
        <front>
          <title>Calculation of Average PSNR Differences between
          RD-Curves</title>

          <author fullname="G. Bjontegaard" initials="G.B."
                  surname="Bjontegaard">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <date month="April" year="2001"/>
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="ITU-T SG16 Q.6 Document" value="VCEG-M33"/>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="Implementations"
                 target="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/H.264/MPEG-4_AVC_products_and_implementations">
        <front>
          <title>H.264/MPEG-4 AVC products and implementations</title>

          <author fullname="Wikipedia" surname="Wikipedia">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <date day="10" month="October" year="2012"/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="MpegLaVp8"
                 target="http://www.mpeg-la.com/main/pid/vp8/default.aspx">
        <front>
          <title>MPEG LA Announces Call for Patents Essential to VP8 Video
          Codec</title>

          <author>
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <date/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="DoJ"
                 target="http://online.wsj.com/article/SB10001424052748703752404576178833590548792.html">
        <front>
          <title>Web Video Rivalry Sparks U.S. Probe</title>

          <author>
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <date/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="Woon"
                 target="http://www.polycom.com/content/www/en/company/news/press-releases/2012/20121004.html">
        <front>
          <title>Polycom Delivers Open Standards-Based Scalable Video Coding
          (SVC) Technology, Royalty-Free to Industry</title>

          <author fullname="B. Woon">
            <organization/>
          </author>

          <date day="4" month="October" year="2012"/>
        </front>
      </reference>
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
