<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd"[
    <!ENTITY rfc2119 PUBLIC '' 
      'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml'>
    <!ENTITY rfc2460 PUBLIC '' 
      'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2460.xml'>
]>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc iprnotified="no"?>
<?rfc strict="yes"?>
<rfc category="std" ipr="trust200902" docName="draft-macaulay-6man-packet-stain-00" obsoletes="" updates="" submissionType="IETF" xml:lang="en">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="IPv6 Packet Staining">IPv6 packet staining</title>
    <author initials="T.M." surname="Macaulay" fullname="Tyson Macaulay">
      <organization>Bell Canada</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>160 Elgin Floor 5</street>
          <city>Ottawa</city>
          <region>Ontario</region>
          <country>Canada</country>
        </postal>
        <email>tyson.macaulay@bell.ca</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date month="February" year="2012" />
    <area>Internet</area>
    <workgroup>6man Working Group</workgroup>
    <abstract>
      <t>This document specifies the application of security staining on an IPv6 datagrams and the minimum requirements for IPv6 nodes staining flows, IPv6 nodes forwarding stained packets and interpreting stains on flows.</t>
      <t>
The usage of the packet staining destination option enables proactive delivery of security intelligence to IPv6 nodes such as firewalls and intrusion prevention systems, and end-points such servers, workstations, mobile and smart devices and an infinite array of as-yet-to-be-invented sensors and controllers.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>
  <middle>
    <section anchor="intro" title="Introduction" toc="default">
      <t>
From the viewpoint of the network layer, a flow is a sequence of
packets sent from a particular source to a particular unicast,
anycast, or multicast destination. From an upper layer viewpoint, a
flow could consist of all packets in one direction of a specific
transport connection or media stream. However, a flow is not
necessarily 1:1 mapped to a transport connection.
</t>
      <t>
Traditionally, flow classifiers have been based on the 5-tuple of
the source and destination addresses, ports, and the transport
protocol type. However, as the growth of internetworked devices
continues under IPv6, security issues associated with the reputation
of the source of flows are becoming a critical criterion associated
with the trust of the data payloads and the security of the
destination end-points and the networks on which they reside.
</t>
      <t>
The usage of security reputational intelligence associated with the
source address field and possibly the port and protocol [REF1] enables
packet-by-packet IPv6 security classification, where the IPv6 header
extensions in the form of Destination Options may be used to stain
each packet with security reputation information such that the network
routing is unaffected, but intermediate security nodes and endpoint
devices can apply policy decisions about incoming information flows
without the requirement to assemble and treat payloads at higher
levels of the stack.
</t>
      <t>
IPv6 packet staining support consists of labeling datagrams with
security reputation information through the addition of an IPv6
destination option in the packet header by packet manipulation
devices (PMDs) in the carrier or enterprise network. This destination
option may be read by in-line security nodes upstream from the packet
destination, as well as by the destination nodes themselves.
</t>
    </section>
    <section title="Conventions used in this document" toc="default">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in <xref target="RFC2119" pageno="false" format="default" />.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="background" title="Background" toc="default">
      <t>
Internet based threats in the form of both malicious software and the agents that control this software  (organized crime, spys, hackitivits) have surpassed the abilities of signature-based security systems; whether they be on the enterprise perimeter, within the corporate network, on the endpoint point or in-the-cloud (internet-based service).  Additionally, the sensitivity of IP network continues to grow as new generation of smart devices is appearing on the networks in the form of broadband  mobile devices, legacy industrial control devices, and very low-power sensors. This diverse collections of IP-based assets is coming to be known as the Internet of Things (IOT).
</t>
      <t>
In response to the accelerating threats, the security vendor community have integrated their products with proprietary forms of security reputation intelligence.  This intelligence is about IP addresses and domains which have been observed engaged in attack-behaviours such as inappropriate messaging and traffic volumes, domain management, Botnet command-and-control channel  exchanges and other indicators of either compromise or malicious intent. [REF 1] IP address may also end up on a security reputation list if  they are identified as compromised through vendor-specific signature-based processes.  
Security reputation intelligence from vendors is typically made available to perimeter and end-point products through proprietary, internet-based queries to vendor information bases.  
</t>
      <t>
This system of using proactive, security reputation intelligence has many benefits, but also several weakness and scaling challenges.  Specifically, existing intelligence systems are:

<list style="numbers"><t>subject to direct attack from the internet on distribution points, for instance</t><t>are proprietary to vendor devices</t><t>require fat-clients consuming both bandwidth and CPU, and</t><t>introduces flow latency while queries are sent, received and processed</t><t>introduces intelligence latency as reputation lists will be inevitably cached and only periodically refreshed given the number and range of vendor-specific processing elements</t></list></t>
      <section anchor="benefits" title="Packet Staining Benefits" toc="default">
        <t>
In contrast to the challenges of current security reputation intelligence systems, packet staining has the following strengths
<list style="numbers"><t>packet staining can occur transparently in the network, presenting no attack surface</t><t>packet staining uses standardized, public domain IPv6 capabilities</t><t>security rules can be easily applied in hardware or firmware</t><t>reading packet stains introduces little to no latency</t><t>near-real-time threat intelligence distribution systems can be implemented can be implemented out of band in PMDs using a standardized packet staining method allowing multiple intelligence sources (vendor sources) to be aggregated and applied in an agnostic (cross-vendor) manner.</t></list></t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="models" title="Implementation and support models" toc="default">
        <t>
Packet staining may be accomplished by different entities including
carriers, enterprises and third-party value-added service providers.
</t>
        <t>
Carriers or service providers may elect to implement staining centres at strategic
locations in the network to provide value-added services on a
subscription basis.  Under this model, subscribers to a security
staining service would see their traffic directed through a staining
centre where Destination Options are added to the IPv6 headers and
IPv4 traffic is encapsulated within IPv6 tunnels, with stained
headers.
</t>
        <t>
Carriers or service providers may elect to stain all IPv6 traffic entering their network,
and allow subscribers to process the stains at their own discretion.
</t>
        <t>
If such upstream, network-based staining services are inappropriate or unavailable,
Enterprise data centre managers / cloud computing service providers
may elect to deploy IPv6 staining at the perimeter into the internal
network, tunnelling all IPv4 traffic, and allow data centre/cloud
service users to process stains at their discretion.
</t>
        <t>
Enterprise may wish to deploy IPv6 on internal networks, and stain all
internal traffic whereby security nodes and end-points may apply
corporate security policy related to reputation.
</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="use_cases" title="Use cases" toc="default">
        <t>
The following are example use-cases for a security technique based
upon a packet staining system.
</t>
        <t>
Organization Perimeter Use-case Traffic to a subscriber is routed
through a PMD in the carrier network configured to stain (apply
Destination Options extensions) all packets to the subscriber (TM)s
IP-range, which have entries in the threat intelligence information
base.  The PMD accesses the information base from a locally cached
file or other method not defined in this draft.  Packets from sources
not in the information base pass through the PDM unchanged.  Packets
from sources in the information base have a Destinations Option added
to the datagram header.  The Destination Options contains reputation
from the information base.  The format of the destination option is
discussed later in this draft.  IPv6 perimeter devices such as
firewalls, web proxies or security routers on the perimeter of the
subscriber network look for Destination Options on incoming packets
with reputation stains.  If a stain is found, the perimeter device
applies the organization policy associated with the reputation
indicated by the stain.  For instance, drop the packet, quarantine the
packet, issue alarms, or pass the packets and associated flow to
specially hardened extra-net authentication systems, or do nothing.
</t>
        <t>
IPv4 support Use-case" IPv4 header fields and options are not
suitable for packet staining; however, there is a clear security
benefit to supporting IPv4 flows.  IPv4 traffic to a subscriber is
routed through a PMD in the carrier network configured to encapsulate
the IPv4 traffic in an IPv6 tunnel.  The PMD applies a stain
(Destination Options extension) to the IPv6 tunnel as per the
Perimeter Use-case above. Subscriber perimeter devices such as
firewalls, web proxies or security routers are configured to support
both native IPv6 flows and IPv6 tunnels contain legacy IPv4 flows.
Perimeter devices look for Destination Options on incoming IPv6
packets with reputation stains.  If a stain is found, the perimeter
device applies the organization policy associated with the reputation
indicated by the stain to the IPv4 packet within the IPv6 tunnel.  In
this manner IPv4 support may be transparent to end-users and
applications.
</t>
        <t>
IPv6 end-point use-case" IPv6 end-points may make use of reputation
stains by processing Destination Options before engaging in any
application level processing.  In the case of certain classes of smart
device, remote and mobile sensors, reputation stains may be a critical
form of security when other mitigations such as signature bases and
firewalls are too power and processor intensive to support.
</t>
        <t>
URL-specific stains" it is a common occurrence to see large public
content portals with millions of users sharing dozens of addresses.
Frequently, malicious content will be loaded to such sites. This content
represents a very small fraction of the otherwise legitimate content
on the site, which may be under the direct control of entirely
separate entities .  Degrading the reputation of IP addresses used by
these large portals based on a very small amount of content is
problematic.  For such sites, reputation stains should have the
ability to include the URL of malicious content, such that the
reputation of the only specific portions of these large portals is
degraded according to threat evidence, rather than the entire IP address, CIDR block, ASN or domain name.
</t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section anchor="reqs" title="Requirements for staining IPv6 packets" toc="default">
      <t>
        <list style="numbers">
          <t>The default behaviour of a security node MUST be to leave a packet
unchanged (apply no stain).</t>
          <t>Reputation stains may be inserted or overwritten by security nodes
in the path.</t>
          <t>Reputation stains may not be applied by the sender/source of the
packet.</t>
          <t>The reputation staining mechanism needs to be visible to all
stain-aware nodes on the path.</t>
          <t>The mechanism needs to be able to traverse nodes that do not
understand the reputation stains. This is required to ensure that
packet-staining can be incrementally deployed over the Internet.</t>
          <t>The presence of the reputation staining mechanism should not
significantly alter the processing of the packet by nodes, unless
policy is explicitly configured. This is required to ensure that
stained packets do not face any undue delays or drops due to a badly
chosen mechanism.</t>
          <t>A PMD should be able to distinguish a trusted stain from an
untrusted stain, through mechanism such as digital signatures or
intrinsic trust among network elements.  </t>
          <t>A staining node MAY apply more specific and selective staining
services according to subscriptions.  Staining nodes SHOULD support
different reputation taxonomies to support different subscribers
and/or interoperability with other staining entities, and have the
ability to stain flows to different subscriber sources according to
different semantics.</t>
        </list>
      </t>
    </section>
    <section title="Packet Stain Destination Option (PSDO)" toc="default">
      <t>The Packet Stain Destination Option (PSDO) is a destination option that can be included in IPv6 datagrams that are inserted by PMDs in order to inform packet staining aware nodes on the path, or endpoints, that the PSDO has an alignment requirement of (none).
</t>
      <figure title="Packet Stain Destination Option Layout" anchor="psdo_layout" suppress-title="false" align="left" alt="" width="" height="">
        <artwork xml:space="preserve" name="" type="" align="left" alt="" width="" height="">
 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
                                +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
                                |  Option Type  | Option Length |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|S|U|                        Stain Data                         |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
</artwork>
      </figure>
      <figure title="" suppress-title="false" align="left" alt="" width="" height="">
        <artwork xml:space="preserve" name="" type="" align="left" alt="" width="" height="">
  Option Type

     8-bit identifier of the type of option. The option identifier
     for the reputation stain option will be allocated by the IANA.

  Option Length

     8-bit unsigned integer.  The length of the option (excluding 
     the Option Type and Option Length fields). 

  S Bit

     When this bit is set, the reputation stain option has been signed.

  U Bit

     When this bit is set, the reputation stain option contains a 
     malicious URL.

  Stain Data

     Contains the staining data.

</artwork>
      </figure>
    </section>
    <section title="Acknowledgements" toc="default">
      <t>The author wishes to achknowledge the guidance and support of Suresh Krishnan from Ericsson's Montreal lab.  The author also wishes to credit Chris Mac-Stoker from NIKSUN for his substantial contributions to the early stages of the packet staining concept.
</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="security" title="Security Considerations" toc="default">
      <t>
Some implementation may elect to no apply digital signature to
reputation stains in the Destination Option, in which case the stain is
not protected in any way, even if IPsec authentication [RFC4302] is in
use.  Therefore an unsigned reputation stain can be forged by an on-path
attacker.  Implementers are advised that any en-route change to an
unsigned security reputation stain value is undetectable. Therefore
packet staining use the Destination Options extension without digital
signatures requires intrinsic trust among the network
elements and the PMD, and the destination node or
intervening security nodes such as firewalls or IDS services. For this
reason, receiving nodes MAY need to take account of the network from
which the stained packet was received.  For instance, a multi-homed
organization may have some service providers with staining services
and others that do not.  A receiving node SHOULD be able to distinguish
which source from which stains are expected.  A receiving node SHOULD
by default ignore any reputation stains from sources (networks or
devices) that have not been specifically configured as trusted.
</t>
      <t>
The reputation intelligence of IP source addresses, ASNs, CIDR blocks
and domains is fundamental to the application of reputation stains
within packet headers.  Such reputation information can be seeded from
a variety of open and closed sources.  Poorly managed or compromised
intelligence information bases can result in denial of service against
legitimate IP addresses, and allow malicious entities to appear
trustworthy.  Intelligence information bases themselves may be
compromised in a variety of ways; for instance the raw information feeds
may be corrupted with erroneous information, alternately the
intelligence reputation algorithms could be flawed in design or
corrupted such that they generate false reputation scores. Therefore
seed intelligence SHOULD be sourced and monitored with demonstratable
diligence.  Similarly, reputation algorithms should be protected from
unauthorized change with multi-layered access controls.
</t>
      <t>
The value of reputation stains will be directly proportional to the
trustworthiness, reliability and reputation of the intelligence source
itself.  Operators of security nodes SHOULD have defined and auditable
methods upon which they select and manage the source of reputation
intelligence and the packet staining infrastructure itself.
</t>
    </section>
    <section title="IANA Considerations" toc="default">
      <t>
This document defines a new IPv6 destination option for carrying
security reputation packet stains. IANA is requested to assign a new
destination option type (TBA1) in the Destination Options registry
maintained at http://www.iana.org/assignments/ipv6-parameters

1) Signed Security Reputation Option,
2) Unsigned Security Reputation Option  
3) Signed Security Reputation Option with malicious URL
4) Unsigned Security Reputation Option  with malicious URL

The act bits for this option need to be 10 and the chg bit needs to be 0.

</t>
    </section>
  </middle>
  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <reference anchor="RFC2119">
        <front>
          <title abbrev="RFC Key Words">Key words for use in RFCs to Indicate Requirement Levels</title>
          <author initials="S." surname="Bradner" fullname="Scott Bradner">
            <organization>Harvard University</organization>
            <address>
              <postal>
                <street>1350 Mass. Ave.</street>
                <street>Cambridge</street>
                <street>MA 02138</street>
              </postal>
              <phone>- +1 617 495 3864</phone>
              <email>sob@harvard.edu</email>
            </address>
          </author>
          <date year="1997" month="March" />
          <area>General</area>
          <keyword>keyword</keyword>
          <abstract>
            <t>
   In many standards track documents several words are used to signify
   the requirements in the specification.  These words are often
   capitalized.  This document defines these words as they should be
   interpreted in IETF documents.  Authors who follow these guidelines
   should incorporate this phrase near the beginning of their document:

<list><t>
      The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL
      NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED",  "MAY", and
      "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in
      RFC 2119.
</t></list></t>
            <t>
   Note that the force of these words is modified by the requirement
   level of the document in which they are used.
</t>
          </abstract>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="BCP" value="14" />
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="2119" />
        <format type="TXT" octets="4723" target="http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc2119.txt" />
        <format type="HTML" octets="17491" target="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/html/rfc2119.html" />
        <format type="XML" octets="5777" target="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/xml/rfc2119.xml" />
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="RFC2460">
        <front>
          <title abbrev="IPv6 Specification">Internet Protocol, Version 6 (IPv6) Specification</title>
          <author initials="S.E." surname="Deering" fullname="Stephen E. Deering">
            <organization>Cisco Systems, Inc.</organization>
            <address>
              <postal>
                <street>170 West Tasman Drive</street>
                <street>San Jose</street>
                <region>CA</region>
                <code>95134-1706</code>
                <country>USA</country>
              </postal>
              <phone>+1 408 527 8213</phone>
              <facsimile>+1 408 527 8254</facsimile>
              <email>deering@cisco.com</email>
            </address>
          </author>
          <author initials="R.M." surname="Hinden" fullname="Robert M. Hinden">
            <organization>Nokia</organization>
            <address>
              <postal>
                <street>232 Java Drive</street>
                <street>Sunnyvale</street>
                <region>CA</region>
                <code>94089</code>
                <country>USA</country>
              </postal>
              <phone>+1 408 990 2004</phone>
              <facsimile>+1 408 743 5677</facsimile>
              <email>hinden@iprg.nokia.com</email>
            </address>
          </author>
          <date year="1998" month="December" />
          <area>Internet</area>
          <keyword>internet protocol version 6</keyword>
          <keyword>IPv6</keyword>
          <abstract>
            <t>
   This document specifies version 6 of the Internet Protocol (IPv6),
   also sometimes referred to as IP Next Generation or IPng.
</t>
          </abstract>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="2460" />
        <format type="TXT" octets="85490" target="http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc2460.txt" />
        <format type="HTML" octets="99496" target="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/html/rfc2460.html" />
        <format type="XML" octets="93343" target="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/xml/rfc2460.xml" />
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="REF1">
        <front>
          <title abbrev="Upstream Intelligence">Upstream Intelligence: anatomy, architecture, case studies and use-cases.</title>
          <author initials="T.M." surname="Macaulay" fullname="(Jeremy Alexander) Tyson Macaulay ">
            <organization>Bell Canada</organization>
          </author>
          <date year="2010 to 2011" month="Aug to Feburary" />
          <area>Internet</area>
          <keyword>Internet Security and Threat Intelligence</keyword>
          <keyword>IPv6</keyword>
          <abstract>
            <t>These documents represent the initial public description of packet and reputation staining for IPv4 and IPv6 networks.</t>
          </abstract>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="Information Assurance Newsletter, DOD" value="" />
        <format type="PDF" target="http://iac.dtic.mil/iatac/download/Vol13_No3.pdf" />
        <format type="PDF" target="http://iac.dtic.mil/iatac/download/Vol13_No4.pdf" />
        <format type="PDF" target="http://iac.dtic.mil/iatac/download/Vol14_No1.pdf" />
      </reference>
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
