<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
    <!-- try to enforce the ID-nits conventions and DTD validity -->
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>    <!-- items used when reviewing the document -->
<?rfc comments="no" ?>  <!-- controls display of <cref> elements -->
<?rfc inline="no" ?>    <!-- when no, put comments at end in comments section,
                                otherwise, put inline -->
<?rfc editing="no" ?>   <!-- when yes, insert editing marks -->

    <!-- create table of contents (set it options).
           Note the table of contents may be omitted
         for very short documents -->

<?rfc toc="yes"?><?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>

    <!-- choose the options for the references. Some like
         symbolic tags in the references (and citations)
         and others prefer numbers. --> 
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?><?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
    <!-- these two save paper: start new paragraphs from the same page etc. -->
<?rfc compact="yes" ?><?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<!-- end of list of processing instructions -->
    <!-- Information about the document.
         categories values: std, bcp, info, exp, and historic
         For Internet-Drafts, specify attribute "ipr".
         (ipr values are: full3667, noModification3667, noDerivatives3667),
         Also for Internet-Drafts, can specify values for
         attributes "iprExtract", and "docName".  Note
         that the value for iprExtract is the anchor attribute
         value of a section that can be extracted, and is only
         useful when the value of "ipr" is not "full3667". -->
    <!-- TODO: verify which attributes are specified only
            by the RFC editor.  It appears that attributes
            "number", "obsoletes", "updates", and "seriesNo"
            are specified by the RFC editor (and not by
            the document author). -->

<rfc    
    category="std"
    ipr="trust200902"
    docName="draft-hanes-dispatch-fax-capability-08" >
<front>
    <title abbrev="Fax Media Feature Tag ">Indicating Fax over IP Capability
    in&nbsp;the&nbsp;Session&nbsp;Initiation&nbsp;Protocol&nbsp;(SIP)</title>

    <!-- add 'role="editor"' below for the editors if appropriate -->    

    <author fullname="David Hanes" initials="D" surname="Hanes">
      <organization>Cisco Systems</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>7200-10 Kit Creek Road</street>
          <city>Research Triangle Park</city>
          <region>NC</region>
          <code>27709</code>
          <country>US</country>
        </postal>
        <email>dhanes@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Gonzalo Salgueiro" initials="G" surname="Salgueiro">
      <organization>Cisco Systems</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>7200-12 Kit Creek Road</street>
          <city>Research Triangle Park</city>
          <region>NC</region>
          <code>27709</code>
          <country>US</country>
        </postal>
        <email>gsalguei@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    
    <author fullname="Kevin P. Fleming" initials="K" surname="Fleming">
      <organization>Digium, Inc.</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>445 Jan Davis Drive NW</street>
          <city>Huntsville</city>
          <region>AL</region>
          <code>35806</code>
          <country>US</country>
        </postal>
        <email>kevin@kpfleming.us</email>
      </address>
    </author>


    <date year="2013" />
<!-- month="May" is no longer necessary note also, day="30" is optional -->
    
    <area>Real Time Applications and Infrastructure</area>    
    
    <!-- WG name at the upperleft corner of the doc, IETF fine for individual submissions -->
    
    <workgroup>DISPATCH</workgroup>
	
    <abstract>
      <t>This document defines and registers with IANA the new 'fax' media
   feature tag for use with SIP.
   Currently, fax calls are indistinguishable from voice at call initiation. Consequently, fax calls can be routed to SIP user agents that are not fax capable. A 'fax' media feature tag implemented in conjunction with caller preferences allows for more accurate fax call routing.</t>
    </abstract>

</front>

<middle>

    <section anchor="Introduction" title="Introduction">
		<t>Fax communications in the Session Initiation Protocol (SIP) [RFC3261] are handled in a "voice first" manner. Indications that a user desires to use a fax transport protocol, such as ITU-T T.38 <xref target="T38"></xref>, to send a fax are not known when the initial INVITE message is sent. The call is set up as a voice call first and then only after it is connected, does a switchover to the T.38 <xref target="T38"></xref> protocol occur. This is problematic in that fax calls can be routed inadvertently to SIP user agents (UAs) that are not fax capable.</t>
	
		<t>To ensure that fax calls are routed to fax capable SIP user agents, an implementation of caller preferences defined in RFC 3841 [RFC3841] can be used. Feature preferences are a part of RFC 3841 [RFC3841] that would allow UAs to express their preference for receiving fax communications. Subsequently SIP servers take these preferences into account to increase the likelihood that fax calls are routed to fax capable SIP user agents.
</t>
	
		<t>This document defines the 'fax' media feature tag for use in the SIP tree as per Section 12.1 of RFC 3840 [RFC3840].  This feature tag will be applied per RFC 3841 [RFC3841] as a feature preference for fax capable UAs.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Terminology" title="Terminology">
		<t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in <xref target="RFC2119"/>.</t>
	</section>
	
	<section anchor="Motivation" title="Motivation">
		<t>In the majority of circumstances, it is preferred that capabilities be handled in the Session Description Protocol (SDP) portion of the SIP [RFC3261] communication. However, fax is somewhat unique in that the ultimate intention of the call is not accurately signaled in the initial SDP exchange. Specifically, indications of T.38 <xref target="T38"></xref> or any other fax transport protocol in the call are not known when the call is initiated by an INVITE message. Fax calls are always considered voice calls until after they are connected. This results in the possibility of fax calls being received by SIP user agents not capable of handling fax transmissions.</t>
		
		<t>For example, Alice wants to send a fax to Bob. Bob has registered two SIP UAs. The first SIP UA is not fax capable but the second one supports the T.38 <xref target="T38"></xref> fax protocol. Currently, SIP servers are unable to know when the call starts that Alice prefers a fax capable SIP UA to handle her call. Additionally, the SIP servers are also not aware of which of Bob's SIP UAs are fax capable.</t>
		
		<t>To resolve this issue of calls not arriving at a UA supporting fax, this document defines a new media feature tag specific to fax per RFC 3840 [RFC3840]. Caller preferences as defined in RFC3841 [RFC3841] can then be used for registering UAs that support fax and routing fax calls to these UAs. Thus, Alice can express up front that she prefers a T.38 <xref target="T38"></xref> fax capable SIP UA for this call. At the same time, Bob's SIP UAs have expressed their fax capabilities as well during registration. Now when Alice places a fax call to Bob, the call is appropriately routed to Bob's fax capable SIP UA.</t>

	</section>
	
<section anchor="Usage" title="Usage of the sip.fax Parameter">
	

<t>The sip.fax media feature tag is a new string parameter, defined in this document, that allows a call to indicate a fax preference.  A receiving UA includes the "sip.fax" media feature tag in the Contact header field of REGISTER messages to indicate that it is fax-capable, and a SIP Registrar includes this tag in the Contact header field of its 200 OK response to confirm the registration of this preference, all as per RFC 3840 <xref target="RFC3840"/>.</t>

<t>A calling UA SHOULD include the "sip.fax" media feature tag in the Accept-Contact header of an INVITE request in order to express its desire for a call to be routed to a fax capable UA.  Otherwise, without this tag, fax call determination is not possible until after the call is connected.  If a calling UA does so, and the SIP network elements that process the call (including the called UA(s)) implement RFC 3840 and RFC 3841 procedures, then the call will be preferentially routed to UAs that have advertised their support for this feature (by including it in the Contact header of their REGISTER requests, as documented above).</t>

<t>It is possible for the calling UA to utilize additional procedures in RFC 3840 and RFC 3841 to express a requirement (instead of a preference) that its call be delivered to fax-capable UAs.  However, the calling UA SHOULD NOT require the "sip.fax" media type. Doing so could result in call failure for a number of reasons, not only because there may not be any receiving UAs registered that have advertised their support for this feature, but also because one or more SIP network elements that process the call may not support RFC 3840 and RFC 3841 processing. A calling UA that wishes to express this requirement should be prepared to relax it to a preference if it receives a failure response indicating that the requirement mechanism itself is not supported by the called UA(s), their proxies, or other SIP network elements.</t>

<t>When calls do connect through the use of "sip.fax" either as a preference
or a requirement, then UAs  should follow standard fax negotiation
procedures documented in ITU-T T.38 <xref target="T38"></xref> for T.38 fax calls and ITU-T G.711 <xref target="G711"></xref> and ITU-T V.152 <xref target="V152"></xref> sections 6 and 6.1 for fax passthrough calls.  Subsequently, the "sip.fax" feature tag has two allowed values: "t38" and "passthrough".  The "t38" value indicates that the impending call will utilize the ITU-T T.38 <xref target="T38"></xref> protocol for the fax transmission.  The "passthrough" value indicates that the ITU-T G.711 <xref target="G711"></xref> codec will be used to transport the fax call.</t>	


</section>


	<section anchor="Example" title="Example">
	
		<t>Bob registers with the fax media feature tag.  The message flow is shown in <xref target="fax_feature_tag_figure"></xref>:</t>
		<t><figure align="center" anchor="fax_feature_tag_figure" title="Fax Media Feature Tag SIP Registration Example">
          <artwork align="center">
          <![CDATA[
SIP Registrar                    Bob's SIP UA                             	  
~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~
      |                               |
      |          REGISTER F1          |
      |<------------------------------|
      |                               |
      |           200 OK F2           |
      |------------------------------>|
      |                               |
		]]></artwork>
        </figure><vspace blankLines="2" /></t>


<t>F1 REGISTER Bob -> Registrar<figure>
<artwork align="left">
<![CDATA[
REGISTER sip:example.com SIP/2.0
Via: SIP/2.0/TCP bob-TP.example.com:5060;branch=z9hG4bK309475a2
From: <sip:bob-tp@example.com>;tag=a6c85cf
To: <sip:bob-tp@pexample.com>
Call-ID: a84b4c76e66710
Max-Forwards: 70
CSeq: 116 REGISTER
Contact: <sip:bob-tp@pc33.example.com;transport=tcp>;+sip.fax="t38"
Expires: 3600
]]></artwork>
</figure></t>

<t>The registrar responds with a 200 OK:</t>

<t>F2 200 OK Registrar -> Bob<figure>
<artwork align="left">
<![CDATA[
SIP/2.0 200 OK
From: <sip:bob-tp@example.com>;tag=a6c85cf
To: <sip:bob-tp@example.com>;tag=1263390604
Contact: <sip:bob-tp@example.com;transport=tcp>;+sip.fax="t38"
Expires: 120
Call-ID: a84b4c76e66710
Via: SIP/2.0/TCP bob-TP.example.com:5060;branch=z9hG4bK309475a2
CSeq: 116 REGISTER
Expires: 3600
]]></artwork>
</figure></t>

<t>Callers desiring to express a preference for fax will include the sip.fax media feature tag in the Accept-Contact header of their INVITE.<figure>
<artwork align="left">
<![CDATA[
 
INVITE sip:bob@biloxi.example.com SIP/2.0
Via: SIP/2.0/TCP client.atlanta.example.com:5060;branch=z9hG4bK74b43
Max-Forwards: 70
From: Alice <sip:alice@atlanta.example.com>;tag=9fxced76sl
To: Bob <sip:bob@biloxi.example.com>
Accept-Contact: *;+sip.fax="t38"
Call-ID: 3848276298220188511@atlanta.example.com
CSeq: 1 INVITE
Contact: <sip:alice@client.atlanta.example.com;transport=tcp>
Content-Type: application/sdp
Content-Length: 151
 
]]></artwork>
</figure></t>

	</section>

	<section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations"> 
		<t>The security considerations related to the use of media feature tags from Section 11.1 of RFC 3840 <xref target="RFC3840"></xref> apply.</t>
	</section>
	
	<section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations"> 
  		<t>This specification adds a new media feature tag to the SIP Media Feature Tag Registration Tree per the procedures defined in RFC 2506 <xref target="RFC2506"></xref> and RFC 3840 <xref target="RFC3840"></xref>.</t>
  		
      <t>
        <list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="Media feature tag name:">sip.fax</t>
          <t hangText="ASN.1 Identifier:">1.3.6.1.8.4.{PH}</t>
          <t hangText="Summary of the media feature indicated by this tag:">This feature tag
      indicates whether a communications device supports the ITU-T T.38 <xref target="T38"></xref> fax protocol ("t38") or the passthrough method of fax transmission using the ITU-T G.711 <xref target="G711"></xref> audio codec ("passthrough").</t>
          <t hangText="Values appropriate for use with this feature tag:">Token with an
      equality relationship.  Values are:<list style="hanging">

	<t hangText="t38:">The device supports the image/t38 media type [RFC3326] and implements ITU-T T.38 <xref target="T38"></xref> for transporting the ITU-T T.30 <xref target="T30"></xref> and ITU-T T.4 <xref target="T4"></xref> fax data over IP.</t>

	<t hangText="passthrough:">The device supports the audio/pcmu and audio/pcma media types [RFC4856] for transporting ITU-T T.30 <xref target="T30"></xref> and ITU-T T.4 <xref target="T4"></xref> fax data using the ITU-T G.711 <xref target="G711"></xref> audio codec. Additional implementation recommendations are in ITU-T V.152 <xref target="V152"></xref> Sections 6 and 6.1.</t></list></t>

          <t hangText="The feature tag is intended primarily for use in the following applications, protocols, services, or negotiation mechanisms: ">This feature tag is most useful in a communications application for the early identification of a Fax over IP (FoIP) call.</t>
          <t hangText="Examples of typical use:">Ensuring a fax call is routed to a fax capable SIP UA.</t>
          <t hangText="Related standards or documents:">RFC&rfc.number;</t>
          <t hangText="Security Considerations:">The security considerations related to the use of media feature tags from Section 11.1 of RFC 3840 <xref target="RFC3840"></xref> apply.</t>
        </list>
      </t>
      
      <t>[[NOTE TO RFC EDITOR: Please change {PH} above to the correct identifier for this entry in the IANA registry for iso.org.dod.internet.features.sip-tree (1.3.6.1.8.4)]]</t>
      
      <t>[[NOTE TO RFC EDITOR: Please change &rfc.number; to the number assigned to this specification, and remove this paragraph on publication.]]</t>
	</section>

    <section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">
    	<t>
    	This document is a result of the unique cooperation between the SIP Forum and the i3 Forum who embarked on a groundbreaking international test program for FoIP to improve the interoperability and reliability of fax communications over IP networks, especially tandem networks. The authors would like to acknowledge the effort and dedication of all the members of the Fax-over-IP (FoIP) Task Group in the SIP Forum and the communications carriers of the I3 Forum that contributed to this global effort.</t>
    	
    	<t>This memo has benefited from the discussion and review of the DISPATCH working group, especially the detailed and thoughtful comments and corrections of Dan Wing, Paul Kyzivat, Christer Holmberg, Charles Eckel, Hadriel Kaplan, Tom Yu, Dale Worley, Adrian Farrel and Pete Resnick.</t>
    	
    	<t>The authors also thank Gonzalo Camarillo for his review and AD sponsorship of this draft and DISPATCH WG chair, Mary Barnes, for her review and support.
    	</t>
    </section>
    
</middle>

<back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119" ?>
	 <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3261" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3840" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3841" ?>
<reference anchor="T38">
           <front>
               <title>
               Procedures for real-time Group 3 facsimile communication over IP Networks
               </title>
               <author>
               <organization>
               International Telecommunication Union
               </organization>
               </author>
               <date month="October" year="2010"/>
           </front>
           <seriesInfo name="ITU-T" value="Recommendation T.38"/>
     </reference>	 
    </references>
    <references title="Informative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2506" ?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.3326" ?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.4856" ?>
<reference anchor="G711">
<front>
<title>Pulse Code Modulation (PCM) of Voice Frequencies</title>
<author>
<organization>International Telephone and Telegraph Consultative Committee</organization>
</author>
<date month="" year="1972" />
</front>

<seriesInfo name="CCITT" value="Recommendation G.711" />

</reference> 

<reference anchor="T30">
<front>
<title>Procedures for document facsimile transmission in the general switched telephone network</title>
<author>
<organization>International Telecommunication Union</organization>
</author>
<date month="September" year="2005" />
</front>

<seriesInfo name="ITU-T" value="Recommendation T.30" />

</reference> 


<reference anchor="T4">
<front>
<title>Standardization of Group 3 facsimile terminals for document transmission</title>
<author>
<organization>International Telecommunication Union</organization>
</author>
<date month="July" year="2003" />
</front>

<seriesInfo name="ITU-T" value="Recommendation T.4" />

</reference> 


<reference anchor="V152">
<front>
<title>Procedures for supporting voice-band data over IP networks</title>
<author>
<organization>International Telecommunication Union</organization>
</author>
<date month="September" year="2010" />
</front>

<seriesInfo name="ITU-T" value="Recommendation V.152" />

</reference> 



	</references>
  </back>
</rfc>