<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="yes"?>
<rfc category="std" docName="draft-bfmk-softwire-unified-cpe-01"
     ipr="trust200902">
  <!-- ***** FRONT MATTER ***** -->

  <front>
    <title abbrev="Generic v4inv6 CPE Provisioning Profile">Unified
    IPv4-in-IPv6 Softwire CPE</title>

    <author fullname="Mohamed Boucadair" initials="M." surname="Boucadair">
      <organization>France Telecom</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>

          <city>Rennes</city>

          <country>France</country>
        </postal>

        <email>mohamed.boucadair@orange.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Ian Farrer" initials="I." surname="Farrer">
      <organization>Deutsche Telekom</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>

          <city></city>

          <country>Germany</country>
        </postal>

        <email>ian.farrer@telekom.de</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Suresh Krishnan" initials="S." surname="Krishnan">
      <organization>Ericsson</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>

          <city></city>

          <country></country>
        </postal>

        <email>suresh.krishnan@ericsson.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date day="19" month="December" year="2012" />

    <area>Internet</area>

    <workgroup>Softwire WG</workgroup>

    <abstract>
      <t>Transporting IPv4 packets encapsulated in IPv6 is a common solution
      to the problem of IPv4 service continuity over IPv6-only provider
      networks. A number of differing functional approaches have been
      developed for this, each having their own specific characteristics. As
      these approaches share a similar functional architecture and use the
      same data plane mechanisms, this memo describes a specification whereby
      a single CPE can interwork with all of the standardized and proposed
      approaches to providing encapsulated IPv4 in IPv6 services.</t>
    </abstract>

    <note title="Requirements Language">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
      document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
      target="RFC2119">RFC 2119</xref>.</t>
    </note>
  </front>

  <!-- ***** MIDDLE MATTER ***** -->

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>IPv4 service continuity is one of the major technical challenges
      which must be considered during IPv6 migration. Over the past few years,
      a number of different approaches have been developed to assist with this
      problem. These approaches, or modes, exist in order to meet the
      particular deployment, scaling, addressing and other requirements of
      different service provider's networks. Section 2 of this document
      describes these approaches in more detail.</t>

      <t>A common feature shared between all of the differing modes is the
      integration of softwire tunnel end-point functionality into the CPE
      router. Due to this inherent data plane similarity, a single CPE may be
      capable of supporting several different approaches. Users may also wish
      to configure a specific mode of operation.</t>

      <t>A service provider's network may also have more than one mode enabled
      in order to support diverse CPE client functionality, during migration
      between modes or where services require specific supporting softwire
      architectures.</t>

      <t>For softwire based services to be successfully established, it is
      essential that the customer end-node, the service provider end-node and
      provisioning systems are able to indicate their capabilities and
      preferred mode of operation.</t>

      <t>This memo describes the logic required by both the CPE tunnel
      end-node and the service provider's provisioning infrastructure so that
      softwire services can be provided in mixed-mode environments.</t>

      <section title="Rationale">
        <t>The following rationale has been adopted for this document:</t>

        <t><list style="format (%d)">
            <t>Describe the functionality of each the different solution modes
            and provide clear distinctions between them</t>

            <t>Simplify solution migration paths: Define unified CPE behavior,
            allowing for smooth migration between the different modes</t>

            <t>Deterministic CPE co-existence behavior: Specify the behavior
            when several modes co-exist in the CPE</t>

            <t>Deterministic service provider co-existence behavior: Specify
            the behavior when several modes co-exist in the service providers
            network</t>

            <t>Re-usability: Maximize the re-use of existing functional blocks
            including tunnel end-points, port restricted NAPT44, forwarding
            behavior, etc.</t>

            <t>Solution agnostic: Adopt neutral terminology and avoid (as far
            as possible) overloading the document with solution-specific
            terms</t>

            <t>Flexibility: Allow operators to compile CPE software only for
            the mode(s) necessary for their chosen deployment context(s)</t>

            <t>Simplicity: Provide a model that allows operators to only
            implement the specific mode(s) that they require without the
            additional complexity of unneeded modes.</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="IPv4 Service Continuity Architectures: A 'Big Picture' Overview">
      <t>The solutions which have been proposed within the Softwire WG can be
      categorized into three main functional approaches, differentiated by the
      amount and type of state that the service provider needs to maintain
      within their network:<?rfc subcompact="yes" ?><list style="format (%d)">
          <t>Full stateful approach (DS-Lite, <xref target="RFC6333"></xref>):
          Requires per-session state to be maintained in the Service
          Provider's network.</t>

          <t>Binding approach (e.g., Lightweight 4over6 (Lw4o6) <xref
          target="I-D.cui-softwire-b4-translated-ds-lite"></xref><xref
          target="I-D.ietf-softwire-public-4over6"></xref> or MAP 1:1 <xref
          target="I-D.ietf-softwire-map"></xref> ): Requires a single
          per-subscriber state (or a few) to be maintained in the Service
          Provider's network.</t>

          <t>Full stateless approach (MAP, <xref
          target="I-D.ietf-softwire-map"></xref>): Does not require
          per-session or per-subscriber state to be maintained in the Service
          Provider's network.</t>
        </list></t>

      <t><?rfc subcompact="no" ?>All these approaches share a similar
      architecture, with a tunnel endpoint located in the CPE and a remote
      tunnel endpoint. All use IPv6 as the transport protocol for the delivery
      of an IPv4 connectivity service using an IPv4-in-IPv6 encapsulation
      scheme <xref target="RFC2473"></xref>.</t>

      <t>Several cases can be envisaged:<?rfc subcompact="yes" ?><list
          style="numbers">
          <t>The CPE is complied to support only one mode: No issue is raised
          by this case.</t>

          <t>The CPE supports several modes but only one mode is explicitly
          configured: No issue is raised by this case.</t>

          <t>The CPE supports several modes but no mode is explicitly enabled:
          the CPE will need additional triggers to decide which mode to
          activate.</t>

          <t>The CPE supports several modes and several modes are configured:
          the CPE will need additional triggers to decide which mode to
          activate.</t>
        </list></t>

      <t><?rfc subcompact="no" ?></t>

      <t>As this document describes a provisioning profile whereby a single
      CPE could be capable of supporting any, or multiple modes, the customer
      should not be required to have any knowledge of the capabilities and
      configuration of their CPE, or of their service provider's network.</t>

      <t>The service provider, however, may have only a single mode enabled,
      or may have multiple modes, but with one preferred mode. For this
      reason, it is necessary to approach the configuration of CPEs from the
      standpoint of the service provider's network capabilities.</t>

      <section title="Functional Elements">
        <t>The functional elements for each of the solution modes are listed
        in <xref target="functional"></xref>:</t>

        <texttable anchor="functional" title="Functional Elements">
          <ttcol align="right">Mode</ttcol>

          <ttcol align="center">Customer side</ttcol>

          <ttcol align="center">Network side</ttcol>

          <c>DS-Lite</c>

          <c>B4</c>

          <c>AFTR</c>

          <c>Lw4o6</c>

          <c>lwB4</c>

          <c>lwAFTR</c>

          <c>MAP</c>

          <c>MAP CE</c>

          <c>MAP BR</c>
        </texttable>

        <t><xref target="description"></xref> describes each functional
        element:</t>

        <texttable anchor="description" title="Required Element Functionality">
          <ttcol align="right">Functional Element</ttcol>

          <ttcol>Description</ttcol>

          <c>B4</c>

          <c>An IPv4-in-IPv6 tunnel endpoint; the B4 creates a tunnel to a
          pre-configured remote tunnel endpoint.</c>

          <c>AFTR</c>

          <c>Provides both an IPv4-in-IPv6 tunnel endpoint and a NAT44
          function implemented in the same node.</c>

          <c>lwB4</c>

          <c>A B4 which supports port-restricted IPv4 addresses. An lwB4 MAY
          also provide a NAT44 function.</c>

          <c>lwAFTR</c>

          <c>An IPv4-in-IPv6 tunnel endpoint which maintains per-subscriber
          address binding. Unlike the AFTR, it MUST NOT perform a NAPT44
          function.</c>

          <c>MAP CE</c>

          <c>A B4 which supports port-restricted IPv4 addresses. It MAY be
          co-located with a NAT44. A MAP CE forwards IPv4-in-IPv6 packets
          using provisioned mapping rules to derive the remote tunnel
          endpoint.</c>

          <c>MAP BR</c>

          <c>An IPv4-in-IPv6 tunnel endpoint. A MAP BR forwards IPv4-in-IPv6
          packets following pre-configured mapping rules.</c>
        </texttable>

        <t><xref target="common"></xref> identifies features required by the
        customer end-node.</t>

        <texttable anchor="common" style="all" title="Supported Features">
          <ttcol align="right">Functional Element</ttcol>

          <ttcol align="center">IPv4-in-IPv6 tunnel endpoint</ttcol>

          <ttcol align="center">Port-restricted IPv4</ttcol>

          <ttcol align="center">Port-restricted NAT44</ttcol>

          <c>B4</c>

          <c>Yes</c>

          <c>N/A</c>

          <c>No</c>

          <c>lwB4</c>

          <c>Yes</c>

          <c>Yes</c>

          <c>Optional</c>

          <c>MAP-E CE</c>

          <c>Yes</c>

          <c>Yes</c>

          <c>Optional</c>
        </texttable>

        <t></t>
      </section>

      <section title="Required Provisoning Information">
        <t><xref target="provisioning"></xref> identifies the provisioning
        information required for each solution mode.</t>

        <texttable anchor="provisioning" title="Provisioning Information">
          <ttcol align="right">Mode</ttcol>

          <ttcol>Provisioning Information</ttcol>

          <c>DS-Lite</c>

          <c>Remote IPv4-in-IPv6 Tunnel Endpoint Address</c>

          <c>Lw4o6</c>

          <c>Remote IPv4-in-IPv6 Tunnel Endpoint Address</c>

          <c></c>

          <c>IPv4 Address</c>

          <c></c>

          <c>Port Set</c>

          <c>MAP-E</c>

          <c>Mapping Rules</c>

          <c></c>

          <c>MAP Domain Parameters</c>
        </texttable>

        <t>Note: MAP Mapping Rules are translated into the following
        configuration parameters: Set of remote IPv4-in-IPv6 tunnel endpoint
        addresses, IPv4 address and port set.</t>

        <t><figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[
  Note: Required provisioning information for each mode may also
        be represented as follows:
  DS-Lite: - Remote IPv4-in-IPv6 Tunnel Endpoint
    Lw4o6: - DS-Lite set of provisioning information
           - IPv4 address
           - Port set
    MAP-E: - Lw4o6 set of provisioning information
           - Forwarding mapping rules

]]></artwork>
          </figure></t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="unifiedcpe" title="Unified Softwire CPE Behaviour">
      <t><?rfc ?>This section specifies a unified CPE behavior capable of
      supporting any one, or combination of, the three modes.</t>

      <section title="IPv4 Address Functional Requirements">
        <t>The following two requirements must be met by the functional
        elements:</t>

        <t><list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="Full IPv4 Address Assingment">All the aforementioned
            modes MUST be designed to allow either a full or a shared IPv4
            address to be assigned to a customer end-node. DS-Lite and MAP-E
            fulfill this requirement. With minor changes, the <xref
            target="I-D.cui-softwire-b4-translated-ds-lite"></xref>
            specification can be updated to assign full IPv4 addresses.</t>

            <t hangText="Customer End-Node NAT">A NAT function within the
            customer end-node is not required for DS-Lite, while it is
            optional for both MAP-E and Lw4o6. When NAT is enabled for MAP-E
            or Lw4o6, the customer end-node NAT MUST be able to restrict the
            external translated source ports to the set of ports that it has
            been provisioned with.</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="generic" title="Generic CPE Bootstrapping Logic">
        <t>The generic provisioning logic is designed to meet the following
        requirements:<list style="symbols">
            <t>When several service continuity modes are supported by the same
            CPE, it MUST be possible to configure a single mode for use.</t>

            <t>For each network attachment, the end-node MUST NOT activate
            more than one mode.</t>

            <t>The CPE MAY be configured by a user or via remote device
            management means (e.g., DHCP, TR-069).</t>

            <t>A network which supports one or several modes MUST return valid
            configuration data enabling requesting devices to unambiguously
            select a single mode to use for attachment.</t>

            <t>A CPE which supports only one mode or it is configured to
            enable only mode MUST ignore any configuration parameter which is
            not required for the mode it supports. </t>
          </list></t>

        <t>This section sketches a generic algorithm to be followed by a CPE
        supporting one or more of the modes listed above. Based on the
        retrieved information, the CPE will determine which mode to
        activate.</t>

        <t><list style="format (%d)">
            <t>If a given mode is enabled (DS-Lite, Lw4o6 or MAP-E), the CPE
            MUST be configured with the required provisioning information
            listed in <xref target="provisioning"></xref>. If all of the
            required information is not available locally, the CPE MUST use
            available provisioning means (e.g., DHCP) to retrieve the missing
            configuration data.</t>

            <t>If the CPE supports several modes, but no mode is explicitly
            enabled, the CPE MUST use available provisioning means (e.g.,
            DHCP) to retrieve available configuration parameters and use the
            availability of individual parameters to ascertain which
            functional mode to configure:<list style="format (2.%d)">
                <t>If only a Remote IPv4-in-IPv6 Tunnel Endpoint is received,
                the CPE MUST proceed as follows:<?rfc subcompact="yes"?><list
                    style="format (2.1.%d)">
                    <t>IPv4-in-IPv6 tunnel endpoint initialization is defined
                    in <xref target="RFC6333"></xref>.</t>

                    <t>Outbound IPv4 packets are forwarded to the next hop as
                    specified in <xref target="forwarding"></xref>.<?rfc subcompact="no" ?></t>
                  </list></t>

                <t>If a Remote IPv4-in-IPv6 Tunnel Endpoint, an IPv4 Address
                and optionally a Port Set are received, the CPE MUST behave as
                follows:<?rfc subcompact="yes" ?><list style="format (2.2.%d)">
                    <t>IPv4-in-IPv6 tunnel endpoint initialization is similar
                    to the B4 <xref target="RFC6333"></xref>.</t>

                    <t>When NAPT44 is required (e.g., because the CPE is a
                    router), a NAPT44 module is enabled.</t>

                    <t>The tunnel endpoint address is selected from the native
                    IPv6 addresses configured on the CPE. No particular
                    considerations are required to be taken into account to
                    generate the Interface Identifier.</t>

                    <t>When a port set is provisioned, the external source
                    ports MUST be restricted to the provisioned set of
                    ports.</t>

                    <t>After translation, outbound IPv4 packets are forwarded
                    to the next hop as specified in <xref
                    target="forwarding"></xref>.<?rfc subcompact="no" ?></t>
                  </list></t>

                <t>If Mapping Rule(s) are received, the CPE MUST behave as
                follows:<?rfc subcompact="yes" ?><list style="format (2.3.%d)">
                    <t>IPv4-in-IPv6 tunnel endpoint initialization is similar
                    to the B4 <xref target="RFC6333"></xref>.</t>

                    <t>The tunnel endpoint is assigned with an IPv6 address
                    which includes an IPv4 address. The MAP Interface
                    Identifier is based on the format specified in Section 2.2
                    of <xref target="RFC6052"></xref>.</t>

                    <t>When NAPT44 is required (e.g., because the CPE is a
                    router), a NAPT44 module is enabled.</t>

                    <t>When a port set is provisioned, the external source
                    port MUST be restricted to the provisioned set of
                    ports.</t>

                    <t>After translation, outbound IPv4 packets then forwarded
                    to the next hop as specified in <xref
                    target="forwarding"></xref>. <?rfc subcompact="no" ?></t>
                  </list></t>
              </list></t>
          </list></t>
      </section>

      <section title="Customer Side DHCP Based Provisioning">
        <t><list style="empty">
            <t>[DISCUSSION NOTE:<list style="numbers">
                <t>This section will be updated to reflect the consensus from
                DHC WG.</t>

                <t>As it is proposed that OPTION_MAP would be used for all new
                softwire provisioning, should we rename OPTION_MAP to
                OPTION_SW (incl. the associated sub-options)?]</t>
              </list></t>

            <t>]</t>
          </list>DHCP-based configuration SHOULD be implemented by the
        customer end-node using the following two DHCP options:</t>

        <t><list hangIndent="20" style="hanging">
            <t hangText="OPTION_AFTR_NAME"><xref target="RFC6334"></xref>
            Provides the FQDN for the remote IPv4-in-IPv6 tunnel
            end-point.</t>

            <t hangText="OPTION_MAP"><xref
            target="I-D.ietf-softwire-map-dhcp"></xref> Provides IPv4-related
            configuration for binding mode and/or mapping rules for stateless
            mode (including MAP parameters such as offset, domain prefix,
            etc.). OPTION_MAP_BIND is a sub-option used to convey an IPv4
            address (for example, encoded as an IPv4-mapped IPv6 address <xref
            target="RFC4291"></xref>). This address is used when binding mode
            is enabled. The receipt of OPTION_MAP_BIND is an implicit
            indication to the customer side device to operate in binding,
            rather than stateless mode.</t>
          </list>The customer end-node uses the DHCP Option Request Option
        (ORO) to request either one or both of these options depending on
        which modes it is capable of and configured to support.</t>

        <t>The DHCP option(s) sent in the response allow the service provider
        to inform the customer end-node which operating mode to enable.</t>

        <t>The following table shows the different DHCP options (and
        sub-options) that the service provider can supply in a response.</t>

        <t></t>

        <texttable anchor="Provision" title="DHCP Option Provisioning Matrix">
          <ttcol align="right">DHCP Option</ttcol>

          <ttcol>Stateful Mode</ttcol>

          <ttcol>Binding Mode</ttcol>

          <ttcol>Stateless Mode</ttcol>

          <c>OPTION_AFTR_NAME</c>

          <c>Yes</c>

          <c>Yes</c>

          <c>Optional</c>

          <c>OPTION_MAP_BIND</c>

          <c>No</c>

          <c>Yes</c>

          <c>No</c>

          <c>OPTION_MAP_RULE</c>

          <c>No</c>

          <c>No</c>

          <c>Yes</c>

          <c>OPTION_MAP_PORTPARAMS</c>

          <c>No</c>

          <c>Optional</c>

          <c>Optional</c>
        </texttable>

        <t>The customer side device MUST interpret the received DHCP
        configuration parameters according to the logic defined in <xref
        target="generic"></xref>:</t>

        <t><list style="symbols">
            <t>If only OPTION_AFTR_NAME is received, then the device MUST
            operate in stateful mode</t>

            <t>If both OPTION_AFTR_NAME and OPTION_MAP_BIND are received then
            the device MUST operate in binding mode</t>

            <t>If one or more OPTION_MAP_RULE options are received, then the
            customer side device MUST operate in stateless mode</t>

            <t>If both OPTION_AFTR_NAME and OPTION_MAP_RULE(s) are received,
            then the customer side device MUST operate as a MAP CE.
            OPTION_AFTR_NAME provides the FQDN of the MAP BR.</t>

            <t>If OPTION_MAP_PORTPARAMS is received as a sub-option to either
            OPTION_MAP_BIND or OPTION_MAP_RULE, then NAPT44 MUST be configured
            using the supplied port-set for external translated source
            ports.</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>From the service providers side, the following rule MUST be
        followed:</t>

        <t><list style="symbols">
            <t>The DHCP server MUST NOT send both OPTION_MAP_BIND and
            OPTION_MAP_RULE in a single OPTION_MAP response.</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="forwarding"
               title="Forwarding Action by the Customer End-Node">
        <t>For all modes, the longest prefix match algorithm MUST be enforced
        to forward outbound IPv4 packets.</t>

        <t>Specifically, this algorithm will:<?rfc ?><list style="symbols">
            <t>Always return the address of the AFTR for the DS-Lite mode.</t>

            <t>Always return the address of the lwAFTR for the binding
            mode.</t>

            <t>Return the next hop according to the pre-configured mapping
            rules for the stateless mode (i.e., MAP-E).</t>
          </list></t>

        <t></t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>Security considerations discussed in Section 7 of <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-softwire-stateless-4v6-motivation"></xref> and Section
      11 of <xref target="RFC6333"></xref> should be taken into account.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>This document does not require any action from IANA.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>Many thanks to T. Tsou, S. Perrault, S. Sivakumar, O. Troan, W. Dec,
      M. Chen, for their review and comments.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <!--  *****BACK MATTER ***** -->

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-softwire-map'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-softwire-map-dhcp'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.2473'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.2119'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.4291'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6052'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.cui-softwire-b4-translated-ds-lite'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6333'?>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6334'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-softwire-public-4over6'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-softwire-stateless-4v6-motivation'?>
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
