<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
  <!ENTITY rfc3501 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3501.xml'>
  <!ENTITY draft-sparks-genarea-mailarch PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.sparks-genarea-mailarch.xml'>

]>

<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<?rfc comments="yes" ?>
<?rfc inline="yes" ?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>

<rfc ipr="trust200902"  category="info" docName="draft-sparks-genarea-imaparch-01">

<front>

<title abbrev="IMAP Access to IETF Email List Archives">
IMAP Access to IETF Email List Archives
</title>

<author initials="R." surname="Sparks" fullname="Robert Sparks" >
 <organization>Tekelec</organization>
 <address>
 <postal>
 <street>17210 Campbell Road</street>
 <street>Suite 250</street>
 <city>Dallas</city>
 <region>Texas</region>
 <code>75254-4203</code>
 <country>USA</country>
 </postal>
 <email>RjS@nostrum.com</email>
 </address>
</author>

<date month="Feb" day="29" year="2012" />

<abstract>
<t>
The IETF makes heavy use of email lists to conduct its work. This often involves
accessing the archived history of those email lists. Participants would
like to have the ability to browse and search those archives using standard IMAP clients.
This memo captures the requirements for providing a service that would allow such
browsing and searching. 
</t>
</abstract>

</front>

<middle>

<section anchor="intro" title="Introduction">
<t>
The IETF makes heavy use of email lists to conduct its work. This often involves
accessing the archived history of those email lists. Work is underway to improve
the web-based browsing and searching of these archives <xref target="I-D.sparks-genarea-mailarch"/>.
Participants would like to have the ability to browse and search those archives using standard IMAP clients.
This memo captures the requirements for providing a service that would allow such browsing and searching. 
</t>
<t>
Discussion of this memo should take place on the ietf@ietf.org mailing list.
</t>
</section>

<section title="Requirements for IMAP access to archived IETF lists">
<t>Many participants would prefer to access the list archives using IMAP <xref target="RFC3501"/>. Providing this access while meeting the following requirements will likely require an IMAP server with specialized capabilities.</t>
<t><list style="hanging">
<t hangText="o">The system should expose the archive using an IMAP interface, with each list
represented as a mailbox.</t>
<t hangText="o">This interface must work with standard IMAP clients.</t>
<t hangText="o">The interface should allow users to each have their own read/unread marks for messages. Allowing other annotation is desirable.</t>
<t hangText="o">The interface must have server-side searching enabled, and should support multiple simultaneous extensive searches. The server should facilitate
the enhanced search capabilities described in <xref target="I-D.sparks-genarea-mailarch"/></t>
<t hangText="o">When the system requires credentials, it must use the datatracker's authentication system
<list style="hanging">
<t hangText="-">While the vast majority of archived lists have an open access policy, some archived lists have restricted archives.  The system must make it possible to limit access to a restricted archive based on login credentials.</t>
</list></t>

</list></t>
</section>

<section title="Security Considerations">
<t>
   Allowing IMAP as an interface for browsing and searching the archives of IETF email lists does not affect
   the security of the Internet in any significant fashion.
</t>
</section>

<section title="IANA Considerations">
<t>
This document has no actions for IANA.
</t>
</section>

<section title="Acknowledgements">
<t>
This text was derived directly from an earlier version of <xref target="I-D.sparks-genarea-mailarch"/> 
which incorporated text suggestions from Alexey Melnikov, Pete Resnick, and S. Moonesamy.
</t>
</section>

<section title="Changelog">
<section title="00 to 01">
<t><list style="numbers">
<t>Added requirements to enable controlled access to restricted archives based on credentials</t>
<t>Generalized the requirement to use the datatracker's credentials.</t>
</list></t>
</section>
<section title="00">
<t><list style="numbers">
<t>Split this set of requirements out from the mailarch doc so that this project could be pursued separately</t>
</list></t>
</section>
</section>

</middle>
<back>

<!--
<references title="Normative References">
</references>
-->

<references title="Informative References">
&rfc3501;
<!--
&draft-sparks-genarea-mailarch;
-->
<reference anchor="I-D.sparks-genarea-mailarch"><front><title>IETF Email List Archiving and Search Tool Requirements</title><author initials="R" surname="Sparks" fullname="Robert Sparks"><organization/></author><date month="February" day="21" year="2012"/><abstract><t>The IETF makes heavy use of email lists to conduct its work. Participants frequently need to search and browse the archives of these lists, and have asked for improved search capabilities.  The current archive mechanism could also be made more efficient.  This memo captures the requirements for improved email list archiving and searching systems.</t></abstract></front><seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-sparks-genarea-mailarch-04"/><format type="TXT" target="http://www.ietf.org/internet-drafts/draft-sparks-genarea-mailarch-04.txt"/></reference>

</references>

</back>
	
</rfc>
