<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/authoring/rfc2629.dtd" [
	<!ENTITY RFC2119 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
]>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc iprnotified="no" ?>
<?rfc strict="no" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="no" ?>
<rfc category="info" docName="draft-xiao-clue-telemedical-use-case-00.txt" ipr="trust200902">
	<front>
		<title abbrev="Telemedicine Use Case"> Use Case for Telemedical with Multi-streams</title>
		<author fullname="Lennard Xiao" initials="L." surname="Xiao">
			<organization>Huawei Technologies Co., Ltd.</organization>
			<address>
				<postal>
					<street/>
					<city>Shenzhen </city>
					<region/>
					<code/>
					<country>PRC</country>
				</postal>
				<email>lennard.xiao@huawei.com</email>
			</address>
		</author>
		<author fullname="Roni Even" initials="R." surname="Even">
			<organization>Huawei Technologies Co., Ltd.</organization>
			<address>
				<postal>
					<street/>
					<city>Tel Aviv</city>
					<region/>
					<code/>
					<country>Israel</country>
				</postal>
				<email>even.roni@huawei.com</email>
			</address>
		</author>
		<date month="July" year="2012"/>
		<workgroup>CLUE WG</workgroup>
		<abstract>
			<t>This memo presenst a telemedicine use case where multiple presentation streams are used for conveying different information in parallel to the main video from the surgery room </t>
		</abstract>
	</front>
	<middle>
		<section title="Introduction">
			<t>
     This use case describes a scenario where multiple presentation streams are used. In this use case, the local site is a surgery room connected to one or more different types of remote sites. 
In the local site three main cameras capture the whole room. Multiple presentation inputs are possible: a surgery camera which is used to provide to zoomed view of the operation, an endoscopic monitor, an X-ray CT image output device, a B-ultrasonic apparatus, a cardiogram generator, an MRI image instrument, etc. These devices are used to provide multiple local video presentation streams to help the surgeon monitor the status of the patient and assist the process of the surgery.</t>
			<t>Three main screens and one (or more) presentation screen(s) are provided. The main screens can be used to display the remote experts. The presentation screen(s) can be used to display multiple presentation streams from local and remote sites simultaneously. Three main cameras capture different parts of the surgery room.  The surgeon can decide the number, the size and the placement of the presentations displayed on the local presentation screen(s). He can also indicate which local presentation captures are provided for the remote sites. The local site can send multiple presentation captures to remote sites and it can receive multiple presentations related to the patient or the procedure from them.  </t>
			<t>One type of remote site is a single or dual screen and one camera system with a consulting expert of a particular field present. In the general case the remote sites can be part of a Telepresence conference with multiple experts to start a consultation. The presentation screens are also provided at the remote sites allowing the experts to see the details of the operation and related data. Like the main site, the experts can decide the number, the size and the placement of the presentations displayed on the presentation screens. The presentation screens can display presentation streams from the surgery room or other remote sites and also presentation streams generated locally by the remote site. Thus the experts can also start sending presentation streams, which can carry medical records, pathology data, or their reference and analysis, etc.</t>
			<t>Another type of remote site is a typical immersive Telepresence room with three camera/screen pairs allowing more experts to join the consultation. These sites can also be used for education. The teacher and the students are in different remote sites. Students can observe and learn the details of the whole procedure, while the teacher can explain and answer questions during the operation.  </t>
			<t>Generally, the education sites can only send streams among themselves. For example, they can share slides and videos, but neither their main captures nor their presentation captures are sent to other sites (i.e. the surgery room and the experts). </t>
			<t>All remote education sites can display the surgery room. Or they can display it on the center screen, and the rest of the screens can show the teacher and the student who is asking a question. </t>
			<t>All remote sites shall display the zoomed surgery view on their presentation screen. Other dynamic and static data can be optional and up to user¡¯s decision.
 </t>
			<t>For all the above sites, more presentation screens can be used to enhance visibility: one screen for zoomed surgery stream and the others for medical image streams, such as MRI images, cardiogram, B-ultrasonic images and pathology data.
 
      
      
      </t>
		</section>
		<section title="Requirement for telemedical use case">
			<t>
				<list style="numbers">
					<t>The solution must enable an endpoint to send and receive multiple presentation captures.</t>
					<t>The solution must support a means to identify presentation captures, including the number, purpose, etc.</t>
					<t>The solution must support multiple presentation sources from different endpoints at the same time.</t>
					<t>The solution must support means of enabling interoperability between Telepresence endpoints that send and receive different numbers of presentation streams.</t>
					<t>The solution must support means of enabling interoperability between Telepresence endpoints where presentation screens are of different resolutions.</t>
					<t>The solution must enable an endpoint to mix multiple presentation captures locally.</t>
				</list>
			</t>
			<t>Note: the last two requirements are included in the CLUE requirement draft:
</t>
		</section>
		<section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
			<t>This document contains no IANA considerations.</t>
		</section>
		<section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
			<t>  While there are likely to be security considerations for 
      any solution for telepresence interoperability, this document 
      has no security considerations. </t>
		</section>
	</middle>
	<back>
		<references title="Informative References">
     &RFC2119;
  
    </references>
	</back>
</rfc>
