<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<!--<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc4748.dtd"> -->

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
    <!ENTITY rfc2119 PUBLIC '' 
      'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml'>
    <!ENTITY rfc5860 PUBLIC '' 
      'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5860.xml'>
    <!ENTITY rfc5586 PUBLIC '' 
      'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5586.xml'>
    <!ENTITY I-D.frost-mpls-tp-loss-delay PUBLIC '' 
      'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.frost-mpls-tp-loss-delay.xml'>
    <!ENTITY I-D.ietf-ccamp-rsvp-te-mpls-tp-oam-ext PUBLIC '' 
      'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-ccamp-rsvp-te-mpls-tp-oam-ext.xml'>
    <!ENTITY rfc3209 PUBLIC '' 
      'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3209.xml'>
    <!ENTITY I-D.ietf-mpls-tp-oam-framework PUBLIC '' 
      'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-mpls-tp-oam-framework.xml'>
]>


<rfc category="std" ipr="trust200902" docName="draft-xiao-mpls-tp-lm-counting-extension-00">

<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>

<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>

<front>
        <title abbrev="Extension to Packet Loss Measurement"> Extension to Packet Loss Measurement for Counting Activation and Deactivation </title>

  <author initials="M" surname="Xiao" fullname="Min Xiao">
      <organization>ZTE Corporation</organization>
      <address>
	<email>xiao.min2@zte.com.cn</email>
      </address>
    </author>

  <author initials="J" surname="Yang" fullname="Jian Yang">
      <organization>ZTE Corporation</organization>
      <address>
	<email>yang_jian@zte.com.cn</email>
      </address>
    </author>

  <author initials="B" surname="Wu" fullname="Bo Wu">
      <organization>ZTE Corporation</organization>
      <address>
	<email>wu.bo@zte.com.cn</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date day='5' month='July' year="2010"/>
  
    <area>Routing</area>
    <workgroup>MPLS Working Group</workgroup>

    <keyword>Request for Comments</keyword>
    <keyword>RFC</keyword>
    <keyword>Internet Draft</keyword>
    <keyword>I-D</keyword>

    <abstract>
<t>Packet loss measurement for MPLS Transport Profile (MPLS-TP) PseudoWires, Label Switched Paths, and Sections, is an important Operation, Administration and Maintenance (OAM) function of the MPLS-TP. When this OAM function is performed, counting the transmitted and received packets at both the source MEP and the sink MEP needs to be activated at first. This document specifies OAM packets and protocol mechanism to facilitate the counting activation and deactivation at the sink MEP, and leave out the unnecessary management configuration at the sink MEP when the MPLS-TP connection is bidirectional or there exists an out-of-band return path.</t>
    </abstract>
    
</front>
  
<middle>

  <section title="Introduction">

  <t>As defined in MPLS-TP OAM requirements <xref target="RFC5860"/>, "the MPLS-TP OAM toolset MUST provide a function to enable the quantification of packet loss ratio over a PW, LSP, or Section, this function MAY either be performed proactively or on-demand, this function SHOULD be performed between End Points of PWs, LSPs, and Sections and it SHOULD be possible to rely on user traffic to perform this functionality".</t>

  <t>To fulfill the above MPLS-TP OAM requirements with respect to packet loss measurement, the coherent general OAM procedures including configuration considerations, and specific function implementation including OAM packets format are specified in <xref target="I-D.ietf-mpls-tp-oam-framework"/> and <xref target="I-D.frost-mpls-tp-loss-delay"/> respectively. From the two documents it can be inferred that when packet loss measurement is performed, counting the transmitted and received packets at both the source MEP and the sink MEP needs to be activated at first, and furthermore the counting should rely on user traffic packets with specific configured PHB. Also note that in this context the source MEP specifies the MEP which will transmit Loss Measurement Query message and the sink MEP specifies the MEP which will reply Loss Measurement Response message.</t>

  <t>This document specifies OAM packets and protocol mechanism to facilitate the counting activation and deactivation at the sink MEP, and leave out the unnecessary management configuration at the sink MEP when the MPLS-TP connection is bidirectional or there exists an out-of-band return path.</t>

    <section title="Conventions">
    <t> The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in RFC 2119 <xref target="RFC2119"/>.</t>
    </section>
       
    <section title="Abbreviations">
    <t> ACH: Associated Channel Header</t>
    <t> G-ACh: Generic Associated Channel</t>
    <t> ICC: ITU Carrier Code</t>
    <t> LM: Loss Measurement</t>
    <t> LSP: Label Switched Path</t>
    <t> MEP: Maintenance Entity Group End Point</t>
    <t> MPLS-TP: MPLS Transport Profile</t>
    <t> OAM: Operations, Administration and Maintenance</t>
    <t> PHB: Per-hop Behavior</t>
    <t> PM: Performance Monitoring</t>
    <t> PW: PseudoWire</t>
    <t> RSVP-TE: Resource Reservation Protocol-Traffic Engineering</t>
    <t> TLV: Type Length Value</t>
    </section>
       
  </section>

  <section title="Counting Activation/Deactivation Packet Format">
  <t>Just like other MPLS-TP OAM packets, the counting activation/deactivation packets will flow over the Generic Associated Channel (G-ACh) <xref target="RFC5586"/> of an MPLS-TP connection. The counting activation/deactivation packets are used to perform signaling between the source MEP and the sink MEP of packet loss measurement.</t> 
  <t>The format of a counting activation/deactivation packet is shown below.</t> 
     <figure anchor="Figure_1" title="Counting Activation/Deactivation Packet">
     <artwork align="left">
     <![CDATA[
      0                   1                   2                   3
      0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
     +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
     |0 0 0 1|Version|   Reserved    | 0xHH (Packet Loss Measurement)|
     +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
     |                         ACH TLV Header                        |
     +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
     |                                                               ~
     ~                      Zero or more ACH TLVs                    ~
     ~                                                               |
     +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
     |                                                               ~
     ~            Counting Activation/Deactivation Message           ~
     ~                                                               |
     +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
     ]]>
     </artwork>
     </figure>
        
     <t>The Version and Reserved field are always set to 0.</t> 
     <t>The Packet Loss Measurement Channel Type is 0xHH (to be assigned by IANA).</t> 
     <t>The ACH TLVs may include (but are not limited to) the IF_ID, Global-ID, ICC, and Authentication TLVs.</t> 
     <t>The format of a counting activation/deactivation message is shown below.</t> 
        
     <figure anchor="Figure_2" title="Counting Activation/Deactivation Message">
     <artwork align="left">
     <![CDATA[
      0                   1                   2                   3
      0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
     +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
     |Version|R| A/D |  Control Code |         Reserved        | PHB |
     +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
     ]]>
     </artwork>
     </figure>
     
     <t>Version</t>
	 <t>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;The Version Number is currently set to 0.</t>
     <t>R flag</t>
	 <list hangIndent="3" style="hanging">
	 <t>The R flag represents the Request/Reply type. Set to 0 for a Request message; Set to 1 for a Reply message.</t>
	 </list>
     <t>A/D</t>
	 <list hangIndent="3" style="hanging">
	 <t>The A/D field represents the Activation/Deactivation type. Set to 0x100 for an Activation message; Set to 0x010 for a Deactivation message; other values are reserved for future use.</t>
	 </list>
     <t>Control Code</t>
	 <list hangIndent="3" style="hanging">
	 <t>According to the value of R flag, the Control Code is set as follow.</t>
     <t>For a Request:</t>
	 </list>
	 <list hangIndent="6" style="hanging">
	 <t>0x0: Request (in-band reply requested).  Indicates that this request has been sent over a bidirectional connection and the reply is expected over the same connection.</t>
	 <t>0x1: Request (out-of-band reply requested).  Indicates that the reply is expected over an out-of-band path.</t>
	 </list>
	 <list hangIndent="3" style="hanging">
     <t>For a Reply:</t>
	 </list>
	 <list hangIndent="6" style="hanging">
	 <t>0x0: Success.  Indicates that the operation succeeded.</t>
	 <t>0x1: Error.  Indicates that the operation failed.</t>
	 </list>
     <t>Reserved</t>
	 <list hangIndent="3" style="hanging">
	 <t>The Reserved bits are for future use and always set to 0.</t>
	 </list>
     <t>PHB</t>
	 <list hangIndent="3" style="hanging">
	 <t>The PHB is set to the PHB value provisioned at the source MEP.</t>
	 </list>
  </section> 

  <section title="Counting Activation Operations">
  <t>As specified in <xref target="I-D.ietf-mpls-tp-oam-framework"/>, before packet loss measurement is initiated, whether the operational mode is proactive monitoring or on-demand monitoring, the measurement parameters need to be provisioned at the source MEP. The provisioned measurement parameters for proactive monitoring include measurement interval and PHB value which identifies the per-hop behavior of packets with loss information, and further include measurement times for on-demand monitoring. Also note that after these packet loss measurement parameters are provisioned and this function is enabled at the source MEP, counting the transmitted and received packets with the provisioned PHB at the source MEP will be activated automatically.</t>
	<section title="Transmitting a Counting Activation Request">
	<t>After initiating a packet loss measurement operation, whether the operational mode is proactive monitoring or on-demand monitoring, the source MEP (i.e. the initiator MEP) will at first transmit a Counting Activation Request to the sink MEP (i.e. the peer MEP). This message is intended to trigger the sink MEP to start counting the transmitted and received packets with the specified PHB.</t> 
	</section> 
	<section title="Receiving a Counting Activation Request">
	<t>Upon the reception of a Counting Activation Request, the sink MEP must inspect this message at first, and if no unexpected field or value is found then the sink MEP should start counting the transmitted and received packets with the received PHB, otherwise specific error should be returned at the sink MEP.</t> 
	</section> 
	<section title="Transmitting a Counting Activation Reply">
	<t>When a Counting Activation Request is received, the sink MEP must transmit a Counting Activation Reply to the source MEP. The Control Code in Counting Activation Reply Message should be set to 0x0 to reflect the successful operation (i.e. activate counting successfully) at the sink MEP, or on the contrary set to 0x1 to reflect the failed operation (i.e. activate counting unsuccessfully) at the sink MEP. The received PHB value should be copied to the same PHB field in the Counting Activation Reply message.</t> 
	</section> 
	<section title="Receiving a Counting Activation Reply">
	<t>Upon the reception of a Counting Activation Reply, the source MEP must inspect this message at first, if no unexpected field or value is found and the received Control Code indicates successful operation at the sink MEP, then the source MEP should start transmitting Loss Measurement Query to commence the procedures defined in <xref target="I-D.frost-mpls-tp-loss-delay"/>, otherwise specific error should be returned at the source MEP. If there is no any Counting Activation Reply received after a while (such as 1 second), then specific error should be returned at the source MEP.</t> 
	</section> 
  </section> 

  <section title="Counting Deactivation Operations">
  <t>As indicated above, before packet loss measurement is initiated, the measurement parameters need to be provisioned at the source MEP, and after this function is enabled, counting the transmitted and received packets with the provisioned PHB at the source MEP will be activated automatically. Similarly with that after the packet loss measurement function is disabled at the source MEP, counting the transmitted and received packets with the provisioned PHB at the source MEP will be deactivated automatically.</t>
	<section title="Transmitting a Counting Deactivation Request">
	<t>After stopping a packet loss measurement operation, the source MEP (i.e. the initiator MEP) will stop transmitting Loss Measurement Query, and then transmit a Counting Deactivation Request to the sink MEP (i.e. the peer MEP). This message is intended to trigger the sink MEP to stop counting the transmitted and received packets with the specified PHB.</t> 
	</section> 
	<section title="Receiving a Counting Deactivation Request">
	<t>Upon the reception of a Counting Deactivation Request, the sink MEP must inspect this message at first, and if no unexpected field or value is found then the sink MEP should stop counting the transmitted and received packets with the received PHB, otherwise specific error should be returned at the sink MEP.</t> 
	</section> 
	<section title="Transmitting a Counting Deactivation Reply">
	<t>When a Counting Deactivation Request is received, the sink MEP must transmit a Counting Deactivation Reply to the source MEP. The Control Code in Counting Deactivation Reply Message should be set to 0x0 to reflect the successful operation (i.e. deactivate counting successfully) at the sink MEP, or on the contrary set to 0x1 to reflect the failed operation (i.e. deactivate counting unsuccessfully) at the sink MEP. The received PHB value should be copied to the same PHB field in the Counting Deactivation Reply message.</t> 
	</section> 
	<section title="Receiving a Counting Deactivation Reply">
	<t>Upon the reception of a Counting Deactivation Reply, the source MEP must inspect this message at first, if no unexpected field or value is found and the received Control Code indicates successful operation at the sink MEP, then there is no action at the source MEP, otherwise specific error should be returned at the source MEP. If there is no any Counting Deactivation Reply received after a while (such as 1 second), then specific error should be returned at the source MEP.</t> 
	</section> 
  </section> 

  <section title="Considerations for Control Plane"> 
  <t>When the packet loss measurement is employed in operational mode of proactive monitoring, the configured measurement parameters can be transferred from the source MEP to the sink MEP through the control plane by extending RSVP-TE <xref target="RFC3209"/>, as specified in <xref target="I-D.ietf-ccamp-rsvp-te-mpls-tp-oam-ext"/>. But in that draft, the sink MEP of one LM session is configured as a source MEP of another LM session, with all the same parameters such as measurement interval and PHB value. Actually there is another option which will distinguish the sink MEP function from the source MEP function when configuring proactive packet loss measurement at an MEP, which means that at the sink MEP only the function of counting the transmitted and received packets with specified PHB will be activated, in other words the sink MEP won't act as a source MEP of another LM session and won't transmit LM message initiatively. The option dictated above help to increase operation flexibility when performing proactive packet loss measurement, and decrease the bandwidth taken up by OAM messages due to that in this case only one LM session is needed. If this option is adopted when configuring parameters of proactive packet loss measurement by control plane, then the "MPLS OAM PM Loss TLV" defined in <xref target="I-D.ietf-ccamp-rsvp-te-mpls-tp-oam-ext"/> can be simplified and the MEP which receives this TLV can trigger only the sink MEP function.</t>
  </section>

  <section title="IANA Considerations"> 
  <t>To be added in a later version of this document.</t>
  </section>
  <section title="Security Considerations">
  <t>To be added in a later version of this document.</t>
  </section>
  <section title="Acknowledgements">
  <t>To be added in a later version of this document.</t>
  </section>  
  
</middle>
  
<back>

    <references title="Normative References">
     &rfc2119;
     &rfc5860;
	 &rfc5586;
	 &I-D.frost-mpls-tp-loss-delay;
	 &I-D.ietf-ccamp-rsvp-te-mpls-tp-oam-ext;
	 &rfc3209;
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
     &I-D.ietf-mpls-tp-oam-framework;
    </references>

</back>
</rfc>

