<?xml version="1.0" ?>

<!--  Why is the following needed??  -->
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM 'rfc2629.dtd'[

<!ENTITY rfc2119 PUBLIC ''
'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml'>

] >


<?rfc iprnotified="yes" ?>
<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
<rfc ipr="trust200902" docName='draft-schott-fmc-requirements-02'> 


<front> 

<!-- Title -->
    <title abbrev="FMC Requirements"> 
    Requirements for Fixed Mobile Convergence  
    </title>
<!-- End of Title-->

<!-- Author information -->

<author initials="S.D." surname="Durel" fullname="Sophie Durel">
    <organization>France Telecom</organization>
    <address>
    <postal>
    <street>
    </street>
    <street></street>
    <city> Rennes  </city> <region></region> <code>35000</code>
    <country>France</country>
    </postal>
    <phone></phone>
    <email>sophie.durel@orange.com</email>
    </address>
    </author>  


<author initials="H.M." surname="Moustafa" fullname="Hassnaa Moustafa">
    <organization>Orange Labs</organization>
    <address>
    <postal>
    <street>
    </street>
    <street></street>
    <city> Issy-Les-Moulineaux </city> <region></region> <code></code>
    <country>France</country>
    </postal>
    <phone></phone>
    <email>hassnaa.moustafa@orange.com</email>
    </address>
    </author>  

<author initials="R.S." surname="Schott" fullname="Roland Schott">
    <organization>Deutsche Telekom</organization>
    <address>
    <postal>
    <street>
    </street>
    <street></street>
    <city> Darmstadt </city> <region></region> <code>64295</code>
    <country>Germany</country>
    </postal>
    <phone></phone>
    <email>Roland.Schott@telekom.de</email>
    </address>
    </author>  

<author initials="C.E." surname="Perkins" fullname="Charles E. Perkins">
    <organization>Futurewei</organization>
    <address>
    <postal>
    <street>
    </street>
    <street></street>
    <city> Santa Clara </city> <region>California</region> <code>94053</code>
    <country>USA</country>
    </postal>
    <phone></phone>
    <email>charlie.perkins@huawei.com</email>
    </address>
    </author>  

<!-- End of Author information -->

   <date year="2012"/>

   <workgroup></workgroup>

<!-- Abstract -->
   <abstract>
   <t>
	Fixed-mobile convergence encompasses a variety of use cases that
	include situations in which a wireless device travels between a
	point of attachment in a mobile network (such as a cellular base
	station) and another point of attachment anchored in a fixed
	network such as a WiFi hotspot.  Convergence then means enabling
	an end-user to access services or retrieve
	content whatever the network access conditions (e.g., fixed
	or mobile access infrastructure), and whether the end-user is
	in motion or not. This document discusses the issues related
	to convergence and elaborates a set of requirements.
   </t>
   </abstract>
<!-- End of Abstract -->

</front>

<middle>

<section title='Introduction'>
   <t>
	With network heterogeneity and huge demand of multimedia and
	audio-visual services and applications as a given, users' satisfaction
	is the aim of each service provider to reduce churn, promote new
	services and improve the ARPU (Average Revenue per User).  The market
	is crowded.  Many players provide Internet and entertainment
	services, which motivates new business models considering users'
	experience and considering roaming agreement between different
	operators.  The new expectation for users'
	consumption style focuses on personalized and interactive usage.
	This allows users on one hand to share content across many devices
	and with other users, but on the other hand to access all content
	seamlessly at the touch of a button.
   </t>
   <t>
	Consequently, Quality of Experience (QoE) has become a crucial
	determinant of the success or failure of the multimedia and audio-visual
	applications and services. QoE evaluates the users' perceived quality
	for the provided services and hence reflects the users' satisfaction.
	Regarding QoS, 3GPP has made architectural definitions as described
	in <xref target='TS23.203'/> and <xref target='TS29.212'/>.
	IETF has also described
	how QoS can be achieved over IP <xref target='RFC5865'/>.	
   </t>
   <t>
	Various meanings can be ascribed to the term Fixed-Mobile Convergence.
	It is not the intention of this document to give a complete definition
	regarding business and technical aspects.
	Fixed-mobile convergence has recently been used to include various
	use cases in which a wireless device travels between a point of
	attachment in a mobile network (such as a cellular base station) and
	another point of attachment anchored in a fixed network such as a
	WiFi hotspot.  Convergence refers to a perceived unification of the
	service level available to applications which is, to the extent
	feasible, independent of the nature of the underlying physical
	medium.
   </t>
   <t> 
	This document discusses issues raised by convergence and elaborates
	a set of requirements based on the problem statement and use cases
	as discussed in
	<xref target='I-D.xue-intarea-fmc-ps'/> and
	<xref target='I-D.sun-fmc-use-case'/>.  These use cases have
	been under discussion in BBF <xref target='WT203'/> and 3GPP [cite].
	The requirements discussed in this document are meant to help the
	IETF community to decide whether it should take part of the
	corresponding effort or not.
   </t>
   <t> 
   </t>
</section> <!-- end of Introduction -->

<?rfc compact="yes" ?> <!--  to hang this off previous section, no new page -->
<section anchor="ProtocolO" title="Caution">
    <t>
	This document is a working tool to help assessing whether additional
	specification effort is required within IETF.
	Technical issues mentioned in this document are those which may
	require carrying out a specification effort within IETF.
   </t>
   <t>
	The goal of this document to enable the analysis of technical issues
	and their requirements.
	These issues are relevant to particular use cases.  The relevant
	use cases and associated requirements need thorough discussion.
   </t>
   <t>
	Some of these technical issues are already covered by some existing
	IETF WGs.  This document may provide motivation to advance such
	items in the standardization process.
   </t>
</section> <!-- end of "Caution" -->

<?rfc compact="yes" ?> <!--  to hang this off previous section, no new page -->

<section title='Terminology'>

   <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
	"SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
	document are to be interpreted as specified in <xref target='RFC2119'/>.
   </t>
   <t>
	The following additional terms are used in this document.
	<vspace blankLines='1' />
   <list style='hanging'>
   <t hangText='aggregation node'></t><t>
	The access network node which connects CPE and UE devices
	to the Internet. 
	<vspace blankLines='1' />
   </t>
   <t hangText='Codec'></t><t>
	Compression/Decompression of multimedia data using either a hardware
	device or software.
	<vspace blankLines='1' />
   </t>
   <t hangText='CPE'></t><t>
	Customer Premises Equipment, that is equipment found in the customer's
	physical location and provided by the network operator or service
	providers. DSL routers, Set-Top-Box (STB), and decoders are
	examples of CPE.
	<vspace blankLines='1' />
   </t>
   <t hangText='FMC'></t><t>
	Fixed Mobile Convergence means enabling an end-user to access
	services or retrieve content whatever the network access conditions
	(e.g., fixed or mobile access infrastructure), and whether the end-
	user is in motion or not. This includes also access conditions with 
	this own service profile although having access by a 3rd party.
	<vspace blankLines='1' />
   </t>
   <t hangText='host_id'></t><t>
	an identifier for the wireless device, as described in
	<xref target='I-D.ietf-intarea-nat-reveal-analysis' />.
	<vspace blankLines='1' />
   </t>
   <t hangText='MN'></t><t>
	"Mobile Node"; a device that can move from one wireless point of
	attachment to another.
	Other standard documents use different terminology for the same idea,
	for instance "UE" (for User Equipment), or AT (for Access Terminal).
	<vspace blankLines='1' />
   </t>
   <t hangText='NFC Identifier'></t><t>
	Near Field Communications identifier.
	<vspace blankLines='1' />
   </t>
   <t hangText='Port set'></t><t>
	a defined set of ports; in this document "port set" is used as an
	example of a host_id.  Each host under the same external IP address
	is assigned a restricted port set. These port sets may then be
	advertised to remote servers. Port sets assigned to hosts may be
	static or dynamic. 
	<vspace blankLines='1' />
   </t>
   <t hangText='SD'></t><t>
	Standard Definition for video using a standard resolution.
	<vspace blankLines='1' />
   </t>
   <t hangText='HD'></t><t>
	High Definition for video using an enhanced resolution.
   </t>
   </list></t>
</section> <!-- end of 'Terminology' -->

<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<section anchor="MN_behind_NAT"
	title="Requirements for MN Identification behind a CPE with NAT">
    <t>
	A popular deployment model in fixed networks is to provide a host
	with a single private IPv4 address at the home or small business
	LAN.  Then, each host within the local network will be assigned a
	private IPv4 address; a NA(P)T function <xref target='RFC2663'/> is
	responsible for translating
	the private IPv4 address to the public IPv4 address assigned to the
	CPE (Customer Premises Equipment).  Similar address translation
	features are also present now in mobile environment; as one example,
	CPE can be connected to mobile infrastructures.	
    </t>
    <t>
	IP address sharing is motivated by a number of different factors.
	And today, some servers use the source IPv4 address as an identifier
	to treat some incoming connections differently. Due to the use of
	NAT44 <xref target='RFC3022'/> and NAT64 <xref target='RFC6146'/>),
	that address will be shared.  In particular, when a server receives
	packets from the same source address, because this address is
	shared, the server does not know which host is the sending host
	<xref target='RFC6269'/>.  To be able to sort out the packets for
	each sending host, the server must have extra information in addition
	to the source IP address, to distinguish the sending host. This
	identifying information is called the "host_id". 
    </t>
    <t>
	As a general matter, the HOST_ID proposals do not seek to make hosts
	any more identifiable than they would be if they were using a public,
	non-shared IP address.  However, depending on the solution proposal,
	the addition of host_id information may allow a device to be
	fingerprinted more easily than it otherwise would be.  Should
	multiple solutions be combined that include different pieces of
	information in the host_id, fingerprinting may become even easier. 
    </t>
    <t>
	A set of solution candidates to mitigate some of the issues
	encountered when address sharing is used have been described and
	compared in <xref target='I-D.ietf-intarea-nat-reveal-analysis'/>.
	Among or aside this set of solutions, a mechanism will have
	to be recommended to supply host_id in the use cases described
	in <xref target='reqs_MNMobility'/> as well as in
	<xref target='I-D.xue-intarea-fmc-ps'/> and
	<xref target='I-D.sun-fmc-use-case'/>.
    </t>
    <t>
	A CPE can also be configured to offer a shared WiFi to any
	visiting host (also called Mobile Node, or simply MN) which
	does not belong to the subscriber (owning the CPE).  A visiting
	MN uses that shared WiFi facility to access its services.
	Granting access to the service is usually conditioned by an access
	control phase (e.g., redirection to captive portal inviting the user
	to authenticate).  Once access to the service is granted, the
	visiting MN can receive its services.  Business model considerations
	for such service offerings are out of scope for this document.
    </t>
<!-- CEP: whether the MN is visiting or not, the requirement is similar -->
    <t>
	Among various ways to offer shared WiFi service, operators may elect
	to re-use the NAT function embedded in the CPE to route the traffic
	issued from the visiting MN.
    </t>
    <t>
	When the traffic of a visiting MN is multiplexed behind the same
	public IP address, upstream devices may be unable to distinguish the
	the traffic of the visiting MN from other traffic issued by devices
	belonging to the subscriber owning the CPE.  This traffic
	identification may be required to enforce dedicated policies
	(e.g., Accounting, QoS policies, legal intercept, legal data
	storage, etc.).  As a result, and in order for the operator
	to still support traffic management for this service, policy
	control/decision/enforcement MUST be based on the specific MN.
	In other words, traffic belonging to a visiting MN MUST be
	explicitly identified.  The host_id jointly with the external IP
	address can be used for this purpose.
    </t>
    <t>
	As one example, port sets can be used as a host-id.  To illustrate,
	suppose the CPE assigns a private IPv4 address and a set of ports
	to a visiting MN.  Then, the CPE can report the assigned port set
	to a aggregation node together with other information such as external
	IPv4 address, MAC address, etc.  This information will be associated
	with the user-id provided during the authentication phase.  The CPE
	then uses that port set for translating packets to and from that
	visiting MN.  The set of ports (assigned by the CPE) and the external
	IP address (assigned to the CPE) are then sufficient to uniquely
	identify a MN.  The reporting phase can be avoided if the CPE is
	pre-configured with a static list of port sets to be used for
	visiting MNs.
    </t>
    <t>
	The use of port sets and some other methods to explicitly identify a
	visiting MN is discussed in
	<xref target='I-D.ietf-intarea-nat-reveal-analysis'/>, but many
	other methods of identification are also possible.
	In order to ease the selection of the appropriate host-id
	solution for the FMC case, below are listed a set of
	requirements to be met:
    </t>
    <t><list style="symbols">
	<t>All traffic MUST be identifiable (including TCP, UDP and ICMP)</t>
	<t>The MN SHOULD be authenticated if it injects its own host-id</t>
 	<t>Otherwise, the CPE SHOULD inject the host-id</t>
  	<t>The CPE SHOULD strip any existing host-id</t>
  	<t>The CPE and the aggregation node MUST support at least one common
		method to convey host-id.</t></list></t>

<?rfc compact="yes" ?> <!--  to hang this off previous section, no new page -->
<section anchor="recom_MN_ID"
	title="Recommendations for MN Identification behind NAT">
    <t>
	We recommend dedicated efforts to specify a mechanism to
	supply host-id for MNs behind CPE and NAT.
    </t>
    <t>
	A solution analysis document for existing solution
	approaches would help.
    </t>
</section> <!-- end of "Recommendations" -->
</section>

<?rfc compact="yes" ?> <!--  to hang this off previous section, no new page -->
<section anchor="reqs_AccSel" title="Requirements for Access Selection">
    <t>
	A multiple access environment requires appropriate choice of the
	access network (cellular, mobile, VPN,...) that the device is likely
	to be connected to.  This selection may
	depend on various criteria such as user's preference, user profile,
	network capabilities and conditions, operator policies, application
	QoS requirements and so on.
	This access selection can happen when the wireless device is first
	connected to an access network, i.e. at bootstrapping phase,
	and when a new access network can be accessed to, for example
	as the device moves.  </t> 
<!-- <?rfc compact="yes" ?>  to hang this off previous section, no new page
<section anchor="recom_AccSel" title="Recommendations for Access Selection"> -->
    <t>
	Relevant information should be collected for each access network type,
	including:
    </t>
	<t> <list style="symbols">
		<t>Available Bandwidth</t>
		<t>Cost</t>
		<t>Latency</t>
		<t>other QoS information</t>
		<t>Operator Network Identification</t>
		<t>Network Protocol Family (IPv4 or IPv6).</t>
	</list> </t>
    <t>
    	Policy access SHOULD also be enabled.
    </t>
    <t>
    	A mapping between the network status and the service requirements
	should be specified to allow the MN to choose the network that best
	matches its service requirements.
    </t>
    <t>
	It should be possible to manage the user's access in the presence
	of several candidate access networks (fixed and mobile).
    </t>

<!-- </section> end of "Recommendations for Access Selection" -->
</section>

<?rfc compact="yes" ?> <!--  to hang this off previous section, no new page -->
<section anchor="reqs_MNMobility"
	title="Requirements for MN Mobility in Fixed Broadband Network">

    <t> The following are the requirements for MN Mobility in
	    Fixed Broadband Network:
	<list style="symbols">
	<t> Handover between networks while the session is active according to
		the network status with the change in the MN attachment.</t>
	<t> Mechanisms and interfaces between operators or/and access
	    networks SHOULD be deployed to
  	    manage the mobility of the traffic flows of their users.  </t>

        <t>Mobility should be enabled whether or not coverage areas overlap.</t>

        <t>Differentiated Services for the mobile device (MN)</t>

        <t>Service guarantee when device is roaming or mobile</t>

        <t>Resiliency in the network nodes should be provided</t>
<!-- CEP: What does this mean? -->
        </list></t>
</section> <!-- end of "MNMobility" -->

<?rfc compact="yes" ?> <!--  to hang this off previous section, no new page -->
<section anchor="reqs_Stream" title="Requirements for Streaming">
    <t> Additional IETF specification may be desirable for personalization
		of streaming services, especially video.</t>

<section anchor="PersonalStream"
		title="Personalization of Video Streaming Service">
    <t>

    </t>

<section anchor="PersonalStreamD" title="Discussion">

    <t>
	The proliferation of streaming services (e.g., video across multiple
	screens and connected devices) motivates video streaming
	service personalization -- especially for users desiring richer
	Quality of Experience (QoE).  Personalization of such 
	services could allow streaming content delivery in a customized
	manner depending on each user, the device used, and the network status
	mainly through the following choices:
    </t>

    <t> i)	delivery network (fixed or mobile), </t>
    <t> ii)	local access network (WiFi, Femto, ADSL, .), </t>
    <t> iii)	delivery mode (unicast, multicast, delivering content
	    			from the one server or from caches, ..) </t>
    <!-- <t> iv)	content format (HD/SD, codec, .).  </t>  -->

    <t>
	In this way, the streaming content could follow the user
	from place to place regardless of the access network type
	and of the mobile node (MN) characteristics.</t>
<!-- Not sure where the "other hand" is detailed.  Is it in the next para? -->
    <t>
	This requires technical solutions to allow the
	selection of the appropriate interface to be used by the MN.
	The MN typically does not have any global view of the congestion
	status of the network.  Moreover, in many cases the owner
	of the device might attempt to gain the highest level of service
	(regardless of the cost of network use by the operator).
	Service levels need to be controlled by the network
	and/or the service domains, not the MN.  Likewise, the ability of
	premium clients to access more QoS resources (e.g. more bandwidth)
	further supports the design guideline enabling
	network choices to be decided by the operator.
    </t>
    <t>
	In many cases, the service level controls required by the
	network operator require traffic monitoring at the aggregation
	node.  This may require further coordination between the
	aggregation node and the CPE in order for the aggregation
	node to have the proper policy information available.
    </t>
    <t>
	To be able to select the appropriate network and adapt the
	content according to the network status there is a need to obtain
	information about the network status and its variation
	<!-- in order to adapt the content --> in a dynamic manner also
	during the session.  For
	example, a session that started with HD content could change
	to SD if the network conditions degrades.  <!-- On the other hand,
	there is a need for updating the content according to the MN
	capabilities. -->  The current adaptive streaming solutions (as the
	HAS: HTTP Adaptive Streaming) mainly count on the MN for selecting
	the suitable content.
    </t>
    <t>
	However, if content adaptation happens at the content source
	(in contrast to HTTP adaptive streaming techniques currently existing,
	the source would only send the appropriate content for each client
	and save network resources.  For example, H.264/AVC video is
	encoded into 2 Mbps for SD and 6Mbps for HD.  A mapping between
	the network status and the service requirements is also needed,
	where the service
	requirements are mainly exhibited by the content source (owned
	by the Content provider or the service provider).  Content adaptation
	directives could also be extracted from the content Metadata.
    </t>

    <t> Personalization of streaming imposes the following requirements:
    <list style="symbols">
    <t>
	Each user connection MUST be identified through identifying each
	MN in a separate manner and distinguishing the MN and the CPE
	identification.  The MN identification could be simply an NFC
	identifier, MAC identifier, ... which is then administratively
	associated with more information reflecting the MN characteristics.
    </t>
    <t>
	Monitoring mechanisms MUST exist allowing the collection of QoS
	information for each access network type.
<!-- Change to "SHOULD"? -->
    </t>
    <t>
	Service layer monitoring (for instance through MPEG2 layer
	monitor for video content) SHOULD exist to choose the network
	best matching the service requirements.
    </t>
<!-- Only makes sense if "QoS" is distinct from "Service Layer" -->
    <t>
	The switch from one network to another MUST maintain
	the session according to the network status with the change
	in the MN attachment.
    </t>
    <t>
	Mechanisms and interfaces between operators SHOULD be deployed
	to control the mobility of traffic flows of their users.
    </t>
    </list></t>
</section>

</section>

<section anchor="recom_stream" title="Recommendations for Streaming">
    <t>
	The IETF SHOULD dedicate efforts to consider several issues
	related to the MN and also to the network status as follows:
    </t>
    <t>
    <list style='numbers'>
    <t>
	Each MN needs to be identified and
	the MN identity needs to be updated during the session each
	time a new terminal is used. The characteristics of each MN
	being used needs to be known also (e.g. supported resolution,
	screen size, available network connectivity "WiFi, 3G, .."
	and the cost of using each type of available networks).
    </t>
    <t>
	Information about is needed for each of the network parameters
	as detailed in <xref target='reqs_AccSel'/>,
    </t>
    <t>
	A mapping between the network status and the service
	requirements needs to exist to enable selection of the network
	that best matches the service requirements.
    </t>
    </list>
    </t>
</section>   
</section>  <!-- end of "Stream"  --> 

<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<section title='Security Considerations'>
    <t> 
	This document focuses on FMC requirements and the interworking of
	"WiFi, 3G, etc..." and should not give rise to any new security
	vulnerabilities beyond those described in
	IPSec <xref target='RFC4301'/>,
	TLS <xref target='RFC5246'/> or
	SRTP <xref target='RFC3711'/>.
	Nevertheless an open network architecture aimed at fulfilling
	the requirements listed in this document may give rise to
	security issues not yet identified.
    </t>
</section>		<!-- end of Security Considerations -->

<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<section title='IANA considerations'>
  <t>None.</t>
</section>

<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<section title='Acknowledgments'>
    <t>
	Contributions, comments, discussions, and remarks provided by 
		David Binet,
		Mohamed Boucadair,
		Christian Jacquenet,
		Daniel Park,
		and Pierrick Seite
	are gratefully acknowledged. 
    </t>
</section>

</middle>


<back>	<!-- a section after the References is called an "Appendix" -->

<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<references title='Normative References'> 
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119"?>
</references>


<references title='Informative references'>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2663"?>
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.3022'?>
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.3711' ?>
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.4301' ?>
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.5246' ?>
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.5865'?>
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.5996'?>
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6146'?>
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6264'?>
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6269'?>
<!-- I-D include directives MUST NOT contain the string "draft" in the name -->
      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-intarea-nat-reveal-analysis'?>
      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.xue-intarea-fmc-ps'?>
      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.sun-fmc-use-case'?>
      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.so-ipsecme-ikev2-cpext'?>

      <reference anchor="TS29.212">
        <front>
	<title>3GPP TS29.212, Policy and Charging Control (PCC)
		over Gx/Sd reference point</title>
          <author>
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date month="December" year="2011" />
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="TS23.203">
        <front>
          <title>3GPP TS23.203, Policy and Charging control architecture</title>
          <author>
            <organization></organization>
          </author>
          <date month="December" year="2011" />
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="TR23.829">
        <front>
	  <title>3GPP TR23.829, Local IP Access and Selected IP
			Traffic Offload (LIPA-SIPTO)</title>
          <author>
            <organization></organization>
          </author>
          <date month="October" year="2010" />
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="WT146">
        <front>
	<title>Broadband Forum Working Text WT-146,
		Subscriber Sessions</title>
          <author>
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date month="June" year="2011" />
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="WT203">
        <front>
	<title>Broadband Forum Working Text WT-203, Interworking
		between Next Generation Fixed and 3GPP Wireless Access
	</title>

          <author>
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date month="December" year="2011" />
        </front>
      </reference>

   	<reference anchor="samog" >
        <front>
          <title abbrev="3GPP 23.852">
		  3GPP TR 23.852 V1.0.0, Study on S2a Mobility based On
		  GTP &amp; WLAN access to EPC (SaMOG) (Release 11)


          </title>
          <author fullname="3GPP"><organization/> </author>
          <date month="December" year="2011" />
        </front>
        </reference>

  	<reference anchor="ieee802.11" >
        <front>
          <title abbrev="IEEE.802-11.2008">
		Information technology - Telecommunications and
		information exchange between systems - Local and
		metropolitan area networks - Specific
		requirements - Part 11: Wireless LAN Medium
		Access Control (MAC) and Physical Layer (PHY)
		specifications", IEEE Standard 802.11, 2008
          </title>
          <author fullname="IEEE"><organization/> </author>
          <date month="" year="2008" />
        </front>
        </reference>

</references>


<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<section anchor="Reactive-Mode" title="Requirements for Content Adaptation">
    <t>
	In this case, adaptation of content format (HD/SD, codec, ...) SHOULD
	be possible when delivering the same content (e.g. video streaming)
	regardless of the access network type and of the 
	mobile node (MN) characteristics.
    </t>

<section anchor="recom2" title="Recommendations for Content Adaptation">
    <t>
	To be able to meet above high level requirement,
	the content adaptation function needs to:
    </t>
    <t>
    <list style='numbers'>
    <t>
	identify the user connection by identifying each MN in a
	separate manner.  The MN identity MUST be updated during the
	session each time a new terminal is used.  The characteristics
	of each MN being used needs to be known also (e.g. supported
	resolution, screen size, available network connectivity "WiFi,
	3G, .." and the cost of using each type of available network).
    </t>

    <t>
    	distinguishing the MN and the CPE identification (MOTIVATION?).
    </t>
    <t>
	rely on service layer monitoring (for instance through MPEG2 layer
	monitor for video content) SHOULD exist to choose the network best
	matching the service requirements.
    </t>
    </list>
    </t>
</section>   
</section>  <!-- end of Reactive Mode --> 

</back> 

</rfc>
