<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!-- This template is for creating an Internet Draft using xml2rfc,
     which is available here: http://xml.resource.org. -->
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!-- One method to get references from the online citation libraries.
     There has to be one entity for each item to be referenced. 
     An alternate method (rfc include) is described in the references. -->
<!ENTITY RFC2119 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3654 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3654.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3746 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3746.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5657 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5657.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.narten-iana-considerations-rfc2434bis SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.narten-iana-considerations-rfc2434bis.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5812 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5812.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5810 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5810.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5811 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5811.xml">
]>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<!-- used by XSLT processors -->
<!-- For a complete list and description of processing instructions (PIs), 
     please see http://xml.resource.org/authoring/README.html. -->
<!-- Below are generally applicable Processing Instructions (PIs) that most I-Ds might want to use.
     (Here they are set differently than their defaults in xml2rfc v1.32) -->
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<!-- give errors regarding ID-nits and DTD validation -->
<!-- control the table of contents (ToC) -->
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<!-- generate a ToC -->
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<!-- the number of levels of subsections in ToC. default: 3 -->
<!-- control references -->
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<!-- use symbolic references tags, i.e, [RFC2119] instead of [1] -->
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<!-- sort the reference entries alphabetically -->
<!-- control vertical white space 
     (using these PIs as follows is recommended by the RFC Editor) -->
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<!-- Start each main section on a new page -->
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<!-- keep one blank line between list items -->
<!-- end of list of popular I-D processing instructions -->
<rfc category="info" docName="draft-joachimpillai-forces-interfelfb-01" ipr="trust200902">
  <!-- category values: std, bcp, info, exp, and historic
     ipr values: full3667, noModification3667, noDerivatives3667
     you can add the attributes updates="NNNN" and obsoletes="NNNN" 
     they will automatically be output with "(if approved)" -->

  <!-- ***** FRONT MATTER ***** -->

  <front>
    <!-- The abbreviated title is used in the page header - it is only necessary if the 
         full title is longer than 39 characters -->

    <title abbrev="ForCES Inter-FE LFB">ForCES Inter-FE LFB</title>

    <!-- add 'role="editor"' below for the editors if appropriate -->

    <!-- Another author who claims to be an editor -->

	<author fullname="Damascane M. Joachimpillai" initials="D.J." surname="Joachimpillai">
		<organization>Verizon</organization>
		<address>
			<postal>
				<street>60 Sylvan Rd</street>
				<!-- Reorder these if your country does things differently -->
				<city>Waltham</city>
				<region>Mass.</region>
				<code>02451</code>
				<country>USA</country>
			</postal>
			<email>damascene.joachimpillai@verizon.com</email>
			<!-- uri and facsimile elements may also be added -->
		</address>
	</author>
 
	<author fullname="Jamal Hadi Salim" initials="J." surname="Hadi Salim">
		<organization>Mojatatu Networks</organization>
		<address>
			<postal>
				<street>Suite 400, 303 Moodie Dr.</street>
				<city>Ottawa</city>
				<code>K2H 9R4</code>
				<region>Ontario</region>
				<country>Canada</country>
			</postal>
			<email>hadi@mojatatu.com</email>
			<!-- uri and facsimile elements may also be added -->
		</address>
	</author>
      
    <!-- If the month and year are both specified and are the current ones, xml2rfc will fill 
         in the current day for you. If only the current year is specified, xml2rfc will fill 
	 in the current day and month for you. If the year is not the current one, it is 
	 necessary to specify at least a month (xml2rfc assumes day="1" if not specified for the 
	 purpose of calculating the expiry date).  With drafts it is normally sufficient to 
	 specify just the year. -->

    <!-- Meta-data Declarations -->
    <date year="2013" />

    <area>Routing</area>

    <workgroup>Internet Engineering Task Force</workgroup>

    <!-- WG name at the upperleft corner of the doc,
         IETF is fine for individual submissions.  
	 If this element is not present, the default is "Network Working Group",
         which is used by the RFC Editor as a nod to the history of the IETF. -->

    <keyword>ForCES</keyword>
    <keyword>Model</keyword>
    <keyword>Extension</keyword>

    <!-- Keywords will be incorporated into HTML output
         files in a meta tag but they have no effect on text or nroff
         output. If you submit your draft to the RFC Editor, the
         keywords will be used for the search engine. -->

    <abstract>
      <t> Forwarding and Control Element Separation (ForCES) defines an
      architectural framework and associated protocols to standardize
      information exchange between the control plane and the forwarding
      plane in a ForCES Network Element (ForCES NE).  RFC5812 has defined
      the ForCES Model provides a formal way to represent the capabilities, 
      state, and configuration of forwarding elements within the context of 
      the ForCES protocol, so that control elements (CEs) can control the FEs 
      accordingly. More specifically, the model describes the logical functions 
      that are present in an FE, what capabilities these functions support, and 
      how these functions are or can be interconnected.</t>
      <t>
      At the moment the ForCES charter restricts the LFB topology to be
      within an FE. This documents describes a non-intrusive way to extend
      the LFB topology across FEs.
      </t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Terminology and Conventions">
      <t/>

      <section title="Requirements Language">
        <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
        "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
        document are to be interpreted as described in <xref target="RFC2119"></xref>.</t>
      </section>
  <section title="Definitions">
	<t> This document follows the terminology defined by the ForCES
   Model in <xref target="RFC5812"></xref>.
   The required definitions are repeated below for clarity.</t>
  
      <t><list style="hanging">
      
<t>
FE Model - The FE model is designed to model the logical processing
functions of an FE. The FE model proposed in this document
includes three components; the LFB modeling of individual Logical
Functional Block (LFB model), the logical interconnection between
LFBs (LFB topology), and the FE-level attributes, including FE
capabilities. The FE model provides the basis to define the
information elements exchanged between the CE and the FE in the
ForCES protocol [RFC5810].
</t>
<t>
LFB (Logical Functional Block) Class (or type) - A template that
represents a fine-grained, logically separable aspect of FE
processing. Most LFBs relate to packet processing in the data
path. LFB classes are the basic building blocks of the FE model.
</t>
<t>
LFB Instance - As a packet flows through an FE along a data path, it
flows through one or multiple LFB instances, where each LFB is an
instance of a specific LFB class. Multiple instances of the same
LFB class can be present in an FE's data path. Note that we often
refer to LFBs without distinguishing between an LFB class and LFB
instance when we believe the implied reference is obvious for the
given context.
</t>
<t>
LFB Model - The LFB model describes the content and structures in an
LFB, plus the associated data definition. XML is used to provide
a formal definition of the necessary structures for the modeling.
Four types of information are defined in the LFB model. The core
part of the LFB model is the LFB class definitions; the other
three types of information define constructs associated with and
used by the class definition. These are reusable data types,
supported frame (packet) formats, and metadata.
</t>
<t>
LFB Metadata - Metadata is used to communicate per-packet state from
one LFB to another, but is not sent across the network. The FE
model defines how such metadata is identified, produced, and
consumed by the LFBs, but not how the per-packet state is
implemented within actual hardware. Metadata is sent between the
FE and the CE on redirect packets.
</t>
<t>ForCES Component - A ForCES Component is a well-defined, uniquely
identifiable and addressable ForCES model building block. A
component has a 32-bit ID, name, type, and an optional synopsis
description. These are often referred to simply as components.
</t>
<t>
LFB Component - An LFB component is a ForCES component that defines
the Operational parameters of the LFBs that must be visible to the
CEs.
</t>
<t>
LFB Topology - LFB topology is a representation of the logical
 interconnection and the placement of LFB instances along the data
path within one FE. Sometimes this representation is called
intra-FE topology, to be distinguished from inter-FE topology.
LFB topology is outside of the LFB model, but is part of the FE
model.
</t>
<t>
FE Topology - FE topology is a representation of how multiple FEs
within a single network element (NE) are interconnected.
Sometimes this is called inter-FE topology, to be distinguished
from intra-FE topology (i.e., LFB topology). An individual FE
might not have the global knowledge of the full FE topology, but
the local view of its connectivity with other FEs is considered to
be part of the FE model.
</t>
<t>
Service Graph - A directed graph of LFB instances whose composition
delivers a packet service.
</t>
	</list></t>
    </section>

    </section>

<section title="Introduction">
    <t> 
    In the ForCES architecture, a packet service can be modelled by composing
    a graph of one or more LFB instances. The reader is refered to the details 
    in <xref target="RFC5812"> the ForCES Model</xref>.
    </t>
    <t> The FEObject LFB capabilities in 
    <xref target="RFC5812">the ForCES Model</xref> define component
    ModifiableLFBTopology which, when advertised as true by the FE, implies FE
    is capable of modifying the LFB graph. The array 
    (SupportedLFBs) contains information about each supported LFB class
    that the FE supports.
    In addition to indicating that the FE supports an LFB
    class, FEs with modifiable LFB topologies include information
    about how LFBs of a specified class may be connected to other LFBs.
    The advertised rules describe which LFB classes a specified LFB
    class may succeed or precede in an LFB topology. 
    The capability of an FE can be queried by the CE upon association.
    </t>
   <t>
   The CE may create a packet service by describing LFB instance
   graph connections via updating the FEOBject LFBTopology component. The 
   created topology contains information about each inter-LFB link within 
   the FE (each link is described in an LFBLinkType dataTypeDef). The 
   LFBLinkType component contains sufficient information to identify 
   precisely the end points of a link of a service graph.
   </t>
   <t>
    Often there are requirements for the packet service graph to cross FE 
    boundaries. This could be from a desire to scale the service or need to 
    interact with LFBs which reside in a separate FE (eg lookaside 
    interface to a shared TCAM, an interconnected chip, or as coarse 
    grained functionality as an external NAT FE box being part of the 
    service graph etc).
   </t>
   <t>
    Given that the ForCES inter-LFB architecture calls out for ability to pass
    metadata between LFBs, it is imperative to define mechanisms to allow
    passing the metadata between inter-FE LFBs (given that packet data passing is
    already taken care of).
   </t>
   <t>
    The ForCES charter restricts the LFB links in a topology to be within a 
    single FE (intra-FE connectivity) and as such both the relevant
    capabilities and component definitions in the FEObject LFB are restricted
    to that scope. This document describes extending the LFB topology across
    FEs i.e inter-FE connectivity without needing any changes to the
    ForCES definitions.
   </t>
  </section>

  <section title="Problem Scope">
  <t> 
  A sample LFB topology <xref target="fig1"></xref> demonstrates
  a service graph for delivering basic IPV4 forwarding service
  within one FE. Note: although the diagram shows LFB classes connecting in the
  graph in reality it is a graph of LFB class instances that are inter-connected.
  </t>
  <t>
  The illustration is meant only as an exercise to showcase how data
  and metadata is sent down or upstream on a graph of LFBs.
  For this reason, it abstracts out any ports in both directions
  and talks about a generic ingress and egress LFB. For illustration
  purposes, the diagram does not show expection or error paths.
  Also left out are details on Reverse Path Filtering, ECMP, multicast
  handling etc. In other words, this is not meant to be a complete description
  of an IPV4 forwarding application; for a more complete example, please refer 
  to the LFBlib document[XXX: ref here].
  </t>
  <t>
  The output of the ingress LFB(s) coming into the IPv4 Validator LFB 
  will have both the IPV4 packets and, depending on the implementation,
  a variety of ingress metadata such as offsets into the different headers, any 
  classification metadata, physical and virtual ports encountered,
  tunnelling information etc. These metadata are lumped together as
  "ingress metadata".
  </t>
  <t>
  Once the IPV4 validator vets the packet (example ensures that no expired TTL etc), 
  it feeds the packet and inherited metadata into the IPV4 unicast LPM LFB. 
  </t>
  <t>
   <figure title="Basic IPV4 packet service LFB topology" align="left" anchor="fig1">
   <artwork><![CDATA[

                    +----+                           
                    |    |                           
         IPV4 pkt   |    | IPV4 pkt     +-----+             +---+     
     +------------->|    |------------->|     |             |   |     
     |  + ingress   |    | + ingress    |IPv4 |   IPV4 pkt  |   |     
     |   metadata   |    | metadata     |Ucast|------------>|   |--+  
     |              +----+              |LPM  |  + ingress  |   |  |  
   +-+-+             IPv4               +-----+  + NHinfo   +---+  |  
   |   |             Validator                   metadata   IPv4   |  
   |   |             LFB                                    NextHop|  
   |   |                                                     LFB   |  
   |   |                                                           |  
   |   |                                                  IPV4 pkt 
   +---+                                        + {ingress + NHdetails}
   Ingress                                             metadata    |
    LFB                                +-------+                   |  
                                       |Egress |                   |  
                                    <--|LFB    |<------------------+  
                                       +-------+     
    ]]></artwork>
   </figure>
  </t>

<t>
The IPV4 unicast LPM LFB does a longest prefix match lookup on the
IPV4 FIB using the destination IP address as a search key. The result is 
typically a next hop selector which is passed downstream as metadata.
</t>
<t>
The Nexthop LFB receives the IPv4 packet with an associated next hop
info metadata. The NextHop LFB consumes the NH info metadata and 
derives from it a table index to look up the next hop table in order to 
find the appropriate egress information. The lookup result
is used to build the next hop details to be used
downstream on the egress. This information may include any source 
and destination information (MAC address to use, if ethernet;) as well egress 
ports.
[Note: It is also at this LFB where typically the forwarding TTL decrement
and IP checksum recalculation occurs.]
</t>
<t>
The details of the egress LFB are considered out of scope for this discussion.
Suffice it is to say that somewhere within or beyond the Egress LFB the
IPV4 packet will be sent out a port (ethernet, virtual or physical etc).
</t>
<section title="Distributing The LFB Topology">
<t>
<xref target="fig2"></xref> demonstrates one way the LFB topology
in <xref target="fig1"></xref> may be split across two FEs (eg two ASICs).
<xref target="fig2"></xref> shows the LFB topology split across FEs after the
IPV4 unicast LPM LFB.
</t>
  <t>
   <figure title="Split IPV4 packet service LFB topology" align="left" anchor="fig2">
   <artwork><![CDATA[
   FE1
 +-------------------------------------------------------------+
 |                            +----+                           |
 | +----------+               |    |                           |
 | | Ingress  |    IPV4 pkt   |    | IPV4 pkt     +-----+      |
 | |  LFB     |+------------->|    |------------->|     |      |
 | |          |  + ingress    |    | + ingress    |IPv4 |      |
 | +----------+    metadata   |    |   metadata   |Ucast|      |
 |      ^                     +----+              |LPM  |      |
 |      |                      IPv4               +-----+      |
 |      |                     Validator              |         |
 |                             LFB                   |         |
 +---------------------------------------------------|---------+
                                                     |
                                                IPv4 packet +
                                              {ingress + NHinfo}
                                                  metadata
   FE2                                               |
 +---------------------------------------------------|---------+
 |                                                   V         | 
 |             +--------+                       +--------+     |
 |             | Egress |     IPV4 packet       | IPV4   |     |
 |       <-----|  LFB   |<--------------------  |NextHop |     |
 |             |        |{ingress + NHdetails}  | LFB    |     |
 |             +--------+      metadata         +--------+     |
 +-------------------------------------------------------------+
    ]]></artwork>
   </figure>
   </t>
   <t>
   Some proprietary inter-connect (example Broadcom Higig over XAUI (XXX: ref 
   needed)) maybe used to carry both the IPV4 packet and the related
   metadata between the IPV4 Unicast LFB and IPV4 NextHop LFB across the two
   FEs.
   </t>
</section>
</section>

<section title="Proposal Overview">
<t>
We address the inter-FE connectivity by proposing an inter-FE LFB.
Using an LFB implies no change to the basic ForCES architecture in
the form of the core LFBs (FE Protocol or Object LFBs). This design choice
was made after considering an alternative approach that would have 
required changes to both the FE Object capabilities
(SupportedLFBs) as well LFBTopology component to describe the inter-FE
connectivity capabilities as well as runtime topology of the LFB instances.
</t>
  <section title="Inserting The Inter-FE LFB">
   <t>
   The distributed LFB topology described in  <xref target="fig2"></xref> is
   re-illustrated in <xref target="fig3"></xref> to show the topology
   location where the inter-FE LFB would fit in.
   </t>

  <t>
   <figure title="Split IPV4 forwarding service with Inter-FE LFB" align="left" anchor="fig3">
   <artwork><![CDATA[
   FE1
 +-------------------------------------------------------------+
 | +----------+               +----+                           |
 | | Ingress  |    IPV4 pkt   |    | IPV4 pkt     +-----+      |
 | |  LFB     |+------------->|    |------------->|     |      |
 | |          |  + ingress    |    | + ingress    |IPv4 |      |
 | +----------+    metadata   |    |   metadata   |Ucast|      |
 |      ^                     +----+              |LPM  |      |
 |      |                      IPv4               +-----+      |
 |      |                     Validator              |         |
 |      |                      LFB                   |         |
 |      |                                  IPv4 pkt + metadata |
 |      |                        {ingress + NHinfo + InterFEid}|
 |      |                                            |         |
 |                                              +----V----+    |
 |                                              | InterFE |    |
 |                                              |   LFB   |    |
 |                                              +---------+    |
 +---------------------------------------------------|---------+
                                                     |
                                      IPv4 packet and metadata
                             {ingress + NHinfo + Inter FE info}
  FE2                                                |
 +---------------------------------------------------|---------+
 |                                              +----V----+    |
 |                                              | InterFE |    |
 |                                              |   LFB   |    |
 |                                              +---------+    |
 |                                                   |         | 
 |                                         IPv4 pkt + metadata |
 |                                          {ingress + NHinfo} |
 |                                                   |         | 
 |             +--------+                       +----V---+     |
 |             | Egress |     IPV4 packet       | IPV4   |     |
 |       <-----|  LFB   |<--------------------  |NextHop |     |
 |             |        |{ingress + NHdetails}  | LFB    |     |
 |             +--------+      metadata         +--------+     |
 +-------------------------------------------------------------+
    ]]></artwork>
   </figure>
   </t>

  <t>
  As can be observed in <xref target="fig3"></xref>, the same details
  passed between IPV4 unicast LPM LFB and the IPV4 NH LFB are passed
  to the egress side of the Inter-FE LFB. In addition an index for
  the inter-FE LFB (interFEid) is passed as metadata.
  </t> 

  <t> 
  The egress of the inter-FE LFB uses the received Inter-FE index (InterFEid
  metadata) to select details for encapsulation towards the neighboring FE.
  These details will include what the 
  source and destination FEID to be communicated to the neighboring FE.
  In addition the original metadata
  and any exception IDs may be passed along with the IPV4 
  packet.
  </t> 
  <t> 
  On the ingress side of the inter-FE LFB the received packet and its associated
  details are used
  to decide the graph continuation i.e which FE instance is to be passed the 
  packet plus the original metadata and exception IDs. 
  In the illustrated case above, an IPV4 Nexthop LFB instance metadata is passed.
  </t> 
  <t> 
  The ingress side of the inter-FE LFB consumes some of the information passed
  (eg the destination FEID)
  and passes on the IPV4 packet alongside with the ingress + NHinfo 
  metadata to the IPV4 NextHop LFB as was done earlier in both 
   <xref target="fig1"></xref> and  <xref target="fig2"></xref>.
  </t> 
  </section>
  <section title="Inter-FE connectivity">
   <t>
   We describe the suggested encapsulation format (<xref target="fig4"></xref>)
   extended from the ForCES redirect packet format. We expect that for any 
   transport mechanism
   used, that a description of how the different fields will be encapsulated
   to be explained. We provide a description of how ethernet encapsulation
   will be used in this case in <xref target="etherencap"></xref>.
   </t>
  <t>
   <figure title="Packet format suggestion" align="left" anchor="fig4">
   <artwork><![CDATA[
             +-- T = NESelector-TLV
             |     +---- NEID
             |     |
             |     +---- Destination FEID
             |     |
             |     +---- Source FEID
             |
             +-- T = ExceptionID-TLV
             |   |
             |   +-- +-Exception Data ILV (I = exceptionID , L= length)
             |   |   |  |
             |   |   |  +----- V= Metadata value
             |   .   |
             |   .   |
             |   .   +-Exception Data ILV
             . 
             |
             +-- T = METADATA-TLV
             |   |
             |   +-- +-Meta Data ILV (I = metaid, L= length)
             |   |   |  |
             |   |   |  +----- V= Metadata value
             |   .   |
             |   .   |
             |   .   +-Meta Data ILV
             . 
             +-- T = REDIRECTDATA-TLV
                 |
                 +--  Redirected packet Data
    ]]></artwork>
   </figure>
   </t>

   <t>
	   XXX: We are going to need two new ForCES TLVs to be defined.
   </t>
   <t>
   The NESelector carries inter-FE information
   described earlier. In some cases, the NESelector
   may be left out in the encapsulation activity (by the inter-FE LFB 
   implementation) if it is already implicitly defined or mapping
   in the transport (eg VLAN/VXLAN or where
   in the case of look-aside interfaces or proprietary
   hard-coded connections such as the one shown in  <xref target="fig2"></xref>).
   <list style="symbols">
   <t>
	   The NESelector carries a 32-bit NEID which defaults to 0. It also
	   carries the destination and source FEIDs. This TLV is new to ForCES
	   and sits in the global ForCES TLV namespace.
   </t>
   <t>
	   The  ExceptionID TLV carries one or more exception IDs within
	   ILVs. The I in the ILV carries a globally defined exceptionID
	   as per-ForCES specification defined by IANA.
	   This TLV is new to ForCES and sits in the global ForCES TLV namespace.
   </t>
   </list>
   </t>
   <t>
   The METADATA and REDIRECTDATA TLV encapsulations are taken directly from
   <xref target="RFC5810"></xref> section 7.9.
   </t>

  <section title="Inter-FE Ethernet connectivity" anchor="etherencap">
   <t>
   It is expected that a variety of transport encapsulations would be applicable
   to carry the format described in 
   <xref target="fig1"></xref>. In the case of exisiting interconnects,
   a description of a mapping to intepret the inter-FE details and translate 
   into proprietary or legacy formatting would need to be defined. 
   As an example, already a variety of metadata passing encapsulations exist 
   which are proprieatary or semi-standard by virtue of being widely deployed.
   These include the NPF LA-1 (XXX: ref here), Broadcom Higig/2 (XXX: ref here),
   as well as interlaken(XXX: ref here). For any mapping towards these definitions
   a different document to describe the mapping, one per transport, is expected 
   to be defined. 
   </t>
   <t>
   In this specific document, we describe a format that is to be used 
   over Ethernet.
  An ethernet type (To be defined) will be used to 
  imply that a wire format is carrying an inter-FE LFB packet. 
   </t>
  <t>
  XXX: The finer details on what the source and destination MAC address 
  selection are left out for the next draft release. Also left out are
  any load balancing/multi-pathing activities across selections of 
  destinations FEs.
   </t>
  <t>
   <figure title="Packet format suggestion" align="left" anchor="fig5">
   <artwork><![CDATA[

          *--+ Ethernet header (ethertype = XXXX)
             |
             +-- T = NESelector-TLV (optional)
             |     +---- NEID
             |     |
             |     +---- Destination FEID
             |     |
             |     +---- Source FEID
             |
             +-- T = ExceptionID-TLV
             |   |
             |   +-- +-Exception Data ILV (I = exceptionID , L= length)
             |   |   |  |
             |   |   |  +----- V= Metadata value
             |   .   |
             |   .   |
             |   .   +-Exception Data ILV
             . 
             |
             +-- T = METADATA-TLV
             |   |
             |   +-- +-Meta Data ILV (I = metaid, L= length)
             |   |   |  |
             |   |   |  +----- V= Metadata value
             |   .   |
             |   .   |
             |   .   +-Meta Data ILV
             . 
             +-- T = REDIRECTDATA-TLV
                 |
                 +--  Redirected packet Data

    ]]></artwork>
   </figure>
   </t>
  <section title="Inter-FE Ethernet Connectivity Issues" anchor="etherissues">
  <t>
	  There are several issues that may arise due to using direct ethernet 
	  encapsulation.
   <list style="symbols">
	   <t>
		   The frame may end up being larger than the MTU. There are
		   several possible solutions:
		   <list>
		   <t>
		   One possible solution is to use large MTUs; however, even
		   that will have limits since the the ethernet frames could grow
		   arbitrarily large with increasing metadata being encapsulated.
		   </t>
		   <t>
		   An alternative approach is to add a fragmentation detail in
		   the encapsulation. A simple approach is to have the inter-FE
		   LFB (egress) add another header which submits total count of 
		   fragments and the fragment number of the submitted packet.
		   The ingress of the inter-FE LFB will keep track of the fragments,
		   assemble them as well as have a timer to discard outstanding 
		   fragments. XXX: If we go this path, we would likely need a
		   top level TLV definition to describe the count.
		   </t>
		   <t>
		   A third option is to limit the amount of metadata that could
		   be transmitted so that the frame is sub-MTU size in presence
		   of large MTU values. It will mean to add knobs to filter out
		   or select which metadata gets encapsulated.
		   </t>
		   <t>
		   A fourth option is to use a transport that provides fragmentation
		   services (such as IP).
		   </t>
		   </list>
	   </t>
	   <t>
		 The frame may be dropped if there is congestion on the receiving
		 FE side. This may necessitate a retransmission mechanism to be 
		 built in. One approach to mitigate this issue is to make sure that
		 inter-FE LFB frames receive the highest priority treatment
		 when scheduled on the wire. A more common approach used in 
		 tunneling is to not care and let the packet originator to
		 resend if they care about reliability.
	   </t>
   </list>
   XXX: These issues will be addressed further in the next draft release.
   Suggestions welcome.
  </t>
   </section>
   </section>
  </section>

  </section>
  <section title="Detailed Description of the inter-FE LFB">
  <t>
	  The inter-FE LFB has two LFB input ports and three
	  LFB output ports.
  </t>
  <t>
   <figure title="Inter-FE LFB" align="left" anchor="fig6">
   <artwork><![CDATA[
                 +-----------------+
                 |                 |
  Encapsulated   |             OUT2+--> decapsulated Packet + metadata
  -------------->|IN2              |     + exception IDs
  Packet         |                 |
                 |                 |
  raw Packet +   |             OUT1+--> encapsulated Packet
  -------------->|IN1              |  
  exceptionIDs+  |                 |
  Metadata +     |    EXCEPTIONOUT +--> Errorid, packet + metadata
                 |                 |
                 +-----------------+

    ]]></artwork>
   </figure>
   </t>
    <section title="Data Handling">
    <t>
    The Inter-FE LFB may be positioned at the egress of an FE.
    In such a case it receives via port IN1, raw packet, metadata, and
    exception
    IDs. The InterFEid metadatum MAY be present on the incoming raw data. 
    The processed encapsulated packet will go out on either port
    OUT1 to a downstream LFB or EXCEPTIONOUT in the case of a failure.
    </t>
    <t> 
    The Inter-FE LFB may be positioned at the ingress of an FE.
    In such a case it receives, via port IN2, an encapsulated packet.
    Successful processing of the packet
    will result in a raw packet with associated metadata and exception IDs
    going downstream to an LFB connected on OUT2. On failure the data
    is sent out EXCEPTIONOUT.
    </t>
    <t>
    The Inter-FE LFB uses the InterFEid metadatum when on an egress of an
    FE to lookup the NextFE table.
    The output result constitutes a matched table row which has the InterFEinfo
    details i.e. the tuple {NEID,Destination FEID,Source FEID} as well
    as a filter list which defines which Metadatum and/or exceptionids
    are to be passed to the neighboring FE.
    It is expected that zero configuration is needed
    in the absence of the InterFEid metadatum and default behavior will
    be utilized.
    </t>
    <t>
    In the egress processing case of successful lookup, the inter-FE LFB will: 
    <list style="symbols">
       <t>
	       add the NESelector TLV data from the lookup result
	</t>
       <t>
	       walk the passed metadatum and encapsulate them within
	       the METADATA-TLV all allowed metadatum.
	</t>
       <t>
	       walk all the passed exceptionIDs and encapsulate all allowed
	       exception IDs within the EXCEPTION-TLV
	</t>
       <t>
	       Encapsulate the data, if present, in REDIRECTDATA-TLV
	</t>
</list>
	The resulting packet is sent to the LFB instance connected to the 
	OUT1 LFB port.
    </t>

    <t>
    In the case of a failed lookup or a zero-value InterFEid, 
    the default inter-FE LFB processing will: 
    <list style="symbols">
       <t>
	       Not add an NESelector TLV 
	</t>
       <t>
	       walk all the passed metadatum and encapsulate into
	       the METADATA-TLV all metadatum.
	</t>
       <t>
	       walk all the passed exceptionIDs and encapsulate all 
	       exceptionID within the EXCEPTION-TLV
	</t>
       <t>
	       Encapsulate the data, if present, in REDIRECTDATA-TLV
	</t>
</list>
	The resulting packet is sent to the LFB instance connected to the 
	OUT1 LFB port.
    </t>

    <t>
	    In the case of ingress processing, the LFB receives an
	    encapsulated packet and extracts the packet data,
	    metadata, and exception IDs.
    </t>
    <t>
	    In the case of processing failure of either ingress or
	    egress positioning of the LFB, the packet and metadata are 
	    sent out the 
	    EXCEPTIONOUT LFB port with proper error id (XXX: More description
	    to be added).
    </t>
    </section>
    <section title="Metadata">
    <t>
    A single (to be define from IANA space) metadatum, InterFEid, is defined.
    </t>
    </section>
    <section title="Components">
    <t>
	    There is a single optional LFB component populated by the CE.
	    The component is an array known as the NextFE table. Each 
	    row of the table constitutes the columns with
	    {NEID,Destination FEID,Source FEID,array of allowed Metaids,
	     array of exception ids}. The table is looked up by a 32 bit
	    index passed from an upstream LFB class instance in the form of
	    InterFEid metadatum.
    </t>
    <t>
	    The CE programs LFB instances in a service graph that require 
	    inter-FE connectivity with InterFEid values to correspond to the 
	    inter-FE LFB NextFE table entries to use.
    </t>
    </section>
    <section title="Capabilities">
	    <t>XXX: If we support multiple encapsulation methods(other than 
		    ethernet), then we could use capabilities to advertise them 
		    as different possibilities. It is envisioned then that
		    the  NextFE table row will have column indicating to the 
		    inter-FE LFB how to encapsulate the different matches.
		    Alternatively this could be left up to the LFB
		    connected in the output port.
	     </t>
    </section>
    <section title="Events">
	    <t>TBA</t>
    </section>
    <section title="Inter-FE LFB XML">
    <t>TBA</t>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">
	  <t>
		  TBA
	  </t>
  </section>

    <!-- Possibly a 'Contributors' section ... -->

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>This memo includes no request to IANA.</t>

    </section>

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>TBD</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <!--  *****BACK MATTER ***** -->

  <back>
    <!-- References split into informative and normative -->

    <!-- There are 2 ways to insert reference entries from the citation libraries:
     1. define an ENTITY at the top, and use "ampersand character"RFC2629; here (as shown)
     2. simply use a PI "less than character"?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119.xml"?> here
        (for I-Ds: include="reference.I-D.narten-iana-considerations-rfc2434bis.xml")

     Both are cited textually in the same manner: by using xref elements.
     If you use the PI option, xml2rfc will, by default, try to find included files in the same
     directory as the including file. You can also define the XML_LIBRARY environment variable
     with a value containing a set of directories to search.  These can be either in the local
     filing system or remote ones accessed by http (http://domain/dir/... ).-->

    <references title="Normative References">
      <!--?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"?-->
      &RFC5810;
      &RFC5812;

    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <!-- Here we use entities that we defined at the beginning. -->

    &RFC2119;
    </references>

    <!-- Change Log

v00 2009-02-17  EH   Initial version
  -->
  </back>
</rfc>
