<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY RFC2119 PUBLIC ''
'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml'> 
<!ENTITY RFC3775 PUBLIC ''
'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3775.xml'> 
<!ENTITY RFC5213 PUBLIC ''
'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5213.xml'> 
<!ENTITY RFC5555 PUBLIC ''
'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5555.xml'> 
<!ENTITY I-D.ietf-netlmm-mip-interactions PUBLIC ''
'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-netlmm-mip-interactions.xml'> 
<!ENTITY I-D.ietf-monami6-multiplecoa PUBLIC ''
'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-monami6-multiplecoa.xml'> 
]>



<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<rfc category="std" docName="draft-premec-mext-extended-home-link-04"
     ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <!--title abbrev="Extended DSMIP6 home link support">Extended Home Link
    Support for DSMIPv6</title-->

    <title abbrev="IPv4 Support for DSMIPv6 IPv6 Home Link">IPv4 Support for
                   DSMIPv6 IPv6 Home Link</title>

    <author role="editor" fullname="Fuad Abinader" initials="F." surname="Abinader">
	  <organization>Nokia Institute of Technology</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Av. Torquato Tapajos, 7200 - Km. 12 - Col Terra Nova</street>
          <city>Manaus</city>
          <region>AM</region>
          <code>69048-660</code>
          <country>BRAZIL</country>
        </postal>
        <email>fabinader@gmail.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Domagoj Premec" initials="D." surname="Premec">
      <organization>Unaffiliated</organization>
      <address>
        <email>domagoj.premec@gmail.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Jouni Korhonen" initials="J." surname="Korhonen">
      <organization>Nokia Siemens Networks</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Linnoitustie 6</street>
          <city>Espoo</city>
          <region></region>
          <code>FI-02600</code>
          <country>FINLAND</country>
        </postal>
        <email>jouni.nospam@gmail.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date year="2009" />

    <area>Internet Area</area>

    <workgroup>MEXT Working Group</workgroup>

    <keyword>dual stack mobile IPv6</keyword>

    <keyword>extended home link</keyword>

    <keyword>IPv6-only home link</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>Mobile IPv6 for Dual Stack Hosts and Routers enables mobility for the
	  mobile node's IPv6 home address or prefix as well as an IPv4 home address,
	  irrespective of the IP version supported on the link that the mobile node
	  is attached to. The home agent maintains binding cache entries for the 
	  IPv6 and IPv4 home addresses assigned to the mobile node when the mobile 
	  node is connected via a foreign link. The binding cache entries are
	  deprecated when the mobile node attaches to its home link. This document 
	  addresses an issue related to the de-registration procedure and the 
	  continued connectivity for the IPv4 home address when the mobile node 
	  attaches to its IPv6-only home link.</t>
    </abstract>

    <note title="Requirements Language">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
      document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
      target="RFC2119"/>.</t>
    </note>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>A Dual-Stack Mobile IPv6 (DSMIPv6) <xref target="RFC5555"/> Home 
	  Agent (HA) may be deployed with some links that are considered by Mobile 
	  Nodes (MNs) as home links that are IPv6 only. A DSMIPv6 MN may attach to 
	  its home link via either a physical or a "virtual" link. As an example, a 
	  DSMIPv6 MN may attach to a network which deploys Proxy Mobile IPv6 
	  (PMIPv6) <xref target="RFC5213"/> in a way similar to the Scenario C 
	  from <xref target="I-D.ietf-netlmm-mip-interactions"/>, where the 
	  non-PMIPv6 domain to which the MN roams can be a different PMIPv6 domain
	  that handles a different MN_HoA; in this case, the MN would receive a Router
	  Advertisement (RA) including the home-link prefix and hence would 
	  perceive to be connected to the home link. The DSMIPv6 MN may also be 
	  attached via a 2G/3G cellular network <xref target="3GPP.23.060"/>, in 
	  which case the link the MN is attached to can also be seen as the home 
	  link. In addition, the MN may also attach to its HA via a physical home 
	  link of the HA. The links in these examples may be in many cases IPv6 only.
	  <xref target="figure-types-home-links"/> illustrate some of these examples:
	  <figure anchor="figure-types-home-links"
          title="Example of Home Links (HL) Types provided by a DSMIPv6 HA">
            <artwork><![CDATA[
                              .--.
                            _(.   `)
                          _( IPv4/6`)_
                         (  Internet  `)
                        ( `  .       )  )
                         `--(_______)--'
                                |
                                | 
                                |
            IPv6-only HL   +----+----+ Dual Stack HL
            ---------------|DSMIP6 HA|--------------
                       IF1 +---------+ IF2      	    
                           |  GW     | 	      	    
                           | eg. GGSN|
                           +---------+
                                | IF3
                                |<-------------IPv6 Virtual HL
                                |
                       (--------|------)
                      (         |       )
                      (   Radio |  NW   )
                       (--------|------) 
                                |	       	       
                                |	       
                            +-------+
                            | DS MN |
                            +-------+]]></artwork>
          </figure></t>
	  
	  <t>As seen on <xref target="figure-types-home-links"/>, if the attaches to 
	  its home link which is dual stack, eg interface IF2, the procedures 
	  described in <xref target="RFC5555"/> handle the deregistration and are 
	  sufficient. However, if the MN returns 
	  through either the IPv6-only (IF1) or IPv6 "virtual" (IF3) home links, 
	  the provisioning of a "IPv6-only home link" for the MN does not imply that 
	  the IPv4 Home Address (HoA) assigned to the MN is also conceptually on the 
	  MN's home link. Furthermore, forwarding IPv4 traffic from the home agent (HA) 
	  to the MN might only be accomplished by tunneling it over the IPv6-only access 
	  link. This basically implies that there are situations where the MN is on its 
	  home link (from the IPv6 point of view), but must still retain a Binding 
	  Cache Entry (BCE) on the HA for the IPv4 HoA in order to be able to send 
	  and receive  IPv4 traffic.</t>

      <t> Since DSMIPv6 does not allow the MN to maintain a BCE for its IPv4 
	  HoA while being attached to the home link from the IPv6 point of view (as
	  stated in Section 4.4.2.1 of <xref target="RFC5555"/>), this document
      extends the DSMIP6 protocol in order to allow the usage of the IPv4 HoA
      from an IPv6-only access link appearing as the "IPv6 home link" to the MN.
	  By means of what is herein defined, a MN attached to an IPv6-only "home 
	  link" is allowed to register its own IPv6 HoA as a Care-of Address (CoA) 
	  for its IPv4 home address, while at the same time de-registering the IPv6 
	  binding. In such scenario, there is no tunneling overhead for the 
	  IPv6 traffic, and the MN is able to tunnel IPv4 traffic using its IPv4 
	  HoA over the IPv6-only access link.</t>

	  <t><xref target="problem-statement"/> describes what occurs (as per the 
	  current DSMIPv6 specification <xref target="RFC5555"/>) with the IPv4 
	  HoA BCE that an MN registers on its HA while attached via a foreign network 
	  with support for IPv6, and then moves to an IPv6-only home link.</t>
	  
      <t><xref target="example-deployment-config"></xref> of this specification 
	  discusses the envisioned deployment scenarios in more detail.</t>

      <t><xref target="solution-overview"></xref> describes how a
      DSMIPv6-enabled MN that is attached to a foreign network returns to the
      "IPv6-only home link" while maintaining IPv4 connectivity.</t>

      <t><xref target="protocol-operation"></xref> provides the details
      for the processing at the MN and HA</t>
    </section> 

    <section title="Terminology">
      <t>General Mobile IPv6 related terminology is defined in <xref
      target="RFC3775"></xref>. DSMIPv6 related terminology is described in <xref
      target="RFC5555"></xref>.
      </t>

      <t><list style="hanging">
        <t hangText="IPv6-only Home Link">
          <vspace blankLines="1"/>
		  A link associated with an HA, which may be physical or virtual, and is
		  considered by an MN as its home link, which supports IPv6 only.
        </t>
      </list>
      </t>


    </section>

	<section anchor="problem-statement" title="Problem Statement">	
		<t>As stated in Section 4.4.2 of <xref target="RFC5555"/>, the presence
		of the IPv4 HoA Option is only mandatory in the Binding Update (BU) message 
		for the situation where the MN does need to register an IPv4 HoA with the HA, 
		otherwise its presence in the BU message is optional. Section 4.4.2.1 of 
		<xref target="RFC5555"/> also states that the MN cannot remove the IPv6 
		HoA BCE while maintaining an IPv4 HoA BCE. From these two statements, 
		it can be concluded that the presence of the IPv4 HoA Option on the BU 
		message that de-registers the IPv6 HoA on the HA when the MN returns 
		to its home link is not mandatory, and that independently of the presence 
		or absence of the IPv4 HoA in the BU message, the HA will remove all bindings 
		(both IPv6 and IPv4) for the MN.</t>

		<t>According to Section 2.3.1 of <xref target="RFC5555"/>, the HA for an MN
		which is attached via a foreign link and has been assigned an IPv6 HoA as well
		as an IPv4 HoA, contains a BCE which includes both the assigned HoAs pointing to
		the MN's IPv4 or IPv6 CoA, like those defined below:<figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[
    v6HoA -> v6CoA
    v4HoA -> v6CoA
          ]]></artwork>
          </figure></t>

		<t>Suppose now that the MN moves to an IPv6-only link which is viewed
		by the MN as its home link. After determining that it has returned to the
		home link, the first action the MN takes is to send a BU to its HA in order
		to de-register the IPv6 CoA on the HA. As the HA cannot remove IPv6 binding 
		while maintaining the IPv4 binding, the MN may or may not include the IPv4 
		HoA (which is optional) in the BU message.
		Once the  HA receives this BU message and determines that it is a 
		de-registration (by either looking for equal source IPv6 address and IPv6 
		HoA Option values OR a lifetime of zero), all bindings for the mobile node 
		will be removed. This will occur no matter if the IPv4 HoA Option was 
		present or not, as it was already stated that  it is not allowed (by Section 
		4.4.2.1 of <xref target="RFC5555"/>) to have an registered IPv4 HoA without 
		a registered IPv6 HoA as well.</t>
		
		<t>If for instance the MN needs an IPv4 HoA BCE while at the home 
		network, according to what is stated on <xref target="RFC5555"/>, 
		one possibility is to send another BU message to register the IPv4 
		HoA after receiving the Binding Acknowledgement (BAck) message for 
		the previous IPv6 de-registration event. However, this creates a gap
		in the provisioning of IPv4 service between the two BU messages which 
		does not allow "seamless handovers", as IPv4 packets may be discarded 
		on the HA while in the gap period because of the lack of the BCE for 
		the IPv4 HoA. In fact, the transport layer connections would most probably 
		be dropped due to the event of IPv6 CoA de-registration. Therefore, the 
		registration of the IPv4 HoA after the initial BU message for de-registering
		the IPv6 HoA would not ensure "seamless handovers". Given that there are no 
		other mechanisms currently supported in <xref target="RFC5555"/> for keeping 
		the IPv4 binding while roaming back to the IPv6-only network, there is a 
		need for extending <xref target="RFC5555"/> in order to allow "seamless 
		handovers" for IPv4.</t>
		
	</section>

    <section anchor="example-deployment-config"
             title="Example Deployment Configuration">
      <t>This section describes an example scenario, where a MN's "home
      link" provides IPv6-only access. As shown on <xref target="Figure-IPv6-only-home-link"/>,
	  the HA is collocated with the default router, and the MN's access link 
	  (i.e. the "home link" from the MN point of view) is configured to support 
	  only IPv6, while the HA has connectivity to
      IPv4/IPv6 Internet on its outbound interface. 
	  
      <figure anchor="Figure-IPv6-only-home-link"
          title="Dual Stack Deployment with IPv6-only Home Link">
          <artwork><![CDATA[
                           .--.
                         _(.   `)
                       _( IPv4/6`)_
                      (  Internet  `)
                     ( `  .       )  )
                      `--(_______)--'
                             |                  
                             | IPv4/6 link
                             |                 
                        +----+----+
                        |DSMIP6 HA|
                        +---------+
                             |                  
                             | IPv6 access link
                             |     
                          +--+--+
                          |  MN |
                          +-----+]]></artwork>
        </figure></t>
		
	  <t>Since the HA in the example shown on 
	  <xref target="Figure-IPv6-only-home-link"/> is a fully functional DSMIPv6 
	  HA, it can provide IPv4 HoA and IPv4 connectivity service to the MN. In 
	  this case, the IPv4 home link appears as a "virtual home link" to the MN 
	  (meaning the MN is always attached to a foreign link from the Mobile IP 
	  point of view) and the MN tunnels the IPv4 traffic via its on-link IPv6 
	  address to the HA, and vice versa. However, from an IPv6 perspective the 
	  MN is on its home link and hence there is no tunnelling of IPv6 packets.</t>

    </section>

    <section anchor="solution-overview" title="Solution Overview">
      <t>The following sections describe the solution to overcome the problem when
		 the MN attaches to an IPv6 only home link with additional information in
		 the Binding Update (BU) and Binding Acknowledgement (BAck) messages.
		 Currently when a MN attaches to its home link, as described 
         in Section 4.4.2.1. of <xref target="RFC5555"/> and in Sections 9.5.
         and 11.5.4. of <xref target="RFC3775"/>), this would cause a de-registration
         of all bindings for the Mobile Node (MN), including the IPv4 HoA.
      </t>
      <section anchor="bu-extensions" title="Binding Update Extensions">
        <t>This specification extends the Binding Update message with a new (X)
        flag.</t>

        <t><figure anchor="Figure-T-Flag-BU" title="Binding Update Message">
            <artwork><![CDATA[
 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
                                +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
                                |          Sequence #           |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|A|H|L|K|M|R|P|F|T|X| Reserved  |           Lifetime            |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
]]></artwork>
          </figure></t>

        <t>Tunnel flag (X)</t>

        <t>A new flag (X) is introduced in the Binding Update message to
           indicate a request to register the IPv6 HoA as the Care-of
           Address (CoA) for the IPv4 HoA. The MN MAY set this flag only when
           it sends a BU message from an IPv6-only link that appears
           as the Mobile IPv6 home link to the MN. If this
           flag is set, the BU message MUST also contain the IPv4
           HoA option <xref target="RFC5555"></xref> and the HA MUST
           retain the binding for the IPv4 HoA. The presence of the flag (X)
		   on the BU message, independently from the Lifetime being non-zero 
		   or not, automatically causes the de-registration of the IPv6 HoA,
		   as it is discussed later on this document 
		   (see <xref target="registration-process-on-home-link"/>).
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="back-extensions" title="Binding Acknowledgment Extensions">
        <t>This specification extends the BAck message with
        a new (X) flag.</t>

        <t><figure anchor="Figure-T-Flag-BAck"
            title="Binding Acknowledgement Message">
            <artwork><![CDATA[
 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
                                +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
                                |   Status      |K|R|P|T|X|Resv.|
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|         Sequence #            |           Lifetime            |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                                                               |
.                                                               .
.                        Mobility options                       .
.                                                               .
|                                                               |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
]]></artwork>
          </figure></t>

        <t>Tunnel Flag (X)</t>

        <t>A new flag (X) is included in the BAck message
           to indicate that the HA has created the Binding Cache Entry (BCE)
           for the IPv4 HoA with the IPv6 HoA as the CoA.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="registration-process-on-home-link" title="Registration Process on the Home Link">
        <t>Assume a MN has been configured with the following three
        addresses:<figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[
    v6HoA  MN's IPv6 home address
    v4HoA  MN's IPv4 home address
    v6HA   HA's IPv6 address
]]></artwork>
          </figure></t>

        <t>and currently is located in an IPv6 foreign network using<figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[
    v6CoA  MN's IPv6 care-of address]]></artwork>
          </figure></t>

        <t>The MN has, using DSMIPv6, already made a registration with the HA
           for both of its home addresses.
        </t>

        <t>When the MN returns home to an IPv6-only home link, the MN sends
           the following packet in order to register its on-link IPv6 address as
           the CoA for the IPv4 HoA. The usage of the
           Alternate Care-of Address option <xref target="RFC3775"/> while on the
           home link is optional and hence it may be omitted:
        </t>

        <t><figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[
    IPv6 Header (src = v6HoA, dst = v6HA)
    ESP Header
    Mobility Header
        type = 5 (Binding Update), X-flag=1
        lifetime non-zero
        [Alternate Care-of Address option (v6HoA)]
        IPv4 Home Address option (v4HoA)
]]></artwork>
          </figure></t>

        <t>The HA sends the following response:<figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[
    IPv6 Header (src = v6HA, dst = v6HoA)
    ESP Header
    Mobility Header 
        type = 6 (Binding Acknowledgement), X-flag=1
        lifetime non-zero
        IPv4 Address Acknowledgement option (v4HoA)
]]></artwork>
          </figure></t>

        <t>Although the packet exchange specified above seems obvious, the
           packet exchange modifies the normal semantics of bindings in two
           ways.
        </t>

        <t>First, according to <xref target="RFC3775"></xref> Section 9.5, the
           HA when processing the BU will determine the
           specified CoA to be the address found in the Alternate
           Care-of Address option, i.e. v6HoA, or detect that the Alternate
           Care-of Address option was omitted. Furthermore, it will determine the
           HoA to be the source address of the IPv6 header, i.e. v6HoA. With
           this input, the HA will conclude the binding update is a
           de-registration, even if lifetime is non-zero. When a DSMIPv6 HA
           detects a de-registration of the IPv6 home address, it releases
           the entries for both the IPv6 and IPv4 HoAs. Therefore, the
           (X) flag introduced by this specification changes the normal
           semantics of
           deletion of a Binding Cache Entry (BCE) as it requires that only the
           IPv6 entry is removed.
        </t>

        <t>Another point relates to the de-registration of the IPv4 HoA
           from the IPv6-only home link. Suppose the MN has
           installed the entry:<figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[
    v4HoA -> v6HoA
          ]]></artwork>
          </figure></t>

        <t>in the Binding Cache (BE). Assume the MN no longer wants IPv4
           connectivity, and wants to clear the BCE. The MN will
           clear the entry by sending a BU
           message with a lifetime of zero. This message is sent using
           v6HoA as source address. However, the BC has no v6HoA
           entry. This means the entry in the BCE cannot be found and
           cleared.
        </t>

        <t>One way to resolve this is to mandate that the MN includes
           the IPv4 HoA as part of the de-registration BU
           message which is then used by the HA to locate the
           corresponding BCE.
        </t>

        <t>Another way to resolve this is to ensure the HA maintains a
           dummy entry for the v6HoA, such that the BC reads:<figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[
    v6HoA -> v6HoA
    v4HoA -> v6HoA
           ]]></artwork>
          </figure></t>

        <t>Inserting such a dummy entry in order to bypass tunneling seems a
           substantial change of semantics. This is essentially the same as the
           concept of the home binding described in Section 5.6.3 of <xref
           target="I-D.ietf-monami6-multiplecoa"></xref>.
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="protocol-operation" title="Protocol Operation"
             toc="default">
      <t>This specification introduces the new (X) flag in the BU
         and BAck messages. The (X) flag in the BU
 		 message indicates a request to bind the IPv6 home address as the 
		 CoA to the IPv4 home address. The (X) flag in BAck
         indicates that the HA successfully created the binding
         between the IPv4 HoA and the IPv6 HoA.
      </t>

      <section title="Mobile Node Considerations">
        <t>When a DSMIPv6-enabled MN is connected to an IPv6-only home link,
           it MAY register its IPv6 HoA as the CoA for its
           IPv4 HoA by setting the (X) flag in the BU message, including
           the IPv4 Home Address option and setting the CoA in the BU
           message to its IPv6 HoA. In this case the MN MUST tunnel any
           IPv4 traffic sourced from the IPv4 HoA via its IPv6 HoA
           to the HA.
        </t>

        <t>If the MN registered its IPv6 HoA as the CoA for
           its IPv4 HoA, the MN MUST maintain a BU list entry for the
           IPv4 HoA containing the IPv6 HoA as the CoA.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section title="Home Agent Considerations">
        <t>If the MN's current CoA as received in the BU
           message equals the MN's IPv6 HoA, the HA MUST
           deprecate the BCE for the IPv6 HoA. If the (X) flag was set and
           the IPv4 HoA was included in the same BU message and the
           lifetime filed is non-zero, the HA MUST update the BCE for the IPv4
           HoA with the IPv6 HoA as the CoA.
        </t>

        <t>If the HA updated the IPv4 BCE with the IPv6 HoA as the
           CoA, it MUST set the (X) flag in the BAck message.
        </t>

        <t>When the MN registers its IPv6 HoA as the CoA
           for the IPv4 HoA, the HA MUST intercept the traffic
           destined to the MN's IPv4 HoA and tunnel it to the
           MN's IPv6 HoA. 
        </t>

        <t>When the HA receives the BU that was sent from the "IPv6-only home
           link" and where the lifetime is set to zero, the HA releases both the
           IPv6 and IPv4 BCEs. If no IPv6 BCE was found, but the BU message
           contains the IPv4 HoA, the HA MUST use the IPv4 HoA
           from the BU message to locate the corresponding IPv4 BCE and release
           it.
        </t>
      </section>

    </section>

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
	<t>The security aspects and implications associated with <xref target="RFC5555"/>
	   are applicable to this document. 
	   This document also recommends that the same level of security is applied 
       to the packets sent natively to/from the MN's on-link home address
       and to the packets on the virtual home link that are tunneled to the
       MN's on-link home address.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>This document specifies a new flag (X) in the Binding Update (BU) 
	     and Binding Acknowledgement (BAck) messages of DSMIPv6 
	     <xref target="RFC5555"/>. This flag is defined in sections 
		 <xref target="bu-extensions" /> and <xref target="back-extensions" />.
	     IANA is requested to allocate the new flag (X) in the Binding
         Update and Binging Acknowledgement messages from the RFC3775
         Binding Update Flags and the RFC3775 Binding Acknowledgment Flags
         registries.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>The authors would like to thank Christian Kaas-Petersen for a
      detailed review and contributions to this document.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      &RFC2119;
      &RFC3775;
	  &RFC5213;
      &RFC5555;
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
	  &I-D.ietf-netlmm-mip-interactions;
      &I-D.ietf-monami6-multiplecoa;

      <reference anchor='3GPP.23.060'>
        <front>
          <title>General Packet Radio Service (GPRS); Service description; Stage 2</title>
          <author><organization>3GPP</organization></author>
          <date month='June' year='2009' />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name='3GPP TS' value='23.060 8.5.1' />
        <format type='HTML' target='http://www.3gpp.org/ftp/Specs/html-info/23060.htm' />
      </reference>
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
