<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY RFC2141 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2141.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3406 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3406.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4358 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4358.xml">
]>

<rfc category="info" docName="draft-cardona-cablelabs-urn-05" ipr="pre5378Trust200902">

<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="rfc2629.xslt" ?>

<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc iprnotified="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>


  <front>

    <title abbrev="URN Namespace for CableLabs">A Uniform Resource Name (URN) Namespace for CableLabs</title>

    <author fullname="Eduardo Cardona" initials="E.C." surname="Cardona">
      <organization>CableLabs</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>858 Coal Creek Circle</street>
          <city>Louisville</city>
          <region>CO</region>
          <code>80027</code>
          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>

        <phone>+1 303 661 3375</phone>
        <email>e.cardona@cablelabs.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    
    <author fullname="Sumanth Channabasappa" initials="S.C." surname="Channabasappa">
      <organization>CableLabs</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>858 Coal Creek Circle</street>
          <city>Louisville</city>
          <region>CO</region>
          <code>80027</code>
          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>
        <phone>+1 303 661 3307</phone>
        <email>sumanth@cablelabs.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    
    <author fullname="Jean-Francois Mule" initials="J-F.M." surname="Mule">
      <organization>CableLabs</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>858 Coal Creek Circle</street>
          <city>Louisville</city>
          <region>CO</region>
          <code>80027</code>
          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>
        <phone>+1 303 661 9100</phone>
        <email>jf.mule@cablelabs.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date month="October" year="2010"/>

    <area>General</area>

    <workgroup>Network Working Group</workgroup>

    <keyword>URN</keyword>
    <keyword>CableLabs</keyword>


    <abstract>
      	<t>
This document describes the Namespace Identifier (NID) 'cablelabs' for Uniform Resource Names (URNs) used to identify resources published by Cable Television Laboratories, Inc. (CableLabs). CableLabs specifies and manages resources that utilize this URN identification model. Management activities for these and other resource types are handled by the manager of the CableLabs' Assigned Names and Numbers registry.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>


  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
	<t>
	CableLabs is a non-profit research and development consortium that is dedicated to pursuing new cable telecommunications technologies and to helping its cable operator members integrate those technical advancements into their business objectives. Within CableLabs, specification activities are organized into projects such as DOCSIS(R), PacketCable(TM), and OpenCable(TM), and technical work is conducted within focus teams.  Product vendors, manufacturers, and cable operator members are invited to join the focus teams that create technical specifications. 
	</t>

	<t>

	Occasionally, CableLabs specification efforts require identifiers in a managed namespace so that they are unique and persistent.  To ensure that the uniqueness is absolute, the registration of a specific Uniform Resource Name (URN) [RFC2141] Namespace ID (NID) for use by CableLabs is being specified in this document, in full conformance with the NID registration process specified in <xref target="RFC3406"></xref>.
	</t>
    </section>

    <section title="URN Specification for CableLabs">
		<t>
			Namespace ID:
			<list hangIndent="5">
				<t>cablelabs</t>
			</list>
		</t>
		<t>
			Registration Information:
			<list hangIndent="5">
				<t>
				registration version number: 1
				<vspace blankLines="0"/>
       				registration date: YYYY-MM-DD [RFC Editor: Please replace YYYY-MM-DD with the date of approval of this document for publication as an RFC.]
				</t>
			</list>
		</t>
		<t>
			Declared registrant of the namespace:
			<list hangIndent="5">
				<t>Registering organization</t>
			</list>
			<list hangIndent="8">
				<t>Name:    Cable Television Laboratories, Inc.
				<vspace blankLines="0"/>
				Address: 858 Coal Creek Circle, Louisville, CO 80027, USA</t>
			</list>
			<list hangIndent="5">
				<t>Designated contact</t>
			</list>
			<list hangIndent="8">
				<t>Role: Manager, Standards
				<vspace blankLines="0"/>
				Email: ietf_standards@cablelabs.com</t>
			</list>
		</t>
		<t>
			Declaration of syntactic structure:
			<list hangIndent="5">
				<t>

The Namespace Specific String (NSS) of all URNs that use the "cablelabs" NID will have the following structure:

		<vspace blankLines="1"/>

               {CLclass}:{CLClassSpecificString}

		<vspace blankLines="1"/>

The "CLclass" is a US-ASCII string that conforms to the URN syntax requirements specified in  <xref target="RFC2141"></xref> and defines a specific class of resource type.  Each class will have a specific labeling scheme that is covered by "CLClassSpecificString", which also conforms to the naming requirements of <xref target="RFC2141"></xref>.



				</t>
				<t>
				CableLabs maintains the CableLabs Assigned Names and Numbers <xref target="CANN"></xref> specification that will contain the assignment of CableLabs resource classes, and the specific registration values assigned for each resource class.
				</t>
			</list>
		</t>
		<t>Relevant ancillary documentation:
			<list hangIndent="5">
				<t>
					CableLabs publishes information regarding the registered resources in the CableLabs' Assigned Names and Numbers specification (<xref target="CANN"></xref>).
				</t>
			</list>
		</t>
		<t>Identifier uniqueness considerations:
			<list hangIndent="5">
				<t>
					CableLabs will manage resource classes using the "cablelabs" NID and will be the authority for managing resources and subsequent strings associated.  CableLabs is expected to guarantee the uniqueness of the strings themselves or it may permit secondary responsibility for certain defined resources.
				</t>
				<t>
					CableLabs could allow the use of experimental type values for testing purposes only. Note that using experimental types may create collisions as multiple users may use the same values for resources and specific strings.
				</t>
			</list>
		</t>	
		<t>Identifier persistence considerations:
			<list hangIndent="5">
				<t>
					CableLabs will update the CableLabs' Assigned Names and Numbers specification (ref: <xref target="CANN"></xref>) to document the registered resources that use the "cablelabs" NID.
				</t>
			</list>
		</t>
		<t>Process of identifier assignment:
			<list hangIndent="5">
				<t>
					CableLabs  will provide procedures for registration of each type of resource that it maintains.  Each such resource may have three types of registration activities:
				</t>
			</list>
			<list hangIndent="8">
				<t>1. Registered values associated with CableLabs documents or services
				<vspace blankLines="0"/>
				2. Registration of values or sub-trees to other entities
				<vspace blankLines="0"/>
				3. Name models for use in experimental purposes</t>
			</list>
		</t>
		
		<t> Process for identifier resolution:
			<list hangIndent="5">
				<t>
					The namespace is not listed with a resolution discovery system; this is not applicable for this URN registration.
				</t>
			</list>
		</t>
		
		<t> Rules for Lexical Equivalence:
			<list hangIndent="5">
				<t>No special considerations; the rules for lexical equivalence of <xref target="RFC2141"></xref> apply.
				</t>
			</list>
		</t>
		
		<t> Conformance with URN Syntax:
			<list hangIndent="5">
				<t>No special considerations.</t>
			</list>
		</t>
		
		<t> Validation mechanism:
			<list hangIndent="5">
				<t>None specified.  URN assignment will be handled by procedures implemented in support of CableLabs activities.
				</t>
			</list>
		</t>				

		<t> Scope:
			<list hangIndent="5">
				<t>Global</t>
			</list>
		</t>				

    </section>

    <?rfc needLines="8" ?>

    <section title="Example">
      <t>The following example represents a hypothetical URN that could be assigned by CableLabs.</t>
	  <t>urn:cablelabs:packetcable-example:ue:rst-sample</t>
      <t>Defines the URN to be used for User Equipment (UE) conforming to the sample Residential SIP Telephony (RST) application specified within CableLabs' PacketCable RST specification suite.</t>
    </section>

   <section title="Namespace Considerations">
      <t>CableLabs develops specifications that may require the use of data models. URN Namespaces are key constructs to manage the definitions of those data models reliably with persistence and uniqueness.</t>
      <t/>
	  <t>The use of URNs should also help specification authors to maintain different versions of URNs and dependencies between urns, across different versions of CableLabs specifications, if they so wish.</t>
    </section>

   <section title="Community Considerations">
      <t>The CableLabs specifications are publicly available or licensed to manufacturers on a nondiscriminatory basis. CableLabs will maintain the allocation of resources for the "cablelabs" NID and maintain updated the corresponding specifications where those resources are referenced or used.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
	<t>
This document adds a new entry in the urn-namespaces registry.  The namespace should be "cablelabs".  This is the defining document.  The entry can be found at: http://www.iana.org/assignments/urn-namespaces and any associated mirrors.
	</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>There are no additional security considerations other than those normally associated with the use and resolution of URNs in general.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">
	<t>
	The authors thank Alfred Hoenes (TR-Sys) for his useful comments and suggestions. The authors also acknowledge that the text from this RFC - <xref target="RFC4358"></xref> - formed the basis for the intial version of this document.
	</t>
    </section>

  </middle>


  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      &RFC2141;
      &RFC3406;
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
	  &RFC4358;
      <reference anchor="CANN"
                 target="http://www.cablelabs.com/specifications/cpSpecs.html">
        <front>
          <title>CableLabs' Assigned Names and Numbers</title>

          <author>
            <organization>Cable Television Laboratories Inc.</organization>
          </author>

          <date year="2009"/>
        </front>
      </reference>
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>

