<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629xslt\rfc2629.dtd" [
	<!ENTITY rfc2119 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
	<!ENTITY rfc1112 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1112.xml">
	<!ENTITY rfc3810 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3810.xml">
	<!ENTITY rfc3376 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3376.xml">
	<!ENTITY rfc2865 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2865.xml">
	<!ENTITY rfc3588 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3588.xml">
	<!ENTITY rfc3748 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3748.xml">
	<!ENTITY rfc4601 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4601.xml">
	<!ENTITY rfc3740 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3740.xml">
	<!ENTITY rfc5296 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5296.xml">
	<!ENTITY I-D.ietf-mboned-maccnt-req SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-mboned-maccnt-req.xml">
	<!ENTITY I-D.ietf-mboned-multiaaa-framework SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-mboned-multiaaa-framework.xml">
	<!ENTITY I-D.ietf-karp-threats-reqs SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-karp-threats-reqs.xml">
	<!ENTITY I-D.ietf-karp-design-guide SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-karp-design-guide.xml">
	<!ENTITY I-D.ietf-karp-framework SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-karp-framework.xml">
	<!ENTITY I-D.ietf-pim-sm-linklocal SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-pim-sm-linklocal.xml">
]>
<?rfc toc="yes" simrefs="yes" compact="yes" subcompact="no" ?>
<rfc category="std" updates="" docName="draft-atwood-mcast-user-auth-01" ipr="trust200811">
	<front>
		<title abbrev="Multicast User Authentication">Multicast User Authentication</title>
		<author fullname="J. William Atwood" initials="W." surname="Atwood">
			<organization>Concordia University/CSE</organization>
			<address>
				<postal>
					<street>1455 de Maisonneuve Blvd, West</street>
					<city>Montreal</city>
					<region>QC</region>
					<code>H3G 1M8</code>
					<country>Canada</country>
				</postal>
				<phone>+1(514)848-2424 ext3046</phone>
				<email>bill@cse.concordia.ca</email>
				<uri>http://users.encs.concordia.ca/~bill</uri>
			</address>
		</author>
		<author fullname="Salekul Islam" initials="S." surname="Islam">
			<organization>INRS-EMT</organization>
			<address>
				<postal>
					<street>800 de La Gauchetiere, suite 800</street>
					<city>Montreal</city>
					<region>QC</region>
					<code>H5A 1K6</code>
					<country>Canada</country>
				</postal>
				<email>Salekul.Islam@emt.inrs.ca</email>
				<uri>http://users.encs.concordia.ca/~salek_is</uri>
			</address>
		</author>
		<date day="08" month="March" year="2010"></date>
		<area>Routing</area>
		<workgroup>MBONED Working Group</workgroup>
		<keyword>Authentication</keyword>
		<keyword>IGMP</keyword>
		<keyword>MLD</keyword>
		<abstract>
			<t>RFC 1112 offers no facilities for participant control or accounting.  This document explores the requirements for such facilities, and offers a potential solution, based on extending the IGMP and MLD "join" operations to carry EAP and/or ERP packets.</t>
		</abstract>
	</front>
	<middle>
		<section title="Introduction">
			<t>The procedure for joining a network-level IP multicast group <xref target="RFC1112"></xref> an open one---a request is made by the receiving host, using MLD (IPv6) <xref target="RFC3810"></xref> or IGMP (IPv4) <xref target="RFC3376"></xref>, and the multicast routing protocol (typically PIM-SM <xref target="RFC4601"></xref>) is responsibile for building a Data Distribution Tree (DDT) to ensure that the data are delivered to the receiving host(s).</t>
			<t>The procedure for joining an application-level group clearly depends on the application.  When IP multicast is used as the data distribution technology, then it is desirable to be able to limit delivery of the network-level multicast data packets to those hosts that have receiving users who are valid members of the application-level group.</t>
			<t>The anyone-can-send, anyone-can-receive nature of IP multicast <xref target="RFC1112"></xref> has resulted in restricted deployment of multicast distribution technology, since it is impossible to generate any revenue from services based on standard multicast.</t>
			<t>However, several pieces of the problem have received significant attention in recent years.  The problem of security and key management for application-level groups has been explored by the Multicast Security (MSEC) working group, and  a framework devised <xref target="RFC3740"></xref>.</t>
      <t>The use of AAA protocols (<xref target="RFC2865">RADIUS</xref>, <xref target="RFC3588">Diameter</xref>) to manage network-level access has been standardized.  These protocols (especially Diameter) can be extended to permit controlling access to application-level groups.</t>
      <t>The requirements for "well-managed" multicast have been stated in <xref target="I-D.ietf-mboned-maccnt-req"></xref>, and a framework for satisfying these requirements with the help of AAA functionality has been described in <xref target="I-D.ietf-mboned-multiaaa-framework"></xref>.</t>
      <t>Finally, work is under way on securing the network routing infrastructure <xref target="I-D.ietf-karp-threats-reqs"></xref> <xref target="I-D.ietf-karp-design-guide"></xref> <xref target="I-D.ietf-karp-framework"></xref> and the exchanges between adjacent multicast routers <xref target="I-D.ietf-pim-sm-linklocal"></xref>.</t>
      <t>However, one key piece is missing.  To minimize the resource wastage that would result from delivering multicast traffic to hosts that have no entitlement to receive them, it is necessary to authenticate and authorize receiving users and to correlate their right to access a group with the action of putting the data on that part of the network that is directly connected to the receiving host.</t>
      
		</section>
		<section title="Terminology">
			<t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED",
      "SHALL", "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and
      "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in <xref target="RFC2119">RFC 2119</xref>.  They indicate
      requirement levels for compliant PIM-SM implementations.</t>
		</section>
		
		<section title="Problem Statement">
        <section title="Authenticating and Authorizing Multicast Users">
        <t>The design of IP multicast <xref target="RFC1112"></xref> ensures that there is no relationship between the receiving hosts and the sending host(s) in a network-level multicast group.  Multicast sending hosts do not even know whether there are receiving hosts or not, much less who they are or whether they are entitled to receive the data.  The receiving host issues a network-level "join" on behalf of a receiving user, using IGMP (IPv4) <xref target="RFC3376"></xref> or MLD (IPv6) <xref target="RFC3810"></xref>, and a designated access router is responsible for grafting itself onto the data distribution tree.  The network exercises no control over this process---it is required to provide the data flow.</t>
        <t>Although specifications exist for encrypting the user data, thus ensuring that only legitimate users can decrypt these data, these specifications provide no way to ensure that the data distribution tree is not extended when a non-authorized receiving user makes a request to join the tree.  Thus, key management and receiving user access control have to be considered as separate problems.</t>
        <t>Given the lack of a relationship between the sending user(s) and the receiving user(s), it is difficult to create and enforce an appropriate business model.</t>
        </section>      
        <section title="Re-authentication and Re-authorization">
        <t>Several scenarios can cause a need for re-authentication and re-authorization:
        <list style="symbols">
									<t>When a user changes the group that he/she wishes to attach to;</t>
									<t>When a user changes the access router used for connection (e.g., wireless roaming);</t>
									<t>When a user changes the medium used for physical connectivity (e.g., cellular to wireless, etc.).</t>
								</list></t>        
        </section>
        <section title="Accounting">
        <t>The fact of delivery of group data needs to be recorded, to enable revenue to be earned.  This is only one of a range of accounting issues that may need to be addressed, which points to the need for a general solution.</t>        
        </section>
        <section title="Independence of Authentication and Authorization Procedures">
        <t>There is a wide range of authentication and authorization procedures that may be desired by an Internet Service Provider, including some that may not yet be standardized.  This implies the adoption of a very general framework for such procedures.</t>
        </section>
        <section title="Coupling of Network and Application Level Controls">
        <t>It is conceivable that a solution could be found for the above issues that would be based on standard network protocols and separate (proprietary or standard) group management protocols.  For example, the key management and distribution protocol associated with the application-level group could have authentication as one of its features.  However, the separation of the network-level controls from the application-level controls enables a significant class of security attacks.  It is therefore important that control of access to the network resources and control of access to the application-level resources be strongly coupled.</t>
                
        </section>
        <section title="Separation of Network Access Controls from Group Access Controls">
        <t>Access to the network is different from access to a group.  As an example, the authorization to watch a particular video presentation may be associated with a specific family member, while the authorization to use the network connection may be associated with an entire family (or to anyone present in the house).</t>
        <t>While existing AAA procedures are designed to control network level access, they must be extended (or alternatives found) if group access must be controlled.</t>        
        </section>
        </section>
        <section title="Proposed Solution">		
		<t>Two levels of action are apparent: the action of joining the network-level data distribution tree, and the action of joining the group, with its accompanying security properties.</t>
		<t>Joining the data distribution tree should not occur unless and until the receiving user has been authenticated and authorized.  One way to ensure that this relationship is enforced is to carry the receiving user authentication material in the network-level join packet.</t>
		<t>To support multiple types of authentication methods, the Extensible Authentication Protocol (EAP) <xref target="RFC3748"></xref> provides a standardized solution.</t>
		<t>To support a method-independent and efficient re-authentication, the EAP Re-Authentication Protocol (ERP) <xref target="RFC5296"></xref> provides a possible solution.  ERP is applicable for mobile receivers <xref target="MulticastMobile"></xref>.</t>
		<t>To permit correlating the join actions (at the group level and the network level) with the accounting procedures, the EAP/ERP packets that are delivered to the access router by the extended network-level join can be forwarded to the local AAA server for a decision, using existing AAA protocols, such as RADIUS or Diameter.  In keeping with the statement in <xref target="I-D.ietf-mboned-multiaaa-framework"></xref> that "A CP may delegate AAA responsibility to an NSP.", we observe that the NSP can distribute the responsibility among a collection of local AAA servers, and that there is sufficient generality in the AAA architectural model that a wide range of policies could be implemented, in support of a wide range of business models.</t>
		</section>
		<section title="Protocol Details">
        <t>Pending incorporation of the material into this document, readers are invited to access <xref target="MulticastReceiver">Islam, et al.</xref>.</t>		
		</section>
		
		<section title="Security Considerations">
			<t>TBD.</t>
			
		</section>
		<section title="IANA Considerations">
		<t>This document has no actions for IANA.</t>
		</section>
		<section title="Acknowledgements">
		<t></t>
		</section>
	</middle>
	<back>
		<references title="Normative References">
      &rfc1112;
      
      &rfc3810;

      &rfc3376;
      
      &rfc2119;

      &rfc2865;

      &rfc3588;

      &rfc3748;
      
     </references>
		<references title="Informative References">
    
      &rfc4601;
      
      &rfc3740;
      
      &rfc5296;
      
      &I-D.ietf-mboned-maccnt-req;

      &I-D.ietf-mboned-multiaaa-framework;
      
      &I-D.ietf-karp-threats-reqs;
      
      &I-D.ietf-karp-design-guide;

      &I-D.ietf-karp-framework;
      
      &I-D.ietf-pim-sm-linklocal;
      
      <reference anchor="MulticastReceiver">
					<front>
						<title>Multicast Receiver Access Control by IGMP-AC, Computer Networks, doi://10.1016/j.comnet.2008.12.005</title>
						<author fullname="Salekul Islam" initials="S." surname="Islam">
							<organization></organization>
						</author>
						<author fullname="J. William Atwood" initials="W." surname="Atwood">
							<organization></organization>
						</author>
						<date month="January" year="2009"></date>
					</front>
				</reference>
				<reference anchor="MulticastMobile">
					<front>
						<title>Receiver Access Control and Secured Handoff in Mobile Multicast using IGMP-AC, LCN 2008, pp. 411--418</title>
						<author fullname="Salekul Islam" initials="S." surname="Islam">
							<organization></organization>
						</author>
						<author fullname="J. William Atwood" initials="W." surname="Atwood" >
							<organization></organization>
						</author>
						<date month="November" year="2008" ></date>
					</front>
				</reference>
    
    
      
   </references>
	</back>
</rfc>
