<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
    <!ENTITY RFC2119 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
    <!ENTITY RFC4271 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4271.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.ietf-grow-mrt SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-grow-mrt.xml">
]>


<rfc category="std" ipr='trust200902' docName='draft-ietf-grow-geomrt-05.txt'>

<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc iprnotified="no" ?>
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>

<front>
	
    <title abbrev='Geo-Location extensions in MRT'>Multi-threaded
   Routing Toolkit (MRT) Border Gateway Protocol (BGP) routing information export format with geo-location extensions</title>
    <author initials="T" surname="Manderson" fullname="Terry Manderson">
	 	<organization abbrev="">ICANN</organization>
		<address><email>terry.manderson@icann.org</email></address>
    </author>
    
    <date year="2011" month="August" />
    <area>Operations</area>
    <workgroup>Global Routing Operations Working Group</workgroup>
    <abstract>
    <t>This document updates the  Multi-threaded
   Routing Toolkit (MRT) export format for Border Gateway Protocol (BGP) routing 
    	information by extending it to include optional terrestrial coordinates of a BGP Collector and its BGP Peers.
	</t>
    </abstract>
</front>


<middle>

<section title="Requirements notation">
  <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL",
  "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY",
  and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as
  described in <xref target="RFC2119"/>.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="intro" title="Introduction">


<t>Researchers and engineers often wish to analyze network behavior by
studying routing protocol transactions and routing information base
snapshots in relation to geographical topologies. Usually the <xref target="RFC4271">Border Gateway Protocol</xref> 
is the subject of study and the analysis can be significantly aided 
by the availability and extension of the <xref target="I-D.ietf-grow-mrt">"Multi-threaded Routing Toolkit (MRT) format"</xref>. 
The MRT format was originally defined in the 
   <xref target="MRT-GUIDE">Multi-threaded Routing Toolkit Programmer's Guide</xref>.
</t>

<t>The addition of geo-location coordinates (longitude and latitude) pertaining to the geographical location of both the BGP collector and 
	its BGP peers to BGP export data enables a researcher or enquiring individual to gain a 
		tererestrial insight to the routes seen by a BGP speaker. Such data may ultimately aide reserachers in understanding any disparity
		between the geographical location of networks and the topological location of networks in addition to the relationships between 
		geographical position and routing anomolies. Such insight could provide future input into network design or network security.</t>
	

<t>
	This memo documents an optional extension to the <xref target="I-D.ietf-grow-mrt">"MRT format"</xref> and introduces an 
	additional definition of a MRT subtype field that includes the terestrial coordinates of a BGP Collector and its BGP Peers.
</t>
	
	
</section>

<section title="Definitions">
<t>Coordinates: A set of geographic latitude and longitude specifying a location on the Earth.</t>
<t>BGP Speaker: A network device which exchanges network routing information using BGP.</t>
<t>Geo-location: Assigning a set of coordinates to a specific artifact, in this case a BGP speaker.</t>
<t>BGP Collector: A BGP speaker (usually passive) that stores and archives BGP routing data from active BGP peers for analysis.</t>
<t>BGP Peer: Either an internal or external <xref target="RFC4271">BGP peer</xref>.</t>
<t>Not A Number (NAN): numeric data type representing an undefined or unrepresentable value. 
	As defined in <xref target="IEEE754">IEEE Standard for Floating-Point Arithmetic</xref>.</t>

</section>

<section title="Geo-location aware MRT Routing Information Subtype">
	

<t>An additional subtype (GEO_PEER_TABLE) is defined for the TABLE_DUMP_v2 format, extending TABLE_DUMP_V2 Type.
</t>

<section title="GEO_PEER_TABLE">

<t>The GEO_PEER_TABLE Subtype updates the TABLE_DUMP_v2 Types to include 
	Geo-location information in the form of <xref target="WGS-84">WGS84</xref> formatted coordinates.</t>
	
	
	<t>The document adds the 7th subtype number and name below. The first 6 subtypes are defined by the 
		<xref target="I-D.ietf-grow-mrt">"MRT format"</xref>.</t>

<figure><artwork>
Subtype Number       Subtype Name
----------------------------------
    7               GEO_PEER_TABLE
</artwork></figure>

<t>The GEO_PEER_TABLE MRT record provides the BGP ID of the
collector, its latitude and longitude in <xref target="WGS-84">WGS84</xref> format,
and a list of indexed peers and their respective latitudes and longitudes in <xref target="WGS-84">WGS84</xref> format. 
</t>

<t>The format and function of the Collector BGP ID, 
Peer Count are as defined by the <xref target="I-D.ietf-grow-mrt">TABLE_DUMP_V2 PEER_INDEX_TABLE format.</xref>.</t>

<t>The Collector Latitude and Collector Longitude are the geographical coordinates of 
	the collector in <xref target="WGS-84">WGS84</xref> datum decimal degrees format stored as a single precision float 
	in the 32 bits allocated to the Collector Latitude and Collector Longitude. The latitude and longitude MAY be a <xref target="IEEE754">Not A Number (NAN)</xref> 
for situations where the geo-location of the collector is considered private. The Collector Latitude and Collector Longitude MUST NOT 
be a mix of <xref target="WGS-84">WGS84</xref> datum coordinate and NAN values.
</t>

<figure title="Format of the GEO_PEER_TABLE"><artwork>
 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                      Collector BGP ID                         |      
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                      Collector Latitude                       |      
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                      Collector Longitude                      |      
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|          Peer Count           |  Peer entries (variable)
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+

</artwork></figure>


<t>The format of the peer entries is shown below.  The Peer Type and the Peer BGP ID is as defined in
	the <xref target="I-D.ietf-grow-mrt">TABLE_DUMP_V2 MRT</xref> PEER_INDEX_TABLE format. The order of the Peer 
		entries in GEO_PEER_TABLE MUST match the order and number as existing in the PEER_INDEX_TABLE.
</t> 


<figure title="Format of peer entries"><artwork>
 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|   Peer Type   |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                         Peer BGP ID                           |      
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                         Peer Latitude                         |      
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                         Peer Longitude                        |      
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+

</artwork></figure>



<t>The Peer Latitude and Peer Longitude are the geographical coordinates of 
	the peer in <xref target="WGS-84">WGS84</xref> datum decimal degrees format stored as a single precision float 
	in the 32 bits allocated to the Peer Latitude and Peer Longitude. The latitude and longitude MAY be a <xref target="IEEE754">Not A Number (NAN)</xref>
for situations where the geo-location of the peer is considered private. The Peer Latitude and Peer Longitude MUST NOT 
be a mix of <xref target="WGS-84">WGS84</xref> datum coordinate and NAN values for a single Peer.
</t>
</section>

<section title="GEO_PEER_TABLE and peer entry values.">
<t>Collector BGP ID: Defined in <xref target="I-D.ietf-grow-mrt">the MRT format</xref></t>
<t>Collector Latitude: Geographic latitude of the BGP collector in <xref target="WGS-84">WGS84</xref> 
datum decimal degrees format stored as a single precision float.</t>
<t>Collector Longitude: Geographic Longitude of the BGP collector in <xref target="WGS-84">WGS84</xref> 
datum decimal degrees format stored as a single precision float.</t>
<t>Peer Count: Defined in <xref target="I-D.ietf-grow-mrt">the MRT format</xref></t>
<t>Peer entries: Defined in <xref target="I-D.ietf-grow-mrt">the MRT format</xref></t>
<t>Peer Type: Defined in <xref target="I-D.ietf-grow-mrt">the MRT format</xref></t>
<t>Peer BGP ID: Defined in <xref target="I-D.ietf-grow-mrt">the MRT format</xref></t>
<t>Peer Latitude: Geographic latitude of the BGP peer in <xref target="WGS-84">WGS84</xref> 
datum decimal degrees format stored as a single precision float.</t>
<t>Peer Longitude: Geographic Longitude of the BGP peer in <xref target="WGS-84">WGS84</xref> 
datum decimal degrees format stored as a single precision float.</t>
</section>



</section>

<section title="BGP Collector Construction">
<t>This section is to aide the reader in understanding the function of a BGP collector.</t>

<t>The BGP Collector is a device (hardware or software based) which speaks the Border Gateway Protocol 
	and its intended function is to store (and archive) the BGP routing data it receives from other 
	BGP speakers it has peering relationships with, providing data for later analysis. The general nature of a BGP 
	Collector is that it is a passive device in that it listens to route updates, and does not announce 
	nor propagate any information it knows or receives. It should be noted that this is not always the case, network 
	operators sometimes enable the collection of BGP routing data on active BGP speakers to obtain a situational view of the 
	routing system as they see it at a particular point in time.</t>

<t>As a fully fledged BGP speaker the BGP Collector can fit into any BGP topology including iBGP, eBGP, and so on. The implementation 
	of a BGP collector in a network topology is therefore limited by that network's use of BGP.</t>
</section>

<section title="Privacy Considerations">
<t>
The GEOPRIV [RFC6280] architecture requires that privacy rules attached to a location object be transmitted 
alongside the location information in the object. If a BGP Collector adds location coordinates to an MRT 
record based on GEOPRIV location objects, then it would have to include privacy rules as well. Since the 
MRT geo-location format does not support the the provision of privacy rules, each location entry in an MRT object 
is assigned the following default privacy rules [RFC4119]:
</t>

<figure><artwork>
-- retransmission-allowed: True
-- retention-expires: 100 years from timestamp of the MRT object
-- ruleset-reference: Empty
-- note-well: Empty
</artwork></figure>

<t>Location information derived from a location object with more restrictive 
privacy rules MUST NOT be included in a MRT geo-location record unless there 
are non-technical measures in place that enforce and communicate the constraints 
on the use of the location information in the MRT geo-location format (e.g., contractual 
agreements between peers).</t>
</section>

<section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">
	<t>Thanks to Andrew Clark, Ernest Foo, Dave Meyer, Larry Bluck, Richard Barnes, and Jeffrey Haas for reviewing this document.</t>
      <t>This document describes a small portion of the research towards the author's Ph.D.</t>
</section>

<section title="IANA Considerations">

<t>This section requests the Internet Assigned Numbers
Authority (IANA) register the additional Subtype code value as:</t>


<figure><artwork>
    7    GEO_PEER_TABLE
</artwork></figure>

<t>in the <xref target="I-D.ietf-grow-mrt">"MRT format"</xref> and Subtype code 
values related to the TABLE_DUMP_v2 type in the MRT 
namespace.</t>


</section>


<section title="Security Considerations">
<t>This extension to the <xref target="I-D.ietf-grow-mrt">"MRT format"</xref> defines fields that are of
a descriptive nature and provide information that is useful in
the analysis of routing systems. As such, the author believes that they do not 
constitute an additional network based security risk. It is recommended that the operators of the BGP collector and BGP peers consider their
own privacy and security concerns before supplying geographical coordinates to BGP data collection systems. Special attention should
be given to the physical security of an organisation before supplying geographical coordinates, especially if the resulting BGP data 
with geo-location extensions is made public.</t>

<t>Entities that operate BGP Collectors, and users of data provided by BGP Collectors, should be aware that the geolocation 
	data supplied by a peer can only be taken at face value. It is possible that a BGP peer may supply coordinates that is purposefully 
	misleading or inaccurate. It is therefore up to the BGP Collector to include this information or not, or use its own methods to either trust or 
	validate the data provided. It is not recommended that a BGP Collector use geographical coordinates not supplied by a BGP peer.</t>
</section>




</middle>



<back>
  <references title="Normative References">
 
    &RFC2119;
    &RFC4271;	
    &I-D.ietf-grow-mrt;
    
  </references>
  <references title="Informative References">
  	
  <reference anchor="WGS-84" target="http://earth-info.nga.mil/GandG/publications/tr8350.2/wgs84fin.pdf">
      <front>
      <title>World Geodetic System 1984</title>
      <author initials="DoD" surname="Geodesy and Geophysics Department" fullname="Geodesy and Geophysics Department">
	<organization abbrev="NIMA">National Imagery and Mapping Agency</organization>
	<address><email>GandG@nima.mil</email></address>
      </author>
      <date month="January" year="2000" />
      </front>
      <format type="HTML" target="http://earth-info.nga.mil/GandG/publications/tr8350.2/wgs84fin.pdf" />
  </reference>
  	
  <reference anchor="MRT-GUIDE" target="http://www.merit.edu/networkresearch/mrtprogrammer.pdf">
      <front>
      <title>MRT Programmer's Guide</title>
      <author initials="C" surname="Labovitz" fullname="Craig Labovitz">
	<organization abbrev="">Arbor Networks</organization>
	<address><email>labovit@arbor.net</email></address>
      </author>
      <date month="November" year="1999" />
      </front>
      <format type="HTML" target="http://www.merit.edu/networkresearch/mrtprogrammer.pdf" />
  </reference>
  
  <reference anchor="IEEE754" target="http://ieeexplore.ieee.org/servlet/opac?punumber=4610933">
      <front>
      <title>IEEE Standard for Floating-Point Arithmetic</title>
      <author fullname="Institute of Electrical and Electronics Engineers (IEEE)">
	<organization abbrev="">IEEE</organization>
      </author>
      <date month="August" year="2008" />
      </front>
      <format type="HTML" target="http://ieeexplore.ieee.org/servlet/opac?punumber=4610933" />
  </reference>
  </references>
</back>
</rfc>
