<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?rfc linefile="1:draft-ietf-dnsop-as112-ops-09.xml"?>
<!-- automatically generated by xml2rfc v1.35 on 2011-05-11T15:28:12Z -->
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
  <!--
--><!-- xml2rfc-processed-entity rfc1034 -->
  <!--
--><!-- xml2rfc-processed-entity rfc1876 -->
  <!--
--><!-- xml2rfc-processed-entity rfc1918 -->
  <!--
--><!-- xml2rfc-processed-entity rfc2870 -->
  <!--
--><!-- xml2rfc-processed-entity rfc4033 -->
  <!--
--><!-- xml2rfc-processed-entity rfc4271 -->
  <!--
--><!-- xml2rfc-processed-entity rfc4786 -->
  <!--
--><!-- xml2rfc-processed-entity rfc5735 -->
  <!--
--><!-- xml2rfc-processed-entity rfc5855 -->
  <!--
--><!-- xml2rfc-processed-entity draft-ietf-dnsop-default-local-zones -->
  <!--
--><!-- xml2rfc-processed-entity draft-ietf-dnsop-as112-under-attack-help-help -->
]>

<rfc category="info" ipr="pre5378Trust200902"
  docName="draft-ietf-dnsop-as112-ops-09">

<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc iprnotified="no" ?>
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>

  <front>
    <title>AS112 Nameserver Operations</title>

    <author initials='J.' surname="Abley" fullname='Joe Abley'>
      <organization>ICANN</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>4676 Admiralty Way, Suite 330</street>
          <city>Marina del Rey</city>
          <region>CA</region>
          <code>90292</code>
          <country>US</country>
        </postal>
        <phone>+1 519 670 9327</phone>
        <email>joe.abley@icann.org</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author initials='W.' surname="Maton" fullname='William F. Maton Sotomayor'>
      <organization abbrev="NRC-CNRC">National Research Council
        of Canada</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>1200 Montreal Road</street>
          <city>Ottawa</city>
          <region>ON</region>
          <code>K1A 0R6</code>
          <country>Canada</country>
        </postal>
        <phone>+1 613 993 0880</phone>
        <email>wmaton@ryouko.imsb.nrc.ca</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date day="11" month="May" year="2011"/>

    <abstract>
      <t>Many sites connected to the Internet make use of IPv4 addresses
        that are not globally-unique.  Examples are the addresses
        designated in RFC 1918 for private use within individual
        sites.</t>

      <t>Devices in such environments may occasionally originate
        Domain Name System (DNS) queries (so-called "reverse lookups")
        corresponding to those private-use addresses. Since the
        addresses concerned have only local significance, it is good
        practice for site administrators to ensure that such queries are
        answered locally. However, it is not uncommon for such queries
        to follow the normal delegation path in the public DNS instead
        of being answered within the site.</t>

      <t>It is not possible for public DNS servers to give
	useful answers to such queries. In addition, due to the
	wide deployment of private-use addresses and the continuing
	growth of the Internet, the volume of such queries is large
	and growing.  The AS112 project aims to provide a distributed
	sink for such queries in order to reduce the load on the
	IN-ADDR.ARPA authoritative servers.  The AS112 project is
	named after the Autonomous System Number (ASN) that was
	assigned to it.</t>

      <t>This document describes the steps required to install
        a new AS112 node, and offers advice relating to such a node's
        operation.</t>
  </abstract>
</front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>Many sites connected to the Internet make use of IPv4
        addresses that are not globally unique.  Examples are the
        addresses designated in <xref target="RFC1918"/> for private
        use within individual sites.</t>
        
      <t>Devices in such environments may occasionally originate
	Domain Name System (DNS) <xref target="RFC1034"/>
        queries (so-called "reverse lookups") corresponding
	to those private-use addresses. Since the addresses concerned
	have only local significance, it is good practice for site
	administrators to ensure that such queries are answered locally
        <xref target="I-D.ietf-dnsop-default-local-zones"/>.
	However, it is not uncommon for such queries to follow the
	normal delegation path in the public DNS instead of being
	answered within the site.</t>

      <t>It is not possible for public DNS servers to give
	useful answers to such queries. In addition, due to the
	wide deployment of private-use addresses and the continuing
	growth of the Internet, the volume of such queries is large
	and growing. The AS112 project aims to provide a distributed
	sink for such queries in order to reduce the load on the
	<xref target="RFC5855">IN-ADDR.ARPA authoritative servers</xref>.</t>

      <t>The AS112 project encompasses a loosely coordinated
	collection of independently operated nameservers. Each
	nameserver functions as a single node in an AS112 <xref
	target="RFC4786">anycast cloud</xref>, and
	is configured to answer authoritatively for a particular
	set of nominated zones.</t>

      <t>The AS112 project is named after the Autonomous System
        Number (ASN) that was assigned to it.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="AS112 DNS Service">
      <section title="Zones" anchor="zones">
        <t>AS112 nameservers answer authoritatively for the following
          zones, corresponding to <xref target="RFC1918"/> private-use
          netblocks:
  
          <list style="symbols">
            <t>10.IN-ADDR.ARPA</t>
            <t>16.172.IN-ADDR.ARPA, 17.172.IN-ADDR.ARPA, ...,
              31.172.IN-ADDR.ARPA</t>
            <t>168.192.IN-ADDR.ARPA</t>
          </list>

          and the following zone, corresponding to the "link local"
          netblock 169.254.0.0/16 listed in <xref target="RFC5735"/>:

          <list style="symbols">
            <t>254.169.IN-ADDR.ARPA</t>
          </list>
        </t>

        <t>To aid identification of AS112 anycast nodes, each
	  node also answers authoritatively for the zone
	  HOSTNAME.AS112.NET.</t>

	<t>See <xref target="dns"/> for the recommended contents
	  of all these zones.</t>

	<t>It is possible that other zones corresponding to private-use
	  infrastructure will be delegated to AS112 servers in the
	  future. A list of zones for which AS112 servers answer
	  authoritatively is maintained at <eref
	  target="http://www.as112.net/"/>.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Nameservers" anchor="nameservers">
        <t>The zones listed in <xref target="zones"/> are delegated to
	  the two nameservers BLACKHOLE-1.IANA.ORG (192.175.48.6)
	  and BLACKHOLE-2.IANA.ORG (192.175.48.42).</t>

        <t>Additionally, the server PRISONER.IANA.ORG (192.175.48.1)
	  is listed in the MNAME field of the SOA records of the
	  IN-ADDR.ARPA zones served by AS112 nameservers.
	  PRISONER.IANA.ORG receives mainly dynamic update queries.</t>

	<t>The addresses of all these nameservers are covered by
	  the single IPv4 prefix 192.175.48.0/24.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Installation of a New Node">
      <section title="Useful Background Knowledge">
	<t>Installation of an AS112 node is relatively straightforward.
	  However, experience in the following general areas may
	  prove useful:

          <list style="symbols">
	    <t>inter-domain routing with <xref
	      target="RFC4271">BGP</xref>;</t>

            <t>DNS authoritative server operations;</t>

	    <t><xref target="RFC4786">anycast</xref> distribution
	      of DNS services.</t>
	  </list>
	</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Topological Location">
	<t>AS112 nodes may be located anywhere on the Internet. For
	  nodes that are intended to provide a public service to
	  the Internet community (as opposed to private use), it
	  may well be advantageous to choose a location that is
	  easily (and cheaply) reachable by multiple providers,
	  such as an Internet exchange point.</t>

        <t>AS112 nodes may advertise their service prefix to BGP
          peers for local use (analogous to a conventional peering
          relationship between two providers) or for global use
          (analogous to a customer relationship with one or more
          providers).</t>

        <t>It is good operational practice to notify the community
          of users that may fall within the reach of a new AS112 node
          before it is installed. At an Internet Exchange, local
          mailing lists usually exist to facilitate such announcements.
          For nodes that are intended to be globally reachable,
          coordination with other AS112 operators is highly recommended.
          See also <xref target="communications"/>.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Operating System and Host Considerations">
        <t>Examples in this document are based on UNIX and UNIX-like
          operating systems, but other operating systems exist which
          are suitable for use in construction of an AS112 node.</t>

        <t>The chosen platform should include support for either
          cloned loopback interfaces, or the capability to bind
	  multiple addresses to a single loopback interface. The
	  addresses of the nameservers listed in <xref
	  target="nameservers"/> will be configured on these
	  interfaces in order that the DNS software can respond to
	  queries properly.</t>

        <t>A host that is configured to act as an AS112 anycast
          node should be dedicated to that purpose, and should not be
          used to simultaneously provide other services. This guidance
          is provided due to the unpredictable (and occasionally high)
          traffic levels that AS112 nodes have been seen to attract.</t>

        <t>System startup scripts should be arranged such that the
          various AS112-related components start automatically following
          a system reboot. The order in which interfaces are configured
          and software components started should be arranged such that
          routing software startup follows DNS software startup, and
          DNS software startup follows loopback interface configuration.</t>

        <t>Wrapper scripts or other arrangements should be employed to
          ensure that the anycast service prefix for AS112 is not advertised
          while either the anycast addresses are not configured, or while
          the DNS software is not running.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Routing Software">
        <t>AS112 nodes signal the availability of AS112 nameservers
          to the Internet using <xref target="RFC4271">BGP</xref>:
          each AS112 node is a BGP speaker, and announces the prefix
          192.175.48.0/24 to the Internet with origin AS 112 (see also
          <xref target="nameservers"/>).</t>

        <t>The examples in this document are based on the
	  <eref target="http://www.quagga.net/">Quagga Routing
	  Suite</eref> running on Linux, but other software packages
	  exist which also provide suitable BGP support for AS112
	  nodes.</t>

	<t>The "bgpd.conf" file is used by Quagga's bgpd daemon, which
	  provides BGP protocol support. The router id in this example
	  is 203.0.113.1; the AS112 node peers with external
	  peers 192.0.2.1 and 192.0.2.2.  Note the local AS number
	  112, and the origination of the prefix 192.175.48.0/24.</t>

        <figure>
          <artwork>
! bgpd.conf
!
hostname as112-bgpd
password &lt;something&gt;
enable password &lt;supersomething&gt;
!
! Note that all AS112 nodes use the local Autonomous System
! Number 112, and originate the IPv4 prefix 192.175.48.0/24.
! All other addresses shown below are illustrative, and
! actual numbers will depend on local circumstances.
!
router bgp 112
 bgp router-id 203.0.113.1
 network 192.175.48.0
 neighbor 192.0.2.1 remote-as 64496
 neighbor 192.0.2.1 next-hop-self
 neighbor 192.0.2.2 remote-as 64497
 neighbor 192.0.2.2 next-hop-self
          </artwork>
        </figure>

	<t>The "zebra.conf" file is required to provide integration
	  between protocol daemons (bgpd, in this case) and the
	  kernel.</t>

        <figure>
          <artwork>
! zebra.conf
!
hostname as112
password &lt;something&gt;
enable password &lt;supersomething&gt;
!
interface lo
!
interface eth0
!
          </artwork>
        </figure>
      </section>

      <section title="DNS Software" anchor="dns">
        <t>Although the queries received by AS112 nodes are
          definitively misdirected, it is important that they be
	  answered in a manner that is accurate and consistent.
          For this reason AS112 nodes operate as <xref
          target="RFC1034">fully-functional
          and standards-compliant DNS authoritative servers</xref>,
          and hence require DNS software.</t>

        <t>Examples in this document are based on
	  <eref target="http://www.isc.org/software/BIND/">ISC
	  BIND9</eref>, but other DNS software exists which is
	  suitable for use in construction of an AS112 node.</t>

	<t>The following is a sample BIND9 "named.conf" file for a
	  dedicated AS112 server. Note that the nameserver is
	  configured to act as an authoritative-only server (i.e.
	  recursion is disabled).  The nameserver is also configured
	  to listen on the various AS112 anycast nameserver addresses,
	  as well as its local addresses.</t>

        <figure>
          <artwork>
// named.conf

// global options

options {
  listen-on {
    127.0.0.1;         // localhost

  // the following address is node-dependent, and should be set to
  // something appropriate for the new AS112 node

    203.0.113.1;       // local address (globally-unique, unicast)

  // the following addresses correspond to AS112 addresses, and
  // are the same for all AS112 nodes

    192.175.48.1;      // prisoner.iana.org (anycast)
    192.175.48.6;      // blackhole-1.iana.org (anycast)
    192.175.48.42;     // blackhole-2.iana.org (anycast)
  };
  directory "/var/named";
  recursion no;        // authoritative-only server
  query-source address *;
};

// log queries,  so that when people call us about unexpected
// answers to queries they didn't realise they had sent, we
// have something to talk about.  Note that activating this
// has the potential to create high CPU load and consume
// enormous amounts of disk space.

logging {
  channel "querylog" { 
    file "/var/log/query.log" versions 2 size 500m;
    print-time yes;
  };
  category queries { querylog; };
};

// RFC 1918

zone "10.in-addr.arpa" { type master; file "db.empty"; };
zone "16.172.in-addr.arpa" { type master; file "db.empty"; };
zone "17.172.in-addr.arpa" { type master; file "db.empty"; };
zone "18.172.in-addr.arpa" { type master; file "db.empty"; };
zone "19.172.in-addr.arpa" { type master; file "db.empty"; };
zone "20.172.in-addr.arpa" { type master; file "db.empty"; };
zone "21.172.in-addr.arpa" { type master; file "db.empty"; };
zone "22.172.in-addr.arpa" { type master; file "db.empty"; };
zone "23.172.in-addr.arpa" { type master; file "db.empty"; };
zone "24.172.in-addr.arpa" { type master; file "db.empty"; };
zone "25.172.in-addr.arpa" { type master; file "db.empty"; };
zone "26.172.in-addr.arpa" { type master; file "db.empty"; };
zone "27.172.in-addr.arpa" { type master; file "db.empty"; };
zone "28.172.in-addr.arpa" { type master; file "db.empty"; };
zone "29.172.in-addr.arpa" { type master; file "db.empty"; };
zone "30.172.in-addr.arpa" { type master; file "db.empty"; };
zone "31.172.in-addr.arpa" { type master; file "db.empty"; };
zone "168.192.in-addr.arpa" { type master; file "db.empty"; };

// RFC 5735

zone "254.169.in-addr.arpa" { type master; file "db.empty"; };

// also answer authoritatively for the HOSTNAME.AS112.NET zone,
// which contains data of operational relevance

zone "hostname.as112.net" {
  type master;
  file "db.hostname.as112.net";
};
          </artwork>
        </figure>

	<t>The "db.empty" file follows, below.  This is the source
	  data used to populate all the IN-ADDR.ARPA zones listed
	  in <xref target="zones"/>. Note that the RNAME specified
	  in the SOA record corresponds to hostmaster@root-servers.org,
	  a suitable e-mail address for receiving technical queries
	  about these zones.</t>

        <figure>
          <artwork>
; db.empty
;
; Empty zone for AS112 server.
;
$TTL    1W
@  IN  SOA  prisoner.iana.org. hostmaster.root-servers.org. (
                               1       ; serial number
                               1W      ; refresh
                               1M      ; retry
                               1W      ; expire
                               1W )    ; negative caching TTL
;
       NS     blackhole-1.iana.org.
       NS     blackhole-2.iana.org.
;
; There should be no other resource records included in this zone.
;
; Records that relate to RFC 1918-numbered resources within the
; site hosting this AS112 node should not be hosted on this
; nameserver.
          </artwork>
        </figure>

	<t>The "db.hostname.as112.net" file follows, below.
	  This zone contains various resource records that provide
	  operational data to users for troubleshooting or measurement
	  purposes, and should be edited to suit local circumstances.
	  Note that the response to the query "HOSTNAME.AS112.NET
	  IN TXT" should fit within a 512 octet DNS/UDP datagram:
	  i.e. it should be available over UDP transport without
	  requiring EDNS0 support.</t>

	<t>The optional <xref target="RFC1876">LOC record</xref>
	  included in the zone apex provides information about the
	  geospatial location of the node.</t>

        <figure>
          <artwork>
; db.hostname.as112.net
;
$TTL    1W
@       SOA     server.example.net. admin.example.net. (
                        1               ; serial number
                        1W              ; refresh
                        1M              ; retry
                        1W              ; expire
                        1W )            ; negative caching TTL
;
        NS      blackhole-2.iana.org.
        NS      blackhole-1.iana.org.
;
        TXT     "Name of Facility or similar" "City, Country"
        TXT     "See http://www.as112.net/ for more information."
;
        LOC     45 25 0.000 N 75 42 0.000 W 80.00m 1m 10000m 10m
          </artwork>
        </figure>
      </section>

      <section title="Testing a Newly-Installed Node">
	<t>The BIND9 tool "dig" can be used to retrieve the TXT
	  resource records associated with the domain "HOSTNAME.AS112.NET",
	  directed at one of the AS112 anycast nameserver addresses.
	  Continuing the example from above, the response received should
	  indicate the identity of the AS112 node that responded to the
	  query. See <xref target="dns"/> for more details about the
	  resource records associated with "HOSTNAME.AS112.NET".</t>

        <figure>
          <artwork>
    % dig @prisoner.iana.org hostname.as112.net txt +short +norec
    "Name of Facility or similar" "City, Country"
    "See http://www.as112.net/ for more information."
    %
          </artwork>
        </figure>

        <t>If the response received indicates a different node is being
          used, then there is probably a routing problem to solve. If
          there is no response received at all, there might be host
          or nameserver problem. Judicious use of tools such as
          traceroute, and consultation of BGP looking glasses might
          be useful in troubleshooting.</t>

        <t>Note that an appropriate set of tests for a new server will
          include queries sent from many different places within the
          expected service area of the node, using both UDP and TCP
          transport, and exercising all three AS112 anycast nameserver
          addresses.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Operations">
      <section title="Monitoring">
        <t>AS112 nodes should be monitored to ensure they are functioning
          correctly, just as with any other production service. An AS112
          node that stops answering queries correctly can cause failures
          and timeouts in unexpected places and can lead to failures in
          dependent systems that can be difficult to troubleshoot.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Downtime">
        <t>An AS112 node that needs to go off-line (e.g. for planned
          maintenance or as part of the diagnosis of some problem)
          should stop advertising the AS112 service prefix to its BGP
          peers. This can be done by shutting down the routing software
          on the node altogether or by causing the routing system to
          withdraw the route.</t>

        <t>Withdrawing the service prefix is important in order to avoid
          blackholing query traffic in the event that the DNS software on
          the node is not functioning normally.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Statistics and Measurement">
        <t>Use of the AS112 node should be measured in order to track
          long-term trends, identify anomalous conditions, and to ensure
          that the configuration of the AS112 node is sufficient to handle
          the query load.</t>

        <t>Examples of free monitoring tools that might be useful to
          operators of AS112 nodes include:

          <list style="symbols">
            <t><eref target="http://www.linux.it/~md/software/">bindgraph</eref></t>
            <t><eref target="http://dns.measurement-factory.com/tools/dnstop/">dnstop</eref></t>
            <t><eref target="http://dns.measurement-factory.com/tools/dsc/">DSC</eref></t>
          </list>
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Communications" anchor="communications">
      <t>It is good operational practice to notify the community
        of users that may fall within the reach of a new AS112 node
        before it is installed. At Internet Exchanges, local
        mailing lists usually exist to facilitate such announcements.</t>

      <t>For nodes that are intended to be globally reachable,
	coordination with other AS112 operators is especially
	recommended.  The mailing list <eref
	target="mailto:as112-ops@lists.dns-oarc.net"/> is operated
	for this purpose.</t>

      <t>Information pertinent to AS112 operations is maintained
        at <eref target="http://www.as112.net/"/>.</t>

      <t>Information about an AS112 node should also be published within
        the DNS, within the "HOSTNAME.AS112.NET" zone. See
        <xref target="dns"/> for more details.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="On the Future of AS112 Nodes">
      <t>It is recommended practice for the operators of recursive
	nameservers to answer queries for zones served by AS112
	nodes locally, such that queries never have an opportunity
	to reach AS112 servers <xref
	target="I-D.ietf-dnsop-default-local-zones"/>. Operational
	experience with AS112 nodes does not currently indicate an
	observable trend towards compliance with those recommendations,
	however.</t>

      <t>It is expected that some DNS software vendors will include
	default configuration that will implement measures such
	as those described in <xref
	target="I-D.ietf-dnsop-default-local-zones"/>.  If such
	software is widely deployed, it is reasonable to assume
	that the query load received by AS112 nodes will decrease;
	however, it is safe to assume that the query load will not
	decrease to zero, and consequently that AS112 nodes will
	continue to provide a useful service for the foreseeable
	future.</t>

      <t>There may be a requirement in the future for AS112 nodes to
        answer for their current set of zones over IPv6 transport.
        Such a requirement would necessitate the assignment of a
        corresponding IPv6 netblock for use as an anycast service
        prefix.</t>

      <t>There may be a requirement in the future for AS112 nodes
        to serve additional zones, or to stop serving particular
        zones that are currently served. Such changes would be
        widely announced in operational forums, and published
        at <eref target="http://www.as112.net/"/>.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>The AS112 nameservers are all named under the domain
        IANA.ORG (see <xref target="nameservers"/>). However,
        the anycast infrastructure itself is operated by a
        loosely-coordinated, diverse mix of organisations across
        the Internet, and is not an IANA function.</t>

      <t>The autonomous system number 112 and the IPv4 prefix
        192.175.48.0/24 were assigned by ARIN.</t>

      <t>This document makes no request of the IANA.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Security Considerations">
      <t>Hosts should never normally send queries to AS112 servers;
	queries relating to private-use addresses should be answered
	locally within a site. Hosts that send queries to AS112
	servers may well leak information relating to private
	infrastructure to the public network, and this could present
	a security risk. This risk is orthogonal to the presence
	or absence of authoritative servers for these zones in the
	public DNS infrastructure, however.</t>

      <t>Queries that are answered by AS112 servers are usually
	unintentional; it follows that the responses from AS112
	servers are usually unexpected. Unexpected inbound traffic
	can trigger intrusion detection systems or alerts by
	firewalls. Operators of AS112 servers should be prepared
	to be contacted by operators of remote infrastructure who
        believe their security has been violated. Advice to those
	who mistakenly believe that responses from AS112 nodes
	constitutes an attack on their infrastructure can be found
	in <xref
	target="I-D.ietf-dnsop-as112-under-attack-help-help"/>.</t>

      <t>The deployment of AS112 nodes is very loosely coordinated
	compared to other services distributed using anycast. The
	malicious compromise of an AS112 node and subversion of the
	data served by the node is hence more difficult to detect
	due to the lack of central management. Since it is conceivable
	that changing the responses to queries received by AS112
	nodes might influence the behaviour of the hosts sending
	the queries, such a compromise might be used as an attack
	vector against private infrastructure.</t>

      <t>Operators of AS112 should take appropriate measures to
        ensure that AS112 nodes are appropriately protected from
        compromise, such as would normally be employed for production
        nameserver or network infrastructure. The guidance provided
        for root nameservers in <xref target="RFC2870"/> may be
        instructive.</t>

      <t>The zones hosted by AS112 servers are not signed with
        DNSSEC <xref target="RFC4033"/>. Given the distributed
        and loosely-coordinated structure of the AS112 service,
        the zones concerned could only be signed if the private
        key material used was effectively public, obviating any
        security benefit resulting from the use of those keys.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Acknowledgements">
        <t>The authors wish to acknowledge the assistance of Bill
	  Manning, John Brown, Marco D'Itri, Daniele Arena, Stephane
	  Bortzmeyer, Frank Habicht, Chris Thompson, Peter Losher,
	  Peter Koch, Alfred Hoenes and S. Moonesamy in the preparation
	  of this document.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc linefile="1:http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1034.xml"?>

<reference anchor='RFC1034'>

<front>
<title abbrev='Domain Concepts and Facilities'>Domain names - concepts and facilities</title>
<author initials='P.' surname='Mockapetris' fullname='P. Mockapetris'>
<organization>Information Sciences Institute (ISI)</organization></author>
<date year='1987' day='1' month='November' /></front>

<seriesInfo name='STD' value='13' />
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='1034' />
<format type='TXT' octets='129180' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc1034.txt' />
</reference>
<?rfc linefile="690:draft-ietf-dnsop-as112-ops-09.xml"?>
      <?rfc linefile="1:http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1918.xml"?>

<reference anchor='RFC1918'>

<front>
<title>Address Allocation for Private Internets</title>
<author initials='Y.' surname='Rekhter' fullname='Yakov Rekhter'>
<organization>Cisco systems</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street>170 West Tasman Drive</street>
<city>San Jose</city>
<region>CA</region>
<code>95134-1706</code>
<country>US</country></postal>
<phone>+1 914 528 0090</phone>
<facsimile>+1 408 526 4952</facsimile>
<email>yakov@cisco.com</email></address></author>
<author initials='R.' surname='Moskowitz' fullname='Robert G. Moskowitz'>
<organization>Chrysler Corporation</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street>25999 Lawrence Ave</street>
<city>Center Line</city>
<region>MI</region>
<code>48015</code>
<country>US</country></postal>
<phone>+1 810 758 8212</phone>
<facsimile>+1 810 758 8173</facsimile>
<email>rgm3@is.chrysler.com</email></address></author>
<author initials='D.' surname='Karrenberg' fullname='Daniel Karrenberg'>
<organization>RIPE Network Coordination Centre</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street>Kruislaan 409</street>
<city>Amsterdam</city>
<region />
<code>1098 SJ</code>
<country>NL</country></postal>
<phone>+31 20 5925065</phone>
<facsimile>+31 20 5925090</facsimile>
<email>Daniel.Karrenberg@ripe.net</email></address></author>
<author initials='G.' surname='Groot' fullname='Geert Jan de Groot'>
<organization>RIPE Network Coordination Centre</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street>Kruislaan 409</street>
<city>Amsterdam</city>
<region />
<code>1098 SJ</code>
<country>NL</country></postal>
<phone>+31 20 5925065</phone>
<facsimile>+31 20 5925090</facsimile>
<email>GeertJan.deGroot@ripe.net</email></address></author>
<author initials='E.' surname='Lear' fullname='Eliot Lear'>
<organization>Silicon Graphics, Inc.</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street>2011 N. Shoreline Blvd.</street>
<street>Mail Stop 15-730</street>
<city>Mountain View</city>
<region>CA</region>
<code>94043-1389</code>
<country>US</country></postal>
<phone>+1 415 960 1980</phone>
<facsimile>+1 415 961 9584</facsimile>
<email>lear@sgi.com</email></address></author>
<date year='1996' month='February' /></front>

<seriesInfo name='BCP' value='5' />
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='1918' />
<format type='TXT' octets='22270' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc1918.txt' />
</reference>
<?rfc linefile="691:draft-ietf-dnsop-as112-ops-09.xml"?>
      <?rfc linefile="1:http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2870.xml"?>

<reference anchor='RFC2870'>

<front>
<title>Root Name Server Operational Requirements</title>
<author initials='R.' surname='Bush' fullname='R. Bush'>
<organization /></author>
<author initials='D.' surname='Karrenberg' fullname='D. Karrenberg'>
<organization /></author>
<author initials='M.' surname='Kosters' fullname='M. Kosters'>
<organization /></author>
<author initials='R.' surname='Plzak' fullname='R. Plzak'>
<organization /></author>
<date year='2000' month='June' />
<abstract>
<t>The primary focus of this document is to provide guidelines for operation of the root name servers.  This document specifies an Internet Best Current Practices for the Internet Community, and requests discussion and suggestions for improvements.</t></abstract></front>

<seriesInfo name='BCP' value='40' />
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='2870' />
<format type='TXT' octets='21133' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc2870.txt' />
</reference>
<?rfc linefile="692:draft-ietf-dnsop-as112-ops-09.xml"?>
      <?rfc linefile="1:http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4033.xml"?>

<reference anchor='RFC4033'>

<front>
<title>DNS Security Introduction and Requirements</title>
<author initials='R.' surname='Arends' fullname='R. Arends'>
<organization /></author>
<author initials='R.' surname='Austein' fullname='R. Austein'>
<organization /></author>
<author initials='M.' surname='Larson' fullname='M. Larson'>
<organization /></author>
<author initials='D.' surname='Massey' fullname='D. Massey'>
<organization /></author>
<author initials='S.' surname='Rose' fullname='S. Rose'>
<organization /></author>
<date year='2005' month='March' />
<abstract>
<t>The Domain Name System Security Extensions (DNSSEC) add data origin authentication and data integrity to the Domain Name System.  This document introduces these extensions and describes their capabilities and limitations.  This document also discusses the services that the DNS security extensions do and do not provide.  Last, this document describes the interrelationships between the documents that collectively describe DNSSEC. [STANDARDS-TRACK]</t></abstract></front>

<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='4033' />
<format type='TXT' octets='52445' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc4033.txt' />
</reference>
<?rfc linefile="693:draft-ietf-dnsop-as112-ops-09.xml"?>
      <?rfc linefile="1:http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4271.xml"?>

<reference anchor='RFC4271'>

<front>
<title>A Border Gateway Protocol 4 (BGP-4)</title>
<author initials='Y.' surname='Rekhter' fullname='Y. Rekhter'>
<organization /></author>
<author initials='T.' surname='Li' fullname='T. Li'>
<organization /></author>
<author initials='S.' surname='Hares' fullname='S. Hares'>
<organization /></author>
<date year='2006' month='January' />
<abstract>
<t>This document discusses the Border Gateway Protocol (BGP), which is an inter-Autonomous System routing protocol.&lt;/t>&lt;t> The primary function of a BGP speaking system is to exchange network reachability information with other BGP systems. This network reachability information includes information on the list of Autonomous Systems (ASes) that reachability information traverses. This information is sufficient for constructing a graph of AS connectivity for this reachability from which routing loops may be pruned, and, at the AS level, some policy decisions may be enforced.&lt;/t>&lt;t> BGP-4 provides a set of mechanisms for supporting Classless Inter-Domain Routing (CIDR). These mechanisms include support for advertising a set of destinations as an IP prefix, and eliminating the concept of network "class" within BGP. BGP-4 also introduces mechanisms that allow aggregation of routes, including aggregation of AS paths.&lt;/t>&lt;t> This document obsoletes RFC 1771. [STANDARDS-TRACK]</t></abstract></front>

<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='4271' />
<format type='TXT' octets='222702' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc4271.txt' />
</reference>
<?rfc linefile="694:draft-ietf-dnsop-as112-ops-09.xml"?>
      <?rfc linefile="1:http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4786.xml"?>

<reference anchor='RFC4786'>

<front>
<title>Operation of Anycast Services</title>
<author initials='J.' surname='Abley' fullname='J. Abley'>
<organization /></author>
<author initials='K.' surname='Lindqvist' fullname='K. Lindqvist'>
<organization /></author>
<date year='2006' month='December' />
<abstract>
<t>As the Internet has grown, and as systems and networked services within enterprises have become more pervasive, many services with high availability requirements have emerged. These requirements have increased the demands on the reliability of the infrastructure on which those services rely.&lt;/t>&lt;t> Various techniques have been employed to increase the availability of services deployed on the Internet. This document presents commentary and recommendations for distribution of services using anycast. This document specifies an Internet Best Current Practices for the Internet Community, and requests discussion and suggestions for improvements.</t></abstract></front>

<seriesInfo name='BCP' value='126' />
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='4786' />
<format type='TXT' octets='56818' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc4786.txt' />
</reference>
<?rfc linefile="695:draft-ietf-dnsop-as112-ops-09.xml"?>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <?rfc linefile="1:http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1876.xml"?>

<reference anchor='RFC1876'>

<front>
<title abbrev='Location Information in the DNS'>A Means for Expressing Location Information in the Domain Name System</title>
<author initials='C.' surname='Davis' fullname='Christopher Davis'>
<organization>Kapor Enterprises, Inc.</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street>238 Main Street</street>
<street>Suite 400</street>
<city>Cambridge</city>
<region>MA</region>
<code>02142</code>
<country>US</country></postal>
<phone>+1 617 576 4532</phone>
<email>ckd@kei.com</email></address></author>
<author initials='P.' surname='Vixie' fullname='Paul Vixie'>
<organization>Vixie Enterprises</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street>Star Route Box 159A</street>
<city>Woodside</city>
<region>CA</region>
<code>94062</code>
<country>US</country></postal>
<phone>+1 415 747 0204</phone>
<email>paul@vix.com</email></address></author>
<author initials='T.' surname='Goodwin' fullname='Tim Goodwin'>
<organization>Public IP Exchange Ltd (PIPEX)</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street>216 The Science Park</street>
<city>Cambridge</city>
<region>England</region>
<code>CB4 4WA</code>
<country>UK</country></postal>
<phone>+44 1223 250250</phone>
<email>tim@pipex.net</email></address></author>
<author initials='I.' surname='Dickinson' fullname='Ian Dickinson'>
<organization>FORE Systems</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street>2475 The Crescent</street>
<street>Solihull Parkway</street>
<city>Birmingham Business Park</city>
<region>England</region>
<code>B37 7YE</code>
<country>UK</country></postal>
<phone>+44 121 7174444</phone>
<email>idickins@fore.co.uk</email></address></author>
<date year='1996' month='January' />
<abstract>
<t>This memo defines a new DNS RR type for experimental purposes.  This RFC describes a mechanism to allow the DNS to carry location information about hosts, networks, and subnets.  Such information for a small subset of hosts is currently contained in the flat-file UUCP maps.  However, just as the DNS replaced the use of HOSTS.TXT to carry host and network address information, it is possible to replace the UUCP maps as carriers of location information.</t>
<t>This RFC defines the format of a new Resource Record (RR) for the Domain Name System (DNS), and reserves a corresponding DNS type mnemonic (LOC) and numerical code (29).</t>
<t>This RFC assumes that the reader is familiar with the DNS,.  The data shown in our examples is for pedagogical use and does not necessarily reflect the real Internet.</t></abstract></front>

<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='1876' />
<format type='TXT' octets='29631' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc1876.txt' />
</reference>
<?rfc linefile="699:draft-ietf-dnsop-as112-ops-09.xml"?>
      <?rfc linefile="1:http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5735.xml"?>

<reference anchor='RFC5735'>

<front>
<title>Special Use IPv4 Addresses</title>
<author initials='M.' surname='Cotton' fullname='M. Cotton'>
<organization /></author>
<author initials='L.' surname='Vegoda' fullname='L. Vegoda'>
<organization /></author>
<date year='2010' month='January' />
<abstract>
<t>This document obsoletes RFC 3330.  It describes the global and other specialized IPv4 address blocks that have been assigned by the Internet Assigned Numbers Authority (IANA).  It does not address IPv4 address space assigned to operators and users through the Regional Internet Registries, nor does it address IPv4 address space assigned directly by IANA prior to the creation of the Regional Internet Registries.  It also does not address allocations or assignments of IPv6 addresses or autonomous system numbers.  This memo documents an Internet Best Current Practice.</t></abstract></front>

<seriesInfo name='BCP' value='153' />
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='5735' />
<format type='TXT' octets='20369' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc5735.txt' />
</reference>
<?rfc linefile="700:draft-ietf-dnsop-as112-ops-09.xml"?>
      <?rfc linefile="1:http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5855.xml"?>

<reference anchor='RFC5855'>

<front>
<title>Nameservers for IPv4 and IPv6 Reverse Zones</title>
<author initials='J.' surname='Abley' fullname='J. Abley'>
<organization /></author>
<author initials='T.' surname='Manderson' fullname='T. Manderson'>
<organization /></author>
<date year='2010' month='May' />
<abstract>
<t>This document specifies a stable naming scheme for the nameservers that serve the zones IN-ADDR.ARPA and IP6.ARPA in the DNS.  These zones contain data that facilitate reverse mapping (address to name).  This memo documents an Internet Best Current Practice.</t></abstract></front>

<seriesInfo name='BCP' value='155' />
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='5855' />
<format type='TXT' octets='23027' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc5855.txt' />
</reference>
<?rfc linefile="701:draft-ietf-dnsop-as112-ops-09.xml"?>
      <?rfc linefile="1:http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-dnsop-default-local-zones.xml"?>

<reference anchor='I-D.ietf-dnsop-default-local-zones'>
<front>
<title>Locally-served DNS Zones</title>

<author initials='M' surname='Andrews' fullname='Mark Andrews'>
    <organization />
</author>

<date month='March' day='14' year='2011' />

<abstract><t>Experience with the Domain Name System (DNS) has shown that there are a number of DNS zones all iterative resolvers and recursive nameservers should automatically serve, unless configured otherwise. RFC 4193 specifies that this should occur for D.F.IP6.ARPA.  This document extends the practice to cover the IN-ADDR.ARPA zones for RFC 1918 address space and other well known zones with similar characteristics.</t></abstract>

</front>

<seriesInfo name='Internet-Draft' value='draft-ietf-dnsop-default-local-zones-15' />
<format type='TXT'
        target='http://www.ietf.org/internet-drafts/draft-ietf-dnsop-default-local-zones-15.txt' />
</reference>
<?rfc linefile="702:draft-ietf-dnsop-as112-ops-09.xml"?>
      <?rfc linefile="1:http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-dnsop-as112-under-attack-help-help.xml"?>

<reference anchor='I-D.ietf-dnsop-as112-under-attack-help-help'>
<front>
<title>I'm Being Attacked by PRISONER.IANA.ORG!</title>

<author initials='J' surname='Abley' fullname='Joe Abley'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='W' surname='Maton' fullname='William Maton'>
    <organization />
</author>

<date month='April' day='29' year='2011' />

<abstract><t>Many sites connected to the Internet make use of IPv4 addresses which are not globally unique.  Examples are the addresses designated in RFC1918 for private use within individual sites.  Hosts should never normally send DNS reverse mapping queries for those addresses on the public Internet.  However, such queries are frequently observed.  Authoritative servers are deployed to provide authoritative answers to such queries as part of a loosely- coordinated effort known as the AS112 project.  Since queries sent to AS112 servers are usually not intentional, the replies received back from those servers are typically unexpected. Unexpected inbound traffic can trigger alarms on intrusion detection systems and firewalls, and operators of such systems often mistakenly believe that they are being attacked.  This document provides background information and technical advice to those firewall operators.</t></abstract>

</front>

<seriesInfo name='Internet-Draft' value='draft-ietf-dnsop-as112-under-attack-help-help-06' />
<format type='TXT'
        target='http://www.ietf.org/internet-drafts/draft-ietf-dnsop-as112-under-attack-help-help-06.txt' />
</reference>
<?rfc linefile="703:draft-ietf-dnsop-as112-ops-09.xml"?>
    </references>

    <section title="History">
      <t>Widespread use of the private address blocks listed in
        <xref target="RFC1918"/> followed that document's publication
        in 1996. At that time the IN-ADDR.ARPA zone was served by
        root servers.</t>

      <t>The idea of off-loading IN-ADDR.ARPA queries relating to
        <xref target="RFC1918"/> addresses from the root nameservers
        was first proposed by Bill Manning and John Brown.</t>

      <t>The use of anycast for distributing authoritative DNS
	service for <xref target="RFC1918"/> IN-ADDR.ARPA zones was
	subsequently proposed at a private meeting of root server
	operators.</t>

      <t>ARIN provided an IPv4 prefix for the anycast service,
	and also the autonomous system number 112 for use in
	originating that prefix. This assignment gave the project
	its name.</t>

      <t>In 2002 the first AS112 anycast nodes were deployed.</t>

      <t>In 2011 the IN-ADDR.ARPA zone was redelegated from the root
        servers to a new set of servers operated independently by
        AfriNIC, APNIC, ARIN, ICANN, LACNIC and the RIPE NCC and
        named according to <xref target="RFC5855"/>.</t>

      <t>The use of anycast nameservers in the AS112 project
	contributed to the operational experience of anycast DNS
	services, and can be seen as a precursor to the anycast
	distribution of other authoritative DNS servers in subsequent
	years (e.g.  various root servers).</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Change History">
      <t>This section to be removed prior to publication.</t>

      <t>
        <list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="00">Initial draft, circulated as
            draft-jabley-as112-ops-00 and reviewed at the
            DNSOP working group meeting at IETF 66.</t>

          <t hangText="00">Document adoped by the DNSOP working
            group and renamed accordingly.</t>

          <t hangText="01">Input from reviewers of DNSOP and
            others, some cosmetic tweaks.</t>

	  <t hangText="02">Version bump as request by DNSOP chairs.
	    Added missing IANA Considerations section. Updated
	    author's addresses. Make http://www.as112.net/ URL
	    consistent.</t>

          <t hangText="03">Fix BLACKHOLE-2.IANA.ORG IP address.</t>

          <t hangText="04">Bump version number. Refresh references.
            Add reference to BIRD. Minor wordsmithing.</t>

          <t hangText="05">Updated following review from Peter Koch.</t>

          <t hangText="06">Updated following review from Alfred Hoenes.</t>

          <t hangText="07">Updated following IESG review.</t>

          <t hangText="08">Updated following review by S. Moonesamy.</t>

          <t hangText="09">Updated following review by Peter Koch.</t>
        </list>
      </t>
    </section>
  </back>
</rfc>
