<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- edited with XMLSPY v5 rel. 3 U (http://www.xmlspy.com)
     by Daniel M Kohn (private) -->

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
    <!ENTITY rfc2119 PUBLIC '' 
      'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml'>
]>

<rfc category="std" docName="draft-ietf-nfsv4-federated-fs-dns-srv-namespace-11.txt" ipr="pre5378Trust200902">


<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>

<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes" ?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3" ?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc iprnotified="no" ?>
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<!-- these two save paper: start new paragraphs from the same page etc. -->
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>


    <front>
        <title abbrev="NFSv4 Global Name Space with DNS SRV">
		Using DNS SRV to Specify a Global File Name Space with NFS version 4
	  </title>
        <author initials='C' surname="Everhart" fullname='Craig Everhart'>
            <organization>
		NetApp
		</organization>
		<address>
		<postal>
			<street>800 Cranberry Woods Drive, Ste. 300</street>
			<city>Cranberry Township</city> <region>PA</region>
			<code>16066</code>
			<country>US</country>
		</postal>
		<phone>+1 724 741 5101</phone>
		<email>everhart@netapp.com</email>
		</address>
        </author>
	  <author initials="W.A." surname="Adamson" fullname='W.A. (Andy) Adamson'>
		<organization>NetApp</organization>
		<address>
		<postal>
			<street>495 East Java Drive</street>
			<city>Sunnyvale</city> <region>CA</region>
			<code>94089</code>
			<country>US</country>
		</postal>
		<phone>+1 734 665 1204</phone>
		<email>andros@netapp.com</email>
		</address>
	  </author>
	  <author initials='J' surname="Zhang" fullname='Jiaying Zhang'>
		<organization>Google</organization>
		<address>
		<postal>
			<street>604 Arizona Avenue</street>
			<city>Santa Monica</city> <region>CA</region>
			<code>90401</code>
			<country>US</country>
		</postal>
		<phone>+1 310 309 6884</phone>
		<email>jiayingz@google.com</email>
		</address>
	  </author>

        <date month="December" year="2011"/>
        <abstract><t>
The NFS version 4 protocol provides a mechanism for a collection of NFS file servers to collaborate
in providing an organization-wide file name space.  The DNS SRV RR allows a simple 
way for an organization to publish the root of its filesystem
name space, even to clients that might not be
intimately associated with such an organization.  The DNS SRV RR can be used to join these
organization-wide file name spaces together to allow construction of a global, uniform NFS
file name space.
</t></abstract>
    </front>

    <middle>
        <section title="Requirements notation">
            <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL",
            "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY",
            and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as
            described in <xref target="RFC2119"/>.</t>
        </section>

	  <section title="Background">
		<t>
Version 4 of the NFS protocol <xref target="RFC3530" /> introduced the fs_locations attribute.  
Use of this attribute was elaborated further in the NFS Version 4 Minor Version 1 protocol <xref target="RFC5661" />,
which also defined an extended version of the attribute as fs_locations_info.
With the advent of these attributes, NFS servers can
cooperate to build a file name space that crosses server boundaries.
The fs_locations and fs_locations_info attributes are used as referrals, so that a file
server may indicate to its client that the file name tree beneath
a given name in the server is not present on itself, but is represented by a filesystem in some other
set of servers.  The mechanism
is general, allowing servers to describe any filesystem as being reachable by requests to any of a
set of servers.
Thus, starting with a single NFS Version 4 server, using these referrals, an NFS Version 4 client
could see a large name space associated with a collection of interrelated NFS Version 4 file servers.  An organization could use this
capability to construct a uniform file name space for itself.
</t><t>
An organization might wish to publish the starting point for this name space to its clients.  In many
cases, the organization will want to publish this starting point to a broader set of possible clients.
At the same time, it is useful to require clients to know only the smallest amount
of information in order to locate the appropriate name space.
Simultaneously, that required
information should be constant through the life of an organization if the clients are not to require
reconfiguration as administrative events change, for instance, a server's name or address.
		</t>
	  </section>

	  <section title="Use of SRV Resource Record in DNS">
<t>
Providing an organization's published filesystem name space is a service, and
the DNS <xref target="RFC1034" /><xref target="RFC1035" /> provides methods for discovery of
that service.
This standard defines a mapping from a domain name to the NFS filesystem(s) associated with that
name; such filesystems are called "domain root" filesystems.  From such filesystems, like other
NFS filesystems, an NFS client can use the standard NFS mechanisms to navigate the rest of the
NFS file servers that make up the filesystem name space for the given domain.
</t><t>
Such "domain root" filesystems are mounted at a conventional point in the NFS client namespace.
The mechanism results in a uniform cross-organizational file name space, similar to that seen in both
AFS <xref target="AFS" /><xref target="RFC5864" /> and 
DCE/DFS <xref target="DFS" />.  An NFS client need know only the
domain name for an organization in order to locate the filesystem name space published by that
organization.
</t><t>
<figure>
<preamble>
The DNS SRV resource record type <xref target="RFC2782" /> is used to locate "domain root" file servers.
  The
format of the DNS SRV record is as follows:
</preamble>
<artwork>
   _Service._Proto.Name TTL Class SRV Priority Weight Port Target
</artwork>
<postamble>
The Service name used is "_domainroot._nfs" (using a "_domainroot" subtype within the "_nfs"
service).  The Protocol without limitation could be either of the labels
"_tcp" or "_udp".
The Target fields 
give the domain names of the NFS servers that export filesystems for the domain's root.
An NFS client may then interpret any of the exported root filesystems as the
root of the filesystem published by the organization
with the given domain name.
</postamble> </figure>
</t><t>
The domain root service is not useful for NFS versions prior to v4, as the fs_locations attribute
was introduced only in NFSv4 (as described in Section 2).
The "_nfs" Service name is not limited to NFSv4; it is possible to use that
prefix in naming additional Services (and their SRV records) that are also applicable
to other versions of NFS (e.g., NFSv3 <xref target="RFC1813"/>.
</t><t>
In order to allow the NFSv4 servers so given to export a variety of filesystems, those file servers
MUST export the given domain's root filesystems at "/.domainroot/{Name}" within
their pseudo-filesystems, where the "{Name}" is the name of the organization as used in the SRV RR.
</t><t>
<figure>
<preamble>
As an example, suppose a client wished to locate the root of the filesystem published by organization example.net.  The
DNS servers for the domain would publish records like
</preamble><artwork>
   $ORIGIN example.net.
   _domainroot._nfs._tcp IN SRV 0 0 2049 nfs1tr.example.net.
   _domainroot._nfs._tcp IN SRV 1 0 18204 nfs2ex.example.net.
</artwork><postamble>
The result domain names nfs1tr.example.net and nfs2ex.example.net indicate NFS Version 4 file servers that
export the root of the published name space for the example.net domain.  In accordance with RFC 2782 <xref target="RFC2782" />,
these records are to be interpreted using the Priority and Weight field values, selecting an appropriate
file server with which to begin a network conversation.  The two file servers would export filesystems
that would be found at "/.domainroot/example.net" in their pseudo-filesystems, which clients would mount.
Clients then carry out subsequent accesses in accordance with the ordinary NFS Version 4 protocol.
The first record uses the port number 2049 assigned to NFS, and another port is specified for the second
record; the NFS servers would provide NFS service at their indicated port numbers, and NFS clients would connect to
the service via the corresponding port numbers on those indicated servers.
</postamble></figure>
</t><t>
Other filesystem protocols could make use of the same "domain root" abstraction, necessarily under
different Service names not specified here.
</t>
	  </section>

	  <section title="Integration with Use of NFS Version 4">
<t>
NFSv4 clients adhering to this specification implement a special directory, analogous to an Automounter
<xref target="AMD1" /><xref target="AMD2" />
directory, the entries in which are domain names that have recently been traversed.  When an application attempts to
traverse a new name in that special directory, the NFSv4 client consults DNS to obtain the SRV data for the given name,
and if successful, it mounts the indicated filesystem(s) in that name in the special directory.
The goal is that NFSv4 applications will be able to lookup an organization's domain name in the special directory,
and the NFSv4 client will be able to discover the filesystem that that organization publishes.
Entries in the special directory will be domain names, and they will each appear to the application as a directory name
pointing to the root directory of the filesystem published by the organization responsible for that domain name.
</t><t>
As noted in Section 3, the domain root service is not useful for NFS versions prior to version 4.
</t>
		<section title="Globally-useful names: conventional mount point">
<t>
<figure>
<preamble>
In order that the inter-organizational name space function as a global name space, the client-side mount point for that name space must be the same on different clients.  Conventionally, on POSIX machines, the name /nfs4/ is be used so that names on one machine will be directly usable on any machine.  Thus, the example.net published filesystem would be accessible as
</preamble><artwork>
	/nfs4/example.net/
</artwork><postamble>
on any POSIX client.  Using this convention, "/nfs4/" is the name of the special directory that is populated with
domain names, leading to file servers and filesystems that capture the results of SRV record lookups.
</postamble></figure>
</t>
		</section>

		<section title="Mount options">
<t>
SRV records are necessarily less complete than the information in the existing NFS Version 4 attributes fs_locations
<xref target="RFC3530" /> or fs_locations_info <xref target="RFC5661" />.
For the rootpath field of fs_location, or the fli_fs_root of fs_locations_info, NFS servers MUST use
the "/.domainroot/{Name}" string.  Thus,
the servers listed as targets for the SRV resource records MUST export the root of the organization's published
filesystem as the directory "/.domainroot/{Name}" (for the given organization Name) in their exported NFS namespaces.
For example, for organization "example.net", the directory "/.domainroot/example.net" would be used.
</t><t>
Chapter 11 of the NFS Version 4.1 document <xref target="RFC5661" /> describes the approach that an
NFS client should take to navigating fs_locations_info information.
</t><t>
The process of mounting an organization's name space should permit the use
of what is likely to impose the lowest cost on the server.  Thus, the NFS client SHOULD NOT insist
on using a writable copy of the filesystem if read-only copies exist, or a zero-age copy rather than a
copy that may be a little older.  The organization's file system representatives can be navigated
to provide access to higher-cost properties such as writability or freshness as necessary, but that the default
use when navigating to the base information for an organization ought to be as low-overhead as possible.
</t>
		</section>
	  <section title="Filesystem integration issues">
<t>
The result of the DNS search SHOULD appear as a (pseudo-)directory in the client name space.
A further refinement is RECOMMENDED: that only fully-qualified domain names appear as directories.  That is, in many
environments, DNS names may be abbreviated from their fully-qualified form.  In such circumstances, multiple names might be given to
NFS clients that all resolve to the same DNS SRV RRs.
The abbreviated form SHOULD be represented in the client's name space cache
as a symbolic link, pointing to the fully-qualified name.  This will allow pathnames obtained with,
say, getcwd() to include the DNS name that is most likely to be usable
outside the scope of any particular DNS abbreviation convention.
</t>
		</section>
	  <section title="Multicast DNS">
<t>
Location of the NFS domain root by this SRV record is intended to be performed
with unicast by using ordinary DNS <xref target="RFC1034" /><xref target="RFC1035" /> 
protocol. 
</t><t>
This document does not define the use of this DNS SRV record format in conjunction with
Multicast DNS (mDNS).  While mDNS could be used
to locate a local domain root via these SRV records, no other domain's root could
be discovered.  This means that mDNS has too little value
to use in locating NFSv4 domain roots.
</t>
	  </section>
	  </section>

	  <section title="Where is this integration carried out?">
<t>
The NFS client is responsible for interpreting SRV records.  
Using something like Automounter <xref target="AMD1" /> <xref target="AMD2" /> technology, the client interprets names
under a particular directory, discovering the appropriate filesystem to mount, and mounting
it in the specified place in the client name space before returning control to the application doing a lookup.
The result of the DNS lookup should be cached (obeying TTL) so
that the result could be returned more quickly the next time.
</t>
	  </section>

        <section title="Security Considerations">
<t>
This functionality introduces a new reliance of NFSv4 on the integrity of DNS.
Forged SRV records in DNS could cause the NFSv4 client to connect to the file servers
of an attacker, not the file servers of an organization.
This is similar to attacks that can be made on the base NFSv4 protocol, if server names
are given in fs_location attributes: the client can be made to connect to the
file servers of an attacker, not the file servers intended to be the target for
the fs_location attributes.
</t><t>
If DNSSEC <xref target="RFC4033" /> is available, it SHOULD be used to avoid both such attacks.
Domain-based service principal names are an additional mechanism that also apply in this case, and it would
be prudent to use them.  They provide a mapping from the domain name that the user specified to
names of security principals used on the NFSv4 servers that are indicated as the targets
in the SRV records (as providing file service for the root filesystems).
</t><t>
With domain-based service principal names, the idea is that one wants to authenticate 
{nfs, domainname, host.fqdn}, not simply {nfs, host.fqdn}, when the
server is a domain's root file server obtained through a DNS SRV RR lookup that may or may not have
been secure.
The domain administrator can thus ensure that only domain root NFSv4 servers have
credentials for such domain-based service principal names.
</t><t><figure><preamble>
Domain-based service principal names are defined in RFCs 5178 <xref target="RFC5178" /> and
5179 <xref target="RFC5179" />.  To make use of RFC 5178's domain-based names, the syntax for "domain-based-name"
MUST be used with a service of "nfs", a domain matching the name of the organization whose root filesystem
is being sought, and a hostname given in the target of the DNS SRV resource record.  Thus, in the example above,
two file servers (nfs1tr.example.net and nfs2ex.example.net) are located as hosting the root filesystem for
the organization example.net.  To communicate with, for instance, the second of the given file servers,
GSS-API is used with the name-type of GSS_C_NT_DOMAINBASED_SERVICE
defined in RFC 5178 and with a symbolic name of
</preamble><artwork>
	nfs@example.net@nfs2ex.example.net
</artwork><postamble>
in order to verify that the named server (nfs2ex.example.net) is authorized to provide the root filesystem
for the example.net organization.
</postamble></figure>
</t><t>
NFSv4 itself contains a facility for the negotiation of security mechanisms
to be used between NFS clients and NFS servers.  Section 3.3 of RFC 3530 <xref target="RFC3530"/>
and Section 2.6 of RFC 5661 <xref target="RFC5661"/> both describe how security
mechanisms are to be negotiated.  As such, there is no need for this document
to describe how that negotiation is to be carried out when the NFS client
contacts the NFS server for the specified domain root filesystem(s).
</t><t>
Using SRV records to advertise the locations of NFS servers
may expose those NFS servers to attacks.  Organizations should carefully consider
whether they wish their DNS servers to respond differentially to different
DNS clients, perhaps exposing their SRV records to only those DNS requests
that originate within a given perimeter, in order to reduce this exposure.
</t>

        </section>
        <section title="IANA Considerations">
<t>
<figure><preamble>
This document requests the assignment of a new Service name without an
associated port number (as defined in RFC 6335 <xref target="RFC6335"/>),
for TCP.

For this new Service, the Reference is this document.
</preamble><artwork>
Service name: domainroot
Transport Protocol(s) TCP
Assignee (REQUIRED)  IESG (iesg@ietf.org)
Contact (REQUIRED)   IETF Chair (chair@ietf.org)
Description (REQUIRED) Subtype of NFS file service, indicating NFS
                    service for the domain root, the root of an
                    organization's published file name space.
Reference (REQUIRED)  This document
Port Number (OPTIONAL)
Service Code (REQUIRED for DCCP only)
Known Unauthorized Uses (OPTIONAL)
Assignment Notes (OPTIONAL)
</artwork></figure>
</t>

        </section>
    </middle>

    <back>

<references title="Normative References">

  <reference anchor='RFC2119'>
      <front>
      <title abbrev='RFC Key Words'>Key words for use in RFCs to Indicate Requirement Levels</title>
      <author initials='S.' surname='Bradner' fullname='Scott Bradner'>
      <organization>Harvard University</organization>
      <address>
      <postal>
      <street>1350 Mass. Ave.</street>
      <street>Cambridge</street>
      <street>MA 02138</street></postal>
      <phone>- +1 617 495 3864</phone>
      <email>sob@harvard.edu</email></address></author>
      <date year='1997' month='March' />
      </front>
    </reference>

    <reference anchor="RFC3530">
	  <front>
      <title>Network File System (NFS) version 4 Protocol</title>
	  <author initials="S." surname="Shepler" fullname="S. Shepler">
        <organization>Sun Microsystems, Inc.</organization>
      </author>
	  <author initials="B." surname="Callaghan" fullname="B. Callaghan">
        <organization>Sun Microsystems, Inc.</organization>
      </author>
	  <author initials="D." surname="Robinson" fullname="D. Robinson">
        <organization>Sun Microsystems, Inc.</organization>
      </author>
	  <author initials="R." surname="Thurlow" fullname="R. Thurlow">
        <organization>Sun Microsystems, Inc.</organization>
      </author>
	  <author initials="C." surname="Beame" fullname="C. Beame">
        <organization>Hummingbird, Ltd.</organization>
      </author>
	  <author initials="M." surname="Eisler" fullname="M. Eisler">
        <organization>Network Appliance, Inc.</organization>
      </author>
	  <author initials="D." surname="Noveck" fullname="D. Noveck">
        <organization>Network Appliance, Inc.</organization>
      </author>
      <date year="2003" month="April" />
      </front>
      <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="3530"/>
      <format type="TXT" octets="600988" 
       target="ftp://ftp.isi.edu/in-notes/rfc3530.txt"/>
    </reference>

    <reference anchor="RFC5661">
	  <front>
      <title>Network File System (NFS) Version 4 Minor Version 1 Protocol</title>
	  <author initials="S." surname="Shepler" fullname="S. Shepler">
        <organization>Storspeed, Inc.</organization>
      </author>
	  <author initials="M." surname="Eisler" fullname="M. Eisler">
        <organization>Network Appliance, Inc.</organization>
      </author>
	  <author initials="D." surname="Noveck, Editors" fullname="D. Noveck">
        <organization>Network Appliance, Inc.</organization>
      </author>
      <date year="2010" month="January" />
      </front>
      <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="5661"/>
      <format type="TXT" octets="600988" 
       target="http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc5661.txt"/>
    </reference>

  <reference anchor="RFC1034">
	<front>
		<title>Domain Names - Concepts and Facilities</title>
		<author initials="P.V." surname="Mockapetris" fullname="Paul Mockapetris">
		<organization />
		</author>
		<date month="November" year="1987" />
	</front>
	<seriesInfo name="RFC" value="1034" />
	<format type="TXT" octets="129180"
	 target="http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc1034.txt" />
  </reference>

  <reference anchor="RFC1035">
	<front>
		<title>Domain Names - Implementation and Specification</title>
		<author initials="P.V." surname="Mockapetris" fullname="Paul Mockapetris">
		<organization />
		</author>
		<date month="November" year="1987" />
	</front>
	<seriesInfo name="RFC" value="1035" />
	<format type="TXT" octets="125626"
	 target="http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc1034.txt" />
  </reference>

  <reference anchor="RFC2782">
	<front>
		<title>A DNS RR for specifying the location of services (DNS SRV)</title>
		<author initials="A." surname="Gulbrandsen" fullname="Arnt Gulbrandsen">
			<organization>Troll Technologies</organization>
		</author>
		<author initials="P." surname="Vixie" fullname="Paul Vixie">
			<organization>Internet Software Consortium</organization>
		</author>
		<author initials="L." surname="Esibov" fullname="Levon Esibov">
			<organization>Microsoft Corporation</organization>
		</author>
		<date month="February" year="2000" />
	</front>
	<seriesInfo name="RFC" value="2782" />
	<format type="TXT" octets="24013"
	 target="http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc2782.txt" />
  </reference>

  <reference anchor="RFC4033">
	<front>
		<title>DNS Security Introduction and Requirements</title>
		<author initials="R." surname="Arends" fullname="Roy Arends">
			<organization>Telematica Institut</organization>
		</author>
		<author initials="R." surname="Austein" fullname="Rob Austein">
			<organization abbrev="ISC">Internet Systems Consortium</organization>
		</author>
		<author initials="M." surname="Larson" fullname="Matt Larson">
			<organization abbrev="VeriSign">VeriSign, Inc.</organization>
		</author>
		<author initials="D." surname="Massey" fullname="Dan Massey">
			<organization>Colorado State University</organization>
		</author>
		<author initials="S." surname="Rose" fullname="Scott Rose">
			<organization abbrev="NIST">National Institute for Standards and Technology</organization>
		</author>
		<date month="March" year="2005" />
	</front>
	<seriesInfo name="RFC" value="4033" />
	<format type="TXT" octets="52445"
	 target="http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc4033.txt" />
  </reference>

  <reference anchor="RFC5178">
	<front>
		<title>Generic Security Service Application Program Interface (GSS-API) Internationalization and Domain-Based Service Names and Name Type</title>
		<author initials="N." surname="Williams" fullname="Nicolas Williams">
			<organization>Sun</organization>
		</author>
		<author initials="A." surname="Melnikov" fullname="Alexey Melnikov">
			<organization>Isode Ltd.</organization>
		</author>
		<date month="May" year="2008" />
	</front>
	<seriesInfo name="RFC" value="5178" />
	<format type="TXT" octets="17262"
	 target="http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc5178.txt" />
  </reference>

  <reference anchor="RFC5179">
	<front>
		<title>Generic Security Service Application Program Interface (GSS-API) Domain-Based Service Names Mapping for the Kerberos V GSS Mechanism</title>
		<author initials="N." surname="Williams" fullname="Nicolas Williams">
			<organization>Sun</organization>
		</author>
		<date month="May" year="2008" />
	</front>
	<seriesInfo name="RFC" value="5179" />
	<format type="TXT" octets="8017"
	 target="http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc5179.txt" />
  </reference>
 
 <reference anchor="RFC5864">
	<front>
		<title>DNS SRV Resource Records for AFS</title>
		<author initials="R." surname="Allbery" fullname="Russ Allbery">
		<organization>Stanford University</organization>
		</author>
		<date month="April" year="2010" />
	</front>
	<seriesInfo name="RFC" value="5864" />
	<format type="TXT"
	 target="http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc5864.txt" />
  </reference>
 
 <reference anchor="RFC6335">
	<front>
		<title>Internet Assigned Numbers Authority (IANA) Procedures for the Management of the Service Name and Transport Protocol Port Number Registry</title>
		<author initials="M." surname="Cotton" fullname="Michelle Cotton">
		<organization>ICANN</organization>
		</author>
		<author initials="L." surname="Eggert" fullname="Lars Eggert">
		<organization>Nokia</organization>
		</author>
		<author initials="J." surname="Touch" fullname="Joe Touch">
		<organization>USC/ISI</organization>
		</author>
		<author initials="M." surname="Westerlund" fullname="Magnus Westerlund">
		<organization>Ericsson</organization>
		</author>
		<author initials="S." surname="Cheshire" fullname="Stuart Cheshire">
		<organization>Stanford University</organization>
		</author>
		<date month="August" year="2011" />
	</front>
	<seriesInfo name="RFC" value="6335" />
	<format type="TXT"
	 target="http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc6335.txt" />
  </reference>
 
</references>
 

<references title="Informative References">

  <reference anchor="DFS">
	<front>
		<title>DEcorum File System Architectural Overview</title>
		<author initials="M.L." surname="Kazar" fullname="Michael L. Kazar">
			<organization>Transarc Corporation</organization>
		</author>
		<author initials="B.W." surname="Leverett" fullname="Bruce W. Leverett">
			<organization>Transarc Corporation</organization>
		</author>
		<author initials="O.T." surname="Anderson" fullname="Owen T. Anderson">
			<organization>Transarc Corporation</organization>
		</author>
		<author initials="V." surname="Apostolides" fullname="Vasilis Apostolides">
			<organization>Transarc Corporation</organization>
		</author>
		<author initials="B.A." surname="Bottos" fullname="Beth A. Bottos">
			<organization>Transarc Corporation</organization>
		</author>
		<author initials="S." surname="Chutani" fullname="Sailesh Chutani">
			<organization>Transarc Corporation</organization>
		</author>
		<author initials="C.F." surname="Everhart" fullname="Craig F. Everhart">
			<organization>Transarc Corporation</organization>
		</author>
		<author initials="W.A." surname="Mason" fullname="W. Anthony Mason">
			<organization>Transarc Corporation</organization>
		</author>
		<author initials="S.-T." surname="Tu" fullname="Shu-Tsui Tu">
			<organization>Transarc Corporation</organization>
		</author>
		<author initials="E.R." surname="Zayas" fullname="Edward R. Zayas">
			<organization>Transarc Corporation</organization>
		</author>
		<date month="June" year="1990" />
	</front>
     <seriesInfo name="Proc. USENIX Summer Conf." value="Anaheim, Calif." />
  </reference>

  <reference anchor="AMD1"
		 target="http://docs.freebsd.org/info/amdref/amdref.pdf">
	<front>
	  <title>Amd: The 4.4 BSD Automounter Reference Manual</title>
	  <author initials="J.-S." surname="Pendry" fullname="Jan-Simon Pendry">
		<organization>Imperial College of Science, London</organization>
	  </author>
	  <author initials="N." surname="Williams" fullname="Nick Williams">
		<organization>Imperial College of Science, London</organization>
	  </author>
	  <date month="March" year="1991" />
	</front>
  </reference>

  <reference anchor="AMD2">
	<front>
	  <title>AMD--AutoMount Daemon</title>
	  <author initials="M." surname="Crosby" fullname="Matthew Crosby">
		<organization>University of Colorado, Boulder</organization>
	  </author>
	  <date month="March" year="1997" />
	</front>
 	<seriesInfo name="Linux Journal 1997, 35es" value="Article 4" />
 </reference>

  <reference anchor="AFS">
	<front>
		<title>An Overview of the Andrew File System"</title>
		<author initials="J.H." surname="Howard" fullname="John H. Howard">
		  <organization abbrev="CMU ITC">"Carnegie Mellon University, Information Technology Center"</organization>
		</author>
		<date month="February" year="1988" />
	</front>
	<seriesInfo name="Proc. USENIX Winter Tech. Conf." value="Dallas" />
  </reference>

  <reference anchor="RFC1813">
	<front>
		<title>NFS Version 3 Protocol Specification</title>
		<author initials="B." surname="Callaghan" fullname="Brent Callaghan">
			<organization>Sun Microsystems, Inc.</organization>
		</author>
		<author initials="B." surname="Pawlowski" fullname="Brian Pawlowski">
			<organization>Sun Microsystems, Inc.</organization>
		</author>
		<author initials="P." surname="Staubach" fullname="Peter Staubach">
			<organization>Sun Microsystems, Inc.</organization>
		</author>
		<date month="June" year="1995" />
	</front>
	<seriesInfo name="RFC" value="1813" />
	<format type="TXT" 
	 target="http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc1813.txt" />
  </reference>

</references>

    </back>

</rfc>

