<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<rfc category="bcp" docName="draft-delregno-pwe3-vccv-mandatory-features-02"
     ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="VCCV Mandatory Control Channel">Mandatory Features of
    Virtual Circuit Connectivity Verification Implementations</title>

    <author fullname="Nick Del Regno" initials="N." role="editor"
            surname="Del Regno">
      <organization>Verizon</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>400 International Pkwy</street>

          <city>Richardson</city>

          <region>TX</region>

          <code>75081</code>

          <country>US</country>
        </postal>

        <phone>972-729-3411</phone>

        <facsimile></facsimile>

        <email>nick.delregno@verizon.com</email>

        <uri></uri>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Vishwas Manral" initials="V." role="editor"
            surname="Manral">
      <organization>IPInfusion Inc.</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>1188 E. Arques Ave.</street>

          <city>Sunnyvale</city>

          <region>CA</region>

          <code>94085</code>

          <country>US</country>
        </postal>

        <phone>408-400-1900</phone>

        <facsimile></facsimile>

        <email>vishwas@ipinfusion.com</email>

        <uri></uri>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="R&uuml;diger Kunze" initials="R." surname="Kunze">
      <organization>Deutsche Telekom</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>

          <city></city>

          <region></region>

          <code></code>

          <country></country>
        </postal>

        <phone></phone>

        <facsimile></facsimile>

        <email>Ruediger.Kunze@telekom.de</email>

        <uri></uri>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Manuel Paul" initials="M." surname="Paul">
      <organization>Deutsche Telekom</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>

          <city></city>

          <region></region>

          <code></code>

          <country></country>
        </postal>

        <phone></phone>

        <facsimile></facsimile>

        <email>Manuel.Paul@telekom.de</email>

        <uri></uri>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Thomas Nadeau" initials="T." surname="Nadeau">
      <organization>Huawei</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>

          <city></city>

          <region></region>

          <code></code>

          <country></country>
        </postal>

        <phone></phone>

        <facsimile></facsimile>

        <email>tnadeau@lucidvision.com</email>

        <uri></uri>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date day="15" month="October" year="2010" />

    <abstract>
      <t>Pseudowire Virtual Circuit Connectivity Verification (VCCV) <xref
      target="RFC5085"></xref> defines several Control Channel (CC) Types for
      MPLS PW's , none of which are preferred or mandatory. As a result,
      independent implementations of different subsets of the three options
      have resulted in interoperability challenges. In RFC5085 the CV type of
      LSP Ping is made the default for MPLS PW's and ICMP Ping is made
      optional. This however, is a recommendation and not a requirement for
      implementations which can also lead to interoperability challenges.</t>

      <t>To enable interoperability between implementations, this document
      defines a subset of control channels that is considered mandatory for
      VCCV implementation. This will ensure that VCCV remains the valuable
      tool it was designed to be in multi-vendor, multi-implementation and
      multi-carrier networks. This document also states requirements for the
      CV type too.</t>

      <t>This draft is specific to MPLS PW's and not L2TPv3 PW. For the L2TPv3
      PW only one CC and CV type are specified and the issues raised in this
      draft do not arise.</t>
    </abstract>

    <note title="Requirements Language">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
      document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
      target="RFC2119">RFC 2119</xref>.</t>
    </note>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t><xref target="RFC5085"></xref> defines three Control Channel types
      for MPLS PW's: Type 1, using the Pseudowire Control Word, Type 2, using
      the Router Alert Label, and Type 3, using TTL Expiration (e.g. MPLS PW
      Label with TTL == 1). While Type 2 (RA Label) is indicated as being "the
      preferred mode of VCCV operation when the Control Word is not present,"
      RFC 5085 does not indicate a mandatory Control Channel to ensure
      interoperable implementations. The closest it comes to mandating a
      control channel is the requirement to support Type 1 (Control Word)
      whenever the control word is present. As such, the three options yield
      seven implementation permutations (assuming you have to support at least
      one Control Channel type to provide VCCV). Many equipment manufacturers
      have gravitated to two common implementation camps: 1) Control Word and
      Router Alert Label support, or 2) TTL Expiration support only.</t>

      <t>As a result, service providers are often faced with diametrically
      opposed support for VCCV Control Channel types when deploying mixed
      vendor networks. As long as operators select vendors from within a camp,
      VCCV can be used as the valuable fault-detection and diagnostic
      mechanism it was created to be. However, due to myriad other unrelated
      requirements associated with large router requirement specifications and
      related acquisitions, practice has shown it to be impractical to deploy
      equipment from only one camp or the other. As a result, this mismatch of
      support between camps often leads to a service provider's inability to
      use an important operational tool in networks supporting Layer 2 VPN
      services.</t>

      <t>This document discusses the three Control Channel options, presents
      pros and cons of each approach and concludes with which Control Channel
      an implementation is required to implement.</t>

      <t>This document also puts an explicit reqirement on the CV type to be
      supported for MPLS PW.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Comparison of Alternative Control Channel Types">
      <t>The following section presents a review of each control channel type
      and the pros and cons of implementing each.</t>

      <section title="Control Channel Type 1: Control Word">
        <t>As noted in <xref target="RFC5085"></xref>, an in-band control
        channel is ideal, since this ensures that the connectivity
        verification messages follow the same path as the PWE3 traffic. VCCV
        Control Channel Type 1, also known as "PWE3 Control Word with 0001b as
        first nibble," is the only "in-band" control channel specified. It
        uses the control word as opposed to using the label to indicate the
        presence of the Connectivity Verification message (CV). This ensures
        that the control channel follows the forwarding path of the associated
        traffic in all cases, including in the case of ECMP hashing.</t>

        <t>The use of the control word is not mandatory on all PWE3
        encapsulations. However based on the current hardware support the
        draft strongly suggest that all implementations SHOULD generically
        support the use of VCCV Control Channel Type 1 for all PWE3
        encapsulations.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Control Channel Type 2:  MPLS Router Alert Label">
        <t>VCCV Control Channel Type 2 is also referred to as "MPLS Router
        Alert Label." In this approach, the VCCV control channel is created by
        using the MPLS router alert label <xref target="RFC3032"></xref> (e.g.
        Label Value = 1) immediately above the pseudowire label. As this label
        is inserted above the pseudowire label and below the PSN tunnel label,
        intermediate label switch routers do not act on the label. However, at
        the egress router, when the PSN tunnel label is popped and the next
        label is examined, the label value of 1 will cause the packet to be
        delivered to a local software module for further processing (e.g.
        processing of the VCCV Connectivity Verification (CV) message).
        Similarly, in the case of penultimate hop-popping, the labeled packet
        arrives with it's top-most label having a label value = 1, causing it
        to be delivered to a local software module for further processing.</t>

        <t>As the processing behavior associated with Router Alert labels is
        germane to all MPLS implementations, VCCV Control Channel Type 2
        should be supported by all implementations. However, there are issues
        with using Router Alert labels in operational networks. First, there
        are known issues related to the use of the Router Alert label and
        possible security risks associated with DoS attacks. While this is
        less of a risk in closed networks, this becomes a larger potential
        issue in inter-provider networks. Second, unlike use of the Control
        Word, inserting a label between the PSN tunnel label and the
        pseudowire label has ECMP implications, resulting in the very real
        possibility of the VCCV Control Channel diverging from the path of the
        associated traffic. While ECMP issues arise from both non-control-word
        control channels, given the security risks of using the Router Alert
        label, the VCCV Control Channel Type 2 cannot be mandatory for VCCV
        implementations.</t>

        <t>All implementations MAY support VCCV Control Channel Type 2 so that
        operators who choose to use this approach can do so in
        mixed-implementation environments. Further, Router Alert Label MUST
        contain an appropriate TTL value, such that the TTL value does not
        cause the CPU exception in any intermediate device in case of PHP.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Control Channel Type 3:  MPLS PW Label with TTL == 1">
        <t>VCCV Control Channel Type 3 is also known as "MPLS PW Label with
        TTL == 1." Unlike VCCV Control Channel Type 2, this approach uses the
        existing pseudowire label to indicate the need for further processing.
        Upon receiving the labeled packet, whether accompanied by a PSN tunnel
        label or alone (in the case of penultimate hop popping), the egress
        router makes a forwarding decision based on the Label Value, assuming
        the TTL is greater than or equal to 2. However, as part of this
        process and prior to forwarding the contents of the labeled packet to
        the attachment circuit (AC), the TTL is decremented. If the TTL value
        of the received packet was equal to 1, the TTL is decremented to 0,
        causing the packet to be sent to the control plane for processing.</t>

        <t>Unlike the Router Alert Label (Label Value == 1), there has been no
        standardization of the pseudowire label TTL to this point. For
        example, <xref target="RFC3985"></xref>, one of the only PWE3 RFCs to
        address TTL at all, states that "when a MPLS label is used as a PW
        Demultiplexer, setting of the TTL value in the PW label is application
        specific." However, no subsequent RFCs have defined the default value
        of the TTL field within the PW demultiplexer. With the advent of VCCV,
        it became clear that a TTL value greater than 1 was needed. Many
        implementations have settled on a default value of 2 for
        single-segment pseudowires, as evidenced by subsequent MIB drafts in
        which the default value of 2 is alluded to, if not explicitly defined.
        Consequently, implementations vary widely with regard to the default
        value of the TTL field and the subsequent behavior when the TTL is
        decremented to 0, if it is decremented at all.</t>

        <t>Similar to VCCV CC Type 2, changing the value of the TTL in the
        existing PW demultiplexer label to something different from the value
        of the labels accompanying the associated traffic, can result in the
        VCCV Control Channel messages diverging from the path of the
        associated traffic when ECMP is employed.</t>

        <t>Implementations MUST support the use of this option.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Mandatory Control Channels">
      <t>Implementations of VCCV, at a minimum, MUST support VCCV Control
      Channel Type 3: MPLS PW Label with TTL == 1. Implementations of VCCV
      MUST also set the default TTL value of the PW demultiplexer label to 2
      for single-segment pseudowires. Further, implementations of VCCV MUST
      decrement the TTL of the PW demultiplexer label in the egress PE, and
      upon reaching a TTL==0, MUST pass the packet to the control plane for
      further processing of the VCCV message contained therein. This provides
      a basic level of interoperability across all implementations of VCCV
      without mandating the use of the control word for all VCCV-enabled
      pseudowire applications. Further, as VCCV is applied to multi-segment
      pseudowires, using Control Channel Type 3 enables PW traceroute to be
      implemented in a manner similar to that of MPLS and IP traceroute,
      through the incrementing of the TTL value in subsequent probes.</t>

      <t>As noted previously, this baseline level of VCCV support does not
      address the aforementioned ECMP issues. Consequently, implementations of
      VCCV SHOULD support VCCV Control Channel Type 1 for pseudowire
      encapsulations for which a control word is not mandatory.</t>

      <t>Implementations of VCCV MUST support VCCV Control Channel Type 1:
      Control Word for all implemented pseudowire encapsulations where use of
      the Control Word is mandatory. Implementations SHOULD support VCCV
      Control Channel Type 1 for implemented pseudowire encapsulations where,
      although optional, use of the control word is elected, on a
      pseudowire-by-pseudowire basis.</t>

      <t>Implementations of VCCV MUST support the appropriate signaling of
      VCCV Control Channel Type support in the pseudowire setup signaling. In
      order to avoid interoperability issues, implementations should negotiate
      VCCV Control Channel Type, in decreasing priority: Type 1 (Control
      Word), Type 3 (TTL Expiration) and Type 2 (Router Alert), when all, or
      any permutation of the three CC Types are supported.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Mandatory CV Types">
      <t>For MPLS PWs, the CV Type of LSP Ping (0x02) MUST be supported, and
      the CV Type of ICMP Ping (0x01) MAY be supported.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>This document makes no request of IANA.</t>

      <t>Note to RFC Editor: this section may be removed on publication as an
      RFC.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>This document describes the VCCV Control Channels which MUST be
      implemented to ensure interoperability in a mixed-implementation
      environment. This document does not change the basic functionality
      associated with VCCV. As a result, no additional security issues are
      raised by this document over those already identified in <xref
      target="RFC5085"></xref>.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">
      <t></t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119"?>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <reference anchor="RFC5085">
        <front>
          <title>Pseudowire Virtual Circuit Connectivity Verification (VCCV):
          A Control Channel for Pseudowires</title>

          <author fullname="Thomas D. Nadeau" initials="T." surname="Nadeau">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date month="December" year="2007" />
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RFC3032">
        <front>
          <title>MPLS Label Stack Encoding</title>

          <author fullname="Eric Rosen" initials="E." surname="Rosen">
            <organization>R</organization>
          </author>

          <date month="January" year="2001" />
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RFC3985">
        <front>
          <title>Pseudo Wire Emulation Edge-to-Edge (PWE3)
          Architecture</title>

          <author fullname="Stewart Bryant" initials="S." surname="Bryant">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date month="March" year="2005" />
        </front>
      </reference>
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
