<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc iprnotified="no" ?>
<?rfc strict="no" ?>
<?rfc compact="no" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<rfc category="info" docName="draft-ietf-alto-deployments-06"
     ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="Deployment Considerations">ALTO Deployment
    Considerations</title>

    <author fullname="Martin Stiemerling" initials="M." surname="Stiemerling" role="editor">
      <organization abbrev="NEC Europe Ltd.">NEC Laboratories
      Europe</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Kurfuerstenanlage 36</street>

          <code>69115</code>

          <city>Heidelberg</city>

          <country>Germany</country>
        </postal>

        <phone>+49 6221 4342 113</phone>

        <facsimile>+49 6221 4342 155</facsimile>

        <email>martin.stiemerling@neclab.eu</email>

        <uri>http://ietf.stiemerling.org</uri>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Sebastian Kiesel" initials="S" surname="Kiesel" role="editor">
      <organization abbrev="University of Stuttgart">University of Stuttgart,
      Computing Center</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Allmandring 30</street>

          <city>Stuttgart</city>

          <code>70550</code>

          <country>Germany</country>
        </postal>

        <email>ietf-alto@skiesel.de</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Stefano Previdi" initials="S." surname="Previdi">
      <organization abbrev="Cisco."> Cisco Systems, Inc. </organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Via Del Serafico 200</street>

          <code>00191</code>

          <city>Rome</city>

          <country>Italy</country>
        </postal>

        <email>sprevidi@cisco.com</email>

      </address>
    </author>


    <date year="2013" />

    <area>APP</area>

    <workgroup>ALTO</workgroup>

    <keyword>ALTO</keyword>

    <keyword>ALTO Deployment Considerations</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>Many Internet applications are used to access resources, such as
      pieces of information or server processes, which are available in
      several equivalent replicas on different hosts. This includes, but is
      not limited to, peer-to-peer file sharing applications. The goal of
      Application-Layer Traffic Optimization (ALTO) is to provide guidance to
      these applications, which have to select one or several hosts from a set
      of candidates, that are able to provide a desired resource. The protocol
      is under specification in the ALTO working group. This memo discusses
      deployment related issues of ALTO for peer-to-peer and CDNs, some
      preliminary security considerations, and also initial guidance for
      application designers using ALTO.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>Many Internet applications are used to access resources, such as
      pieces of information or server processes, which are available in
      several equivalent replicas on different hosts. This includes, but is
      not limited to, peer-to-peer file sharing applications and Content
      Delivery Networks (CDNs). The goal of Application-Layer Traffic
      Optimization (ALTO) is to provide guidance to applications, which have
      to select one or several hosts from a set of candidates, that are able
      to provide a desired resource. The basic ideas of ALTO are described in
      the problem space of ALTO is described in <xref target="RFC5693"></xref>
      and the set of requirements is discussed in <xref
      target="RFC6708"></xref>.</t>

      <t>However, there are no considerations about what operational issues
      are to be expected once ALTO will be deployed. This includes, but is not
      limited to, location of the ALTO server, imposed load to the ALTO
      server, or from whom the queries are performed.</t>

      <t>Comments and discussions about this memo should be directed to the
      ALTO working group: alto@ietf.org.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="sec.general_deployment" title="General Considerations">
     <t>The ALTO protocol is a client/server protocol, operating between a
      number of ALTO clients and an ALTO server, as sketched in <xref
      target="fig.overview"></xref>. The ALTO working groups defines the ALTO
      protocol <xref target="I-D.ietf-alto-protocol"></xref>.</t>

      <t><figure anchor="fig.overview"
          title="Network Overview of ALTO Protocol">
          <artwork><![CDATA[              +----------+
              |  ALTO    |
              |  Server  |
              +----------+
                    ^
             _.-----|------.
         ,-''       |       `--.
       ,'           |           `.
      (     Network |             )
       `.           |           ,'
         `--.       |       _.-'
             `------|-----''
                    v
 +----------+  +----------+   +----------+
 |  ALTO    |  |  ALTO    |...|  ALTO    |
 |  Client  |  |  Client  |   |  Client  |
 +----------+  +----------+   +----------+
]]></artwork>
        </figure></t>

      <section anchor="sec.general_overview" title="General Placement of ALTO">
        <t>The ALTO server and ALTO clients can be situated at various
        entities in a network deployment. The first differentiation is whether
        the ALTO client is located on the actual host that runs the
        application, as shown in <xref target="fig.tracker_less"></xref>,
        (e.g., peer-to-peer filesharing application) or if the ALTO client is
        located on resource directory, as shown in <xref
        target="fig.tracker"></xref> (e.g., a tracker in peer-to-peer
        filesharing).</t>

        <t><figure anchor="fig.tracker_less"
            title="Overview of protocol interaction between ALTO elements,scenario without tracker">
            <artwork><![CDATA[                                               +-----+
                                          =====|     |**
                                      ====     +-----+  *
                                  ====            *     *
                              ====                *     *
     +-----+     +------+=====                 +-----+  *
     |     |.....|      |======================|     |  *
     +-----+     +------+=====                 +-----+  *
   Source of      ALTO        ====                *     *
   topological    service         ====            *     *
   information                        ====     +-----+  *
                                          =====|     |**
                                               +-----+
   Legend:
   === ALTO client protocol
   *** Application protocol
   ... Provisioning protocol]]></artwork>
          </figure></t>

        <t><xref target="fig.tracker_less"></xref> shows the operational model
        for applications that do not use a tracker, such as, edonky, or in if
        the tracker should be the querying party. This use case also holds
        true for CDNs. The ALTO server can also be queried by CDNs to get a
        guidance about where the a particular client accessing data in the CDN
        is exactly located in the ISP's network.</t>

        <t><figure anchor="fig.tracker"
            title="Overview of protocol interaction between ALTO elements, scenario with tracker">
            <artwork><![CDATA[                                               +-----+
                                             **|     |**
                                           **  +-----+  *
                                         **       *     *
                                       **         *     *
     +-----+     +------+     +-----+**        +-----+  *
     |     |.....|      |=====|     |**********|     |  *
     +-----+     +------+     +-----+**        +-----+  *
   Source of      ALTO        Resource **         *     *
   topological    service     directory  **       *     *
   information               ("tracker")   **  +-----+  *
                                             **|     |**
                                               +-----+
                                                Peers
   Legend:
   === ALTO client protocol
   *** Application protocol
   ... Provisioning protocol]]></artwork>
          </figure></t>

        <t>However, <xref target="fig.tracker"></xref> does not denote where
        the ALTO elements are actually located, i.e., if the tracker and the
        ALTO server are in the same ISP's domain, or if the tracker and the
        ALTO server are managed/owned/located in different domains. The latter
        is the typical use case, e.g., taking Pirate Bay as example that
        serves Bittorrent peers world-wide.</t>

      </section>

      <section anchor="sec.alto_apps" title="Relationship between ALTO and Applications">
        <t>ALTO is intended to be used by a wide-range of applications.
		However, any application using ALTO must also work if no ALTO
		servers can be found or if no responses to ALTO queries are
		received, e.g., due to connectivity problems or overload situation
		(see also <xref target="RFC6708"/>). (Editor's note: better
		text needed here!)
	    </t>
	  </section>
	  
      <section anchor="sec.guidance" title="Provided Guidance">
        <t>ALTO gives guidance to applications on what IP addresses or IP
        prefixes, and such which hosts are to be preferred according to the
        operator of the ALTO server. The general assumption of the ALTO WG is
        that a network operator would always express to prefer hosts in its
        own network while hosts located outside its own network are to be
        avoided (are undesired to be considered by the applications). This
        might be applicable in some cases but may not be applicable in the
        general case. The ALTO protocol gives only the means to let the ALTO
        server operator to express is preference, whatever this preference is.
        This section explores this space.</t>

        <section title="Keeping Traffic Local in Network">
          <t>ALTO guidance can be used to let applications prefer other peers
          within the same network operator's network instead of randomly
          connecting to other peers which are located in another operator's
          network. <xref target="fig.network_local"></xref> shows such a
          scenario where peers prefer peers in the same network (e.g., Peer 1
          and Peer 2 in ISP1 and Peer 3 and Peer 4 in ISP2). </t>

          <t><figure anchor="fig.network_local"
              title="ALTO Traffic Network Localization">
              <artwork><![CDATA[
                         ,-------.         +-----------+
       ,---.          ,-'         `-.      |   Peer 1  |
    ,-'     `-.      /     ISP 1   ########|ALTO Client|
   /           \    /              #  \    +-----------+
  /    ISP X    \   |              #  |    +-----------+
 /               \  \              ########|   Peer 2  |
;             +----------------------------|ALTO Client|
|             |   |   `-.         ,-'      +-----------+
|             |   |      `-------'                      
|             |   |      ,-------.         +-----------+
:             |   ;   ,-'         `########|   Peer 3  |
 \            |  /   /     ISP 2   # \     |ALTO Client|
  \           | /   /              #  \    +-----------+
   \          +---------+          #  |    +-----------+
    `-.     ,-'     \   |          ########|   Peer 4  |
       `---'         \  +------------------|ALTO Client| 
                      `-.         ,-'      +-----------+ 
                         `-------'                       

    Legend:
    ### preferred "connections"
    --- non-preferred "connections"
]]></artwork>
            </figure>TBD: Describes limits of this approach (e.g., traffic
          localization guidance is of less use if the peers cannot upload);
          describe how maps would look like.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Off-Loading Traffic from Network">
          <t>Another scenario where the use of ALTO can be beneficial is in
          mobile broadband networks, e.g., CDMA200 or UMTS, but where the
          network operator may have the desire to guide peers in its own
          network to use peers in remote networks. One reason can be that the
          wireless network is not made for the load cause by, e.g.,
          peer-to-peer applications, and the operator has the need that peers
          fetch their data from remote peers in other parts of the Internet.
          </t>

          <t><figure anchor="fig.network_de_local"
              title="ALTO Traffic Network De-Localization">
              <artwork><![CDATA[
                         ,-------.         +-----------+
       ,---.          ,-'         `-.      |   Peer 1  |
    ,-'     `-.      /     ISP 1   +-------|ALTO Client|
   /           \    /              |  \    +-----------+
  /    ISP X    \   |              |  |    +-----------+
 /               \  \              +-------|   Peer 2  |
;             #-###########################|ALTO Client|
|             #   |   `-.         ,-'      +-----------+
|             #   |      `-------'                      
|             #   |      ,-------.         +-----------+
:             #   ;   ,-'         `+-------|   Peer 3  |
 \            #  /   /     ISP 2   | \     |ALTO Client|
  \           # /   /              |  \    +-----------+
   \          ###########          |  |    +-----------+
    `-.     ,-'     \   #          +-------|   Peer 4  |
       `---'         \  ###################|ALTO Client| 
                      `-.         ,-'      +-----------+ 
                         `-------'                       

    Legend:
    === preferred "connections"
    --- non-preferred "connections"
]]></artwork>
            </figure><xref target="fig.network_de_local"></xref> shows the
          result of such a guidance process where Peer 2 prefers a connection
          with Peer4 instead of Peer 1, as shown in <xref
          target="fig.network_local"></xref>.</t>

          <t>TBD: Limits of this approach in general and with respect to p2p.
          describe how maps would look like.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Intra-Network Localization/Bottleneck Off-Loading">
          <t>The above sections described the results of the ALTO guidance on
          an inter-network level. However, ALTO can also be used to guide
          peers on which internal peers are to be preferred. For instance, to
          guide Peers on a remote network side to prefer to connect to each
          other, instead of crossing a bottleneck link, a backhaul link to
          connect the side to the network core. <xref
          target="fig.no_intra_network_local"></xref> shows such a scenario
          where Peer 1 and Peer 2 are located in Net 2 of ISP1 and connect via
          a low capacity link to the core (Net 1) of the same ISP1. Peer1 and
          Peer 2 would both exchange their data with remote peers, probably
          clogging the bottleneck link. </t>

          <t><figure anchor="fig.no_intra_network_local"
              title="Without Intra-Network ALTO Traffic Localization">
              <artwork><![CDATA[
                            ,-------.         +-----------+
       ,---.             ,-'         `-.      |   Peer 1  |
    ,-'     `-.         /     ISP 1  #########|ALTO Client|
   /           \       /      Net 2  #   \    +-----------+
  /    ISP 1    \      |     #########   |    +-----------+
 /     Net 1     \     \     #           /    |   Peer 2  |
;             ###;      \    #      ##########|ALTO Client|
|               X~~~~~~~~~~~~X#######,-'      +-----------+
|             ### |  ^      `-------'                      
|                 |  |
:                 ;  |
 \               /  Bottleneck 
  \             / 
   \           /
    `-.     ,-' 
       `---'  
    Legend:
    ### peer "connections"
    ~~~ bottleneck link
]]></artwork>
            </figure></t>

          <t>The operator can guide the peers in such a situation to try first
          local peers in the same network islands, avoiding or at least
          lowering the effect on the bottleneck link, as shown in <xref
          target="fig.intra_network_local"></xref>.</t>

          <t><figure anchor="fig.intra_network_local"
              title="With Intra-Network ALTO Traffic Localization">
              <artwork><![CDATA[
                            ,-------.         +-----------+
       ,---.             ,-'         `-.      |   Peer 1  |
    ,-'     `-.         /     ISP 1  #########|ALTO Client|
   /           \       /      Net 2  #   \    +-----------+
  /    ISP 1    \      |             #   |    +-----------+
 /     Net 1     \     \             #########|   Peer 2  |
;                ;      \           ##########|ALTO Client|
|                #~~~~~~~~~~~########,-'      +-----------+
|             ### |  ^      `-------'                      
|                 |  |
:                 ;  |
 \               /  Bottleneck 
  \             / 
   \           /
    `-.     ,-' 
       `---'  
    Legend:
    ### peer "connections"
    ~~~ bottleneck link
]]></artwork>
            </figure>TBD: describe how maps would look like.</t>
        </section>
      </section>
	 <section title="Provisiong ALTO Maps">
      <t>This section will describe how ALTO maps in the protocol can be
	  populated before using them.
	  </t>
	  </section>
	  
    </section>

	
	<section anchor="sec.ISP_deployment" title="Deployment Considerations by ISPs">
	  <t>The Internet is a large network constituted of multiple 
	  networks worldwide. Numerous of these networks are built by telecom 
	  operators or network operators (named ISP in this memo), and these networks 
	  provide network connectivity, such as cable 
	  networks, 3G and so on. As well as some of networks are built by universities 
	  or big organizations themselves, and these networks are used to provide 
	  connectivity for research and work. The essence of Internet is its 
	  connectivity and sharing capability. However, ISPs emphasize network's 
	  manageability and controllability, because ISPs provide public network 
	  access service for most person and families, they need to manage, to control 
	  and to audit the traffic. Thus, it's important for ISPs to understand the 
	  requirement of optimizing traffic, and how to deploy ALTO service in 
	  these manageability and controllability networks.
	  </t>
	
	<section anchor="sec.ISP_deployment_req" title="Requirement for Traffic Optimization by ISPs">
	  <t>All networks of ISPs are connected to each other through peering points. 
	  From view of business mode, the inter-network settlement is needed in traffic 
	  exchanging between these ISP's networks. The current settlement can be costly. 
	  So to save these cost, the simple and basic method is to decrease the traffic 
	  exchange across the peering points and keep the traffic in own network area.
	  </t>
	  <t>For some large ISPs, their whole network is layered. The upper layer network 
	  includes one or several backbone networks, and the lower layer network includes 
	  multiple access networks. These access networks are connected to backbone 
	  networks, and the exchange traffic with others through backbone network. In 
	  this kind of layered network, the bandwidth of backbone network is important 
	  and may be scarce. Traffic should be limited to the access networks, so to
          decrease the usage of backbone as far as possible.
	  </t>
	  <t>Compared to fixed networks, mobile networks have some special characters, 
	  including small link bandwidth, high cost, limited radio frequency resource, 
	  and terminal battery. In mobile network, the usage of wireless link should 
	  be decreased as far as possible and be high-efficient. For example, in the
          case of a P2P service, the clients in the fixed network should decrease the
          data transport  from the clients in the mobile networks, as well as the
          clients in the mobile networks should prefer the data transmission from the
          clients in the fixed networks.
	  </t>
	</section>
	
	<section anchor="sec.ISP_deployment2" title="Considerations for ISPs">
	<section title="Very small ISPs with simple Network Structure">
	<t>
	For very small ISPs, the traffic optimizing problem they focus is that how to decrease 
	the traffic exchanging with other ISPs, because of high settlement costs. To use the ALTO 
	service to optimize traffic, small ISPs can define two optimization areas: one 
	is their own network; the other is all outer networks connected with their network. 
	The cost map can be defined like this: the cost of link between clients of inner 
	ISP's networks is lower than from clients of outer ISP's networks to clients of 
	inner ISP's networks. So the client of this ISP will prefer to require data from 
	the clients in the same ISP with high priority.
	</t>
	<t>One example is given as below in <xref target="fig.small_ISPs3"/>. ISP A is one small ISP, only having one access 
	network. In ALTO service deploying, we can define ISP A to be one optimization area, 
	named as PID1, and define other networks to be the other optimization area, named as 
	PID2. C1 is denoted as the link cost in inner ISP A. C2 is denoted as the link cost 
	from PID2 to PID1. We define the cost map as:
	</t>
	<t>C1&lt;C2	</t>
	<figure anchor="fig.small_ISPs3"
              title="ALTO deployment in small ISPs">
        <artwork><![CDATA[
           -----------
       ////           \\\\
     //                   \\
   //                       \\                  /-----------\
  | +---------+               |             ////             \\\\
  | | ALTO    |  ISP A        |    C2      |    Other Networks   |
 |  | Service |  PID 1         <-----------     PID 2
  | +---------+  C1           |            |                     |
  |                           |             \\\\             ////
   \\                       //                  \-----------/
     \\                   //
       \\\\           ////
           -----------

	]]></artwork>
    </figure>	
	</section>
	
	<section title="Large ISPs with layered fixed Network Structure">
	<t>For large ISPs with layered fixed network structure, the traffic 
	optimizing problems they focus will include that: using backbone 
	network by high-efficiency, adjusting traffic balance in different 
	access networks according to traffic conditions and management 
	policies, and considering settlement cost with other ISPs. So in 
	ALTO service deploying to this kind of large ISP, first the 
	optimization area can be defined according to real network 
	condition. For example, each access network can be defined to 
	be one optimization area. Then cost can be defined according to 
	the optimizing requirement by ISPs. There is one example described
        below and also shown in <xref target="fig.large_ISPs"/>.
	</t>
	
	<t>In this example, ISP A has one backbone network and three 
	access networks, named as AN A, AN B, and AN C. A P2P application 
	is used in this example. For the traffic optimization, the first 
	requirement is to decrease the P2P traffic of backbone network 
	in inner ISP A; and the second requirement is to decrease the P2P 
	traffic to outer ISPs. Always, the second requirement is prior to 
	the first one. Also, we assume that the settlement rate with ISP B 
	is lower than with other ISPs. Then ISP A can deploy ALTO service 
	to meet the need of traffic optimization. We will give the detail 
	example of ALTO service definition and configuration according to 
	requirements above.
	</t>
	
	<t>In inner network of ISP A, we can define each access network to 
	be one optimization area, and assign one PID to every access network, 
	such as PID1, PID2, and PID 3. Because of different settlement with 
	different outer ISPs, we define ISP B to be one optimization area, 
	and assign PID 4 to it, as well as define all other networks to be 
	one optimization area and PID 5.
	</t>
	
	<t>We assign cost names (C1, C2, C3, C4, C5, C6, C7) as the figure 
	below. C1 is denoted as the link cost in inner AN A, the same as C2 
	and C3. C4 is denoted as the link cost from PID 1 to PID 2, the same 
	as C5. C6 is denoted as the link cost from the ISP B to ISP A. C7 is 
	denoted as the link cost from other networks to ISP A.
	</t>
	
	<t>	According to discussion of the first requirement and the second 
	requirement above, the relationship of these costs will be defined as:
	(C1, C2, C3) &lt; (C4, C5) &lt; (C6) &lt; (C7)
	</t>
	<t>This is one very simple example above, in which we do not consider 
	the different link type of access network. In deploying ALTO service 
	in real network, we must consider more real network conditions and 
	requirements. One real example is described in greater detail in
        <xref target="I-D.lee-alto-chinatelecom-trial"></xref>.
	</t>
	
<figure anchor="fig.large_ISPs" title="ALTO deployment in large ISPs with layered 
fixed network structures">
        <artwork><![CDATA[
 +------------------------------------+         +----------------+
 | ISP A  +---------------+           |         |                |
 |        |    Backbone   |           |   C6    |      ISP B     |
 |     +--+    Network    +---+       |<--------+      PID 4     |
 |     |  +-------+-------+   |       |         |                |
 |     |          |           |       |         |                |
 |     |          |           |       |         +----------------+
 | +---+--+    +--+---+     +-+----+  |
 | |AN A  | C4 |AN B  |  C5 |AN C  |  |
 | |PID 1 +--->|PID 2 |<----+PID 3 |  |
 | |C1    |    |C2    |     |C3    |  |         +----------------+
 | +---+--+    +---+--+     +-+----+  |         |                |
 |                                    |   C7    | Other Networks |
 |                                    |<--------+ PID 5          |
 |                                    |         |                |
 |                                    |         |                |
 +------------------------------------+         +----------------+

	]]></artwork>
    </figure>	
    </section>	
	
	<section title="ISPs with Mobile Network">
	<t>For ISPs with mobile network and fixed network, the traffic 
	optimizing problems they focus will be optimizing the mobile traffic, 
	except problems on last hop section. Wireless radio frequency resource 
	is scarce and costly in mobile network. The requirement of traffic 
	optimization in mobile network is mainly decreasing the usage of radio 
	resource. The ALTO service can be deployed to meet these needs.
	</t>
	
	<t>For example in one ISP A as below in <xref target="fig.mobile_ISPs2"/>,
        there is one mobile network 
	is connected to backbone network. In this kind of network structure, 
	mobile network can be defined as one optimization area, and assigned 
	PID 1. We also define other PID and cost as figure below.
	</t>
	
	<t>To decrease the usage of wireless link, the relationship of these 
	costs will be defined to:
	</t>
	
	<t>From view of mobile network:(C4 &lt; C1). This means that, the 
	clients in mobile network requiring data resource from clients of 
	the other access networks is prior to clients of mobile network. 
	This policy can decrease the usage of wireless link and power 
	consumption in terminal.	
	</t>
	
	<t>From view of AN A:(C2 &lt; C6, C5 = maximum cost). This means that, 
	to other optimization area, requiring data from mobile network should 
	be avoided.	
	</t>
	<figure anchor="fig.mobile_ISPs2" title="ALTO deployment in ISPs with mobile network">
        <artwork><![CDATA[
 +-----------------------------------------------------------------+
 |                                                                 |
 |  ISP A                 +-------------+                          |
 |               +--------+   ALTO      +---------+                |
 |               |        |   Service   |         |                |
 |               |        +------+------+         |                |
 |               |               |                |                |
 |               |               |                |                |
 |               |               |                |                |
 |       +-------+-------+       | C6    +--------+------+         |
 |       |     AN A      |<--------------       AN B     |         |
 |       |     PID 2     |   C7  |       |      PID 3    |         |
 |       |     C2         -------------->|      C3       |         |
 |       +---------------+       |       +---------------+         |
 |             ^    |            |              |     ^            |
 |             |    |            |              |     |            |
 |             |    |C4          |              |     |            |
 |          C5 |    |            |              |     |            |
 |             |    |   +--------+---------+    |     |            |
 |             |    +-->|  Mobile Network  |<---+     |            |
 |             |        |  PID 1           |          |            |
 |             +------- |  C1              |----------+            |
 |                      +------------------+                       |
 +-----------------------------------------------------------------+

	]]></artwork>
    </figure>			
	</section>
	</section>
	
	</section>
	
	
	
	
	
    <section anchor="sec.p2p_cons" title="Using ALTO for P2P">
      <figure anchor="fig.global_tracker"
              title="Global tracker accessing ALTO server at various ISPs">
        <artwork><![CDATA[                              ,-------.
       ,---.               ,-'         `-.   +-----------+
    ,-'     `-.           /     ISP 1     \  |   Peer 1  |*****
   /           \         / +-------------+ \ |           |    *
  /    ISP X    \   +=====>+ ALTO Server |  )+-----------+    *
 /               \  =    \ +-------------+ / +-----------+    *
; +-----------+   : =     \               /  |   Peer 2  |    *
| |  Tracker  |<====+      `-.         ,-'   |           |*****
| |ALTO Client|<====+         `-------'      +-----------+   **
| +-----------+   | =         ,-------.                      **
:        *        ; =      ,-'         `-.   +-----------+   **
 \       *       /  =     /     ISP 2     \  |   Peer 3  |   **
  \      *      /   =    / +-------------+ \ |           |*****
   \     *     /    +=====>| ALTO Server |  )+-----------+  ***
    `-.  *  ,-'          \ +-------------+ / +-----------+  ***
       `-*-'              \               /  |   Peer 4  |*****
         *                 `-.         ,-'   |           | ****
         *                    `-------'      +-----------+ ****
         *                                                 ****
         *                                                 ****
         ***********************************************<******
    Legend:
    === ALTO client protocol
    *** Application protocol
]]></artwork>
      </figure>

      <t><xref target="fig.global_tracker"></xref> depicts a tracker-based
      system, where the tracker embeds the ALTO client. The tracker itself is
      hosted and operated by an entity different than the ISP hosting and
      operating the ALTO server. Initially, the tracker has to look-up the
      ALTO server in charge for each peer where it receives a ALTO query for.
      Therefore, the ALTO server has to discover the handling ALTO server, as
      described in <xref target="I-D.ietf-alto-server-discovery"></xref>.
	However, the
      peers do not have any way to query the server themselves. This setting
      allows to give the peers a better selection of candidate peers for their
      operation at an initial time, but does not consider peers learned
      through direct peer-to-peer knowledge exchange. This is called peer
      exchange (PEX) in bittorent, for instance.</t>

      <t><figure anchor="fig.localALTOServer"
          title="Global Tracker - Local ALTO Servers">
          <artwork><![CDATA[
                         ,-------.         +-----------+
       ,---.          ,-'         `-.  +==>|   Peer 1  |*****
    ,-'     `-.      /     ISP 1     \ =   |ALTO Client|    *
   /           \    / +-------------+<=+   +-----------+    *
  /    ISP X    \   | + ALTO Server |<=+   +-----------+    *
 /               \  \ +-------------+ /=   |   Peer 2  |    *
;   +---------+   :  \               / +==>|ALTO Client|*****
|   | Global  |   |   `-.         ,-'      +-----------+   **
|   | Tracker |   |      `-------'                         **
|   +---------+   |      ,-------.         +-----------+   **
:        *        ;   ,-'         `-.  +==>|   Peer 3  |   **
 \       *       /   /     ISP 2     \ =   |ALTO Client|*****
  \      *      /   / +-------------+<=+   +-----------+  ***
   \     *     /    | | ALTO Server |<=+   +-----------+  ***
    `-.  *  ,-'     \ +-------------+ /=   |   Peer 4  |*****
       `-*-'         \               / +==>|ALTO Client| ****
         *            `-.         ,-'      +-----------+ ****
         *               `-------'                       ****
         *                                               ****
         ***********************************************<****
    Legend:
    === ALTO client protocol
    *** Application protocol


]]></artwork>
        </figure>The scenario in <xref target="fig.localALTOServer"></xref>
      lets the peers directly communicate with their ISP's ALTO server (i.e.,
      ALTO client embedded in the peers), giving thus the peers the most
      control on which information they query for, as they can integrate
      information received from trackers and through direct peer-to-peer
      knowledge exchange.</t>

      <t><figure anchor="fig-p4p_approach"
          title="P4P approach with local tracker and local ALTO server">
          <artwork><![CDATA[
                          ,-------.         +-----------+
        ,---.          ,-'  ISP 1  `-.  ***>|   Peer 1  |
     ,-'     `-.      /+-------------+\ *   |           |
    /           \    / +   Tracker   |<**   +-----------+
   /    ISP X    \   | +-----===-----+<**   +-----------+
  /               \  \ +-----===-----+ /*   |   Peer 2  |
 ;   +---------+   :  \+ ALTO Server |/ ***>|           |
 |   | Global  |   |   +-------------+      +-----------+
 |   | Tracker |   |      `-------'
 |   +---------+   |                        +-----------+
 :          ^      ;      ,-------.         |   Peer 3  |
  \         *     /    ,-'  ISP 2  `-.  ***>|           |
   \        *    /    /+-------------+\ *   +-----------+
    \       *   /    / +   Tracker   |<**   +-----------+
     `-.    *,-'     | +-----===-----+ |    |   Peer 4  |<*
        `---*        \ +-----===-----+ /    |           | *
            *         \+ ALTO Server |/     +-----------+ *
            *          +-------------+                    *
            *             `-------'                       *
            ***********************************************
     Legend:
     === ALTO client protocol
     *** Application protocol
]]></artwork>
        </figure></t>

      <t>There are some attempts to let ISP's to deploy their own trackers, as
      shown in <xref target="fig-p4p_approach"></xref>. In this case, the
      client has no chance to get guidance from the ALTO server, other than
      talking to the ISP's tracker. However, the peers would have still chance
      the contact other trackers, deployed by entities other than the peer's
      ISP.</t>

      <t><xref target="fig-p4p_approach"></xref> and <xref
      target="fig.global_tracker"></xref> ostensibly take peers the
      possibility to directly query the ALTO server, if the communication with
      the ALTO server is not permitted for any reason. However, considering
      the plethora of different applications of ALTO, e.g., multiple tracker
      and non-tracker based P2P systems and or applications searching for
      relays, it seems to be beneficial for all participants to let the peers
      directly query the ALTO server. The peers are also the single point
      having all operational knowledge to decide whether to use the ALTO
      guidance and how to use the ALTO guidance. This is a preference for the
      scenario depicted in Figure <xref
      target="fig.localALTOServer"></xref>.</t>





    <section anchor="sec.alto_in_tracker_p2p" title="Using ALTO for Tracker-based Peer-to-Peer Applications">

        <t>The scope of this section is the interaction of peer-to-peer
        applications that use a centralized resource directory ("tracker"),
        with the ALTO service. In this scenario, the resource consumer
        ("peer") asks the resource directory for a list of candidate
        resource providers, which can provide the desired resource.</t>

        <t>For efficiency reasons (i.e., message size), usually only a
        subset of all resource providers known to the resource directory
        will be returned to the resource consumer.  Some or all of these
        resource providers, plus further resource providers learned by other
        means such as direct communication between peers, will be contacted
        by the resource consumer for accessing the resource.  The purpose of
        ALTO is giving guidance on this peer selection, which is supposed to
        yield better-than-random results.
        
        The tracker response as well as the ALTO guidance are most
        beneficial in the initial phase after the resource consumer has
        decided to access a resource, as long as only few resource providers
        are known. Later, when the resource consumer has already exchanged
        some data with other peers and measured the transmission speed,
        the relative importance of ALTO may dwindle.</t>
        
        <t>The ALTO protocol specification
        <xref target="I-D.ietf-alto-protocol"/> details how an ALTO client
        can query an ALTO server for guiding information and receive the
        corresponding replies. However, in the considered scenario of a
        tracker-based P2P application, there are two fundamentally different
        possibilities where to place the ALTO client:</t>


            <t><list style='numbers'>
                <t>ALTO client in the resource consumer ("peer")</t>
                <t>ALTO client in the resource directory ("tracker")</t>
            </list></t>

            <t>In the following, both scenarios are compared in order to 
            explain the need for third-party ALTO queries.</t>

            <t>In the first scenario (see <xref target="fig.rcq"/>),
            the resource consumer queries the resource directory
            for the desired resource (F1). 
            The resource directory returns a list
            of potential resource providers without considering ALTO (F2).
            It is
            then the duty of the resource consumer to invoke ALTO (F3/F4),
            in order to solicit guidance regarding this list.</t>

            <t>In the second scenario (see <xref target="fig.3pq"/>),
            the resource directory has an
            embedded ALTO client, which we will refer to as RDAC in this
            document. After receiving a query for a given resource (F1)
            the resource directory invokes the RDAC to evaluate
            all resource providers it knows (F2/F3).  Then it returns a, 
            possibly
            shortened, list containing the "best" resource providers to the
            resource consumer (F4).</t>



	<t>
      <figure anchor="fig.tracker_random_preselect"
              title="Tracker-based P2P Application with random peer preselection">
        <artwork><![CDATA[
 .............................          .............................
 : Tracker                   :          : Peer                      :
 :   ______                  :          :                           :
 : +-______-+                :          :            k good         :
 : |        |     +--------+ : P2P App. : +--------+ peers +------+ :
 : |   N    |     | random | : Protocol : | ALTO-  |------>| data | :
 : | known  |====>| pre-   |*************>| biased |       | ex-  | :
 : | peers, |     | selec- | : transmit : | peer   |------>| cha- | :
 : | M good |     | tion   | : n peer   : | select | n-k   | nge  | :
 : +-______-+     +--------+ : IDs      : +--------+ bad p.+------+ :
 :...........................:          :.....^.....................:
											  |
                                              | ALTO
                                              | client protocol
                                            __|___
                                          +-______-+
                                          |        |
                                          | ALTO   |
                                          | server |
                                          +-______-+
]]></artwork>
        </figure></t>



        <t><figure anchor="fig.rcq" 
            title="Basic message sequence chart for 
            resource consumer-initiated ALTO query">
            <artwork><![CDATA[
Peer w. ALTO cli.            Tracker               ALTO Server 
--------+--------       --------+--------       --------+--------
        | F1 Tracker query      |                       |    
        |======================>|                       |
        | F2 Tracker reply      |                       |    
        |<======================|                       |    
        | F3 ALTO client protocol query                 |
        |---------------------------------------------->|    
        | F4 ALTO client protocol reply                 |
        |<----------------------------------------------|    
        |                       |                       |    

====  Application protocol (i.e., tracker-based P2P app protocol)
----  ALTO client protocol
]]></artwork>
        </figure></t>



	<t>
      <figure anchor="fig.tracker_alto_client"
              title="Tracker-based P2P Application with ALTO client in tracker">
        <artwork><![CDATA[
 .............................          .............................
 : Tracker                   :          : Peer                      :
 :   ______                  :          :                           :
 : +-______-+                :          :                           :
 : |        |     +--------+ : P2P App. :  k good peers &  +------+ :
 : |   N    |     | ALTO-  | : Protocol :  n-k bad peers   | data | :
 : | known  |====>| biased |******************************>| ex-  | :
 : | peers, |     | peer   | : transmit :                  | cha- | :
 : | M good |     | select | : n peer   :                  | nge  | :
 : +-______-+     +--------+ : IDs      :                  +------+ :
 :.....................^.....:          :...........................:
                       |
                       | ALTO
                       | client protocol
                     __|___
                   +-______-+
                   |        |
                   | ALTO   |
                   | server |
                   +-______-+
]]></artwork>
        </figure></t>



        <t><figure anchor="fig.3pq" 
            title="Basic message sequence chart for third-party ALTO query">
            <artwork><![CDATA[
      Peer               Tracker w. RDAC           ALTO Server 
--------+--------       --------+--------       --------+--------
        | F1 Tracker query      |                       |    
        |======================>|                       |
        |                       | F2 ALTO cli. p. query |
        |                       |---------------------->|    
        |                       | F3 ALTO cli. p. reply |
        |                       |<----------------------|
        | F4 Tracker reply      |                       |    
        |<======================|                       |    
        |                       |                       |    

====  Application protocol (i.e., tracker-based P2P app protocol)
----  ALTO client protocol
]]></artwork>
        </figure></t>



            <t>Note: the message sequences depicted in 
            <xref target="fig.rcq"/> and <xref target="fig.3pq"/> may occur 
            both in the target-aware and the target-independent query mode 
            (c.f. <xref target="RFC6708"/>). In the 
            target-independent query mode 
            no message exchange with the ALTO server might be needed after 
            the tracker query, because the candidate resource providers could
            be evaluated using a locally cached "map", which has been
            retrieved from the ALTO server some time ago.</t>

            
            <t>The problem with the first
            approach is, that while the resource directory might know
            thousands of peers taking part in a swarm, the list returned to
            the resource consumer is usually shortened for efficiency
            reasons. Therefore, the "best" (in the sense of ALTO) potential
            resource providers might not be contained in that list anymore,
            even before ALTO can consider them.</t>

            <t>For illustration, consider a simple model of a swarm, in
            which all peers fall into one of only two categories: assume
            that there are "good" ("good" in the sense of ALTO's 
            better-than-random peer selection, based on an arbitrary desired
            rating criterion) and "bad' peers only. Having more different
            categories makes the maths more complex but does not change
            anything to the basic outcome of this analysis.
            ssume that the swarm has a total number of N peers, out
            of which are M "good" and N-M "bad" peers, which are all
            known to the tracker. A new peer wants to join the swarm and 
            therefore asks the tracker for a list of peers.</t>

            <t>If, according to the first approach, the tracker randomly
            picks n peers from the N known peers, the result can be
            described with the hypergeometric distribution. The probability
            that the tracker reply contains exactly k "good" peers (and
            n-k "bad" peers) is:</t>

<t><artwork><![CDATA[

            / m \   / N - m \
            \ k /   \ n - k /
P(X=k) =  ---------------------
                  / N \
                  \ n /


        / n \        n!
with    \ k /  = -----------    and    n! = n * (n-1) * (n-2) * .. * 1
                  k! (n-k)!

]]></artwork></t>

            <t>The probability that the reply contains at most k "good"
            peers is: P(X&lt;=k)=P(X=0)+P(X=1)+..+P(X=k).</t>

            <t>For example, consider a swarm with N=10,000 peers known to the
            tracker, out of which M=100 are "good" peers. If the tracker
            randomly selects n=100 peers, the formula yields for the
            reply: P(X=0)=36%, P(X&lt;=4)=99%. That is, 
            with a probability of approx. 36% this list
            does not contain a single "good" peer, and with 99%
            probability there are only four or less of the "good" peers on
            the list.  Processing this
            list with the guiding ALTO information will ensure that the few
            favorable peers are ranked to the top of the list; however, the
            benefit is rather limited as the number of favorable peers in
            the list is just too small.</t>
            
            <t>Much better traffic optimization
            could be achieved if the tracker would evaluate all known peers
            using ALTO, and return a list of 100 peers afterwards.
            This list would then include a significantly higher fraction of 
            "good" peers. (Note, that if the tracker returned
            "good" peers only, there might be a risk that the swarm might
            disconnect and split into several disjunct partitions.  However,
            finding the right mix of ALTO-biased and random peer selection
            is out of the scope of this document.) </t>
            
            <t>Therefore, from an overall optimization perspective,
            the second scenario with the ALTO client embedded in
            the resource directory
            is advantageous, because it is ensured that the
            addresses of the "best" resource providers are actually
            delivered to the resource consumer. An architectural
            implication of this insight is that the ALTO server discovery
            procedures must support third-party discovery. That is,
            as the tracker issues ALTO queries on behalf of the peer
            which contacted the tracker, the
            tracker must be able to discover an ALTO server that can
            give guidance suitable for the that respective peer.</t>

    </section>




      <section anchor="sec.alto_p2p_expectations" title="Expectations of ALTO">
        <t>This section hints to some recent experiments conducted with
        ALTO-like deployments in Internet Service Provider (ISP) network's.
        NTT performed tests with their HINT server implementation and dummy
        nodes to gain insight on how an ALTO-like service influence a
        peer-to-peer systems <xref
        target="I-D.kamei-p2p-experiments-japan"></xref>. The results of an
        early experiment conducted in the Comcast network are documented
        here<xref target="RFC5632"></xref></t>
      </section>
    </section>

	
	
    <section anchor="sec.cdn_cons" title="Using ALTO for CDNs">
      <t><xref target="sec.general_deployment"></xref> discussed the placement and
      usage of ALTO for P2P systems, but not beyond. This section discuss the
      usage of ALTO for Content Delivery Networks (CDNs). CDNs are used to
      bring a service (e.g., a web page, videos, etc) closer to the location
      of the user &ndash; where close refers to shorten the distance between
      the client and the server in the IP topology. CDNs use several
      techniques to decide which server is closest to a client requesting a
      service. One common way to do so, is relying on the DNS system, but
      there are many other ways, see <xref target="RFC3568"></xref>.</t>

      <t>The general issue for CDNs, independent of DNS or HTTP Redirect based
      approaches (see, for instance, <xref
      target="I-D.penno-alto-cdn"></xref>), is that the CDN logic has to match
      the client's IP address with the closest CDN cache. This matching is not
      trivial, for instance, in DNS based approaches, where the IP address of
      the DNS original requester is unknown (see <xref
      target="I-D.vandergaast-edns-client-ip"></xref> for a discussion of this
      and a solution approach).</t>

   <section title="Request Routing using the Endpoint Cost Service">
    <t>Alternatively, the Request Router may request the Endpoint service
    from the ALTO client.</t>

    <t>Specifically, the Request Router requests the Endpoint Cost Service
    in order to rank/rate the content locations (i.e., IP addresses of
    CDN nodes) based on their distance/cost (by default the Endpoint
    Cost Service operates based on Routing Distance) from/to the user
    address.</t>

    <t>Once the Request Router obtained from the ALTO Server the ranked
list
    of locations (for the specific user) it can incorporate this
    information into its selection mechanisms in order to point the user
    to the most appropriate location.</t>

    <t>A Request Router that uses the Endpoint Cost Service may query the
    ALTO Server for rankings of CDN Node IP addresses for each
    interesting host and cache the results for later usage.</t>

    <t>Maps Services and ECS deliver similar ALTO service by allowing the
    CDN to optimize internal selection mechanisms. Both services deliver
    similar level of security, confidentiality of layer-specific
    information (i.e.: application and network) however, Maps and ECS
    differ in the way the ALTO service is delivered and address a
    different set of requirements in terms of topology information and
    network operations.</t>

   <section title="ALTO Topology Vs. Network Topology">

    <t>The ALTO server builds a ALTO-specific network topology that
    represents the network as it should be understood and utilized by
the
    application layer (the CDN). Besides the security requirements that
    consist of not delivering any confidential or critical information
    about the infrastructure, there are efficiency requirements in terms
    of what visibility of the network, and which level of granularity,
it
    is required by the CDN and more in general by the application layer.
    </t>

    <t>The ALTO server builds topology (for either Map and ECS services)
    based on multiple sources that may include: routing protocols,
network
    policies, state and performance information, geo-location, etc. In
all
    cases, the ALTO topology will not contain any details that would
    endanger the network integrity and security (e.g.: There will be no
    leaking of OSPF/ISIS/BGP databases to ALTO clients).</t>
    </section>

   <section title="Topology Computation and ECS Delivery">

    <t>ECS allows the CDN not to have to implement any specific algorithm
    or mechanism in order to retrieve, maintain and process network
    topology information (of any kind). The complexity of the network
    topology (computation, maintenance and distribution) is kept in the
    ALTO server and ECS is delivered on demand. Thus ECS is used in
    order to implement a lightweight integration of ALTO services in
    the CDN layer. ECS implies an ALTO and CDN implementation with the
    necessary scalability in order to cope with the amount of
    transactions that CDN and ALTO server will have to handle (knowing
    that the CDN is able to cache ALTO ECS results for further use).
    </t>

    <t>The ALTO server delivering ECS may integrate various information
    sources such as routing topology, policies, state and performance,
    geo-location, etc, and deliver the ranking service to the CDN upon
    request.  The network topology information is controlled, managed
    by the ALTO server and the CDN benefits from ranking services in
    order to optimize application layer mechanisms used for content
    location selection. This allows the ALTO server to enhance and
    modify the way the topology information sources are used and
    combined without requiring any update in the mechanisms the ECS
    is delivered and do not require any update process between ALTO and
    the CDN.</t>
    </section>

   <section title="Ranking Service">

    <t>When a user request a given content, the CDN locates the content in
    one or more caches and executes a selection algorithms in order to
    redirect the user to the 'best' cache.  In order to achieve that,
the
    CDN issues an ECS request with the endpoint address (IPv4/IPv6) of
    the user (content requester) and the set of endpoint addresses of
the
    content caches (content targets).  The ALTO server, receives the
    request and ranks the list of content targets addresses based on
    their distance from the content requester.  By default, according to
    <xref target="I-D.ietf-alto-protocol"/>, the distance represents the
    routing cost as
    computed by the routing layer (OSPF, ISIS, BGP) and may take into
    consideration other routing criteria such as MPLS-VPN (MP-BGP) and
    MPLS-TE (RSVP), policy and state and performance information in
    addition to other information sources (policy, geo-location, state
    and performance).</t>

    <t>Once the ALTO server computed the distance it replies with the
ranked
    list of content target addresses.  The list being ranked by
distance,
    the CDN is capable of integrating the rankings into its selection
    process (that will also incorporate other criteria) and redirect the
    user accordingly.</t>
   </section>

   <section title="Ranking and Network Events">

    <t>ALTO server ranks addresses based on topology information it
acquires
    from the network.  The different methods and algorithms through
which
    the ALTO server computes topology information and rankings is out of
    the scope of this document.  However, and in the case the rankings
    are based on routing (IP/MPLS) topology, it is obvious that network
    events may impact the ranking computation.  The scope of the ECS
    service delivered to a CDN is not to maintain the CDN aware of any
    possible network topology changes since, due to redundancy of
current
    networks, most of the network events happening in the infrastructure
    will have limited impact on the CDN.  However, catastrophic events
    such as main trunks failures or backbone partition will have to take
    into account by the ALTO server so to redirect traffic away from the
    failure impacted area.</t>
   </section>

   <section title="Caching and Lifetime">

    <t>Each reply sent back by the ALTO server to the ALTO client running
in
    the CDN has a validity in time so that the CDN can cache the results
    in order to re-use it and hence reducing the number of transactions
    between CDN and ALTO server.  The ALTO server may indicate in the
    reply message how long the content of the message is to be
considered
    reliable and insert a lifetime value that will be used by the CDN in
    order to cache (and then flush or refresh) the entry.</t>

    <t>An ALTO server implementation may want to keep state about ALTO
clients
    so to inform and signal to these clients when a major network event
    happened so to clear the ALTO cache in the client. In a CDN/ALTO
    interworking architecture where there's a few CDN component
interacting
    with the ALTO server there are no scalability issues in maintaining
    state about clients in the ALTO server.</t>
   </section>

   <section title="Redirection">

    <t>When ALTO server receives an ECS request, it may not have the most
    appropriate topology information in order to accurately determine
the
    ranking.  In such case, the ALTO server, may want to adopt the
    following strategies:
    <list style="symbols">

    <t>Reply with available information (best effort).</t>

    <t>Redirect the request to another ALTO server presumed to have
       better topology information (redirection).</t>

    <t>Doing both (best effort and redirection).  In this case, the
reply
       message contains both the rankings and the indication of another
       ALTO server where more accurate rankings may be delivered.</t>
     </list>

	</t>

    <t>The decision process that is used to determine if redirection is
    necessary (and which mode to use) is out of the scope of this
    document.  As an example, an ALTO server may decide to redirect any
    request having addresses that are located into a remote Autonomous
    System.  In such case the redirection message includes the ALTO
    server to be used and that resides in the remote AS.  Redirection
    implies communication between ALTO servers so to be able to signal
    their identity, location and type of visibility (AS number).</t>
    </section>

   <section title="Groups and Costs">

    <t>An automated ALTO implementation may use dynamic algorithms to
    aggregate network topology.  However, it is often desirable to
have a
    mechanism through which the network operator can control the level
    and details of network aggregation based on a set of requirements
and
    constraints.  IP/MPLS networks make use of a common mechanism to
    aggregate and group prefixes that is called BGP Communities.  BGP is
    the protocol all SP networks use in order to exchange information
    about their prefix reachability.  BGP Community us an attribute used
    to tag a prefix so to group prefixes based on mostly any criteria
(as
    an example, most SP networks originate BGP prefixes with communities
    identifying the Point of Presence (PoP) where the prefix has been
    originated).</t>

    <t>The ALTO server may leverage the BGP information that is available
in
    the SP network layer and compute group of prefixes.  By policy, the
    ALTO server operator may decide an arbitrary cost to set between
    groups.  Alternatively, there are algorithms that allows a dynamic
    computation of cost between groups.</t>
    </section>
    </section>
    </section>

	
    <section anchor="sec.advanced" title="Advanced Features">
<section anchor="advanced" title="Cascading ALTO Servers">
      <t>The main assumptions of ALTO seems to be each ISP operates its own
      ALTO server independently, irrespectively of the ISP's situation. This
      may true for most envisioned deployments of ALTO but there are certain
      deployments that may have different settings. <xref
      target="fig-alto-proxy"></xref> shows such setting, were for example, a
      university network is connected to two upstream providers. ISP2 if the
      national research network and ISP1 is a commercial upstream provider to
      this university network. The university, as well as ISP1, are operating
      their own ALTO server. The ALTO clients, located on the peers will
      contact the ALTO server located at the university.</t>

      <t><figure anchor="fig-alto-proxy" title="Cascaded ALTO Server">
          <artwork><![CDATA[
      +-----------+
      |   ISP1    |
      |   ALTO    |
      |  Server   |
      +----------=+
         ,-------=            ,------.
      ,-'        =`-.      ,-'         `-.
     /   Upstream=   \    /   Upstream    \
    (       ISP1 =    )  (       ISP2      )
     \           =   /    \               /
      `-.        =,-'      `-.         ,-'
         `---+---=            `+------'
             |   =             |
             |   =======================
             |,-------------.  |       =
           ,-+               `-+    +-----------+
         ,'      University     `.  |University |
        (        Network          ) |   ALTO    |
         `.  =======================|  Server   |
           `-=               +-'    +-----------+
             =`+------------'|
             = |             |
      +--------+-+         +-+--------+
      |   Peer1  |         |   PeerN  |
      +----------+         +----------+
]]></artwork>
        </figure></t>

      <t>In this setting all "destinations" useful for the peers within ISP2
      are free-of-charge for the peers located in the university network
      (i.e., they are preferred in the rating of the ALTO server). However,
      all traffic that is not towards ISP2 will be handled by the ISP1
      upstream provider. Therefore, the ALTO server at the university has also
      to include the guidance given by the ISP1 ALTO server in its replies to
      the ALTO clients. This can be called cascaded ALTO servers.</t>
    </section>
	
	<section anchor="sec.v4v6" title="ALTO for IPv4 and IPv6">
	<t>TBD</t>
	</section>

	<section anchor="sec.monitoring" title="Monitoring ALTO">
      <t>In addition to providing configuration, an ISP providing ALTO may want 
	  to deploy a monitoring infrastructure to assess the benefits of ALTO and 
	  adjust its ALTO configuration according to the results of the monitoring.</t>
	  
	  <t>To construct an effective monitoring infrastructure, the ISP should
	  (1) define the performance metrics to be monitored; (2) and identify and 
	  deploy data sources to collect data to compute the performance metrics. We 
	  discuss both below.</t>

	  <t>[Editor's note: Is there a relationship to the IPPM working group
          at the IETF?]</t>

	  <section title="Monitoring Metrics Definition">
	  <t><list style='symbols'>
		<t>Inter-domain ALTO-Integrated Application Traffic (Network metric): 
		This metric includes total cross domain traffic generated by applications 
		that utilize ALTO guidance.  This metric evaluates the impacts of ALTO on 
		the inbound and outbound traffic of a domain.</t>
		
		<t>Total Inter-domain Traffic (Network metric): This is similar to the 
		preceding but focuses on all of the traffic, ALTO aware or not. One 
		possibility is that some of the reduction of interdomain traffic by 
		ALTO aware applications may (XXX missing words?). This metric is always 
                used with the preceding 
		and the following metrics.</t>
		
		<t>Intra-domain ALTO-Integrated Application Traffic (Network metric).
                (XXX description missing)</t>
		
		<t>Network hop count (Network metric): This metric provides the average 
		number of hops that traffic traverses inside a domain. ALTO may reduce 
		not only traffic volume but also the hops. The metric can also indirectly 
		reflect some application performance (e.g., latency).</t>
		
		<t>Application download rate (Application metric): This metric measures 
		application performance directly. Download means inbound traffic to one 
		user. Global average means the average value of all users' download rates 
		in one or more domains.</t>
		
		<t>Application Client type audit(Application metric): this metric gives 
		the audit of client types in ALTO service. The current types include fixed 
		network client and mobile network client.</t></list>
	  </t>
	  </section>
	  <section title="Monitoring Data Sources">
	  <t>The preceding metrics are derived from data sources. We identify three data 
	  sources.</t>
	  <t><list style='numbers'>
		<t>Application Log Server: Many application systems deploy Log Servers to 
		collect data.</t>
		
		<t>P2P Clients: Some P2P applications may not have Log Servers. When available, 
		P2P client logs can provide data. This is for P2P application</t>
		
		<t>OAM: Many ISPs deploy OAM systems to monitor IP layer traffic. An OAM 
		provides traffic monitoring of every network device in its management area. 
		It provides data such as link physical bandwidth and traffic volumes.</t>
              </list>
	  </t> 
	  </section>
	  <section title="Monitoring Structure">
	  <t>As discussed in the preceding section, some data sources are from ISP 
	  while some others are from application.  When there is a collaboration 
	  agreement between the ISP and an application, there can be an integrated 
	  monitoring system as shown in the figure below.  In particular, an application 
	  developer may deploy Monitor Clients to communicate with Monitor Server of 
	  the ISP to transmit raw data from the Log Server or P2P clients of the application 
	  to the ISP.</t>
      <t><figure anchor="fig.alto-monitoring" title="Monitoring Structure">
          <artwork><![CDATA[
  +------------------------------------------------+
  |                                                |
  |  New Entities            +--------------------------------------+
  |                          |                Service Provider      |
  |                          |                (P2P/CDN Operator etc)|
  |    +-----------+         |   +-----------+     |                |
  |    |ALTO Server|-------------|ALTO Client|     |                |
  |    +-----------+         |   +-----------+     |                |
  |                          |                     |  +----------+  |
  |                          |                     |  |Log Server|  |
  |                          |                     |  +----------+  |
  |   +--------------+       |  +--------------+   |  +----------+  |
  |   |Monitor Server|----------|Monitor Client|   |  |P2P Client|  |
  |   +--------------+       |  +--------------+   |  +----------+  |
  |          |               |                     |                |
  | +--------|--------+      +--------------------------------------+
  +-|--------|--------|----------------------------+
    |        |        |
    |        |        |
    |      +---+      |
    |      |OAM|      |
    |      +---+      |
    |             ISP |
     -----------------
]]></artwork>
        </figure></t>	  
	  
	  </section>
	</section>
	
</section>
	
	
   

    <section anchor="risks" title="Known Limitations of ALTO">
      <t>This section describes some known limitations of ALTO in general or
      specific mechanisms in ALTO.</t>

      <section title="Limitations of Map-based Approaches">
        <t>The specification of the ALTO protocol <xref
        target="I-D.ietf-alto-protocol"></xref> uses, amongst others
        mechanism, so-called network maps. The network map approach uses Host
        Group Descriptors that group one or multiple subnetworks (i.e., IP
        prefixes) to a single Host Group Descriptor. A set of IP prefixes is
        called partition and the associated Host Group Descriptor is called
        partition ID. The "costs" between the various partition IDs is stored
        in a second map, the cost map. Map-based approaches are chosen as they
        lower the signaling load on the server, as the maps have only to be
        retrieved if they are changed.</t>

        <t>The main assumption for map-based approaches is that the
        information provided in these maps is static for a longer period of
        time, where this period of time refers to days, but not hours or even
        minutes. This assumption is fine, as long as the network operator does
        not change any parameter, e.g., routing within the network and to the
        upstream peers, IP address assignment stays stable (and thus the
        mapping to the partitions). However, there are several cases where
        this assumption is not valid, as:</t>

        <t><list style="numbers">
            <t>ISPs reallocate IPv4 subnets from time to time;</t>

            <t>ISPs reallocate IPv4 subnets on short notice;</t>

            <t>IP prefix blocks may be assigned to a single DSLAM which serves
            a variety of access networks.</t>
          </list></t>

        <!-- text below is a copy of Rich Woundy's comment -->

        <t>For 1): ISPs reallocate IPv4 subnets within their infrastructure
        from time to time, partly to ensure the efficient usage of IPv4
        addresses (a scarce resource), and partly to enable efficient route
        tables within their network routers. The frequency of these
        "renumbering events" depend on the growth in number of subscribers and
        the availability of address space within the ISP. As a result, a
        subscriber's household device could retain an IPv4 address for as
        short as a few minutes, or for months at a time or even longer. <list
            style="hanging">
            <t>Some folks have suggested that ISPs providing ALTO services
            could sub-divide their subscribers' devices into different IPv4
            subnets (or certain IPv4 address ranges) based on the purchased
            service tier, as well as based on the location in the network
            topology. The problem is that this sub-allocation of IPv4 subnets
            tends to decrease the efficiency of IPv4 address allocation. A
            growing ISP that needs to maintain high efficiency of IPv4 address
            utilization may be reluctant to jeopardize their future
            acquisition of IPv4 address space.</t>
          </list> However, this is not an issue for map-based approaches if
        changes are applied in the order of days.</t>

        <!-- text above is a copy of Rich Woundy's comment -->

        <t>For 2): ISPs can use techniques, such as ODAP (XXX) that allow the
        reallocation of IP prefixes on very short notice, i.e., within
        minutes. An IP prefix that has no IP address assignment to a host
        anymore can be reallocate to areas where there is currently a high
        demand for IP addresses.</t>

        <t>For 3): In DSL-based access networks, IP prefixes are assigned to
        DSLAMs which are the first IP-hop in the access-network between the
        CPE and the Internet. The access-network between CPE and DSLAM (called
        aggregation network) can have varying characteristics (and thus
        associated costs), but still using the same IP prefix. For instance
        one IP addresses IP11 out of a IP prefix IP1 can be assigned to a VDSL
        (e.g., 2 MBit/s uplink) access-line while the subsequent IP address
        IP12 is assigned to a slow ADSL line (e.g., 128 kbit/s uplink). These
        IP addresses are assigned on a first come first served basis, i.e.,
        the a single IP address out of the same IP prefix can change its
        associated costs quite fast. This may not be an issue with respect to
        the used upstream provider (thus the cross ISP traffic) but depending
        on the capacity of the aggregation-network this may raise to an
        issue.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Limitiations of Non-Map-based Approaches">
        <t>The specification of the ALTO protocol <xref
        target="I-D.ietf-alto-protocol"></xref> uses, amongst others
        mechanism, a mechanism called Endpoint Cost Service. ALTO clients can
        ask guidance for specific IP addresses to the ALTO server. However,
        asking for IP addresses, asking with long lists of IP addresses, and
        asking quite frequent may overload the ALTO server. The server has to
        rank each received IP address which causes load at the server. This
        may be amplified by the fact that not only a single ALTO client is
        asking for guidance, but a larger number of them.</t>

        <t>Caching of IP addresses at the ALTO client or the usage of the H12
        approach <xref target="I-D.kiesel-alto-h12"></xref> in conjunction
        with caching may lower the query load on the ALTO server.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="General Challenges">
        <t>An ALTO server stores information about preferences (e.g., a list
        of preferred autonomous systems, IP ranges, etc) and ALTO clients can
        retrieve these preferences. However, there are basically two different
        approaches on where the preferences are actually processed:<list
            style="numbers">
            <t>The ALTO server has a list of preferences and clients can
            retrieve this list via the ALTO protocol. This preference list can
            be partially updated by the server. The actual processing of the
            data is done on the client and thus there is no data of the
            client's operation revealed to the ALTO server .</t>

            <t>The ALTO server has a list of preferences or preferences
            calculated during runtime and the ALTO client is sending
            information of its operation (e.g., a list of IP addresses) to the
            server. The server is using this operational information to
            determine its preferences and returns these preferences (e.g., a
            sorted list of the IP addresses) back to the ALTO client.</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>Approach 1 (we call it H1) has the advantage (seen from the client)
        that all operational information stays within the client and is not
        revealed to the provider of the server. On the other hand, does
        approach 1 require that the provider of the ALTO server, i.e., the
        network operator, reveals information about its network structure
        (e.g., AS numbers, IP ranges, topology information in general) to the
        ALTO client.</t>

        <t>Approach 2 (we call it H2) has the advantage (seen from the
        operator) that all operational information stays with the ALTO server
        and is not revealed to the ALTO client. On the other hand, does
        approach 2 require that the clients send their operational information
        to the server.</t>

        <t>Both approaches have their pros and cons and are extensively
        discussed on the ALTO mailing list. But there is basically a dilemma:
        Approach 1 is seen as the only working solution by peer-to-peer
        software vendors and approach 2 is seen as the only working by the
        network operators. But neither the software vendors nor the operators
        seem to willing to change their position. However, there is the need
        to get both sides on board, to come to a solution.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

     <section title="Extensions to the ALTO Protocol">	
	This section lists possible future extensions to the ALTO protocol.
	
	    <section anchor="host_group_descriptors" title="Host Group
    Descriptors">

        <t>Host group descriptors are used in the ALTO client protocol
        to describe the location of a host in the network topology.
        The ALTO client protocol specification defines a basic set of
        host group descriptor types, which have to be supported by all
        implementations, and an extension procedure for adding new descriptor
        types <!--(see <xref target="req_acp_hla"/>)-->.
        The following list gives an overview on further host group
        descriptor types that have been proposed in the past, or which are in
        use by ALTO-related prototype implementations. This list is
        not intended as normative text. Instead, the only purpose of
        the following list is to document the descriptor types that have been
        proposed so far, and to solicit further feedback and discussion:</t>
        <t><list style='symbols'>
            <t>Autonomous System (AS) number</t>
            <t>Protocol-specific group identifiers, which expand to a set of
            IP address ranges (CIDR) and/or AS numbers. In one specific
            solution proposal, these are called Partition ID (PID).</t>
        </list></t>
    </section>
   <section anchor="rating_criteria" title="Rating Criteria">

        <t>Rating criteria are used in the ALTO client protocol to express
        topology- or connectivity-related properties, which are evaluated in
        order to generate the ALTO guidance. 
        The ALTO client protocol specification defines a basic set of
        rating criteria, which have to be supported by all
        implementations, and an extension procedure for adding new criteria
        <!--(see <xref target="req_acp_rc"/>)-->.
        The following list gives an overview on further rating criteria
        that have been proposed in the past, or which are in
        use by ALTO-related prototype implementations. This list is
        not intended as normative text. Instead, the only purpose of
        the following list is to document the rating criteria that have been
        proposed so far, and to solicit further feedback and discussion:</t>

        <section anchor="rating_criteria_distance" 
            title="Distance-related Rating Criteria">
        <t><list style='symbols'>

            <t>Relative topological distance: relative means that a larger
            numerical value means greater distance, but it is up to the ALTO
            service how to compute the values, and the ALTO client will not
            be informed about the nature of the information. One way of
            generating this kind of information MAY be counting AS hops, but
            when querying this parameter, the ALTO client MUST NOT assume
            that the numbers actually are AS hops.</t>

            <t>Absolute topological distance, expressed in the number of
            traversed autonomous systems (AS).</t>

            <t>Absolute topological distance, expressed in the number of
            router hops (i.e., how much the TTL value of an IP packet will
            be decreased during transit).</t>

            <t>Absolute physical distance, based on knowledge of the
            approximate geolocation (continent, country) of an IP
            address.</t>

        </list></t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="rating_criteria_charging" 
            title="Charging-related Rating Criteria">
        <t><list style='symbols'>
            <t>Traffic volume caps, in case the Internet access of the
            resource consumer is not charged by "flat rate". For each
            candidate resource provider, the ALTO service could indicate the
            amount of data that may be transferred from/to this resource
            provider until a given point in time, and how much of this amount 
            has already been consumed.  Furthermore, it would have to be
            indicated how excess traffic would be handled (e.g., blocked,
            throttled, or charged separately at an indicated price). The
            interaction of several applications running on a host, out of
            which some use this criterion while others don't, as well as the
            evaluation of this criterion in resource directories, which
            issue ALTO queries on behalf of other peers, are for further
            study.</t>
        </list></t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="rating_criteria_performance" 
            title="Performance-related Rating Criteria">
        <t>The following rating criteria are subject to the remarks below.</t>
        <t><list style='symbols'>
            <t>The minimum achievable throughput between the resource
            consumer and the candidate resource provider, which is considered 
            useful by the application (only in ALTO queries), or</t>
            <t>An arbitrary upper bound for the throughput from/to the
            candidate resource provider (only in ALTO responses). This may be,
            but is not necessarily the provisioned access bandwidth of the
            candidate resource provider.</t>
            <t>The maximum round-trip time (RTT) between resource consumer
            and the candidate resource provider, which is acceptable for the
            application for useful communication with the candidate resource
            provider (only in ALTO queries), or</t>
            <t>An arbitrary lower bound for the RTT between resource
            consumer and the candidate resource provider (only in ALTO
            responses). This may be, for example, based on measurements of
            the propagation delay in a completely unloaded network.  </t>
        </list></t>


        <t>The ALTO client MUST be aware, that with high probability,
        the actual performance values differ significantly from these
        upper and lower bounds. In particular, an ALTO client
        MUST NOT consider the "upper bound for throughput" parameter
        as a permission to send data at the indicated rate without
        using congestion control mechanisms.</t>

        <t>The discrepancies are due to various reasons, including,
        but not limited to the facts that</t>
        <t><list style='symbols'>
            <t>the ALTO service is not an admission control system</t>
            <t>the ALTO service may not know the instantaneous congestion
            status of the network</t>
            <t>the ALTO service may not know all link bandwidths, i.e.,
            where the bottleneck really is, and there may be shared
            bottlenecks</t>
            <t>the ALTO service may not know whether the candidate peer
            itself is overloaded</t>
            <t>the ALTO service may not know whether the candidate peer
            throttles the bandwidth it devotes for the considered
            application</t>
            <t>the ALTO service may not know whether the candidate peer will
            throttle the data it sends to us (e.g., because of some fairness
            algorithm, such as tit-for-tat)</t>
        </list></t>

        <t>Because of these inaccuracies and the lack of complete,
        instantaneous state information, which are inherent to the ALTO
        service, the application must use other mechanisms (such as passive
        measurements on actual data transmissions) to assess the currently
        achievable throughput, and it MUST use appropriate congestion
        control mechanisms in order to avoid a congestion collapse.
        Nevertheless, these rating criteria may provide a useful shortcut
        for quickly excluding candidate resource providers from such
        probing, if it is known in advance that connectivity is in any
        case worse than what is considered the minimum useful value by the
        respective application.</t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="rating_criteria_inappropriate" 
            title="Inappropriate Rating Criteria">
        <t>Rating criteria that SHOULD NOT be defined for and used by the 
        ALTO service include:</t>
        <t><list style='symbols'>
            <t>Performance metrics that are closely related to the
            instantaneous congestion status. The definition of
            alternate approaches for congestion control is explicitly
            out of the scope of ALTO. Instead, other appropriate
            means, such as using TCP based transport, have to be used
            to avoid congestion.</t>
            <!--
            <t>The provisioned access bandwidth, e.g. of cable / DSL
            customers.  This has been proposed several times and questioned,
            because of problems with privacy, fears that "premium" customers
            with high access bandwidth might attract so much traffic that
            their service becomes de-facto worse, etc.</t>
            -->
        </list></t>
        </section>
 
    </section>
	
	</section>

   <section anchor="AC_API" title="API between ALTO Client and Application">
      <t>This sections gives some informational guidance on how the interface
      between the actual application using the ALTO guidance and the ALTO
      client can look like.</t>

      <t>This is still TBD.</t>
    </section>
	
    <section title="Security Considerations">
      <t>The ALTO protocol itself, as well as, the ALTO client and server
      raise new security issues beyond the one mentioned in <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-alto-protocol"></xref> and issues related to message
      transport over the Internet. For instance, Denial of Service (DoS) is of
      interest for the ALTO server and also for the ALTO client. A server can
      get overloaded if too many TCP requests hit the server, or if the query
      load of the server surpasses the maximum computing capacity. An ALTO
      client can get overloaded if the responses from the sever are, either
      intentionally or due to an implementation mistake, too large to be
      handled by that particular client.</t>

      <section title="Information Leakage from the ALTO Server">
        <t>The ALTO server will be provisioned with information about the
        owning ISP's network and very likely also with information about
        neighboring ISPs. This information (e.g., network topology, business
        relations, etc) is consider to be confidential to the ISP and must not
        be revealed.</t>

        <t>The ALTO server will naturally reveal parts of that information in
        small doses to peers, as the guidance given will depend on the above
        mentioned information. This is seen beneficial for both parties, i.e.,
        the ISP's and the peer's. However, there is the chance that one or
        multiple peers are querying an ALTO server with the goal to gather
        information about network topology or any other data considered
        confidential or at least sensitive. It is unclear whether this is a
        real technical security risk or whether this is more a perceived
        security risk.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="ALTO Server Access">
        <t>Depending on the use case of ALTO, several access restrictions to
        an ALTO server may or may not apply. For an ALTO server that is solely
        accessible by peers from the ISP network (as shown in <xref
        target="fig.localALTOServer"></xref>), for instance, the source IP
        address can be used to grant only access from that ISP network to the
        server. This will "limit" the number of peers able to attack the
        server to the user's of the ISP (however, including botnet
        computers).</t>

        <t>On the other hand, if the ALTO server has to be accessible by
        parties not located in the ISP's network (see Figure <xref
        target="fig.global_tracker"></xref>), e.g., by a third-party tracker
        or by a CDN system outside the ISP's network, the access restrictions
        have to be more loose. In the extreme case, i.e., no access
        restrictions, each and every host in the Internet can access the ALTO
        server. This might no the intention of the ISP, as the server is not
        only subject to more possible attacks, but also on the load imposed to
        the server, i.e., possibly more ALTO clients to serve and thus more
        work load.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Faking ALTO Guidance">
        <t>It has not yet been investigated how a faked or wrong ALTO guidance
        by an ALTO server can impact the operation of the network and also the
        peers.</t>

        <t>Here is a list of examples how the ALTO guidance could be faked and
        what possible consequences may arise: <list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="Sorting">An attacker could change to sorting order of
            the ALTO guidance (given that the order is of importance,
            otherwise the ranking mechanism is of interest), i.e., declaring
            peers located outside the ISP as peers to be preferred. This will
            not pose a big risk to the network or peers, as it would mimic the
            "regular" peer operation without traffic localization, apart from
            the communication/processing overhead for ALTO. However, it could
            mean that ALTO is reaching the opposite goal of shuffling more
            data across ISP boundaries, incurring more costs for the ISP.</t>

            <t hangText="Preference of a single peer">A single IP address
            (thus a peer) could be marked as to be preferred all over other
            peers. This peer can be located within the local ISP or also in
            other parts of the Internet (e.g., a web server). This could lead
            to the case that quite a number of peers to trying to contact this
            IP address, possibly causing a Denial of Service (DoS) attack.</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>

      <t>This section is solely giving a first shot on security issues related
      to ALTO deployments.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Conclusion">
      <t>This is the first version of the deployment considerations and for
      sure the considerations are yet incomplete and imprecise.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119" ?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3568" ?>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6708" ?>

      <?rfc include="reference.I-D.ietf-alto-protocol" ?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5693" ?>

      <?rfc include="reference.I-D.ietf-alto-server-discovery"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.I-D.vandergaast-edns-client-ip"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.I-D.penno-alto-cdn"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.I-D.kamei-p2p-experiments-japan"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.I-D.kiesel-alto-h12"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5632"?>
	  
	  <?rfc include="reference.I-D.lee-alto-chinatelecom-trial"?>
    </references>

    <appendix title="Contributors List and Acknowledgments">
      <t>This memo is the result of contributions made by several people,
	such as:
	<list style="symbols">
	<t>Xianghue Sun, Lee Kai, and Richard Yang contributed
	<xref target="sec.ISP_deployment"/> and
	<xref target="sec.monitoring"/>.</t>
	<t>Stefano Previdi contributed Section <xref target="sec.cdn_cons"/>
	on "Using ALTO for CDNs". </t>
        </list>
      </t>
        

      <t>   Martin Stiemerling is partially supported by the CHANGE project (
   http://www.change-project.eu), a research project supported by the
   European Commission under its 7th Framework Program (contract no.
   257422).  The views and conclusions contained herein are those of the
   authors and should not be interpreted as necessarily representing the
   official policies or endorsements, either expressed or implied, of
   the CHANGE project or the European Commission.
      </t>

    </appendix>
  </back>
</rfc>
