<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [

    <!ENTITY RFC1035 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1035.xml">
    <!ENTITY RFC2119 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
    <!ENTITY RFC2629 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2629.xml">
    <!ENTITY RFC5280 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5280.xml">
    <!ENTITY RFC3552 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3552.xml">
    <!ENTITY RFC3642 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3642.xml">
    <!ENTITY RFC4033 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4033.xml">
    <!ENTITY RFC4055 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4055.xml">
    <!ENTITY RFC4648 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4648.xml">
    <!ENTITY RFC5395 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5395.xml">
    <!ENTITY I-D.hallambaker-donotissue SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.draft-hallambaker-donotissue-03.xml">
]>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<rfc category="exp" docName="draft-hallambaker-revocation-options-00" ipr="trust200902">

    <front>
        <title abbrev="Options for Improving PKIX Revocation">Options for Improving PKIX Revocation</title>
        <author fullname="Phillip Hallam-Baker" initials="P. M." surname="Hallam-Baker">
            <organization>Comodo Group Inc.</organization>
            <address>
                <email>philliph@comodo.com</email>
            </address>
        </author>

        <date day="7" month="April" year="2011" />

        <area>General</area>

        <workgroup>Internet Engineering Task Force</workgroup>

        <keyword>DNS</keyword>
        <keyword>DNSSEC</keyword>
        <keyword>PKIX</keyword>

        <abstract>
            <t>
            In recent weeks a number of proposals have been made for improving the
            effectiveness of certificate revocation. This document is an attempt
            to bring these proposals atogether and analyze them with respect to 
            a use cases and requirements framework.
            </t>
        </abstract>
    </front>

    <middle>
        <section title="Definitions">
            <section title="Requirements Language">
                <t>
                    The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
                    "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
                    document are to be interpreted as described in <xref target="RFC2119">RFC 2119</xref>.
                </t>
            </section>
            <section title="Defined Terms">
                <t>The following terms are used in this document:</t>
                <t>
                    <list style="hanging">


                        <t hangText="Certificate">
                            An X.509 Certificate, as specified in <xref target="RFC5280">RFC 5280</xref>.
                        </t>
                        <t hangText="Certification Policy (CP)">
                            Specifies the criteria that a Certification Authority undertakes to meet
                            in its issue of certificates.
                        </t>
                        <t hangText="Certification Practices Statement (CPS)">
                            Specifies the means by which the criteria of the Certification Policy
                            are met. In most cases this will be the document against which the
                            operations of the Certification Authority are audited.
                        </t>
                        <t hangText="Certification Authority (CA)">
                            An entity that issues Certificates in accordance with a specified
                            Certification Policy.
                        </t>
                        <t hangText="Domain">
                            The set of resources associated with a DNS Domain Name.
                        </t>
                        <t hangText="Domain Name">
                            A DNS Domain name as specified in <xref target="RFC1035">RFC 1035</xref>
                            and revisions.
                        </t>
                        <t hangText="Domain Name System (DNS)">
                            The Internet naming system specified in <xref target="RFC1035">RFC 1035</xref>
                            and revisions.
                        </t>
                        <t hangText="DNS Security (DNSSEC)">
                            Extensions to the DNS that provide authentication services as specified in
                            <xref target="RFC4033">RFC 4033</xref>
                            and revisions.
                        </t>
                        <t hangText="Key">
                            A cryptographic key.
                        </t>
                        <t hangText="Public Key Infrastructure X.509 (PKIX)">
                            Standards and specifications issued by the IETF that apply the
                            <xref target="X.509">X.509</xref> certificate standards specified
                            by the ITU to Internet applications as specified in
                            <xref target="RFC5280">RFC 5280</xref> and related documents.
                        </t>
                        <t hangText="Resource Record (RR)">
                            A set of attributes bound to a Domain Name.
                        </t>
                        <t hangText="Relying Party">
                            A party that makes use of an application whose operation depends on
                            use of a Certificate or Key for making a security decision.
                        </t>
                        <t hangText="Relying Application">
                            An application whose operation depends on
                            use of a Certificate or Key for making a security decision.
                        </t>

                    </list>
                </t>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section title="Use Cases">
            <t>TBS</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Constraints">

            <section title="[C-Legacy-Browser]">
                <t>
                    The legacy base of browsers does not support hard fail 
                    when an OCSP responder is unavailable
                </t>
            </section>
            <section title="[C-Legacy-Server]">
                <t> The legacy base of servers does not support OCSP stapling  
                              </t>
            </section>
            <section title="[C-Legacy-DNS]">
                <t> The legacy DNS does not provide for cryptographic authentication of responses   
                             </t>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section title="Requirements">
            <section title="[R-Fraud]">
                <t>Prevent clients relying on mis-issued or fraudulently issued certificates       
                         </t>
            </section>
            <section title="[R-Comp]">
                <t>  Prevent clients relying on certificates that were legitimately 
                issued but have since been compromised (e.g. subject key is compromised) 
                               </t>


            </section>

        </section>
        <section title="Metrics">
            <section title="[M-Client-Efficiency]">
                <t>Time spent checking certificate status in the browser  
                              </t>
            </section>
            <section title="[M-Server-Admin]">
                <t> Complexity of server operations.
                                </t>
            </section>
        </section>

        <section title="Proposals">

            <section title="[P-CAA]">
                <t>

                    Certificate Authority Authorization
                    <xref target="I-D.hallambaker-donotissue"></xref> provides a general purpose, 
                    extensible platform that allows domain name owners to express 
                    certificate issue requirements. Although currently limited to 
                    specification of trust roots, it is extensible to allow additional 
                    properties to be agreed and specified. While the security of CAA 
                    is improved with deployment of DNSSEC in the specified zone, CAA 
                    is still an effective control without DNSSEC.
                </t>
                <t>
                    Deployment of CAA does not require code at the client or server, 
                    except that the DNS server used must be recent enough to support 
                    specification of unknown RRs. It is thus compatible with 
                    [C-Legacy-Browser] and [C-Legacy-Server].
                </t>
            </section>
            <section title="  [P-Short]">



                <t>
                    Certificate is issued for short lifetime (24-72 hours). Servers 
                    must thus ensure that they continuously update their certificate 
                    stores to download and install certificates as they are issued.
                </t>
                <t>
                    One critical issue in this approach is the synchronization of 
                    the relying party clock to that of the issuing CA (presumed to 
                    be within a few seconds of UTC). In order to avoid unnecessary 
                    rejection of certificates it is probably desirable for a server 
                    to only start using a certificate 24 hours after the 
                    notValidBefore time and to renew the certificate 24 hours 
                    before the notValidAfter time is reached. Experts 
                    are currently looking into the detailed implications of timing 
                    and short lived certificates.
                </t>
                <t>
                    By itself, [P-Short] meets criteria [R-Comp] but not [R-Fraud] 
                    since an attacker can simply request issue of a long lived 
                    certificate from a compromised CA.
                </t>
                <t>
                    [P-Short] is netural with respect to [M-Client-Efficiency] and 
                    requires a significant change to server administration and is 
                    thus negative for [M-Server-Admin] in the short term. In the 
                    long term however, it is much easier to guarantee the reliability 
                    of a certificate download that must happen every day and is thus 
                    automated, than a procedure that happens once a year and is likely 
                    to be forgotten.
                </t>
                <t>
                    Deployment of [P-Short] is fully compatible with the legacy base 
                    of deployed browsers which will all accept short lifetime 
                    certificates and refuse to rely on a certificate that has expired.

                </t>
                <section title=" [P-Short]+[P-CAA]">


                    <t>
                        Use of [P-Short] in combination with an appropriate flag in 
                        [P-CAA] allows the requirement [R-Fraud] to be met, provided 
                        that either the CA or the client software checks the CAA record.
                    </t>
                    <t>
                        This proposal is identical with respect to the metrics 
                        and constraints as [P-Short]
                    </t>
                </section>
                <section title="[P-Short-Optimized]">


                    <t>
                        If the lifetime of a short lived certificate is shorter 
                        than the validity period accepted for an OCSP or CRL response, 
                        a client MAY choose to rely on the short lived certificate 
                        without performing the customary revocation checking. A PKIX 
                        certificate extension MAY be specified as a means of enabling 
                        a client to determine that a certificate is intended for use 
                        as a short-lived certificate without revocation checking.
                    </t>
                    <t>[P-Short-Optimized] allows an improvement in the metric 
                    [M-Client-Efficiency] by eliminating the need for separate revocation 
                    checking.  
                                  </t>
                </section>
            </section>
            <section title=" [P-Stapling-Flag]">



                <t>
                    A certificate includes a flag that tells relying parties that 
                    it is only to be used with TLS implementations that support OCSP
                     stapling. Should a client attempt to connect to the server that 
                     does not offer the stapled OCSP response, the connection is 
                     invalid and must be aborted.
                </t>
                <t>
                    [P-Stapling-Flag] arguably requires less administration effort 
                    than [P-Short] as it allows the site to continue to use long lived 
                    certificates and is thus better on [M-Server-Admin]. The principal 
                    disadvantage being that it requires deployment of a server that
                     can support stapling and is thus worse on [C-Legacy-Server]. 
                     The stapling flag will only be observed by new clients and the 
                     proposal thus fails to meet [C-Legacy-Browser].
                </t>
            </section>
            <section title="[P-OCSP-LOCAL][P-OCSP-LOCAL-2ND]">


                <t>
                    Another proposal similar to [P-Short] is for the subject to host 
                    their own OCSP responder which is in theory less likely to be 
                    vulnerable to failure. This may be the primary OCSP responder 
                    [P-OCSP-LOCAL] or merely a secondary [P-OCSP-LOCAL-2ND].
                </t>
                <t>
                    While this approach does not require server support for OCSP 
                    stapling and is thus compatible with [C-Legacy-Server], the 
                    administrative effort for the subject is considerably greater 
                    and it thus fails on [M-Server-Admin].
                </t>
            </section>

        </section>


        <section title="Security Considerations">
            <t>
                [TBS]
            </t>
        </section>

        <section title="IANA Considerations">
            <t>None</t>
        </section>
        <section title="Acknowledgements">
            <t>
            This draft draws on input from many contributors, in some cases the 
            same proposal being made more than once in different contexts. The 
            concept of short lived certificates was proposed in WAP forum. 
            This proposal and the proposal to use local OCSP was mentioned on a 
            Mozilla telecon.
            </t>
        </section>
    </middle>



    <back>
        <references title="Normative References">
            &RFC1035;
            &RFC2119;

            &RFC4033;

            &RFC5280;

            <reference anchor="X.509">
                <front>
                    <title>
                        ITU-T Recommendation X.509 (11/2008): Information
                        technology - Open systems interconnection - The
                        Directory: Public-key and attribute certificate
                        frameworks
                    </title>
                    <author>
                        <organization>
                            International Telecommunication Union
                        </organization>
                    </author>
                    <date month="November" year="2008"/>
                </front>
                <seriesInfo name="ITU-T Recommendation" value="X.509"/>
                <format type="HTML" target="http://www.itu.int/itu-t/recommendations/rec.aspx?rec=X.509"/>
            </reference>

            &I-D.hallambaker-donotissue;   
        </references>
        <!--<references title="Non Normative References">

        </references>-->


    </back>
</rfc>
