<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd"[
  <!ENTITY rfc2629 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2629.xml'>
    <!ENTITY RFC1035 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1035.xml">
    <!ENTITY RFC2119 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
    <!ENTITY RFC2629 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2629.xml">
    <!ENTITY RFC5280 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5280.xml">
    <!ENTITY RFC3552 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3552.xml">
    <!ENTITY RFC3642 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3642.xml">    
    <!ENTITY RFC4033 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4033.xml">
    <!ENTITY RFC4055 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4055.xml">
    <!ENTITY RFC4648 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4648.xml">
    <!ENTITY RFC5395 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5395.xml">
  <!ENTITY RFC4366 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4366.xml">
  <!ENTITY RFC2616 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2616.xml">  
  <!ENTITY RFC4627 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4627.xml">
  <!ENTITY RFC3709 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3709.xml">
    <!ENTITY RFC4648 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4648.xml">
    <!ENTITY RFC3339 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3339.xml">
  <!ENTITY draft-hallambaker-httpsession SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.draft-hallambaker-httpsession-01.xml">  
]>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<rfc category="std" docName="draft-hallambaker-wsconnect-04" ipr="trust200902">

  <front>
    <title abbrev="JSON Service Connect (JCX) Protocol">JSON Service Connect (JCX) Protocol</title>
    <author fullname="Phillip Hallam-Baker" initials="P. M." surname="Hallam-Baker">
      <organization>Comodo Group Inc.</organization>
      <address>
        <email>philliph@comodo.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date day="8" month="July" year="2013" />

    <area>General</area>

    <workgroup>Internet Engineering Task Force</workgroup>

    <abstract>
      <t>
        JSON Service Connect (JCX) is a JSON/REST Web Service that may be used to
        establish and maintain a 'connection binding' of a device to an account
        held with a Web Service Provider. Multiple connection bindings may be
        established under the same account to support multiple devices and/or
        multiple users of a single device. A connection binding permits a 
        device to securely connect to one or more services offered by the Web Service 
        Provider with support for protocol and protocol version agilty and
        fault tollerance.
      </t>
      <t>
        The protocol is presented as a HTTP/JSON Web Service and uses the HTTP 
        session continuation mechanism for 
        authentication of transaction messages and supports 
        negotiation of a HTTP session continuation mechanism context for the
        established endpoint connections.
      </t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Definitions">
      <section title="Requirements Language">
        <t>
          The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
          "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
          document are to be interpreted as described in <xref target="RFC2119" />.
        </t>
      </section>

    </section>
    <section title="Introduction and Purpose">
      <t>
        JSON Service Connect (JCX) is a Web Service that may be used to 
        establish and maintain a 'connection binding' of a device to an account 
        held with a Web Service Provider (WSP).
      </t>
      <t>
        JCX is presented in JSON encoding <xref target="RFC4627" /> over a HTTP
        Session <xref target="RFC2616" /> using HTTP Session Continuation
        <xref target="I-D.hallambaker-httpsession" /> for message layer 
        authentication and TLS transport for confidentiality and 
        server authentication.<xref target="RFC4627" />
      </t>
      <t>
        A Connection Binding comprises a set of long term credentials used to 
        authenticate interactions with the JCX service itself and a set of
        'Service Connections' to specific services offered by the Web Service 
        Provider.
      </t>
      <t>
        Each service connection in turn comprises a collection of 'Instance 
        Connections' which describe a specific instances of the Web Service.
      </t>
      <t>
        For example Alice is a consumer and example.com a provider of a range
        of Web Services including anti-malware protection and management of
        home automation devices. Alice has 42 devices of different types that
        each make use of one or more of the Web Services proviced by example.com.
        All the devices are enrolled in the same JCX account 'alice@example.com'
        but each device has a unique connection binding and different devices 
        make use of different Web Services. 
      </t>
      <t>
        The centralized account provides Alice with
        a single point of control from which she can authorize the addition of
        new devices to the account or the removal of devices that are deactivated.
        This allows Alice to avoid the need to manage a device such as a 
        network-enabled lightswitch through the lightswitch itself.
      </t>
    <t>
      To ensure continuity of service
        in case of network failure or administration work, example.com provides
        multiple instances of its Web Services hosted on different machines. 
        Different users MAY be granted access to a different collection of
        service instances according to their needs and the service tier they
        are subscribed to. 
      </t>
      <section title="Establishing a Web Service Provider Account">
        <t>
          The means by
          which the Web Service Provider Account is established is outside 
          the scope of this document.
        </t>
      <t>
        In a typical case the user would establish an account with their
        chosen Web Service Provider through the normal process of using
        a Web Browser to access the Web Service Provider's site and 
        entering such data as the Web Service Provider requires into 
        a HTML form.
        </t>
        <t>
          Depending on the circumstances, the data provided by the 
          applicant may require verification before the account
          is created.
          </t>
        <t>
          [Default accounts for appliances that are going to be implicitly authenticated
          by reference to the network they are on.]
        </t>
      </section>      
      <section title="Establishing a Connection Binding">
        <t>
          A connection binding represents a long term association 
          between a device and an account at the Web Service Provider.
          The association includes the establishment of an authentication
          context between the device and the JCX service.
        </t>
        <t>
          An authentication context consists of:
          <list>
            <t>
              A Context Identifier.
            </t>
            <t>
              An authentication algorithm.
            </t>
        <t>
          A secret key.
        </t>

          </list>
        </t>
        <t>
          The context identifier is an opaque string assigned by the 
          JCX service. Following the approach introduced in Kerberos, 
          a JCX service MAY eliminate the need to store
          authentication context information by encoding the authentication
          algorithm and encrypted secret key in the context identifier.
        </t>
        <t>
          The authentication context can ensure that
          future communications are secured against impersonation if 
          and only if the original process of establishing a connection
          binding was secured against communication. Mutual authentication
          is therefore an essential requirement.
        </t>
        <t>
          The means by which the connection binding is established 
          depend on the affordances of the device in question. Establishing
          a connection binding to a device with a keyboard is easily 
          accomplished through use of a one-time PIN code. But many
          embedded devices do not provide a keyboard or similar
          affordance.
        </t>

        <t>
          The following modes of session establishement are supported:
          <list>
            <t>PIN Code Establishement.</t>
            <t>Out of Band Completion.</t>
            <t>QR Code Establishement.</t>
          </list>
        </t>
        <section title="PIN Code Establishement.">
          <t>To establish a connection binding for a new mobile phone, Alice
          logs into her JCX account manager and requests a new PIN code.
          She then starts the application that makes use of a JCX account
          and selects 'create new binding'. She is prompted for and enters
          her account name (alice@example.com) and PIN.</t>
          <t>
            The client connects to the JCX service and verifies that the
            TLS certificate presented is correct for example.com and 
            has been issued in accordance with issue practices that
            ensure an appropriately high degree of trust (e.g. the CABForum
            Extended Validation requirements).
          </t>
        </section>
        <section title="Out of Band Completion.">
          <t>
            To establish a connection binding for her new toaster oven, 
            Alice plugs the appliance into her local network and enters
            her account name into the device. Since she has not obtained
            a PIN code in advance, she leaves the entry blank.
          </t>
        <t>
          To complete the process, Alice logs into her JCX account where 
          she sees that a new device is available to add to the account.
          To help identify the correct device, there is a picture of the
          toaster oven, the model name and serial number.
          </t>
        </section>
        <section title="QR Code Preauthorization.">
          <t>
            Alice decides to remodel the kitchen completely and plans to install 
            a dozen new network enabled LED light fixtures. Using an 
            application on the mobile phone she enabled earlier, Alice
            scans a QR code attached to each fixture before the 
            devices are installed. When the fixtures are installed and powered,
            the connection binding is preauthorized.
          </t>
        </section>    
      </section>
    </section>

    
<!-- Auto generated examples from JCXExamples.xml -->

<section title="Example Uses" anchor="ConnectionRequestExample">
  <section title="PIN code establishment">
	<t>
		Alice buys a new laptop computer which she wishes to use with
		the malware protection service provided by example.com. Alice
		has an existing account 'alice' with this Web Service Provider and
		obtains a pin code Q80370-1RA606-F04B from the Web Service Provider
		Web site.
	</t>
	<t>
		Alice enters the values alice@example.com and
		Q80370-1RA606-F04B into the Web Service client she wishes to use 
		with the Web Service Provider on the new laptop.
	</t>
	<t>
		The client obtains the JCX service for example.com using
		DNS SRV discovery. The client establishes a TLS connection to
		the service and verifies that the certificate provided has
		a valid certificate path, has not been revoked and meets the
		validation criteria of the client. Since the purpose of 
		this particular Web Service client is to provide security, the 
		client requires that an Extended Validation certificate be
		presented.

	</t>
	<t>
		Having established a TLS connection to the JCX Service, the client
		sends the following HTTP request:
	</t>
          <figure>
            <artwork>
<![CDATA[POST /.well-known/OmniConnect/ HTTP/1.1
Content-Type: application/json;charset=UTF-8
Cache-Control: no-store
Host: localhost
Content-Length: 310
Expect: 100-continue
Connection: Keep-Alive

{
  "OpenPINRequest": {
    "Encryption": ["A128CBC",
      "A256CBC",
      "A128GCM",
      "A256GCM"],
    "Authentication": ["HS256",
      "HS384",
      "HS512",
      "HS256T128"],
    "Account": "alice",
    "Domain": "example.com",
    "HaveDisplay": false,
    "Challenge": "xf_RYs5somZqoYNC_Mbwjg"}}
]]>
            </artwork>
          </figure>
	<t>
		To prevent man in the middle attack, the client does not send the PIN 
		code in the initial request. The PIN code is only sent after the service
		responds with a challenge nonce to be used to prevent replay attack.
	</t>
	<t>
		The service receives the request, determines that is meets its
		access control policy and selects a set of cryptographic parameters
		from the set proposed by the client. In this case the service prefers
		the use of AES128CBC for encryption and the HS256 Message Authentication
		Code for authentication. 
	</t>
	<t>
		The service determines that a PIN code has been issued for the account and
		uses the value of that PIN to generate a response to the challenge
		presented by the client. A new challenge is generated to test the
		client knowledge of the PIN.
	</t>
	<t>
	    [TBS: Is there a need for the service to be able to support multiple 
		outstanding PIN codes for the same account? This could be supported by
		providing the last 2 significant characters of the PIN code to the
		service which could use it as an index. This would enable several hundred
		simultaneous outstanding requests which should be enough for most applications.
		Large volume applications would need to use a different scheme.]
	</t>
	<t>
		The service sends the following response to the client:
	</t>
          <figure>
            <artwork>
<![CDATA[HTTP/1.1 NonAuthoritativeInformation Passcode
Content-Length: 496
Date: Mon, 08 Jul 2013 20:15:20 GMT
Server: Microsoft-HTTPAPI/2.0

{
  "OpenPINResponse": {
    "Status": 203,
    "StatusDescription": "Passcode",
    "Challenge": "sfTWtVrClirYDwgPDWIMVA",
    "ChallengeResponse":
    "WKhKz1SmPy6e6S_4Jna9qoCtgEarkIsX-F38KKP9P9s",
    "Cryptographic": {
      "Secret": "ItBc_kEA3qHg6yX6yBxH1g",
      "Encryption": "A128CBC",
      "Authentication": "HS256",
      "Ticket":
      "IM0-ckQhshugjI3tqNXOLg9U1vH_AwbVjTn6er3ujSBhfQKNDEAexBBaz2
      crf1D4TlwzRI9kBky0zPj_9GcfvMXztfxy3Px31TkgnQ3ZWyuUgZ7NhEjU7
      Ua5p5gNIm0B17JRksbJ4D2imJYpL28Olw"}}}
]]>
            </artwork>
          </figure>

	<t>
		To complete the transaction, the client sends a TicketRequest message
		to the service containing a response to the PIN challenge sent by the
		service (ChallengeResponse). 
		
	</t>
	<t>
		The TicketRequest message is authenticated using HTTP Session authentication
		under the shared secret specified in the OpenResponse message:
	</t>

          <figure>
            <artwork>
<![CDATA[POST /.well-known/OmniConnect/ HTTP/1.1
Content-Type: application/json;charset=UTF-8
Cache-Control: no-store
Session: Value=4jgdv2Zab4ZzeWvtiVWuXzLoQR1xIqZWYofPnWQRqTk;
  Id=IM0-ckQhshugjI3tqNXOLg9U1vH_AwbVjTn6er3ujSBhfQKNDEAexBBaz2cr
  f1D4TlwzRI9kBky0zPj_9GcfvMXztfxy3Px31TkgnQ3ZWyuUgZ7NhEjU7Ua5p5g
  NIm0B17JRksbJ4D2imJYpL28Olw
Host: localhost
Content-Length: 95
Expect: 100-continue

{
  "TicketRequest": {
    "ChallengeResponse":
    "XVfo6g13In7PBHi36RSY9zFlWjQGZKtwZLrcr3IpR7E"}}
]]>
            </artwork>
          </figure>

	<t>
		The service checks the value of ChallengeResponse against the 
		known PIN and if the result is correct establishes parameters
		for the Connection Binding for the device.
	</t>
	<t>
		In this case the server uses the Session Id parameter to 
		encode permissions associated with the request as described
		in [Appendix TBS]. Accordingly the server must replace the
		Session Id whenever the associated permissions change.
		Accordingly, the server replaces the cryptographic parameters 
		specified in the OpenResponse request for use in future
		JCX service requests.

    In this case the server returns three connections, each
    offering a
    different transport protocol option. Each connection specifies
     its
    own set of cryptographic parameters (or will when the code is
     written
    for that).
	</t>
	<t>
		The service also returns a service connection the malware 
		protection service the client requested access to. This
		service connection specifies three different service instances.
		Each service instance has its own set of cryptographic
		parameters for use with HTTP session authentication. 
		In this case the three different service instances offer
		different means of accessing the same service: as a JSON
		Web Service over HTTP, using a binary encoding over a 
		UDP transport and tunnelling via DNS.
	</t>
          <figure>
            <artwork>
<![CDATA[HTTP/1.1 OK Complete
Content-Length: 813
Date: Mon, 08 Jul 2013 20:15:20 GMT
Server: Microsoft-HTTPAPI/2.0

{
  "TicketResponse": {
    "Status": 200,
    "StatusDescription": "Complete",
    "Cryptographic": [{
        "Protocol": "OBPConnection",
        "Secret": "hXAqqh4NEjwtRDSoKIvtzA",
        "Encryption": "A128CBC",
        "Authentication": "HS256",
        "Ticket":
        "Xjt69Q12akY0P8nOt-SzJR6N07JjvP8uknob-65yHXVCyADVWyrRbkXp
        DVGvJvmeQci1p1IBciAQ1ydiGEkFZgqzmNWMXDuxBOwyJXUhkQs"}],
    "Service": [{
        "Port": 0,
        "Priority": 0,
        "Weight": 0,
        "Transport": "WebService",
        "Cryptographic": {
          "Protocol": "OBPQuery",
          "Secret": "aOWP9WTGASL6-PSWzd-7Jg",
          "Encryption": "A128CBC",
          "Authentication": "HS256",
          "Ticket":
          "1QH5InQETNdZLGV_tZrpK1Si1oYclVSa8uwFF-7tjpPGy9WagID61I
          62VR8NgilvA7aOf06KVucpkjYwLU7M06JYhDW2jwenzwYqPbOjVjA"}
          }]}}
]]>
            </artwork>
          </figure>
	</section>
	<section title="Unbinding">
      <t>
	    After a year of use, Alice decides to replace the laptop with a new one.
		Before selling the old laptop on EBay, she tells the Web Service client to
		cancel the connection to the Web Service Provider.
	  </t>
	  <t>
	    The client sends the following mesasage to the provider:
	  </t>
          <figure>
            <artwork>
<![CDATA[POST /.well-known/OmniConnect/ HTTP/1.1
Content-Type: application/json;charset=UTF-8
Cache-Control: no-store
Session: Value=xNQbmTL8KI_TphOwQx8QUxyxhh4PTwJO1XmXh7waapY;
  Id=IM0-ckQhshugjI3tqNXOLg9U1vH_AwbVjTn6er3ujSBhfQKNDEAexBBaz2cr
  f1D4TlwzRI9kBky0zPj_9GcfvMXztfxy3Px31TkgnQ3ZWyuUgZ7NhEjU7Ua5p5g
  NIm0B17JRksbJ4D2imJYpL28Olw
Host: localhost
Content-Length: 24
Expect: 100-continue

{
  "UnbindRequest": {}}
]]>
            </artwork>
          </figure>
	  <t>
	    The Session ID specifies the connection binding. Since the Unbind Request 
		is only valid for that connection binding, there is no need to specify the
		connection binding further in the request.
	  </t>
	  <t>
	    The server verifies that the request was authenticated and returns a 
		successful response:
	  </t>
          <figure>
            <artwork>
<![CDATA[HTTP/1.1 OK Unbound
Content-Length: 79
Date: Mon, 08 Jul 2013 20:15:20 GMT
Server: Microsoft-HTTPAPI/2.0

{
  "UnbindResponse": {
    "Status": 200,
    "StatusDescription": "Unbound"}}
]]>
            </artwork>
          </figure>


		  <t>
		  [TBS: Add in the status response back into the JSON message. ]
		  </t>
	</section>
	<section title="Out of Band Completion">
	  <t>
        Alice purchases an Internet enabled coffee pot. The installer configures 
		the coffee pot in her kitchen but does not have access to Alice's JCX 
		account or a PIN code to configure it.
      </t>

	  <t>
	    The installer configures the coffee pot to use the JCX account specified
		by Alice. The coffee pot does not have a pssscode to enter but does have
		a link to an image of the coffee pot.
	  </t>
      	  <t>
	    The client sends the following request:
	  </t>
	  <t>
	    [TBS: non pin code example]
	  </t>

	  <t>
	    Since the client does not have a PIN code, there is no need to 
		return a challenge. Instead the service returns the status "OOB" to 
		indicate that the transaction will be completed out of band.
	  </t>

	  <t>
	    [TBS: non pin code example]
	  </t>



	  <t>
	    By default the coffee pot attempts to complete the JCX connection at ten second 
		intervals for the first ten minutes, every thirty seconds for the next
		hour, every five minutes for the following 24 hours and once an hour 
		thereafter.
	  </t>
      <t>
	    The client sends the following request to check the status of the request:
	  </t>
	  <t>
	    [TBS: should add in a parameter 'don't call again for x seconds']
	  </t>

	  <t>
	    The first service response tells the coffee pot not to ask again until
		five minutes have elapsed:
	  </t>
	  <t>
	    [TBS: non pin code example]
	  </t>

	  <t>
		The installer calls Alice to tell her that the coffee pot is ready to
		connect. Alice authorizes the connection remotely via the Web Service
		Provider's Web site. Alice identifies the request to connect the
		coffee pot by means of the image provided. She can also use the same 
		image to help determine which connection to cancel when the coffee pot
		is replaced.
	  </t>
	  <t>
	    The next time the coffee pot requests a status update, the service
		responds with the connection binding parameters:
	  </t>
	  <t>
	    [TBS: non pin code example]
	  </t>
        </section>
        </section>
<!-- End section of automatically generated text -->


    



<section title="OBPConnection">


<section title="Message: Message">


<!-- No parameters -->

</section>
<section title="Message: Response">


<t> <list style="hanging" hangIndent="6">
<t hangText="Status : Integer [0..1]   "><vspace />
Application layer server status code
</t>
<t hangText="StatusDescription : String [0..1]   "><vspace />
Describes the status code (ignored by processors)
</t>
</list></t>

</section>
<section title="Message: ErrorResponse">

<t>
An error response MAY be returned in response to any request.
</t>
<t>
Note that requests MAY be rejected by the code implementing
the transport binding before application processing begins
and so a server is not guaranteed to provide an error response
message.
</t>

<!-- No parameters -->

</section>
<section title="Message: Request">


<!-- No parameters -->

</section>
<section title="Structure: Cryptographic">

<t>
Parameters describing a cryptographic context.
</t>

<t> <list style="hanging" hangIndent="6">
<t hangText="Protocol : Label [0..1]   "><vspace />
OBP tickets MAY be restricted to use with either the management
protocol (Management) or the query protocol (Query). If so a 
service would typically 
specify a ticket with a long expiry time or no expiry for use with 
the management protocol and a separate ticket for use with the 
query protocol.
</t>
<t hangText="Secret : Binary [1..1]   "><vspace />
Shared secret
</t>
<t hangText="Encryption : Label [1..1]   "><vspace />
Encryption Algorithm selected
</t>
<t hangText="Authentication : Label [1..1]   "><vspace />
Authentication Algorithm selected
</t>
<t hangText="Ticket : Binary [1..1]   "><vspace />
Opaque ticket issued by the server that identifies
the cryptographic parameters for encryption and
authentication of the message payload.
</t>
<t hangText="Expires : DateTime [0..1]   "><vspace />
Date and time at which the context will expire
</t>
</list></t>

</section>
<section title="Structure: ImageLink">


<t> <list style="hanging" hangIndent="6">
<t hangText="Algorithm : Label [0..1]   "><vspace />
Image encoding algorithm (e.g. JPG, PNG)
</t>
<t hangText="Image : Binary [0..1]   "><vspace />
Image data as specified by algorithm
</t>
</list></t>

</section>
<section title="Structure: Connection">

<t>
Contains information describing a network connection.
</t>

<t> <list style="hanging" hangIndent="6">
<t hangText="Name : Name [0..1]   "><vspace />
DNS Name. Since one of the functions of an OBP service is name
resolution, a DNS name is only used to establish a connection if
connection by means of the IP address fails.
</t>
<t hangText="Port : Integer [0..1]   "><vspace />
TCP or UDP port number.
</t>
<t hangText="Address : String [0..1]   "><vspace />
IPv4 (32 bit) or IPv6 (128 bit) service address
</t>
<t hangText="Priority : Integer [0..1]   "><vspace />
Service priority. Services with lower priority numbers SHOULD
be attempted before those with higher numbers.
</t>
<t hangText="Weight : Integer [0..1]   "><vspace />
Weight to be used to select between services of equal priority.
</t>
<t hangText="Transport : Label [0..1]   "><vspace />
OBP Transport binding to be used valid values are HTTP, DNS and UDP.
</t>
<t hangText="Expires : DateTime [0..1]   "><vspace />
Date and time at which the specified connection context will expire.
</t>
<t hangText="Cryptographic : Cryptographic [0..1]   "><vspace />
Cryptographic Parameters.
</t>
</list></t>

</section>
<section title="Bind">

<t>
Binding a device is a two step protocol that begins with the
Start Query followed by a sequence of Ticket queries.
</t>

</section>
<section title="Message: BindRequest">

<t>
The following parameters MAY occur in either a
StartRequest or TicketRequest:
</t>

<t> <list style="hanging" hangIndent="6">
<t hangText="Encryption : Label [0..Many]   "><vspace />
Encryption Algorithm that the client accepts. A Client MAY
offer multiple algorithms. If no algorithms are specified then
support for the mandatory to implement algorithm is assumed.
Otherwise mandatory to implement algorithms MUST be 
specified explicitly.
</t>
<t hangText="Authentication : Label [0..Many]   "><vspace />
Authentication Algorithm that the client accepts.
If no algorithms are specified then
support for the mandatory to implement algorithm is assumed.
Otherwise mandatory to implement algorithms MUST be 
specified explicitly. 
</t>
</list></t>

</section>
<section title="Message: OpenPINRequest">

<t>
The OpenRequest Message is used to begin a device binding transaction.
Depending on the authentication requirements of the service the
transaction may be completed in a single query or require a 
further Ticket Query to complete.
</t>
<t>
If authentication is required, the mechanism to be used depends on
the capabilities of the device, the requirements of the broker and
the existing relationship between the user and the broker.
</t>
<t>
If the device supports some means of data entry, authentication 
MAY be achieved by entering a passcode previously delivered out
of band into the device.
</t>
<t>
The OpenRequest specifies the properties of the service
(Account, Domain) and Device (ID, URI, Name) that will remain
constant throughout the period that the device binding is active
and parameters to be used for the mutual authentication protocol.
</t>

<t> <list style="hanging" hangIndent="6">
<t hangText="Account : String [0..1]   "><vspace />
Account name of the user at the OBP service
</t>
<t hangText="Domain : Name [0..1]   "><vspace />
Domain name of the OBP broker service
</t>
<t hangText="HavePasscode : Boolean [0..1]  Default =False "><vspace />
If 'true', the user has entered a passcode value for 
use with passcode authentication.
</t>
<t hangText="HaveDisplay : Boolean [0..1]  Default =False "><vspace />
Specifies if the device is capable of displaying information
to the user or not.
</t>
<t hangText="Challenge : Binary [0..1]   "><vspace />
Client challenge value to be used in authentication challenge
mechanism as described in section <xref target="ChallengeResponse" />
</t>
<t hangText="DeviceID : URI [0..1]   "><vspace />
Device identifier unique for a particular instance of a device such as a MAC or EUI-64 address expressed as a URI
</t>
<t hangText="DeviceURI : URI [0..1]   "><vspace />
Device identifier specifying the type of device, e.g. an xPhone.
</t>
<t hangText="DeviceImage : ImageLink [0..1]   "><vspace />
An image identifying the physical appearance of the device. 
</t>
<t hangText="DeviceName : String [0..1]   "><vspace />
Descriptive name for the device that would distinguish it 
from other similar devices, e.g. 'Alice's xPhone".
</t>
</list></t>

</section>
<section title="Message: OpenPINResponse">

<t>
An Open request MAY be accepted immediately or be held pending
completion of an inband or out-of-band authentication process.
</t>
<t>
The OpenResponse returns a ticket and a set of cryptographic
connection parameters in either case. If the 
</t>

<t> <list style="hanging" hangIndent="6">
<t hangText="Challenge : Binary [0..1]   "><vspace />
Challenge value to be used by the client to respond
to the server authentication challenge.
</t>
<t hangText="ChallengeResponse : Binary [0..1]   "><vspace />
Server response to authentication challenge by the client
as described in section <xref target="ChallengeResponse" />
</t>
<t hangText="Cryptographic : Cryptographic [0..1]   "><vspace />
Cryptographic Parameters.
</t>
<t hangText="VerificationImage : ImageLink [0..Many]   "><vspace />
Link to an image to be used in an image verification mechanism.
</t>
</list></t>

</section>
<section title="Message: TicketRequest">

<t>
The TicketRequest message is used to (1) complete a binding request
begun with an OpenRequest and (2) to refresh ticket or connection 
parameters as necessary.
</t>

<t> <list style="hanging" hangIndent="6">
<t hangText="ChallengeResponse : Binary [0..1]   "><vspace />
The response to a serer authentication challenge 
as described in section <xref target="ChallengeResponse" />
</t>
</list></t>

</section>
<section title="Message: TicketResponse">

<t>
The TicketResponse message returns cryptographic and/or connection
context information to a client.
</t>

<t> <list style="hanging" hangIndent="6">
<t hangText="Cryptographic : Cryptographic [0..Many]   "><vspace />
Cryptographic Parameters.
</t>
<t hangText="Service : Connection [0..Many]   "><vspace />
A Connection describing an OBP service point
</t>
</list></t>

</section>
<section title="Unbind">

<t>
Requests that a previous device association be deleted.
</t>

</section>
<section title="Message: UnbindRequest">

<t>
Since the ticket identifies the binding to be deleted, the
only thing that the unbind message need specify is that
the device wishes to cancel the binding.
</t>

<!-- No parameters -->

</section>
<section title="Message: UnbindResponse">

<t>
Reports on the success of the unbinding operation.
</t>
<t>
If the server reports success, the client SHOULD delete the
ticket and all information relating to the binding.
</t>
<t>
A service MAY continue to accept a ticket after an unbind request
has been granted but MUST NOT accept such a ticket for
a bind request.
</t>

<!-- No parameters -->

</section>

</section>



    

    
    
    
    <section title="Mutual Authentication" anchor="MutualAuth">
      <t>
        A Connection Service MAY require that a connection request be  
        authenticated. Two authentication mechanisms are         defined.
      </t>
      <t>
        <list style="hanging">

          <t hangText="PIN Code">
            The client and server demonstrate mutual
            knowledge of
            a PIN code previously exchanged out of band.
          </t>

          <t hangText="Out of Band Confirmation">
           The request for access is  
            confirmed out of band.
          </t>

        </list>
      </t>
	  <t>
	    In addition, services MAY accept the use of any message or transport 
		layer authentication scheme. For example HTTP Session Continuation or
		Transport Layer Security with client authentication.
	  </t>
    
      <section title="PIN Authentication" anchor="ChallengeResponse">
        <t>
          PIN code authentication provides users with a simple and often familiar
		  mechanism for authenticating the connection request. The means by which
		  the user obtains the PIN code is outside the scope of this document.
		  Possible methods for distributing the PIN code include obtaining the
		  code from an account management Web site provided by the Web Service
		  Provider, letter post, email and in person.
        </t>
        <t>
          Although the PIN value is never exposed on the wire in any form,
          the protcol considers the PIN value to be text encoded  
          in UTF8 encoding.
        </t>
		<t>
		  To encourage readability, the use of space (0x20) and hyphen (0x2D)
		  characters to arrange PIN characters into groups of four to seven
		  characters is encouraged. To avoid the risk of this practice introducing
		  user error, space and hyphen characters are ignored when processing the PIN 
		  value.
		</t>
        <t>
		  Support for the full UNICODE character set in PIN codes is intended
		  to facilitate provision of PIN codes in the user's native language.
		  Web Service Providers MAY make use of any UNICODE characters they
		  choose but capricious choices are likely to cause users difficulty.
		  For example a PIN code MAY contain the ZAPF Dingbats thick tick mark 
		  (U+2704) but users would almost certainly find it difficult to enter
		  and may confuse it with the similar thin tick mark (U+2703).
        </t>
		<t>
		  Servers that support PIN Authorization SHOULD offer the choice of a 
		  PIN that only uses numeric 
		  digits ('0', '1', '2', '3', '4', '5', '6', '7', '8', '9'). Clients
		  that support PIN Authorization MUST allow entry of PINS that only 
		  contain numeric digits.
		</t>
        <t>
          The PIN Mechanism is a three step process:
        </t>
        <t>
          <list>
            <t>
              The client sends an OpenRequest message to the
              Service containing a challenge value CC.
            </t>
            <t>
              The service returns an OpenResponse message
              containing to the client a server
              challenge value SV and a server response value SR.
            </t>
            <t>
              The client sends a TicketRequest message to the
              service containing
              a client response value CR.
            </t>
          </list>
        </t>
        <t>
          Since no prior authentication key has been established
          the OpenRequest and OpenResponse messages are
          sent without message authentication.
        </t>
        <t>
          The Challenge values CC,  and SC are cryptographic
          nonces. The nonces  
          SHOULD be generated using an appropriate cryptographic
           random
          source. The nonces MUST be at least as long as 128
          bits, MUST be at least  
          the minimum key size  
          of the authentication algorithm used and MUST NOT more
           than 640 bits  
          in length (640 bits should be enough for anybody).
        </t>
        <t>
          The server response and client response values are
          generated
          using an authentication algorithm selected by the
          server from the
          choices proposed by the client in the OpenRequest
          message.
        </t>
        <t>
          The algorithn chosen may be a MAC algorithm or an  
          encrypt-with-authentication (EWA) algorithm. If an EWA
           is specified,  
          the encrypted data is discarded and only the
          authentication  
          value is used in its place.
        </t>
        <t>
          Let A(d,k) be the authentication value obtained by
          applying the  
          authentication algorithm with key k to data d.
        </t>
        <t>
          To create the Server Response value, the UTF8 encoding
           of the
          PIN value 'P' is first pre-processed to remove space and
		  hyphen characters, then
		  converted into a symmetric key KPC by using the
           Client
          challenge value as the key
          truncating if necessary and then applied to the
          of the
          OpenRequest message:
        </t>
<figure>
            <artwork>
<![CDATA[
	KPC = A (PIN, CC)
	SR = A (Secret + OpenRequest, KPC)
		  ]]>
            </artwork>
          </figure>
        <t>
          In the Web Service Binding, the Payload of the message
           is the  
          HTTP Body as presented on the wire. The Secret and
          Server  
          Challenge are presented in their
          binary format and the '+' operator stands for simple
          concatenation
          of the binary sequences.
        </t>
        <t>
          This protocol construction ensures that the party
          constructing
          SR:
        </t>
        <t>
          <list>
            <t>
              Knows the PIN code value (through the construction
               of KPC).
            </t>
            <t>
              Is responding to the Open Request Message (SR
              depends on  
              OpenRequest).
            </t>
            <t>
              Has knowlege of the secret key which MUST be used
               to  
              authenticate the following
              TicketRequest/TicketResponse
              interaction that will establish the actual
              connection.
            </t>
            <t>
              Does not provide an oracle the PIN value. That is,
               the protocol  
              does not provide a service that reveals the (since
               the value SR
              includes the value SC which is a random nonce
              generated
              by the server and cannot be predicted by the
              client).
            </t>
          </list>
        </t>

        <t>
          To create the Client Response value, secret key is
          applied  
          to the PIN value and server Challenge:
        </t>
<figure>
            <artwork>
<![CDATA[
	CR = A (PIN + SC + OpenResponse, Secret)
]]>
            </artwork>
          </figure>
                <t>
          Note that the server can calculate the value of the
          Client Response
          token at the time that it generates the Server
          Challenge.
          This minimizes the amount of state that needs to be
          carried from  
          one request to the next in the Ticket value when using
           the stateless
          server implementation described in section <xref target="stateless" />
        </t>
        <t>
          This protocol construction ensures that the generator
          of CR
        </t>
        <t>
          <list>
            <t>
              Knows the PIN value.
            </t>
            <t>
              Is respoding to the OpenResponse generated by the
               server.
            </t>
          </list>
        </t>
        <t>
          Note that while disclosure of an oracle for the PIN
          value is a  
          concern in the  
          construction of CR, this is not the case in the
          construction of  
          SR since the client has already demonstrated knowledge
           of the  
          PIN value.
        </t>

        </section>

        <section title="Example: Latin PIN Code">
          <t>
            The Connection Request example of section  
            <xref target="ConnectionRequestExample" />
            demonstrates the use
            of an alphanumeric PIN code using the Latin alphabet.
          </t>
          <t>
            The PIN code is [Q80370-1RA606-F04B] and the authentication algorithm
             is [HS256].
            The value KPC is calculated thus:
          </t>
<t>
PIN: 51 38 30 33 37 30 2d 31 52 41 36 30 36 2d 46 30 34 42 </t>
<t>
Client Challenge: c5 ff d1 62 ce 6c a2 66 6a a1 83 42 fc c6 f0 8e </t>
<t>
KPC: 66 df 59 06 14 26 72 5e 21 39 9c df 9c 51 48 aa bb b9 eb 73 cf e7 54 6c 5b 00 47 b1 81 31 f2 4b </t>
          <t>
			For the sake of example, we take the OpenRequest message 
			payload to be {...}.
            The data over which the hash value is calulated is
            Secret + OpenRequest:
          </t>

<t>
Secret: 22 d0 5c fe 41 00 de a1 e0 eb 25 fa c8 1c 47 d6 </t>
<t>
Request Payload: 7b 2e 2e 2e 7d </t>
<t>
Server Response: 26 6b 9f 07 6a a7 01 5d 74 bc 69 a0 fe fb c3 48 28 cc 3e a4 aa e5 68 b5 05 4e 20 b0 65 7d 73 c6 </t>
          <t>
            The data for the client response is PIN + Server Challenge + Payload:
          </t>
<t>
PIN: 51 38 30 33 37 30 2d 31 52 41 36 30 36 2d 46 30 34 42 </t>
<t>
Server Challenge: b1 f4 d6 b5 5a c2 96 2a d8 0f 08 0f 0d 62 0c 54 </t>
<t>
Request Payload: 7b 2e 2e 2e 7d </t>
          <t>
            Applying the key Secret to the data produces the
            client
            response:
          </t>
<t>
Client Response: fa dc 7e 72 8c 1b 92 49 c3 98 95 6d fa 15 17 84 ec f3 dd 38 08 d2 b1 a7 1b 60 78 01 83 7d 70 c6 </t>
        </section>
        <section title="Example: Cyrillic PIN Code">
          <t>
            If the PIN code in the earlier example was 'parol1' (the Russian 
            for 'password1') in Cyrilic script the value KP would be calculated as follows
          </t>
<t>
PIN: d0 bf d0 b0 d1 80 d0 be d0 bb d1 8c 31 </t>
<t>
KPC: 66 df 59 06 14 26 72 5e 21 39 9c df 9c 51 48 aa bb b9 eb 73 cf e7 54 6c 5b 00 47 b1 81 31 f2 4b </t>
          <t>
            The rest of the protocol would then continue as
            before.
          </t>
        </section>

      <section title="Out of Band Confirmation" anchor="OOBConfirmation">
        <t>
          The Out Of Band Confirmation mechanism is a three step  
          process in which:
        </t>
        <t>
          <list>
            <t>
              The client makes an OpenRequest message to the
              service
              and obtains an OpenResponse message.
            </t>
            <t>
              The connection binding is
              authorized through an out of band process.
            </t>
            <t>
              The client makes a TicketRequest to the service
              and obtains a TicketResponse message to complete  
              the exchange.
            </t>
          </list>
        </t>
        <t>
          Since no prior authentication key has been established
          the  
          OpenRequest and OpenResponse messages are sent without  
          authentication.
        </t>
        <t>
          The principal concern in the Out Of Band Confirmation  
          mechanism is ensuring that the party authorizing the
          request is able to identify which party originated
          the request they are attempting to identify.
        </t>
        <t>
          If a device has the ability to display an image it
          MAY set the HasDisplay=true in the OpenRequest message.
          If the broker recieves an OpenRequest with the
          HasDisplay
          value set to true, the OpenResponse MAY contain one or
           more
          VerificationImage entries specifying image data that
          is
          to be displayed to the user by both the client and the
          confirmation interface.
        </t>
        <t>
          Before confirming the request, the user SHOULD verify  
          that the two images are the same and reject the request
          in the case that they are not.
        </t>
        <t>
          Many devices do not have a display capability, in
          particular
          an embedded device such as a network switch or a
          thermostat.
          In this case the device MAY be identified by means of
           the
          information provided in  
          DeviceID, DeviceURI, DeviceImage and DeviceName.
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>





    <section title="Protocol Binding">

      <t>
        A single protocol binding is defined:
        <list>
          <t>JSON encoding is used to express JCX messages.</t>
          <t>A HTTP session layer with HTTP session continuation is used for message authentication.</t>
          <t>TLS transport is required for confidentiality and service authentication.</t>
        </list>
      </t>
      <t>
        Implementations MAY support use of alternative encodings, session layers or transports
        provided that the necessary confidentiality and authentication criteria described 
        below are met. The means by which negotiation of the use of such encodings is achieved
        is outside the scop of this document.
      </t>

      <t>
        
      </t>
      <section title="JSON encoding">
        <t>
          Messages are expressed in JSON encoding <xref target="RFC4627" />. 
        </t>
        

        <t>
          Protocol schema types are mapped to JSON encoding as follows:
          <list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="Integer">
              Data of type Integer  is encoded using the JSON number
              encoding.</t>
            <t hangText="Name">Data of type Name is encoded using the JSON string
            encoding.</t>
            <t hangText="String">Data of type String is encoded using the JSON string
            encoding.</t>            
            <t hangText="Binary">Data of type Binary  is converted to strings using
            the Base64url encoding specified in <xref target="RFC4648" />
            and encoded using the JSON string type.</t>
        <t hangText="DateTime">Data of type DateTime  is converted to string using the
          UTC time conversion specified in <xref target="RFC3339" /> with a UTC 
          offset of 00:00.
          </t>
          </list>
        </t>
        
      
      </section>
      <section title="HTTP Session Layer">
        <t>
          Messages are presented over a HTTP session layer
          <xref target="RFC2616" />.
          The use of HTTP as 
          a session layer permits multiple Web Services on the same host to 
          share the same DNS name, IP address and port number and enables use
          of HTTP Session Continuation <xref target="I-D.hallambaker-httpsession" />
          for message authentication.
        </t>
        <t>
          Use of HTTP Session Continuation mechanism allows message authentication 
          data to be presented in the HTTP message
          header rather than the message content provides a clean separation of
          the message authentication data from the data being authenticated.
          The scope of the authentication data is simply the message content 
          after transport encoding (e.g. chunked) has been removed.
        </t>
        <t>
          The use of HTTP session continuation is necessary to achieve mutual
          authentication even though TLS transport is required.
        </t>
        <t>
          Only the HTTP Session header is used. The negotiation of the Session
          parameters is performed within JCX.
        </t>
        <t>
          [TO-DO: Specify TLS binding options?]
        </t>
        <t>
          [TO-DO: Switch back from using JOSE algorithm names to HTTP Session 
          algorithm names]
        </t>
      </section>
      <section title="TLS transport">
        <t>
          TLS transport <xref target="RFC4627" /> is used
        </t>
        <t>
          Support for the PKIX logotype extension <xref target="RFC3709" /> is highly recommended
        </t>
        <t>Use of an enhanced assurance certificate (e.g. CABForum EV) is likely 
        to be required in most
        applications and is strongly recommended if Lotypes are used.
      </t>

      </section>
    </section>
    <section title="Service Identification and Discovery">
      <t>
        The prefix '[PREFIX-TBD]' has been registered for use as a protocol
        identifier for JCX in the URI, SRV and Well Known Location registries.
      </t>      
      <t>
        The URI form identifying a JCX account identifier is:
      </t>
      <t>
        PREFIX-TBD:&lt;service&gt;:&lt;account&gt;:&lt; or
        PREFIX-TBD:&lt;service&gt;:&lt;account&gt;:&lt;:subaccount&gt;
      </t>
      <t>
        Where &lt;service&gt; is the DNS name of the Web Service Provider, 
        &lt;account&gt; is the name of the account at the service provider and
        &lt;subaccount&gt; is an optional sub-account specifier.
      </t>
      <t>
        Use of the URI form is only needed in cases where the purpose of 
        the identifier is not clear from the context, in a HTML anchor for 
        example. A JCX client requesting entry of the service account identifier 
        MUST support entry of the short form identifier:
      </t>
      <t>
        &lt;account&gt;@&lt;service&gt; or
        &lt;:subaccount&gt;/&lt;account&gt;@&lt;service&gt;
        </t>

      <t>
        DNS Service (SRV) record discovery is the preferred method of host discovery 
        as this provides for fault tollerance and load balancing. 
        
      </t>
      <t>
        JCX clients SHOULD support use of DNS SRV records for host discovery and 
        MUST support use of DNS A/AAAA records for host discovery. 
      </t>
      <t>
        A compliant JCX service MUST be offered at the .well-known location
        /.well-known/PREFIX-TBD. Use of JCX protocol at other service locations
        is permissible for testing and
        protocol development purposes but such configurations are not 
        compliant and clients are not required to support them. The URL for 
        the JCX service is therefore:
      </t>
      <t>
        https://&lt;service&gt;/.well-known/PREFIX-TBD
      </t>
    </section>
    <section title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>
        [List of contributors]
      </t>
    </section>
    <section title="Security Considerations">

      <section title="Denial of Service">
      </section>
      <section title="Breach of Trust">
      </section>
      <section title="Coercion">
      </section>

    </section>

    <section title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>
        [TBS list out all the code points that require an IANA
        registration]
      </t>
    </section>

  </middle>



  <back>


    <references title="Normative References">
      &RFC1035;
      &RFC2119;
      &RFC2616;
      &RFC4366;
      &RFC4627;
      &RFC4648;
      &RFC3339;      
      &draft-hallambaker-httpsession;
      <reference anchor="X.509">
        <front>
          <title>
            ITU-T Recommendation X.509 (11/2008): Information
            technology - Open systems interconnection - The
            Directory: Public-key and attribute certificate
            frameworks
          </title>
          <author>
            <organization>
              International Telecommunication Union
            </organization>
          </author>
          <date month="November" year="2008" />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="ITU-T Recommendation" value="X.509" />
        <format type="HTML" target="http://www.itu.int/itu-t/recommendations/rec.aspx?rec=X.509" />
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="X.680">
        <front>
          <title>
            ITU-T Recommendation X.680 (11/2008): Information
            technology - Abstract Syntax Notation One (ASN.1):
            Specification of basic notation
          </title>
          <author>
            <organization>
              International Telecommunication Union
            </organization>
          </author>
          <date month="November" year="2008" />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="ITU-T Recommendation" value="X.680" />
        <format type="HTML" target="http://www.itu.int/itu-t/recommendations/rec.aspx?rec=X.680" />
      </reference>

    </references>
    <references title="Non Normative References">
      &RFC3709;
        </references>

    <section title="Stateless server" anchor="stateless">
	<t>
		The protocol is designed to permit but not require 
		the server to store connection binding state in the 
		Session ID of the HTTP Session Continuation authentication
		mechanism.
	</t>
	<t>
		The Session IDs are opaque as far as the client is concerned.
		The client receives the Session ID from the service and returns it 
		with each request. The internal structure of the Session ID is
		therefore outside the scope of this specification but is
		provided here to assist implementers.
	</t>
	<t>
		In the PIN Authentication example, two SessionIDs are 
		issued by the server:
	</t>

	<t>
		<list>
			<t>
				A temporary ID in response to the initial client OpenRequest.
			</t>
			<t>
				A connection binding ID when the client PIN confirmation is accepted and the 
				connection binding is created.
			</t>
		</list>
	</t>
	<t>
		Both tickets have the same common wrapper structure:
	</t>
  <t>
    IV + Encrypt ( Ticket + Mac ( Ticket, Key) Key)
  </t>
  <t>
    Where
    <list>
      <t hangText="IV">The Initialization vector for the encryption scheme</t>
      <t hangText="Encrypt">The Encryption algorithm (AES in CBC Mode)</t>
      <t hangText="Ticket">The ticket data</t>
      <t hangText="MAC">The Message Authentication algorithm (HMAC-SHA2-256)</t>
    </list>
  </t>

	<section title="Temporary  ID">
		<t>
			The temporary ticket returned in the OpenRequest example above
			is represented in Base64URL encoding as follows:
		</t>
		<t>
		IM0-ckQhshugjI3tqNXOLg9U1vH_AwbVjTn6er3ujSBhfQKNDEAexBBaz2crf1D4T
  lwzRI9kBky0zPj_9GcfvMXztfxy3Px31TkgnQ3ZWyuUgZ7NhEjU7Ua5p5gNIm0B
  17JRksbJ4D2imJYpL28Olw

		</t>
<t>The format of the ticket is 16

</t>
<t>
IV: 20 cd 3e 72 44 21 b2 1b a0 8c 8d ed a8 d5 ce 2e </t>
<t>
Encrypted Data: 0f 54 d6 f1 ff 03 06 d5 8d 39 fa 7a bd ee 8d 20 61 7d 02 8d 0c 40 1e c4 10 5a cf 67 2b 7f 50 f8 4e 5c 33 44 8f 64 06 4c b4 cc f8 ff f4 67 1f bc c5 f3 b5 fc 72 dc fc 77 d5 39 20 9d 0d d9 5b 2b 94 81 9e cd 84 48 d4 ed 46 b9 a7 98 0d 22 6d 01 d7 b2 51 92 c6 c9 e0 3d a2 98 96 29 2f 6f 0e 97 </t>

<t>
The encrypted data is decrypted under the master key of the server. In this example
the server has a single fixed key that does not change over time. There should really 
be a key index prefixing it to identify the key number.
</t>

<t>
The Master Key is: ca 00 d4 de ba f2 fc 68 57 a7 58 e5 61 0a 39 4c </t>

<t>
The decrypted data contains the algorithm identifiers, shared secret and message authentication code:
</t>


<t>
Version Number: 00 </t>
<t>
Key Identifier: 01 </t>
<t>
Authentication Algorithm: 00 </t>
<t>
Encryption Algorithm: 00 </t>
<t>
Key Data: 22 d0 5c fe 41 00 de a1 e0 eb 25 fa c8 1c 47 d6 </t>
<t>
User Name Length: 11 </t>
<t>
User Name: 61 6c 69 63 65 40 65 78 61 6d 70 6c 65 2e 63 6f 6d </t>
<t>
Client Challenge Length: 10 </t>
<t>
Client Challenge: c5 ff d1 62 ce 6c a2 66 6a a1 83 42 fc c6 f0 8e </t>
<t>
Server Challenge Length: 10 </t>
<t>
Server Challenge: b1 f4 d6 b5 5a c2 96 2a d8 0f 08 0f 0d 62 0c 54 </t>
<t>
Message Authentication Code: 72 19 96 25 20 d9 d0 bf 78 cd 7f c9 31 73 51 ac 8f 69 19 f3 18 0f 9f d4 2d 2a 43 40 17 a7 71 e1 </t>
	</section>
	<section title="Connection Binding ID">

	<t>
	The format of the Connection binding ticket is similar to that of the 
	Temporary ticket except that it does not contain the Client or Server 
	challenge nonces.
	</t>
<t>
IV: 5e 3b 7a f5 0d 76 6a 46 34 3f c9 ce b7 e4 b3 25 </t>
<t>
Encrypted Data: 1e 8d d3 b2 63 bc ff 2e 92 7a 1b fb ae 72 1d 75 42 c8 00 d5 5b 2a d1 6e 45 e9 0d 51 af 26 f9 9e 41 c8 b5 a7 52 01 72 20 10 d7 27 62 18 49 05 66 0a b3 98 d5 8c 5c 3b b1 04 ec 32 25 75 21 91 0b </t>
<t>
The decrypted data is:
</t>


<t>
Version Number: 00 </t>
<t>
Key Identifier: 00 </t>
<t>
Authentication Algorithm: 00 </t>
<t>
Encryption Algorithm: 00 </t>
<t>
Key Data: 85 70 2a aa 1e 0d 12 3c 2d 44 34 a8 28 8b ed cc </t>
<t>
User Name Length: 0c </t>
<t>
User Name: 65 40 65 78 61 6d 70 6c 65 2e 63 40 </t>
<t>
Message Authentication Code: 8b 28 66 c0 c1 e0 35 de 43 dc b0 0c c9 64 81 90 10 73 2b 6c 51 5e 7e 47 af 58 e6 92 37 82 17 5c </t>

	</section>
</section>



  </back>
</rfc>
