<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [>
  <!ENTITY rfc2119 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml'>
  <!ENTITY i-d.seedorf-lmap-alto PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.seedorf-lmap-alto.xml'>
  <!ENTITY i-d.ietf-alto-protocol PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-alto-protocol.xml'>
]>
<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc iprnotified="no" ?>
<?rfc strict="no" ?>
<?rfc compact="no" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>

<rfc category="info" docName="draft-goergen-lmap-fcc-00" ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="ALTO Maps">Aggregating large-scale measurements for 
Application Layer Traffic Optimization (ALTO) Protocol</title>

    <author fullname="David Goergen" initials="D." surname="Goergen">
      <organization>University of Luxembourg</organization>

      <address>
        <email>david.goergen@uni.lu</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Radu State" initials="R." surname="State">
      <organization>University of Luxembourg</organization>

      <address>
        <email>radu.state@uni.lu</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Vijay K. Gurbani" initials="V." surname="Gurbani">
      <organization>Bell Labs, Alcatel-Lucent</organization>

      <address>
        <email>vijay.gurbani@alcatel-lucent.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date year="2013" />

    <area>Operations and Management</area>

    <workgroup>LMAP WG</workgroup>

    <keyword>ALTO</keyword>

    <keyword>LMAP</keyword>

    <abstract>

      <t>Analyzing and aggregating large-scale broadband measurements
      is essential to study trends and derive network analytics.  These trends 
      and analyses could be made available through well defined protocols 
      such as the Application Layer Traffic Optimization (ALTO) protocol.
      However, ALTO requires network information to be distilled
      and abstracted in form of a network map and a cost map.  We describe
      our methodology for analyzing the United States Federal Communication 
      Commission's (FCC) Measuring Broadband America (MBA) dataset to 
      derive required topology and cost maps suitable for consumption by
      an ALTO server.</t>

    </abstract>

    <note title="Requirements Language">

      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
      document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
      target="RFC2119">RFC 2119</xref>.</t>

    </note>

  </front>

  <middle>
  
    <section title="Introduction" anchor="intro">
    
      <t>Measuring broadband performance is increasingly important as 
      communications continue to move towards the Internet.
      Internet service providers (ISP), national agencies and other entities
      gather broadband data and may provide some, or all, of the dataset
      to the public for analysis.  As <xref target="I-D.seedorf-lmap-alto"/>
      notes, there are two extremes prevalent for presenting large-scale data.
      One is in the form of charts, figures, or summarized reports amenable
      for easy and quick consumption.  The other extreme includes releasing
      raw data in the form of large files containing tables formatted as 
      values separated by a delimiter.  While the former is indispensable 
      to acquire a summary view of the dataset, it does not suffice for
      additional analysis beyond what is presented.  Conversely, the problem
      with the latter option (raw files) is that the unsuspecting user 
      perusing them is lost in the deluge of data.</t>

      <t><xref target="I-D.seedorf-lmap-alto"/> offers the argument that
      a reasonable medium between the two extremes may be a protocol
      that allows a constrained set of user-driven ad-hoc queries on 
      the dataset.  It further offers that the Application Layer Traffic
      Optimization (ALTO) protocol <xref target="I-D.ietf-alto-protocol"/>
      be the protocol of choice that allows such reasoning on the dataset.
      A necessary prerequisite for using ALTO is abstracting the 
      network information into a form that is suitable for consumption by
      the protocol.  The implication of using ALTO is that data from any 
      large-scale measurement effort must first be distilled in two maps: a 
      topology map and a cost map.  Further analysis and ad-hoc queries
      can be subsequently performed on the normalized dataset.</t>

      <t>In the United States, the Federal Communication Commission (FCC)
      has embarked on a nationwide performance study of residential wireline
      broadband service <xref target="fcc"/>.  Our aim is to use the raw
      datasets from this study for analysis and to create a topology
      map and a cost map from this dataset.  ALTO queries aimed at these 
      maps will enable users and interested parties to fulfill the use 
      cases listed in Section 2 of <xref target="I-D.seedorf-lmap-alto"/>.</t>

    </section> <!-- section intro -->

    <section title="Challenges in data analysis" anchor="challenges">
      <t>The FCC Measuring Broadband America (MBA) study consisted of
      7,782 volunteers spread across the United States with adequate
      geographic diversity.  Volunteers opted in for the study, however,
      each of the volunteers remained anonymous.  An opaque integral 
      number (unit_id) represented a subscriber in the raw dataset.  This
      unit_id remains constant during the duration of the study in the dataset
      and uniquely identifies a volunteer subscriber, even if the subscriber
      switches the ISP.  More detail about the methodology used is described 
      in <xref target="fcc"/>.</t>

      <t>The dataset consisted of 12 tables, each table corresponding to
      the data drawn from a certain performance test.  For the analysis 
      we present in this document we focus on the "curr_dns" table, which 
      contains the time taken for the ISP's recursive DNS resolver to return a
      DNS A RR for a popular website domain name.  This test was ran 
      approximately every hour in a 24-hour period, and produced about 75-78
      million records per month.  This resulted in a typical file size in 
      the range of 6-7 GBytes per month.  We note that the "curr_dns" table
      is one of the smaller tables in the dataset.</t>

      <t>The first challenge, therefore, was to arrive at computing resources
      comparable in scale with respect to the dataset consisting of millions
      of records spread across gigabyte-sized files.  To analyze the volume 
      of data we used a canonical Map-Reduce computational paradigm on a
      Hadoop cluster (more details on the methodology are outlined in 
      <xref target="unit-id"/>).</t>

      <t>A second, more pressing challenge, was to identify the geographic
      location of the unit_ids generating the data.  In order to derive
      a topological map and impose costs on the links, it is important to
      know the physical locations of the unit_ids that contributed the
      measurements.  However, in the MBA dataset, the population is 
      anonymized and the individual subscriber reporting the measurement
      data is simply referred to by an opaque integral number.  Therefore,
      an important task was to use the information in the public tables
      to reveal a coarse location of the subscriber.</t>

      <t>We outline the
      methodology we used to do so in the next section.  We stress that 
      this methodology does not identify the specific location of a
      subscriber, who still remains anonymous.  Instead, it simply locates
      the subscriber in a larger metropolitan region.  This level of 
      granularity suffices for our work.</t>

    </section> <!-- challenges -->

    <section title="Geo-locating the units" anchor="unit-id">

     <t>To geo-locate the units, we simply note that broadband subscriber
     devices are likely to be configured using DHCP by their ISP.  Besides
     imparting an IP address to the subscriber device, DHCP also populates
     the DNS name servers the subscriber devices uses for DNS queries.
     In most installations, these DNS name servers are located in close
     physical proximity of the subscriber device.  The FCC technical 
     appendix states that the DNS resolution tests were targeted directly 
     at the ISP's recursive resolvers to circumvent caching and users 
     configuring the subscriber device to circumvent the ISP's DNS resolvers. 
     Therefore, a reasonable approximation of a subscribers geo-location 
     could be the geographic location of the DNS name server serving the 
     subscriber.  We use this very heuristic to geo-locate a subscriber.</t>

     <t>Thus our first, and very simple filter consisted of obtaining a
     mapping from a unit_id (representing a subscriber) to one or more
     DNS name servers that the unit_id is sending DNS requests to.  It
     turned out that while this was a necessary condition for advancing,
     it was not a sufficient one.  The raw data would need to be
     further processed to reduce inconsistencies and remove outliers.  A 
     number of interesting artifacts were uncovered during further processing 
     of the data.  These artifacts informed the selection of the unit_ids
     for further analysis.</t>

      <t>The artifacts are documented below.
      <list style="symbols">
       <t>A handful of unit_ids were geo-located in areas outside
       the contiguous United States, such as Ukraine, Poland or the United
       Kingdom.  We theorize that the subscribers corresponding to the
       unit_ids geo-located outside the contiguous United States had
       simply configured their devices to use alternate DNS servers,
       probably located outside the United States.  We removed these
       records before conducting our analysis.</t>
       <t>We also observed a reasonable number of non-ISP DNS resolvers,
       especially Google's 8.8.8.8 and 8.8.4.4 and OpenDNS 208.67.222.222 
       and 208.67.220.220.  These 4 public DNS servers are geo-located in 
       California.  We removed these records to ensure that the specific
       location that these resolvers represented was not oversampled.</t>
       <t>We noticed that a large number of unit_ids were being geo-located
       in Potwin, Kansas.  Intrigued as to why there appeared to be a large
       population of Internet users being located in a small rural community
       in Kansas, we investigated further.  It appears that Potwin, Kansas 
       is the geographical center of the United States and a number of ISPs 
       have chosen to establish data centers in or around the Potwin area.
       These ISPs generally locate their primary or secondary DNS name 
       servers in Potwin-area data centers, thus accounting for the 
       popularity of Potwin as an Internet destination.  We continue
       to further investigate on minimizing the impact of such natural
       aggregation points that, if not accounted for, will skew our
       results in an unwarranted direction.</t>
       <t>We observed some unit_ids changing ISPs during the observation
       period.  This is a normal occurrence and to the extent that the
       unit_id is geo-located in the same geographical area after the
       change in ISP, we do not exclude such unit_ids from further 
       analysis.</t>
      </list>
     </t>

     <t>Subsequent filters extracted the stable unit_ids from our dataset.
     In order to determine which unit_id are stable, i.e., remain 
     constant with respect to their geographic location over the 
     observation period from January to December 2012, we extracted for 
     each unit_id the IP address of each DNS name server it consulted.
     This is obtained by applying the map reduce paradigm on 
     the DNS dataset. We extracted for each unit_id the triggered DNS 
     servers and obtained the individual DNS servers accessed by a unit_id. 
     This was repeated for each month of the observation period. The 
     resulting sets were cleaned up of private IP addresses and other
     artifacts discussed above.  The cleaned set consisted of about
     8000 distinct unit_id.</t>
 
     <t>In order to determine the stability of each unit_id we proceeded 
     to sum up the occurrences of IP addresses over the whole 
     observation period separated in monthly files. If the IP address of 
     a DNS server occurred 12 times this meant that the unit_id always 
     accessed the same DNS server and therefore remained stable over the 
     observation period. The obtained stable unit_ids, around 1500, will be
     used for further analysis.  Assuming a 99% confidence level and +/-
     3 point margin of error, we will require a sample of 1494 unit_ids.
     With our stable unit_id set of 1500 unit_ids, we are now positioned
     to perform further analysis on the dataset to create the full
     topology and cost maps.</t>

<!-- NOTE NOTE NOTE: Need to talk to David about this paragraph.

     <t>analysed by using the net_usage files which describe the available 
     bandwidth for the observation period. The stable unit-ids can be 
     used as a measurement point for the quality of service offer by 
     the associated ISP in a given region. Furthermore it can be used 
     to analysing population movement by degradation or spontaneous 
     increase in the bandwidth. Furthermore some additional analysis is 
     performed by closely analysis the unit_id and IP address tuple that 
     did not obtain a perfect score of 12. Here we could find some other 
     stable unit_id , for example those who change the ISP or who 
     connected to the secondary DNS server. In order to detect this we 
     aggregate the ISP information publically available with our set to 
     further investigate this.</t>
-->
     <t><xref target="unit-id-table"/> presents a sample of the 
     geographic location data that we have uncovered for unit_ids.
     A complete list of identified units superimposed on the geographical 
     map of the United States is available at http://cdb.io/13UOHgD.</t>

     <texttable anchor="unit-id-table">
      <ttcol align="left">Unit ID</ttcol>
      <ttcol align="left">City, State</ttcol>
      <ttcol align="left">Latitude/Longitude</ttcol>
      <c>872</c><c>Morganville, NJ</c><c>40.35950089,-74.26280212</c>
      <c>885</c><c>Madison, WI</c><c>43.07310104,-89.40119934</c>
      <c>898</c><c>Foley, AL</c><c>30.40660095,-87.68360138</c>
      <c>7969</c><c>Manteca, CA</c><c>37.79740143,-121.2160034</c>
      <c>8024</c><c>Quincy, MA</c><c>42.25289917,-71.00229645</c>
      <postamble>Sample unit identification tuples</postamble>
     </texttable>

    </section> <!-- unit-id -->
    
    <section title="Conclusions and future work" anchor="conclusions">
     <t>Identification of the geographic location of the unit_ids
     generating the performance data is essential in order to continue
     the work.  We have presented a methodology and some early results
     in identifying a geographic location.  This location, although
     coarse, suffices for our future work that will consist of further
     data mining and analysis to create appropriate ALTO network and
     cost maps.</t>
    </section> <!-- conclusions -->

    <section title="IANA Considerations">
    
      <t>This document does not contain any IANA considerations</t>

    </section>

    <section title="Security Considerations">
    
      <t>There are no security artifacts that have been invalidated
      due to our analysis.  All of our analysis was performed on publicly
      available data.  However, we do note that some privacy may have
      been lost based on our analysis.  In the raw dataset, the unit
      identifiers are opaque strings with no immediate correlation with
      a geographic location.  After our analysis, while the unit 
      identifiers still remain opaque, they are nonetheless correlated
      to a specific, though coarse, geographic location.</t>
      
    </section>

  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
   
      &rfc2119;
      
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
   
      &i-d.seedorf-lmap-alto;
      &i-d.ietf-alto-protocol;
      <reference anchor="fcc">
       <front>
        <title>Measuring Broadband America</title>
        <author>
         <organization>United States Federal Communications Commission
         </organization>
        </author>
       </front>
       <seriesInfo name='Accessed July 12, 2013,'
                   value="http://www.fcc.gov/measuring-broadband-america"/>
      </reference>
    
    </references>

  </back>
</rfc>
