<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!-- Convert to HTML and Text with xml2rfc: http://xml.resource.org. -->
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
  <!ENTITY RFC2119 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
  <!ENTITY RFC0793 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.0793.xml">
  <!ENTITY RFC5681 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5681.xml">
  <!ENTITY RFC3465 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3465.xml">

<!--  <!ENTITY I-D.ford-mptcp-multiaddressed SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.draft-ford-mptcp-multiaddressed-01.xml">-->
]>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<!-- use symbolic references tags, i.e, [RFC2119] instead of [1] -->
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>

<rfc category="exp" docName="draft-ietf-mptcp-congestion-03" ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="MPTCP Congestion Control">Coupled Congestion Control for Multipath Transport Protocols</title>
    <author fullname="Costin Raiciu" initials="C." surname="Raiciu">
      <organization>University College London</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Gower Street</street>
          <city>London</city>
          <code>WC1E 6BT</code>
          <country>UK</country>
        </postal>
        <email>c.raiciu@cs.ucl.ac.uk</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Mark Handley" initials="M." surname="Handley">
      <organization>University College London</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Gower Street</street>
          <city>London</city>
          <code>WC1E 6BT</code>
          <country>UK</country>
        </postal>
        <email>m.handley@cs.ucl.ac.uk</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Damon Wischik" initials="D." surname="Wischik">
      <organization>University College London</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Gower Street</street>
          <city>London</city>
          <code>WC1E 6BT</code>
          <country>UK</country>
        </postal>
        <email>d.wischik@cs.ucl.ac.uk</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date day="11" month="April" year="2011" />

    <area>General</area>
    <workgroup>Internet Engineering Task Force</workgroup>
    <keyword>multipath tcp congestion control</keyword>
    <abstract>
      <t>Often endpoints are connected by multiple paths, but communications are 
usually restricted to a single path per connection. Resource usage within the network 
would be more efficient were it possible for these multiple paths to be used concurrently. 
Multipath TCP is a proposal to achieve multipath transport in TCP.</t>

      <t>New congestion control algorithms are needed for multipath transport protocols 
such as Multipath TCP, as single path algorithms have a series of issues in the multipath context. 
One of the prominent problems is that running existing algorithms such 
as TCP New Reno independently on each path would give the multipath flow 
more than its fair share at a bottleneck link traversed by more than one of its subflows. 
Further, it is desirable that 
a source with multiple paths available will transfer more traffic using the least congested of the paths, 
hence achieving resource pooling. This would increase the overall efficiency of the network and also its 
robustness to failure.</t>

      <t>This document presents a congestion control algorithm which couples the congestion control
algorithms running on different subflows by linking their increase functions, and dynamically controls 
the overall aggresiveness of the multipath flow. The result is a practical algorithm
that is fair to TCP at bottlenecks while moving traffic away from congested links. </t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
      <section title="Requirements Language">
        <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
        "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
        document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
        target="RFC2119">RFC 2119</xref>.</t>
      </section>

   <section title="Introduction" anchor="sec_intro">
      <t>Multipath TCP (MPTCP, <xref target="I-D.ford-mptcp-multiaddressed"/>) is a set of extensions to regular TCP 
<xref target="RFC0793"/> that allows one TCP connection to be spread across multiple paths. MPTCP distributes load 
through the creation of separate "subflows" across potentially disjoint paths.</t>

<t>How should congestion control be performed for multipath TCP? First, each subflow must have its own
congestion control state (i.e. cwnd) so that capacity on that path is matched by offered load. 
The simplest way to achieve this goal is to simply run TCP New Reno congestion control <xref target="RFC5681"/> 
on each subflow. However this solution is unsatisfactory as it gives the multipath flow an unfair share
when the paths taken by its different subflows share a common bottleneck.</t>

<t>Bottleneck fairness is just one requirement multipath congestion control should meet. The 
following three goals capture the desirable properties of a practical multipath congestion control algorithm:
<list style="symbols">
<t>Goal 1 (Improve Throughput) A multipath flow should perform at least as well as a single path flow would on the best 
of the paths available to it. </t>
<t>Goal 2 (Do no harm) A multipath flow should not take up more
     capacity from any of the resources shared by its different paths, than if it was a single flow
     using only one of these paths.  This guarantees it will not unduly harm
     other flows.</t>
<t>Goal 3 (Balance congestion) A multipath flow should move as much traffic as possible off its most congested paths, 
subject to meeting the first two goals.</t>
</list>
</t>

<t>Goals 1 and 2 together ensure fairness at the bottleneck. Goal 3 captures the concept of resource pooling 
<xref target="WISCHIK"/>: if each multipath flow sends more data through its least congested path, the traffic in the
network will move away from congested areas. This improves robustness and overall throughput, among other things. 
The way to achieve resource pooling is to effectively "couple" the congestion control loops for 
the different subflows. 
</t>

<t>We propose an algorithm that couples only the additive increase function of the subflows,
and uses unmodified TCP New Reno behavior in case of a drop. The algorithm relies on the traditional
TCP mechanisms to detect drops, to retransmit data, etc.</t>

<t>Detecting shared bottlenecks reliably is quite difficult, but is just one part of a bigger question.
This bigger question is how much bandwidth a multipath user should use in total, even if there is no shared
bottleneck.</t>

<t>The congestion controller aims to set the multipath flow's aggregate bandwidth to be the same as a regular
TCP flow would get on the best path available to the multipath flow. 
To estimate the bandwidth of a
regular TCP flow, the multipath flow estimates loss rates and round trip times and computes the target 
rate. Then it adjusts the overall aggresiveness (parameter alpha) to achieve the desired rate. 
</t>

<t>While the mechanism above applies always, its effect depends on whether the multipath TCP flow influences or does 
not influence the link loss rates (high vs. low statistical multiplexing).
If MPTCP does not influence link loss rates, MPTCP will get the same throughput as TCP on the best path.
In cases with low statistical multiplexing, where the multipath flow influences the loss rates on the 
path, the multipath throughput will be strictly higher than a single TCP would get on any of the paths. 
In particular, if using two idle paths, multipath throughput will be sum of the two paths' throughput.</t>

<t>This algorithm ensures bottleneck fairness and fairness in the broader, network sense. 
We acknowledge that current TCP fairness criteria are far from
ideal, but a multipath TCP needs to be deployable in the current 
Internet. If needed, new fairness criteria can be implemented by 
the same algorithm we propose by appropriately scaling the overall aggressiveness.</t>

      <t>It is intended that the algorithm presented here can be applied to other multipath transport protocols, 
such as alternative multipath extensions to TCP, or indeed any other congestion-aware transport protocols. However, 
for the purposes of example this document will, where appropriate, refer to the MPTCP protocol.</t>

<!--talk about robustness, refer to the NSDI paper!-->
<t>The design decisions and evaluation of the congestion control algorithm are published in <xref target="NSDI"/>.
</t>

<t>The algorithm presented here only extends TCP New Reno congestion control for multipath operation. 
It is foreseeable that other congestion controllers will be implemented for multipath transport
 to achieve the bandwidth-scaling properties of the newer congestion control algorithms for regular TCP (such 
as Compound TCP and Cubic). </t>

<!--<t>each aiming to achieve different properties in the resource pooling/fairness/stability design space. In 
particular, solutions that give better resource pooling may be proposed. This algorithm is conservative 
from this point of view, sacrificing resource pooling for stability.</t>-->
</section>

<section title="Coupled Congestion Control Algorithm" anchor="sec_cc">

<t>The algorithm we present only applies to the increase phase of the congestion avoidance 
state specifying how the window inflates upon receiving an ack. 
The slow start, fast retransmit, and fast 
recovery algorithms, as well as the multiplicative decrease of the congestion avoidance state
 are the same as in TCP <xref target="RFC5681"/>.</t>

<t>Let cwnd_i be the congestion window on the subflow i. Let tot_cwnd be the sum of the congestion windows of all
subflows in the connection.
Let p_i, rtt_i and mss_i be the loss rate, 
round trip time (i.e. smoothed round trip time estimate) 
and maximum segment size on subflow i. </t>

<t>We assume throughout this document that the congestion window is maintained 
in bytes, unless otherwise specified. We briefly describe the algorithm for
packet-based implementations of cwnd in section <xref target="sec_impl_packet"/>. 
</t>

<t>Our proposed "Linked Increases" algorithm MUST:
<list style="symbols">
<t>For each ack received on subflow i, increase cwnd_i by min (alpha*bytes_acked*mss_i/tot_cwnd , bytes_acked*mss_i/cwnd_i )</t>
<!--<t>For each drop event on subflow i, decrease set ssthresh_i to max(cwnd_i/2,2*mss_i), and
set cwnd_i to ssthresh_i + 3*mss_i. A drop
event is one or more packet drops experienced by a subflows in the same round trip time. </t>-->
</list>
</t>

<!--<t>The decrease function is the
same as in TCP New Reno, so we will not discuss it further in the remainder of this document.</t>-->

<t>The increase formula takes the minimum between the computed increase for the multipath 
subflow (first argument to min), and the increase TCP would get in the same scenario (the second argument).
In this way, we ensure that any multipath subflow cannot be more aggressive than a TCP flow in the same circumstances,
hence achieving goal 2 (do no harm).
</t> 

<t>"alpha" is a parameter of the algorithm that describes the aggresiveness of the multipath flow.
To meet Goal 1 (improve throughput), the value of alpha 
is chosen such that the aggregate throughput of the multipath flow is equal to the throughput a TCP flow would get if it ran on 
the best path. </t>

<t>To get an intuition of what the algorithm is trying to do, let's take the case where all the 
subflows have the same round trip time and MSS. In this case the algorithm will grow the total 
window by approximately alpha*MSS per RTT. 
This increase is distributed to the individual flows according to their instantaneous window size. 
Subflow i will increase by alpha*cwnd_i/tot_cwnd segments per RTT.</t> 

<t>Note that, as in standard TCP, when tot_cwnd is large the increase may be 0. In this case 
the increase MUST be set to 1. We discuss how to implement this formula in 
practice in the next section. </t>

<t>We assume appropriate byte counting (ABC, <xref target="RFC3465"/>) is used, 
hence the bytes_acked variable records the number of bytes newly acknowledged. If ABC is not used, bytes_acked 
SHOULD be set to mss_i.</t>

<t>To compute tot_cwnd, it is an easy mistake to sum up cwnd_i across all subflows: when a flow is in fast retransmit,
its cwnd is typically inflated and no longer represents the real congestion window. The correct behavior is to use 
the ssthresh value for flows in fast retransmit when computing tot_cwnd. To cater for connections that are app limited,
the computation should consider the minimum between flight_size_i and cwnd_i, and flight_size_i and ssthresh_i where 
appropriate.
</t>

<t>The total throughput of a multipath flow depends on the value of alpha and the loss rates, maximum segment sizes 
and round trip times of its paths. Since we require
that the total throughput is no worse than the throughput a single TCP would get on the best path, it is 
impossible to choose a-priori a single value of alpha that achieves the desired throughput in every ocasion. Hence, alpha
must be computed based on the observed properties of the paths. </t>

<t>
The formula to compute alpha is:
</t>

<figure>
           <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[           
	                           cwnd_i 
	                      max --------
			       i         2
			           rtt_i
	  alpha = tot_cwnd * ----------------
	                    /      cwnd_i \ 2
	                    | sum ---------|
			    \  i   rtt_i  /

            ]]></artwork>
</figure>

<t>The formula is derived by equalizing the rate of the multipath flow with the 
rate of a TCP running on the best path, and solving for alpha.
</t>

</section>

<section title="Implementation Considerations">
<t>
  The formula for alpha above implies that alpha is a floating point value. This would require 
performing costly floating point operations whenever an ACK is received, Further, in many kernels
floating point operations are disabled. There is an easy way to approximate the above calculations
using integer arithmetic. 
</t>

<t>Let alpha_scale be an integer. When computing alpha, use alpha_scale * tot_cwnd instead of tot_cwnd, and
do all the operations in integer arithmetic. </t>

<t>Then, scale down the increase per ack by alpha_scale. The algorithm is:
<list style="symbols">
<t>For each ack received on subflow i, increase cwnd_i by min ( (alpha*bytes_acked*mss_i/tot_cwnd)/alpha_scale , bytes_acked*mss_i/cwnd_i )</t>
</list>
</t>

<t>Alpha scale denotes the precision we want for computing alpha. 
Observe that the errors in computing the numerator or the
denominator in the formula for alpha are quite small, as the cwnd in bytes is typically much larger than the RTT
(measured in ms). </t>

<t>With these changes, all the operations can be done using integer arithmetic. We propose alpha_scale be 
a small power of two, to allow using faster shift operations instead of multiplication and division. 
Our experiments show that using alpha_scale=512 works well in a wide range of scenarios. 
Increasing alpha_scale increases precision, but also increases the risk of overflow when computing alpha. 
Using 64bit operations would solve this issue. Another option is to dynamically adjust alpha_scale when 
computing alpha; in this way we avoid overflow and obtain maximum precision.
</t>

<t>
It is possible to implement the algorithm by calculating tot_cwnd on each ack, however this would be costly
especially when the number of subflows is large. To avoid this overhead the implementation MAY choose to 
 maintain a new per connection state variable called tot_cwnd. If it does so, the implementation will update 
tot_cwnd value whenever the individual subflows' windows are updated.
Updating only requires one more addition 
or subtraction operation compared to the regular, per subflow congestion control code, so its performance impact 
should be minimal. </t>

<t>Computing alpha per ack is also costly. We propose alpha be a per connection variable, 
computed whenever there is a drop and once per RTT otherwise. More specifically, let cwnd_new be the
new value of the congestion window after it is inflated or after a drop. 
Update alpha only if cwnd_i/mss_i != cwnd_new_i/mss_i. 
</t>

<t>In certain cases with small RTTs, computing alpha can still be expensive. We observe that if RTTs were constant, 
it is sufficient to compute alpha once per drop, as alpha does not change between drops (the insight here is that 
cwnd_i/cwnd_j = constant as long as both windows increase). Experimental 
results show that even if round trip times are
not constant, using average round trip time instead of instantaneous round trip time 
gives good precision for computing alpha. Hence, it is possible to compute  
alpha only once per drop according to the formula above, by replacing rtt_i with rtt_avg_i. 
</t>

<t>If using average round trip time, rtt_avg_i will be computed by sampling 
the rtt_i whenever the window can accomodate one more packet, i.e.
when cwnd / mss &lt; (cwnd+increase)/mss. The samples are averaged once per sawtooth into rtt_avg_i. 
This sampling ensures that there is no sampling bias for larger windows.</t>

<t>Given tot_cwnd and alpha, the congestion control algorithm is run for each subflow 
independently, with similar complexity to the standard TCP increase code
<xref target="RFC5681"/>. </t>

<section title="Implementation Considerations when CWND is Expressed in Packets" anchor="sec_impl_packet">

<t>When the congestion control algorithm maintains cwnd in packets rather than bytes, 
the algorithms above must change to take into account path mss. 
</t>

<t>To compute the increase when an ack is received, the implementation for multipath
congestion control is a simple extension of the TCP New Reno code.  
In TCP New Reno cwnd_cnt is an additional state variable that tracks the number of 
segments acked since the last cwnd increment; cwnd is incremented only 
when cwnd_cnt > cwnd; then cwnd_cnt is set to 0. </t>

<t>In the multipath case, cwnd_cnt_i is maintained for each 
subflow as above, and cwnd_i is increased by 1 when 
cwnd_cnt_i > max(alpha_scale * tot_cwnd / alpha, cwnd_i). 
</t>

<t>When computing alpha for packet-based stacks, the errors in computing the
terms in the denominator are larger (this is because cwnd is much smaller and rtt may
be comparatively large). Let max be the index of the subflow used in the numerator. 
To reduce errors, it is easiest to move rtt_max (once calculated)
from the numerator to the denominator, obtaining the equivalent formula below. </t>

<figure>
           <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[
                                            cwnd_max 
     alpha = alpha_scale * tot_cwnd * -----------------------
                                     /     rtt_max * cwnd_i \ 2
                                     | sum -----------------|
                                     \  i        rtt_i      /

            ]]></artwork>
</figure>

<t>Note that the formula for computing alpha does not take into account path mss,
and is the same for stacks that keep cwnd in bytes or packets. 
With this formula, the
algorithm for computing alpha will match the rate of TCP on the best path
in B/s for byte-oriented stacks, and in packets/s in packet-based stacks. 
In practice, mss rarely changes between paths so this shouldn't be a problem.</t>

<t> 
However, it is simple to derive formulae allowing packet-based stacks to 
achieve byte rate fairness (and viceversa) if needed. In particular, for packet-based stacks  
wanting byte-rate fairness, the formula above changes as follows: cwnd_max is replaced by 
cwnd_max * mss_max * mss_max, while cwnd_i is replaced with cwnd_i * mss_i. 
</t>
</section>   

</section>

<section title="Discussion">

<t>To achieve perfect resource pooling, one must couple both increase and decrease of congestion windows across subflows,
as in <xref target="KELLY"/>. Yet this tends to exhibit "flappiness": when the paths have similar levels of 
congestion, the congestion controller will tend to allocate all the window to one random subflow, and allocate zero window
to the other subflows. The controller will perform random flips between these stable points. This doesn't seem desirable 
in general, and is particularly bad when the achieved rates depend on the RTT (as in the current Internet): in such a case,
the resulting rate with fluctuate unpredictably depending on which state the controller is in, hence violating Goal 1. </t>

<t>By only coupling increases our proposal removes flappiness but also reduces the extent of 
resource pooling the protocol achieves.

The algorithm will allocate window to the subflows such that p_i * cwnd_i = constant, for all i. Thus, 
when the loss rates of the subflows are equal, each subflow will get an equal window, removing flappiness.  
When the loss rates differ, progressively more window will be allocated to the flow with the lower loss rate. 
In contrast, perfect resource pooling requires that all the window should be allocated on the path with the lowest
loss rate.
</t>

</section>

    <section title="Security Considerations" anchor="sec_security">
      <t>None.</t>
      <t>Detailed security analysis for the Multipath TCP protocol itself is included in <xref target="I-D.ford-mptcp-multiaddressed"/> and [REF]</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>We thank Christoph Paasch for his suggestions for computing alpha in packet-based stacks. The authors are supported by Trilogy (http://www.trilogy-project.org), a research project (ICT-216372) partially funded by the European Community under its Seventh Framework Program.  The views expressed here are those of the author(s) only.  The European Commission is not liable for any use that may be made of the information in this document.</t>
    </section>

    <!-- Possibly a 'Contributors' section ... -->

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>None.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <!--  *****BACK MATTER ***** -->

  <back>
    <!-- References split into informative and normative -->

    <!-- There are 2 ways to insert reference entries from the citation libraries:
     1. define an ENTITY at the top, and use "ampersand character"RFC2629; here (as shown)
     2. simply use a PI "less than character"?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119.xml"?> here
        (for I-Ds: include="reference.I-D.narten-iana-considerations-rfc2434bis.xml")

     Both are cited textually in the same manner: by using xref elements.
     If you use the PI option, xml2rfc will, by default, try to find included files in the same
     directory as the including file. You can also define the XML_LIBRARY environment variable
     with a value containing a set of directories to search.  These can be either in the local
     filing system or remote ones accessed by http (http://domain/dir/... ).-->

    <references title="Normative References">
    &RFC2119;
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      &RFC0793;

      &RFC3465;

      &RFC5681;

      &I-D.ford-mptcp-multiaddressed; 

      <reference anchor='WISCHIK' target="http://ccr.sigcomm.org/online/files/p47-handleyA4.pdf">
        <front>
          <title abbrev="The Resource Pooling Principle">The Resource Pooling Principle</title>
          <author initials='D.' surname='Wischik' fullname='Damon Wischik'>
            <organization>University College London</organization>
          </author>
          <author initials='M.' surname='Handley' fullname='Mark Handley'>
            <organization>University College London</organization>
          </author>
          <author initials='M.' surname='Bagnulo Braun' fullname='Marcelo Magnulo Braun'>
            <organization>UC3M, Madrid</organization>
          </author>
          <date month="October" year="2008"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="ACM SIGCOMM CCR" value="vol. 38 num. 5, pp. 47-52"/>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor='NSDI' target="http://www.cs.ucl.ac.uk/staff/c.raiciu/files/mptcp-nsdi.pdf">
        <front>
          <title abbrev="MPTCP-CC">Design, Implementation and Evaluation of Congestion Control for Multipath TCP</title>
          <author initials='D.' surname='Wischik' fullname='Damon Wischik'>
            <organization>University College London</organization>
          </author>
          <author initials='C.' surname='Raiciu' fullname='Costin Raiciu'>
            <organization>University College London</organization>
          </author>
          <author initials='A.' surname='Greenhalgh' fullname='Adam Greenhalgh'>
            <organization>University College London</organization>
          </author>
          <author initials='M.' surname='Handley' fullname='Mark Handley'>
            <organization>University College London</organization>
          </author>
          <date month="March" year="2011"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="Usenix NSDI" value=""/>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor='KELLY' target="http://portal.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=1064415">
        <front>
          <title abbrev="Stability of end-to-end algorithms for joint routing and rate control">Stability of end-to-end algorithms for joint routing and rate control</title>
          <author initials='F.' surname='Kelly' fullname='Frank Kelly'>
            <organization>University of Cambridge</organization>
          </author>
          <author initials='T.' surname='Voice' fullname='Thomas Voice'>
            <organization>University of Cambridge</organization>
          </author>
          <date year="2005"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="ACM SIGCOMM CCR" value="vol. 35 num. 2, pp. 5-12"/>
      </reference>
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
