<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
	<!ENTITY rfc2119 PUBLIC '' 
	'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml'>
	<!ENTITY rfc2560 PUBLIC '' 
	'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2560.xml'>
	<!ENTITY rfc3779 PUBLIC '' 
	'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3779.xml'>
	<!ENTITY rfc3971 PUBLIC '' 
	'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3971.xml'>
	<!ENTITY rfc4193 PUBLIC ''
	'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4193.xml'>
	<!ENTITY rfc5280 PUBLIC '' 
	'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5280.xml'>
	<!ENTITY ietf-sidr-res-certs SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.draft-ietf-sidr-res-certs-19.xml">
	<!ENTITY ietf-csi-proxy-send SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.draft-ietf-csi-proxy-send-05.xml">
	<!ENTITY ietf-sidr-arch SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.draft-ietf-sidr-arch-11.xml">
	<!ENTITY ietf-sidr-cp SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.draft-ietf-sidr-cp-15.xml">
	<!ENTITY ietf-csi-send-name-type-registry SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.draft-ietf-csi-send-name-type-registry-06.xml">
]>

<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>

<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc iprnotified="no" ?>
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>

<rfc category="std" ipr="trust200902" docName="draft-ietf-csi-send-cert-10"
	updates="3971">

<front> 
	<title abbrev="SEND certificate profile and management">Certificate profile and certificate management for SEND</title>
		<author initials="R.G.M." surname="Gagliano" fullname="Roque Gagliano">
			<organization>Cisco Systems</organization>
			<address>
				<postal>
					<street>Avenue des Uttins 5</street>
					<city>Rolle</city>
					<region></region>
					<code>1180</code>
					<country>Switzerland</country>
				</postal>
				<email>rogaglia@cisco.com</email>
			</address>
		</author>
<author initials="S.K." surname="Krishnan" fullname='Suresh Krishnan'>
<organization>Ericsson</organization>
	<address>
	<postal>
	<street>8400 Decarie Blvd.</street>
	<city>Town of Mount Royal</city>
		<region>QC</region>
		<country>Canada</country>
	</postal>
<phone>+1 514 345 7900 x42871</phone>
<email>suresh.krishnan@ericsson.com</email>
	</address>
</author>
<author initials="A" surname="Kukec" fullname="Ana Kukec">
<organization>University of Zagreb</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street>Unska 3</street>
<city>Zagreb</city>
<country>Croatia</country>
</postal>
<email>ana.kukec@fer.hr</email>
</address>
</author>

<date month="November" year="2010" />
<abstract><t>SEcure Neighbor Discovery (SEND) Utilizes X.509v3 certificates for performing router authorization. This document specifies a certificate profile for SEND based on Resource Certificates along with extended key usage values required for SEND.</t></abstract>
</front>

<middle>
<section title="Requirements notation">
<t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL",
"SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY",
and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as
described in <xref target="RFC2119"/>.</t>
</section>

<section title="Introduction">
<t>SEcure Neighbor Discovery <xref target="RFC3971"/> (SEND) utilizes X.509v3 certificates that include the <xref target="RFC3779"></xref> extension for IPv6 addresses to certify a router&apos;s authorization to advertise IPv6 prefix for the Neighbor Discovery (ND) Protocol. The SEND specification defines a basic certificate profile for SEND. The certificate profile defined in this document supersedes the profile for router certificates specified in <xref target="RFC3971"/>.  That is, certificates used in SEND (by routers, proxies, or address owners) MUST conform to this certificate profile and MAY conform to the original profile in <xref target="RFC3971"/>.</t>

<t>The Resource Public Key Infrastructure (RPKI) is the global PKI that attests to the allocation of IP address space. The RPKI represents the centralized model referred in Section 6.2 of <xref target="RFC3971"/>. Consequently, SEND will use the RPKI certificate profile and certificate validation detailed in <xref target="I-D.ietf-sidr-res-certs"></xref>. A consequence of the use of RPKI certificate profile, the certificate validation method described in RFC3971 is updated with the certificate validation method in <xref target="I-D.ietf-sidr-res-certs"></xref>. </t>
<t>Since the RFC 3779 IPv6 addresses extension does not mention what functions the node can perform for the certified IPv6 space, it becomes impossible to know the reason for which the certificate was issued. In order to facilitate issuance of certificates for specific functions, it is necessary to utilize the ExtKeyUsageSyntax field (optional in RPKI Certificates) of the X.509 certificate to mention the purpose why the certificate was issued. This document specifies four extended key usage values, one for routers, two for proxies, and one for address owners, for use with SEND.</t>
<t>In RFC 3971 two deployment models were described: centralized and decentralized. This document describes the different deployment models that can be used with the SEND certificates defined here. </t>
</section>

<section title="Terminology">
<t>
<list style="hanging" hangIndent="26">
<t hangText="Certified IPv6 address space"> IPv6 address space included in an X.509v3 certificate using RFC 3779 extension for IPv6 addresses.
</t>
<t hangText="End Entity (EE)"> An entity in the PKI that is not a CA.
</t>
<t hangText="ISP"> Internet Service Provider.
</t>
<t hangText="NIR"> National Internet Registry.
</t>
<t hangText="RIR"> Regional Internet Registry.
</t>
<t hangText="RPKI"> Resource PKI established in accordance with <xref target="I-D.ietf-sidr-arch"></xref>.
</t>
<t hangText="RPKI certificates">Certificates defined in <xref target="I-D.ietf-sidr-res-certs"></xref>.
</t>
<t hangText="SEND certificates"> Certificates described in <xref target="RFC3971"/> and extended in this document. They are end-entity certificates that belong either to SEND routers, SEND hosts or SEND Proxies: 
<list style="symbols" hangIndent="2">
<t>Router Authorization Certificates defined in <xref target="RFC3971"/>.</t>
<t>Owner Authorization Certificates defined in <xref target="RFC3971"/>.</t>
<t>Secure Proxy ND Certificates defined in <xref target="I-D.ietf-csi-proxy-send"/>.</t>
</list>
</t>
<t hangText="SEND KeyPurposeId"> An Extended Key Usage (EKU) value for SEND, such as the four introduced in this document.</t>
</list>
</t>
</section>

<section title="SEND Certificate profile">
<t>SEND certificates MUST comply with the RPKI resource profile <xref target="I-D.ietf-sidr-res-certs"></xref>. A Router Authorization Certificate example is included in the Appendix A.</t>
<t>In sections 2, 4.9.10 and 4.9.11 <xref target="I-D.ietf-sidr-res-certs"></xref> it is stated that RFC 3779 resource extensions MUST be critical and MUST be present in all Resource Certificates. SEND certificates MUST include the IP Resources extension <xref target="RFC3779"/>.  This extension MUST include at least one address block for the IPv6 Address Family (AFI=0002), as described in Section 4.9.10 of <xref target="I-D.ietf-sidr-res-certs"></xref>. SEND certificates MUST NOT have more than one IP Resources extension.</t>

<section title="Unconstrained Certified subnet prefixes">
<t>Section 7.3 of <xref target="RFC3971"/> defines the Unconstrained Certified subnet prefixes category by using certificates containing either the null prefix or no prefix extension at all.</t>
<t>When using RPKI certificate profile, prefix extensions are mandatory and the null prefix MUST be validated. However, a certificate may inherit its parent's prefix or range by using the "inherit" element for IPv6 AFI as defined in RFC3779. The use of the "inherit" element is permited in <xref target="I-D.ietf-sidr-res-certs"></xref>.</t>
<t>Consequently, this document updates section 7.3 of RFC 3971 adding the following text under Unconstrained:</t>
<t>Network operators that do not want to constrain routers to route particular subnet prefixes but rather inherit them from its parent certificate, should configure routers with certificates containing the "inherit" element for IPv6 AFI.</t>
</section>
</section>

<section title="Deployment Models">
<t>RFC 3971 describes two deployment models:centralized and decentralized. These models were differentiated by having one or many trust anchor. In this document we introduce two new deployment models, not based on the number of trust anchors but on the localization of the SEND deployment.</t>
<t>The local SEND deployment model represent those cases where SEND deployment is confined to an administrative domain. In this scenario, the deployment of SEND MAY be done independently of the existence of deployment in the upper RPKI hierarchy (i.e. an end user could perform local SEND deployment without the need of RPKI deployment in its ISP). This model requires the use of local trust anchors and configuring islands of trust. This model MAY include Unique Local Addresses(ULAs) <xref target="RFC4193"/>.</t>
<t>The public SEND deployment models represent those cases where SEND deployment is linked to RPKI deployment as described in <xref target="I-D.ietf-sidr-arch"></xref>. Trust anchor material MAY be part of a different administrative domain (i.e. RIR, NIR or ISPs). It is a global model suitable for mobile users.</t>
<t>These two models are not mutually exclusive. It is entirely possible to have a hybrid model that incorporates features from both these models. In one such hybrid deployment model most IP address resources (e.g. global unicast addresses) would be certified under the global RPKI, while some others (e.g., ULAs) are certified under local TAs.</t>
</section>

<section title="Trust Anchor Material">
<t>Relying parties (e.g., end hosts that implement SEND and process these router certificates) MUST be configured with one or more trust anchors to enable validation of the routers' certificates. Section 6.5 of RFC 3971 and <xref target="I-D.ietf-csi-send-name-type-registry"></xref> list the trust anchor configuration options for end hosts using SEND.</t>
<t>In the local SEND deployment model, it is possible to use as trust anchor a certificate that includes in its RFC 3779 address extension the prefix ::/0. In this case no new trust anchor material would be needed when renumbering. However, if trying to move from the local deployment model to the public deployment model, new trust anchor material will have to be distributed to relying parties.</t>
</section>

<section title="Extended Key Usage Values">
<t>
The Internet PKI document <xref target="RFC5280"/> specifies the extended key usage X.509 certificate extension. The extension indicates one or more purposes for which the certified public key may be used. The extended key usage extension can be used in conjunction with key usage extension, which indicates the intended purpose of the certified public key. The EKU extension is defined as optional in <xref target="I-D.ietf-sidr-res-certs"></xref> for end entity certificates but MUST be present when issuing end entity certificates for SEND.

<vspace blankLines='1'/>
The extended key usage extension syntax is repeated here for convenience:
<vspace blankLines='1'/>
&nbsp;&nbsp;ExtKeyUsageSyntax  ::=  SEQUENCE SIZE (1..MAX) OF KeyPurposeId
<vspace blankLines='1'/>
&nbsp;&nbsp;KeyPurposeId  ::=  OBJECT IDENTIFIER
<vspace blankLines='1'/>
This specification defines four KeyPurposeId values: one for authorizing routers (Router Authorization Certificates), two for authorizing proxies (Secure Proxy ND Certificates), and one for address owners (Owner Authorization Certificates). Additional KeyPurposeId values may be specified in standard track documents.
<vspace blankLines='1'/>
The inclusion of the router authorization value (id-kp-sendRouter) indicates that the certificate has been issued for allowing the router to generate RA and Redirect messages for any prefix(es) encompassed (as defined in Section 7.1 of <xref target="I-D.ietf-sidr-res-certs"></xref>) by the IP address space included in the X.509 extensions for IP addresses.
<vspace blankLines='1'/>
The inclusion of the proxied routing authorization value (id-kp-sendProxiedRouter)
indicates that the certificate has been issued for allowing the proxy
to perform proxying of RA and Redirect messages for any prefix(es)
encompassed by the IP address space included in the X.509 extensions for IP addresses.
<vspace blankLines='1'/>
The inclusion of the proxied owner authorization value (id-kp-sendProxiedOwner)
indicates that the certificate has been issued for allowing the proxy to
perform proxying of NS, NA and RS messages for any address encompassed by the IP address space included in the X.509 extensions for IP addresses.
<vspace blankLines='1'/>
The inclusion of the owner authorization value (id-kp-sendOwner) indicates that the
certificate has been issued for allowing the node to use any
address(es) that is/are encompassed by the IP address space included in the X.509 extensions for IP addresses. For an address in such certificate the node can assign the address to an interface, send/receive traffic from/to this address, and can send/respond NS, NA and RS messages about that address.
<vspace blankLines='1'/>

&nbsp;&nbsp;send-kp OBJECT IDENTIFIER ::=
<vspace blankLines='0'/>
&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;{ iso(1) identified-organization(3) dod(6) internet(1)
<vspace blankLines='0'/>
&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;security(5) mechanisms(5) pkix(7) kp(3) }
<vspace blankLines='1'/>
&nbsp;&nbsp;id-kp-sendRouter OBJECT IDENTIFIER ::= { id-kp 23 }
<vspace blankLines='1'/>	
&nbsp;&nbsp;id-kp-sendProxiedRouter OBJECT IDENTIFIER ::= { id-kp 24 }
<vspace blankLines='1'/>
&nbsp;&nbsp;id-kp-sendOwner OBJECT IDENTIFIER ::= { id-kp 25 }
<vspace blankLines='1'/>
&nbsp;&nbsp;id-kp-sendProxiedOwner OBJECT IDENTIFIER ::= { id-kp 26 }
<vspace blankLines='1'/>
As described in <xref target="I-D.ietf-sidr-res-certs"></xref>, the extended key usage extension, if present, MUST be non-critical.
<vspace blankLines='1'/>
Relying Parties MUST require the extended key usage extension to be present in a certificate, and they MAY require a particular KeyPurposeId value to be present (such as id-kp-sendRouter or sendProxiedRouter) within the extended key usage extension. If multiple KeyPurposeId values are included, the relying parties need not recognize all of them, as long as the required KeyPurposeId value is present.Relying parties MUST reject certificates that do not contain at least one SEND KeyPurposeId even if they include the anyExtendedKeyUsage OID defined in <xref target="RFC5280"/>.
</t>
</section>

<section title="CRL profile and revocation">
<t>RPKI requires the use of CRLs <xref target="I-D.ietf-sidr-res-certs"></xref>.The host will obtain the necessary CRLs and perform the certificate validation method described in <xref target="I-D.ietf-sidr-res-certs"/>. </t>
<section title="Online Certificate Status Protocol (OCSP) Considerations">
<t>A host MAY use OCSP <xref target="RFC2560"/> protocol to verify the revocation status of a certificate.</t>
<t>By adopting the <xref target="I-D.ietf-sidr-res-certs"></xref> as the certificate profile for SEND, the host SHOULD NOT assume that certificates will include the URI of an OCSP server as part of its Authority Information Access (AIA) extension. This is particularly evident in the SEND public deployment model as OCSP services are not required by <xref target="I-D.ietf-sidr-cp"></xref>.</t>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="validation" title="Certificate validation">
<t>This section updates section 6.3.1 of <xref target="RFC3971"/> by introducing new validations without introducing any conflict.</t>
<t>The host MUST perform the certificate validation method described in <xref target="I-D.ietf-sidr-res-certs"></xref>.	The validation of certificates that uses the "inherit" element is describe in RFC 3779 where the existence of a parent prefix or range is required.</t>
<t>The host MUST verify that the Key PurposedId value corresponding to the Neighbor Discovery message type is present as described in Section 7.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
<t>This document makes use of object identifiers to identify EKUs and the ASN.1 (Abstract Syntax Notation One) module found in <xref target="APPB"/>. The EKUs and ASN.1 module OID are registered in an arc delegated by IANA to the PKIX Working Group. No further action by IANA is necessary for this document.</t>
</section>
<section title="Security Considerations">
<t>The certification authority needs to ensure that the correct values for the extended key usage are inserted in each certificate that is issued. Relying parties may accept or reject a particular certificate for an intended use based on the information provided in these extensions.  Incorrect representation of the information in the extended key usage field can cause the relying party to reject an otherwise appropriate certificate or accept a certificate that ought to be rejected.  In particular, since a SEND certificate attests that its subject is authorized to play a given role in the SEND protocol, certificates that contain incorrect EKU values can enable some of the same attacks that SEND was meant to prevent.  For example, if a malicious host can obtain a certificate that authorizes it to act as a router for a given prefix, then it can masquerade as a router for that prefix, e.g., in order to attract traffic from local nodes.</t>
</section>
<section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">
<t>The authors would like to thank Alberto Garcia, Stephen Kent, Sean Turner, Roni Even, Richard Barnes, Alexey Melnikov, Jari Arkko, David Harrington and Tim Polk for their reviews and suggestions on the earlier versions of this document. </t>
</section>
</middle>

<back>
<references title="Normative References"> &rfc2119;&rfc2560;&rfc3779;&rfc3971;&rfc4193;&rfc5280;&ietf-sidr-res-certs;&ietf-sidr-cp;&ietf-csi-send-name-type-registry;
</references>

<references title="Informative References">&ietf-sidr-arch;&ietf-csi-proxy-send;</references>
<section title="Router Authorization Certificate example">
<figure align="left">
<artwork>
Certificate:
    Data:
        Version: 3 (0x2)
        Serial Number: 249 (0xf9)
        Signature Algorithm: sha256WithRSAEncryption
        Issuer: CN=EXAMPLE-CA-2342342652346
        Validity
            Not Before: Jul  2 10:06:32 2010 GMT
            Not After : Jul  2 10:06:32 2011 GMT
        Subject: CN=SEND-EXAMPLE-123432
        Subject Public Key Info:
            Public Key Algorithm: rsaEncryption
                Public-Key: (2048 bit)
                Modulus:
                    00:b7:06:0d:8e:f7:39:0a:41:52:93:59:a8:f5:63:
                    3f:2e:3d:24:17:9d:19:aa:09:ff:c0:2a:f3:c6:99:
                    d7:34:0d:bf:f1:e9:73:b5:8f:dc:d4:91:d6:5d:cb:
                    9c:b8:2b:41:63:c1:8f:f7:48:54:02:89:07:24:c3:
                    b0:6e:11:5a:7d:c0:38:88:4b:d9:3b:93:c7:ca:4d:
                    a4:00:a2:d3:6d:14:15:8f:15:08:4d:4e:b3:8a:cc:
                    de:2d:e0:7a:9b:c0:6e:14:f6:a7:ae:b9:e0:c5:18:
                    60:75:3d:d3:50:00:47:0d:86:5b:1c:a0:85:81:af:
                    2b:84:98:49:7d:60:a2:e8:4f:6d:40:ba:d5:fe:de:
                    de:41:53:c7:c4:f4:d3:1a:41:cd:dc:9f:08:43:33:
                    48:00:57:e4:56:93:7d:dd:19:12:e8:bf:26:b3:4b:
                    30:ac:b8:9c:b1:37:05:18:3c:7b:6b:26:d7:c9:15:
                    c9:4a:eb:1b:fa:92:38:46:27:44:96:8a:a1:12:c1:
                    09:77:4a:7b:a5:07:88:a6:36:30:98:70:79:b6:44:
                    7e:b1:c9:4c:5b:11:56:e8:14:50:f7:f8:e5:ed:f1:
                    ac:a4:31:46:36:77:05:c9:63:fe:c3:ab:54:e2:bd:
                    79:1d:14:d1:c2:80:36:d3:be:e6:c7:a2:47:59:1b:
                    75:9f
                Exponent: 65537 (0x10001)
        X509v3 extensions:
            X509v3 Authority Key Identifier: 
                keyid:4C:5D:56:82:15:8A:67:A6:8C:69:67:68:88
                :6F:15:E5:C9:96:58:EB

            X509v3 CRL Distribution Points: 

                Full Name:
                  URI:rsync://rsync.example.exampledomain/
                  EXAMPLE-CA-2342342652346/EXAMPLE-CA.crl

            X509v3 Subject Key Identifier: 
                B8:69:EB:36:23:F1:C4:21:65:DD:13:76:EE:90:AF
                :F7:CD:E3:61:CD
            X509v3 Key Usage: critical
                Digital Signature
            sbgp-ipAddrBlock: critical
                IPv6:
                  2001:db8:cafe:bebe::/64

            X509v3 Extended Key Usage: 
                1.3.6.1.5.5.7.3.23
    Signature Algorithm: sha256WithRSAEncryption
        92:14:38:6e:45:83:1b:cb:7c:45:0d:bc:7f:6e:36:bf:82:cc:
        7e:00:91:ea:f4:24:43:cc:00:3c:3f:c2:99:0c:c6:b9:20:2e:
        ca:dc:df:94:0d:c9:a1:75:c4:5c:39:a1:cf:9f:e1:40:9c:aa:
        a9:80:76:d1:3a:91:d9:db:2f:cd:3c:05:50:52:eb:28:47:d0:
        ab:d3:fd:6f:30:17:16:7f:c6:0f:2b:25:bb:db:29:d7:bb:4e:
        f3:7c:2d:e1:04:b7:f0:bc:d5:8a:ba:8c:0d:39:22:48:02:d1:
        67:fb:35:5c:b6:83:03:63:7c:73:03:70:20:de:fb:d7:12:ed:
        6f:a1:ff:b2:a6:39:fb:55:9a:07:bd:68:40:0f:6f:d5:24:34:
        cf:e8:dd:76:33:2a:d0:b9:1b:ae:a8:68:86:17:f8:13:35:0e:
        f6:04:ec:2a:39:88:06:70:c6:e8:56:87:f7:35:54:2a:28:2c:
        92:47:a9:89:39:d7:72:24:21:9d:02:52:f9:7c:76:7f:e9:cd:
        09:6e:82:f4:da:6c:f9:72:b2:64:98:b5:0c:6a:38:8d:81:e5:
        fc:50:46:6f:38:40:56:06:92:5a:e0:86:5d:55:f5:7b:85:b2:
        68:4f:49:72:e0:fa:2c:bf:9e:7d:aa:28:17:ca:04:b8:ae:69:
        c9:04:28:12
</artwork>
</figure>
</section>

<section anchor="APPB" title="ASN.1 Module">
<figure align="left">
<artwork>
SENDCertExtns { iso(1) identified-organization(3) dod(6) internet(1)
 security(5) mechanisms(5) pkix(7) id-mod(0)
 id-mod-send-cert-extns(71) }

DEFINITIONS IMPLICIT TAGS ::= 

BEGIN

-- OID Arc

id-kp  OBJECT IDENTIFIER  ::=
 { iso(1) identified-organization(3) dod(6) internet(1)
   security(5) mechanisms(5) pkix(7) kp(3) }

-- Extended Key Usage Values

id-kp-sendRouter OBJECT IDENTIFIER ::= { id-kp 23 }
id-kp-sendProxiedRouter OBJECT IDENTIFIER ::= { id-kp 24 }
id-kp-sendOwner OBJECT IDENTIFIER ::= { id-kp 25 }
id-kp-sendProxiedOwner OBJECT IDENTIFIER ::= { id-kp 26 }

END
</artwork>
</figure>
</section>

</back>
</rfc>