<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="rfc2629.xslt"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY RFC1035 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1035.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC1918 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1918.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC2119 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC2131 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2131.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3315 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3315.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3424 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3424.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3596 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3596.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3693 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3693.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4848 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4848.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5012 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5012.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5389 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5389.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5625 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5625.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5687 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5687.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5985 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5985.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5986 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5986.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6280 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6280.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.cheshire-nat-pmp PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.cheshire-nat-pmp.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.ietf-geopriv-held-measurements PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-geopriv-held-measurements.xml">
]>
<?rfc rfcedstyle="no"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="no"?>
<?rfc iprnotified="yes"?>
<?rfc strict="yes"?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>

<rfc category="std" ipr="trust200902" docName="draft-ietf-geopriv-res-gw-lis-discovery-07">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="LIS Discovery by IP"> Location Information Server (LIS) Discovery using IP
      address and Reverse DNS </title>

    <author initials="M." surname="Thomson" fullname="Martin Thomson">
      <organization>Microsoft</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>3210 Porter Drive</street>
          <city>Palo Alto</city>
          <region>CA</region>
          <code>94304</code>
          <country>US</country>
        </postal>

        <phone>+1 650-353-1925</phone>
        <email>martin.thomson@gmail.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author initials="R.P." surname="Bellis" fullname="Ray Bellis">
      <organization>Nominet UK</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Edmund Halley Road</street>
          <city>Oxford</city>
          <code>OX4 4DQ</code>
          <country>United Kingdom</country>
        </postal>
        <phone>+44 1865 332211</phone>
        <email>ray.bellis@nominet.org.uk</email>
        <uri>http://www.nominet.org.uk/</uri>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date year="2013"/>
    <area>RAI</area>
    <workgroup>GEOPRIV</workgroup>
    <keyword>Internet-Draft</keyword>
    <keyword>HELD</keyword>
    <keyword>LIS</keyword>
    <keyword>Discovery</keyword>
    <keyword>NAT</keyword>
    <keyword>Residential Gateway</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>
	The residential gateway is a device that has become an integral part of home networking
	equipment. Discovering a Location Information Server (LIS) is a necessary part of acquiring
	location information for location-based services. However, discovering a LIS when a
	residential gateway is present poses a configuration challenge, requiring a method that is
	able to work around the obstacle presented by the gateway.
      </t>

      <t>
	This document describes a solution to this problem. The solution provides alternative domain
	names as input to the LIS discovery process based on the network addresses assigned to a
	Device.
      </t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>

    <section anchor="intro" title="Introduction">
      <t>
        A Location Information Server (LIS) is a service provided by an access network. The LIS uses
        knowledge of the access network topology and other information to generate location
        information for Devices. Devices within an access network are able to acquire location
        information from a LIS.
      </t>

      <t>
	The relationship between a Device and an access network might be transient. Configuration of
	the correct LIS at the Device ensures that accurate location information is available.
	Without location information, some network services are not available.
      </t>

      <t>
	The configuration of a LIS IP address on a Device requires some automated process. This is
	particularly relevant when one considers that Devices might move between different access
	networks served by different LISs. <xref target="RFC5986">LIS Discovery</xref> describes a
	method that employs the Dynamic Host Configuration Protocol (<xref target="RFC2131"
	>DHCPv4</xref>, <xref target="RFC3315">DHCPv6</xref>) as input to U-NAPTR <xref
	target="RFC4848"/> discovery.
      </t>

      <t>
	A residential gateway, or home router, provides a range of networking functions for Devices
	within the network it serves. Unfortunately in most cases these functions effectively
	prevent the successful use of DHCP for LIS discovery.
      </t>

      <t>
	One drawback with DHCP is that universal deployment of a new option takes a considerable
	amount of time. Often, networking equipment needs to be updated in order to support the new
	option. Of particular concern are the millions of residential gateway devices used to
	provide Internet access to homes and businesses. While <xref target="RFC5986"/> describes
	functions that can be provided by residential gateways to support LIS discovery, gateways
	built before the publication of this specification are not expected (and are likely not
	able) to provide these functions.
      </t>

      <t>
	This document explores the problem of configuring Devices with a LIS address when a
	residential gateway is interposed between the Device and access network. <xref target="ps"/>
	defines the problem and <xref target="ip-dns"/> describes a method for determining a domain
	name that can be used for discovery of the LIS.
      </t>

      <t>
	In some cases, the solution described in this document is based on a <xref target="RFC3424"
	>UNilateral Self-Address Fixing (UNSAF)</xref> method. For those cases, this solution is
	considered transitional until such time as the recommendations for residential gateways in
	<xref target="RFC5986"/> are more widely deployed. Considerations relating to UNSAF
	applications are described in <xref target="iab"/>.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="conventions" title="Conventions used in this document">
      <t>
	The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT",
	"RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in
	<xref target="RFC2119"/>.
      </t>

      <t>
        This document uses terminology established in <xref target="RFC6280"/> and <xref
        target="RFC5012"/>.  The terms Device and LIS are capitalized throughout when they are used
        to identify the roles defined in <xref target="RFC6280"/>.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="ps" title="Problem Statement">

      <t><xref target="topo"/> shows a simplified network topology for fixed wire-line Internet
      access. This arrangement is typical when wired Internet access is provided. The diagram shows
      two network segments: the access network provided by an internet service provider (ISP), and
      the residential network served by the residential gateway.
      </t>

      <t>
	There are a number of variations on this arrangement, as documented in Section 3.1 of <xref
	target="RFC5687"/>. In each of these variations the goal of LIS discovery is to identify the
	LIS in the access network.
      </t>

      <figure anchor="topo" title="Simplified Network Topology">
        <artwork><![CDATA[
                 ________
               (/        \)
              (( Internet ))
               (\________/)
                    |
                    |
              .- - -|- - - - - - - - - - - -.
             (      |                        )
            (   +--------+       +-------+    )
  Access    (   | Access |. . . .|  LIS  |    )
  Network   (   |  Node  |       |       |    )
   (ISP)    (   +--------+       +-------+    )
             (       \               \       )
              `- - - -\- - - - - - - -\- - -'
                       \               \
                        \               |
               .- - - - -\- - - - - - - + -.
              (           \             |   )
             (      +-------------+     :    )
             (      | Residential |     |    )
 Residential (      |   Gateway   |     :    )
   Network   (      +-------------+     |    )
             (         /        \      /     )
             (        /          \    /      )
             (   +--------+    +--------+    )
             (   | Device |    | Device |    )
             (   +--------+    +--------+    )
              (                             )
               `- - - - - - - - - - - - - -'
   ]]></artwork>
      </figure>


      <t>
	A particularly important characteristic of this arrangement is the relatively small
	geographical area served by the residential gateway. Given a small enough area, it is
	reasonable to delegate the responsibility for providing Devices within the residential
	network with location information to the ISP. The ISP is able to provide location
	information that identifies the residence, which should be adequate for a wide range of
	purposes.
      </t>

      <t>
	A residential network that covers a larger geographical area might require a dedicated LIS,
	a case that is outside the scope of this document.
      </t>

      <t>
	The goal of LIS discovery is to identify a LIS that is able to provide the Device with
	accurate location information. In the network topology described, this means identifying the
	LIS in the access network. The residential gateway is a major obstacle in achieving this
	goal.
      </t>

      <section title="Residential Gateway">
        <t>
	  A residential gateway can encompass several different functions including: modem, Ethernet
	  switch, wireless access point, router, network address translation (NAT), DHCP server, DNS
	  relay and firewall. Of the common functions provided, the NAT function of a residential
	  gateway has the greatest impact on LIS discovery.
	</t>

        <t>
	  An ISP is typically parsimonious about their IP address allocations; each customer is
	  allocated a limited number of IP addresses. Therefore, NAT is an extremely common function
	  of gateways. NAT enables the use of multiple Devices within the residential network.
	  However NAT also means that Devices within the residence are not configured by the ISP
	  directly.
	</t>

        <t>
	  When it comes to discovering a LIS, the fact that Devices are not configured by the ISP
	  causes a significant problem. Configuration is the ideal method of conveying the
	  information necessary for discovery. Devices attached to residential gateways are usually
	  given a generic configuration that includes no information about the ISP network. For
	  instance, DNS configuration typically points to a DNS relay on the gateway device. This
	  approach ensures that the local network served by the gateway is able to operate without a
	  connection to the ISP, but it also means that Devices are effectively ignorant of the ISP
	  network.
	</t>

        <t><xref target="RFC5986"/> describes several methods that can be applied by a residential
        gateway to assist Devices in acquiring location information. For instance, the residential
        gateway could forward LIS address information to hosts within the network it serves.
        Unfortunately, such an active involvement in the discovery process only works for new
        residential gateway devices that implement those recommendations.
	</t>

        <t>
          Where residential gateways already exist, direct involvement of the gateway in LIS
          discovery requires that the residential gateway be updated or replaced. The cost of
          replacement is difficult to justify to the owner of the gateway, especially when it is
          considered that the gateway still fills its primary function: Internet access.
          Furthermore, updating the software in such devices is not feasible in many cases. Even if
          software updates were made available, many residential gateways cannot be updated
          remotely, inevitably leading to some proportion that is not updated.
        </t>

        <t>
          This document therefore describes a method that can be used by Devices to discover their
          LIS without any assistance from the network.
        </t>

      </section>

      <section title="Residential Gateway Security Features">
        <t>
	  A network firewall function is often provided by residential gateways as a security
	  measure. Security features like intrusion detection systems help protect users from
	  attacks. Amongst these protections is a port filter that prevents both inbound and
	  outbound traffic on certain TCP and UDP ports. Therefore, any solution needs to consider
	  the likelihood of traffic being blocked.
	</t>
      </section>

    </section>

    <section anchor="ip-dns" title="IP-based DNS Solution">

      <t>
        <xref target="RFC5986">LIS discovery</xref> uses a DNS-based Dynamic Delegation Discovery
        Service (DDDS) system as the basis of discovery. Input to this process is a domain name. Use
        of DHCP for acquiring the domain name is specified, but alternative methods of acquisition
        are permitted.
      </t>

      <t>
        This document specifies a means for a Device to discover several alternative domain names
        that can be used as input to the DDDS process. These domain names are based on the IP
        address of the Device. Specifically, the domain names are a portion of the reverse DNS trees
        - either the <spanx style="verb">.in-addr.arpa.</spanx> or <spanx
        style="verb">.ip6.arpa.</spanx> tree.
      </t>

      <t>
        The goal of this process is to make a small number of DDDS queries in order to find a LIS.
        After LIS discovery using the DHCP-based process in <xref target="RFC5986"/> has failed, a
        Device can:
        <list style="numbers">
          <t>
            Collect a set of IP addresses that refer to the Device (<xref target="getip"/>).
          </t>
          <t>
            Convert each IP address into DNS names in the <spanx style="verb">in-addr.arpa.</spanx>
            or <spanx style="verb">ip6.arpa.</spanx> tree (<xref target="dns-names"/>).
          </t>
          <t>
            Perform the DDDS process for LIS discovery on those DNS names (<xref
            target="RFC5986"/>).
          </t>
          <t>
            Shorten the DNS names by some number of labels and repeat the DDDS process (<xref
            target="shorten-dns"/>).
          </t>
        </list>
      </t>

      <t>
	A Device might be reachable at one of a number of IP addresses. In the process described, a
	Device first identifies each IP address that it is potentially reachable from. From each of
	these addresses, the Device then selects up to three domain names for use in discovery.
	These domain names are then used as input to the DDDS process.
      </t>

      <section anchor="getip" title="Identification of IP Addresses">
        <t>
	  A Device identifies a set of potential IP addresses that currently result in packets being
	  routed to it. These are ordered by proximity, with those addresses that are used in
	  adjacent network segments being favoured over those used in public or remote networks. The
	  first addresses in the set are those that are assigned to local network interfaces.
	</t>

        <t>
	  A Device can use the Session Traversal Utilities for NAT (STUN) <xref target="RFC5389"/>
	  mechanism to determine its public reflexive transport address. The host uses the <spanx
	  style="verb">Binding Request</spanx> message and the resulting <spanx
	  style="verb">XOR-MAPPED-ADDRESS</spanx> parameter that is returned in the response.
	</t>

        <t>
	  Alternative methods for determining other IP addresses MAY be used by the Device. <xref
	  target="UPnP-IGD-WANIPConnection1">Universal Plug and Play (UPnP)</xref> and <xref
	  target="I-D.cheshire-nat-pmp">NAT Port Mapping Protocol (NAT-PMP)</xref> are both able to
	  provide the external address of a residential gateway device when enabled. These as well
	  as proprietary methods for determining other addresses might also be available.  Because
	  there is no assurance that these methods will be supported by any access network, these
	  methods are not mandated. Note also that in some cases, methods that rely on the view of
	  the network from the residential gateway device could reveal an address in a private
	  address range (see <xref target="assumptions"/>).
	</t>

        <t>
	  In many instances, the IP address produced might be from a private address range. For
	  instance, the address on a local network interface could be from a private range allocated
	  by the residential gateway. In other cases, methods that rely on the view of the network
	  (UPnP, NAT-PMP) from the residential gateway device could reveal an address in a private
	  address range if the access network also uses NAT. For a private IP address, the derived
	  domain name is only usable where the DNS server used contains data for the corresponding
	  private IP address range.
	</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="dns-names" title="Domain Name Selection">
        <t>
	  The domain name selected for each resulting IP address is the name that would be used for
	  a reverse DNS lookup. The domain name derived from an IP version 4 address is in the
	  <spanx style="verb">.in-addr.arpa.</spanx> tree and follows the construction rules in
	  Section 3.5 of <xref target="RFC1035"/>. The domain name derived from an IP version 6
	  address is in the <spanx style="verb">.ip6.arpa.</spanx> tree and follows the construction
	  rules in Section 2.5 of <xref target="RFC3596"/>.
	</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="shorten-dns" title="Shortened DNS Names">
        <t>
          Additional domain names are added to allow for a single DNS record to cover a larger set
          of addresses. If the search on the domain derived from the full IP address does not
          produce a NAPTR record with the desired service tag (e.g., <spanx
          style="verb">LIS:HELD</spanx>), a similar search is repeated based on a shorter domain
          name, using a part of the IP address:
          <list style="symbols">
            <t>
              For IP version 4, the resulting domain name SHOULD be shortened successively by one
              and two labels and the query repeated. This corresponds to a search on a /24 or /16
              network prefix. This allows for fewer DNS records in the case where a single access
              network covering an entire /24 or /16 network is served by the same LIS.
            </t>

            <t>
              For IP version 6, the resulting domain SHOULD be shortened successively by 16, 18, 20
              and 24 labels and the query repeated. This corresponds to a search on a /64, /56, /48
              or /32 network prefix.
            </t>
          </list> 
        </t>
	<t>
	  This set of labels is intended to provide network operators with a degree of flexibility
	  in where LIS discovery records can be placed without significantly increasing the number
	  of DNS names that are searched.  This does not attach any other significance to these
	  specific zone cuts, or create a classful addressing hierachy based on the reverse DNS
	  tree.
	</t>
        <t>
          For example, the IPv4 address <spanx style="verb">192.0.2.75</spanx> could result in
          queries to:
          <list style="symbols">
            <t>75.2.0.192.in-addr.arpa.
	    </t>
            <t>2.0.192.in-addr.arpa.
	    </t>
            <t>0.192.in-addr.arpa.
	    </t>
          </list>
        </t>
        <t>
          Similarly, the IPv6 address <spanx style="verb">2001:DB8::28e4:3a93:4429:dfb5</spanx>
          could result in queries to:
          <list style="symbols">
            <t>5.b.f.d.9.2.4.4.3.9.a.3.4.e.8.2.0.0.0.0.0.0.0.0.8.b.d.0.1.0.0.2 .ip6.arpa.
	    </t>
            <t>0.0.0.0.0.0.0.0.8.b.d.0.1.0.0.2.ip6.arpa.
	    </t>
            <t>0.0.0.0.0.0.8.b.d.0.1.0.0.2.ip6.arpa.
	    </t>
            <t>0.0.0.0.8.b.d.0.1.0.0.2.ip6.arpa.
	    </t>
            <t>8.b.d.0.1.0.0.2.ip6.arpa.
	    </t>
          </list>
        </t>
        <t>
          The limited number of labels by which each name is shortened is intended to limit the
          number of DNS queries performed by Devices. If no LIS is discovered by this method, the
          result will be that no more than five U-NAPTR resolutions are invoked for each IP address.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section title="When To Use The Reverse DNS Method">
        <t>
	  The DHCP method described in <xref target="RFC5986"/> MUST be attempted on all local
	  network interfaces before attempting this method. This method is employed either because
	  DHCP is unavailable, when the DHCP server does not provide a value for the access network
	  domain name option, or if a request to the resulting LIS results in a HELD <spanx
	  style="verb">notLocatable</spanx> error or equivalent.
	</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="private-address" title="Private Address Spaces">
        <t>
	  Addresses from a private use address space can be used as input to this method. In many
	  cases, this applies to addresses defined in <xref target="RFC1918"/>, though other address
	  ranges could have limited reachability where this advice also applies. This is only
	  possible if a DNS server with a view of the same address space is used. Public DNS servers
	  cannot provide useful records for private addresses.
	</t>

        <t>
	  Using an address from a private space in discovery can provide a more specific answer if
	  the DNS server has records for that space. <xref target="privatespace"/> shows a network
	  configuration where addresses from an ISP network could better indicate the correct LIS.
	  Records in DNS B can be provided for the 10.0.0.0/8 range, potentially dividing that range
	  so that a more local LIS can be selected.
	</t>

        <figure anchor="privatespace" title="Address Space Example">
          <artwork><![CDATA[
  _____        ________
 ( DNS ).....(/        \)      Public
 (__A__)    (( Internet ))     Address
             (\________/)      Space
                   |
                 [NAT]
  _____       _____|_____
 ( DNS )....(/           \)    Private
 (__B__)   (( ISP Network ))   Address Space
            (\___________/)    (e.g. 10.0.0.0/8)
                   |
               [Gateway]
               ____|____
             (/         \)     Private
            (( Residence ))    Address Space
             (\_________/)     (e.g. 192.168.0.0/16)
   ]]></artwork>
        </figure>

        <t>
	  The goal of automatic DNS configuration is usually to select a local DNS, which suits
	  configurations like the one shown. However, use of public DNS or STUN servers means that a
	  public IP address is likely to be found. For STUN in particular, selecting a public server
	  minimizes the need for reconfiguration when a Device moves. Adding records for the public
	  address space used by an access network ensures that the discovery process succeeds when a
	  public address is used.
	</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="assumptions" title="Necessary Assumptions and Restrictions">
        <t>
	  When used by a Device for LIS discovery this is an UNSAF application and is subject to the
	  limitations described in <xref target="iab"/>.
	</t>

        <t>
	  It is not necessary that the IP address used is unique to the Device, only that the
	  address can be somehow related to the Device or the access network that serves the Device.
	  This allows a degree of flexibility in determining this value, although <xref
	  target="security">security considerations</xref> might require that the address be
	  verified to limit the chance of falsification.
	</t>

        <t>
	  This solution assumes that the public reflexive transport address used by a Device is in
	  some way controlled by the access network provider, or some other related party. This
	  implies that the corresponding <spanx style="verb">.in-addr.arpa.</spanx> or <spanx
	  style="verb">.ip6.arpa.</spanx> record can be updated by that entity to include a useful
	  value for the LIS address.
	</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Failure Modes">
        <t>
          Successful use of private addresses relies on a DNS server that has records for the
          address space that is used. Using a public IP address increases the likelihood of this.
          This document relies on STUN to provide the Device with a public reflexive transport
          address. Configuration of a STUN server is necessary to ensure that this is successful.
        </t>

        <t>
	  In cases where a virtual private network (VPN) or other tunnel is used, the entity
	  providing a public IP address might not be able to provide the Device with location
	  information. It is assumed that this entity is able to identify this problem and indicate
	  this to the Device (using the <spanx style="verb">notLocatable</spanx> HELD error, or
	  similar). This problem is described in more detail in <xref target="RFC5985"/>.
	</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Deployment Considerations">
        <t>
          An access network provider SHOULD provide NAPTR records for each public IP address that is
          used for Devices within the access network.
        </t>

        <t>
          Any DNS server internal to a NAT SHOULD also include records for the private address
          range.  These records might only be provided to clients making requests from the private
          address range.  Doing so allows clients within the private address range to discover a LIS
          based on their IP address prior to any address translation.  In geographically distributed
          networks that use a private address range, this enables the use of a different LIS for
          different locations, based on the IP address range used at each location.  Use of a
          public, translated IP address for the network can still work, but it might result in a
          suboptimal LIS selection.
        </t>

        <t>
          NAPTR records can be provided for individual IP addresses. To limit the proliferation of
          identical records, a single record can be placed at higher nodes of the tree
          (corresponding to /24 and /16 for IPv4; /64, /56, /48 and /32 for IPv6). A record at a
          higher point in the tree (those with a shorter prefix) applies to all addresses lower in
          the tree (those with a longer prefix); records at the lower point override those at higher
          points, thus allowing for exceptions to be specified.
        </t>
      </section>

    </section>

    <section anchor="iana" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>[RFC Editor: please remove this section prior to publication.]</t>
      <t>
	This document has no IANA actions.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="privacy" title="Privacy Considerations">
      <t>
        As with all uses of geolocation information, it is very important that measures be taken to
        ensure that location information is not provided to unauthorized parties.  The mechanism
        defined in this document is focused on the case where a device is learning its own location,
        so that it can provide that location information to applications.  We assume that the device
        learning its own location is not a privacy risk.  There are then two remaining privacy
        risks: The use of geolocation by applications, and abuse of the location configuration
        protocol.
      </t>

      <t>
        The privacy considerations around the use of geolocation by applications vary considerably
        by application context.  A framework for location privacy in applications is provided in
        <xref target="RFC6280"/>.
      </t>

      <t>
        The mechanism specified in this document allows a device to discover its local LIS, from
        which it then acquires its location using a Location Configuration Protocol <xref
        target="RFC5687"/>.  If an unauthorized third party can spoof the LCP to obtain a target's
        location information, then the mechanism in this document could allow them to discover the
        proper server to attack for a given IP address.  Thus, it is important that a LIS meet the
        security requirements of the LCP it implements.  For HELD, these requirements are laid out
        in Section 9 of <xref target="RFC5985"/>.
      </t>
      
      <t>
        A Device that discovers a LIS using the methods in this document MUST NOT provide that LIS
        with additional information that might reveal its position, such as the location
        measurements described in <xref target="I-D.ietf-geopriv-held-measurements"/>, unless it has
        a secondary method for determining the authenticity of the LIS, such as a white list.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>
	The security considerations described in <xref target="RFC5986"/> apply to the discovery
	process as a whole. The primary security concern is with the potential for an attacker to
	impersonate a LIS.
      </t>

      <t>
	The added ability for a third party to discover the identity of a LIS does not add any
	concerns, since the identity of a LIS is considered public information.
      </t>

      <t>
        In addition to existing considerations, this document introduces further security
        considerations relating to the identification of the IP address. It is possible that an
        attacker could attempt to provide a falsified IP address in an attempt to subvert the rest
        of the process.
      </t>

      <t>
        <xref target="RFC5389"/> describes attacks where an attacker is able to ensure that a Device
        receives a falsified reflexive address. An on-path attacker might be able to ensure that a
        falsified address is provided to the Device.  Even though STUN messages are protected by a
        STUN MESSAGE-INTEGRITY attribute, which is an HMAC that uses a shared secret, an on-path
        attacker can capture and modify packets, altering source and destination addresses to
        provide falsified addresses.
      </t>

      <t>
	This attack could result in an effective means of denial of service, or a means to provide a
	deliberately misleading service. Notably, any LIS that is identified based on a falsified IP
	address could still be a valid LIS for the given IP address, just not one that is useful for
	providing the Device with location information. In this case, the LIS provides a HELD <spanx
	style="verb">notLocatable</spanx> error, or an equivalent. If the falsified IP address is
	under the control of the attacker, it is possible that misleading (but verifiable) DNS
	records could indicate a malicious LIS that provides false location information.
      </t>

      <t>
        In all cases of falsification, the best remedy is to perform some form of independent
        verification of the result. No specific mechanism is currently available to prevent attacks
        based on falsification of reflexive addresses; it is suggested that Devices attempt to
        independently verify that the reflexive transport address provided is accurate.  An
        independent, trusted source of location information could aid in verification, even in the
        trusted source is unable to provide information with the same accuracy as the discovered
        LIS.
      </t>

      <t>
	Use of private address space effectively prevents use of the usual set of trust anchors for
	DNSSEC. Only a DNS server that is able to see the same private address space can provide
	useful records. A Device that relies on DNS records in the private address space portion of
	the <spanx style="verb">.in-addr.arpa.</spanx> or <spanx style="verb">.ip6.arpa.</spanx>
	trees MUST either use an alternative trust anchor for these records or rely on other means
	of ensuring the veracity of the DNS records.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="iab" title="IAB Considerations">
      <t>
	The IAB has studied the problem of <xref target="RFC3424">Unilateral Self-Address Fixing
	(UNSAF)</xref>, which is the general process by which a client attempts to determine its
	address in another realm on the other side of a NAT through a collaborative protocol
	reflection mechanism, such as STUN.
      </t>

      <t>
	This section only applies to the use of this method of LIS discovery by Devices and does not
	apply to its use for third-party LIS discovery.
      </t>

      <t>
	The IAB requires that protocol specifications that define UNSAF mechanisms document a set of
	considerations. <list style="numbers">
          <t>
	    Precise definition of a specific, limited-scope problem that is to be solved with the
	    UNSAF proposal. <vspace blankLines="1"/> <xref target="ps"/> describes the limited scope
	    of the problem addressed in this document.
	  </t>

          <t>
	    Description of an exit strategy/transition plan. <vspace blankLines="1"/> <xref
	    target="RFC5986"/> describes behaviour that residential gateways require in order for
	    this short term solution to be rendered unnecessary. When implementations of the
	    recommendations in LIS discovery are widely available, this UNSAF mechanism can be made
	    obsolete.
	  </t>

          <t>
	    Discussion of specific issues that may render systems more "brittle". <vspace
	    blankLines="1"/> A description of the necessary assumptions and limitations of this
	    solution are included in <xref target="assumptions"/>. <vspace blankLines="1"/> Use of
	    STUN for discovery of a reflexive transport address is inherently brittle in the
	    presence of multiple NATs or address realms. In particular, brittleness is added by the
	    requirement of using a DNS server that is able to view the address realm that contains
	    the IP address in question. If address realms use overlapping addressing space, then
	    there is a risk that the DNS server provides information that is not useful to the
	    Device.
	  </t>

          <t>
	    Identify requirements for longer term, sound technical solutions; contribute to the
	    process of finding the right longer term solution. <vspace blankLines="1"/> A longer
	    term solution is already provided in <xref target="RFC5986"/>. However, that solution
	    relies on widespread deployment. The UNSAF solution provided here is provided as an
	    interim solution that enables LIS access for Devices that are not able to benefit from
	    deployment of the recommendations in <xref target="RFC5986"/>.
	  </t>

          <t>
	    Discussion of the impact of the noted practical issues with existing deployed NATs and
	    experience reports. <vspace blankLines="1"/> The UNSAF mechanism depends on the
	    experience in deployment of <xref target="RFC5389">STUN</xref>. On the whole, existing
	    residential gateway devices are able to provide access to STUN and DNS service reliably,
	    although regard should be given to the size of the DNS response (see <xref
	    target="RFC5625"/>).
	  </t>

        </list>
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="ack" title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>
        Richard Barnes provided the text in <xref target="privacy"/>.
      </t>
    </section>

  </middle>

  <back>

    <references title="Normative References"> &RFC1035; &RFC2119; &RFC3596;
      &RFC5986; &I-D.ietf-geopriv-held-measurements; </references>

    <references title="Informative References"> &RFC1918; &RFC2131; &RFC3315; &RFC3424; &RFC3693; &RFC4848;
      &RFC5012; &RFC5389; &RFC5687; &RFC6280; <reference anchor="UPnP-IGD-WANIPConnection1">
        <front>
          <title> Internet Gateway Device (IGD) Standardized Device Control Protocol V 1.0:
            WANIPConnection:1 Service Template Version 1.01 For UPnP Version 1.0 </title>
          <author>
            <organization>UPnP Forum</organization>
          </author>
          <date day="12" month="Nov" year="2001"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="DCP" value="05-001"/>
      </reference> &I-D.cheshire-nat-pmp; &RFC5625;  &RFC5985; </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
